<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 01:21:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>NOEMA$^{\rm 3D}$: A first kpc resolution study of a $z\sim1.5$ main sequence barred galaxy channeling gas into a growing bulge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07925v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a very deep CO(3-2) observation of a massive, gas-rich, main sequence, barred spiral galaxy at $z\approx1.52$. Our data were taken with the IRAM-NOEMA interferometer for a 12-antenna equivalent on-source integration time of $\sim$ 50 hours. We fit the major axis kinematics using forward modelling of a rotating disk, and then subtract the two-dimensional beam convolved best-fit model revealing signatures of planar non-circular motions in the residuals. The inferred in-plane radial velocities are remarkably large, of the order of $\approx60$ km/s. Direct comparisons with a high-resolution, simulated, gas-rich, barred galaxy, obtained with the moving mesh code AREPO and the TNG sub-grid model, show that the observed non-circular gas flows can be explained as radial flows driven by the central bar, with an inferred net inflow rate of the order of the SFR. Given the recent evidence for a higher-than-expected fraction of barred disk galaxies at cosmic noon, our results suggest that rapid gas inflows due to bars could be important evolutionary drivers for the dominant population of star-forming galaxies at the peak epoch of star and galaxy formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07925v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stavros Pastras, Reinhard Genzel, Linda J. Tacconi, Karl Schuster, Roberto Neri, Natascha M. F\"orster Schreiber, Thorsten Naab, Capucine Barfety, Andreas Burkert, Yixian Cao, Jianhang Chen, Fran\c{c}oise Combes, Ric Davies, Frank Eisenhauer, Juan M. Espejo Salcedo, Santiago Garc\'ia-Burillo, Rodrigo Herrera-Camus, Jean-Baptiste Jolly, Lilian L. Lee, Minju M. Lee, Daizhong Liu, Dieter Lutz, Amit Nestor Shachar, Eleonora Parlanti, Sedona H. Price, Claudia Pulsoni, Alvio Renzini, Letizia Scaloni, Taro T. Shimizu, Volker Springel, Amiel Sternberg, Eckhard Sturm, Giulia Tozzi, Stijn Wuyts, Hannah \"Ubler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lyman-Break Galaxies in the Mpc-Scale Environments Around Three $z\sim7.5$ Quasars With JWST Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07932v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the Mpc-scale environments of the three highest redshift luminous quasars at $z\geq 7.5$ (J031343.84-180636.40, J134208.11+092838.61, and J100758.27+211529.21) to understand their connection to large-scale structure. Cosmological simulations show that these early supermassive black holes (SMBHs) are expected to form in the most massive dark matter halos. Therefore, it is expected that they are anchors of galaxy overdensities if luminous matter traces the underlying dark matter structure of the Universe. Using JWST NIRCam (F090W/F115W/F250M/F360M/F430M) imaging, we observe the large-scale structure out to $\sim13$ comoving Mpc around these quasars. We select F090W-dropout Lyman Break galaxies (LBGs) and F430M-excess [OIII] emitters in the three fields. We find 18, 21, and 6 LBG candidates in the fields of J0313, J1342, and J1007, respectively, resulting in a wide range of overdensities ($1+\delta \sim 19,\,24,$ and $7$). The photometric redshifts indicate serendipitous foreground and background overdensities in the J0313 field. The joint angular autocorrelation of the combined LBG sample shows significant clustering on $&lt;1.8$ comoving Mpc scales, demonstrating that the selected galaxies are likely associated with the large-scale structure surrounding the quasars. This first systematic study of $z\sim 7.5$ quasars shows a diverse set of quasar environments at the onset of their formation, providing empirical data to help constrain theoretical predictions of early structure formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07932v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Pudoka, Feige Wang, Xiaohui Fan, Jinyi Yang, Jaclyn Champagne, Zijian Zhang, Sof\'ia Rojas-Ruiz, Eduardo Ba\~nados, Silvia Belladitta, Sarah E. I. Bosman, Anna-Christina Eilers, Xiangyu Jin, Hyunsung D. Jun, Mingyu Li, Weizhe Liu, Chiara Mazzucchelli, Jan-Torge Schindler, Julien Wolf, Yunjing Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic Clones of the Most Distant Galaxies in the Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07935v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Synergies between JWST and ALMA are unveiling a population of bright, super-early ($z&gt;10$) galaxies, including systems like GS-z14-0 ($z=14.2$) and GHZ2 ($z=12.3$) with extreme FIR line ratios (${\rm [OIII]88\mu m/[CII]158\mu m} &gt; 3$) that challenge galaxy formation models. To clarify this issue, we identify in the SERRA zoom-in simulations a synthetic analogue, Amaryllis, of these sources, and track its evolution from $z=16$ to $z=7$. During this period, Amaryllis grows from $\log(M_\star/M_\odot) \sim 7.4$ to $10.3$, linking super-early progenitors to the massive galaxy population at the end of reionization. At $z=11.5$, Amaryllis closely matches the observed properties of GS-z14-0, including $M_\star$, SFR, and the luminosity of FIR ([OIII]88$\mu$m) and UV (e.g. CIII]$1908$) lines. We find that high [OIII]/[CII] ratios appear during short, merger-driven starburst episodes, when low metallicity ($Z \sim 0.02\,Z_\odot$) and high ionization conditions ($U_{\rm ion} \sim 0.1$) push the ISM far from equilibrium. These extreme FIR line ratios are thus transient and linked to major mergers that ignite strong ionized gas outflows. Despite such a dynamically violent environment, strikingly, Amaryllis develops a dynamically cold gaseous disk ($V/\sigma \sim 4-6$) as early as $z \sim 11$, while its stellar component remains dispersion-dominated down to $z\sim7$. The co-existence of ordered rotation and merger-driven disturbances in $z&gt;10$ galaxies can explain the tentative disk signatures in GS-z14-0.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07935v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahsa Kohandel, Andrea Pallottini, Andrea Ferrara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultraviolet Properties of Multi-phase Gas Toward the Inner Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07969v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a systematic study of the multi-phase interstellar gas in the Inner Galaxy using HST/STIS absorption spectroscopy of 16 massive stars located at spectroscopic distances between 1.3 and 10 kpc in the region $-30^\circ\lesssim l \lesssim+30^\circ$ and $-15^\circ\lesssim b \lesssim+15^\circ$. These sight lines probe gas above and below the Sagittarius Carina, Scutum Crux-Centaurus, Norma, and Near 3 kpc spiral arms in a range of $z$-height from 0 to 1.5 kpc. Along the 16 sight lines, we measure velocity centroids for 800 UV absorption-line components across multiple gas phases (molecular CO, neutral, low ion, and high ion). We find that 619/800 components have velocities that are consistent with a simple model of co-rotation with the disk, indicating that multi-phase gas with disk-like kinematics extends at least 1 kpc into the halo. We present a database of absorption-line parameters that can be used for kinematic modeling of gas flows into and out of the Galactic disk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07969v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frances H. Cashman, Andrew J. Fox, Debopam Som, Bart P. Wakker, Robert A. Benjamin, Dhanesh Krishnarao, David M. French, Rongmon Bordoloi, Felix J. Lockman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JWST Observations of Young protoStars (JOYS): overview of program and early results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08002v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The embedded phase is a crucial period in the development of a young star. Mid-IR observations, now possible with JWST with unprecedented sensitivity, spectral resolution and sharpness are key for probing many physical and chemical processes on sub-arcsecond scales. JOYS addresses a wide variety of questions, from protostellar accretion and the nature of primeval jets, winds and outflows, to the chemistry of gas and ice, and the characteristics of embedded disks. We introduce the program and show representative results. MIRI-MRS data of 17 low-mass and 6 high-mass protostars show a wide variety of features. Atomic line maps differ among refractory (e.g., Fe), semi-refractory (e.g., S) and volatile elements (e.g., Ne), linked to their different levels of depletion and local (shock) conditions. Nested, stratified jet structures consisting of an inner ionized core seen in [Fe II] with an outer H2 layer are commonly seen. Wide-angle winds are found in low-J H2 lines. [S I] follows the jet in the youngest protostars, but is concentrated on source when more evolved. [Ne II] reveals a mix of jet shock and photoionized emission. H I lines measure accretion, but are also associated with jets. Molecular emission (CO2, C2H2, HCN, H2O, ..) is cool compared with disks, and likely associated with hot cores. Deep ice absorption features reveal not just the major ice components but also ions (as part of salts) and complex organic molecules, with comparable abundances from low- to high-mass sources. A second detection of HDO ice in a solar-mass source is presented with HDO/H2O ~ 0.4%, providing a link with disks and comets. A deep search for solid O2 suggests it is not a significant oxygen reservoir. Only few embedded Class I disks show the same forest of water lines as Class II disks do, perhaps due to significant dust extinction of the upper layers [abridged].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08002v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. F. van Dishoeck, {\L}. Tychoniec, W. R. M. Rocha, K. Slavicinska, L. Francis, M. L. van Gelder, T. P. Ray, H. Beuther, A. Caratti o Garatti, N. G. C. Brunken, Y. Chen, R. Devaraj, V. C. Geers, C. Gieser, T. P. Greene, K. Justtanont, V. J. M. Le Gouellec, P. J. Kavanagh, P. D. Klaassen, A. G. M. Janssen, M. G. Navarro, P. Nazari, S. Notsu, G. Perotti, M. E. Ressler, S. D. Reyes, A. D. Sellek, B. Tabone, C. Tap, N. C. M. A. Theijssen, L. Colina, M. G\"udel, Th. Henning, P. -O. Lagage, G. \"Ostlin, B. Vandenbussche, G. S. Wright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights into the 3D layered structure of nearby open clusters through N-body simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08184v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. Open clusters (OCs) are important for understanding star formation, dynamics, and evolution. Previous studies have indicated a relationship between cluster structure and member star properties, but the formation mechanism of the layered structure of OCs remains unclear. Aims. We study the three-dimensional spatial distribution of 279 nearby OCs to understand the formation mechanism of the layered structure. Methods. We analyzed the spatial distribution of member stars within each OC and correlated the presence of a layered structure with the number of member stars. Additionally, we performd N-body simulations to model the evolution of OCSN 125. We assessd the correlation between the binary fraction, the most massive star, and the radius of the layered structure in each simulated OC. Results. Our analysis reveals that OCs with fewer member stars tend to lack a layered structure. The results from N-body simulations indicate that the presence of a layered structure is strongly influenced by dynamical factors, particularly the most massive star and the binary fraction. Massive stars drive mass loss through supernova explosions and stellar winds, which weaken the spatial layering. Furthermore, clusters with higher binary fractions exhibit a weaker layered structure, likely due to energy equipartition, dynamical friction, and perturbations caused by binary systems. These factors contribute to delaying core collapse and slowing the emergence of a layered structure. Conclusions. Our findings suggest that dynamical interactions, including the effects of the most massive stars and binary fraction, play a critical role in the formation and disruption of the layered structure in OCs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08184v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lang Kaixiang, Zhang Yu, Niu Hubiao, Jayanand Maurya, Liu Jinzhong, Liu Guimei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Evolutionary Map of the Universe: A new radio atlas for the southern hemisphere sky</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08271v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the Evolutionary Map of the Universe (EMU) survey conducted with the Australian Square Kilometre Array Pathfinder (ASKAP). EMU aims to deliver the touchstone radio atlas of the southern hemisphere. We introduce EMU and review its science drivers and key science goals, updated and tailored to the current ASKAP five-year survey plan. The development of the survey strategy and planned sky coverage is presented, along with the operational aspects of the survey and associated data analysis, together with a selection of diagnostics demonstrating the imaging quality and data characteristics. We give a general description of the value-added data pipeline and data products before concluding with a discussion of links to other surveys and projects and an outline of EMU's legacy value.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08271v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. M. Hopkins (Macquarie University Australia), A. Kapinska (National Radio Astronomy Observatory USA), J. Marvil (National Radio Astronomy Observatory USA), T. Vernstrom (, Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Bentley Australia, ICRAR The University of Western Australia Crawley Australia), J. D. Collier (Australian SKA Regional Centre Curtin Institute of Radio Astronomy, Inter-University Institute for Data Intensive Astronomy, Western Sydney University Penrith Australia), R. P. Norris (Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Epping Australia, Western Sydney University Penrith Australia), Y. A. Gordon (University of Wisconsin-Madison Madison USA), S. W. Duchesne (, Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Bentley Australia), L. Rudnick (University of Minnesota Minneapolis USA), N. Gupta (, Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Bentley Australia), E. Carretti (INAF - Istituto di Radioastronomia Bologna Italy), C. S. Anderson (Australian National University Canberra Australia), S. Dai (Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Epping Australia), G. G\"urkan (University of Hertfordshire Hatfield UK, Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Bentley Australia), D. Parkinson (Korea Astronomy and Space Science Institute Daejeon Republic of Korea), I. Prandoni (INAF - Istituto di Radioastronomia Bologna Italy), S. Riggi (INAF - Osservatorio Astrofisico di Catania Italy), C. S. Saraf (Korea Astronomy and Space Science Institute Daejeon Republic of Korea), Y. K. Ma (Australian National University Canberra Australia), M. D. Filipovi\'c (Western Sydney University Penrith Australia), G. Umana (INAF - Osservatorio Astrofisico di Catania Italy), B. Bahr-Kalus (INAF - Osservatorio Astrofisico di Torino Pino Torinese Italy, INFN - Sezione di Torino Italy, Universit\`a degli Studi di Torino Italy), B. S. Koribalski (Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Epping Australia, Western Sydney University Penrith Australia), E. Lenc (Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Epping Australia), A. Ingallinera (INAF - Osservatorio Astrofisico di Catania Italy), J. Afonso (Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o Universidade de Lisboa Lisbon Portugal, Departamento de F\'isica Faculdade de Ci\^encias Universidade de Lisboa Lisbon Portugal), A. Ahmad (Western Sydney University Penrith Australia), U. T. Ahmed (Australian Astronomical Optics Macquarie University Australia), E. L. Alexander (University of Leeds UK), H. Andernach (Th\"uringer Landessternwarte Tautenburg Germany, Universidad de Guanajuato Mexico), J. Asorey (Universidad de Zaragoza Spain), A. J. Battisti (International Centre for Radio Astronomy Research, Australian National University Canberra Australia, ARC Centre of Excellence for All Sky Astrophysics in 3 Dimensions), M. Bilicki (Center for Theoretical Physics Polish Academy of Sciences Warsaw Poland), A. Botteon (INAF - Istituto di Radioastronomia Bologna Italy), M. J. I. Brown (Monash University Australia), M. Br\"uggen (University of Hamburg Germany), M. Cowley (Queensland University of Technology Brisbane Australia, University of Southern Queensland Toowoomba Australia), K. C. Dage (International Centre for Radio Astronomy Research - Curtin University Perth Australia), C. L. Hale (Department of Physics, University of Oxford UK), M. J. Hardcastle (University of Hertfordshire Hatfield UK), R. Kothes (Herzberg Research Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics National Research Council Canada Penticton Canada, University of Alberta Edmonton Canada), S. Lazarevi\'c (Western Sydney University Penrith Australia, Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Epping Australia, Astronomical Observatory Belgrade Serbia), Y. -T. Lin (Institute of Astronomy and Astrophysics Academia Sinica), K. J. Luken (Western Sydney University Penrith Australia), J. P. Moss (Victoria University of Wellington Kelburn Wellington New Zealand), J. Prathap (Macquarie University Australia, Macquarie University Astrophysics and Space Technologies Research Centre Sydney Australia, ARC Centre of Excellence for All Sky Astrophysics in 3 Dimensions), S. F. Rahman (Lahore University of Management Sciences, NCBC at NED University of Engineering and Technology Pakistan), T. H. Reiprich (University of Bonn Germany), C. J. Riseley (Ruhr-Universit\"at Bochum Germany, Universit\`a degli Studi di Bologna Italy, INAF - Istituto di Radioastronomia Bologna Italy), M. Salvato (Max-Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics Garching Germany), N. Seymour (International Centre for Radio Astronomy Research Curtin University Bentley Australia), S. S. Shabala (University of Tasmania Hobart Australia), D. J. B. Smith (University of Hertfordshire Hatfield UK), M. Vaccari (Inter-University Institute for Data Intensive Astronomy and Department of Physics and Astronomy University of the Western Cape Cape Town South Africa, Inter-University Institute for Data Intensive Astronomy Department of Astronomy University of Cape Town South Africa, INAF - Istituto di Radioastronomia Bologna Italy), J. Th. van Loon (Lennard-Jones Laboratories Keele University UK), O. I. Wong (, Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Bentley Australia, ICRAR The University of Western Australia Crawley Australia), R. Z. E. Alsaberi (Gifu University Gifu Japan, Western Sydney University Penrith Australia), A. D. Asher (Western Sydney University Penrith Australia, Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Epping Australia), B. D. Ball (University of Alberta Edmonton Canada), D. Barbosa (Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o Universidade de Lisboa Lisbon Portugal, Departamento de F\'isica Faculdade de Ci\^encias Universidade de Lisboa Lisbon Portugal), N. Biava (Th\"uringer Landessternwarte Tautenburg Germany, INAF - Istituto di Radioastronomia Bologna Italy), A. C. Bradley (Western Sydney University Penrith Australia), R. Carvajal (Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o Universidade de Lisboa Lisbon Portugal, Departamento de F\'isica Faculdade de Ci\^encias Universidade de Lisboa Lisbon Portugal), E. J. Crawford (Western Sydney University Penrith Australia), T. J. Galvin (, Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Bentley Australia), M. T. Huynh (, Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Bentley Australia, ICRAR The University of Western Australia Crawley Australia), D. A. Leahy (University of Calgary Canada), I. Matute (Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o Universidade de Lisboa Lisbon Portugal, Departamento de F\'isica Faculdade de Ci\^encias Universidade de Lisboa Lisbon Portugal), V. A. Moss (Australia Telescope National Facility CSIRO Space and Astronomy Epping Australia), C. Pappalardo (Instituto de Astrof\'isica e Ci\^encias do Espa\c{c}o Universidade de Lisboa Lisbon Portugal, Departamento de F\'isica Faculdade de Ci\^encias Universidade de Lisboa Lisbon Portugal), Z. J. Smeaton (Western Sydney University Penrith Australia), V. Velovi\'c (Western Sydney University Penrith Australia), T. Zafar (Macquarie University Australia)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Polarisation Sky Survey of the Universe's Magnetism (POSSUM): Science Goals and Survey Description</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08272v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Australian SKA Pathfinder (ASKAP) offers powerful new capabilities for studying the polarised and magnetised Universe at radio wavelengths. In this paper, we introduce the Polarisation Sky Survey of the Universe's Magnetism (POSSUM), a groundbreaking survey with three primary objectives: (1) to create a comprehensive Faraday rotation measure (RM) grid of up to one million compact extragalactic sources across the southern ~50 per cent of the sky (20,630 deg$^2$); (2) to map the intrinsic polarisation and RM properties of a wide range of discrete extragalactic and Galactic objects over the same area; and (3) to contribute interferometric data with excellent surface brightness sensitivity, which can be combined with single-dish data to study the diffuse Galactic interstellar medium. Observations for the full POSSUM survey commenced in May 2023 and are expected to conclude by mid-2028. POSSUM will achieve an RM grid density of around 30-50 RMs per square degree with a median measurement uncertainty of ~1 rad m$^{-2}$. The survey operates primarily over a frequency range of 800-1088 MHz, with an angular resolution of 20'' and a typical RMS sensitivity in Stokes $Q$ or $U$ of 18 $\mu$Jy beam$^{-1}$. Additionally, the survey will be supplemented by similar observations covering 1296-1440 MHz over 38 per cent of the sky. POSSUM will enable the discovery and detailed investigation of magnetised phenomena in a wide range of cosmic environments, as well as the interplay between these components. This paper reviews the current science case developed by the POSSUM Collaboration and provides an overview of POSSUM's observations, data processing, outputs, and its complementarity with other radio and multi-wavelength surveys, including future work with the SKA. [Abstract abridged]</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08272v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. M. Gaensler, G. H. Heald, N. M. McClure-Griffiths, C. S. Anderson, C. L. Van Eck, J. L. West, A. J. M. Thomson, J. P. Leahy, L. Rudnick, Y. K. Ma, Takuya Akahori, G. G\"urkan, T. L. Landecker, S. A. Mao, S. P. O'Sullivan, W. Raja, X. Sun, T. Vernstrom, Lerato Baidoo, Ettore Carretti, A. R. Taylor, A. G. Willis, Erik Osinga, J. D. Livingston, E. L. Alexander, David Alonso-L\'opez, A. D. Amaral, T. An, Andrea Bracco, S. Bradbury, Marcus Br\"uggen, Chakali Eswaraiah, Torsten En{\ss}lin, T. J. Galvin, Marijke Haverkorn, A. M. Hopkins, Sebastian Hutschenreuter, Shinsuke Ideguchi, S. Jaswanth, S. Lyla Jung, J. F. Kaczmarek, Roland Kothes, Sanja Lazarevi\'c, Denis Leahy, Francesca Loi, Joshua R. Marvil, Ray Norris, Ayush Pandhi, Jason M. Price, C. J. Riseley, P. Ryder, Amit Seta, Vasundhara Shaw, A. X. Shen, C. Sobey, J. Stil, Chiara Stuardi, Gupta Upasana, Shannon Vanderwoude, Velibor Velovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Statistics of Gas Density, Velocity, and Magnetic Fields in Cool-Core Galaxy Clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08275v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding turbulence within the Intracluster Medium (ICM) of galaxy clusters is pivotal for comprehending their evolution and dynamics. Employing 3D magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) simulations of galaxy cluster mergers, we examine the statistical properties of gas density, magnetic fields, and velocity, particularly emphasizing the central regions spanning 400 kpc. The simulations feature varied initial plasma $\beta$ values (100, 200, and 500), mirroring conditions in massive cool-core clusters such as Perseus. Our findings indicate that while the statistical histogram distributions of gas density and velocity appear similar across different $\beta$ scenarios, their spatial distributions and morphological patterns exhibit noticeable differences. Through the application of the second-order structure function, we identified a scaling relation in velocity fluctuations, characterized by a slope of 1/2 and predominantly dominated by solenoidal components. Furthermore, our analysis reveals a pronounced anisotropy in both velocity and magnetic field fluctuations, with more significant fluctuations along the direction perpendicular to the magnetic fields. This anisotropy is scale-dependent, becoming more pronounced at smaller scales, and exhibits a decreasing trend in scenarios where the magnetic field is relatively weak, particularly at $\beta=500$. This suggests that the anisotropic nature of these fluctuations is predominantly regulated by the magnetic fields. Additionally, we test the efficacy of the Synchrotron Intensity Gradient (SIG) method for tracing magnetic fields in these environments. The SIG shows a global agreement with the magnetic field across all three $\beta$ scenarios, confirming the SIG's insensitivity to the medium's magnetization level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08275v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Hu, Alex Lazarian, G. Brunetti, John A. ZuHone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tidal Debris Candidates from the $\omega$ Centauri Accretion Event and its Role in Building Up the Milky Way Halo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08353v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We identify stellar tidal debris from the $\omega$ Centauri ($\omega$ Cen) system among field stars in the APOGEE survey via chemical tagging using a neural network trained on APOGEE observations of the $\omega$ Cen core. We find a total of 463 $\omega$ Cen debris candidates have a probability $P &gt; 0.8$ of sharing common patterns in their chemical abundances across a range of individual elements or element combinations, including [C+N], O, Mg, Al, Si, Ca, Ni, and Fe. Some debris candidates show prograde or retrograde disk-like kinematics, but most show kinematics consistent with the accreted halo, showing high radial actions, $J_{R}$, values. We find that a sample of Gaia-Sausage-Enceladus (GES) members are chemically distinct from the $\omega$ Cen core, suggesting that $\omega$ Cen is associated to an independent merger event shaping the Milky Way halo. However, a connection between GSE and $\omega$ Cen cannot be ruled out. A detailed comparison with $N$-body simulations indicates that the $\omega$ Cen progenitor was a massive dwarf galaxy ($\gtrsim 10^8 M_{\odot}$). The existence of a metal-poor high-$\alpha$ chemically homogeneous halo debris is also reported.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08353v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Borja Anguiano, Arik Mitschang, Takanobu Kirihara, Yutaka Hirai, Danny Horta, Sten Hasselquist, Ricardo P. Schiavon, Steven R. Majewski, Andrew C. Mason, Adrian M. Price-Whelan, Carlos Allende Prieto, Verne Smith, Katia Cunha, David L. Nidever</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutron-Capture Element Signatures in Globular Clusters: Insights from the Gaia-ESO Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08399v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Globular clusters (GCs) are key to understanding the formation and evolution of our Galaxy. While the abundances of light and Fe-peak elements in GCs have been widely studied, investigations into heavier, neutron-capture elements -- and their connection to multiple stellar populations and GC origins -- remain limited. In this work, we analysed the chemical abundances of neutron-capture elements in GCs to trace the Galactic halo and to explore possible links to the MP phenomenon. Our goal is to better constrain the nature of the polluters responsible for intracluster enrichment and to distinguish the origin of GCs through the chemical signature of neutron-capture elements. We examined 14 GCs from the Gaia-ESO Survey, spanning a wide metallicity range, [Fe/H] from -0.40 to -2.32, using a homogeneous methodology. We focused on the abundances of Y, Zr, Ba, La, Ce, Nd, Pr, and Eu, derived from FLAMES-UVES spectra. These were compared with predictions from a stochastic Galactic chemical evolution model. With the exception of Zr, the model broadly reproduces the observed trends in neutron-capture elements. In some GCs, we found strong correlations between hot H-burning products (Na, Al) and s-process elements, pointing to a shared nucleosynthesis site, e.g., asymptotic giant branch stars of different masses and/or fast-rotating massive stars. We also detect a distinct difference in [Eu/Mg] ratio between in-situ ($\langle$[Eu/Mg]$\rangle$ = 0.14 dex) and ex-situ ($\langle$[Eu/Mg]$\langle$ = 0.32 dex) GCs, highlighting their different enrichment histories. Finally, on average, Type II GCs (NGC 362, NGC 1261, and NGC 1851) showed a s-process element spread ratio between second- and first-generations about twice as large as those seen in Type I clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08399v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Schiappacasse-Ulloa, L. Magrini, S. Lucatello, S. Randich, A. Bragaglia, E. Carretta, G. Cescutti, F. Rizzuti, C. Worley, F. Lucertini, L. Berni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding molecular ratios in the carbon and oxygen poor outer Milky Way with interpretable machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08410v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. The outer Milky Way has a lower metallicity than our solar neighbourhood, but still many molecules are detected in the region. Molecular line ratios can serve as probes to better understand the chemistry and physics in these regions. Aims. We use interpretable machine learning to study 9 different molecular ratios, helping us understand the forward connection between the physics of these environments and the carbon and oxygen chemistries. Methods. Using a large grid of astrochemical models generated using UCLCHEM, we study the properties of molecular clouds of low oxygen and carbon initial abundance. We first try to understand the line ratios using a classical analysis. We then move on to using interpretable machine learning, namely Shapley Additive Explanations (SHAP), to understand the higher order dependencies of the ratios over the entire parameter grid. Lastly we use the Uniform Manifold Approximation and Projection technique (UMAP) as a reduction method to create intuitive groupings of models. Results. We find that the parameter space is well covered by the line ratios, allowing us to investigate all input parameters. SHAP analysis shows that the temperature and density are the most important features, but the carbon and oxygen abundances are important in parts of the parameter space. Lastly, we find that we can group different types of ratios using UMAP. Conclusions. We show the chosen ratios are mostly sensitive to changes in the carbon initial abundance, together with the temperature and density. Especially the CN/HCN and HNC/HCN ratio are shown to be sensitive to the initial carbon abundance, making them excellent probes for this parameter. Out of the ratios, only CS/SO shows a sensitivity to the oxygen abundance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08410v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gijs Vermari\"en, Serena Viti, Johannes Heyl, Francesco Fontani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Origin of the Shell Structure in the Primary Outflow from IRAS 15398-3359</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08470v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: IRAS 15398-3359, a Class 0 protostar in Lupus I star forming region, is associated with three generations of outflows. The primary outflow, i.e., the most recent one, shows internal structure named ``shell structure'' in the near infrared emission map. The shell structure is also seen in the emission lines of CO, H$_2$CO, and others species. We find a similar structure in an underexpanded jet produced in aerodynamics and other engineering applications. A high pressure gas ejected through a nozzle expands to form a supersonic flow. When the pressure of the ejected gas becomes lower than that of the ambient gas, the jet is compressed to form a shock wave. The shock heated gas expands again to form substructures along the jet. We examine the similarity between the primary outflow of IRAS 15398-3359 and industrial underexpanded jet and the possibility that the shell structure of the former is due to repeated expansion and compression in the direction perpendicular to the jet propagation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08470v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoyuki Hanawa, Yuki Okoda, Yao-Lun Yang, Nami Sakai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of recaptures, ejections and mergers of stellar mass binaries over multiple encounters with SgrA*</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08499v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A common origin for a host of stellar phenomena in galactic centres is the tidal encounter between stellar binaries and a massive black hole (MBH), known as the ``Hills mechanism''. Following the encounter, binaries may disrupt into an ejected star and a captured one, they may merge, or survive to either fly away or come back for one or more subsequent encounters, until they are either disrupted or fly away. In this paper, we analyse how a binary's fate depends on its orbital parameters, by following its evolution through up to three subsequent pericentre passages. We choose an initial population of circular binaries on parabolic orbits. We present results from our restricted three-body formalism, whose strength lies in the ability to easily explore a multidimensional parameter space and make predictions independent of the binary physical properties. We find that fates depend strongly on orbital inclination, how deep the encounter is into the MBH tidal sphere and on the binary eccentricity, developed during encounters. Generally, non retrograde trajectories, high eccentricities or deep encounters produce disruptions preferentially. Disruption is the most common fate. A significant fraction of the surviving binaries fly away at velocities typically two orders of magnitude smaller than those of ejected stars. Multiple encounters boost disruptions by 20\% or more. Finally, using an example system, we investigate the effect of finite stellar sizes and lifetimes, showing that mergers occur 31\% of the time, and that disruptions are still boosted by 10\% through subsequent passages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08499v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Biancamaria Sersante, Zephyr Penoyre, Elena Maria Rossi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cracking the relation between mass and 1P-star fraction of globular clusters: III. Initial distributions of in-situ and ex-situ clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08626v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Galactic globular clusters consist of two main stellar populations, the pristine (1P) and polluted (2P) stars. The fraction of 1P stars in clusters, $F_{1P}$, is a decreasing function of the cluster present-day mass, $m_{prst}$. The information about cluster formation it contains has yet to be unlocked. Paper I demonstrated that the observed distribution $(m_{prst},F_{1P})$ of Galactic globular clusters can result from a pristine-star fraction that is inversely proportional to their birth mass, $m_{ecl}$. This relation was then calibrated with a fixed stellar mass threshold for 2P-star formation, $m_{th}$, i.e., $F_{1P}=m_{th}/m_{ecl}$. We now estimate the masses $m_{init}$ of Galactic globular clusters as they start their long-term gas-free evolution in the Galaxy and we map their behavior in the $(m_{init},F_{1P})$ space. Several dissolution time-scales are tested (with and without primordial mass segregation), each yielding its own initial cluster distribution $(m_{init},F_{1P})$. The $(m_{init},F_{1P})$ distributions are mapped according to cluster origin, with the emphasis on the Disk, Low-Energy and Gaia-Enceladus cluster groups of Massari et al. (2019). All three initial distributions $(m_{init},F_{1P})$ are more compact than their present-day counterparts since dynamical evolution scatters clusters in the $F_{1P}$ versus cluster-mass space. The Disk initial distribution is the tightest one and potential reasons for this are discussed. Its power-law representation allows us to generalize the initial mass threshold of Paper I and prompts us to represent the cluster $({\rm mass},F_{1P})$ distribution in a log-log space. No evidence is found suggesting that, initially, the pristine-star fraction of globular clusters depends on their metallicity on top of their mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08626v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Genevi\`eve Parmentier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter Velocity Distributions for Direct Detection: Astrophysical Uncertainties are Smaller Than They Appear</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07924v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The sensitivity of direct detection experiments depends on the phase-space distribution of dark matter near the Sun, which can be modeled theoretically using cosmological hydrodynamical simulations of Milky Way-like galaxies. However, capturing the halo-to-halo variation in the local dark matter speeds -- a necessary step for quantifying the astrophysical uncertainties that feed into experimental results -- requires a sufficiently large sample of simulated galaxies, which has been a challenge. In this work, we quantify this variation with nearly one hundred Milky Way-like galaxies from the IllustrisTNG50 simulation, the largest sample to date at this resolution. Moreover, we introduce a novel phase-space scaling procedure that endows every system with a reference frame that accurately reproduces the local standard-of-rest speed of our Galaxy, providing a principled way of extrapolating the simulation results to real-world data. The predicted speed distributions are consistent with the Standard Halo Model, a Maxwell-Boltzmann distribution peaked at the local circular speed and truncated at the escape speed. The dark matter-nucleon cross section limits placed by these speed distributions vary by ~60% about the median. This places the 1-sigma astrophysical uncertainty at or below the level of the systematic uncertainty of current ton-scale detectors, even down to the energy threshold. The predicted uncertainty remains unchanged when sub-selecting on those TNG galaxies with merger histories similar to the Milky Way. Tabulated speed distributions, as well as Maxwell-Boltzmann fits, are provided for use in computing direct detection bounds or projecting sensitivities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07924v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dylan Folsom, Carlos Blanco, Mariangela Lisanti, Lina Necib, Mark Vogelsberger, Lars Hernquist</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The full iron budget in simulated galaxy clusters: The chemistry between gas and stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07936</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07936v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Heavy chemical elements such as iron in the intra-cluster medium (ICM) of galaxy clusters are a signpost of the interaction between the gas and stellar components. Observations of the ICM metallicity in present-day massive systems, however, pose a challenge to the underlying assumption that the cluster galaxies have produced the amount of iron that enriches the ICM. We evaluate the iron share between ICM and stars within simulated galaxy clusters with the twofold aim of investigating the origin of possible differences with respect to observational findings and of shedding light on the observed excess of iron on the ICM with respect to expectations based on the observed stellar population. We evaluated the iron mass in gas and stars in a sample of 448 simulated systems with masses M500 &gt; 1e14 Msun at z=0.07. These were extracted from the high-resolution (352 cMpc/h)^3 volume of the Magneticum cosmological hydrodynamical simulations. We compared our results with observational data of low-redshift galaxy clusters. The iron share in simulated clusters features a shallow dependence on the total mass, and its value is close to unity on average. In the most massive simulated systems, the iron share is thus smaller than observational values by almost an order of magnitude. The dominant contribution to this difference is related to the stellar component, whereas the chemical properties of the ICM agree well overall with the observations. We find larger stellar mass fractions in simulated massive clusters, which in turn yield higher stellar iron masses, than in observational data. Consistently with the modelling, we confirm that the stellar content within simulated present-day massive systems causes the metal enrichment in the ICM. It will be crucial to alleviate the stellar mass discrepancy between simulations and observations to definitely assess the iron budget in galaxy clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07936v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Veronica Biffi, Elena Rasia, Stefano Borgani, Simona Ghizzardi, Umberto Maio, Klaus Dolag, Fabio Gastaldello, Luca Tornatore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galaxy cluster virial quantities from extrapolating strong lensing mass profiles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07945v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the radial total mass profiles of nine massive galaxy clusters ($M_\mathrm{200c}&gt;5\times10^{14}$ M$_\odot$) in the redshift range $0.2 &lt; z &lt; 0.9$. These clusters were observed as part of the CLASH, HFF, BUFFALO, and CLASH-VLT programs, that provided high-quality photometric and spectroscopic data. Additional high-resolution spectroscopic data were obtained with MUSE at the VLT. Our research is based on strong lensing analyses that rely on these measurements. From these data, we measure the projected total mass profiles of each galaxy cluster in our sample. We fit these mass profiles with one-component, spherically symmetric mass models including the Navarro-Frenk-White (NFW), non-singular isothermal sphere, beta model, and Hernquist profiles. We perform a Bayesian analysis to sample the posterior probability distributions of the free parameters of the models. We find that the NFW, Hernquist, and beta models are the most suitable profiles to fit the measured projected cluster total mass profiles. Moreover, we test the robustness of our results in a twofold way: we slightly modify the center of the projected mass profiles and the radial range of the considered region. We employ the results obtained with the Hernquist profile to compare our total mass estimates ($M_\mathrm{H}^\mathrm{tot} = M_\mathrm{H} (r\rightarrow + \infty)$), with the $M_\mathrm{200c}$ values from weak lensing studies. Through this analysis, we find scaling relations between $M_\mathrm{H}^\mathrm{tot}$ and $M_\mathrm{200c}$ and the value of the scale radius, $r_\mathrm{S}$, and $R_\mathrm{200c}$. Interestingly, we also find that the $M_\mathrm{200c}$ values, obtained by extrapolating the fitted total mass profiles, are very close to the weak lensing results. This feature can be exploited in future studies on clusters and cosmology, as it provides an easy way to infer galaxy cluster virial masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07945v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Maraboli, Claudio Grillo, Pietro Bergamini, Carlo Giocoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Map-level baryonification: unified treatment of weak lensing two-point and higher-order statistics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07949v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Precision cosmology benefits from extracting maximal information from cosmic structures, motivating the use of higher-order statistics (HOS) at small spatial scales. However, predicting how baryonic processes modify matter statistics at these scales has been challenging. The baryonic correction model (BCM) addresses this by modifying dark-matter-only simulations to mimic baryonic effects, providing a flexible, simulation-based framework for predicting both two-point and HOS. We show that a 3-parameter version of the BCM can jointly fit weak lensing maps' two-point statistics, wavelet phase harmonics coefficients, scattering coefficients, and the third and fourth moments to within 2% accuracy across all scales $\ell &lt; 2000$ and tomographic bins for a DES-Y3-like redshift distribution ($z \lesssim 2$), using the FLAMINGO simulations. These results demonstrate the viability of BCM-assisted, simulation-based weak lensing inference of two-point and HOS, paving the way for robust cosmological constraints that fully exploit non-Gaussian information on small spatial scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07949v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alan Junzhe Zhou, Marco Gatti, Dhayaa Anbajagane, Scott Dodelson, Matthieu Schaller, Joop Schaye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of stellar winds on the pair-instability supernova rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07959v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Very massive stars (VMSs, $M_{\star}$ $\geq$ 100 M$_{\odot}$) play a crucial role in several astrophysical processes. At low metallicity, they might collapse directly into black holes, or end their lives as pair-instability supernovae. Recent observational results set an upper limit of $0.7\,{}\mathrm{ yr}^{-1} \,{}\mathrm{ Gpc}^{-3}$ on the rate density of pair-instability supernovae in the nearby Universe. However, most theoretical models predict rates exceeding this limit. Here, we compute new VMS tracks with the MESA code, and use them to analyze the evolution of the (pulsational) pair-instability supernova rate density across cosmic time. We show that stellar wind models accounting for the transition between optically thin and thick winds yield a pair-instability supernova rate $\mathcal{R}_{\mathrm{PISN}}\sim{}0.1$ Gpc$^{-3}$ yr$^{-1}$ at redshift $z\sim{}0$, about two orders of magnitude lower than our previous models. We find that the main contribution to the pair-instability supernova rate comes from stars with metallicity $Z\sim{}0.001-0.002$. Stars with higher metallicities cannot enter the pair-instability supernova regime, even if their zero-age main sequence mass is up to 500 M$_\odot$. The main reason is that VMSs enter the regime for optically thick winds during the main sequence at metallicity as low as $Z\sim{4}\times{}10^{-4}$. This enhances the mass loss rate, quenching the growth of the He core and thus preventing the onset of pair-instability in later evolutionary stages. This result highlights the critical role of mass loss in shaping the final fate of very massive stars and the rate of pair-instability supernovae.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07959v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Simonato, Stefano Torniamenti, Michela Mapelli, Giuliano Iorio, Lumen Boco, Franca De Domenico-Langer, Cecilia Sgalletta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NuSTAR Detection of an Absorption Feature in ESP 39607: Evidence for an Ultra-fast Inflow?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07963v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the serendipitous discovery of an absorption feature at 4.8 keV in the NuSTAR spectra of ESP 39607, a Seyfert 2 galaxy at $z = 0.201$, observed in May 2023 and August 2024. The feature is detected in both observations with individual significance levels between 2 and 3$\sigma$, computed with multiple statistical methods. The combined probability of detecting it in both observations is $\gtrsim$4$\sigma$. The absorption feature is consistent with an ultra-fast inflow (UFI) potentially associated with Fe XXV or Fe XXVI K$\alpha$ transitions. The inferred inflow velocity is $\sim$0.15-0.20$c$, with an estimated launching radius of 22-89 $R_g$, depending on the assumed iron transition and whether radiation pressure is accounted for. Photoionization modeling associates the UFI primarily with Fe XXV K$\alpha$ absorption, blended with a minor contribution from Fe XXVI K$\alpha$. Alternative explanations, including associations with the warm-hot intergalactic medium or outflows of lighter elements, were investigated but found unlikely. If confirmed, this detection represents a rare example of a UFI, providing valuable evidence into extreme and/or non-standard accretion processes near supermassive black holes. Follow-up observations with higher-resolution X-ray spectroscopy, such as with XMM-Newton or XRISM, will be essential to confirm the nature of this feature and better constrain the physical mechanisms driving it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07963v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Peca, Michael J. Koss, Roberto Serafinelli, Claudio Ricci, C. Megan Urry, Giulia Cerini, Peter G. Boorman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The present-day cosmic phosphorus abundance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08428v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The present-day phosphorus abundance in the solar neighbourhood is determined from a sample of OB-type stars. This is in order to constrain the endpoint of the galactochemical evolution of phosphorus in the course of stellar nucleosynthesis over cosmic time and to provide an abundance baseline for the study of the depletion of phosphorus onto dust grains in the interstellar medium. A model atom for P II/III/IV based on a comprehensive new set of ab initio data for line transitions, photoionisations and electron-impact excitation was developed. Non-local thermodynamic equilibrium (non-LTE) line formation calculations with the codes DETAIL and SURFACE were conducted, based on LTE line-blanketed hydrostatic model atmospheres computed with the ATLAS12 code. High-resolution optical spectra for a sample of 42 apparently slowly rotating main-sequence OB-type stars and B-type supergiants in the solar vicinity within ~500 pc and beyond, out to a distance of ~2 kpc, were analysed. The non-LTE effects on the formation of the P II/III/IV lines are discussed. Non-LTE effects on the stellar abundances range from zero to ~0.3 dex. Where available in the spectra, ionisation balance between two phosphorus ionic species is achieved. Accurate and precise abundances are provided for the sample stars, statistical and systematic 1 sigma uncertainties are typically each well below 0.1 dex. The present-day cosmic phosphorus abundance in the solar neighbourhood is constrained to log(P/H)+12 = 5.36 +- 0.14, which is compatible with the solar photospheric abundance, but lower than derived by LTE analyses of neutral phosphorus lines in solar-type stars. The amount of phosphorus depleted onto dust grains is ~0.25 dex.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08428v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Aschenbrenner, K. Butler, N. Przybilla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical and near-infrared spectroscopy of quasars at $z&gt;6.5$: public data release and composite spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07612v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present optical and near-infrared (NIR) spectroscopic observations for a sample of $45$ quasars at $6.50 &lt; z \leq 7.64$ with absolute magnitudes at $1450$ {\AA} in the range $-28.82 \leq M_{1450} \leq -24.13$ and their composite spectrum. The median redshift and $M_{1450}$ of the quasars in the sample are $z_{\rm{median}}=6.71$ and $M_{1450,\rm{median}} \simeq -26.1$, respectively. The NIR spectra are taken with echelle spectrographs, complemented with additional data from optical long slit instruments, and then reduced consistently using the open-source Python-based spectroscopic data reduction pipeline PypeIt. The median of the mean signal-to-noise ratios per $110$ km s$^{-1}$ pixel in the J, H, and K band (median $\langle \rm{SNR}_{\lambda} \rangle$) is: median $\langle \rm{SNR}_{J} \rangle=9.7$, median $\langle \rm{SNR}_{H} \rangle=10.3$, and median $\langle \rm{SNR}_{K} \rangle=11.7$; demonstrating the good data quality. This work presents the largest medium/moderate-resolution sample of quasars at $z&gt;6.5$ from ground-based instruments. Despite the diversity in instrumental setups and spectral quality, the data set is uniformly processed and well-characterized, making it ideally suited for several scientific goals, including the study of the quasar proximity zones and damping wings, the Ly$\alpha$ forest, the intergalactic medium's metal content, as well as other properties such as the distribution of SMBH masses and Eddington ratios. Our composite spectrum is compared to others at both high and low-$z$ from the literature, showing differences in the strengths of many emission lines, probably due to differences in luminosity among the samples, but a consistent continuum slope, which proves that the same spectral features are preserved in quasars at different redshift ranges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07612v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf787</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Silvia Onorato, Joseph F. Hennawi, Jan-Torge Schindler, Jinyi Yang, Feige Wang, Aaron J. Barth, Eduardo Ba\~nados, Anna-Christina Eilers, Sarah E. I. Bosman, Frederick B. Davies, Bram P. Venemans, Chiara Mazzucchelli, Silvia Belladitta, Fabio Vito, Emanuele Paolo Farina, Irham T. Andika, Xiaohui Fan, Fabian Walter, Roberto Decarli, Masafusa Onoue, Riccardo Nanni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Turbulent Support (TS) and Global Hierarchical Collapse (GHC) models for molecular clouds compared. Differences, convergence, and myths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10406v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide a detailed comparison between the ``turbulent support'' (TS) and ``global hierarchical collapse'' (GHC) models for molecular clouds and star formation, their respective interpretations of the observational data, the features they share, and suggested tests and observations to discern between them. Also, we clarify common misconceptions in recent literature about the global and hierarchical nature of the GHC scenario, and briefly discuss the evolution of some aspects of both models toward convergence. TS assumes that star-forming molecular clouds and their substructures are either in approximate virial equilibrium between gravity and turbulence or overvirial, so that the cloud is either confined or expanding, and its substructures (clumps, filaments and cores) are produced by turbulent compressions. In this scheme, the star formation rate (SFR) is time-independent and determined by the turbulent and gravitational parameters of the clouds, in particular the virial parameter $\av$. Conversely, GHC assumes that most star-forming molecular clouds and their substructures are part of a continuous gravitationally-driven flow, each accreting from their parent structure. Therefore, GHC is an intrinsically {\it evolutionary} model for the clouds and their star formation rate, determined by the evolution of the collapse flow. It interprets nonthermal motions as a mixture of infall and turbulent components, with the relative importance of the former increasing as the objects become denser and/or more massive, and thus $\av$ is an {\it evolving variable} of the clouds. Tests that may provide clues to distinguishing between TS and GHC must take into account that the innermost parts of globally gravitationally bound structures may not locally appear bound, and thus the binding may have to be searched for at the largest scale of the structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10406v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrique V\'azquez-Semadeni, Aina Palau, Gilberto C. G\'omez, Griselda Arroyo-Ch\'avez, Christian Alig, Javier Ballesteros-Paredes, Vianey Camacho, Alessio Traficante, Alejandro Gonz\'alez-Samaniego, Manuel Zamora-Avil\'es, Andreas Burkert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galaxy populations in protoclusters at cosmic noon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08412v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the physical properties and redshift evolution of simulated galaxies residing in protoclusters at cosmic noon, to understand the influence of the environment on galaxy formation. This work is to build clear expectations for the ongoing ODIN survey, devoted to mapping large-scale structures at z=2.4, 3.1, and 4.5 using Ly$\alpha$-emitting galaxies (LAEs) as tracers. From the IllustrisTNG simulations, we define subregions centered on the most massive clusters ranked by total stellar mass at z=0 and study the properties of galaxies within, including LAEs. To model the LAE population, we take a semi-analytical approach that assigns Ly$\alpha$ luminosity and equivalent width based on the UV luminosities to galaxies in a probabilistic manner. We investigate stellar mass, star formation rate, major mergers, and specific star formation rate of the population of star-forming galaxies and LAEs in the field and protocluster environment and trace their evolution. We find that the overall shape of the UV luminosity function (LF) in simulated protocluster environments is characterized by a shallower faint-end slope and an excess on the bright end, signaling different formation histories for galaxies therein. The difference is milder for the Ly$\alpha$ LF. While protocluster galaxies follow the same SFR-$M_{\odot}$ scaling relation as average field galaxies, a larger fraction appears to have experienced major mergers in the last 200 Myr and as a result shows enhanced star formation at a ~60% level, leading to a flatter distribution in both SFR and $M_{\odot}$ relative to galaxies in the average field. We find that protocluster galaxies, including LAEs, begin to quench much earlier (z~0.8-1.6) than field galaxies (z~0.5-0.9); our result is in agreement with recent observational results and highlights the importance of large-scale environment on the overall formation history of galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08412v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Moira Andrews, M. Celeste Artale, Ankit Kumar, Kyoung-Soo Lee, Tess Florek, Kaustub Anand, Candela Cerdosino, Robin Ciardullo, Nicole Firestone, Eric Gawiser, Caryl Gronwall, Lucia Guaita, Sungryong Hong, Ho Seong Hwang, Jaehyun Lee, Seong-Kook Lee, Nelson Padilla, Jaehong Park, Roxana Popescu, Vandana Ramakrishnan, Hyunmi Song, F. Vivanco C\'adiz, Mark Vogelsberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decomposing Infrared Luminosity Functions into Star-Forming and AGN Components using CIGALE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08541v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study presents a comprehensive analysis of the infrared (IR) luminosity functions (LF) of star-forming (SF) galaxies and active galactic nuclei (AGN) using data from the ZFOURGE survey. We employ CIGALE to decompose the spectral energy distribution (SED) of galaxies into SF and AGN components to investigate the co-evolution of these processes at higher redshifts and fainter luminosities. Our CIGALE-derived SF and AGN LFs are generally consistent with previous studies, with an enhancement at the faint end of the AGN LFs. We attribute this to CIGALE's capability to recover low-luminosity AGN more accurately, which may be underrepresented in other works. We find evidence for a significant evolutionary epoch for AGN activity below $z \approx 2$, comparable to the peak of cosmic star formation at $z \approx 2$, which we also recover well. Based on our results, the gas supply in the early universe favoured the formation of brighter star-forming galaxies from high-redshift until $z=2$, below which the gas for SF becomes increasingly exhausted. In contrast, AGN activity peaked earlier and declined more gradually, suggesting a possible feedback scenario in which AGN positively influence SF.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08541v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel J. Lyon, Michael J. Cowley, Oliver Pye, Andrew M. Hopkins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Super-Jeans fragmentation in massive star-forming regions revealed by triangulation analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14610v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding the fragmentation of the gas cloud and the formation of massive stars remains one of the most challenging questions of modern astrophysical research. Either the gas fragments in a Jeans-like fashion, after which the fragments grow through accretion, or the fragmentation length is larger than the Jeans length from the start. Despite significant observational efforts, a consensus has not been reached. The key is to infer the initial density distribution upon which gravitational fragmentation occurs. Since cores are the products of the fragmentation process, the distances between adjacent cores serve as a scale indicator. Based on this observation, we propose a Delaunay triangulation-based approach to infer the density structure before the fragmentation and establish the link between density distribution and gas fragmentation length. We find that at low density, the fragmentation is Jeans-like, and at high densities, the core separations are larger than the prediction of the Jeans fragmentation. This super-Jeans fragmentation is a key step toward the formation of massive stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14610v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guang-Xing Li, Mengke Zhao, Xing Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C-19 and Hot, Wide, Star Streams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22966</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22966v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The C-19 star stream has the abundance characteristics of an unusually metal poor globular cluster but kinematically is uncharacteristically hot and wide for a cluster stream, having a line of sight velocity dispersion of 7 +/- 2 km/s and a 1-sigma width of 240 pc. We show that the tidal dissolution of an old, lower mass, globular cluster in a CDM galactic halo can create a hot, wide stream currently near orbital apocenter. A cosmological Milky Way n-body simulation motivates the parameters for an evolving Milky Way halo potential containing an orbiting subhalo population in which we model a star cluster progenitor of C-19. The same model parameters have been used for a GD-1 stream model. The ~7 km/s velocity dispersion is readily accomplished with an evolving CDM subhalo population, a progenitor cluster mass ~2x10^4 M_sun and an orbit that keeps the progenitor orbital pericenter within about 10 kpc of the Milky Way dark halo or its precursors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22966v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raymond G. Carlberg, Rodrigo Ibata, Nicolas F. Martin, Else Starkenburg, David S. Aguado, Khyati Malhan, Kim Venn, Kim Venn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sloan Digital Sky Survey Reverberation Mapping Project: Insights on Maximizing Efficiency in Lag Measurements and Black-Hole Masses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06885v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Multi-year observations from the Sloan Digital Sky Survey Reverberation Mapping (SDSS-RM) project have significantly increased the number of quasars with reliable reverberation-mapping lag measurements. We statistically analyze target properties, light-curve characteristics, and survey design choices to identify factors crucial for successful and efficient RM surveys. Analyzing 172 high-confidence ("gold") lag measurements from SDSS-RM for the H$\beta$, MgII, and CIV emission lines, we find that the Durbin-Watson statistic (a statistical test for residual correlation) is the most significant predictor of light curves suitable for lag detection. Variability signal-to-noise ratio and emission-line placement on the detector also correlate with successful lag measurements. We further investigate the impact of observing cadence on survey design by analyzing the effect of reducing observations in the first year of SDSS-RM. Our results demonstrate that a modest reduction in observing cadence to $\sim$1.5 weeks between observations can retain approximately 90% of the lag measurements compared to twice-weekly observations in the initial year. Provided similar and uniform sampling in subsequent years, this adjustment has a minimal effect on the overall recovery of lags across all emission lines. These results provide valuable inputs for optimizing future RM surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06885v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Homayouni, Yuanzhe Jiang, W. N. Brandt, C. J. Grier, Jonathan R. Trump, Yue Shen, Keith Horne, Patrick B. Hall, Scott F. Anderson, Luis C. Ho, D. P. Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The central engine of low-luminosity radio galaxy 3C 270 (NGC 4261)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10591v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the polarization spectra of the nucleus of 3C~270. We confirm that the polarization angle of both the continuum and the emission lines are close to perpendicular to the jet direction after careful correction of interstellar polarization, which indicates polar scattering. The Stokes flux spectrum resembles the total flux spectrum, with no need for a broad component from the Broad Line Region. Over 94\% of a sample of Seyfert I broad line profile would be significantly detected if present in our polarized flux spectrum. We favor the hypothesis that we are observing the continuum including any contribution from Radiatively Inefficient Accretion Flow and beamed synchrotron instead of a Big Blue Bump, as well as the innermost Narrow Line Region, through reflection. This makes 3C~270 the third known case, after NGC~4258 and Centaurus~A, where only narrow lines (and the continuum, if present) are scattered, with no evidence of an underlying Big Blue Bump.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10591v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengzhang Jiang, Robert Antonucci, Jose A. Acosta-Pulido, Patrick Ogle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shear-gravity transition determines the steep velocity dispersion-size relation in molecular clouds: confronting analytical formula with observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03027v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The velocity dispersion-size relation ($\sigma_{\rm v}\sim R^{\beta}$) is a crucial indicator of the dynamic properties of interstellar gas, where the slope is considered as $\beta \sim 0.5$. Recent observations reveal a steep velocity dispersion-size relation with the slope $\beta&gt; 0.6$, which cannot be explained by a single mechanism with only gravity ($\beta\sim0.5$) or shear ($\beta \sim 1$). We present a two-component model $\sigma_{\rm v_{total}} = \lambda_1 \sigma_{\rm v_{g}} + \lambda_2 \sigma_{\rm v_{shear}} = A[(GM/R)^{\frac{1}{2}} + f(R/t_{\rm shear})]$ to explain the steep velocity dispersion-size relation for clouds larger than several parsecs in observations from e.g. Miville-Desch\^{e}nes et al. (2017), Zhou et al. (2022) and Sun et al. (2024). We find that, above several parsecs, the velocity dispersion of small clouds is mainly caused by self-gravity, while large clouds are primarily affected by shear, and these two regimes are linked by a gradual transition with a transition scale $\sim100$ pc -- the scale height of the Galactic molecular gas disk. The variation of cloud velocity dispersion-size relation with the Galactocentric distance results from the variation of both cloud internal density structure and Galactic shear rate. Our two-component model captures how the dynamics of the molecular gas can be affected by both internal and external factors, and we expect it to be applied to data from galaxies with different physical conditions to reveal the physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03027v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/adc095</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Heng Xie, Guang-Xing Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Pitfalls of Using Lyman Alpha Damping Wings in High-z Galaxy Spectra to Measure the Intergalactic Neutral Hydrogen Fraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13899v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Lyman Alpha damping wing is seen in absorption against the spectra of high-redshift galaxies. Modeling of this wing is a way to measure the volume neutral hydrogen fraction of the Universe, as well as to measure the strength of HI absorption in the form of a damped Ly{\alpha} absorber (DLA). We use very high-quality ultraviolet spectra of low-z galaxies to create mock high-redshift, low-resolution spectra complete with a damping wing resulting from the IGM and HI absorption from local, dense gas to mimic current James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) observations of the early universe. The simulated spectra are used to test the ability to recover the "true" values of the column density of the DLA (N_DLA) and the volume neutral hydrogen fraction (x_HI) of the IGM through modified stellar continuum fitting. We find that the ability to recover the true values of N_DLA and x_HI simultaneously is compromised by degeneracies between these two parameters, and the spectral shape itself at low-resolution (R~100). The root mean squared error between the recovered and true column density of the DLAs is on the order of 1 dex. This error somewhat decreases with improved resolution (R~1000), but systematically underestimates N_DLA when Ly{\alpha} emission is present in the mock spectra. The recovered values of x_HI are poorly constrained and do not improve substantially with the higher resolution. We recommend accounting for these sources of uncertainty and biases when using galaxies' Ly{\alpha} damping wings to measure the intergalactic neutral hydrogen fraction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13899v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mason Huberty, Claudia Scarlata, Matthew J. Hayes, Simon Gazagnes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Carbon accretion and desorption by interstellar polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06248v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two key questions of the chemistry of Polycyclic Aromatic Hydrocarbons (PAHs) in the interstellar medium (ISM) are addressed: i) the way carbon is returned from PAHs to the interstellar gas after the very efficient accretion of C+ ions onto PAHs; ii) the PAH contribution to the high abundance of small carbon molecules observed in UV-irradiated regions. They are addressed based on the structure and stability of the various isomers of the complexes formed by PAHs and their cations with atomic carbon. Carbon complexes with coronene are studied by B3LYP/6-311+G**) calculations, in order to determine the behaviour of C+ and C complexes with larger pericondensed interstellar PAHs, which are thought to be dominant in the ISM. The most stable forms of [C-coronene]+ cation include 7C and 4C rings, C+ insertion into a CH bond, and a 5C ring with a short exocyclic cumulene chain, and similarly for neutral [C-coronene]. The subsequent evolution of similar complexes with pericondensed PAHs, in diffuse clouds, is discussed under the action of interstellar UV photons and H atoms, as a function of the PAH size. Despite the complexity of such a processing, it seems probable that, for small PAHs, these complexes efficiently lose a C2H2 molecule from repeated photodissociations. However, this conclusion needs to be confirmed by the identification of reaction paths and the computation of activation energies. The case of the evolution of larger [C-PAH] complexes is less clear. The processing may explain the observed balance between C+ and PAHs, at least in the diffuse ISM. The formation of C2H2 from PAH catalysis is a key input for the chemistry of small carbon molecules in diffuse clouds. C+ accretion might frequently form stable PAHs that contain a peripheral pentagonal ring and form a significant fraction of interstellar PAHs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06248v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202453102</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A, 696, A180 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alain Omont, Holger F. Bettinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euclid Quick Data Release (Q1). A first view of the star-forming main sequence in the Euclid Deep Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15314v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The star-forming main sequence (SFMS) is a tight relation observed between stellar masses and star formation rates (SFR) in a population of galaxies. This relation is observed at different redshifts, in various morphological, and environmental domains, and is key to understanding the underlying relations between a galaxy budget of cold gas and its stellar content. Euclid Quick Data Release 1 (Q1) gives us the opportunity to investigate this fundamental relation in galaxy formation and evolution. We complement the Euclid release with public IRAC observations of the Euclid Deep Fields, improving the quality of recovered photometric redshifts, stellar masses, and SFRs, as is shown both with simulations and a comparison with available spectroscopic redshifts. From Q1 data alone, we recover more than $\sim 30\,\mathrm{k}$ galaxies with $\log_{10} (M_\ast/M_\odot) &gt; 11$, giving a precise constraint of the SFMS at the high-mass end. We investigated the SFMS, in a redshift interval between $0.2$ and $3.0$, comparing our results with the existing literature and fitting them with a parameterisation taking into account the presence of a bending of the relation at the high-mass end, depending on the bending mass, $M_0$. We find good agreement with previous results in terms of $M_0$ values, and an increasing trend for the relation scatter at higher stellar masses. We also investigate the distribution of physical (e.g. dust absorption, $A_V$, and formation age) and morphological properties (e.g., S\'ersic index and radius) in the SFR--stellar mass plane, and their relation with the SFMS. These results highlight the potential of Euclid in studying the fundamental scaling relations that regulate galaxy formation and evolution in anticipation of the forthcoming Data Release 1.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15314v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Euclid Collaboration, A. Enia, L. Pozzetti, M. Bolzonella, L. Bisigello, W. G. Hartley, C. Saulder, E. Daddi, M. Siudek, G. Zamorani, P. Cassata, F. Gentile, L. Wang, G. Rodighiero, V. Allevato, P. Corcho-Caballero, H. Dom\'inguez S\'anchez, C. Tortora, M. Baes,  Abdurro'uf, A. Nersesian, L. Spinoglio, J. Schaye, Y. Ascasibar, D. Scott, E. Duran-Camacho, S. Quai, M. Talia, Z. Mao, N. Aghanim, B. Altieri, A. Amara, S. Andreon, N. Auricchio, H. Aussel, C. Baccigalupi, M. Baldi, A. Balestra, S. Bardelli, A. Basset, P. Battaglia, R. Bender, A. Biviano, A. Bonchi, E. Branchini, M. Brescia, J. Brinchmann, S. Camera, G. Ca\~nas-Herrera, V. Capobianco, C. Carbone, J. Carretero, S. Casas, F. J. Castander, M. Castellano, G. Castignani, S. Cavuoti, K. C. Chambers, A. Cimatti, C. Colodro-Conde, G. Congedo, C. J. Conselice, L. Conversi, Y. Copin, F. Courbin, H. M. Courtois, M. Cropper, A. Da Silva, H. Degaudenzi, G. De Lucia, A. M. Di Giorgio, C. Dolding, H. Dole, F. Dubath, C. A. J. Duncan, X. Dupac, S. Dusini, A. Ealet, S. Escoffier, M. Fabricius, M. Farina, R. Farinelli, F. Faustini, S. Ferriol, F. Finelli, S. Fotopoulou, M. Frailis, E. Franceschi, P. Franzetti, S. Galeotta, K. George, B. Gillis, C. Giocoli, P. G\'omez-Alvarez, J. Gracia-Carpio, B. R. Granett, A. Grazian, F. Grupp, L. Guzzo, S. Gwyn, S. V. H. Haugan, J. Hoar, W. Holmes, I. M. Hook, F. Hormuth, A. Hornstrup, P. Hudelot, K. Jahnke, M. Jhabvala, B. Joachimi, E. Keih\"anen, S. Kermiche, A. Kiessling, B. Kubik, M. K\"ummel, M. Kunz, H. Kurki-Suonio, Q. Le Boulc'h, A. M. C. Le Brun, D. Le Mignant, S. Ligori, P. B. Lilje, V. Lindholm, I. Lloro, G. Mainetti, D. Maino, E. Maiorano, O. Mansutti, O. Marggraf, M. Martinelli, N. Martinet, F. Marulli, R. Massey, D. C. Masters, S. Maurogordato, E. Medinaceli, S. Mei, M. Melchior, Y. Mellier, M. Meneghetti, E. Merlin, G. Meylan, A. Mora, M. Moresco, L. Moscardini, R. Nakajima, C. Neissner, S. -M. Niemi, J. W. Nightingale, C. Padilla, S. Paltani, F. Pasian, K. Pedersen, W. J. Percival, V. Pettorino, S. Pires, G. Polenta, M. Poncet, L. A. Popa, F. Raison, R. Rebolo, A. Renzi, J. Rhodes, G. Riccio, E. Romelli, M. Roncarelli, E. Rossetti, B. Rusholme, R. Saglia, Z. Sakr, A. G. S\'anchez, D. Sapone, B. Sartoris, J. A. Schewtschenko, M. Schirmer, P. Schneider, T. Schrabback, M. Scodeggio, A. Secroun, G. Seidel, S. Serrano, P. Simon, C. Sirignano, G. Sirri, J. Skottfelt, L. Stanco, J. Steinwagner, C. Surace, P. Tallada-Cresp\'i, A. N. Taylor, H. I. Teplitz, I. Tereno, S. Toft, R. Toledo-Moreo, F. Torradeflot, I. Tutusaus, L. Valenziano, J. Valiviita, T. Vassallo, G. Verdoes Kleijn, A. Veropalumbo, Y. Wang, J. Weller, A. Zacchei, F. M. Zerbi, I. A. Zinchenko, E. Zucca, M. Ballardini, E. Bozzo, C. Burigana, R. Cabanac, A. Cappi, D. Di Ferdinando, J. A. Escartin Vigo, L. Gabarra, M. Huertas-Company, J. Mart\'in-Fleitas, S. Matthew, N. Mauri, R. B. Metcalf, A. Pezzotta, M. P\"ontinen, C. Porciani, I. Risso, V. Scottez, M. Sereno, M. Tenti, M. Viel, M. Wiesmann, Y. Akrami, I. T. Andika, S. Anselmi, M. Archidiacono, F. Atrio-Barandela, C. Benoist, K. Benson, P. Bergamini, D. Bertacca, M. Bethermin, A. Blanchard, L. Blot, H. B\"ohringer, S. Borgani, A. S. Borlaff, M. L. Brown, S. Bruton, A. Calabro, B. Camacho Quevedo, F. Caro, C. S. Carvalho, T. Castro, F. Cogato, T. Contini, A. R. Cooray, O. Cucciati, S. Davini, F. De Paolis, G. Desprez, A. D\'iaz-S\'anchez, J. J. Diaz, S. Di Domizio, J. M. Diego, P. -A. Duc, Y. Fang, A. G. Ferrari, P. G. Ferreira, A. Finoguenov, A. Fontana, F. Fontanot, A. Franco, K. Ganga, J. Garc\'ia-Bellido, T. Gasparetto, V. Gautard, E. Gaztanaga, F. Giacomini, F. Gianotti, G. Gozaliasl, M. Guidi, C. M. Gutierrez, A. Hall, S. Hemmati, C. Hern\'andez-Monteagudo, H. Hildebrandt, J. Hjorth, J. J. E. Kajava, Y. Kang, V. Kansal, D. Karagiannis, K. Kiiveri, C. C. Kirkpatrick, S. Kruk, J. Le Graet, L. Legrand, M. Lembo, F. Lepori, G. Leroy, G. F. Lesci, J. Lesgourgues, L. Leuzzi, T. I. Liaudat, A. Loureiro, J. Macias-Perez, G. Maggio, M. Magliocchetti, E. A. Magnier, C. Mancini, F. Mannucci, R. Maoli, C. J. A. P. Martins, L. Maurin, M. Miluzio, P. Monaco, C. Moretti, G. Morgante, C. Murray, K. Naidoo, A. Navarro-Alsina, S. Nesseris, F. Passalacqua, K. Paterson, L. Patrizii, A. Pisani, D. Potter, M. Radovich, P. -F. Rocci, S. Sacquegna, M. Sahl\'en, D. B. Sanders, E. Sarpa, C. Scarlata, A. Schneider, M. Schultheis, D. Sciotti, E. Sellentin, F. Shankar, L. C. Smith, S. A. Stanford, K. Tanidis, G. Testera, R. Teyssier, S. Tosi, A. Troja, M. Tucci, C. Valieri, A. Venhola, D. Vergani, G. Verza, P. Vielzeuf, N. A. Walton, E. Soubrie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass Modeling the Andromeda Dwarf Galaxies: Andromeda VI and Andromeda XXIII</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04475v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurately mapping the mass profiles of low mass dwarf spheroidal (dSph) galaxies allows us to test predictions made by dark matter (DM) models. To date, such analyses have primarily been performed on Milky Way (MW) satellites. Meanwhile, the Andromeda Galaxy (M31) is home to 35 known dwarf galaxies, yet only two have been successfully mass-modeled so far. In order to better understand the nature of dark matter, a more comprehensive study of Local Group dwarfs is necessary. In this study, we have undertaken a dynamical study of two higher-luminosity Andromeda dwarf galaxies: Andromeda VI (And VI) and Andromeda XXIII (And XXIII). We infer an enclosed mass for And VI of M(r &lt; r$_{\rm{h}}$) = (4.9 $\pm$ 1.5) $\times$ 10$^{7}$ M$_{\odot}$, corresponding to a mass-to-light ratio of $[M/L]_{r_{\rm{h}}}$ = (27.1 $\pm$ 8.2) M$_{\odot}$/L$_{\odot}$. We infer an enclosed mass for And XXIII of M(r &lt; r$_{\rm{h}}$) = (3.1 $\pm$ 1.9) $\times$ 10$^{7}$ M$_{\odot}$, corresponding to a mass-to-light ratio of $[M/L]_{\rm{r_{h}}}$ = (90.2 $\pm$ 53.9) M$_{\odot}$/L$_{\odot}$. Using the dynamical Jeans modeling tool, GravSphere, we determine And VI and And XXIII's dark matter density at 150 pc, finding $\rho_{\rm{DM,VI}}$(150 pc) = (1.4 $\pm$ 0.5) $\times$ 10$^{8}$ M$_{\odot}$ kpc$^{-3}$ and $\rho_{\rm{DM,XXIII}}$(150 pc) = 0.5$\substack{+0.4 \\ -0.3} \times$ 10$^{8}$ M$_{\odot}$ kpc$^{-3}$. Our results make And VI the first mass-modeled M31 satellite to fall into the cuspy regime, while And XXIII has a lower density, implying either a more cored central dark matter density, or a lowering of the density through tides. This adds And XXIII to a growing list of M31 dwarfs with a central density lower than most MW dwarfs and lower than expected for isolated dwarfs in the Standard Cosmology. This could be explained by the M31 dwarfs having experienced stronger tides than their Milky Way counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04475v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Connor S. Pickett, Michelle L. M. Collins, R. Michael Rich, Justin I. Read, Emily J. E. Charles, Nicolas Martin, Scott Chapman, Alan McConnachie, Alessandro Savino, Daniel R. Weisz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The "Dark-Matter Dominated" Galaxy Segue 1 Modeled with a Black Hole and no Dark Halo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06198v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The dwarf spheroidal galaxy, Segue 1, is thought to have one of the largest ratios of dark matter to stellar mass. Using orbit-based dynamical models, we model Segue 1, including a dark halo and a central black hole. The best-fit model requires a black hole mass of $4 \pm 1.5 \times 10^5\ M_\odot$. The value of the black hole mass is the same with or without a dark halo. The mass-to-light ratio of the stars is poorly constrained by the dynamical modeling, reflecting that Segue 1 is dominated by mass other than stars. Dynamical models that exclude a black hole provide a worse fit and require a dark halo with very small scale radii of around 100 parsecs. Additionally, the zero black hole models require a stellar orbital distribution that is highly radially biased. The model with a black hole provides an orbital structure that is close to isotropic, more similar to other well-studied systems. We argue that the two-parameter models of stars and black hole provide a better description of Segue 1 than the three-parameter models of stars and two dark halo components. Additional support for a central black hole comes from a significant increase in the central rotation. Using individual velocities, we measure a rotation amplitude of $9.0 \pm 2.4\ \mathrm{km\ s^{-1}}$. Segue 1 is likely being tidally stripped at large radii, and we might be witnessing the remnant nucleus of a more massive system. Alternatively, given the high black hole mass relative to the stellar mass, Segue 1 is analogous to Little Red Dots seen in the early Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06198v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathaniel Lujan, Karl Gebhardt, Richard Anantua, Owen Chase, Maya H. Debski, Claire Finley, Loraine V. Gomez, Om Gupta, Alex J. Lawson, Izabella Marron, Zorayda Martinez, Connor A. Painter, Yonatan Sklansky, Hayley West</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bridging the micro-Hz gravitational wave gap via Doppler tracking with the Uranus Orbiter and Probe Mission: Massive black hole binaries, early universe signals and ultra-light dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02306v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: With the recent announcement by NASA's \textit{Planetary Science and Astrobiology Decadal Survey 2023-2032}, a priority flagship mission to the planet Uranus is anticipated. Here, we explore the prospects of using the mission's radio Doppler tracking equipment to detect gravitational waves (GWs) and other analogous signals related to dark matter (DM) over the duration of its interplanetary cruise. We develop a methodology to stack tracking data and account for time varying detector geometry, thereby constructing the sensitivity of the mission to GWs over the wide frequency range of $3\times 10^{-9}$ Hz to $10^{-4}$ Hz. We find that the mission has the potential to fill the gap between pulsar timing and space-based-interferometry GW observatories. If improvements in reducing \textit{Cassini} era noise by a factor of $\sim$10 are implemented, we forecast the detection of $\mathcal{\mathcal{O}}(\rm{few})$ individual massive black hole binaries using two independent population models. Additionally, we determine the mission's sensitivity to both astrophysical and primordial stochastic gravitational wave backgrounds, as well as its capacity to test, or even confirm via detection, ultralight DM models. In all these cases, the tracking of the spacecraft over its interplanetary cruise would enable coverage of unexplored regions of parameter space, where signals from new phenomena in our Universe may be lurking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02306v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenz Zwick, Deniz Soyuer, Daniel J. D'Orazio, David O'Neill, Andrea Derdzinski, Prasenjit Saha, Diego Blas, Alexander C. Jenkins, Luke Zoltan Kelley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Gaussianity Beyond the Scalar Sector: A Search for Tensor and Mixed Tensor-Scalar Bispectra with Planck Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10595v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Primordial gravitational waves could be non-Gaussian, just like primordial scalar perturbations. Although the tensor two-point function has thus-far remained elusive, the three-point function could, in principle, be large enough to be detected in Cosmic Microwave Background temperature and polarization anisotropies. We perform a detailed analysis of tensor and mixed tensor-scalar non-Gaussianity through the Planck PR4 bispectrum, placing constraints on eleven primordial templates, spanning various phenomenological and physical regimes including modifications to gravity, additional fields in inflation, and primordial magnetic fields. All analysis is performed using modern quasi-optimal binned estimators, and yields no evidence for tensor non-Gaussianity, with a maximum detection significance of $2\sigma$. Our constraints are derived primarily from large-scales (except for tensor-scalar-scalar models), and benefit greatly from the inclusion of $B$-modes. Although we find some loss of information from binning, mask effects and residual foreground contamination, our $f_{\rm NL}$ bounds improve over those of previous analyses by $(20-700)\%$, with six of the eleven models being analyzed for the first time. Unlike for scalar non-Gaussianity, future low-noise experiments such as LiteBIRD, the Simons Observatory and CMB-S4, will yield considerable improvement in tensor non-Gaussianity constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10595v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver H. E. Philcox, Maresuke Shiraishi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Fast, Analytic Empirical Model of the Gaia Data Release 3 Astrometric Orbit Catalog Selection Function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.00654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.00654v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In June 2022, the Gaia mission released a catalog of astrometric orbital solutions for 168,065 binary systems, by far the largest such catalog to date. The catalog's selection function is difficult to characterize because of choices made in its construction. Understanding the catalog's selection function is required to model and interpret its contents. We use a combination of analytic and empirical prescriptions to construct a function that computes the probability that a binary with a given set of properties would have been published in the Gaia Data Release 3 astrometric orbit catalog. This is a complementary approach to the more accurate but significantly more computationally expensive approach of El-Badry et al. (2024). We also construct a binary population synthesis model to validate our characterization of the selection function, finding good agreement with the actual Gaia NSS catalog, with the exception of the orbital eccentricity distribution. The NSS catalog suggests high-eccentricity orbits are relatively uncommon at intermediate periods $100 \lesssim P_{orb} \lesssim 1000$ days. As an example application of the selection function, we estimate the Gaia DR3 detection probabilities of the star + BH binaries Gaia BH1 and BH2, and find them to be 0.38 and 0.27, respectively. Compared to the values obtained by detailed modeling in El-Badry et al. (2024), the probabilities are identical for BH1, and within a factor of 2 for BH2. We also estimate the population of Sun-like star + BH binaries in the Galaxy to be $\sim 3000$ for $100 &lt; P_{orb} &lt; 400$ day, $&lt; 800$ for $400 &lt; P_{orb} &lt; 1000$ day, and $&lt; 12,000$ for $1000 &lt; P_{orb} &lt; 1500$ day.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.00654v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Casey Y. Lam (Carnegie Observatories), Kareem El-Badry (Caltech), Joshua D. Simon (Carnegie Observatories)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is MOND necessarily nonlinear?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.07106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.07106v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The iconic, deep-MOND-limit (DML) relation between acceleration and mass, $a\sim (M\mathcal{A}_0)^{1/2}/r$, implies that, in MOND, accelerations cannot be linear in the mass distribution ($\mathcal{A}_0\equiv Ga_0$ is the DML constant, and $a_0$ the MOND acceleration). This leads to important idiosyncracies of MOND, such as a breakdown of the strong equivalence principle, and the resulting ``external-field effect''. I show that the DML axioms are, in themselves, consistent with a, possibly unique, nonrelativistic, action-based, linear formulation of the DML. This model suffers from important drawbacks, which may make it unacceptable as a basis for a full-fledged MOND theory. The model is unique among MOND theories propounded to date not only in being linear -- hence not exhibiting an external-field effect, for example -- but in constituting a modification of both Newtonian inertia and Newtonian gravity. This linear and time-local model inspires and begets several, one-parameter families of models. One family employs nonlinear, time-nonlocal kinetic terms, but still linear gravitational-field equations. Other families generalize the DMLs of AQUAL and QUMOND, modifying gravity as well as inertia. All families employ fractional time derivatives and possibly fractional Laplacians. At present, I cannot base some acceptable MOND theory on these models -- for example, I cannot offer a sensible umbrella theory that interpolates between these DML models and Newtonian dynamics. They are, however, quite useful in elucidating various matter-of-principle aspects of MOND; e.g., they help to understand which predictions follow from only the basic tenets of MOND -- so-called primary predictions -- and which are secondary, i.e., theory dependent. The models may also show the way to a wider class of MOND theories. (Abridged.)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.07106v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.104033</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 104033 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mordehai Milgrom</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
