<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.GA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA</link>
    <description>astro-ph.GA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.GA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 05:01:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Scavenger hunt: Selection of obscured active galactic nuclei combining multiband optical variability and colors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07109</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07109v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As wide-field optical surveys such as Vera Rubin Observatory's Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) begin operations, time-domain astronomy is facing a data revolution, paving the road for new, expanded variability studies. This work leverages the complementary power of optical variability and color selection to identify active galactic nuclei (AGN), focusing on optimizing the identification of obscured AGN, typically more challenging to distinguish from inactive galaxies based on optical variability alone. The analysis is designed to provide valuable insights in the context of performance preview for the LSST, albeit using a scaled-down version of the LSST dataset. We present the first combined AGN selection based on g+r+i band light curves from the VST-COSMOS survey, spanning 3.3 yr. We identify AGN candidates independently in each band using a random forest (RF) classifier trained on features mainly related to optical variability, along with six optical/infrared colors and a morphology indicator. We subsequently merge the three band-specific samples in order to enhance selection purity and reliability. We then focus on defining a subset of features that significantly improve the identification of obscured AGN. The RF classifiers yield a consistent performance across the three bands, highlighting the critical role of contamination. Using the combined three-band plus color selection we successfully recover $58^{+9}_{-8}\%$ of all AGN and $69^{+10}_{-8}\%$ of the known obscured AGN that have been independently confirmed in all three bands. When requiring confirmation in two out of the three bands, these fractions increase to $69^{+10}_{-8}\%$ and $80^{+10}_{-9}\%$, respectively. We also demonstrate that, while combining variability features with colors is crucial to improve obscured AGN selection, relying solely on color features returns a markedly higher contamination rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07109v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202556680</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Demetra De Cicco, Stefano Cavuoti, Maurizio Paolillo, Vincenzo Petrecca, Ylenia Maruccia, Paula S\'anchez-S\'aez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the dynamical evolution of binary stars in multiple-population globular clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07119v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The presence of multiple stellar populations in globular clusters leads to a complex dynamical environment that significantly influences the evolution of binary stars, which in turn impacts the evolution of the cluster itself. For this study, we used a series of Monte Carlo simulations run with the MOCCA code to investigate the long-term dynamical evolution of binary stars in globular clusters hosting two distinct stellar populations. We explored how global binary properties such as incidence, fraction, and spatial distribution evolve over time due to the unique dynamical environment associated with each population. Our results show how binaries in the more centrally concentrated second population (P2) experience increased rates of hardening and disruption relative to the first population (P1), leading to distinct radial profiles in binary incidence and fraction. We also demonstrate the difference in spatial mixing timescales for binaries compared to single stars, where binary stars in each population retain some memory of their initial configurations even after complete single star mixing. Additionally, we investigated the formation and evolution of mixed binaries (binaries composed of a P1 component and a P2 component), which form primarily within the core through dynamical interactions. Finally, we studied main sequence--white dwarf binaries and find that they represent a larger fraction of binaries in P1 compared to P2. The results of this paper highlight the interplay between cluster dynamics and the evolution of binary stars and how binaries can act as tracers of the cluster's initial conditions and dynamical evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07119v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Bruce, E. Vesperini, A. Askar, E. Bortolan, M. Giersz, J. Hong, A. Hypki, A. P. Milone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AGN versus Star-formation: A MUSE Analysis of NGC 1365</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07124v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Active galactic nuclei (AGN) and star formation feedback may heat and remove gas from galaxies in a process that quenches ongoing star formation and shapes the evolution of galaxies. Potential impacts from these processes can be seen in the complex and interconnected signatures of AGN and star formation activity throughout a galaxy. Here, we analyze archival integral field unit (IFU) data for the nearby Seyfert galaxy, NGC 1365, as observed with the Multi Unit Spectroscopic Explorer (MUSE) instrument on the Very Large Telescope (VLT). Our analysis probes the ionization and kinematic properties of NGC 1365 at high spatial resolution over unprecedentedly large physical scales (approximately 40 kpc), allowing us to trace the effects of feedback throughout nearly an entire galaxy. We use these optical IFU data in conjunction with observations from the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) and Chandra X-ray Observatory to analyze and compare maps of emission line flux, ionization state, star formation, and gas kinematics. In doing so, we identify a region of BPT-identified unexpectedly high ionization relative to surrounding areas in the star forming arms, and work to identify its source, finding that shock heating may play a significant role. Results from this analysis allow us to place constraints on the relative impact of AGN and star formation processes on the star forming gas in NGC 1365, as well as begin to inform our understanding on the global impacts of feedback in galaxy populations as a whole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07124v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyla Mullaney, Kelly E. Whalen, Jenna Cann, Kimberly Weaver, Jeffrey McKaig, Sara Doan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The stellar velocity anisotropy of strong lensing massive elliptical galaxies and its role in the inference of the Hubble parameter $H_0$ using spatially resolved kinematics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07159v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One of the biggest challenges in cosmology, the Hubble Tension, requires independent measurements of $H_0$, and strong lensing with time-delay cosmography is a promising avenue. The inclusion of spatially resolved kinematic data helps break the mass--sheet degeneracy, a key limitation in strong lensing. Kinematics, however, suffers from its own degeneracy due to unknown stellar velocity anisotropy, which can bias galaxy mass profile inferences. We investigate the bias in $H_0$ using a sample of ten massive elliptical galaxies at $z=0.2$ from the Illustris $TNG100$ simulations. We generate mock line-of-sight velocity-dispersion maps resembling JWST NIRSpec observations and test four anisotropy models: Osipkov--Merritt (OM), Mamon--Lokas (ML), constant $\beta$, and a generalized--OM (gOM) profile, under both kinematics-only and joint kinematics plus strong lensing analyses. We find a sub-percent average bias in $H_{0}$ across ten galaxies with joint modeling for three models: $+0.2 \pm 1.6\%$ (ML), $-0.9 \pm 1.9\%$ (constant) and $-0.9 \pm 1.6\%$ (gOM), with $\sim 5\%$ scatter. Joint modeling reduces bias, improves precision, and mitigates outlier results. Overall, the gOM model best recovers galaxy parameters and delivers the most accurate $H_{0}$ relative to posterior uncertainties considering both analyses. However, the single-parameter OM model produces large systematic biases: with kinematics only data, $H_{0}$ errors can exceed $20\%$, and even with joint modeling, produces an overall bias of $+11.5 \pm 1.3\%$ (OM). The higher bias in OM is unlikely to average out across an ensemble of galaxies. Our findings highlight the impact of anisotropy assumptions on $H_{0}$ inference and, more broadly, in galaxy dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07159v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vishal Verma, Quinn Minor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Massive Star Population in the Sextans A Dwarf Galaxy from HST UV Photometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07177v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We build a catalog of massive (M&gt;$8~$M$_\odot$) main sequence stars in the \mbox{metal-poor} ($\sim0.1~$Z$_\odot$) dwarf irregular galaxy Sextans A. HST WFC3 UV photometry in the 275 and 336 nm wideband filters is arranged in a Color-Magnitude Diagram (CMD), and overlaid on top of stellar evolutionary tracks from the MIST library. The star properties (mass, age, etc.) are computed with a Finite Element (FE) interpolation of the stellar tracks. The FE method, originally developed for solid mechanics problems, provides a general framework for interpolating fields inside domains of complex geometry. Besides the interpolated properties, the algorithm computes their gradients with respect to the photometry. These sensitivities provide a direct an efficient estimate of the associated uncertainties. Our catalog contains 655 stars, with the most massive one estimated at $58\pm11~$M$_\odot$. A comparison with a ground-based spectroscopic census of OB stars yields only 8 matches, evidencing the minimal overlap between both datasets. The mass estimates derived from the UV CMD and the spectral classification are in good agreement for the majority of O-type stars found in both datasets. Our catalog provides an extensive list of candidates for followup spectroscopic observation, which could improve our understanding of the early evolutionary stages of massive \mbox{low-metallicity} stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07177v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Flores, Elena Fantino, Giuseppina Battaglia, Antonio Aparicio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clump-Scale Dust Attenuation in Epoch of Reionization Galaxies: Spatially Resolved Properties from FirstLight Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07347v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding dust attenuation in galaxies at both integrated and spatially resolved scales is fundamental for accurately determining the physical properties of galaxies. Recent high-spatial-resolution observations with ALMA and JWST enable investigations of spatially resolved properties in high-redshift galaxies ($z \gtrsim 6$), but spatial variations in dust properties remain poorly constrained. We use cosmological zoom-in simulations combined with post-processing dust radiative transfer calculations for 376 clumpy galaxies at $z=6$-$9$ with stellar masses of $M_* \gtrsim 10^9 \, M_\odot$. For each system, we investigate dust attenuation and re-emission properties for three components: system-integrated, individual clumps, and diffuse regions. We find that system-integrated attenuation curves are grayer than the Calzetti curve, even when assuming MW- or SMC-type dust. Attenuation curves of individual clumps are even grayer, while diffuse regions exhibit steeper curves owing to enhanced scattering in optically thin environments. Since the effects of optical depth and dust-star geometry are intrinsically degenerate in attenuation curves, we introduce a toy model based on the IRX-$\Delta\beta$ plane, where $\Delta\beta$ denotes the difference between attenuated and intrinsic UV slopes. Applying this framework, we find that clumps have dust column densities approximately an order of magnitude higher than system-integrated values and exhibit co-spatial or dust-extended geometries. In contrast, system-integrated attenuation reflects star-extended geometries driven by contributions from optically thin diffuse regions. We apply this framework to REBELS-IFU galaxies at $z \sim 7$ and find good agreement with our simulation predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07347v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yurina Nakazato, Kosei Matsumoto, Akio K. Inoue, Daniel Ceverino, Takashi Hosokawa, Daisuke Toyouchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Galactic Nuclei and STaR fOrmation in Nearby Galaxies AGNSTRONG. III. A Study on Ionized and Warm Molecular Gas Outflows of 6 Type-2 AGNs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07392v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Active galactic nucleus (AGN)-driven gas outflows are one of the best tracers of AGN feedback in action, as these powerful outflows expel/heat or compress the surrounding interstellar medium (ISM), thus quenching or enhancing star-forming activity in their hosts. Studying the kinematics of outflows in different gas phases is crucial for comprehending how AGNs impact the ISM within their host galaxies. However, the differences in the physical natures of ionized and warm molecular gas outflows remain largely unexplored. To obtain a complete picture of AGN outflows and their feedback effects, we present a study of both ionized and warm molecular gas outflows in six type-2 AGNs ($z&lt;0.1$) that exhibit strong ionized outflows in previous optical observations. Utilizing the Triple Spectrograph and Double Spectrograph instruments on the Palomar 200-inch Hale Telescope, we conduct spatially resolved measurements in the slit direction of strong emission lines from both ionized and warm molecular gas, such as $\rm [O\ III]$, $\rm Pa\alpha$, $\rm H_{2}$ 1-0 S(1), etc., allowing for a direct comparison of their outflow properties. One out of six AGNs shows significant ionized and warm molecular outflows in near-infrared bands, exhibiting the most powerful kinematics and highest luminosity. A positive correlation between the kinematics and AGN luminosity is shown, suggesting that more luminous AGNs, which reflect higher levels of AGN activity, tend to have a greater impact on the gases, probably driving the outflows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07392v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruisong Xia, Chen Qin, Huynh Anh N. Le, Yongquan Xue, Shifu Zhu, Mengqiu Huang, Hao Liu, Xiaozhi Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Properties of Galactic Outflows Driven by Starburst at Cosmic Noon: Insights from Hydrodynamical Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07592v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate starburst-driven galactic outflows in low-mass galaxies ($9.0 &lt; \log(M_*/M_\odot) &lt; 10.0$) at cosmic noon using high-resolution 3D hydrodynamical simulations based on a framework that can reproduce the multiphase outflows in M82. The simulations produce starbursts lasting 20-30 Myr, with peak star formation rates of 2-68 M$_\odot \,\rm{yr}^{-1}$. Outflow properties vary strongly with time, radial distance to galaxy center, stellar mass, and gas fraction, exhibiting velocities of 50-1000 $\,\rm{km\,s}^{-1}$, mass outflow rates of 0.3-20 M$_\odot \,\rm{yr}^{-1}$, and mass loading factors, $\eta_\mathrm{M}$, of 0.24-6.26. The cool phase ($8000 &lt; T \le 2 \times 10^4$ K) dominates the outflow, and properties of the cool and warm phases are broadly consistent with observations. At $M_*= 10^{9.5}\,M_\odot$, average $\eta_\mathrm{M}$ for the total, cool, and warm phases are $\sim$1.2, 0.75, and 0.25, respectively. The mass loading factor decreases with increasing galaxy stellar mass, but increases with star formation rate. Given strong temporal and spatial evolution, scaling slopes from limited samples should be treated with caution. Our total $\eta_\mathrm{M}$ values are higher than FIRE-2 by 0.06 dex but lower than EAGLE and TNG50 by 0.50 and 0.84 dex. Accounting for methodological differences in outflow measurement reduces these gaps to 0.2-0.4 dex, suggesting that part of the discrepancy between observations and simulations reported in the literature may arise from inconsistent definitions and measurement methods, though differences in individual phases persist. Larger observational and simulation samples, together with consistent methods for measuring outflow properties, are required to draw robust conclusions about the scaling relations of galactic outflows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07592v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huan Chen, Weishan Zhu, Xue-Fu Li, Tian-Rui Wang, Antonios Katsianis, Long-Long Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>K-DRIFT Science Theme: Galaxies in the Faint Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08283v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Low-surface-brightness (LSB) structures serve as evidence of the intricate mass assembly of galaxies, and dedicatedly studying them promises to give us profound insights into the evolutionary history of galaxies. Furthermore, delving into the properties of star formation (SF) in the LSB regime can broaden our understanding of SF activity in regions characterized by low surface gas density, thereby shedding light on fundamental cosmic processes. However, systematic uncertainties may hamper the exploration of the LSB universe by limiting detectable SB levels. Indeed, despite dedicated advancements in telescope and observing techniques over decades, achieving ultra-deep photometric depths in optical wavelengths remains a formidable challenge. To overcome this challenge and explore the LSB universe that we have yet to see, we have been developing a novel telescope called K-DRIFT. This paper outlines the telescope's specification and describes various LSB features we aim for, explicitly focusing on nearby individual galaxies. To further advance the capabilities of the K-DRIFT survey, focused on LSB detection, we present several feasible research topics that utilize other survey data together and discuss the role of LSB observation in understanding the evolution of galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08283v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Woowon Byun, Yongmin Yoon, Jongwan Ko, Yun Hee Lee, Gain Lee, Ho Seong Hwang, Cristiano G. Sabiu, Kwang-il Seon, Kyungwon Chun, Jihye Shin, Jinsu Rhee, Jae-Woo Kim, Jaewon Yoo, Jaehyun Lee, Sang-Hyun Chun, Hong Soo Park, Soung-Chul Yang, Sungryong Hong, Jeehye Shin, Hyowon Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CFHT MegaCam Two Deep Fields Imaging Survey (2DFIS) I: Overview</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08312v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the Two Deep Fields Imaging Survey (2DFIS), a wide-field imaging program conducted with the Canada-France-Hawaii Telescope (CFHT) targeting two astrophysically distinct regions: one containing a repeating fast radio burst (FRB) source and another hosting a candidate of a rotating galaxy cluster. Achieving a depth of r~26mag, the survey enables a search for faint optical counterparts and environmental signatures associated with the FRB, while high-quality photometric and galaxy shape measurements in the cluster field support a weak-lensing analysis of its mass distribution. This paper describes the observing strategy and data processing methodology adopted for 2DFIS, including the use of the LSST Science Pipelines with survey-specific adaptations for CFHT/MegaCam data. We outline a complete workflow for transforming raw CFHT exposures into science-ready data products, including calibrated single-epoch images, multi-band coadded mosaics, and extensive source catalogs. These data products provide the foundation for ongoing and future studies of FRB host environments, cluster mass reconstruction, and related cosmological applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08312v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Binyang Liu, Wentao Luo, Martin Kilbinger, Shenming Fu, Ian Dell'Antonio, Liping Fu, Xian Zhong Zheng, Yi-fu Cai, Cheng Jia, Ning Jiang, Qinxun Li, Yicheng Li, Shurui Lin, Christopher J. Miller, Surhud S. More, Huiyuan Wang, Yibo Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CFHT MegaCam Two Deep Fields Imaging Survey (2DFIS) II: Decoding the Lensing Profile of a "Rotating" Cluster with Deep CFHT Imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08360v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a multi-wavelength analysis of the galaxy cluster RXCJ0110.0+1358 ($z=0.058$), a rotating cluster candidate, combining deep CFHT imaging, SDSS photometry, spectroscopic redshifts, and XMM-Newton X-ray observations. We find a notable discrepancy between the optical and X-ray views: while optical data reveal a pronounced bimodal galaxy distribution with significant kinematic substructure signatures, the X-ray emission exhibits a single, smoothly extended component centered on the BCG. Our weak lensing analysis resolves this discrepancy by revealing that the mass is predominantly concentrated in the southeast ($\log M_{200}/M_\odot = 14.04_{-0.40}^{+0.24}$), while the northwestern substructure has a negligible mass ($\sim 10^{13} M_\odot$). This immense mass disparity rules out the dynamical possibility of a rotating system. We demonstrate that the apparent optical bimodality arises from the projection of a filament, which led optical group-finding algorithms to misclassify these galaxies as cluster members. This contamination creates a spurious substructure that mimics a rotation signal and leads to an overestimation of the luminosity-based halo mass, resolving the observed inconsistencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08360v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yicheng Li, Liping Fu, Wentao Luo, Binyang Liu, Wei Du, Martin Kilbinger, Calum Murray, Christopher J. Miller, Ray Wang, David Turner, Lance Miller, Dezi Liu, Mario Radovich, Jean-Paul Kneib, Huanyuan Shan, Kaiwen Mai, Zicheng Wang, Haoran Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stratification of the AGN-Driven multi-phase outflows in the dwarf Seyfert galaxy NGC 4395</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08447v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a multi-wavelength study of nuclear outflows in the nearby dwarf Seyfert galaxy NGC~4395, which hosts an intermediate-mass black hole. Using \textit{JWST}/NIRSpec and MIRI IFU spectroscopy (1.66--28.6~$\mu$m), together with ALMA and Gemini/GMOS data, we probe the ionised and molecular gas on parsec scales. The JWST nuclear spectra reveal 134 emission lines, including H\,\textsc{i}, He, numerous fine-structure lines, H$_2$ rotational/ro-vibrational transitions, and several PAH bands. Modelling of the H$_2$ rotational lines reveals three warm/hot molecular components ($T\!\approx\!580$, 1480, and 2900~K), along with a cold ($&lt;50$~K) phase traced by ALMA CO(2--1). Outflow signatures are detected in cold and warm/hot molecular gas, in H\,\textsc{i}, and in 36 fine-structure lines spanning ionisation potentials of 7.6--300~eV. Ionised outflow velocities range from 127 to 716~km\,s$^{-1}$, with blueshifted and redshifted components consistent with a stratified biconical geometry. The cold molecular gas shows a mass outflow rate nearly 1--2 orders of magnitude larger than that of the warm/hot molecular and ionised phases. The kinetic coupling efficiency is 0.003--0.12\% for the coronal-line gas and 0.4--1.4\% for the H\,\textsc{i} outflow, indicating that only the low-ionisation gas significantly impacts the surrounding ISM. Outflow velocity and the fraction of flux in the outflowing component increase with ionisation potential, implying that the most highly ionised gas originates closest to the AGN and is most efficiently accelerated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08447v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Payel Nandi, Luis Colina, Rogemar A. Riffel, Miguel Pereira Santaella, C. S. Stalin, D. J. Saikia, Javier Alvarez-Marquez, Markus Kissler-Patig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GaLactic and Extragalactic All-sky Murchison Widefield Array survey eXtended (GLEAM-X) III: Galactic Plane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08475v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the third data release for the Galactic and Extragalactic All-Sky Murchison Widefield Array eXtended (GLEAM-X) survey, covering = 3800 deg2 of the southern Galactic Plane (GP) with \ang{233} &lt; l &lt; \ang{44} and |b| &lt; \ang{11} across a frequency range of 72 - 231 MHz divided into 20 sub-bands. GLEAM-X observations were taken using the "extended" Phase-II configuration of the Murchison Widefield Array (MWA), which features baselines ranging from approximately 12 m to 5 km. This configuration limits sensitivity to the diffuse structure of the GP, with an angular resolution range of about 45'' to 2'. To achieve lower noise levels while being sensitive to a wide range of spatial scales (45''- \ang{15}), we combined these observations with the previous Galactic and Extragalactic All-Sky Murchison Widefield Array (GLEAM) survey. For the area covered, we provide images spanning the whole frequency range. A wide-band image over 170 - 231 MHz, with RMS noise of = 3 - 6 mJy/beam and source position accuracy within 1 arcseconds, is then used to perform source-finding, which yields 98,207 elements measured across 20 x 7.68 MHz frequency bands. The catalogue is 90% complete at 50 mJy within \ang{233} &lt; l &lt; \ang{324} and at 125 mJy in \ang{290} &lt; l &lt; \ang{44}, while it is 99.3% reliable overall. All the images and the catalogue are available online for download.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08475v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/pasa.2025.10094</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>S. Mantovanini, N. Hurley-Walker, K. Ross, S. W. Duchesne, G. Anderson, T. J. Galvin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Tidal Disruption Events and Compact Object Plunges in Nuclear Star Clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08574v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study tidal disruption events (TDEs) and compact object inspirals in nuclear star clusters (NSCs) hosting a central supermassive black hole (SMBH), focusing on their role in SMBH growth. Using the STARDISK version of the direct N-body code NBODY6++GPU, we perform pilot simulations with two improved models: one for mass fallback from TDEs and another for compact object plunges based on orbital decay timescales. Our results show that mass accretion via TDEs peaks within the first 2 Myr and decreases more rapidly for higher initial SMBH masses, with roughly half the disrupted stellar debris being accreted. Compact object accretion is confined mostly to orbits with pericenters between 4 and 27 Schwarzschild radii and is suppressed by an order of magnitude when inspiral criteria are applied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08574v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Cho, Kai Wu, Francesco Flammini Dotti, Taras Panamarev, Rainer Spurzem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An unusual pair of interstellar HI features and a related white dwarf star inside the HI cavity surrounding the Upper Sco-Cen OB2 Association</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08756v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two mysterious unresolved HI structures at velocities of +12 and -6 km/s were discovered in high resolution 21-cm survey data in the direction of a faint white dwarf star. Examination of the HI morphology in this area of sky shows that the star and HI features exists in a large cavity in interstellar HI surrounding the Upper Sco-Cen OB2 Association. The cavity may have been created by an ancient supernova. It is hypothesized that the pair of HI features and filamentary HI structure found in its immediate vicinity may be the remnants of a planetary nebula some 3 x 10^5 years old that have cooled to the point that the gas is neutral and emitting the 21-cm spectral line. This remnant has maintained the morphological characteristics of the original planetary nebula because it expanded into a volume of space relatively devoid of interstellar gas that would otherwise have absorbed any traces of the original nebula.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08756v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gerrit L. Verschuur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CHIMPS2: The physical properties and star formation efficiency of molecular gas in the Central Molecular Zone</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08824v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present Local Thermodynamic Equilibrium (LTE) estimates of the physical properties and star formation efficiency (SFE) of molecular gas in the Central Molecular Zone (CMZ), using new $^{12}$CO $J=2\to1$ observations from the James Clerk Maxwell Telescope. Combined with CHIMPS2 $^{12}$CO and $^{13}$CO $J=3\to2$, and SEDIGISM $^{13}$CO $J=2\to1$ data, we estimate a median excitation temperature of $T_{\rm ex} = 11$K for $^{13}$CO throughout the CMZ, with peaks exceeding $120$K in the Sgr B1/B2 complex. Cooler gas dominates around Sgr A and nearby clouds. We derive a median H$_{2}$ column-density of $N(\mathrm{H}2) = 2 \times 10^{22}$ cm$^{-2}$ and a total $^{13}$CO-traced gas mass of $M_{\rm gas} = 7 \times 10^6$ M$_\odot$, consistent with previous estimates when accounting for spatial coverage. The instantaneous SFE is assessed using Hi-GAL compact sources detected at 70-$\mu m$ and 160--500-$\mu m$. The 70-$\mu m$-bright SFE, tracing current star formation, is modest overall but elevated in Sgr B1/B2, the Arches cluster, and Sgr C. In contrast, the 160--500-$\mu m$ SFE, tracing cold pre-stellar gas, is more broadly enhanced, particularly in the dust ridge clouds and towards negative longitudes surrounding Sgr C. The contrasting distributions suggest an evolutionary gradient in SFE, consistent with a transition from dense, cold gas to embedded protostars. Our results imply that the CMZ may be enter a more active phase of star formation, with large reservoirs of gas primed for future activity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08824v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. M. King, T. J. T. Moore, S. N. Longmore, D. J. Eden, J. D. Henshaw, A. J. Rigby, R. Rani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The contribution of neutral gas to Faraday tomographic data at low frequencies. A first extensive comparison between real and synthetic data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08839v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: LOFAR observations of diffuse interstellar polarization at meter wavelengths reveal intricate polarized intensity structures with an unexpected correlation with neutral HI filaments that could not be reproduced in simulations with low cold neutral medium (CNM) abundance. We investigate whether MHD simulations of thermally bi-stable neutral interstellar medium, with a range of CNM fraction, can reproduce the properties of the 3C196 field, the high Galactic latitude test field. Using 50 pc simulations with varying levels of turbulence and compressibility, we generated synthetic 21 cm and synchrotron observations, including instrumental noise and beam effects, for different line-of-sight orientations relative to the magnetic field. We developed MOOSE, a code to generate synthetic synchrotron polarization and Faraday tomography. We also developed a metric based on the HOG algorithm, to quantify the relative contribution of cold and warm neutral medium structures to the Faraday tomographic data. The synthetic observations show levels of polarization intensity and RM values comparable to the 3C196 field, indicating that thermal electrons associated with the neutral HI phase can account for a significant fraction of the synchrotron polarized emission at 100-200 MHz. The simulations consistently reveal a correlation between CNM and Faraday tomographic structures that depends on turbulence level, magnetic field orientation, and observational noise, but only weakly on CNM fraction. We found slightly weaker CNM-Synchrotron polarized emission correlation level than observed in the 3C196 field. These results suggest that low-frequency polarimetric observations provide a valuable probe of magnetic-field morphology in the multi-phase Solar-neighborhood ISM, while simultaneously underscoring the need for improved modeling of the turbulent, multi-phase, and partially ionized interstellar medium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08839v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack Berat, Marc-Antoine Miville-Desch\^enes, Andrea Bracco, Patrick Hennebelle, Jeremy Scholtys</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AMICO galaxy clusters in KiDS-1000: Splashback radius from weak lensing and cluster-galaxy correlation function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07114v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the splashback radius analysis of the Adaptive Matched Identifier of Clustered Objects (AMICO) galaxy cluster sample in the fourth data release of the Kilo Degree Survey (KiDS). The sample contains 9049 rich galaxy clusters within $z\in[0.1,0.8]$, with shear measurements available for 8730 of them. We measure and model the stacked reduced shear, $g_{\rm t}$, and the cluster-galaxy correlation function, $w_{\rm cg}$, in bins of observed intrinsic richness, $\lambda^*$, and redshift, $z$. Building on the methods employed in recent cosmological analyses, we model the average splashback radius, $r_{\rm sp}$, of the underlying dark matter halo distribution, accounting for the known systematic uncertainties affecting measurements and theoretical models. By modelling $g_{\rm t}$ and $w_{\rm cg}$ separately, in the cluster-centric radial range $R\in[0.4,5]$ $h^{-1}$Mpc, we constrain $r_{\rm sp}$, the mass accretion rate, $\Gamma$, and the relation between $\mathcal{R}_{\rm sp}\equiv r_{\rm sp}/r_{200\rm m}$ and the peak height, $\nu_{200\rm m}$, over the mass range $M_{200\rm m}\in[0.4,20]$ $10^{14}h^{-1}$M$_\odot$. The two probes provide consistent results that also agree with $\Lambda$-cold dark matter model predictions. Our $\mathcal{R}_{\rm sp}$ constraints are consistent with those from previous observations. For $g_{\rm t}$ and $w_{\rm cg}$, we achieve a precision of 14% and 10% per cluster stack, respectively. The higher precision of $w_{\rm cg}$, enabled by its combination with weak-lensing constraints on the mass-richness relation, highlights the complementarity of lensing and clustering in measuring $r_{\rm sp}$ and constraining the properties of the infalling material region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07114v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. F. Lesci, C. Giocoli, F. Marulli, M. Romanello, L. Moscardini, M. Sereno, M. Maturi, M. Radovich, G. Castignani, H. Hildebrandt, L. Ingoglia, E. Puddu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPHEREx as a frontier for infrared transients: Classification of new Galactic FU Ori outbursts and classical novae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07129v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate proof-of-concept of a new strategy for studying infrared (IR) transients enabled by the newly launched SPHEREx space mission, by leveraging its synergy with the NEOWISE space mission. With its fifteen year baseline and all-sky mid-IR coverage, NEOWISE provides an excellent avenue to discover thousands of slowly evolving infrared outbursts. With its all-sky spectro-photometric coverage and mid-IR sensitivity matching NEOWISE, SPHEREx is uniquely positioned to provide low-resolution IR spectra for the vast majority of these outbursts, several of which are too obscured for ground-based spectroscopic classification. As a demonstration of this approach, we present SPHEREx spectra for eight Galactic transients identified in NEOWISE. This sample includes two previously known FU Orionis-type (FUOr) outbursts whose SPHEREx spectra exhibit clear signatures of cool molecular absorption and three known classical novae showing strong emission lines in SPHEREx. Using these sources as templates, we identify two new FUOrs and one previously missed Galactic nova. Our results highlight the potential of SPHEREx for systematic explorations of the relatively underexplored dynamic infrared sky.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07129v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viraj Karambelkar, Kishalay De, Lynne A. Hillenbrand, J. L. Sokoloski, Danielle Frostig, Julianne Dalcanton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of a lithium dip in ~35 Myr "Snake" Open Clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07367v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the discovery of a lithium dip (Li-dip) in the stellar "Snake" (age = $35 \pm 5$ Myr), challenging the classical view that Li-dips emerge only at ages $\gtrsim 150$ Myr. Using high-resolution spectra from GALAH DR4 ($R \sim 28,000$) for 211 member stars, we identify a clear depletion feature in a $T_{\mathrm{eff}}$ range of 6200--6800 K with a depth of $\Delta A(\mathrm{Li}) \approx 0.40$ dex. Our analysis reveals two key advances: the Li-dip appears $\gtrsim 100$ Myr earlier than the previous observations, and within the dip temperature range, a significant correlation is found between rotational velocity and lithium depletion. Specifically, fast rotators ($v \sin i &gt; 25$ km s$^{-1}$) exhibit stronger lithium depletion than slow rotators ($v \sin i &lt; 25$ km s$^{-1}$). This trend suggests that faster rotators develop stronger rotational shear at the convective-radiative boundary, which enhances turbulent mixing and accelerates lithium destruction. It is also found that the lower temperature edge of the lithium plateau can reach as low as 5500 K for the young open clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07367v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yun-Yi Zhang, Hai-Jun Tian, Jian-Rong Shi, Cheng-Cheng Xie, Xiang-Ming Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmology with one galaxy: An analytic formula relating $\Omega_{\rm m}$ with galaxy properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07651v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Standard cosmological analyses typically treat galaxy formation and cosmological parameter inference as decoupled problems, relying on population-level statistics such as clustering, lensing, or halo abundances. However, classical studies of baryon fractions in massive galaxy clusters have long suggested that gravitationally bound systems may retain cosmological information through their baryonic content. Building on this insight, we present the first analytic and physically interpretable cosmological tracer that links the matter density parameter, $\Omega_m$, directly to intrinsic galaxy-scale observables, demonstrating that cosmological information can be extracted from individual galaxies. Using symbolic regression applied to state-of-the-art hydrodynamical simulations from the CAMELS project, we identify a compact functional form that robustly recovers $\Omega_m$ across multiple simulation suites (IllustrisTNG, ASTRID, SIMBA, and Swift-EAGLE), requiring only modest recalibration of a small number of coefficients. The resulting expression admits a transparent physical interpretation in terms of baryonic retention and enrichment efficiency regulated by gravitational potential depth, providing a clear explanation for why $\Omega_m$ is locally encoded in galaxy properties. Our work establishes a direct, interpretable bridge between small-scale galaxy physics and large-scale cosmology, opening a complementary pathway to cosmological inference that bypasses traditional clustering-based statistics and enables new synergies between galaxy formation theory and precision cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07651v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kito Liao, Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro, Romain Teysser, Natal\'i S. M. de Santi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Viscosity on Sloshing Cold Fronts in Galaxy Clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07661v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The viscous properties of the intracluster medium (ICM) remain poorly constrained. Cold fronts-sharp discontinuities formed during cluster mergers-offer a potential avenue to probe the effective viscosity of the ICM. Velocity shear across these fronts should generate Kelvin-Helmholtz instabilities (KHI), unless viscosity or magnetic tension suppresses them. We perform cluster merger simulations incorporating four ICM viscosity models: (A) inviscid, (B) isotropic Spitzer viscosity, (C) anisotropic Braginskii viscosity, and (D) Braginskii viscosity limited by microinstabilities. The isotropic Spitzer viscosity (case B) strongly suppresses KHI, producing smooth cold front surfaces, while the inviscid (A) and microinstability-limited (D) cases show prominent ripples. The Braginskii case (C) yields intermediate suppression. We also vary the plasma $\beta$ parameter ($\beta \approx$ 100 and 1600) to examine how a changing magnetic field strength affects the results. Stronger magnetic fields further suppress KHI, leading to smoother fronts and reduced differences between different viscosity models, while also widening the range of permitted pressure anisotropies when microinstability-based limiters are present. These results indicate that both viscosity and magnetic fields play crucial roles in stabilising sloshing cold fronts in galaxy clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07661v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming-Hsueh Hsieh, H. -Y. Karen Yang, John ZuHone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisted Pseudodisk and Asymmetric Mass Accretion on the Circumstellar Disk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07741</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07741v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We model gas inflow patterns onto circumstellar disks and the evolution of the pseudodisk using three-dimensional resistive MHD simulations. Starting from a prestellar core without turbulence and with a misalignment between the initial magnetic field and rotation axis, the simulations are performed for $\sim10^5$ yr after protostar formation. After disk formation, the magnetic field around the disk becomes significantly distorted due to the disk rotational motion. Consequently, the structure of the pseudodisk also evolves into a complex morphology. As a result, both accretion onto the disk and outflow become asymmetric and anisotropic. Accretion to the disk occurs primarily through narrow-channel flows or streams. The time evolution of the infalling envelope leads to non-steady accretion onto the disk, which in turn causes variability in the mass accretion onto the central protostar. This study demonstrates that complex infalling envelope structures and channelized accretion flows onto the disk naturally arise even without assuming turbulence or external asymmetric inflows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07741v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahiro N. Machida, Shingo Hirano, Shantanu Basu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pulsars and Millisecond Pulsars I: Advancements, Open Questions and finding Gaps via statistical insights</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08065v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a statistical study of pulsars and millisecond pulsars (MSPs) based on multiwavelength observations in the Galactic Field and Globular Clusters. We examine their emission properties, timing behavior, and spatial distributions, and discuss how theoretical models are required to interpret these observational trends. We focus on the magnetic field spin relation, including spin up through accretion in binaries and spin down driven by magnetic dipole radiation. Using numerical tools such as NBODY6++GPU, CMC, and COMPASS, we explore how dynamical interactions and binary evolution shape the properties of compact objects. Despite major progress, several open questions remain regarding binary interactions, magnetic field evolution, and the incorporation of pulsar physics into large scale simulations. Our analysis highlights the need for improved modeling frameworks to better understand the formation pathways and long term evolution of pulsars and MSPs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08065v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.52526/25792776-24.71.2-351 10.52526/25792776-24.71.2-351</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications of BAO, 71(2), 351-359, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Maria Rah, Areg Mickaelian, Francesco Flammini Dotti, Rainer Spurzem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pulsars and Millisecond Pulsars II: Deep diving into the Evolutionary Mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08106v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This second paper in our series investigates the evolutionary mechanisms that shape pulsars and millisecond pulsars (MSPs) across different astrophysical environments. We focus on the physical processes that govern spin evolution, magnetic field decay, binary interactions, and recycling pathways. Using observational constraints together with theoretical models, we examine how accretion, magnetic braking, and dynamical encounters contribute to the long-term evolution of compact objects. We also explore how these mechanisms differ between the Galactic Field and Globular Clusters, where stellar densities and interaction rates vary significantly. By integrating insights from population studies and numerical tools such as NBODY6++GPU, CMC, and COMPASS, we aim to clarify the dominant channels that lead to the formation and transformation of pulsars and MSPs. Our results highlight key uncertainties in current models and outline the physical ingredients required for more accurate simulations of compact object evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08106v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.52526/25792776-25.72.1-55</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications of BAO, Vol. 72, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Maria Rah, Rainer Spurzem, Francesco Flammini Dotti, Areg Mickaelian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A comprehensive catalogue of high-mass X-ray binaries in the Large Magellanic Cloud detected during the first eROSITA all-sky survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08152v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Magellanic Clouds, the closest star-forming galaxies to the Milky Way, offer an excellent environment to study high-mass X-ray binaries. While the Small Magellanic Cloud has been thoroughly investigated with over 120 systems identified, the Large Magellanic Cloud has lacked a complete survey due to its large angular size. Most prior studies targeted central or high-star-formation regions. The SRG/eROSITA all-sky surveys now enable a comprehensive coverage of the LMC, particularly due to its close vicinity to the south ecliptic pole. This work aims to improve our understanding of the HMXB population in the LMC by building a flux-limited catalogue. This allows us to compare sample properties with those of HMXB populations in other nearby galaxies. Using detections during the first eROSITA all-sky survey, we cross-matched X-ray positions with optical and infrared catalogues to identify candidate HMXBs. We assigned flags based on multi-wavelength follow-up observations and archival data, using properties of known LMC HMXBs. These flags defined confidence classes for our candidates. We detect sources down to X-ray luminosities of a few $10^{34}$ erg s$^{-1}$, resulting in a catalogue of 53 objects, including 28 confirmed HMXBs and 21 new eROSITA detections. We identify several likely supergiant systems, including a candidate supergiant fast X-ray transient with phase-dependent flares. We find three Be stars with likely white dwarf companions. Two of the Be/WD candidates show steady luminosities across four eROSITA scans, unlike the post-nova states seen in the majority of previous Be/WD reports. Our catalogue is the first to cover the entire LMC since the ROSAT era, providing a basis for statistical population studies. Using the HMXB population, we estimate the LMC star-formation rate to be $(0.22^{+0.06}_{-0.07})$ M$_{\odot}$yr$^{-1}$, which is in agreement with other tracers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08152v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202555693</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>D. Kaltenbrunner, C. Maitra, F. Haberl, J. Bodensteiner, D. Bogensberger, D. A. H. Buckley, M. R. L. Cioni, J. Greiner, I. Monageng, A. Udalski, G. Vasilopoulos, R. Willer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Host Galaxies of Binary Black Hole Mergers with Next-Generation Gravitational Wave Detector Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08459v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Identifying the host galaxy of a binary black hole (BBH) merger detected via gravitational waves (GWs) remains a challenge due to the absence of electromagnetic counterparts and the large localization volumes produced by current-generation detectors. A confident host association would provide stellar population properties to constrain BBH formation channels and enable measurements of cosmological parameters such as the Hubble constant, H0. We simulate BBH mergers in nearby (z&lt;0.25) host galaxies to evaluate the feasibility of host identification with future GW detector networks, including configurations with the planned LIGO-India detector and third-generation detectors such as the Einstein Telescope (ET) and Cosmic Explorer (CE). We construct two injection grids to explore variations in BBH mass, distance, and directional sensitivity, and infer localization volumes using the Fisher Information Matrix (FIM)-based parameter estimation implemented through BILBY. To assess the prospects for unique host identification, we introduce a set of diagnostics: theoretical comoving volume thresholds for galaxies of a given stellar mass, derived from galaxy stellar mass functions, a metallicity-based volume threshold motivated by progenitor environment models, stellar mass fractions to quantify candidate host prominence, and the probability of chance alignment (p_c). These metrics provide ways to evaluate host associations and constrain BBH formation channels. We find that future networks that include ET and CE localize BBH mergers to volumes smaller than those theoretical thresholds, implying potentially unique host identification, out to ~1000 Mpc at a rate of ~100 yr^{-1}. While associations for individual events may remain uncertain, our framework is well-suited to population-level analyses, enabling constraints on BBH formation scenarios in the era of next-generation GW detector networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08459v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumedha Biswas, Andrew Levan, Peter G. Jonker, Kendall Ackley, Gregory Ashton, Nikhil Sarin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A mapping method of age estimation for binary stars: Application to the $\alpha$ Centauri system A and B</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08879v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given the wealth of data provided by Gaia and the upcoming PLATO mission, it is essential to improve stellar models to obtain accurate stellar ages. Our objective is to apply a mapping technique to estimate the age of a system and the initial chemical composition. We also evaluate the influence of observational uncertainties in mass and heavy-element mixtures on results. We applied an inverse calibration method to the evolution of a multiple stellar system, assuming that the stars share the same age and initial chemical composition. This approach determines age, the initial mass fractions of helium ($Y_{ini}$) and heavy elements ($Z_{ini}$), as well as the convective mixing-length parameters ($\alpha_A $ and $\alpha_B$). It uses the observed luminosities ($L_A$ and $L_B$), radii ($R_A$ and $R_B$), and surface chemical compositions ($Z/X_A$ and $Z/X_B$). We used the most recent observational data for $M$, $R$, $L$, and $[Fe/H]$ of $\alpha$ Centauri A and B as input data for our method. We compared two assumptions for the $Z/X$ ratio, following the results for the solar composition. For an assumed high solar $Z/X_\odot =0.0245$, we obtain an age of $7.8 \pm 0.6$ Ga, $Y_{ini} = 0.284 \pm 0.004$, and $Z_{ini} = 0.0335 \pm 0.0015$. For a low solar $Z/X_\odot = 0.0181$, the derived age is $8.7 \pm 0.6$ Ga, $Y_{ini} = 0.267 \pm 0.008$, and $Z_{ini} = 0.025 \pm 0.002$. Observational errors in the stellar masses of $\pm$0.002 lead to an age error of 0.6 Ga. Overshooting of $0.05-0.20H_p$ at the boundary of the convective core increases the age by $0.6-2.1$ Ga. Models with higher $Z/X$ and radiative cores, with ages of $7.2-7.8$ Ga, appear preferable and show better agreement with the observed asteroseismic frequencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08879v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Th\'evenin, V. A. Baturin, A. V. Oreshina, P. Morel, S. V. Ayukov, L. Bigot, A. B. Gorshkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of a double white dwarf in the Galactic globular cluster NGC 6397</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08898v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Binaries in the cores of globular clusters are known to prevent the gravitational collapse of the cluster, and simulations predict that the core of NGC 6397 contains a large number of white dwarfs (WDs), of which many are expected to be part of a binary system. In this work, we report the discovery of a compact binary system consisting of two WDs in the centre of the Galactic globular cluster NGC 6397. The system, known in the literature as NF1, was observed as part of a MUSE radial-velocity survey aiming at characterizing the binary population in the centre of NGC 6397. The spectral analysis of NF1 provides an effective temperature of 16000 K and a surface gravity (log g) of 5.72 (cgs), which is consistent with an extremely low-mass He-core WD nature. This is further supported by the mass of 0.23 +/- 0.03 Msun obtained from fitting the star's spectral energy distribution using its HST magnitude in various filters. The system has a circular orbit with a period of 0.54 days. The radial velocities show a large semi-amplitude of 200 km/s, implying a minimum mass of 0.78 Msun for the invisible companion, which is likely another WD, or a neutron star if the inclination of the system is smaller than about 50 deg. Some significant residuals in radial velocity remain with our best orbital solution and we tested whether a model with a third body can explain these deviations. While this possibility seems promising, additional measurements are needed to confirm whether the star is actually part of a triple system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08898v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian G\"ottgens, Marilyn Latour, Ulrich Heber, Sebastian Kamann, Kyle Kremer, Sven Martens, Stefan Dreizler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is the nitrogen-rich source PN K4-47 a true planetary nebula?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08959v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: PN K4-47 is a young planetary nebula that exhibits shock-excited bipolar lobes and a complex molecular environment, with the highest number of molecules detected within a planetary nebula. It has been questioned whether K4-47 is indeed a `typical' planetary nebula, or may be more exotic in nature. We examine this question using optical imaging and spectroscopy, and sub-millimetre and radio interferometry. Our observations spatially resolve the sub-millimetre environment of K4-47 for the first time. We find elongated CO (2-1) emission along a similar PA to the optical bipolar outflow. We derive a distance upper limit of 6 kpc to the source. The source hosts a fast ($\sim$350 km s$^{-1}$) bipolar optical outflow, and a slow (~50-60 km s$^{-1}$) molecular outflow along a similar PA. The outflow velocity indicates an age of 336 $\pm$ 119 yr. We also find that the excitation temperature and density of the atomic gas is~20 kK and 2800 cm$^{-3}$, respectively. The elemental and isotopic enrichment of K4-47 infers an AGB progenitor mass of 4-6 M$_{\odot}$, which corresponds to a white dwarf mass of ~1 M$_{\odot}$, following the initial-final mass relation for white dwarfs. We find that the core of K4-47 must contain 10$^{-2}$ M$_{\odot}$ of dust to explain the extinction, and that photoionisation alone cannot explain the excitation of the atomic gas. We instead require an additional heating mechanism, with shocks a likely scenario. It is likely that the progenitor star of K4-47 was a J-type carbon AGB star, which formed the molecular and dusty circumstellar environment. The bipolar outflow is later triggered, punching through the circumstellar environment, producing shocks, and shaping the environment into the elongated structure seen in the sub-millimetre. We therefore classify K4-47 as a genuine, if unusual, planetary nebula.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08959v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Steinmetz, Tomasz Kaminski, David Jones, Marcin Hajduk, Denise R. Goncalves, Stavros Akras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Galaxy Light profile neural Networks (GaLNets). II. Bulge-Disc decomposition in optical space-based observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.05909v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bulge-disk (B-D) decomposition is an effective diagnostic to characterize the galaxy morphology and understand its evolution across time. So far, high-quality data have allowed detailed B-D decomposition to redshift below 0.5, with limited excursions over small volumes at higher redshifts. Next-generation large sky space surveys in optical, e.g. from the China Space Station Telescope (CSST), and near-infrared, e.g. from the space EUCLID mission, will produce a gigantic leap in these studies as they will provide deep, high-quality photometric images over more than 15000 deg2 of the sky, including billions of galaxies. Here, we extend the use of the Galaxy Light profile neural Network (GaLNet) to predict 2-S\'ersic model parameters, specifically from CSST data. We simulate point-spread function (PSF) convolved galaxies, with realistic B-D parameter distributions, on CSST mock observations to train the new GaLNet and predict the structural parameters (e.g. magnitude, effective radius, Sersic index, axis ratio, etc.) of both bulge and disk components. We find that the GaLNet can achieve very good accuracy for most of the B-D parameters down to an $r$-band magnitude of 23.5 and redshift $\sim$1. The best accuracy is obtained for magnitudes, implying accurate bulge-to-total (B/T) estimates. To further forecast the CSST performances, we also discuss the results of the 1-S\'ersic GaLNet and show that CSST half-depth data will allow us to derive accurate 1-component models up to $r\sim$24 and redshift z$\sim$1.7.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.05909v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Qiu, Nicola R. Napolitano, Rui Li, Yuedong Fang, Crescenzo Tortora, Shiyin Shen, Luis C. Ho, Weipeng Lin, Leyao Wei, Ran Li, Zuhui Fan, Yang Wang, Guoliang Li, Hu Zhan, Dezi Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Millimeter-wave observations of Euclid Deep Field South using the South Pole Telescope: A data release of temperature maps and catalogs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00298v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Context. The South Pole Telescope third-generation camera (SPT-3G) has observed over 10,000 square degrees of sky at 95, 150, and 220 GHz (3.3, 2.0, 1.4 mm, respectively) and will significantly overlap the ongoing 14,000 square-degree Euclid Wide Survey. The Euclid collaboration recently released Euclid Deep Field South (EDF-S) observations of 23 square degrees at wide field depths in the first quick data release (Q1). Aims. With the goal of releasing complementary millimeter-wave data and encouraging legacy science, we performed dedicated observations of a 57-square-degree field overlapping the EDF-S. Methods. The observing time totaled 20 days, and we reached noise depths of 4.3, 3.8, and 13.2 $\mu$K-arcmin at 95, 150, and 220 GHz, respectively. Results. In this work we present the temperature maps and two catalogs constructed from these data. The emissive source catalog contains 601 objects (334 inside EDF-S) with 54% synchrotron-dominated sources and 46% thermal dust emission-dominated sources. The 5$\sigma$ detection thresholds are 1.7, 2.0, and 6.5 mJy in the three bands. The cluster catalog contains 217 cluster candidates (121 inside EDF-S) with median mass $M_{500c}=2.12 \times 10^{14} M_{\odot}/h_{70}$ and median redshift $z$ = 0.70, corresponding to an order-of-magnitude improvement in cluster density over previous tSZ-selected catalogs in this region (3.81 clusters per square degree). Conclusions. The overlap between SPT and Euclid data will enable a range of multiwavelength studies of the aforementioned source populations. This work serves as the first step toward joint projects between SPT and Euclid and provides a rich dataset containing information on galaxies, clusters, and their environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00298v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202555798</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A, 706, A17 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. Archipley, A. Hryciuk, L. E. Bleem, K. Kornoelje, M. Klein, A. J. Anderson, B. Ansarinejad, M. Aravena, L. Balkenhol, P. S. Barry, K. Benabed, A. N. Bender, B. A. Benson, F. Bianchini, S. Bocquet, F. R. Bouchet, E. Camphuis, M. G. Campitiello, J. E. Carlstrom, J. Cathey, C. L. Chang, S. C. Chapman, P. Chaubal, P. M. Chichura, A. Chokshi, T. -L. Chou, A. Coerver, T. M. Crawford, C. Daley, T. de Haan, R. P. Deane, K. R. Dibert, M. A. Dobbs, M. Doohan, A. Doussot, D. Dutcher, W. Everett, C. Feng, K. R. Ferguson, K. Fichman, B. Floyd, A. Foster, S. Galli, A. E. Gambrel, R. W. Gardner, F. Ge, N. Goeckner-Wald, A. Gonzalez, S. Grandis, T. R. Greve, R. Gualtieri, F. Guidi, S. Guns, N. W. Halverson, R. Hill, E. Hivon, G. P. Holder, W. L. Holzapfel, J. C. Hood, N. Huang, F. K\'eruzor\'e, A. R. Khalife, L. Knox, M. Korman, C. -L. Kuo, K. Levy, A. E. Lowitz, C. Lu, G. P. Lynch, A. Maniyar, E. S. Martsen, F. Menanteau, M. Millea, J. Montgomery, Y. Nakato, T. Natoli, G. I. Noble, Y. Omori, A. Ouellette, Z. Pan, K. A. Phadke, A. W. Pollak, K. Prabhu, W. Quan, S. Raghunathan, M. Rahimi, A. Rahlin, C. L. Reichardt, C. Reuter, M. Rouble, J. E. Ruhl, E. Schiappucci, A. Simpson, J. A. Sobrin, B. Stalder, A. A. Stark, N. Sulzenauer, C. Tandoi, B. Thorne, C. Trendafilova, C. Umilta, J. D. Vieira, A. Vitrier, D. Vizgan, Y. Wan, A. Wei{\ss}, N. Whitehorn, W. L. K. Wu, M. R. Young, J. A. Zebrowski, D. Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shadows of the Colossus: Hierarchical Black Hole Mergers in a 10-million-body Globular Cluster Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21916v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The LIGO/Virgo/Kagra (LVK) Collaboration has detected numerous binary black hole mergers with properties that challenge standard binary evolution scenarios, such as component masses above the pair-instability gap and high spin magnitudes. Dense stellar environments such as globular clusters provide a natural channel for producing such systems through hierarchical mergers, where black hole remnants formed in earlier mergers are retained in the cluster and undergo successive mergers. However, gravitational-wave recoil kicks often eject merger remnants from typical globular clusters, which limits hierarchical growth. Massive clusters with deeper potential wells, such as those found in giant elliptical galaxies like M87, may overcome this barrier, but direct simulations of such massive globular clusters remains computationally challenging. In this study, we present a 10-million-body cluster simulation performed with the $\texttt{Cluster Monte Carlo}$ ($\texttt{CMC}$) code, referred to as $\texttt{colossus}$, which serves as a proxy for the most massive low-metallicity globular clusters observed in the local Universe. This simulation demonstrates that extended chains of hierarchical mergers can occur in massive globular clusters, producing black holes up to fifth generation with masses approaching $250\,M_\odot$, comparable to the most massive LVK events observed to date (e.g., GW231123). Combining the $\texttt{colossus}$ simulation with the previous $\texttt{CMC Cluster Catalog}$, we develop a framework to extrapolate binary black hole merger predictions for the thousands of globular clusters seen in the Virgo Supercluster.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21916v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ae2de5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJ 998, 138 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aidan Mai, Kyle Kremer, Fulya K{\i}ro\u{g}lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Gaussian Magnetic Structures in the Small-Scale Turbulent Dynamo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.03072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.03072v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The small-scale turbulent dynamo is a key mechanism for amplifying galactic magnetic fields, yet the resulting field morphology remains poorly understood. Using 3D driven turbulence simulations across a range of compressibilities, characterised by Mach number, and Minkowski functionals, we quantitatively investigate the morphology of magnetic fields generated by the small-scale turbulent dynamo in both the exponentially growing kinematic stage and the statistically steady saturated stage. In both stages and across all Mach numbers, we find that the magnetic field departs significantly from a Gaussian random field. Magnetic structures are statistically less curved and more interconnected in the saturated stage than in the kinematic stage, with these morphological differences decreasing as compressibility increases. Our work provides a quantitative description of how density fluctuations in turbulence and the back-reaction of amplified magnetic fields via the Lorentz force together shape complex, non-Gaussian magnetic structures, and offers a valuable framework for comparing simulations with both analytical models and polarisation observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.03072v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sasi M. Behara, Amit Seta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projection Effects in Barred Galaxies Causing Wrong Interpretation of Radial Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20267v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Galaxy disks in rotation are sometimes the site of radial flows, especially in their gas component. It is important to estimate the outflows, due to AGN or supernovae feedback, or inflows due to bar gravity torques. However, these radial flows may be confused with non-circular motions, which are quite frequent in the center of galaxy disks. We use a simulated giant, barred spiral galaxy from the GalMer database to study the non-circular motions induced by the bar. Our goal is to identify the spurious radial flows that kinematics modeling algorithms can detect, assuming circular orbits for the gas. Using mock data of a strongly barred galaxy, we quantify the radial velocities computed by the 3D-Barolo algorithm for different disk inclinations and several bar orientations in the plane of the sky: along the major and minor kinematic axes and at 45{\deg} from them. Our results show that projection effects cause kinematics modeling algorithms to confuse the radial component of velocity due to elliptical orbits with significant radial flows with mean values up to 92 km.s$^{-1}$, within the bar region. The computed rotation curve is also wrongly estimated inside the bar region, by as much as 150 km.s$^{-1}$ for the highest inclination.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20267v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Salibur, A. Hall\'e, F. Combes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Connecting Star Formation in the Milky Way and Nearby Galaxies -II. An Observationally Driven Analytical Model for Predicting Cloud-Scale Star Formation Rates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22985v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct a model by integrating observational constraints from the Milky Way and nearby galaxies to predict cloud-scale star formation rates (SFRs). In the model, we first estimate the initial total mass of clumps in a cloud based on the cloud mass, and then generate the initial clump population of the cloud using the initial clump mass function. Next, we model the star formation histories (SFHs) of the cloud to assign an age to each clump. We then sort out the intermediate-age clumps and calculate the total embedded cluster mass. Finally, we predict the SFR based on the duration of the embedded phase. The model-predicted SFR is broadly consistent with the observed SFR, supporting the plausibility of the model. The model primarily provides a theoretical framework that integrates a wide range of observational results, thereby clarifying the tasks for future observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22985v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. W. Zhou, Amelie Saintonge, Sami Dib, Pavel Kroupa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The shape-velocity alignment of satellites forged by tidal locking and dynamical friction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07637v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Utilizing the TNG50 simulation, we study two types of alignments for satellites/subhalos: 1) the alignment of their major axes with the galactocentric radial directions (radial alignment), and 2) with the motion directions (orbital alignment). We find that radial alignment is substantially stronger than orbital alignment, with both signals being consistently stronger for subhalos than for satellites. Interestingly, inward- and outward-moving satellites/subhalos show contrasting orbital alignment behaviors, which can be understood in terms of their radial alignment, orbit decay due to dynamical friction and the effect of tidal stripping. The orbital alignment is stronger in more massive halos. In the end, we explore the orbital alignment measured by a mock observer, and find that the observed alignment for MW satellites is due to projection effects, as the major axes of satellites lie within their orbital planes, approximately coplanar with the observer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07637v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Yang, Wenting Wang, Ting S. Li, Sergey E. Koposov, Jiaxin Han, Feihong He, Zhaozhou Li, Zhongxu Zhai, Binbin Gao, Carles G. Palau, Zhenlin Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MAMMOTH-LyC: Investigating the Role of Galaxy Mergers in a Strong Lyman Continuum Leaker at $z=2.39$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.23202v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The MAMMOTH-LyC survey is a cycle 30 Hubble Space Telescope (HST) medium program obtaining 18-orbit-deep WFC3/UVIS F225W imaging in two massive galaxy protocluster fields at $z\sim2.2$. We introduce this survey by reporting the discovery of J1244-LyC1, a strong Lyman continuum (LyC) leaker at $z = 2.39$, exhibiting clear merger signatures. J1244-LyC1 has a highly significant ($10\sigma$) LyC detection, corresponding to an absolute escape fraction of $f_{\mathrm{esc}} \! =\!36\%\pm4\%$ ($1\sigma$). The LyC emission is spatially resolved into multiple peaks that coincide with the system's disturbed morphology, confirming genuine multi-site LyC leakage. With a stellar mass of $10^{10.2}{M_\odot}$, J1244-LyC1 is both the first confirmed high-redshift LyC-leaking merger and the most massive LyC emitter known to date. We interpret J1244-LyC1 as a merger-driven starburst system in which tidal interactions have disrupted the interstellar medium, creating multiple low-column-density pathways that facilitate LyC escape. This discovery provides the first direct evidence of spatially resolved LyC escape in a merging system, offering new insight into the potential role of major mergers in driving the cosmic reionization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.23202v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengzhe Wang, Xin Wang, Matthew A. Malkan, Harry I. Teplitz, Rebecca L. Davies, Karl Glazebrook, Keunho J. Kim, Themiya Nanayakkara, Hang Zhou, Yiming Yang, Chao-Wei Tsai, Yuxuan Pang, Zheng Cai, Xiaohui Fan, Alaina Henry, Zihao Li, Dong Dong Shi, Xian Zhong Zheng, Zhiyu Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of Gravitational Anomaly at Low Acceleration from a Highest-quality Sample of 36 Wide Binaries with Accurate 3D Velocities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.21728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.21728v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We set out to accurately measure gravity in the low-acceleration range $(10^{-11},10^{-9})$ m s$^{-2}$ from 3D motions of isolated wide binary stars. Gaia DR3 provides precise measurements of the four sky-plane components of the 3D relative displacement and velocity ($\mathbf{r}, \mathbf{v}$) for a wide binary, but not comparably precise line-of-sight (radial) separation and relative velocity $v_{r}$. Based on our new observations and the public databases/publications, we assemble a sample of 36 nearby (distance $&lt;150$pc) wide binaries in the low-acceleration regime with accurate values of $v_{r}$ (uncertainty $&lt; 100$ m s$^{-1}$). Kinematic contaminants such as undetected stellar companions are well under control using various observational diagnostics such as Gaia's ruwe parameter, the color-magnitude diagram, multi-epoch observations of radial velocities, Speckle interferometric follow-up observations, and requiring Hipparcos-Gaia proper motion consistency. For the parameter $\Gamma \equiv \log_{10}\sqrt{\gamma}$ with $\gamma \equiv G/G_{\rm N}$ (where $G$ is a parameter generalizing Newton's constant $G_{\rm N}$ in elliptical orbits), we find $\Gamma=0.102_{-0.021}^{+0.023}$, inconsistent with standard gravity at $4.9\sigma$, giving a gravity boost factor of $\gamma=1.600_{-0.141}^{+0.171}$. Four wide binaries have 3D relative velocities exceeding their estimated Newtonian escape velocities with $1&lt;v_{\rm obs}/v_{\rm escN}\le1.2$. These systems are unlikely to be chance associations and are expected in a nonstandard paradigm such as Milgromian dynamics (MOND). The hypothesis that Newtonian gravity can be extrapolated to the low-acceleration limit is falsified by this independent study with accurate 3D velocities. Future radial velocity monitoring and Speckle interferometric imaging for larger samples will be useful to refine the present result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.21728v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. -H. Chae, B. -C. Lee, X. Hernandez, V. G. Orlov, D. Lim, D. A. Turnshek, Y. -W. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WLM: Dynamics of an isolated Dwarf Irregular Galaxy Under Ram Pressure in the Local Group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.02652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.02652v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: WLM is an archetypal dwarf irregular galaxy that has not experienced interactions with major Local Group galaxies within the past 8 Gyr. It has recently been shown that WLM is losing its gas due to ram pressure forces exerted by the surrounding intergalactic medium (IGM). In this work, we explore how ram pressure may also affect the WLM gas kinematics, and we show that its dynamics is especially perturbed at its outskirts, explaining the asymmetric rotation between the approaching and receding sides. Moreover, we have been able to decompose WLM in two main components, a compact one with a solid-body rotation that resembles a bar-like structure, and a more extended one with a characteristic double-horn profile suggesting an edge-on disk. The former is relatively unaffected by ram pressure while the latter has its dynamics considerably affected by ram pressure. This study shows that mass estimates of a dwarf galaxy like WLM should account for a full modeling of its dynamical components, especially accounting for its asymmetric rotation curve.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.02652v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neel Kolhe (LIRA, Observatoire de Paris, Universite PSL, CNRS), Francois Hammer (LIRA, Observatoire de Paris, Universite PSL, CNRS), Yanbin Yang (LIRA, Observatoire de Paris, Universite PSL, CNRS), Brenda Namumba (Instituto de Astrofisica de Andalucia), Laurent Chemin (Universite de Strasbourg, CNRS, Observatoire astronomique de Strasbourg, UMR 7550, Instituto de Astrofisica, Departamento de Ciencias Fisicas, Universidad Andres Bello), Philippe Amram (Aix Marseille Univ, CNRS, CNES, LAM), Roger Ianjamasimanana (Instituto de Astrofisica de Andalucia), Claude Carignan (Department of Astronomy, University of Cape Town, Departement de physique, Universite de Montreal, Complexe des sciences MIL, Observatoire d'Astrophysique de l'Universit\'e Ouaga)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intermediate-Mass Black Hole Formation from Hierarchical Mergers in Galactic Nuclei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.04176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.04176v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dense stellar environments like nuclear star clusters (NSCs) can dynamically assemble gravitational wave (GW) sources. We consider a population of single stellar mass black holes (BHs) in the inner $0.1$~pc of a NSC surrounding a $4 \times 10^6$~M$_\odot$ supermassive black hole (SMBH). Using a semianalytic model, we account for direct collisions between BHs and stars and GW capture between BHs. We explore the effect of the initial BH mass and spin distributions on their final properties and the production of GW sources. Specifically, we consider upper and lower limits for the BH initial mass distribution, and we account for the possibility that a subset of our initial population are the merger products of primordial BH binaries. We find that $\sim 500$ M$_{\odot}$ intermediate mass black holes (IMBHs) can form for our upper limit mass distribution, while our lower limit mass distribution forms none. Most IMBHs $\gtrsim 200$~M$_\odot$ eventually sink towards the center of the cluster and merge with the SMBH. We also find successive BH-star collisions can produce low-spinning BHs with $\chi \lesssim 0.2$. Our results have implications for LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA sources. We find that the overall merger rate depends primarily on the initial BH mass distribution and is $\gtrsim 10^{-9}$~yr$^{-1}$ per galaxy for our range of initial conditions. However, primordial binaries can change the number of second and higher generation mergers by an order of magnitude.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.04176v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amanda Newton, Sanaea C. Rose, Fulya K{\i}ro\u{g}lu, Bao-Minh Hoang, Frederic A. Rasio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ELFO: A Python Package for Emission Line Fitting Optimization in Integral Field Spectroscopy Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.05396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.05396v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Integral field spectroscopy (IFS) provides spatially resolved spectra, enabling detailed studies that address the physical and kinematic properties of the interstellar medium. A critical step in analyzing IFS data is the decomposition of emission lines, where different velocity components are often modeled with Gaussian profiles. However, conventional fitting methods that treat each spectrum independently often yield spatial discontinuities in the fitting results. Here, we present Emission Line Fitting Optimization (ELFO), a Python package for IFS spectral fitting. ELFO uses the results of neighboring spectra to determine multiple initial guesses and selects the result that exhibits spatial smoothness. We tested ELFO on IFS data of two quasars obtained from the Multi-Unit Spectroscopic Explorer, where it successfully corrected anomalous fits, revealed previously unresolved substructures, and made large-scale kinematic structures more evident. With minor modifications, this method can also be easily adapted to other IFS data and different emission lines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.05396v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-3881/ae3087</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hui Guo, Guilin Liu, Jianghui Xu, Chao Geng, Zhicheng He, Shiyin Shen, Lei Hao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpreting Cosmological Information from Neural Networks in the Hydrodynamic Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17839v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: What happens when a black box (neural network) meets a black box (simulation of the Universe)? Recent work has shown that convolutional neural networks (CNNs) can infer cosmological parameters from the matter density field in the presence of complex baryonic processes. A key question that arises is, which parts of the cosmic web is the neural network obtaining information from? We shed light on the matter by identifying the Fourier scales, density scales, and morphological features of the cosmic web that CNNs pay most attention to. We find that CNNs extract cosmological information from both high and low density regions: overdense regions provide the most information per pixel, while underdense regions -- particularly deep voids and their surroundings -- contribute significantly due to their large spatial extent and coherent spatial features. Remarkably, we demonstrate that there is negligible degradation in cosmological constraining power after aggressive cutting in both maximum Fourier scale and density. Furthermore, we find similar results when considering both hydrodynamic and gravity-only simulations, implying that neural networks can marginalize over baryonic effects with minimal loss in cosmological constraining power. Our findings point to practical strategies for optimal and robust field-level cosmological inference in the presence of uncertainly modeled astrophysics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17839v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ae0b5a</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Astrophys. J. 994 129 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arnab Lahiry, Adrian E. Bayer, Francisco Villaescusa-Navarro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free-floating Planets Produced by Planet-Planet Scatterings: Ejection Velocity and Survival Rate of Their Moons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.18239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.18239v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The discovery of numerous free-floating planets (FFPs) has intensified interest in their origins and dynamical histories. A leading formation mechanism is planet-planet scatterings in unstable multi-planetary systems, which can naturally lead to planetary ejections. If these planets originally host moons, it remains an open question whether such satellites can remain gravitationally bound to FFPs after ejection. In this work, we investigate both the ejection velocity of FFPs produced by planet-planet scatterings and the survival rate of their potential moons; we estimate the latter by determining the statistics of the minimum planet-planet distance prior to planet ejection, and comparing it to the initial orbital radius of the moon relative to its host planet. Using the circular restricted three-body framework, we derive an analytical boundary for the ejection velocity based on Jacobi energy conservation, which agrees with the results of integrations. We also identify a minimum planetary mass required for successful ejection. For two-planet systems with finite planetary masses, we use simulations and analytical arguments to determine how the ejection velocity scales with the planetary mass and initial semi-major axis. We contrast our results to the ejection of planets around binaries in unstable orbits. Extending our analysis to three-planet systems yields similar results, reinforcing the robustness of our conclusions. These findings offer insights into the property of FFPs and inform future efforts to search for exomoons around them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.18239v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ae394f</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Xiumin Huang, Dong Lai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-noise Fourier Transform Spectroscopy Enabled by Superconducting On-Chip Filterbank Spectrometers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.06771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.06771v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Historically employed spectroscopic architectures used for large field of view mapping spectroscopy in millimetere and sub-millimetre astronomy suffer from significant drawbacks. On-chip filterbank spectrometers are a promising technology in this respect; however, they must overcome an orders-of-magnitude increase in detector counts, efficiency loss due to dielectric properties, and stringent fabrication tolerances that currently limit scaling to resolutions of order 1000 over a large array. We propose coupling a medium-resolution Fourier transform spectrometer to a low-resolution filterbank spectrometer focal plane, which serves as a post-dispersion element. In this arrangement, medium resolution imaging spectroscopy is provided by the Fourier transform spectrometer, while the low resolution filterbank spectrometer serves to decrease the photon noise inherent in typical broadband Fourier transform spectrometer measurements by over an order of magnitude. This is achieved while maintaining the excellent imaging advantages of both architectures. We present predicted mapping speeds for a filterbank-dispersed Fourier transform spectrometer from a ground-based site and a balloon-borne platform. We also demonstrate the potential that an instrument of this type has for an R~1000 line intensity mapping experiment using the James Clerk Maxwell Telescope as an example platform. We demonstrate that a filterbank-dispersed Fourier transform spectrometer would be capable of R~1000 measurements of CO power spectra with a signal-to-noise ratio of 10--100 with surveys of $10^5$--$10^6$ spectrometer hours.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.06771v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris S. Benson, Peter S. Barry, Patrick Ashworth, Harry Gordon-Moys, Kirit S. Karkare, Izaak Morris, Gethin Robson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPHEREx Pre-Perihelion Mapping of $\mathrm{H_2O}$, $\mathrm{CO_2}$, and $\mathrm{CO}$ in Interstellar Object 3I/ATLAS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07318v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: From 01- to 15-Aug-2025UT, the SPHEREx spacecraft observed interstellar object 3I/ATLAS. Using $R=40-130$ spectrophotometry at $\lambda=0.7-5$ $\mu$m, light curves, spectra, and imaging of ATLAS were obtained. From these, robust detections of water gas emission at $2.7-2.8$ $\mu$m and $CO_2$ gas at $4.23-4.27$ $\mu$m plus tentative detections of $^{13}CO_2$ and $CO$ gas were found. A slightly extended $H_2O$ coma was detected, and a huge $CO_2$ atmosphere of extending out to at least $4.2 \times 10^{5}$ km was discovered. Gas production rates and 1$\sigma$ errors for $H_2O$, $^{12}CO_2$, $^{13}CO_2$, and $CO$ were $Q_{gas} = 3.2 \times 10^{26} \pm 20\%$, $1.6 \times 10^{27} \pm 10\%$, $1.3 \times 10^{25} \pm 25\%$, and $1.0 \times 10^{26} \pm 25\%$, respectively. Co-addition of all $\lambda = 1.0-1.5$ $\mu$m scattered light continuum images from produced a high SNR image consistent with an unresolved source. The scattered light lightcurve showed $\lesssim 15\%$ variability over the observation period. The absolute brightness of ATLAS at $1.0-1.5$ $\mu$m is consistent with a $&lt; 2.5$ km radius nucleus surrounded by a 100 times brighter coma. The $1.5-4.0$ $\mu$m continuum structure shows a strong feature commensurate with water ice absorption seen in KBOs and distant comets. The observed cometary behavior of ATLAS, including its preponderance of $CO_2$ emission, lack of $CO$ output, small size, and predominance of large icy chunks of material in a flux-dominant coma is similar to the behavior of short period comet 103P/Hartley 2, the ''hyperactive comet'' flyby target of the NASA Deep Impact extended mission in 2010. This correspondence suggests that ISOs can be significantly thermally processed before ejection into the ISM, and by comparison to 1I and 2I, can be widely variable in their physical outcome.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07318v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carey M. Lisse, Yoonsoo P. Bach, Brendan P. Crill, Phil M. Korngut, Ari J. Cukierman, Sean A. Bryan, Asantha Cooray, C. Darren Dowell, Michael W. Werner, Joseph L. Hora, Zafar Rustamkulov, Jeong-Eun Lee, Bumhoo Lim, Y. R. Fernandez, Volker Tolls, W. T. Reach, O. Dor\'e, Michael Zemcov, James J. Bock, Yun-Ting Cheng, C. Champagne, Seungwon Choi, M. Connelley, J. P. Emery, Spencer Everett, Andreas L. Faisst, Jooyeon Geem, Howard Hui, Masateru Ishiguro, Sunho Jin, Hangbin Jo, Max Mahlke, Daniel C. Masters, Gary J. Melnick, Chi H. Nguyen, Roberta Paladini, M. L. Sitko, Yujin Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Any Light Particle Searches with ALPS II: first science results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.14110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.14110v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The light-shining-through-a-wall experiment ALPS II at DESY in Hamburg searched for axions and similar lightweight particles in its first science campaign from February to May 2024. No evidence for the existence of such particles was found. For pseudoscalar bosons like the axion, with masses below about 0.1 meV, we achieved a limit for the di-photon coupling strength of 1.5e-9 1/GeV at a 95% confidence level. This is more than a factor of 20 improvement compared to all previous similar experiments. We also provide limits on photon interactions for scalar, vector and tensor bosons. An achievement of this first science campaign is the demonstration of stable operation and robust calibration of the complex experiment. Currently, the optical system of ALPS II is being upgraded aiming for another two orders of magnitude sensitivity increase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.14110v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel C. Brotherton, Sandy Croatto, Jacob Egge, Aldo Ejlli, Henry Fr\"adrich, Joe Gleason, Hartmut Grote, Ayman Hallal, Michael T. Hartman, Harold Hollis, Katharina-Sophie Isleif, Friederike Januschek, Kanioar Karan, Sven Karstensen, Todd Kozlowski, Axel Lindner, Manuel Meyer, Guido M\"uller, Gulden Othman, Jan H. P\~old, David Reuther, Andreas Ringwald, Elmeri Rivasto, Jos\'e Alejandro Rubiera Gimeno, J\"orn Schaffran, Uwe Schneekloth, Christina Schwemmbauer, Aaron D. Spector, David B. Tanner, Dieter Trines, Li-Wei Wei, Benno Willke, Rachel Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Appearance of Self-gravitating AGN Disks Powered by Stellar Objects: Universal Effective Temperature in the Optical Continuum and Application to Little Red Dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06954v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We revisit the spectral appearance of extended self-gravitating accretion disks around supermassive black holes. Using dust-poor opacity tables, we show that all optically thick disk solutions possess a universal outer effective temperature of $T_{\rm eff}\sim 4000-4500$K, closely resembling compact, high-redshift sources known as Little Red Dots (LRDs). Assuming the extended disk is primarily heated by stellar sources, this ``disk Hayashi limit" fixes the dominant optical continuum temperature of the disk spectrum independent of accretion rate $\dot{M}$, black hole mass $M_\bullet$, and disk viscosity $\alpha$, and removes the parameter-tuning required in previous disk interpretations of LRDs. We construct global self-gravitating accretion disk models with radially varying accretion rates, suggesting that burning of embedded stellar objects can both efficiently power the emission of the outer disk and hollow out the inner disk, strongly suppressing variable UV/X-ray associated with a standard quasar. The resulting disk emission is dominated by a luminous optical continuum while a separate, non-variable UV component arises from stellar populations on the nuclear to galaxy scale. We map the optimal region of parameter space for such systems and show that LRD-like appearances are guaranteed for $\dot{M}/\alpha \gtrsim 0.1 M_\odot /{\rm yr}$, a threshold insensitive to $M_\bullet$, below which the system may transition into classical non-self-gravitating AGN disks, potentially a later evolution stage. We expect this transition to be accompanied by the enhancement of metallicity and production of dust, giving rise to far infrared emission. This picture offers a physically motivated and quantitative framework connecting LRDs with AGNs and their associated nuclear stellar population.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06954v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Xian Chen, Hanpu Liu, Ruancun Li, Bingjie Wang, Yilun Ma, Yan-Fei Jiang, Jenny E. Greene, Eliot Quataert, Jeremy Goodman</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
