<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.KT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.KT</link>
    <description>math.KT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.KT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 01:42:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Regularity of an FI-module via the derivative functor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.08260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.08260v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We characterize the regularity of an FI-module using the derivative functors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.08260v1</guid>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cihan Bahran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gorenstein cohomological dimension and stable categories for groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.09589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.09589v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: First we study the Gorenstein cohomological dimension ${\rm Gcd}_RG$ of groups $G$ over coefficient rings $R$, under changes of groups and rings; a characterization for finiteness of ${\rm Gcd}_RG$ is given. Some results in literature obtained over the coefficient ring $\mathbb{Z}$ or rings of finite global dimension are generalized to more general cases. Moreover, we establish a model structure on the weakly idempotent complete exact category $\mathcal{F}ib$ consisting of fibrant $RG$-modules, and show that the homotopy category $\mathrm{Ho}(\mathcal{F}ib)$ is triangle equivalent to both the stable category $\underline{\mathcal{C}of}(RG)$ of Benson's cofibrant modules, and the stable module category ${\rm StMod}(RG)$. The relation between cofibrant modules and Gorenstein projective modules is discussed, and we show that under some conditions such that ${\rm Gcd}_RG&lt;\infty$, ${\rm Ho}(\mathcal{F}ib)$ is equivalent to the stable category of Gorenstein projective $RG$-modules, the singularity category, and the homotopy category of totally acyclic complexes of projective $RG$-modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.09589v4</guid>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local systems in diffeology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.13084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2108.13084v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By making use of Halperin's local systems over simplicial sets and the model structure of the category of diffeological spaces due to Kihara, we introduce a framework of rational homotopy theory for such smooth spaces with arbitrary fundamental groups. As a consequence, we have an equivalence between the homotopy categories of fibrewise rational diffeological spaces and an algebraic category of minimal local systems elaborated by G\'omez-Tato, Halperin and Tanr\'e. In the latter half of this article, a spectral sequence converging to the singular de Rham cohomology of a diffeological adjunction space is constructed with the pullback of relevant local systems. In case of a stratifold obtained by attaching manifolds, the spectral sequence converges to the Souriau--de Rham cohomology algebra of the diffeological space. By using the pullback construction, we also discuss a local system model for a topological homotopy pushout.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2108.13084v4</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katsuhiko Kuribayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On P^1-stabilization in unstable motivic homotopy theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.04631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.04631v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyze stabilization with respect to ${\mathbb P}^1$ in the Morel--Voevodsky unstable motivic homotopy theory. We introduce a refined notion of cellularity (a.k.a., biconnectivity) in various motivic homotopy categories taking into account both the simplicial and Tate circles. Under suitable cellularity hypotheses, we refine the Whitehead theorem by showing that a map of nilpotent motivic spaces can be seen to be an equivalence if it so after taking (Voevodsky) motives. We then establish a version of the Freudenthal suspension theorem for ${\mathbb P}^1$-suspension, again under suitable cellularity hypotheses. As applications, we resolve Murthy's conjecture on splitting of corank $1$ vector bundles on smooth affine algebras over algebraically closed fields having characteristic $0$ and compute new unstable motivic homotopy of motivic spheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.04631v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aravind Asok, Tom Bachmann, Michael J. Hopkins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An obstruction theory for strictly commutative algebras in positive characteristic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16681v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This is the first in a sequence of articles exploring the relationship between commutative algebras and $E_\infty$-algebras in characteristic $p$ and mixed characteristic. In this paper we lay the groundwork by defining a new class of cohomology operations over $\mathbb F_p$ called cotriple products, generalising Massey products. We compute the secondary cohomology operations for a strictly commutative dg-algebra and the obstruction theories these induce, constructing several counterexamples to characteristic 0 behaviour, one of which answers a question of Campos, Petersen, Robert-Nicoud and Wierstra. We construct some families of higher cotriple products and comment on their behaviour. Finally, we distingush a subclass of cotriple products that we call higher Steenrod operations and conclude with our main theorem, which says that $E_\infty$-algebras can be rectified if and only if the higher Steenrod operations vanish coherently.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16681v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ois\'in Flynn-Connolly</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
