<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.KT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.KT</link>
    <description>math.KT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.KT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 04:00:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>$\mathbb{A}^1$-invariant motivic cohomology of schemes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09915v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Voevodsky outlined a conjectural programme that his slice filtration in motivic homotopy theory should give rise to a good theory of $\mathbb{A}^1$-invariant motivic cohomology. This paper achieves his vision in the generality of arbitrary quasicompact, quasiseparated schemes, by introducing a theory of $\mathbb{A}^1$-invariant motivic cohomology which is related to Weibel's homotopy $K$-theory via an Atiyah--Hirzebruch spectral sequence, and which we compare to \'etale and syntomic cohomology in the style of the original conjectures of Beilinson and Lichtenbaum. In addition, it is represented by an absolute motivic spectrum and therefore satisfies cdh descent, and modules over it offer a candidate for the derived category of $\mathbb{A}^1$-invariant motives. We establish some of Voevodsky's open conjectures on slices, in particular relating the zeroth slice of the motivic sphere to homotopy $K$-theory. In the final section we prove analogous results for the Hermitian $K$-theory of qcqs schemes on which $2$ is invertible.
  As an auxiliary tool we introduce cdh-motivic cohomology, defined as the cdh sheafification of the left Kan extension of the motivic cohomology of smooth $\mathbb{Z}$-schemes. We offer a new approach to control the latter, independent of previous work on $\mathbb{A}^1$-invariant motivic cohomology of smooth schemes over mixed characteristic Dedekind domains: our approach is based on recent developments in $p$-adic cohomology, in particular syntomic and prismatic cohomology. The cdh-motivic cohomology is also a necessary ingredient in the last two authors' and Bouis' construction of non-$\mathbb{A}^1$-invariant motivic cohomology of qcqs schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09915v1</guid>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Bachmann, Elden Elmanto, Matthew Morrow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous six-functor formalism on locally compact Hausdorff spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13537v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the functor sending a locally compact Hausdorff space $X$ to the $\infty$-category of spectral sheaves $\mathrm{Shv}(X; \mathrm{Sp})$ is initial among all continuous six-functor formalisms on the category of locally compact Hausdorff spaces. Here, continuous six-functor formalisms are those valued in dualizable presentable stable $\infty$-categories and satisfying canonical descent, profinite descent, and hyperdescent. As an application, we generalize Efimov's computation of the algebraic $K$-theory of sheaves to all localizing invariants on continuous six-functor formalisms. Our results show that localizing invariants behave analogously to compactly supported sheaf cohomology theories when evaluated on continuous six-functor formalisms on locally compact Hausdorff spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13537v2</guid>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingchong Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real spin bordism and orientations of topological $\mathrm{K}$-theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00963v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct a commutative orthogonal $C_2$-ring spectrum, $\mathrm{MSpin}^c_{\mathbb{R}}$, along with a $C_2$-$E_{\infty}$-orientation $\mathrm{MSpin}^c_{\mathbb{R}} \to \mathrm{KU}_{\mathbb{R}}$ of Atiyah's Real K-theory. Further, we define $E_{\infty}$-maps $\mathrm{MSpin} \to (\mathrm{MSpin}^c_{\mathbb{R}})^{C_2}$ and $\mathrm{MU}_{\mathbb{R}} \to \mathrm{MSpin}^c_{\mathbb{R}}$, which are used to recover the three well-known orientations of topological $\mathrm{K}$-theory, $\mathrm{MSpin}^c \to \mathrm{KU}$, $\mathrm{MSpin} \to \mathrm{KO}$, and $\mathrm{MU}_{\mathbb{R}} \to \mathrm{KU}_{\mathbb{R}}$, from the map $\mathrm{MSpin}^c_{\mathbb{R}} \to \mathrm{KU}_{\mathbb{R}}$. We also show that the integrality of the $\hat{A}$-genus on spin manifolds provides an obstruction for the fixed points $(\mathrm{MSpin}^c_{\mathbb{R}})^{C_2}$ to be equivalent to $\mathrm{MSpin}$, using the Mackey functor structure of $\underline{\pi}_*\mathrm{MSpin}^c_{\mathbb{R}}$. In particular, the usual map $\mathrm{MSpin} \to \mathrm{MSpin}^c$ does not arise as the inclusion of fixed points for any $C_2$-$E_{\infty}$-ring spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00963v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zachary Halladay, Yigal Kamel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clarification and Coinduction of Tambara Functors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08066v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Tambara functors are equivariant analogues of rings arising in representation theory and equivariant homotopy theory. We introduce the notion of a clarified Tambara functor and show that under mild conditions every Tambara functor admits a decomposition as a product of coinductions of clarified Tambara functors; projection onto the non-coinduced part defines a reflective localization we call clarification. Through this perspective we study Morita invariance and $K$-theory of Tambara functors, field-like Tambara functors, and Nullstellensatzian clarified Tambara functors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08066v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noah Wisdom</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
