<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.HE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.HE</link>
    <description>astro-ph.HE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.HE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 04:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 03 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Simple fits for the neutrino luminosities from protoneutron star cooling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00769v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a simple fit function, $L_{\nu_i}(t) = C\, t^{-\alpha}\, e^{-(t/\tau)^{n}}$, to parametrize the luminosities of neutrinos and antineutrinos of all flavors during the protoneutron star (PNS) cooling phase at post-bounce times $t \gtrsim 1$ s. This fit is based on results from a set of neutrino-hydrodynamics simulations of core-collapse supernovae in spherical symmetry. The simulations were performed with an energy-dependent transport for six neutrino species and took into account the effects of convection and muons in the dense and hot PNS interior. We provide values of the fit parameters $C$, $\alpha$, $\tau$, and $n$ for different neutron star masses and equations of state as well as correlations between these fit parameters. Our functional description is useful for analytic supernova modeling, for characterizing the neutrino light curves in large underground neutrino detectors, and as a tool to extract information from measured signals on the mass and equation of state of the PNS and on secondary signal components on top of the PNS's neutrino emission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00769v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Lucente (University of Bari, INFN Bari, KIP, Heidelberg, ITP, Heidelberg), Malte Heinlein (MPI for Astrophysics, Garching, TUM School of Nat. Sciences, Garching), H. -Thomas Janka (MPI for Astrophysics, Garching), Alessandro Mirizzi (University of Bari, INFN Bari)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Radio Study of Persistent Radio Sources in Nearby Dwarf Galaxies: Implications for Fast Radio Bursts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00784v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present 1 - 12 GHz Karl G. Jansky Very Large Array observations of 9 off-nuclear persistent radio sources (PRSs) in nearby (z &lt; 0.055) dwarf galaxies, along with high-resolution European very-long baseline interferometry (VLBI) Network (EVN) observations for one of them at 1.7GHz. We explore the plausibility that these PRSs are associated with fast radio burst (FRB) sources by examining their properties, physical sizes, host-normalized offsets, spectral energy distributions (SEDs), radio luminosities, and light curves, and compare them to those of the PRSs associated with FRBs 20121102A and 20190520B, two known active galactic nuclei (AGN), and one likely AGN in our sample with comparable data, as well as other radio transients exhibiting characteristics analogous to FRB-PRSs. We identify a single source in our sample, J1136+2643, as the most promising FRB- PRS, based on its compact physical size and host-normalized offset. We further identify two sources, J0019+1507 and J0909+5955, with physical sizes comparable to FRB-PRSs, but which exhibit large offsets and flat spectral indices potentially indicative of a background AGN origin. We test the viability of neutron star wind nebulae and hypernebulae models for J1136+2643, and find that the physical size, luminosity, and SED of J1136+2643 are broadly consistent with these models. Finally, we discuss the alternative interpretation that the radio sources are instead powered by accreting massive black holes and outline future prospects and follow-up observations for differentiating between these scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00784v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Dong (Northwestern/CIERA), T. Eftekhari, W. Fong, S. Bhandari, E. Berger, O. S. Ould-Boukattine, J. W. T. Hessels, N. Sridhar, A. Reines, B. Margalit, J. Darling, A. C. Gordon, J. E. Greene, C. D. Kilpatrick, B. Marcote, B. D. Metzger, K. Nimmo, A. E. Nugent, Z. Paragi, P. K. G. Williams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AT2018fyk: Candidate Tidal Disruption Event by a (Super)massive Black Hole Binary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00894v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The tidal disruption event (TDE) AT2018fyk has unusual X-ray, UV, and optical light curves that decay over the first $\sim$600d, rebrighten, and decay again around 1200d. We explain this behavior as a one-off TDE associated with a massive black hole (BH) \emph{binary}. The sharp drop-offs from $t^{-5/3}$ power laws at around 600d naturally arise when one BH interrupts the debris fallback onto the other BH. The BH mass $M_\bullet$ derived from fitting X-ray spectra with a slim disk accretion model and, independently, from fitting the early UV/optical light curves, is smaller by two orders of magnitude than predicted from the $M_\bullet$--$\sigma_*$ host galaxy relation, suggesting that the debris is accreted onto the secondary, with fallback cut off by the primary. Furthermore, if the rebrightening were associated with the primary, it should occur around 5000d, not the observed 1200d. The secondary's mass and dimensionless spin is $M_{\bullet,{\rm s}}=2.7^{+0.5}_{-1.5} \times 10^5 M_\odot$ and $a_{\bullet,{\rm s}}&gt;0.3$ (X-ray spectral fitting), while the primary's mass is $M_{\bullet,{\rm p}}=10^{7.7\pm0.4}M_\odot$ ($M_\bullet$-$\sigma_*$ relation). An intermediate mass BH secondary is consistent with the observed UV/optical light curve decay, i.e., the secondary's outer accretion disk is too faint to produce a detectable emission floor. The time of the first accretion cutoff constrains the binary separation to be $(6.7\pm 1.2) \times 10^{-3}~{\rm pc}$. X-ray spectral fitting and timing analysis indicate that the hard X-rays arise from a corona above the secondary's disk. The early UV/optical emission, suggesting a super-Eddington phase for the secondary, possibly originates from shocks arising from debris circularization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00894v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Wen, P. G. Jonker, A. J. Levan, D. Li, N. C. Stone, A. I. Zabludoff, Z. Cao, T. Wevers, D. R. Pasham, C. Lewin, E. Kara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bumpy Superluminous Supernovae Powered by Magnetar-star Binary Engine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01224v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Wolf-Rayet stars in close binary systems can be tidally spun up by their companions, potentially leaving behind fast-spinning highly-magnetized neutron stars, known as ``magnetars", after core collapse. These newborn magnetars can transfer rotational energy into heating and accelerating the ejecta, producing hydrogen-poor superluminous supernovae (SLSNe). In this {\em{Letter}}, we propose that the magnetar wind of the newborn magnetar could significantly evaporate its companion star, typically a main-sequence or helium star, if the binary system is not disrupted by the SN kick. The subsequent heating and acceleration of the evaporated star material along with the SN ejecta by the magnetar wind can produce a post-peak bump in the SLSN lightcurve. Our model can reproduce the primary peaks and post-peak bumps of four example observed multiband SLSN lightcurves, revealing that the mass of the evaporated material could be $\sim0.4-0.6\,M_\odot$ if the material is hydrogen-rich. We suggest that the magnetar could induce strongly enhanced evaporation from its companion star near the pericenter if the orbit of the post-SN binary is highly eccentric, ultimately generating multiple post-peak bumps in the SLSN lightcurves. This ``magnetar-star binary engine" model offers a possible explanation for the evolution of polarization, along with the origin and velocity broadening of late-time hydrogen or helium broad spectral features observed in some bumpy SLSNe. The diversity in the lightcurves and spectra of SLSNe may be attributed to the wide variety of companion stars and post-SN binary systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01224v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin-Ping Zhu, Liang-Duan Liu, Yun-Wei Yu, Ilya Mandel, Ryosuke Hirai, Bing Zhang, Aming Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the nova shock physics with future gamma-ray observations of the upcoming outburst from T Coronae Borealis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01257v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nova shocks behave like scaled-down supernova remnant shocks with a lifetime of only a few weeks or months, thereby providing a unique opportunity to study the dynamics of non-relativistic shocks as well as the shock acceleration physics.Recently, GeV and TeV gamma-ray emissions from an outburst of the recurrent nova RS Ophiuchi have been observed. The light curves of the gamma-ray emissions suggest that they arise from an external shock, which is formed as the nova ejecta interacts with the ambient medium. The shock is thought to transit from an adiabatic shock to a radiative one at later times, but no such later observations are available for RS Ophiuchi. In addition, the spectral evolution of the gamma-ray outburst of RS Ophiuchi was not well measured, and hence the related particle acceleration mechanisms are not well understood. T Coronae Borealis (T CrB) is another recurrent nova in Milky Way and its last outburst was nearly ten times brighter than RS Ophiuichi. Recently the optical light curve of T CrB displayed a state transition behavior before the eruption, and it was predicted that T CrB will undergo an outburst in the near future. By performing a theoretical investigation, we find that Fermi-LAT could capture the transition of the shock from the adiabatic phase to the radiative phase at the GeV band, thanks to a longer detectable time than that of RS Ophiuchi.Due to its higher brightness, we also find that imaging atmospheric Cherenkov telescopes (IACTs) such as MAGIC and VERITAS, and extensive air shower experiments such as LHAASO could detect the nova outburst and measure the gamma-ray spectrum in the very-high-energy (VHE, energy above 0.1 TeV) band more precisely. This can be used to constrain the high-energy cutoff index in the accelerated proton spectrum and the acceleration efficiency, which will shed light on the particle acceleration physics in nova shocks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01257v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian-He Zheng, Ruo-Yu Liu, Min Zha, Xiang-Yu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convection and the Core $g$-mode in Proto-Compact Stars -- A detailed analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01449v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a detailed analysis of the dynamics of proto-compact star (PCS) convection and the core ${}^2\!g_1$-mode in core-collapse supernovae based on general relativistic 2D and 3D neutrino hydrodynamics simulations. Based on 2D simulations, we derive a mode relation for the core $g$-mode frequency in terms of PCS and equation of state parameters, and discuss its limits of accuracy. This relation may prove useful for parameter inference from future supernova gravitational wave (GW) signals if the core $g$-mode or an emission gap at the avoided crossing with the fundamental mode can be detected. The current 3D simulation does not show GW emission from the core $g$-mode due to less power in high-frequency convective motions to excite the mode, however. Analysing the dynamics of PCS convection in 3D, we find that simple scaling laws for convective velocity from mixing-length theory (MLT) do not apply. Energy and lepton number transport is instead governed by a more complex balance between neutrino fluxes and turbulent fluxes that results in roughly uniform rates of change of entropy and lepton number in the PCS convection zone. Electron fraction and enthalpy contrasts in PCS convection are not well captured by the MLT gradient approximation. We find distinctly different spectra for the turbulent kinetic energy and turbulent fluctuations in the electron fraction, which scale approximately as $l^{-1}$ without a downturn at low $l$. We suggest that the different turbulence spectrum of the electron fraction is naturally expected for a passive scalar quantity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01449v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pia Jakobus, Bernhard Mueller, Alexander Heger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the Concordance $\Lambda$CDM model using Gamma-Ray Bursts together with Supernovae Ia and Planck data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01452v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Hubble constant, $H_0$, tension is the tension among the local probes, Supernovae Ia, and the Cosmic Microwave Background Radiation. It has been almost a decade, and this tension still puzzles the community. Here, we add intermediate redshift probes, such as Gamma-Ray Bursts (GRB) and Quasars (QS0s), to check if and to what extent these higher redshift probes can reduce this tension. We use the three-dimensional fundamental plane relation among the prompt peak luminosity, the luminosity at the end of the plateau emission, and its rest frame duration. We find similar trend in GRB intrinsic parameters as previously seen in Pantheon-Plus intrinsic parameters. We find an apparent $3.14\sigma$ tension for the GRB intrinsic parameter $b$. Indeed, this tension disappears and the parameters are actually compatible within $2.26\sigma$. Another interesting point is that the 3D relation plays an important role in conjunction with Supernovae data with Pantheon Plus and that this apparent discrepancy show how it is important the correction for selection biases and redshift evolution. The incorporation of redshift evolution correction results in a reduction of the GRB tension to $2.26\sigma$ when adjusting correction parameters. We envision that with more data this indication of tension will possibly disappear when the evolutionary parameters of GRBs are computed with increased precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01452v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shahnawaz A. Adil, Maria G. Dainotti, Anjan A. Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Effect of a Dark Matter Core on the Structure of a Rotating Neutron Star</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01487v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neutron stars represent unique laboratories, offering insights into the physics of supranuclear-density matter and serving as potential hosts for dark matter. This study explores the impact of dark matter cores on rapidly rotating neutron stars through the two-fluid approximation, assuming minimal interaction between baryonic matter and dark matter. The investigation employs phenomenological models for fermionic and bosonic dark matter, revealing that universal relations governing mass and radius changes due to rotation remain largely unaffected in the presence of a dark matter core. Specifically, for a 5 % dark matter mass fraction, the percent deviations in total mass ($M_{tot}$), the baryonic equatorial radius ($R_{Be}$), and polar-to-equatorial baryonic radius ratio ($R_{ratioB}$) are within 3.9 %, 1.8 %, and 1.4 %, respectively. These findings suggest that the universal relations governing neutron star shape can be utilized to infer constraints on the properties of dark matter cores even in cases where the dark matter significantly softens the neutron star's equation of state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01487v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Konstantinou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insight-HXMT View of the BHC Swift J1727.8-1613 during its outburst in 2023</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01498v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The transient Galactic black hole candidate Swift J1727.8-1613 went through an outburst for the very first time that started in August 2023 and lasted for almost 6 months. We study the timing and spectral properties of this source using publicly available archival Insight-HXMT data for the first 10 observation IDs that last from MJD 60181 to 60198 with a total of 92 exposures for all three energy bands. We extracted the quasi-periodic oscillation properties by model fitting the power density spectrum and from those properties we designate that the QPOs are type-C in nature. We also conclude that the origin of the QPOs could be the shock instabilities, formed in the transonic accretion flow around black holes. The spectral analysis was performed using simultaneous data from the three on-board instruments LE, ME, and HE of HXMT in the broad energy band of $2-150 $ keV. To achieve the best fit, we needed a combination of interstellar absorption, power-law, multi-color disk-blackbody continuum, gaussian emission/absorption, and power-law reflection by neutral material. From the spectral properties, we found that the source was in an intermediate state at the start of the analysis period and was making a transition toward the softer states. The shock (the boundary layer of the corona) moved inward in progressive days in accordance with the spectral nature. We found that the source is present in a high-inclination binary system. The hydrogen column density was found with an average value of $0.27_{-0.17}^{+0.08}\times10^{22}$ cm$^{-2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01498v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaushik Chatterjee, Santanu Mondal, Chandra B. Singh, Mutsumi Sugizaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astrophysical constraints from synchrotron emission on very massive decaying dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00798v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: If the cosmological dark matter (DM) couples to Standard Model (SM) fields, it can decay promptly to SM states in a highly energetic hard process, which subsequently showers and hadronizes to give stable particles including $e^\pm$, $\gamma$, $p^{\pm}$ and $\nu\bar{\nu}$ at lower energy. If the DM particle is very heavy, the high-energy $e^\pm$, due to the Klein-Nishina cross section suppression, preferentially lose energy via synchrotron emission which, in turn, can be of unusually high energies. Here, we present novel bounds on heavy decaying DM up to the Planck scale, by studying the synchrotron emission from the $e^\pm$ produced in the ambient Galactic magnetic field. In particular, we explore the sensitivity of the resulting constraints on the DM decay width to (i) different SM decay channels, to (ii) the Galactic magnetic field configurations, and (iii) to various different DM density profiles proposed in the literature. We find that constraints from the synchrotron component complement and improve on constraints from very high-energy cosmic-ray and gamma-ray observatories targeting the prompt emission when the DM is sufficiently massive, most significantly for masses in excess of $10^{12}\text{ GeV}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00798v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pankaj Munbodh, Stefano Profumo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds on the mass of superradiantly unstable scalar fields around Kerr black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01003v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work we compute numerical bounds on the mass $\mu$ of superradiantly unstable scalar fields in a Kerr black hole background using the continued fraction method. We show that the normalized upper bound on the mass $\mu$ increases with the angular momentum number $\ell$ and the azimuthal number $m$, approaching the most stringent analytical bound known to date when $\ell=m \gg 1$. We also provide an analytical fit to the numerically determined mass bound as a function of the dimensionless spin parameter $a/M$ of the black hole with an accuracy of the order $0.1\%$ for the fundamental mode with $\ell=m=1$, and of the order $1\%$ for higher-order modes (up to $\ell=m=20$). We argue that this analytical fit is particularly useful in astrophysical scenarios, since the lowest $\ell=m$ modes are capable of producing the strongest observable imprints of superradiance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01003v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maur\'icio Richartz, Jo\~ao Lu\'is Rosa, Emanuele Berti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Particle-theory input for neutron-star physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01141v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding the properties and physical phase of the dense strongly interacting matter present in the cores of neutron stars or created in their binary mergers remains one of the most prominent open problems in nuclear astrophysics. While most microscopic analyses have historically relied on solvable phenomenological models of nuclear and quark matter, in recent years a model-independent approach utilizing only controlled ab-initio calculations and astrophysical observations has emerged as a viable alternative.
  In these lecture notes, I review recent progress in first-principles weak-coupling calculations within high-density quark matter, shedding light on its thermodynamic and transport properties. I cover the most important technical tools used in such calculations, introduce selected highlight results, and explain how this information can be used in phenomenological studies of neutron-star physics. The notes do not offer a self-consistent treatment of the topics covered, but rather aim at filling gaps in existing textbooks on thermal field theory and at connecting the dots in a story developed in several recent research articles, to which the interested reader is directed for further technical details.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01141v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksi Vuorinen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recurrent Nova V2487 Oph Had Superflares in 1941 and 1942 With Radiant Energies 10$^{42.5\pm1.6}$ Ergs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01210v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: V2487 Ophiuchi (V2487 Oph) is a recurrent nova with classical nova eruptions in 1900 and 1998, and it is also the most extreme known superflare star. These superflares are roughly-hour-long flares with amplitudes and optical energies reaching up to 1.10 mag and $10^{39.21}$ ergs, with the superflares recurring once-a-day. The V2487 Oph superflares are certainly operating with the same mechanism as all the other types of superflare stars, where magnetic loops are twisted and stretched until reconnection occurs, whereupon ambient electrons are accelerated to relativistic energies and then emitted bremsstrahlung radiation from X-ray to radio. V2487 Oph is unique among known superflare stars in that one of the loop footprints is in an accretion disk. This exact mechanism was theoretically predicted by M. R. Hayashi and colleagues in 1996. Now, I have found two superflares recorded on Harvard archival photographs from the years 1941 and 1942. These two superflares have $B$ magnitude amplitudes of $&gt;$1.83 and $&gt;$2.00 mag and total radiated energies of $10^{42.4}$ and $10^{42.5}$ ergs with bolometric corrections. Each has emitted energies of $\sim$30-billion Carringtons, in units of the most energetic solar flare. Further, I find superflares in the Zwicky Transient Factory light curves, so V2487 Oph has been superflaring from 1941 to 2023. For the observed number distribution of $dN/dE$=$4E^{-2}$ superflares per year, for $E$ in units of $10^{41}$ ergs, the emitted energy in superflare light is $10^{42.1}$ erg in each year, or $10^{44.1}$ ergs from 1941 to 2023.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01210v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bradley E. Schaefer (Louisiana State University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical experiments on stationary, oscillating, and damped spherical galaxy models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01235v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We numerically analyse solutions of the spherically symmetric gravitational Vlasov-Poisson system close to compactly supported stable steady states. We observe either partially undamped oscillations or macroscopically damped solutions. We investigate for many steady states to which of these behaviours they correspond. A linear relation between the exponents of polytropic steady states and the qualitative behaviour close to them is identified. Undamped oscillations are also observed around not too concentrated King models and around all shells with a sufficiently large vacuum region. We analyse all solutions both at the non-linear and linearised level and find that the qualitative behaviours are identical at both. To relate the observed phenomena to theoretical results, we further include a comprehensive numerical study of the radial particle periods in the equilibria.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01235v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Straub</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Satellite lines from autoionizing states of Fe XVI and the problems with the X-ray Fe XVII lines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01274v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present new calculations of atomic data needed to model autoionizing states of Fe XVI. We compare the state energies, radiative and excitation data with a sample of results from previous literature. We find a large scatter of results, the most significant ones in the autoionization rates, which are very sensitive to the configuration interaction and state mixing. We find relatively good agreement between the autoionization rates and the collisional excitation rates calculated with the R-matrix suite of programs and autostructure. The largest model, which includes J-resolved states up to n=10, produces ab-initio wavelengths and intensities of the satellite lines which agree well with solar high-resolution spectra of active regions, with few minor wavelength adjustements. We review previous literature, finding many incorrect identifications, most notably those in the NIST database. We provide several new tentative identifications in the 15-15.7 A range, and several new ones at shorter wavelengths, where previous lines were unidentified. Compared to the previous CHIANTI model, the present one has an increased flux in the 15--15.7 A range at 2 MK of a factor of 1.9, resolving the discrepancies found in the analysis of the Marshall Grazing Incidence X-Ray Spectrometer (MaGIXS) observation. It appears that the satellite lines also resolve the long-standing discrepancy in the intensity of the important Fe XVII 3D line at 15.26 A.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01274v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Del Zanna, N. R. Badnell, P. J. Storey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GRBoondi: A code for evolving Generalized Proca theories on arbitrary backgrounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01348v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While numerical simulations offer unparalleled precision and robustness in studying complex physical systems, their execution is often hindered by complexity, costliness, and time consumption due to the intricate equations involved. This challenge is already encountered in General Relativity, where non-flat spacetimes exacerbate the computational burden. This complexity is further intensified when dealing with additional degrees of freedom. To address this challenge head-on, we introduce GRBoondi, a groundbreaking fixed-background numerical relativity code designed to provide a unified interface for numerically solving Generalized Proca theories. GRBoondi grants users the ability to make arbitrary modifications to the Proca equations of motion on any background, providing a robust and versatile tool for exploring diverse classes of Generalized Proca theories. This letter serves as part of the submission of GRBoondi to the Journal of Open Source Software. For access to the code, please visit https://github.com/ShaunFell/GRBoondi.git.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01348v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaun David Brocus Fell, Lavinia Heisenberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancements in Streamlining Time-Domain and Multi-Messenger Astronomy Follow-Up Infrastructure at Keck Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01500v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With active time-domain surveys like the Zwicky Transient Facility, the anticipated Rubin Observatory's Legacy Survey of Space and Time, and multi-messenger experiments such as LIGO/VIRGO/KANGRA for gravitational wave detection and IceCube for high-energy neutrino events, there is a new era in both time-domain and multi-messenger astronomy. The Astro2020 decadal survey highlights effectively responding to these astronomical alerts in a timely manner as a priority, and thus, there is an urgent need for the development of a seamless follow-up infrastructure at existing facilities that are capable of following up on detections at the survey depths. At the W. M. Keck Observatory (WMKO), we are actively constructing critical infrastructure, aimed at facilitating the Target-of-Opportunity (ToO) trigger, optimizing observational planning, streamlining data acquisition, and enhancing data product accessibility. In this document, we provide an overview of these developing services and place them in context of existing observatory infrastructure like the Keck Observatory Archive (KOA) and Data Services Initiative (DSI).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01500v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chien-Hsiu Lee, Jeffrey A. Mader, Tyler Coda, Jo Hayashi, Max Brodheim, Lucas Fuhrman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symbiotic stars in X-rays IV: XMM-Newton, Swift and TESS observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01508v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: White dwarf symbiotic binaries are detected in X-rays with luminosities in the range of 10$^{30}$ to 10$^{34}$ lumcgs. Their X-ray emission arises either from the accretion disk boundary layer, from a region where the winds from both components collide or from nuclear burning on the white dwarf surface. In our continuous effort to identify X-ray emitting symbiotic stars, we studied four systems using observations from the Neil Gehrels Swift Observatory and XMM-Newton satellites in X-rays and from TESS in the optical. The X-ray spectra were fit with absorbed optically thin thermal plasma models, either single- or multitemperature with kT $&lt;$ 8 keV for all targets. Based on the characteristics of their X-ray spectra, we classified BD Cam as possible $\beta$-type, V1261 Ori and CD -27 8661 as $\delta$-type, and confirmed NQ Gem as $\beta$/$\delta$-type. The $\delta$-type X-ray emission most likely arise in the boundary layer of the accretion disk, while in the case of BD Cam, its mostly-soft emission originates from shocks, possibly between the red giant and WD/disk winds. In general, we have found that the observed X-ray emission is powered by accretion at a low accretion rate of about 10$^{-11}$ M$_{\odot}$ yr$^{-1}$. The low ratio of X-ray to optical luminosities, however indicates that the accretion-disk boundary layer is mostly optically thick and tends to emit in the far or extreme UV. The detection of flickering in optical data provides evidence of the existence of an accretion disk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01508v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isabel J. Lima, G. Juan M. Luna, Koji Mukai, Alexandre S. Oliveira, Jennifer L. Sokoloski, Fred Walter, Natalia Palivanas, Natalia E. Nu\~nez, Rafael R. Souza, Rosana A. N. Araujo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the X-ray polarimetric properties of LMC X-3 with IXPE, NICER, and Swift/XRT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.06830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.06830v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The incoming Imaging X-ray Polarimetry Explorer (IXPE) observations of X-ray binaries provide a new tool to investigate the underlying accretion geometry. Here we report the first measurements of X-ray polarization of the extra-galactic black-hole X-ray binary LMC X$-$3. We find a polarization fraction of $\sim 3%$ at a polarization angle of $\sim 135^\circ$ in the $2-8$ keV energy band with statistical significance at the 7$\sigma$ level. This polarization measurement significantly exceeds the minimum detectable polarization threshold of 1.2% for the source, ascertained at a 99% confidence level within the $2-8$ keV energy band. The simultaneous spectro-polarimetric fitting of NICER, Swift/XRT, and IXPE revealed the presence of a disc with a temperature of $\sim$1 keV and a Comptonized component with a power-law index of $\sim$ 2.4, confirming the soft nature of the source. The polarization degree increases with energy from $\sim$3% in the $2-5.7$ keV band to $\sim$9% in the $5.7-8$ keV band, while the polarization angle is energy independent. The observed energy dependence and the sudden jump of polarization fraction above 5 keV supports the idea of a static slab coronal geometry for the Comptonizing medium of LMC X$-$3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.06830v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akash Garg (IUCAA), Divya Rawat (IUCAA), Mariano M\'endez (Kapteyn Astronomical Institute)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Type Ia Supernova Progenitor Properties and Their Host Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03473v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an eigenfunction method to analyze 161 visual light curves (LCs) of Type Ia supernovae (SNe Ia) obtained by the Carnegie Supernova Project to characterize their diversity and host-galaxy correlations. The eigenfunctions are based on the delayed-detonation scenario using three parameters: the LC stretch being determined by the amount of deflagration-burning governing the 56Ni production, the main-sequence mass M_MS of the progenitor white dwarf controlling the explosion energy, and its central density rho_c shifting the 56Ni distribution. Our analysis tool (SPAT) extracts the parameters from observations and projects them into physical space using their allowed ranges M_MS &lt; 8 M_sun, rho_c &lt; 7-8x10^9g/cc. The residuals between fits and individual LC-points are ~ 1-3% for ~ 92% of objects. We find two distinct M_MS groups corresponding to a fast (~ 40-65 Myrs) and a slow(~ 200-500 Myrs) stellar evolution. Most underluminous SNe Ia have hosts with low star formation but high M_MS, suggesting slow evolution times of the progenitor system. 91T-likes SNe show very similar LCs and high M_MS and are correlated to star formation regions, making them potentially important tracers of star formation in the early Universe out to z = 4-11. Some 6% outliers with `non-physical' parameters can be attributed to superluminous SNe Ia and subluminous SNe Ia with hosts of active star formation. For deciphering the SNe Ia diversity and high-precision SNe Ia cosmology, the importance is shown for LCs covering out to ~ 60 days past maximum. Finally, our method and results are discussed within the framework of multiple explosion scenarios, and in light of upcoming surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03473v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudeshna Chakraborty, Benjamin Sadler, Peter Hoeflich, Eric Hsiao, M. M. Phillips, C. R. Burns, T. Diamond, I. Dominguez, L. Galbany, S. A. Uddin, C. Ashall, K. Krisciunas, S. Kumar, T. B. Mera, N. Morrell, E. Baron, M. C. Contreras, M. D. Stritzinger, N. N. Suntzeff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Broadband non-thermal emission of odd radio circles induced by explosive galactic outflow remnants and their evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12099v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Odd radio circles (ORCs) are mysterious rings of faint, diffuse emission recently discovered in radio surveys, some of which may be associated with galaxies in relatively dense environments. We propose such ORCs to be synchrotron emission from remnants of explosive galactic outflows, calling them OGREs, and discuss their broadband non-thermal emission and evolution. We posit that a large amount of energy was ejected from the central galaxy in the past, creating an outgoing shock that accelerates cosmic rays. Assuming plausible values for the density, temperature and magnetic field of the ambient medium, consistency with the observed spectral index, size and power of the ORCs requires the energy to be as high as ~10^60 erg, suggesting that their sources could be active galactic nuclei. We calculate the spectral energy distributions (SEDs) of the OGREs and their evolution, including synchrotron, inverse Compton (IC) and bremsstrahlung emission from electrons, and pion-decay emission from protons. We find that the SEDs of the younger OGREs are not greatly different from those of older ones currently observable as ORCs if radiative cooling of electrons is effective. As such younger OGREs are expected to be rarer and smaller, they may not be readily observable. However, if radiative cooling of electrons is ineffective, younger OGREs may be detectable in X-rays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12099v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yutaka Fujita, Norita Kawanaka, Susumu Inoue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy spectra of elemental groups of cosmic rays with the KASCADE experiment data and machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.08279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.08279v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the reconstruction of the mass component spectra of cosmic rays (protons, helium, carbon, silicon and iron) and their mean mass composition, at energies from 1.4 to 100 PeV. The results are derived from the archival data of the extensive air shower experiment KASCADE. We use a novel machine learning technique developed specifically for this reconstruction, and post-LHC hadronic interaction models: QGSJet-II.04, EPOS-LHC and Sibyll 2.3c. We have found an excess of the proton component and a deficit of intermediate and heavy nuclei components compared to the original KASCADE results. The spectra of protons and helium show a knee-like behavior at ~ 4.4 PeV and ~ 11 PeV, with significances 5.2${\sigma}$ and 3.9${\sigma}$, respectively. The spectrum of the iron component has a hint (2.4${\sigma}$) of a hardening at ~ 4.5 PeV, which can be interpreted as a counterpart of a hardening in the proton spectrum at 166 TeV, recently reported by the GRAPES-3 experiment. The systematic uncertainties of our analysis were found to be smaller than those of the original KASCADE, as well as those of IceTop and TALE experiments, over the most part of the energy range studied. We also estimated separately the uncertainty related to the difference between the three mentioned hadronic interaction models. We also compute a mean logarithm mass of cosmic ray flux as a function of energy. It is in agreement with the results of IceTop, TALE and LHAASO within the uncertainties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.08279v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Yu. Kuznetsov, N. A. Petrov, I. A. Plokhikh, V. V. Sotnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on Lorentz invariance violation from the LHAASO observation of GRB 221009A</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.09079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.09079v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In some quantum gravity (QG) theories, Lorentz symmetry may be broken above the Planck scale. The Lorentz invariance violation (LIV) may induce observable effects at low energies and be detected at high energy astrophysical measurements. The Large High Altitude Air Shower Observatory(LHAASO) has detected the onset, rise, and decay phases of the afterglow of GRB 221009A, covering a wide energy range of photons approximately from $0.2$ to $18$ TeV. This observation provides an excellent opportunity to study the Lorentz invariance violation effect. In this study, we simultaneously utilize the data from the KM2A and WCDA detectors of LHAASO, and apply two event by event methods, namely the pair view method and maximum likelihood method, to investigate LIV. We obtain stringent constraints on the QG energy scale. For instance, through the maximum likelihood method, we determine the 95$\%$ confidence level lower limits to be $E_{QG,1} &gt; 14.7 (6.5)\times 10^{19}$GeV for the subluminal (superluminal) scenario of $n = 1$, and $E_{QG,2} &gt; 12.0 (7.2)\times 10^{11}$GeV for the subluminal (superluminal) scenario of $n = 2$. We find that the rapid rise and slow decay behaviors of the afterglow can impose strong constraints on the subluminal scenario, while the constraints are weaker for the superluminal scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.09079v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2024/04/060</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP 04 (2024) 060</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Ming Yang, Xiao-Jun Bi, Peng-Fei Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization properties of 128 non-repeating fast radio bursts from the first CHIME/FRB baseband catalog</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17378v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a 400-800 MHz polarimetric analysis of 128 non-repeating fast radio bursts (FRBs) from the first CHIME/FRB baseband catalog, increasing the total number of FRB sources with polarization properties by a factor of ~3. 89 FRBs have &gt;6${\sigma}$ linearly polarized detections, 29 FRBs fall below this significance threshold and are deemed linearly unpolarized, and for 10 FRBs the polarization data are contaminated by instrumental polarization. For the 89 polarized FRBs, we find Faraday rotation measure (RM) amplitudes, after subtracting approximate Milky Way contributions, in the range 0.5-1160 rad m$^{-2}$ with a median of 53.8 rad m$^{-2}$. Most non-repeating FRBs in our sample have RMs consistent with Milky Way-like host galaxies and their linear polarization fractions range from &lt;10% to 100% with a median of 63%. We see marginal evidence that non-repeating FRBs have more constraining lower limits than repeating FRBs for the host electron-density-weighted line-of-sight magnetic field strength. We classify the non-repeating FRB polarization position angle (PA) profiles into four archetypes: (i) single component with constant PA (57% of the sample), (ii) single component with variable PA (10%), (iii) multiple components with a single constant PA (22%), and (iv) multiple components with different or variable PAs (11%). We see no evidence for population-wide frequency-dependent depolarization and, therefore, the spread in the distribution of fractional linear polarization is likely intrinsic to the FRB emission mechanism. Finally, we present a novel method to derive redshift lower limits for polarized FRBs without host galaxy identification and test this method on 20 FRBs with independently measured redshifts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17378v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayush Pandhi, Ziggy Pleunis, Ryan Mckinven, B. M. Gaensler, Jianing Su, Cherry Ng, Mohit Bhardwaj, Charanjot Brar, Tomas Cassanelli, Amanda M. Cook, Alice P. Curtin, Victoria M. Kaspi, Mattias Lazda, Calvin Leung, Dongzi Li, Kiyoshi W. Masui, Daniele Michilli, Kenzie Nimmo, Aaron Pearlman, Emily Petroff, Masoud Rafiei-Ravandi, Ketan R. Sand, Paul Scholz, Kaitlyn Shin, Kendrick Smith, Ingrid Stairs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gamma-ray Bursts as Distance Indicators by a Statistical Learning Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04551v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Gamma-ray bursts (GRBs) can be probes of the early universe, but currently, only 26% of GRBs observed by the Neil Gehrels Swift Observatory GRBs have known redshifts ($z$) due to observational limitations. To address this, we estimated the GRB redshift (distance) via a supervised statistical learning model that uses optical afterglow observed by Swift and ground-based telescopes. The inferred redshifts are strongly correlated (a Pearson coefficient of 0.93) with the observed redshifts, thus proving the reliability of this method. The inferred and observed redshifts allow us to estimate the number of GRBs occurring at a given redshift (GRB rate) to be 8.47-9 $yr^{-1} Gpc^{-1}$ for $1.9&lt;z&lt;2.3$. Since GRBs come from the collapse of massive stars, we compared this rate with the star formation rate highlighting a discrepancy of a factor of 3 at $z&lt;1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04551v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Giovanna Dainotti, Aditya Narendra, Agnieszka Pollo, Vahe Petrosian, Malgorzata Bogdan, Kazunari Iwasaki, Jason Xavier Prochaska, Enrico Rinaldi, David Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of the first anti-glitch event in the rotation-powered pulsar PSR B0540-69</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18158v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Using data from the Neutron star Interior Composition ExploreR (NICER) observatory, we identified a permanent spin frequency decrease of $\Delta\nu=-(1.04\pm0.07)\times 10^{-7}\,\mathrm{Hz}$ around MJD 60132 in the rotation-powered pulsar PSR B0540-69, which exhibits a periodic signal at a frequency of $\nu\sim 19.6\,\mathrm{Hz}$. This points to an anti-glitch event, a sudden decrease of the pulsar's rotational frequency without any major alteration in the pulse profile or any significant increase of the pulsed flux. Additionally, no burst activity was observed in association with the anti-glitch. To date, observations of the few known anti-glitches have been made in magnetars or accreting pulsars. This is the first anti-glitch detected in a rotation-powered pulsar. Given its radiatively quiet nature, this anti-glitch is possibly of internal origin. Therefore, we tentatively frame this event within a proposed mechanism for anti-glitches where the partial `evaporation' of the superfluid component leads to an increase of the normal component's moment of inertia and a decrease of the superfluid one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18158v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/ad4488</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Youli Tuo, M. M. Serim, Marco Antonelli, Lorenzo Ducci, Armin Vahdat, Mingyu Ge, Andrea Santangelo, Fei Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chandra Study of the Proper Motion of HST-1 in the Jet of M87</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19272v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The radio galaxy M87 is well known for its jet, which features a series of bright knots observable from radio to X-ray wavelengths. We analyze the X-ray image and flux variability of the knot HST-1 in the jet. Our analysis includes all 112 available Chandra ACIS-S observations from 2000-2021, with a total exposure time of $\sim$887 ks. We use de-convolved images to study the brightness profile of the X-ray jet and measure the relative separation between the core and HST-1. From 2003-2005 (which coincides with a bright flare from HST-1), we find a correlation between the flux of HST-1 and its offset from the core. In subsequent data, we find a steady increase in this offset, which implies a bulk superluminal motion for HST-1 of 6.6$\pm$0.9 c (2.0$\pm$0.3 pc yr$^{-1}$), in keeping with prior results. We discuss models for the flux-offset correlation that feature either two or four emission regions separated by tens of parsecs. We attribute these results to moving shocks in the jet, that allow us to measure the internal structure of the jet.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19272v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rameshan Thimmappa, Joey Neilsen, Daryl Haggard, Michael A. Nowak, Sera Markoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Afterglow: Light Dark Matter Boosted by Supernova Neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.06864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.06864v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A novel analysis is performed, incorporating time-of-flight (TOF) information to study the interactions of dark matter (DM) with standard model particles. After supernova (SN) explosions, DM with mass $m_\chi\lesssim\mathcal{O}({\rm MeV})$ in the halo can be boosted by SN neutrinos (SN$\nu$) to relativistic speed. The SN$\nu$ boosted DM (BDM) arrives on Earth with TOF which depends only on $m_\chi$ and is independent of the cross section. These BDMs can interact with detector targets in low-background experiments and manifest as afterglow events after the arrival of SN$\nu$. The characteristic TOF spectra of the BDM events can lead to large background suppression and unique determination of $m_\chi$. New cross section constraints on $\sqrt{\sigma_{\chi e} \sigma_{\chi\nu}}$ are derived from SN1987a in the Large Magellanic Cloud with data from the Kamiokande and Super-Kamiokande experiments. Potential sensitivities for the next galactic SN with Hyper-Kamiokande are projected. This analysis extends the existing bounds on $\sqrt{\sigma_{\chi e}\sigma_{\chi \nu}}$ over a broad range of $r_\chi=\sigma_{\chi \nu}/\sigma_{\chi e}$. In particular, the improvement is by 1-3 orders of magnitude for $m_\chi&lt;\mathcal{O}(100\,{\rm keV})$ for $\sigma_{\chi e}\sim\sigma_{\chi \nu}$. Prospects of exploiting TOF information in other astrophysical systems to probe exotic physics with other DM candidates are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.06864v4</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.130.111002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 130, 111002 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yen-Hsun Lin, Wen-Hua Wu, Meng-Ru Wu, Henry Tsz-King Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of afterglows from light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos in current and future large underground detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.03522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.03522v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Supernova neutrino boosted dark matter (SN$\nu$ BDM) and its afterglow effect have been shown to be a promising signature for beyond Standard Model (bSM) physics. The time-evolution feature of SN$\nu$ BDM allows for %the possibly direct inference of DM mass $m_\chi$, and results in significant background suppression with improving sensitivity. This paper extends the earlier study and provides a general framework for computing the SN$\nu$ BDM fluxes for a supernova that occurs at any location in our galaxy. A bSM $U(1)_{L_\mu-L_\tau}$ model with its gauge boson coupling to both DM and the second and third generation of leptons is considered, which allows for both DM-$\nu$ and DM-$e$ interactions. Detailed analysis of the temporal profile, angular distribution, and energy spectrum of the SN$\nu$ BDM are performed. Unique signatures in SN$\nu$ BDM allowing extraction of $m_\chi$ and detail features that contain information of the underlying interaction type are discussed. Expected sensitivities on the above new physics model from Super-Kamiokande, Hyper-Kamiokande, and DUNE detections of BDM events induced by the next galactic SN are derived and compared with the existing bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.03522v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.108.083013</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 108, 083013 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yen-Hsun Lin, Tsung-Han Tsai, Guey-Lin Lin, Henry Tsz-King Wong, Meng-Ru Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrobaryonic axion: hair of neutron stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.18794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.18794v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Axion-like particles are predicted in many physics scenarios beyond the Standard Model (SM). Their interactions with SM particles may arise from the triangle anomaly of the associated global symmetry, along with other SM global and gauge symmetries, including anomalies with the global baryon number and electromagnetic gauge symmetries. We initiate the phenomenological study of the corresponding ``electrobaryonic axion", a particle that couples with both the baryon chemical potential and the electromagnetic field. Neutron stars, particularly magnetars, possessing high baryon density and strong magnetic fields, can naturally develop a thin axion hair around their surface. In this study, we calculate this phenomenon, considering the effects of neutron star rotation and general relativity. For axion particles lighter than the neutron star rotation frequency, the anomalous interaction can also induce the emission of axion particles from the neutron star. This emission, in the light axion regime, can have a significant contribution to the neutron star cooling rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.18794v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Bai, Carlos Henrique de Lima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Black holes surrounded by generic matter distributions: polar perturbations and energy flux</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.00932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.00932v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a numerical approach to compute polar parity perturbations within fully relativistic models of black hole systems embedded in generic, spherically symmetric, anisotropic fluids. We apply this framework to study gravitational wave generation and propagation from extreme mass-ratio inspirals in the presence of several astrophysically relevant dark matter models, namely the Hernquist, Navarro-Frenk-White, and Einasto profiles. We also study dark matter spike profiles obtained from a fully relativistic calculation of the adiabatic growth of a BH within the Hernquist profile, and provide a closed-form analytic fit of these profiles. Our analysis completes prior numerical work in the axial sector, yielding a fully numerical pipeline to study black hole environmental effects. We study the dependence of the fluxes on the DM halo mass and compactness. We find that, unlike the axial case, polar fluxes are not adequately described by simple gravitational-redshift effects, thus offering an exciting avenue for the study of black hole environments with gravitational waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.00932v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.084068</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Speeney, Emanuele Berti, Vitor Cardoso, Andrea Maselli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Changing-look Active Galactic Nuclei with the Sloan Digital Sky Survey V: First Year Results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.01933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.01933v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: "Changing-look" active galactic nuclei (CL-AGNs) challenge our basic ideas about the physics of accretion flows and circumnuclear gas around supermassive black holes. Using first-year Sloan Digital Sky Survey V (SDSS-V) repeated spectroscopy of nearly 29,000 previously known AGNs, combined with dedicated follow-up spectroscopy, and publicly available optical light curves, we have identified 116 CL-AGNs where (at least) one broad emission line has essentially (dis-)appeared, as well as 88 other extremely variable systems. Our CL-AGN sample, with 107 newly identified cases, is the largest reported to date, and includes $\sim0.4\%$ of the AGNs reobserved in first-year SDSS-V operations. Among our CL-AGNs, 67% exhibit dimming while 33% exhibit brightening. Our sample probes extreme AGN spectral variability on months to decades timescales, including some cases of recurring transitions on surprisingly short timescales ($\lesssim 2$ months in the rest frame). We find that CL events are preferentially found in lower-Eddington-ratio ($f_{Edd}$) systems: Our CL-AGNs have a $f_{Edd}$ distribution that significantly differs from that of a carefully constructed, redshift- and luminosity-matched control sample (Anderson-Darling test yielding $p_{\rm AD}\approx 6\times10^{-5}$; median $f_{Edd}\approx0.025$ vs. $0.043$). This preference for low $f_{Edd}$ strengthens previous findings of higher CL-AGN incidence at lower $f_{Edd}$, found in smaller samples. Finally, we show that the broad MgII emission line in our CL-AGN sample tends to vary significantly less than the broad H$\beta$ emission line. Our large CL-AGN sample demonstrates the advantages and challenges in using multi-epoch spectroscopy from large surveys to study extreme AGN variability and physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.01933v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad2f30</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJ 966 85 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Grisha Zeltyn, Benny Trakhtenbrot, Michael Eracleous, Qian Yang, Paul Green, Scott F. Anderson, Stephanie LaMassa, Jessie Runnoe, Roberto J. Assef, Franz E. Bauer, W. N. Brandt, Megan C. Davis, Sara E. Frederick, Logan B. Fries, Matthew J. Graham, Norman A. Grogin, Muryel Guolo, Lorena Hern\'andez-Garc\'ia, Anton M. Koekemoer, Mirko Krumpe, Xin Liu, Mary Loli Mart\'inez-Aldama, Claudio Ricci, Donald P. Schneider, Yue Shen, Marzena \'Sniegowska, Matthew J. Temple, Jonathan R. Trump, Yongquan Xue, Joel R. Brownstein, Tom Dwelly, Sean Morrison, Dmitry Bizyaev, Kaike Pan, Juna A. Kollmeier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian $\mathcal{F}$-statistic-based parameter estimation of continuous gravitational waves from known pulsars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17025v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a new method and implementation to obtain Bayesian posteriors on the amplitude parameters $\{h_0, \cos \iota, \psi, \phi_0\}$ of continuous-gravitational waves emitted by known pulsars. This approach leverages the well-established $\mathcal{F}$-statistic framework and software. We further explore the benefits of employing a likelihood function that is analytically marginalized over $\phi_0$, which avoids signal degeneracy problems in the $\psi$-$\phi_0$ subspace. The method is tested on simulated signals, hardware injections in Advanced-LIGO detector data, and by performing percentile-percentile (PP) self-consistency tests of the posteriors via Monte-Carlo simulations. We apply our methodology to PSR J1526-2744, a recently discovered millisecond pulsar. We find no evidence for a signal and obtain a Bayesian upper limit $h_0^{95\%}$ on the gravitational-wave amplitude of approximately $7 \times 10^{-27}$, comparable with a previous frequentist upper limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17025v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.104002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 104002 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. Ashok, P. B. Covas, R. Prix, M. A. Papa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MeV gamma rays from Q-ball decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01675v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the supersymmetric Q balls which decay at present and find that they create a distinctive spectrum of gamma rays at around O(10) MeV. The charge of the Q ball is lepton numbers in order for the lifetime to be as long as the present age of the universe, and the main decay products are light leptons. However, as the charge of the Q ball decreases, the decay channel into pions becomes kinematically allowed towards the end of the decay, and the pions are produced at rest. Immediately, $\pi^0$ decays into two photons with the energy of 67.5 MeV, half the pion mass, which exhibits a unique emission line. In addition, $\pi^\pm$ decay into $\mu^\pm$, which further decay with emitting internal bremsstrahlung, whose spectrum has a sharp cutoff at $\sim$50 MeV. If the observations would find these peculiar features of the gamma-ray spectrum in the future, it could be a smoking gun of the supersymmetric Q-ball decay at present.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01675v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shinta Kasuya, Masahiro Kawasaki, Naomi Tsuji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Illuminating Black Hole Shadow with Dark Matter Annihilation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16673v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Event Horizon Telescope (EHT) has revolutionized our ability to study black holes by providing unprecedented spatial resolution and unveiling horizon-scale details. With advancements leading to the next-generation EHT, there is potential to probe even deeper into the black hole's dark region, especially the inner shadow characterized by low-intensity foreground emissions from the jet, thanks to a significant enhancement in dynamic range by two orders of magnitude. We demonstrate how such enhanced observations could transform supermassive black holes into powerful probes for detecting annihilating dark matter, which can form a dense profile in the vicinity of supermassive black holes, by examining the morphology of the black hole image.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16673v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Chen, Ran Ding, Yuxin Liu, Yosuke Mizuno, Jing Shu, Haiyue Yu, Yanjie Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
