<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.HE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.HE</link>
    <description>astro-ph.HE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.HE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 04:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Tracing back the birth environments of Type Ia supernova progenitor stars: A pilot study based on 44 early-type host galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13057v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The environmental dependence of Type Ia supernova (SN Ia) luminosities is well-established, and efforts are being made to find its origin. Previous studies typically use the currently-observed status of the host galaxy. However, given the delay time between the birth of the progenitor star and the SN Ia explosion, the currently-observed status may differ from the birth environments of the SN Ia progenitor star. In this paper, employing the chemical evolution and accurately determined stellar population properties of 44 early-type host galaxies, we, for the first time, estimate the SN Ia progenitor star birth environment, specifically $[Fe/H]_{Birth}$ and $[\alpha/Fe]_{Birth}$. We show that $[\alpha/Fe]_{Birth}$ has a $30.4^{+10.6}_{-10.1}\%$ wider range than $[\alpha/Fe]_{Current}$, while the range of $[Fe/H]_{Birth}$ is not statistically different ($17.9^{+26.0}_{-27.1}\%$) to that of $[Fe/H]_{Current}$. The birth and current environments of [Fe/H] and [$\alpha$/Fe] are sample from different populations (p-values of the KS test &lt; 0.01). We find that light-curve fit parameters are insensitive to $[Fe/H]_{Birth}$ ($&lt;0.9\sigma$ for the non-zero slope), while a linear trend is observed with HRs at the 2.4$\sigma$ significance level. With $[\alpha/Fe]_{Birth}$, no linear trends ($&lt;1.1\sigma$) are observed. Interestingly, we find that $[\alpha/Fe]_{Birth}$ clearly splits the SN Ia sample into two groups: SN Ia exploded in $[\alpha/Fe]_{Birth}$-rich or $[\alpha/Fe]_{Birth}$-poor environments. SNe Ia exploded in different $[\alpha/Fe]_{Birth}$ groups have different weighted-means of light-curve shape parameters: $0.81\pm0.33$ ($2.5\sigma$). They are thought to be drawn from different populations (p-value = 0.01). Regarding SN Ia colour and HRs, there is no difference in the weighted-means ($&lt;1.0\sigma$) and distributions (p-value &gt; 0.27) of each $[\alpha/Fe]_{Birth}$ group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13057v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Young-Lo Kim, Llu\'is Galbany, Isobel Hook, Yijung Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of the disk magnetization on MHD disk wind signature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13077v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Observation of blue-shifted X-ray absorption lines indicates the presence of wind from the accretion disk in X-ray binaries. Magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) driving is one of the possible wind launching mechanisms. Recent theoretical development makes magnetic accretion-ejection self-similar solutions much more generalized, and wind can be launched even at much lower magnetization compared to equipartition value, which was the only possibility beforehand. Here, we model the transmitted spectra through MHD driven photoionized wind - models which have different values of magnetizations. We investigate the possibility of detecting absorption lines by the upcoming instruments XRISM and Athena. Attempts are made to find the robustness of the method of fitting asymmetric line profiles by multiple Gaussians. We use photoionization code XSTAR to simulate the transmitted model spectra. Fake observed spectra are finally produced by convolving model spectra with instruments' responses. Since the line asymmetries are apparent in the convolved spectra as well, this can be used as an observable diagnostic to fit for, in future XRISM and Athena spectra. We demonstrate some amount of rigor in assessing the equivalent widths of the major absorption lines, including the Fe XXVI Ly$\alpha$ doublets which can be clearly distinguished in the superior quality, future high resolution spectra. Disk magnetization becomes another crucial MHD variable that can significantly alter the absorption line profiles. Low magnetization pure MHD outflow models are dense enough to be observed by the existing or upcoming instruments. Thus these models become simpler alternatives to MHD-thermal models. Fitting with multiple Gaussians is a promising method to handle asymmetric line profiles, as well as the Fe XXVI Ly$\alpha$ doublets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13077v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudeb Ranjan Datta, Susmita Chakravorty, Jonathan Ferreira, Pierre-Olivier Petrucci, Timothy R Kallman, Jonatan Jacquemin-Ide, Nathan Zimniak, Joern Wilms, Stefano Bianchi, Maxime Parra, Ma\"ica Clavel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutral Fraction of Hydrogen in the Intergalactic Medium Surrounding High-Redshift Gamma-Ray Burst 210905A</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13126</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13126v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Epoch of Reionization (EoR) is a key period of cosmological history in which the intergalactic medium (IGM) underwent a major phase change from being neutral to almost completely ionized. Gamma-ray bursts (GRBs) are luminous and unique probes of their environments that can be used to study the timeline for the progression of the EoR. Here we present a detailed analysis of the ESO Very Large Telescope X-shooter spectrum of GRB 210905A, which resides at a redshift of z ~ 6.3. We focus on estimating the fraction of neutral hydrogen, xHI, on the line of sight to the host galaxy of GRB 210905A by fitting the shape of the Lyman-alpha damping wing of the afterglow spectrum. The X-shooter spectrum has a high signal to noise ratio, but the complex velocity structure of the host galaxy limits the precision of our conclusions. The statistically preferred model suggests a low neutral fraction with an 3-sigma upper limit of xHI &lt; 0.15, indicating that the IGM around the GRB host galaxy is mostly ionized. We discuss complications in current analyses and potential avenues for future studies of the progression of the EoR and its evolution with redshift.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13126v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. M. Fausey, S. Vejlgaard, A. J. van der Horst, K. E. Heintz, L. Izzo, D. B. Malesani, K. Wiersema, J. P. U. Fynbo, N. R. Tanvir, S. D. Vergani, A. Saccardi, A. Rossi, S. Campana, S. Covino, V. D'Elia, M. De Pasquale, D. Hartmann, P. Jakobsson, C. Kouveliotou, A. Levan, A. Martin-Carrillo, A. Melandri, J. Palmerio, G. Pugliese, R. Salvaterra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Timing analysis of the newly discovered black hole candidate Swift J1727.8-1613 with Insight-HXMT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13127v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the results obtained from an X-ray timing study of the new black hole candidate (BHC) Swift J1727.8-1613. The work is based on Hard X-ray Modulation Telescope (Insight-HXMT) observations carried out during the 2023 outburst. Prominent type-C low-frequency Quasi-periodic Oscillations (LFQPOs) are detected throughout the observations. With the substantial effective area of the Insight-HXMT at high energies, we examine the energy dependence of various parameters, including the centroid frequency, fractional rms, and phase lags of the type-C QPOs. Our findings align closely with those observed in high-inclination systems. During the initial stage of the outburst, a peaked noise component is also detected, the frequency of which is highly correlated with the LFQPO frequency, aligning with the Psaltis-Belloni-van der Klis (PBK) relation. By assuming that the peaked noise originates from the precession of the accretion disc, the spin of this source can be constrained. Our results suggest that this source may possess a high spin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13127v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Yu, Qing-Cui Bu, Shuang-Nan Zhang, He-Xin Liu, Liang Zhang, Lorenzo Ducci, Lian Tao, Andrea Santangelo, Victor Doroshenko, Yue Huang, Zi-Xu Yang, Jin-Lu Qu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematic errors in searches for nanohertz gravitational waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13175v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A number of pulsar timing arrays have recently reported preliminary evidence for the existence of a nanohertz frequency gravitational-wave background. These analyses rely on detailed noise analyses, which are inherently complex due to the many astrophysical and instrumental factors that contribute to the pulsar noise budget. We investigate whether realistic systematic errors, stemming from misspecified noise models that fail to capture salient features of the pulsar timing noise, could bias the evidence for gravitational waves. We consider two plausible forms of misspecification: small unmodeled jumps and unmodeled chromatic noise. Using simulated data, we calculate the distribution of the commonly used optimal statistic with no signal present and using plausibly misspecified noise models. By comparing the optimal statistic distribution with the distribution created using ``quasi-resampling'' techniques (such as sky scrambles and phase shifts), we endeavor to determine the extent to which plausible misspecification might lead to a false positive. The results are reassuring: we find that quasi-resampling techniques tend to underestimate the significance of pure-noise datasets. We conclude that recent reported evidence for a nanohertz gravitational-wave background is likely robust to the most obvious sources of systematic errors; if anything, the significance of the signal is potentially underestimated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13175v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentina Di Marco, Andrew Zic, Ryan M. Shannon, Eric Thrane</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-ray analysis of Seyfert 1 galaxies with optical polarization: a test for unification models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In accordance with the AGN Unified Model, observed polarization can be related to the orientation of the line of sight with respect to the torus. AGN X-ray emission arises from the central region and carries the imprints of the obscuring material. We aim to test a unified scheme based on optical polarization using X-ray absorption. Using the XMM-Newton data of 19, optically polarized Seyfert 1 sources, we developed a systematic analysis by fitting a baseline model to test the presence of X-ray neutral or ionized (warm) absorption. We find that 100\% of the polar-polarized sources show the presence of absorption, with 70\% favoring the presence of a warm absorber. In contrast, the equatorial-polarized sources show a fraction of absorbed spectra of 75\%, with only 50\% consistent with the presence of a warm absorber.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13194v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miriam Gudi\~no, Elena Jim\'enez-Bail\'on, Anna Lia Longinotti, Matteo Guainazzi, Miguel Cervi\~no, Aitor Robleto-Or\'us</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Repeating X-ray bursts: Interaction between a neutron star and clumps partially disrupted from a planet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13333v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Repeating X-ray bursts from the Galactic magnetar SGR 1806-20 have been observed with a period of 398 days. Similarly, periodic X-ray bursts from SGR 1935+2154 with a period of 238 days have also been observed. Here we argue that these X-ray bursts could be produced by the interaction of a neutron star (NS) with its planet in a highly elliptical orbit. The periastron of the planet is very close to the NS, so it would be partially disrupted by the tidal force every time it passes through the periastron. Major fragments generated in the process will fall onto the NS under the influence of gravitational perturbation. The collision of the in-falling fragments with the NS produces repeating X-ray bursts. The main features of the observed X-ray bursts, such as their energy, duration, periodicity, and activity window, can all be explained in our framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13333v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdusattar Kurban, Xia Zhou, Na Wang, Yong-Feng Huang, Yu-Bin Wang, Nurimangul Nurmamat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From known to unknown: cosmic rays transition from the Sun, the Galaxy, and the Extra-Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13482v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Sun stands out as the closest and clearest astrophysical accelerator of cosmic rays, while other objects within and beyond the galaxy remain enigmatic. It is probable that the cosmic ray spectrum and mass components from these celestial sources share similarities, offering a novel approach to study their origin. In this study, we analyze of spectra and mass in the energy range from MeV to 10~EeV. We find: (1) the mean-logarithmic mass $\rm\left\langle lnA \right\rangle$ distribution with energy exhibits much clearer feature structures than the spectra; (2) a 100~TeV bump is presented in the $\rm\left\langle lnA \right\rangle$ distribution; (3) for protons, the knee is located at $\sim2$ PeV, the boundary between the galaxy and extra-galaxy occurs at $\sim30$ PeV, marked by a sharp dip; (4) the all-particle spectrum exhibits hardening at $\sim30$~PeV due to the contribution of nearby galaxies, and the extra-galactic dominate $\sim0.7$~EeV. We hope the LHAASO experiment can perform spectral measurements of individual species to validate our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13482v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Hua Yao, Yi-Qing Guo, Wei Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The bicoherence study of quasi-periodic oscillations in MAXI J1535-571</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13606v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Bicoherence is a way to measure the phase coupling of triplets of Fourier frequencies. We use this method to analyze quasi-periodic oscillations (QPOs) in the black hole X-ray binary MAXI J1535$-$571 during its 2017 September-October outburst. The bicoherence provides an interesting new diagnostic to uncover QPO behaviour and the relationships between QPO harmonics and broadband noise. The bicoherence pattern of type-C QPOs starts as a 'web' pattern and changes to a 'hypotenuse' pattern after the presence of type-B QPOs, indicating that MAXI J1535$-$571 is a low-inclination source. The intensity of bicoherence also exhibits variations across different energy bands. We try to explain the bicoherence results in the scenario of a dual-corona geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13606v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyuan Zhu, Xiao Chen, Wei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sculpting the Morphology of Supernova Remnant Pa 30 via Efficient Ejecta Cooling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate in a proof-of-concept numerical hydrodynamics calculation that the narrow radial filamentary structures seen in Pa 30 could be generated through highly efficient cooling (e.g. via line emission) in the ejecta. Efficient cooling in the ejecta causes a drop of pressure support in Rayleigh-Taylor fingers, leading them to be compressed, and suppressing the growth of Kelvin-Helmholtz instability. Following this result, we make three predictions that could determine whether this is the mechanism responsible for shaping Pa 30: First, we predict very strong emission lines, strong enough to cool a significant fraction of the shock energy in an expansion time. Secondly, we predict that the forward shock should be highly corrugated on small scales, with the shock front closely following the structure of the filaments. Third, we predict that these filaments should be nearly ballistic, with velocities around 90% of the free-expansion velocity ($v \approx 0.9 ~r/t$). These predictions should be falsifiable in follow-up observations of this remnant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13641v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul C. Duffell, Abigail Polin, Soham Mandal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on VHE gamma-ray emission of Flat Spectrum Radio Quasars with the MAGIC telescopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13713v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Flat spectrum radio quasars (FSRQs) constitute a class of jetted active galaxies characterized by a very luminous accretion disk, prominent and rapidly moving line-emitting cloud structures (Broad Line Region, BLR), and a surrounding dense dust structure known as dusty torus. The intense radiation field of the accretion disk strongly determines the observational properties of FSRQs.
  While hundreds of such sources have been detected at GeV energies, only a handful of them exhibit emission in the very-high-energy (VHE, E $\gtrsim 100$ GeV) range.
  This study presents the results and interpretation derived from a cumulative observation period of 174 hours dedicated to nine FSRQs conducted with the MAGIC telescopes from 2008 to 2020. Our findings indicate no statistically significant ($\geq$ 5 $\sigma$) signal for any of the studied sources, resulting in upper limits on the emission within the VHE energy range.
  In two of the sources, we derived quite stringent constraints on the $\gamma$-ray emission in the form of upper limits. Our analysis focuses on modeling the VHE emission of these two sources in search for hints of absorption signatures within the broad line region (BLR) radiation field. For these particular sources, constraints on the distance between the emission region and the central black hole are derived using a phenomenological model. Subsequently, these constraints are tested using a framework based on a leptonic model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13713v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> MAGIC Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Examining a hadronic $\gamma$-ray scenario for the radiative shell &amp; molecular clouds of the old GeV supernova remnant G298.6$-$0.0</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13723</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13723v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Based on the 13.7~yr Fermi-LAT data, Yeung et al. (2023) claimed detection of two $\gamma$-ray sources (Src-NE and Src-NW) associated with the supernova remnant (SNR) G298.6$-$0.0, and interpreted it as an old GeV SNR interacting with molecular clouds (MCs). In this follow-up study, we refine the flux measurements below 2~GeV with Fermi-LAT event types of better angular reconstruction. Then, we report our cosmic-ray phenomenology in a hadronic scenario, considering both the shell and MC regions of SNR G298.6$-$0.0. We confirm that both the $\gamma$-ray spectra of Src-NE and Src-NW exhibit spectral breaks at $1.50_{-0.50}^{+0.60}$~GeV and $0.68_{-0.11}^{+0.32}$~GeV, respectively. Src-NW has a harder broadband photon index than Src-NE, suggesting an appreciable difference between the physical separations of their respective emission sites from SNR G298.6$-$0.0. The cosmic-ray spectrum responsible for Src-NE starts with a minimum energy $E_\mathrm{CR,min}=1.38_{-0.16}^{+0.47}$~GeV, and has a proton index $\Gamma_\mathrm{CR}=2.57_{-0.21}^{+0.18}$ below the exponential cutoff energy $E_\mathrm{CR,max}=240_{-150}^{+240}$~GeV. Accordingly, we argue that Src-NE is dominated by the SNR shell, while only a minor portion of lower-energy emission is contributed by the MCs interacting with the SNR. The cosmic-ray population for Src-NW starts at a higher energy such that the $E_\mathrm{CR,min}$ ratio of Src-NW to Src-NE is $\gtrsim$2. The high $E_\mathrm{CR,min}$, as well as the high cosmic-ray energy density required ($\sim$26~eV~cm$^{-3}$), supports the interpretation that Src-NW is predominantly the $\gamma$-ray emission from the farther MCs being bombarded by protons that had earlier escaped from SNR G298.6$-$0.0. By comparing the high-energy features of G298.6$-$0.0 with those of analogical SNRs, especially SNR W28 and SNR W44, we further constrain the age of SNR G298.6$-$0.0 to be 10--30~kyr.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13723v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul K. H. Yeung, Shiu-Hang Lee, Tsunefumi Mizuno, Aya Bamba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observational signatures of Rotating compact objects in Plasma space-time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12439v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We have investigated the characteristics of shadows cast by the Kerr black hole in the presence of plasma and compared them to those of a rotating wormhole in a uniform plasma space-time for an observer at infinity. Interestingly, for the same uniform plasma density, the apparent shadow size of the rotating wormhole is always greater than that of the Kerr black hole. To further distinguish the two compact objects we studied the deflection angle and did a comparative study in the presence of the uniform and non-uniform plasma profiles. The goal of this whole exercise is to deepen our understanding of the observational phenomena of these astrophysical objects. The analysis reveals the importance of specific plasma distribution profiles, the impact of plasma on the shadow diameter, and the behavior of deflection angles in different plasma scenarios. We have calculated constraints on the plasma parameters by considering observational data and employing analytical formulations, we have calculated constraints on the plasma parameters. Our work therefore provides valuable insights into the behavior of light rays near compact objects in plasma space-time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12439v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saurabh Kumar, Akhil Uniyal, Sayan Chakrabarti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shock and Cosmic Ray Chemistry Associated with the Supernova Remnant W28</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13305v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Supernova remnants (SNRs) exert strong influence on the physics and chemistry of the nearby molecular clouds (MCs) through shock waves and the cosmic rays (CRs) they accelerate. To investigate the SNR-cloud interaction in the prototype interacting SNR W28 (G6.4$-$0.1), we present new observations of $\rm HCO^+$, HCN and HNC $J=1\text{--}0$ lines, supplemented by archival data of CO isotopes, $\rm N_2H^+$ and $\rm H^{13}CO^+$. We compare the spatial distribution and spectral line profiles of different molecular species. Using local thermodynatic equilibrium (LTE) assumption, we obtain an abundance ratio $N({\rm HCO^+})/N({\rm CO})\sim10^{-4}$ in the northeastern shocked cloud, which is higher by an order of magnitude than the values in unshocked clouds. This can be accounted for by the chemistry jointly induced by shock and CRs, with the physical parameters previously obtained from observations: preshock density $n_{\rm H}\sim 2\times 10^{5}\rm \ cm^{-3}$, CR ionization rate $\zeta=2.5\times 10^{-15} \rm \ s^{-1}$ and shock velocity $V_{\rm s}=15\text{--}20\rm \ km\ s^{-1}$. Towards a point outside the northeastern boundary of W28 with known high CR ionization rate, we estimate the abundance ratio $ N({\rm HCO^+})/N({\rm N_2H^+}) \approx 0.6\text{--}3.3$, which can be reproduced by a chemical simulation if a high density $n_{\rm H}\sim 2\times 10^5 \ \rm cm^{-3}$ is adopted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13305v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tian-Yu Tu, Yang Chen, Ping Zhou, Samar Safi-Harb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of hydrostatic LTE atmosphere models to interpretation of supersoft X-ray sources spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13557v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Super-soft X-ray sources (SSSs) are accreting white dwarfs (WDs) with stable or recurrent thermonuclear burning on their surfaces. High resolution X-ray spectra of such objects are rather complex, can consist of several components, and are difficult to interpret accurately. The main emission source is the hot surface of the WD, and the emergent radiation can potentially be described by hot WD model atmospheres. We present a new set of such model atmosphere spectra computed in the effective temperature range from $100\rm\,kK$ to $1000\rm\,kK$, for eight values of surface gravity, and three different chemical compositions. These compositions correspond to the solar one and to the Large and Small Magellanic Clouds with decreased heavy element abundances, at one-half and one-tenth of the solar value. The presented model grid covers a broad range of physical parameters, and thus can be applied to a wide range of objects. It is also publicly available in XSPEC format. As an illustration, we applied it here for the interpretation of Chandra and XMM grating spectra of two classical SSSs, namely, CAL$\,83$ (RX$\,$J0543.5$-$6823) and RX$\,$J0513.9$-$6951. The obtained effective temperatures and surface gravities of $T_{\rm eff} \approx 560\,$kK, $\log g \approx 8.6-8.7$, and $T_{\rm eff} \approx 630 {\rm kK}, \log g \approx 8.5-8.6$, respectively, are in a good agreement with previous estimations for both sources. Derived WD~mass estimations are within $1.1-1.4\,M_\odot$ for CAL 83 and $1.15-1.4\, M_\odot$ for RX$\,$J0513.9$-$6951. The mass of the WD in CAL$\,83$ is consistent with the mass predicted from the respective model of recurrent thermonuclear burning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13557v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. F. Suleimanov (University of Tuebingen), A. S. Tavleev (University of Tuebingen), V. Doroshenko (University of Tuebingen), K. Werner (University of Tuebingen)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Circularly-polarized nanoshot pairs from the Crab pulsar</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13559v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discover that multiple nanoshot pairs separated uniformly by about 21{\mu}s exist in a giant radio pulse from the Crab pulsar. In a few of such pairs, two nanoshots are left-hand and righthand circularly polarized, respectively. This nanoshot pair with both signs of circular polarization is proposed to produce through splitting of a linearly-polarized nanoshot by the extreme Faraday effect, which relies on highly-asymmetrical pair plasma and intense fields of nanoshots. Asymmetrical pair plasmas should be related to discharge activities in the pulsar. Nanoshot fields are strong enough to induce cyclotron resonance in the magnetosphere, which significantly reduces the speed of right-circularly polarized mode. This work implies that nanoshots are generated in the inner magnetosphere, and can also explain the circular polarization and reversed Faraday rotation of fast ratio bursts from magnetars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13559v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hui-Chun Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The enigmatic origin of two dormant BH binaries: Gaia BH1 and Gaia BH2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13579v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The two systems that have been confirmed as dormant (no X-ray emission detected) black hole (BH) - low-mass star binaries (Gaia BH1 and Gaia BH2) in the latest Gaia mission data release (DR3) are very intriguing in the context of their evolution. Both systems consist of $\sim 9 \mathrm{M_{\odot}}$ BH and $\sim 1 \mathrm{M_{\odot}}$ star orbiting each other on a wide, eccentric orbit ($e\sim 0.5$). We argue that the formation of Gaia BH-like systems through the isolated binary evolution (IBE) channel under standard common envelope assumptions and from dynamical interactions in young massive and open clusters is equally probable, and the formation rate of those binaries is on order of $10^{-7} \mathrm{M_{\odot}}^{-1}$ in both channels. What plays an important role in formation of Gaia BH-like systems in the case of IBE channel is the mutual position of the natal kick velocity vector and the binary angular momentum vector. We find that the natal kicks of median magnitude $\sim 40$ km/s are preferred for the formation of Gaia BH1-like binaries. $\sim 94\%$ of those binaries is formed with BH spin misaligned to orbital axis by less than $40^{\circ}$. Gaia BH2-like binaries form if the low velocity natal kick (of median magnitude $\sim 20$ km/s) is directed within $15^{\circ}$ about the orbital plane. We follow the subsequent evolution of the binaries once formed as Gaia BH1 and Gaia BH2 systems to investigate their connection with the low-mass X-ray binary population.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13579v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iwona Kotko, Sambaran Banerjee, Krzysztof Belczynski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-ray Polarization of the Black Hole X-ray Binary 4U 1630-47 Challenges Standard Thin Accretion Disk Scenario</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.12752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.12752v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Large energy-dependent X-ray polarization degree is detected by the Imaging X-ray Polarimetry Explorer ({IXPE}) in the high-soft emission state of the black hole X-ray binary 4U 1630--47. The highly significant detection (at $\approx50\sigma$ confidence level) of an unexpectedly high polarization, rising from $\sim6\%$ at $2$ keV to $\sim10\%$ at $8$ keV, cannot be easily reconciled with standard models of thin accretion discs. In this work we compare the predictions of different theoretical models with the {IXPE} data and conclude that the observed polarization properties are compatible with a scenario in which matter accretes onto the black hole through a thin disc, covered by a partially-ionized atmosphere flowing away at mildly relativistic velocities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.12752v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad226e</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024 ApJ 964 77</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ajay Ratheesh, Michal Dov\v{c}iak, Henric Krawczynski, Jakub Podgorn\'y, Lorenzo Marra, Alexandra Veledina, Valery Suleimanov, Nicole Rodriguez Cavero, James Steiner, Jiri Svoboda, Andrea Marinucci, Stefano Bianchi, Michela Negro, Giorgio Matt, Francesco Tombesi, Juri Poutanen, Adam Ingram, Roberto Taverna, Andrew West, Vladimir Karas, Francesco Ursini, Paolo Soffitta, Fiamma Capitanio, Domenico Viscolo, Alberto Manfreda, Fabio Muleri, Maxime Parra, Banafsheh Beheshtipour, Sohee Chun, Niccol\`o Cibrario, Niccol\`o Di Lalla, Sergio Fabiani, Kun Hu, Philip Kaaret, Vladislav Loktev, Romana Miku\v{s}incov\'a, Tsunefumi Mizuno, Nicola Omodei, Pierre-Olivier Petrucci, Simonetta Puccetti, John Rankin, Silvia Zane, Sixuan Zhang, Iv\'an Agudo, Lucio Antonelli, Matteo Bachetti, Luca Baldini, Wayne Baumgartner, Ronaldo Bellazzini, Stephen Bongiorno, Raffaella Bonino, Alessandro Brez, Niccol\`o Bucciantini, Simone Castellano, Elisabetta Cavazzuti, Chien-Ting Chen, Stefano Ciprini, Enrico Costa, Alessandra De Rosa, Ettore Del Monte, Laura Di Gesu, Alessandro Di Marco, Immacolata Donnarumma, Victor Doroshenko, Steven Ehlert, Teruaki Enoto, Yuri Evangelista, Riccardo Ferrazzoli, Javier Garcia, Shuichi Gunji, Kiyoshi Hayashida, Jeremy Heyl, Wataru Iwakiri, Svetlana Jorstad, Fabian Kislat, Takao Kitaguchi, Jeffery Kolodziejczak, Fabio La Monaca, Luca Latronico, Ioannis Liodakis, Simone Maldera, Fr\'ed\'eric Marin, Alan Marscher, Herman Marshall, Francesco Massaro, Ikuyuki Mitsuishi, C. -Y. Ng, Stephen O'Dell, Chiara Oppedisano, Alessandro Papitto, George Pavlov, Abel Peirson, Matteo Perri, Melissa Pesce-Rollins, Maura Pilia, Andrea Possenti, Brian Ramsey, Oliver Roberts, Roger Romani, Carmelo Sgr\`o, Patrick Slane, Gloria Spandre, Douglas Swartz, Toru Tamagawa, Fabrizio Tavecchio, Yuzuru Tawara, Allyn Tennant, Nicholas Thomas, Alessio Trois, Sergey Tsygankov, Roberto Turolla, Jacco Vink, Martin Weisskopf, Kinwah Wu, Fei Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Effect of Thermal Torques on AGN Disc Migration Traps and Gravitational Wave Populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.07546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.07546v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accretion discs in active galactic nuclei (AGN) foster black hole (BH) formation, growth, and mergers. Stellar mass BHs migrate inwards under the influence of hydrodynamical torques unless they encounter a region where the torque flips sign. At these migration traps, BHs accumulate and merge via dynamical or gas-assisted interactions, producing high-frequency LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA (LVK) gravitational wave (GW) sources and potentially cutting off the supply of extreme mass ratio inspirals that would otherwise make low-frequency, {\it LISA}-band GWs. In this paper, we study the interplay between different types of migration torques, focusing especially on the ``thermal torques'' generated by the thermal response of the AGN to embedded stellar-mass BHs that accrete through their own mini-discs.In contrast to previous work, we find that Type I torques cannot produce migration traps on their own, but thermal torques often do, particularly in low-mass AGN. The migration traps produced by thermal torques exist at much larger radii ($\sim 10^{3-5}$ gravitational radii) than do previously identified Type I traps, carrying implications for GW populations at multiple frequencies. Finally, we identify a bifurcation of AGN discs into two regimes: migration traps exist below a critical AGN luminosity, and do not at higher luminosities. This critical luminosity is fit as $\log_{10} L_{\rm AGN}^c = 45 - 0.32 \log_{10}{(\alpha/0.01)}$ where $\alpha$ is the AGN alpha viscosity parameter, a range compatible with recent claims that LVK GWs are not preferentially associated with high-luminosity AGN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.07546v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae828</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Evgeni Grishin, Shmuel Gilbaum, Nicholas C. Stone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of Magnetic Field and Turbulence in the TeV halo around Monogem Pulsar</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.13342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.13342v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetic fields are ubiquitous in the interstellar medium, including extended objects such as supernova remnants and diffuse halos around Pulsars. Its turbulent characteristics govern the diffusion of cosmic rays and the multi-wavelength emission from PWNe. However, the geometry and turbulence nature of the magnetic fields in the ambient region of PWN is still unknown. Recent gamma-ray observations from HAWC and synchrotron observations suggest a highly suppressed diffusion coefficient compared to the mean interstellar value. In this study, we present the first direct observational evidence of the orientation of the mean magnetic field and turbulent characteristics by employing a recently developed statistical parameter `Y$_{turb}$' in the extended halo around the Monogem pulsar. Our study points two possible scenarios: nearly aligned toward the line of sight (LoS) with compressible modes dominance or high inclination angle toward LoS and characterized by Alfv\'enic turbulence. The first scenario appears consistent with other observational signatures. Furthermore, we report that the magnetic field has an observed correlation length of approximately $3 \pm 0.6 {\rm pc}$ in the Monogem halo. Our study highlights the pivotal role of magnetic field and turbulence in unraveling the physical processes in TeV halos and cosmic ray transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.13342v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sunil Malik, Ka Ho Yuen, Huirong Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SN 2020zbf: A fast-rising hydrogen-poor superluminous supernova with strong carbon lines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.06814v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: SN\,2020zbf is a hydrogen-poor superluminous supernova (SLSN) at $z = 0.1947$ that shows conspicuous \ion{C}{II} features at early times, in contrast to the majority of H-poor SLSNe. Its peak magnitude is $M_{\rm g}$ = $-21.2$~mag and its rise time ($\lesssim 26.4$ days from first light) places SN\,2020zbf among the fastest rising type I SLSNe. We used spectra taken from ultraviolet (UV) to near-infrared wavelengths to identify spectral features. We paid particular attention to the \ion{C}{II} lines as they present distinctive characteristics when compared to other events. We also analyzed UV and optical photometric data and modeled the light curves considering three different powering mechanisms: radioactive decay of $^{56}$Ni, magnetar spin-down, and circumstellar medium (CSM) interaction. The spectra of SN\,2020zbf match the model spectra of a C-rich low-mass magnetar-powered supernova model well. This is consistent with our light curve modeling, which supports a magnetar-powered event with an ejecta mass $M_{\rm ej}$ = 1.5~$\rm M_\odot$. However, we cannot discard the CSM-interaction model as it may also reproduce the observed features. The interaction with H-poor, carbon-oxygen CSM near peak light could explain the presence of \ion{C}{II} emission lines. A short plateau in the light curve around 35 -- 45 days after peak, in combination with the presence of an emission line at 6580~\AA,\ can also be interpreted as being due to a late interaction with an extended H-rich CSM. Both the magnetar and CSM-interaction models of SN\,2020zbf indicate that the progenitor mass at the time of explosion is between 2 and 5~$\rm M_\odot$. Modeling the spectral energy distribution of the host galaxy reveals a host mass of 10$^{8.7}$~$\rm M_\odot$, a star formation rate of 0.24$^{+0.41}_{-0.12}$~$\rm M_\odot$~yr$^{-1}$, and a metallicity of $\sim$ 0.4~$\rm Z_\odot$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.06814v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202348166</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>A. Gkini, R. Lunnan, S. Schulze, L. Dessart, S. J. Brennan, J. Sollerman, P. J. Pessi, M. Nichol, L. Yan, C. M. B. Omand, T. Kangas, T. Moore, J. P. Anderson, T. -W. Chen, E. P. Gonzalez, M. Gromadzki, Claudia P. Guti\'errez, D. Hiramatsu, D. A. Howell, N. Ihanec, C. Inserra, C. McCully, T. E. M\"uller-Bravo, C. Pellegrino, G. Pignata, M. Pursiainen, D. R. Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simple numerical X-ray polarization models of reflecting axially symmetric structures around accreting compact objects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.15647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.15647v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a series of numerical models suitable for X-ray polarimetry of accreting systems. Firstly, we provide a spectropolarimetric routine that integrates reflection from inner optically thick walls of a geometrical torus of arbitrary size viewed under general inclination. In the studied example, the equatorial torus is illuminated by a central isotropic source of X-ray power-law emission, representing a hot corona. Nearly neutral reprocessing inside the walls is precomputed by Monte Carlo code STOKES that incorporates both line and continuum processes, including multiple scatterings and absorption. Applying a conversion script to the torus reflection output, we created tabular dependencies for a new XSPEC model, called xsstokes. In this version, xsstokes enables efficient X-ray polarimetric fitting of the torus parameters, observer's inclination and primary emission properties, interpolating for arbitrary state of primary polarization. We provide comparisons of the results to a more sophisticated Monte Carlo simulation. Since the polarization interpolation routine works for any axially symmetric reflecting structure, we provide another version of xsstokes that is suitable for approximating nearly neutral reflection from a distant optically thick disc of small geometrical thickness. It uses the same precomputed Monte Carlo reprocessing, but assumes local illumination averaged for a selected range of incident angles, representing a toy model of a diffuse corona of various physical extent. Assessing both model variants, we conclude that the resulting polarization can be tens of % and perpendicularly/parallelly oriented towards the rotation axis, if the reflecting medium is rather vertically/equatorially distributed with respect to a compact central source.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.15647v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Podgorn\'y, M. Dov\v{c}iak, F. Marin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-ray diagnostics of Cassiopeia A's "Green Monster": evidence for dense shocked circumstellar plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02491v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recent survey of the core-collapse supernova remnant Cassiopeia A (CasA) with the MIRI instrument on board the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) revealed a large structure in the interior region, referred to as the "Green Monster". Although its location suggests that it is an ejecta structure, the infrared properties of the "Green Monster" hint at a circumstellar medium (CSM) origin. In this companion paper to the JWST Cas A paper, we investigate the filamentary X-ray structures associated with the "Green Monster" using Chandra X-ray Observatory data. We extracted spectra along the "Green Monster" as well as from shocked CSM regions. Both the extracted spectra and a principal component analysis show that the "Green Monster" emission properties are similar to those of the shocked CSM. The spectra are well-fit by a model consisting of a combination of a non-equilibrium-ionization model and a power-law component, modified by Galactic absorption. All the "Green Monster" spectra show a blueshift corresponding to a radial velocity of around -2300 km/s, suggesting that the structure is on the near side of Cas A. The ionization age is around $n_{e}t = 1.5 \times 10^{11}$ cm$^{-3}s. This translates into a pre-shock density of ~12 cm$^{-3}$, higher than previous estimates of the unshocked CSM. The relatively high net and relatively low radial velocity suggest that this structure has a relatively high density compared to other shocked CSM plasma. This analysis provides yet another piece of evidence that the CSM around Cas A's progenitor was not that of a smooth steady wind profile.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02491v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/ad2fc5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Astrophysical Journal Letters, Volume 964, Issue 1, id.L11, 10 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jacco Vink (Anton Pannekoek Institute/GRAPPA, University of Amsterdam), Manan Agarwal (Anton Pannekoek Institute/GRAPPA, University of Amsterdam), Patrick Slane (Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics), Ilse de Looze (Sterrenkundig Observatorium, Ghent University), Dan Milisavljevic (Purdue University), Dan Patnaude (Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics), Tea Temim (Princeton University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sun and core-collapse supernovae are leading probes of the neutrino lifetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00116v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The large distances travelled by neutrinos emitted from the Sun and core-collapse supernovae together with the characteristic energy of such neutrinos provide ideal conditions to probe their lifetime, when the decay products evade detection. We investigate the prospects of probing invisible neutrino decay capitalising on the detection of solar and supernova neutrinos as well as the diffuse supernova neutrino background (DSNB) in the next-generation neutrino observatories Hyper-Kamiokande, DUNE, JUNO, DARWIN, and RES-NOVA. We find that future solar neutrino data will be sensitive to values of the lifetime-to-mass ratio $\tau_1/m_1$ and $\tau_2/m_2$ of $\mathcal{O}(10^{-1} - 10^{-2})$ s/eV. From a core-collapse supernova explosion at $10$ kpc, lifetime-to-mass ratios of the three mass eigenstates of $\mathcal{O}(10^5)$ s/eV could be tested. After $20$ years of data taking, the DSNB would extend the sensitivity reach of $\tau_1/m_1$ to $10^{8}$ s/eV. These results promise an improvement of about $6 -15$ orders of magnitude on the values of the decay parameters with respect to existing limits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00116v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Mart\'inez-Mirav\'e, Irene Tamborra, Mariam T\'ortola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About the ability of agnostic X-ray tests of the Kerr Hypothesis to discover new physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.18962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.18962v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the past decade, we have seen an unprecedented progress in our ability of testing general relativity in the strong field regime with black hole observations. Most studies have focused on the so-called tests of the Kerr hypothesis: they have tried to verify whether the spacetime geometry around black holes is described by the Kerr solution as expected in general relativity. One can follow either a theory-specific analysis or an agnostic approach. Each strategy has its advantages and disadvantages. In this work, we study the ability of agnostic X-ray tests of the Kerr hypothesis to discover new physics. We simulate X-ray observations of bright Galactic black holes of specific theories of gravity and we analyze the simulated data with a reflection model employing the correct theory of gravity and another reflection model for agnostic tests of the Kerr hypothesis. Our results suggest that agnostic X-ray tests are valid tools to discover new physics, but their constraining power may be lower than a theory-specific analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.18962v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.064059</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 064059 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shuaitongze Zhao, Shafqat Riaz, Cosimo Bambi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
