<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.HE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.HE</link>
    <description>astro-ph.HE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.HE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 04:00:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Time evolution of the synchrotron X-ray emission in Kepler's SNR: the effects of turbulence and shock velocity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18980v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The maximum energy of electrons in supernova remnant (SNR) shocks is typically limited by radiative losses, where the synchrotron cooling time equals the acceleration time. The low speed of shocks in a dense medium increases the acceleration time, leading to lower maximum electron energies and fainter X-ray emissions. However, in Kepler's SNR, an enhanced electron acceleration, which proceeds close to the Bohm limit, occurs in the north of its shell, where the shock is slowed by a dense circumstellar medium (CSM). To investigate whether this scenario still holds at smaller scales, we analyzed the temporal evolution of the X-ray synchrotron flux in filamentary structures, using the two deepest Chandra/ACIS X-ray observations, performed in 2006 and 2014. We examined spectra from different filaments, we measured their proper motion and calculated the acceleration to synchrotron time-scale ratios. The interaction with the turbulent and dense northern CSM induces competing effects on electron acceleration: on one hand, turbulence reduces the electron mean free path enhancing the acceleration efficiency, on the other hand, lower shock velocities increase the acceleration time-scale. In most filaments, these effects compensate each other, but in one region the acceleration time-scale exceeds the synchrotron time-scale, resulting in a significant decrease in nonthermal X-ray emission from 2006 to 2014, indicating fading synchrotron emission. Our findings provide a coherent understanding of the different regimes of electron acceleration observed in Kepler's SNR through various diagnostics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18980v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincenzo Sapienza, Marco Miceli, Oleh Petruk, Aya Bamba, Satoru Katsuda, Salvatore Orlando, Fabrizio Bocchino, Tracey DeLaney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating short GRB jets in late binary neutron star merger environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19002v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The electromagnetic emission and the afterglow observations of the binary neutron star merger event GW 170817A confirmed the association of the merger with a short gamma-ray burst (sGRB) harboring a narrow ($5${\deg}-$10${\deg}) and powerful ($10^{49}$-$10^{50}~$erg) jet. Using the 1~second-long neutrino-radiation-GR-MHD simulation of coalescing neutron stars of Kiuchi et al. (2023) and following the semi-analytical estimates of Pais et al. (2023), we inject a narrow, powerful, unmagnetized jet into the post-merger phase. We explore different opening angles, luminosities, central engine durations, and times after the merger. We explore early ($0.1~$s following the merger) and late ($1~$s) jet launches; the latter is consistent with the time delay of $\approx 1.74~$s observed between GW 170817 and GRB 170817A. We demonstrate that the semi-analytical estimates correctly predict the jets' breakout and collimation conditions. When comparing our synthetic afterglow light curves to the observed radio data of GW170807, we find a good agreement for a $3 \times 10^{49}$ ergs jet launched late with an opening angle in the range $\simeq 5${\deg}-$7${\deg}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19002v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Pais, Tsvi Piran, Kenta Kiuchi, Masaru Shibata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eight Years of Light from ASASSN-15oi: Towards Understanding the Late-time Evolution of TDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19019v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the results from an extensive follow-up campaign of the Tidal Disruption Event (TDE) ASASSN-15oi spanning $\delta t \sim 10 - 3000$ d, offering an unprecedented window into the multiwavelength properties of a TDE during its first $\approx 8$ years of evolution. ASASSN-15oi is one of the few TDEs with strong detections at X-ray, optical/UV, and radio wavelengths and featured two delayed radio flares at $\delta t \sim 180$ d and $\delta t \sim 1400$ d. Our observations at $&gt; 1400$ d reveal an absence of thermal X-rays, a late-time variability in the non-thermal X-ray emission, and sharp declines in the non-thermal X-ray and radio emission at $\delta t \sim 2800$ d and $\sim 3000$ d, respectively. The UV emission shows no significant evolution at $&gt;400$ d and remains above the pre-TDE level. We show that a cooling envelope model can explain the thermal emission consistently across all epochs. We also find that a scenario involving episodic ejection of material due to stream-stream collisions is conducive to explaining the first radio flare. Given the peculiar spectral and temporal evolution of the late-time emission, however, constraining the origins of the second radio flare and the non-thermal X-rays remains challenging. Our study underscores the critical role of long-term, multiwavelength follow-up.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19019v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Hajela (U. of Copenhagen), K. D. Alexander, R. Margutti, R. Chornock, M. Bietenholz, C. T. Christy, M. Stroh, G. Terreran, R. Saxton, S. Komossa, J. S. Bright, E. Ramirez-Ruiz, D. L. Coppejans, J. K. Leung, Y. Cendes, E. Wiston, T. Laskar, A. Horesh, G. Schroeder, Nayana A. J., M. H. Wieringa, N. Velez, E. Berger, P. K. Blanchard, T. Eftekhari, S. Gomez, M. Nicholl, H. Sears, B. A. Zauderer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rates and beaming angles of GRBs associated with compact binary coalescences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19033v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Some, if not all, binary neutron star (BNS) coalescences, and a fraction of neutron - star black hole (NSBH) mergers, are thought to produce sufficient mass-ejection to power Gamma-Ray Bursts (GRBs). However, this fraction, as well as the distribution of beaming angles of BNS-associated GRBs, are poorly constrained from observation. Recent work applied machine learning tools to analyze GRB light curves observed by {\textit{Fermi}}/GBM and {\it Swift}/BAT. GRBs were segregated into multiple distinct clusters, with the tantalizing possibility that one of them (BNS cluster) could be associated with BNSs and another (NSBH cluster) with NSBHs. As a proof of principle, assuming that all GRBs detected by {\it Fermi}/GBM and {\it Swift}/BAT associated with BNSs (NSBHs) lie in the BNS (NSBH) cluster, we estimate their rates ($\mathrm{Gpc}^{-3}\mathrm{yr}^{-1}$). We compare these rates with corresponding BNS and NSBH rates estimated by the LIGO-Virgo-Kagra (LVK) collaboration from the first three observing runs (O1, O2, O3). We find that the BNS rates are consistent with LVK's rate estimates, assuming a uniform distribution of beaming fractions ($f_b \in [0.01, 0.1]$). Conversely, using the LVK's BNS rate estimates, assuming all BNS mergers produce GRBs, we are able to constrain the beaming angle distribution to $\theta_j \in [0.8^{\circ}, 38.8^{\circ}]$ at $90\%$ confidence. We similarly place a lower limit on the fraction of GRB-Bright NSBHs to $f_B \gtrsim 0.10$ ($f_B \gtrsim 0.022$) with {\it Fermi}/GBM ({\it Swift}/BAT) data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19033v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shasvath J. Kapadia,  Dimple, Dhruv Jain, Resmi Lekshmi, Kuntal Misra, K. G. Arun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Redshift constrain of BL Lac PKS 1424+240</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19134v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the period between 2009 and 2015, several very high-energy (VHE $&gt; 100$ GeV) gamma-ray flaring events from the BL Lac object PKS 1424+240 were observed by the Cerenkov telescopes VERITAS and MAGIC. It had uncertain redshift ($z$) and using spectroscopical measurement, Paiano et al. (2017) found it to be $z=0.604$. Using four different extragalactic background light (EBL) models and the photohadronic model, nine independently observed VHE gamma-ray spectra of PKS 1424+240 are analyzed and a global $\chi^2$ fit is performed on all observations to estimate the best-fit value for the redshift for each EBL model. Confidence levels (CL) intervals for the redshift are also estimated using all the EBL models. This method is tested by comparing our analysis with the observed value. It is shown that the photohadronic scenario provides an excellent description of all the observed spectra. It is found that the EBL model of Dom\'inguez et al. (2011) is the one that provides the most restrictive limits on the redshift of PKS 1424+240, but in our analysis, $z=0.604$ lies within the $3\sigma$ CL interval of the EBL model of Saldana-Lopez et al. (2021).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19134v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarira Sahu, D. I. P\'aez-S\'anchez, B. Medina-Carrillo, R. de J. Pacheco-Ak\'e, G. S\'anchez-Col\'on, Subhash Rajpoot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The centrifugal acceleration and the Y-point of the Pulsar Magnetosphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19138v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the centrifugal acceleration in an axisymmetric pulsar magnetosphere under the ideal-MHD approximation. We solved the field-aligned equations of motion for flows inside the current sheet with finite thickness. We find that flows coming into the vicinity of a Y-point become super fast. The centrifugal acceleration takes place efficiently, and most of the Poynting energy is converted into kinetic energy. However, the super fast flow does not provide enough centrifugal drift current to open the magnetic field. Opening of the magnetic field is possible by the plasmas that are accelerated in the azimuthal direction with a large Lorentz factor in the closed field region. We find that this acceleration takes place if the field strength increases toward the Y-point from inside. The accelerated plasma is transferred from the closed field region to the open field region by magnetic reconnection with plasmoid emission. We also estimate the Lorentz factor to be reached in the centrifugal wind.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19138v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shinpei Shibata, Shota Kisaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 2021 outburst of 2S 1417-624 revisited with AstroSat</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents the first ever broadband (0.7-25.0 keV) timing and spectral analysis of Be-HMXB 2S 1417-624 during its 2021 outburst. Using AstroSat observations, coherent pulsations at ~17.36633 s (MJD 59239.082) were detected in 0.7-7.0 keV SXT and 3.0-25.0 keV LAXPC data. The pulse profile was dual peaked at all energies, with the relative intensity of main peak increasing with energy. The peaks in the SXT profiles were broad and comprised of several mini-structures. The LAXPC profiles were relatively smooth and had higher pulsed fraction which increased with energy. The SXT+LAXPC simultaneous energy spectrum is well described by an absorbed power-law with exponential cut-off, along with ~1.6 keV black body component and 6.47 keV emission line. A model comprising of an absorbed power law with high energy cutoff plus a partial covering absorber and Gaussian emission line also fits the spectrum quite well. These results have been compared with timing and spectral features during the previous outbursts of this transient pulsar.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19194v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chetana Jain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Phase-resolved View of "Heartbeat"-like variability in IGR J17091-3624 During the 2022 Outburst</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19388v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: IGR J17091-3624, in addition to GRS 1915+105, is the only black hole X-ray binary that displays ``heartbeat"-like variability characterized by structured flares with high amplitudes. In this study, we conduct a detailed phase-resolved analysis of the recently identified ``heartbeat"-like Class X variability in IGR J17091-3624 during its 2022 outburst, utilizing data from NICER and NuSTAR observations. A shortage in the high-energy (&gt;20 keV) X-ray flux is detected at peak phases of the soft X-ray flare at a ~15 sigma confidence level from the phase-folded light curves. Furthermore, our phase-resolved spectral analysis reveals variations in the spectral shape, particularly showing significant synchronous variations in the disk temperature and flux with the count rate. These findings imply that the flare is primarily driven by instabilities within the accretion disk, consistent with previous studies on the well-known Class rho variability in GRS 1915+105. However, we also observe a positive correlation between the disk temperature and flux over the flare cycle, which differs from a loop relation between the two parameters found in the Class rho variability. This could suggest differences in underlying physical processes between the two variability classes. Variations in the Componization component during flares are also observed: the electron temperature and covering fraction show anti-correlations with the disk flux, revealing potential interactions between the accretion disk and the corona during these flares.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19388v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qing-Cang Shui, Shu Zhang, Jing-Qiang Peng, Shuang-Nan Zhang, Yu-Peng Chen, Ling-Da Kong, Zhuo-Li Yu, Long Ji, Peng-Ju Wang, Zhi Chang, Hong-Xing Yin, Jian Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase resolved deadtime of the Crab pulsar using IXPE data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19411v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: After receiving an X-ray photon, an X-ray detector is not operational for a duration known as deadtime. It is detector specific and its effect on the data depends upon the luminosity of the source. It reduces the observed photon count rate in comparison to the expected one. In periodic sources such as the Crab pulsar, it can distort the folded light curve (FLC). An undistorted FLC of the Crab pulsar is required in combination with its polarization properties for studying its X-ray emission mechanism. This work derives a simple formula for the distortion of the FLC of a pulsar caused by the detector deadtime, and validates it using Crab pulsar data from the X-ray observatories {{\it NICER}} and {{\it NUSTAR}}, which have very small and relatively large detector deadtimes respectively. Then it derives a method for correcting the distorted FLC of the Crab pulsar in {{\it IXPE}} data, which has intermediate detector deadtime. The formula is verified after addressing several technical issues. This work ends with a discussion of why an undistorted FLC is important for studying the formation of cusps in the FLC of the Crab pulsar.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19411v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Vivekanand</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polar cap region and plasma drift in pulsars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19473v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pulsars often display systematic variations in the position and/or intensity of the subpulses, the components that comprise each single pulse. Although the drift of these subpulses was observed in the early years of pulsar research, and their potential for understanding the elusive emission mechanism was quickly recognised, there is still no consensus on the cause of the drift. We explore the electrodynamics of two recently proposed or refined drift models: one where plasma lags behind corotation, connecting the drift with the rotational pole; and another where plasma drifts around the electric potential extremum of the polar cap. Generally, these are different locations, resulting in different drift behaviours, that can be tested with observations. In this study, however, we specifically examine these models in the axisymmetric case, where the physics is well understood. This approach seems counter-intuitive as both models then predict similar large-scale plasma drift. However, it allows us to show, by studying conditions \emph{within} the sparks for both models, that the lagging behind corotation (LBC) model is inconsistent with Faraday's law. The modified carousel (MC) model, where plasma drifts around the electric potential extremum, not only aligns with Faraday's law, but also provides a future direction for developing a comprehensive model of plasma generation in the polar cap region. Unlike previous models, which considered the drift only inside the discharging regions, the MC model reveals that the electric field \emph{between} the discharges is not completely screened, and plasma drifts there -- a paradigm shift for the drifting subpulse phenomenon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19473v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrzej Szary, Joeri van Leeuwen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Pulsar Timing Precision with Single Pulse Fluence Clustering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19615v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Traditional pulsar timing techniques involve averaging large numbers of single pulses to obtain a high signal-to-noise (S/N) profile, which is matched to a template to measure a time of arrival (TOA). However, the morphology of individual single pulses varies greatly due to pulse jitter. Pulses of different fluence contribute differently to the S/N of the pulse average. Our study proposes a method that accounts for these variations by identifying a range of states and timing each separately. We selected two 1-hour observations of PSR J2145-0750, each in a different frequency band with the Green Bank Telescope. We normalized the pulse amplitudes to account for scintillation effects and probed different excision algorithms to reduce radio-frequency interference. We then measured four pulse parameters (amplitude, position, width, and energy) to classify the single pulses using automated clustering algorithms. For each cluster, we calculated an average pulse profile and template and used both to obtain a TOA and TOA error. Finally, we computed the weighted average TOA and TOA error, the latter as a metric of the total timing precision for the epoch. The TOA is shifted relative to the one obtained without clustering, and we can estimate the shift with this weighting using the same data. For the 820 MHz and 1400 MHz bands, we obtained TOA uncertainties of 0.057 microseconds and 0.46 microseconds, compared to 0.066 microseconds and 0.74 microseconds when no clustering is applied. We conclude that tailoring this method could help improve the timing precision for certain bright pulsars in NANOGrav's dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19615v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sofia V. Sosa Fiscella, Michael T. Lam, Maura A. McLaughlin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inspecting binary-neutron-star mergers as production sites of high-energy neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19957v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The end state of binary-neutron-star (BNS) mergers can manifest conditions to produce high-energy neutrinos. Inspired by the event GW170817, detected in gravitational waves and in optical/infrared emission, we investigate a scenario in which cosmic-ray (CR) particles are accelerated, in a population of BNS mergers, in the energy range from the knee to the ankle. By taking into account the measured thermal and non-thermal energy density of the photon fields in the source environment as a function of the time after the merger, we model the CR interactions and the consequent neutrino production. We propagate the escaped CR and neutrino fluxes through the extragalactic space and compare the expected diffuse fluxes to the experimental data and current limits. Depending on the accelerated CR mass composition and on the contribution of this possible source class to the sub-ankle CR flux, we provide indications on the rate of BNS merger events and the amount of baryons present in the source site.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19957v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone Rossoni, Denise Boncioli, G\"unter Sigl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-scale Magnetic Field Model of GRB Afterglow Polarization: Effects of Field Anisotropy, Off-axis Viewing Angle, and Ordered Field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19962v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The afterglows of gamma-ray bursts are non-thermal electron synchrotron emissions from relativistic shocks. The origin of strong magnetic field in the emission region remains elusive, and two field amplification mechanisms via the plasma kinetic and magnetohydrodynamic instabilities have been discussed. The polarimetric observations are a powerful probe to distinguish these two mechanisms. So far, most theoretical works have focused on the former mechanism and constructed afterglow polarization models with microscopic-scale turbulence whose coherence length is much smaller than the thickness of the blast wave. In this work, focusing on the latter mechanism, we utilize our semi-analytic model of the synchrotron polarization with large-scale turbulence whose coherence length is comparable to the thickness of the blast wave to investigate the effect of magnetic field anisotropy and the observer viewing angle. We find that the polarization in our large-scale turbulence model can exhibit both behaviors characteristic of the microscopic-scale turbulence model and those not seen in the microscopic-scale model. Then we find that the large-scale model could explain all the polarimetric observational data to date that seem to be forward shock emission. We also examine the effect of ordered-field component, and find that polarization degree and polarization angle constant in time are realized only when the energy density ratio of the ordered and fluctuated components is $\gtrsim 50$. In this case, however, the polarization degree is much higher than the observed values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19962v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asuka Kuwata, Kenji Toma, Sara Tomita, Jiro Shimoda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Parameters in the Blazar Jet Magnetic Field Model on Axion-Like Particle Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20118v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interaction between axion-like particles (ALPs) and photons induces ALP-photon oscillations in astrophysical magnetic fields, leading to spectral distortions in the $\gamma$-ray spectrum of blazars. The primary uncertainty of this phenomenon may originate from the magnetic field within the jet of the blazar. While many studies have explored the effects of ALP-photon oscillations using typical values for jet magnetic field parameters, it is important to recognize that these parameters can be constrained by multi-wavelength observations. In this study, we utilize the high energy $\gamma$-ray spectrum of Mrk 421 obtained from MAGIC and Fermi-LAT observations. By employing multi-wavelength fitting with a one-zone synchrotron self-Compton model, we derive the parameters characterizing the magnetic field model within the jet, and investigate their impacts on the ALP constraints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20118v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lin-Qing Gao, Xiao-Jun Bi, Jun Li, Peng-Fei Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the leptonic contribution to the ultra high-energy diffuse gamma-ray background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20186v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ultra high-energy (UHE) diffuse gamma-ray background holds important information on the propagation of cosmic rays in the Galaxy. However, its measurements suffer from a contamination from unresolved sources whose importance remains unclear. In this Letter, we propose a novel data-driven estimate of the contribution of unresolved leptonic sources based on the information present in the ATNF and the LHAASO catalogs. We find that in the inner Galaxy at most $\sim60\%$ of the diffuse flux measured by LHAASO at $10\,\rm{TeV}$ may originate from unresolved leptonic sources, and this fraction drops with energy to less than $20\%$ at $100\,\rm{TeV}$. In the outer Galaxy, the contribution of unresolved leptonic sources is always subdominant. It is less than $\sim 20\%$ at $10\,\rm{TeV}$ and less than $\sim 8\%$ above $\sim25\,\rm{TeV}$. We conclude that the UHE diffuse background should be dominated by photons from a hadronic origin above a few tens of $\rm{TeV}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20186v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samy Kaci, Gwenael Giacinti, Dmitri Semikoz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay between the non-resonant streaming instability and self-generated pressure anisotropies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18978v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The non-thermal particles escaping from collisionless shocks into the surrounding medium can trigger a non-resonant streaming instability that converts parts of their drift kinetic energy into large amplitude magnetic field perturbations, and promote the confinement and acceleration of high energy cosmic rays. We present simulations of the instability using an hybrid-Particle-in-Cell approach including Monte Carlo collisions, and demonstrate that the development of the non-resonant mode is associated with important ion pressure anisotropies in the background plasma. Depending on the initial conditions, the anisotropies may act on the instability by lowering its growth and trigger secondary micro-instabilities. Introducing collisions with neutrals yield a strong reduction of the magnetic field amplification as predicted by linear fluid theory. In contrast, Coulomb collisions in fully ionized plasmas are found to mitigate the self-generated pressure anisotropies and promote the growth of the magnetic field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18978v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexis Marret, Andrea Ciardi, Roch Smets</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weighing The Options: The Unseen Companion in LAMOST J2354 is Likely a Massive White Dwarf</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19004</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19004v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: LAMOST J235456.73+335625 (J2354) is a binary system hosting a $\sim 0.7~\rm M_\odot$ K dwarf and a $\sim 1.4~\rm M_\odot$ dark companion, supposedly a neutron star, in a 0.48d orbit. Here we present high- and low-resolution spectroscopy to better constrain the properties of the system. The low-resolution spectrum confirms that the luminous star is a slightly metal-poor K dwarf and strengthens the limits on any optical flux from the dimmer companion. We use the high-resolution spectra to measure atmospheric parameters ($T_{\rm eff}$, $\log g$, [Fe/H], $v_{\rm rot}\sin i$) and abundances for 8 elements for the K dwarf. We refine the mass of the compact object to $M_{\rm co} \sim 1.3~\rm M_\odot$ with a minimum mass of $M_{\rm co, min} = 1.23\pm0.04~\rm M_\odot$. The expected overabundance of intermediate-mass elements from the incident supernova ejecta is not detected in the K-dwarf atmosphere. This contrasts with known binaries hosting neutron stars where almost all companions show evidence for polluting material. Moving the neutron-star progenitor further from the K-dwarf at the time of explosion to minimize atmospheric pollution requires a finely-tuned kick to produce the current orbital separation of $\sim 3.3~\rm R_\odot$. Instead, we find that a massive white dwarf with a cooling age of $\gtrsim 3~$Gyr satisfies all observational constraints. The system likely experienced two common-envelope phases leading to its current state because the white dwarf progenitor was massive enough to ignite He-shell burning. The system will become a cataclysmic variable in the distant future when the K-dwarf evolves off of the main sequence. These short-period high-$q$ binaries represent an intriguing formation pathway for compact double white dwarf binaries and thermonuclear supernovae. An ultraviolet spectrum is the most promising avenue for directly detecting the white dwarf companion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19004v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Tucker, A. J. Wheeler, D. M. Rowan, M. E. Huber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Waveform models for the gravitational-wave memory effect: Extreme mass-ratio limit and final memory offset</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19017v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The gravitational-wave (GW) memory effect is a strong-field relativistic phenomenon that is associated with a persistent change in the GW strain after the passage of a GW. The nonlinear effect arises from interactions of GWs themselves in the wave zone and is an observable effect connected to the infrared properties of general relativity. The detection of the GW memory effect is possible with LIGO and Virgo in a population of binary-black-hole (BBH) mergers or from individual events with next-generation ground- and space-based GW detectors or pulsar timing arrays. Matched-filtering-based searches for the GW memory require accurate, and preferably rapid-to-evaluate waveform models of the memory effect's GW signal. One important element of such a waveform model is a model for the final memory offset -- namely, the net change in strain between early and late times. In this paper, we construct a model for the final memory offset from the merger of nonspinning BBH systems in quasicircular orbits. A novel ingredient of this model is that we first compute the memory signal for extreme mass-ratio inspirals using a high post-Newtonian-order analytic calculation, and we use this analytical result to fix the coefficient in the fit which is linear in the mass-ratio. The resulting memory-offset fit could be used for detecting the GW memory for binaries that merge on a timescale that is short relative to the inverse of the low-frequency cutoff of a GW detector. Additionally, this fit will be useful for analytic waveform models of the GW memory signals in the time and frequency domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19017v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arwa Elhashash, David A. Nichols</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Axion signals from neutron star populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19028v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neutron stars provide a powerful probe of axion dark matter, especially in higher frequency ranges where there remain fewer laboratory constraints. Populations of neutron stars near the Galactic Centre have been proposed as a means to place strong constraints on axion dark matter. One downside of this approach is that there are very few direct observations of neutron stars in this region, introducing uncertainties in the total number of neutron stars in this ``invisible" population at the Galactic Centre, whose size must be inferred through birth rate modelling. We suggest this number could also be reduced due to stellar dynamics carrying stars away from the Galactic Centre via large kick velocities at birth. We attempt to circumvent the uncertainty on the Galactic Centre population size by modelling the axion signal from better understood populations outside the Galactic Centre using {\tt PsrPopPy} which is normalised against pulsar observations. We consider lower-frequency, wider-angle searches for this signal via a range of instruments including MeerKAT and SKA-low but find that the sensitivity is not competitive with existing constraints. Finally, returning to the Galactic Centre, we compare populations to single objects as targets for axion detection. Using the latest modelling of axion-photon conversion in the Galactic Centre magnetar, we conclude that within astrophysical uncertainties, the Galactic Centre population and the magnetar could give comparable sensitivities to axion dark matter, suggesting one should continue to search for both signals in future surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19028v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>U. Bhura, R. A. Battye, J. I. McDonald, S. Srinivasan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Gravity Corrections to Hawking Radiation via GUP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19268v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we explore the effects of a Generalized Uncertainty Principle (GUP) on Schwarzschild black hole. In particular, we incorporate the effects of GUP into the Parikh-Wilczek tunneling process for Hawking radiation. To this effect, we observe that results obtained due to GUP correction resemble that of the Reissner-Nordstr\"{om} black hole, showing similarities to the nature of an electric charge. We also find that, within this framework, the emission is not purely thermal, thus addressing the information loss problem through the correlation function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19268v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaurav Bhandari, S. D. Pathak, Manabendra Sharma, Maxim Yu Khlopov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Type Ia Supernovae From The First Generation Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19357v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Type Ia Supernovae (SNe Ia) discovered at redshift $z\lesssim2.5$ are presumed to be produced from Population (Pop) I/II stars. {In this work, we investigate the production of SNe Ia from Pop III binaries in the cosmological framework. We derive the SN Ia rate as a function of redshift under a theoretical context for the production of first generation stars and emanate the likelihood of their detection by the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST).} {Assuming the initial stellar mass function (IMF) favors low-mass stars as from recent numerical simulations, we found Pop III stars may give rise to a considerable amount of SNe Ia at high redshift and Pop III stars may even be the dominant SN Ia producer at z $\gtrsim 6$.} {In an optimistic scenario, we expect $\sim 1(2)$ SNe Ia from Pop III stars at $z\approx 4(5)$ for a survey of area $300 \;\rm arcmin^2$ during a $3\;\rm yr$ period with JWST. The same survey may record more than $\sim 400$ SNe Ia at lower redshift ($z\lesssim 2.5$) but with only about one of them from Pop III progenitors. There will be $\sim 6$ Pop III SNe Ia in the same field of view at redshifts of $5-10$.} Observational constraints on SN Ia rates at the redshift range of $5-10$ can place crucial constraints on the IMF of Pop III stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19357v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenwei Li, Lifan Wang, Zhanwen Han, Xuefei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$I$-Love-$Q$, and $\delta M$ too: The role of the mass in universal relations of compact stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20151v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the study of rotating neutron stars the $I$-Love-$Q$ relations refer to the existence of various approximate, equation of state-independent relations involving the moment of inertia, the Love number and the quadrupole moment. These relations are relevant for observational astrophysics, since they allow (in theory) the inference of any two quantities within the $I$-Love-$Q$ triad out of the third one alone. However, the quantities involved in the relations are, in fact, normalized by a parameter $M_0$ that arises in the usual perturbative analytical approach as the mass of the background configuration. Since $M_0$ is not the mass of the rotating star $M_S$, it is not an observational quantity, which may affect the application of the relations to actual observations. This situation is usually ignored in most studies by taking $M_0$ to be the mass of the star, an approximation that can, in some cases, be inconsistent. In this paper we extract the value of $M_0$ using an $\textit{extended}$ version of the universal relations that involve a fourth parameter, $\delta M$, proportional to the difference $M_S-M_0$. We analyze to which degree this extended set of relations yields a more precise inference of compact star properties and equation of state parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20151v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eneko Aranguren, Jos\'e A. Font, Nicolas Sanchis-Gual, Ra\"ul Vera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Search for IceCube sub-TeV Neutrinos Correlated with Gravitational-Wave Events Detected By LIGO/Virgo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.15970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.15970v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The LIGO/Virgo collaboration published the catalogs GWTC-1, GWTC-2.1 and GWTC-3 containing candidate gravitational-wave (GW) events detected during its runs O1, O2 and O3. These GW events can be possible sites of neutrino emission. In this paper, we present a search for neutrino counterparts of 90 GW candidates using IceCube DeepCore, the low-energy infill array of the IceCube Neutrino Observatory. The search is conducted using an unbinned maximum likelihood method, within a time window of 1000 s and uses the spatial and timing information from the GW events. The neutrinos used for the search have energies ranging from a few GeV to several tens of TeV. We do not find any significant emission of neutrinos, and place upper limits on the flux and the isotropic-equivalent energy emitted in low-energy neutrinos. We also conduct a binomial test to search for source populations potentially contributing to neutrino emission. We report a non-detection of a significant neutrino-source population with this test.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.15970v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/aceefc</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJ 959 (2023) 96</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>R. Abbasi, M. Ackermann, J. Adams, S. K. Agarwalla, J. A. Aguilar, M. Ahlers, J. M. Alameddine, N. M. Amin, K. Andeen, G. Anton, C. Arg\"uelles, Y. Ashida, S. Athanasiadou, S. N. Axani, X. Bai, A. Balagopal V., M. Baricevic, S. W. Barwick, V. Basu, R. Bay, J. J. Beatty, K. -H. Becker, J. Becker Tjus, J. Beise, C. Bellenghi, S. BenZvi, D. Berley, E. Bernardini, D. Z. Besson, G. Binder, D. Bindig, E. Blaufuss, S. Blot, F. Bontempo, J. Y. Book, C. Boscolo Meneguolo, S. B\"oser, O. Botner, J. B\"ottcher, E. Bourbeau, J. Braun, B. Brinson, J. Brostean-Kaiser, R. T. Burley, R. S. Busse, D. Butterfield, M. A. Campana, K. Carloni, E. G. Carnie-Bronca, S. Chattopadhyay, N. Chau, C. Chen, Z. Chen, D. Chirkin, S. Choi, B. A. Clark, L. Classen, A. Coleman, G. H. Collin, A. Connolly, J. M. Conrad, P. Coppin, P. Correa, S. Countryman, D. F. Cowen, P. Dave, C. De Clercq, J. J. DeLaunay, D. Delgado L\'opez, H. Dembinski, K. Deoskar, A. Desai, P. Desiati, K. D. de Vries, G. de Wasseige, T. DeYoung, A. Diaz, J. C. D\'iaz-V\'elez, M. Dittmer, A. Domi, H. Dujmovic, M. A. DuVernois, T. Ehrhardt, P. Eller, R. Engel, H. Erpenbeck, J. Evans, P. A. Evenson, K. L. Fan, K. Fang, A. R. Fazely, A. Fedynitch, N. Feigl, S. Fiedlschuster, C. Finley, L. Fischer, D. Fox, A. Franckowiak, E. Friedman, A. Fritz, P. F\"urst, T. K. Gaisser, J. Gallagher, E. Ganster, A. Garcia, L. Gerhardt, A. Ghadimi, C. Glaser, T. Glauch, T. Gl\"usenkamp, N. Goehlke, J. G. Gonzalez, S. Goswami, D. Grant, S. J. Gray, S. Griffin, S. Griswold, C. G\"unther, P. Gutjahr, C. Haack, A. Hallgren, R. Halliday, L. Halve, F. Halzen, H. Hamdaoui, M. Ha Minh, K. Hanson, J. Hardin, A. A. Harnisch, P. Hatch, A. Haungs, K. Helbing, J. Hellrung, F. Henningsen, L. Heuermann, N. Heyer, S. Hickford, A. Hidvegi, C. Hill, G. C. Hill, K. D. Hoffman, K. Hoshina, W. Hou, T. Huber, K. Hultqvist, M. H\"unnefeld, R. Hussain, K. Hymon, S. In, A. Ishihara, M. Jacquart, M. Jansson, G. S. Japaridze, K. Jayakumar, M. Jeong, M. Jin, B. J. P. Jones, D. Kang, W. Kang, X. Kang, A. Kappes, D. Kappesser, L. Kardum, T. Karg, M. Karl, A. Karle, U. Katz, M. Kauer, J. L. Kelley, A. Khatee Zathul, A. Kheirandish, J. Kiryluk, S. R. Klein, A. Kochocki, R. Koirala, H. Kolanoski, T. Kontrimas, L. K\"opke, C. Kopper, D. J. Koskinen, P. Koundal, M. Kovacevich, M. Kowalski, T. Kozynets, K. Kruiswijk, E. Krupczak, A. Kumar, E. Kun, N. Kurahashi, N. Lad, C. Lagunas Gualda, M. Lamoureux, M. J. Larson, F. Lauber, J. P. Lazar, J. W. Lee, K. Leonard DeHolton, A. Leszczy\'nska, M. Lincetto, Q. R. Liu, M. Liubarska, E. Lohfink, C. Love, C. J. Lozano Mariscal, L. Lu, F. Lucarelli, A. Ludwig, W. Luszczak, Y. Lyu, J. Madsen, K. B. M. Mahn, Y. Makino, S. Mancina, W. Marie Sainte, I. C. Mari\c{s}, S. Marka, Z. Marka, M. Marsee, I. Martinez-Soler, R. Maruyama, F. Mayhew, T. McElroy, F. McNally, J. V. Mead, K. Meagher, S. Mechbal, A. Medina, M. Meier, S. Meighen-Berger, Y. Merckx, L. Merten, J. Micallef, T. Montaruli, R. W. Moore, Y. Morii, R. Morse, M. Moulai, T. Mukherjee, R. Naab, R. Nagai, M. Nakos, U. Naumann, J. Necker, M. Neumann, H. Niederhausen, M. U. Nisa, A. Noell, S. C. Nowicki, A. Obertacke Pollmann, V. O'Dell, M. Oehler, B. Oeyen, A. Olivas, R. Orsoe, J. Osborn, E. O'Sullivan, H. Pandya, N. Park, G. K. Parker, E. N. Paudel, L. Paul, C. P\'erez de los Heros, J. Peterson, S. Philippen, S. Pieper, A. Pizzuto, M. Plum, A. Pont\'en, Y. Popovych, M. Prado Rodriguez, B. Pries, R. Procter-Murphy, G. T. Przybylski, J. Rack-Helleis, K. Rawlins, Z. Rechav, A. Rehman, P. Reichherzer, G. Renzi, E. Resconi, S. Reusch, W. Rhode, M. Richman, B. Riedel, E. J. Roberts, S. Robertson, S. Rodan, G. Roellinghoff, M. Rongen, C. Rott, T. Ruhe, L. Ruohan, D. Ryckbosch, S. Athanasiadou, I. Safa, J. Saffer, D. Salazar-Gallegos, P. Sampathkumar, S. E. Sanchez Herrera, A. Sandrock, M. Santander, S. Sarkar, S. Sarkar, J. Savelberg, P. Savina, M. Schaufel, H. Schieler, S. Schindler, B. Schl\"uter, F. Schl\"uter, T. Schmidt, J. Schneider, F. G. Schr\"oder, L. Schumacher, G. Schwefer, S. Sclafani, D. Seckel, S. Seunarine, A. Sharma, S. Shefali, N. Shimizu, M. Silva, B. Skrzypek, B. Smithers, R. Snihur, J. Soedingrekso, A. S{\o}gaard, D. Soldin, G. Sommani, C. Spannfellner, G. M. Spiczak, C. Spiering, M. Stamatikos, T. Stanev, T. Stezelberger, T. St\"urwald, T. Stuttard, G. W. Sullivan, I. Taboada, S. Ter-Antonyan, W. G. Thompson, J. Thwaites, S. Tilav, K. Tollefson, C. T\"onnis, S. Toscano, D. Tosi, A. Trettin, C. F. Tung, R. Turcotte, J. P. Twagirayezu, B. Ty, M. A. Unland Elorrieta, A. K. Upadhyay, K. Upshaw, N. Valtonen-Mattila, J. Vandenbroucke, N. van Eijndhoven, D. Vannerom, J. van Santen, J. Vara, J. Veitch-Michaelis, M. Venugopal, S. Verpoest, D. Veske, C. Walck, T. B. Watson, C. Weaver, P. Weigel, A. Weindl, J. Weldert, C. Wendt, J. Werthebach, M. Weyrauch, N. Whitehorn, C. H. Wiebusch, N. Willey, D. R. Williams, M. Wolf, G. Wrede, X. W. Xu, J. P. Yanez, E. Yildizci, S. Yoshida, F. Yu, S. Yu, T. Yuan, Z. Zhang, P. Zhelnin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter Annihilation and Pair-Instability Supernovae</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.20044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.20044v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the evolution of heavy stars ($M\ge40{\rm M}_\odot$) undergoing pair-instability in the presence of annihilating dark matter. Focusing on the scenario where the dark matter is in capture-annihilation equilibrium, we model the profile of energy injections in the local thermal equilibrium approximation. We find that significant changes to masses of astrophysical black holes formed by (pulsational) pair-instability supernovae can occur when the ambient dark matter density $ \rho_{\rm DM} \gtrsim10^9 \rm \, GeV \, cm^{-3}$. There are two distinct outcomes, depending on the dark matter mass. For masses $m_{\rm DM}\gtrsim1$ GeV the DM is primarily confined to the core. The annihilation increases the lifetime of core helium burning, resulting in more oxygen being formed, fueling a more violent explosion during the pair-instability-induced contraction. This drives stronger pulsations, leading to lighter black holes being formed than predicted by the standard model. For masses $m_{\rm DM}\lesssim0.5$ GeV there is significant dark matter in the envelope, leading to a phase where the star is supported by the energy from the annihilation. This reduces the core temperature and density, allowing the star to evade the pair-instability allowing heavier black holes to be formed. We find a mass gap for all models studied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.20044v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 109 (2024) 10, 103021</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Djuna Croon, Jeremy Sakstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Type Ia Supernova Progenitor Properties and Their Host Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03473v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an eigenfunction method to analyze 161 visual light curves (LCs) of Type Ia supernovae (SNe Ia) obtained by the Carnegie Supernova Project to characterize their diversity and host-galaxy correlations. The eigenfunctions are based on the delayed-detonation scenario using three parameters: the LC stretch being determined by the amount of deflagration-burning governing the 56Ni production, the main-sequence mass M_MS of the progenitor white dwarf controlling the explosion energy, and its central density rho_c shifting the 56Ni distribution. Our analysis tool (SPAT) extracts the parameters from observations and projects them into physical space using their allowed ranges M_MS &lt; 8 M_sun, rho_c &lt; 7-8x10^9g/cc. The residuals between fits and individual LC-points are ~ 1-3% for ~ 92% of objects. We find two distinct M_MS groups corresponding to a fast (~ 40-65 Myrs) and a slow(~ 200-500 Myrs) stellar evolution. Most underluminous SNe Ia have hosts with low star formation but high M_MS, suggesting slow evolution times of the progenitor system. 91T-likes SNe show very similar LCs and high M_MS and are correlated to star formation regions, making them potentially important tracers of star formation in the early Universe out to z = 4-11. Some 6% outliers with `non-physical' parameters can be attributed to superluminous SNe Ia and subluminous SNe Ia with hosts of active star formation. For deciphering the SNe Ia diversity and high-precision SNe Ia cosmology, the importance is shown for LCs covering out to ~ 60 days past maximum. Finally, our method and results are discussed within the framework of multiple explosion scenarios, and in light of upcoming surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03473v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad4702</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Astrophysical Journal (2024), Volume 969, Number 2, 80</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sudeshna Chakraborty, Benjamin Sadler, Peter Hoeflich, Eric Hsiao, M. M. Phillips, C. R. Burns, T. Diamond, I. Dominguez, L. Galbany, S. A. Uddin, C. Ashall, K. Krisciunas, S. Kumar, T. B. Mera, N. Morrell, E. Baron, M. C. Contreras, M. D. Stritzinger, N. N. Suntzeff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surveying the onset and evolution of supermassive black holes at high-z with AXIS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07669v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The nature and origin of supermassive black holes (SMBHs) remain an open matter of debate within the scientific community. While various theoretical scenarios have been proposed, each with specific observational signatures, the lack of sufficiently sensitive X-ray observations hinders the progress of observational tests. In this white paper, we present how AXIS will contribute to solving this issue. With an angular resolution of 1.5$^{\prime\prime}$ on-axis and minimal off-axis degradation, we have designed a deep survey capable of reaching flux limits in the [0.5-2] keV range of approximately 2$\times$10$^{-18}$ \fcgs~ over an area of 0.13 deg$^2$ in approximately 7 million seconds (7 Ms). Furthermore, we have planned an intermediate depth survey covering approximately 2 deg$^2$ and reaching flux limits of about 2$\times$10$^{-17}$ \fcgs ~ in order to detect a significant number of SMBHs with X-ray luminosities (L$_X$) of approximately 10$^{42}$ \lx up to z$\sim$10. These observations will enable AXIS to detect SMBHs with masses smaller than 10$^5$ \ms, assuming Eddington-limited accretion and a typical bolometric correction for Type II AGN. AXIS will provide valuable information on the seeding and population synthesis models of SMBH, allowing for more accurate constraints on their initial mass function (IMF) and accretion history from z$\sim$0-10. To accomplish this, AXIS will leverage the unique synergy of survey telescopes such as JWST, Roman, Euclid, LSST, and the new generation of 30m class telescopes. These instruments will provide optical identification and redshift measurements, while AXIS will discover the smoking gun of nuclear activity, particularly in the case of highly obscured AGN or peculiar UV spectra as predicted and recently observed in the early Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07669v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/universe10070276</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Nico Cappelluti, Adi Foord, Stefano Marchesi, Fabio Pacucci, Angelo Ricarte, Melanie Habouzit, Fabio Vito, Meredith Powell, Michael Koss, Richard Mushotzky, the AXIS AGN-SWG</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Green Bank North Celestial Cap Survey IX: Timing Follow-up for 128 Pulsars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.07471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.07471v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Green Bank North Celestial Cap survey is one of the largest and most sensitive searches for pulsars and transient radio objects. Observations for the survey have finished; priorities have shifted toward long-term monitoring of its discoveries. In this study, we have developed a pipeline to handle large datasets of archival observations and connect them to recent, high-cadence observations taken using the Canadian Hydrogen Intensity Mapping Experiment (CHIME) telescope. This pipeline handles data for 128 pulsars and has produced measurements of spin, positional, and orbital parameters that connect data over observation gaps as large as 2000 days. We have also measured glitches in the timing residuals for five of the pulsars included and proper motion for 19 sources (13 new). We include updates to orbital parameters for 19 pulsars, including 9 previously unpublished binaries. For two of these binaries, we provide updated measurements of post-Keplerian binary parameters, which result in much more precise estimates of the total masses of both systems. For PSR J0509+3801, the much improved measurement of the Einstein delay yields much improved mass measurements for the pulsar and its companion, 1.399(6)\Msun and 1.412(6)\Msun, respectively. For this system, we have also obtained a measurement of the orbital decay due to the emission of gravitational waves: $\dot{P}_{\rm B} = -1.37(7)\times10^{-12}$, which is in agreement with the rate predicted by general relativity for these masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.07471v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad11f0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>journal = {\apj}, year = 2024, month = feb, volume = {962}, number = {2}, pages = {167},</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. E. McEwen, J. K. Swiggum, D. L. Kaplan, C. M. Tan, B. W. Meyers, E. Fonseca, G. Y. Agazie, P. Chawla, K. Crowter, M. E. DeCesar, T. Dolch, F. A. Dong, W. Fiore, E. Fonseca, D. C. Good, A. G. Istrate, V. M. Kaspi, V. I. Kondratiev, J. van Leeuwen, L. Levin, E. F. Lewis, R. S. Lynch, K. W. Masui, J. W. McKee, M. A. McLaughlin, H. Al Noori, E. Parent, S. M. Ransom, X. Siemens, R. Spiewak, I. H. Stairs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for 10--1000 GeV neutrinos from Gamma Ray Bursts with IceCube</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11515v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the results of a search for 10--1,000 GeV neutrinos from 2,268 gamma-ray bursts over 8 years of IceCube-DeepCore data. This work probes burst physics below the photosphere where electromagnetic radiation cannot escape. Neutrinos of tens of GeVs are predicted in sub-photospheric collision of free streaming neutrons with bulk-jet protons. In a first analysis, we searched for the most significant neutrino-GRB coincidence using six overlapping time windows centered on the prompt phase of each GRB. In a second analysis, we conducted a search for a group of GRBs, each individually too weak to be detectable, but potentially significant when combined. No evidence of neutrino emission is found for either analysis. The most significant neutrino coincidence is for Fermi-GBM GRB bn 140807500, with a p-value of 0.097 corrected for all trials. The binomial test used to search for a group of GRBs had a p-value of 0.65 after all trial corrections. The binomial test found a group consisting only of GRB bn 140807500 and no additional GRBs. The neutrino limits of this work complement those obtained by IceCube at TeV to PeV energies. We compare our findings for the large set of GRBs as well as GRB 221009A to the sub-photospheric neutron-proton collision model and find that GRB 221009A provides the most constraining limit on baryon loading. For a jet Lorentz factor of 300 (800), the baryon loading on GRB 221009A is lower than 3.85 (2.13) at a 90% confidence level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11515v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad220b</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJ 964 126 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> IceCube Collaboration, R. Abbasi, M. Ackermann, J. Adams, S. K. Agarwalla, J. A. Aguilar, M. Ahlers, J. M. Alameddine, N. M. Amin, K. Andeen, G. Anton, C. Arg\"uelles, Y. Ashida, S. Athanasiadou, L. Ausborm, S. N. Axani, X. Bai, A. Balagopal V., M. Baricevic, S. W. Barwick, V. Basu, R. Bay, J. J. Beatty, J. Becker Tjus, J. Beise, C. Bellenghi, C. Benning, S. BenZvi, D. Berley, E. Bernardini, D. Z. Besson, E. Blaufuss, S. Blot, F. Bontempo, J. Y. Book, C. Boscolo Meneguolo, S. B\"oser, O. Botner, J. B\"ottcher, J. Braun, B. Brinson, J. Brostean-Kaiser, L. Brusa, R. T. Burley, R. S. Busse, D. Butterfield, M. A. Campana, K. Carloni, E. G. Carnie-Bronca, S. Chattopadhyay, N. Chau, C. Chen, Z. Chen, D. Chirkin, S. Choi, B. A. Clark, A. Coleman, G. H. Collin, A. Connolly, J. M. Conrad, P. Coppin, P. Correa, D. F. Cowen, P. Dave, C. De Clercq, J. J. DeLaunay, D. Delgado, S. Deng, K. Deoskar, A. Desai, P. Desiati, K. D. de Vries, G. de Wasseige, T. DeYoung, A. Diaz, J. C. D\'iaz-V\'elez, M. Dittmer, A. Domi, H. Dujmovic, M. A. DuVernois, T. Ehrhardt, A. Eimer, P. Eller, E. Ellinger, S. El Mentawi, D. Els\"asser, R. Engel, H. Erpenbeck, J. Evans, P. A. Evenson, K. L. Fan, K. Fang, K. Farrag, A. R. Fazely, A. Fedynitch, N. Feigl, S. Fiedlschuster, C. Finley, L. Fischer, D. Fox, A. Franckowiak, P. F\"urst, J. Gallagher, E. Ganster, A. Garcia, L. Gerhardt, A. Ghadimi, C. Glaser, T. Glauch, T. Gl\"usenkamp, J. G. Gonzalez, D. Grant, S. J. Gray, O. Gries, S. Griffin, S. Griswold, K. M. Groth, C. G\"unther, P. Gutjahr, C. Ha, C. Haack, A. Hallgren, R. Halliday, L. Halve, F. Halzen, H. Hamdaoui, M. Ha Minh, M. Handt, K. Hanson, J. Hardin, A. A. Harnisch, P. Hatch, A. Haungs, J. H\"au{\ss}ler, K. Helbing, J. Hellrung, J. Hermannsgabner, L. Heuermann, N. Heyer, S. Hickford, A. Hidvegi, C. Hill, G. C. Hill, K. D. Hoffman, S. Hori, K. Hoshina, W. Hou, T. Huber, K. Hultqvist, M. H\"unnefeld, R. Hussain, K. Hymon, S. In, A. Ishihara, M. Jacquart, O. Janik, M. Jansson, G. S. Japaridze, M. Jeong, M. Jin, B. J. P. Jones, N. Kamp, D. Kang, W. Kang, X. Kang, A. Kappes, D. Kappesser, L. Kardum, T. Karg, M. Karl, A. Karle, A. Katil, U. Katz, M. Kauer, J. L. Kelley, A. Khatee Zathul, A. Kheirandish, J. Kiryluk, S. R. Klein, A. Kochocki, R. Koirala, H. Kolanoski, T. Kontrimas, L. K\"opke, C. Kopper, D. J. Koskinen, P. Koundal, M. Kovacevich, M. Kowalski, T. Kozynets, J. Krishnamoorthi, K. Kruiswijk, E. Krupczak, A. Kumar, E. Kun, N. Kurahashi, N. Lad, C. Lagunas Gualda, M. Lamoureux, M. J. Larson, S. Latseva, F. Lauber, J. P. Lazar, J. W. Lee, K. Leonard DeHolton, A. Leszczy\'nska, M. Lincetto, Y. Liu, M. Liubarska, E. Lohfink, C. Love, C. J. Lozano Mariscal, L. Lu, F. Lucarelli, W. Luszczak, Y. Lyu, J. Madsen, E. Magnus, K. B. M. Mahn, Y. Makino, E. Manao, S. Mancina, W. Marie Sainte, I. C. Mari\c{s}, S. Marka, Z. Marka, M. Marsee, I. Martinez-Soler, R. Maruyama, F. Mayhew, T. McElroy, F. McNally, J. V. Mead, K. Meagher, S. Mechbal, A. Medina, M. Meier, Y. Merckx, L. Merten, J. Micallef, J. Mitchell, T. Montaruli, R. W. Moore, Y. Morii, R. Morse, M. Moulai, T. Mukherjee, R. Naab, R. Nagai, M. Nakos, U. Naumann, J. Necker, A. Negi, M. Neumann, H. Niederhausen, M. U. Nisa, A. Noell, A. Novikov, S. C. Nowicki, A. Obertacke Pollmann, V. O'Dell, B. Oeyen, A. Olivas, R. Orsoe, J. Osborn, E. O'Sullivan, H. Pandya, N. Park, G. K. Parker, E. N. Paudel, L. Paul, C. P\'erez de los Heros, J. Peterson, S. Philippen, A. Pizzuto, M. Plum, A. Pont\'en, Y. Popovych, M. Prado Rodriguez, B. Pries, R. Procter-Murphy, G. T. Przybylski, C. Raab, J. Rack-Helleis, K. Rawlins, Z. Rechav, A. Rehman, P. Reichherzer, E. Resconi, S. Reusch, W. Rhode, B. Riedel, A. Rifaie, E. J. Roberts, S. Robertson, S. Rodan, G. Roellinghoff, M. Rongen, A. Rosted, C. Rott, T. Ruhe, L. Ruohan, D. Ryckbosch, I. Safa, J. Saffer, D. Salazar-Gallegos, P. Sampathkumar, S. E. Sanchez Herrera, A. Sandrock, M. Santander, S. Sarkar, S. Sarkar, J. Savelberg, P. Savina, M. Schaufel, H. Schieler, S. Schindler, L. Schlickmann, B. Schl\"uter, F. Schl\"uter, N. Schmeisser, T. Schmidt, J. Schneider, F. G. Schr\"oder, L. Schumacher, S. Sclafani, D. Seckel, M. Seikh, S. Seunarine, R. Shah, S. Shefali, N. Shimizu, C. Silva, M. Silva, B. Skrzypek, B. Smithers, R. Snihur, J. Soedingrekso, A. S{\o}gaard, D. Soldin, P. Soldin, G. Sommani, C. Spannfellner, G. M. Spiczak, C. Spiering, M. Stamatikos, T. Stanev, T. Stezelberger, T. St\"urwald, T. Stuttard, G. W. Sullivan, I. Taboada, S. Ter-Antonyan, M. Thiesmeyer, W. G. Thompson, J. Thwaites, S. Tilav, K. Tollefson, C. T\"onnis, S. Toscano, D. Tosi, A. Trettin, C. F. Tung, R. Turcotte, J. P. Twagirayezu, M. A. Unland Elorrieta, A. K. Upadhyay, K. Upshaw, A. Vaidyanathan, N. Valtonen-Mattila, J. Vandenbroucke, N. van Eijndhoven, D. Vannerom, J. van Santen, J. Vara, J. Veitch-Michaelis, M. Venugopal, M. Vereecken, S. Verpoest, D. Veske, A. Vijai, C. Walck, Y. Wang, C. Weaver, P. Weigel, A. Weindl, J. Weldert, A. Y. Wen, C. Wendt, J. Werthebach, M. Weyrauch, N. Whitehorn, C. H. Wiebusch, D. R. Williams, L. Witthaus, A. Wolf, M. Wolf, G. Wrede, X. W. Xu, J. P. Yanez, E. Yildizci, S. Yoshida, R. Young, S. Yu, T. Yuan, Z. Zhang, P. Zhelnin, P. Zilberman, M. Zimmerman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A blind search for intraday gamma-ray transients with Fermi-LAT: Detections of GRB and solar emissions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.08946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.08946v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a search for intraday transient gamma-ray signals using 15.4 years of the Fermi Large Area Telescope data. The search is based on a recently developed variable-size sliding-time-window (VSSTW) analysis and aimed at studying variable gamma-ray emission from gamma-ray bursts and the Sun. We refined the algorithm for searches for transient sources in order to solve the search problem within a reasonable amount of CPU time. These refinements allowed us to increase the number of gamma-ray bursts, solar flares, and quiescent solar events detected with the VSSTW technique by several times compared to the previous VSSTW search. The current search revealed a new gamma-ray signal recorded with Fermi-LAT on 2018 January 12. This signal is probably from a GRB and deserves an exploration of the existing archival multi-wavelength observations in order to identify it in an unambiguous way. We also report a gamma-ray signal from the solar flare on 2023 December 31 that occurred during the 25th solar cycle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.08946v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202449251</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A 687, A196 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>D. A. Prokhorov, A. Moraghan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dzhanibekov Effect as a Possible Source of Magnetar Activity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.16783v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetars, which are neutron stars with strong magnetic fields, exhibit occasional bursting activities. The shape of a magnetar is not perfectly spherical due to the Lorentz force exerted by its strong magnetic fields and is described as a triaxial body. We study the unstable free precession in a triaxial magnetar; one of the principal axes undergoes an upside-down flip. This flip is known as the Dzhanibekov effect. We find that during the flip, the Euler force can suddenly disturb the force balance on the surface layer of the magnetar, potentially leading to plastic flow of the layer. This, in turn, may trigger different forms of magnetar activity, such as the emission of the bursts and/or of gravitational waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.16783v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoki Wada, Jiro Shimoda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection prospects of very and ultra high-energy gamma rays from extended sources with ASTRI, CTA, and LHAASO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03731v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Context. The recent discovery of several ultra high-energy gamma-ray emitters in our Galaxy represents a significant advancement towards the characterisation of its most powerful accelerators. Nonetheless, in order to unambiguously locate the regions where the highest energy particles are produced and understand the responsible physical mechanisms, detailed spectral and morphological studies are required, especially given that most of the observed sources were found to be significantly extended. Aims. In these regards, pointing observations with the next-generation Imaging Atmospheric Cherenkov Telescopes, such as the Cherenkov Telescope Array (CTA) Observatory and the ASTRI Mini-Array (ASTRI), are expected to provide significant improvements. Here we aim to identify the most promising sources to target in future observations. Methods. For this purpose, we performed a comparative analysis of the expected performance of ASTRI and CTA, computing their differential sensitivities towards extended sources, and further explored their capabilities with respect to specific case studies, including follow-ups of existing gamma-ray source catalogues. Results. We find that almost all of the sources thus far detected by LHAASO-WCDA and in the H.E.S.S. Galactic Plane Survey will be in the reach of ASTRI and CTA with about 300 and 50 hours of exposure, respectively. For the highest energy emitters detected by LHAASO-KM2A, in turn, we provide a list of the most promising objects that would require further investigation. We additionally examined specific classes of sources in order to identify potentially detectable gamma-ray emitters, such as passive molecular clouds (i.e. illuminated by the cosmic-ray sea) and pulsars surrounded by a halo of runaway particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03731v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Silvia Celli, Giada Peron</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of Gravitational Waves from the Coalescence of a $2.5\text{-}4.5~M_\odot$ Compact Object and a Neutron Star</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04248v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the observation of a coalescing compact binary with component masses $2.5\text{-}4.5~M_\odot$ and $1.2\text{-}2.0~M_\odot$ (all measurements quoted at the 90% credible level). The gravitational-wave signal GW230529_181500 was observed during the fourth observing run of the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA detector network on 2023 May 29 by the LIGO Livingston Observatory. The primary component of the source has a mass less than $5~M_\odot$ at 99% credibility. We cannot definitively determine from gravitational-wave data alone whether either component of the source is a neutron star or a black hole. However, given existing estimates of the maximum neutron star mass, we find the most probable interpretation of the source to be the coalescence of a neutron star with a black hole that has a mass between the most massive neutron stars and the least massive black holes observed in the Galaxy. We provisionally estimate a merger rate density of $55^{+127}_{-47}~\text{Gpc}^{-3}\,\text{yr}^{-1}$ for compact binary coalescences with properties similar to the source of GW230529_181500; assuming that the source is a neutron star-black hole merger, GW230529_181500-like sources constitute about 60% of the total merger rate inferred for neutron star-black hole coalescences. The discovery of this system implies an increase in the expected rate of neutron star-black hole mergers with electromagnetic counterparts and provides further evidence for compact objects existing within the purported lower mass gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04248v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/ad5beb</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJL 970, L34 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> The LIGO Scientific Collaboration,  the Virgo Collaboration,  the KAGRA Collaboration, A. G. Abac, R. Abbott, I. Abouelfettouh, F. Acernese, K. Ackley, S. Adhicary, N. Adhikari, R. X. Adhikari, V. K. Adkins, D. Agarwal, M. Agathos, M. Aghaei Abchouyeh, O. D. Aguiar, I. Aguilar, L. Aiello, A. Ain, P. Ajith, S. Ak\c{c}ay, T. Akutsu, S. Albanesi, R. A. Alfaidi, A. Al-Jodah, C. All\'en\'e, A. Allocca, S. Al-Shammari, P. A. Altin, S. Alvarez-Lopez, A. Amato, L. Amez-Droz, A. Amorosi, C. Amra, A. Ananyeva, S. B. Anderson, W. G. Anderson, M. Andia, M. Ando, T. Andrade, N. Andres, M. Andr\'es-Carcasona, T. Andri\'c, J. Anglin, S. Ansoldi, J. M. Antelis, S. Antier, M. Aoumi, E. Z. Appavuravther, S. Appert, S. K. Apple, K. Arai, A. Araya, M. C. Araya, J. S. Areeda, L. Argianas, N. Aritomi, F. Armato, N. Arnaud, M. Arogeti, S. M. Aronson, K. G. Arun, G. Ashton, Y. Aso, M. Assiduo, S. Assis de Souza Melo, S. M. Aston, P. Astone, F. Attadio, F. Aubin, K. AultONeal, G. Avallone, D. Azrad, S. Babak, F. Badaracco, C. Badger, S. Bae, S. Bagnasco, E. Bagui, J. G. Baier, L. Baiotti, R. Bajpai, T. Baka, M. Ball, G. Ballardin, S. W. Ballmer, S. Banagiri, B. Banerjee, D. Bankar, P. Baral, J. C. Barayoga, B. C. Barish, D. Barker, P. Barneo, F. Barone, B. Barr, L. Barsotti, M. Barsuglia, D. Barta, A. M. Bartoletti, M. A. Barton, I. Bartos, S. Basak, A. Basalaev, R. Bassiri, A. Basti, D. E. Bates, M. Bawaj, P. Baxi, J. C. Bayley, A. C. Baylor, P. A. Baynard II, M. Bazzan, V. M. Bedakihale, F. Beirnaert, M. Bejger, D. Belardinelli, A. S. Bell, V. Benedetto, W. Benoit, I. Bentara, J. D. Bentley, M. Ben Yaala, S. Bera, M. Berbel, F. Bergamin, B. K. Berger, S. Bernuzzi, M. Beroiz, C. P. L. Berry, D. Bersanetti, A. Bertolini, J. Betzwieser, D. Beveridge, N. Bevins, R. Bhandare, U. Bhardwaj, R. Bhatt, D. Bhattacharjee, S. Bhaumik, S. Bhowmick, A. Bianchi, I. A. Bilenko, G. Billingsley, A. Binetti, S. Bini, O. Birnholtz, S. Biscoveanu, A. Bisht, M. Bitossi, M. -A. Bizouard, J. K. Blackburn, L. A. Blagg, C. D. Blair, D. G. Blair, F. Bobba, N. Bode, G. Boileau, M. Boldrini, G. N. Bolingbroke, A. Bolliand, L. D. Bonavena, R. Bondarescu, F. Bondu, E. Bonilla, M. S. Bonilla, A. Bonino, R. Bonnand, P. Booker, A. Borchers, V. Boschi, S. Bose, V. Bossilkov, V. Boudart, A. Boudon, A. Bozzi, C. Bradaschia, P. R. Brady, M. Braglia, A. Branch, M. Branchesi, J. Brandt, I. Braun, M. Breschi, T. Briant, A. Brillet, M. Brinkmann, P. Brockill, E. Brockmueller, A. F. Brooks, B. C. Brown, D. D. Brown, M. L. Brozzetti, S. Brunett, G. Bruno, R. Bruntz, J. Bryant, F. Bucci, J. Buchanan, O. Bulashenko, T. Bulik, H. J. Bulten, A. Buonanno, K. Burtnyk, R. Buscicchio, D. Buskulic, C. Buy, R. L. Byer, G. S. Cabourn Davies, G. Cabras, R. Cabrita, V. C\'aceres-Barbosa, L. Cadonati, G. Cagnoli, C. Cahillane, J. Calder\'on Bustillo, T. A. Callister, E. Calloni, J. B. Camp, M. Canepa, G. Caneva Santoro, K. C. Cannon, H. Cao, L. A. Capistran, E. Capocasa, E. Capote, G. Carapella, F. Carbognani, M. Carlassara, J. B. Carlin, M. Carpinelli, G. Carrillo, J. J. Carter, G. Carullo, J. Casanueva Diaz, C. Casentini, S. Y. Castro-Lucas, S. Caudill, M. Cavagli\`a, R. Cavalieri, G. Cella, P. Cerd\'a-Dur\'an, E. Cesarini, W. Chaibi, P. Chakraborty, S. Chalathadka Subrahmanya, J. C. L. Chan, M. Chan, K. Chandra, R. -J. Chang, S. Chao, P. Char, E. L. Charlton, P. Charlton, E. Chassande-Mottin, C. Chatterjee, Debarati Chatterjee, Deep Chatterjee, D. Chattopadhyay, M. Chaturvedi, S. Chaty, K. Chatziioannou, A. Chen, A. H. -Y. Chen, D. Chen, H. Chen, H. Y. Chen, J. Chen, K. H. Chen, Y. Chen, Yanbei Chen, Yitian Chen, H. P. Cheng, P. Chessa, H. T. Cheung, S. Y. Cheung, F. Chiadini, G. Chiarini, R. Chierici, A. Chincarini, M. L. Chiofalo, A. Chiummo, C. Chou, S. Choudhary, N. Christensen, S. S. Y. Chua, P. Chugh, G. Ciani, P. Ciecielag, M. Cie\'slar, M. Cifaldi, R. Ciolfi, F. Clara, J. A. Clark, J. Clarke, T. A. Clarke, P. Clearwater, S. Clesse, E. Coccia, E. Codazzo, P. -F. Cohadon, S. Colace, M. Colleoni, C. G. Collette, J. Collins, S. Colloms, A. Colombo, M. Colpi, C. M. Compton, G. Connolly, L. Conti, T. R. Corbitt, I. Cordero-Carri\'on, S. Corezzi, N. J. Cornish, A. Corsi, S. Cortese, C. A. Costa, R. Cottingham, M. W. Coughlin, A. Couineaux, J. -P. Coulon, S. T. Countryman, J. -F. Coupechoux, P. Couvares, D. M. Coward, M. J. Cowart, R. Coyne, K. Craig, R. Creed, J. D. E. Creighton, T. D. Creighton, P. Cremonese, A. W. Criswell, J. C. G. Crockett-Gray, S. Crook, R. Crouch, J. Csizmazia, J. R. Cudell, T. J. Cullen, A. Cumming, E. Cuoco, M. Cusinato, P. Dabadie, T. Dal Canton, S. Dall'Osso, S. Dal Pra, G. D\'alya, B. D'Angelo, S. Danilishin, S. D'Antonio, K. Danzmann, K. E. Darroch, L. P. Dartez, A. Dasgupta, S. Datta, V. Dattilo, A. Daumas, N. Davari, I. Dave, A. Davenport, M. Davier, T. F. Davies, D. Davis, L. Davis, M. C. Davis, P. J. Davis, M. Dax, J. De Bolle, M. Deenadayalan, J. Degallaix, M. De Laurentis, S. Del\'eglise, F. De Lillo, D. Dell'Aquila, W. Del Pozzo, F. De Marco, F. De Matteis, V. D'Emilio, N. Demos, T. Dent, A. Depasse, N. DePergola, R. De Pietri, R. De Rosa, C. De Rossi, R. DeSalvo, R. De Simone, A. Dhani, R. Diab, M. C. D\'iaz, M. Di Cesare, G. Dideron, N. A. Didio, T. Dietrich, L. Di Fiore, C. Di Fronzo, M. Di Giovanni, T. Di Girolamo, D. Diksha, A. Di Michele, J. Ding, S. Di Pace, I. Di Palma, F. Di Renzo,  Divyajyoti, A. Dmitriev, Z. Doctor, E. Dohmen, P. P. Doleva, D. Dominguez, L. D'Onofrio, F. Donovan, K. L. Dooley, T. Dooney, S. Doravari, O. Dorosh, M. Drago, J. C. Driggers, J. -G. Ducoin, L. Dunn, U. Dupletsa, D. D'Urso, H. Duval, P. -A. Duverne, S. E. Dwyer, C. Eassa, M. Ebersold, T. Eckhardt, G. Eddolls, B. Edelman, T. B. Edo, O. Edy, A. Effler, J. Eichholz, H. Einsle, M. Eisenmann, R. A. Eisenstein, A. Ejlli, R. M. Eleveld, M. Emma, K. Endo, A. J. Engl, E. Enloe, L. Errico, R. C. Essick, H. Estell\'es, D. Estevez, T. Etzel, M. Evans, T. Evstafyeva, B. E. Ewing, J. M. Ezquiaga, F. Fabrizi, F. Faedi, V. Fafone, S. Fairhurst, A. M. Farah, B. Farr, W. M. Farr, G. Favaro, M. Favata, M. Fays, M. Fazio, J. Feicht, M. M. Fejer, R. Felicetti, E. Fenyvesi, D. L. Ferguson, S. Ferraiuolo, I. Ferrante, T. A. Ferreira, F. Fidecaro, P. Figura, A. Fiori, I. Fiori, M. Fishbach, R. P. Fisher, R. Fittipaldi, V. Fiumara, R. Flaminio, S. M. Fleischer, L. S. Fleming, E. Floden, E. M. Foley, H. Fong, J. A. Font, B. Fornal, P. W. F. Forsyth, K. Franceschetti, N. Franchini, S. Frasca, F. Frasconi, A. Frattale Mascioli, Z. Frei, A. Freise, O. Freitas, R. Frey, W. Frischhertz, P. Fritschel, V. V. Frolov, G. G. Fronz\'e, M. Fuentes-Garcia, S. Fujii, T. Fujimori, P. Fulda, M. Fyffe, B. Gadre, J. R. Gair, S. Galaudage, V. Galdi, H. Gallagher, S. Gallardo, B. Gallego, R. Gamba, A. Gamboa, D. Ganapathy, A. Ganguly, B. Garaventa, J. Garc\'ia-Bellido, C. Garc\'ia N\'u\~nez, C. Garc\'ia-Quir\'os, J. W. Gardner, K. A. Gardner, J. Gargiulo, A. Garron, F. Garufi, C. Gasbarra, B. Gateley, V. Gayathri, G. Gemme, A. Gennai, V. Gennari, J. George, R. George, O. Gerberding, L. Gergely, S. Ghonge, Archisman Ghosh, Sayantan Ghosh, Shaon Ghosh, Shrobana Ghosh, Suprovo Ghosh, Tathagata Ghosh, L. Giacoppo, J. A. Giaime, K. D. Giardina, D. R. Gibson, D. T. Gibson, C. Gier, P. Giri, F. Gissi, S. Gkaitatzis, J. Glanzer, F. Glotin, J. Godfrey, P. Godwin, N. L. Goebbels, E. Goetz, J. Golomb, S. Gomez Lopez, B. Goncharov, Y. Gong, G. Gonz\'alez, P. Goodarzi, S. Goode, A. W. Goodwin-Jones, M. Gosselin, A. S. G\"ottel, R. Gouaty, D. W. Gould, K. Govorkova, S. Goyal, B. Grace, A. Grado, V. Graham, A. E. Granados, M. Granata, V. Granata, S. Gras, P. Grassia, A. Gray, C. Gray, R. Gray, G. Greco, A. C. Green, S. M. Green, S. R. Green, A. M. Gretarsson, E. M. Gretarsson, D. Griffith, W. L. Griffiths, H. L. Griggs, G. Grignani, A. Grimaldi, C. Grimaud, H. Grote, D. Guerra, D. Guetta, G. M. Guidi, A. R. Guimaraes, H. K. Gulati, F. Gulminelli, A. M. Gunny, H. Guo, W. Guo, Y. Guo, Anchal Gupta, Anuradha Gupta, Ish Gupta, N. C. Gupta, P. Gupta, S. K. Gupta, T. Gupta, N. Gupte, J. Gurs, N. Gutierrez, F. Guzman, H. -Y. H, D. Haba, M. Haberland, S. Haino, E. D. Hall, E. Z. Hamilton, G. Hammond, W. -B. Han, M. Haney, J. Hanks, C. Hanna, M. D. Hannam, O. A. Hannuksela, A. G. Hanselman, H. Hansen, J. Hanson, R. Harada, A. R. Hardison, K. Haris, T. Harmark, J. Harms, G. M. Harry, I. W. Harry, J. Hart, B. Haskell, C. -J. Haster, J. S. Hathaway, K. Haughian, H. Hayakawa, K. Hayama, R. Hayes, A. Heffernan, A. Heidmann, M. C. Heintze, J. Heinze, J. Heinzel, H. Heitmann, F. Hellman, P. Hello, A. F. Helmling-Cornell, G. Hemming, O. Henderson-Sapir, M. Hendry, I. S. Heng, E. Hennes, C. Henshaw, T. Hertog, M. Heurs, A. L. Hewitt, J. Heyns, S. Higginbotham, S. Hild, S. Hill, Y. Himemoto, N. Hirata, C. Hirose, S. Hoang, S. Hochheim, D. Hofman, N. A. Holland, K. Holley-Bockelmann, Z. J. Holmes, D. E. Holz, L. Honet, C. Hong, J. Hornung, S. Hoshino, J. Hough, S. Hourihane, E. J. Howell, C. G. Hoy, C. A. Hrishikesh, H. -F. Hsieh, C. Hsiung, H. C. Hsu, W. -F. Hsu, P. Hu, Q. Hu, H. Y. Huang, Y. -J. Huang, A. D. Huddart, B. Hughey, D. C. Y. Hui, V. Hui, S. Husa, R. Huxford, T. Huynh-Dinh, L. Iampieri, G. A. Iandolo, M. Ianni, A. Iess, H. Imafuku, K. Inayoshi, Y. Inoue, G. Iorio, M. H. Iqbal, J. Irwin, R. Ishikawa, M. Isi, M. A. Ismail, Y. Itoh, H. Iwanaga, M. Iwaya, B. R. Iyer, V. JaberianHamedan, C. Jacquet, P. -E. Jacquet, S. J. Jadhav, S. P. Jadhav, T. Jain, A. L. James, P. A. James, R. Jamshidi, J. Janquart, K. Janssens, N. N. Janthalur, S. Jaraba, P. Jaranowski, R. Jaume, W. Javed, A. Jennings, W. Jia, J. Jiang, J. Kubisz, C. Johanson, G. R. Johns, N. A. Johnson, N. K. Johnson-McDaniel, M. C. Johnston, R. Johnston, N. Johny, D. H. Jones, D. I. Jones, R. Jones, S. Jose, P. Joshi, L. Ju, K. Jung, J. Junker, V. Juste, T. Kajita, I. Kaku, C. Kalaghatgi, V. Kalogera, M. Kamiizumi, N. Kanda, S. Kandhasamy, G. Kang, J. B. Kanner, S. J. Kapadia, D. P. Kapasi, S. Karat, C. Karathanasis, R. Kashyap, M. Kasprzack, W. Kastaun, T. Kato, E. Katsavounidis, W. Katzman, R. Kaushik, K. Kawabe, R. Kawamoto, A. Kazemi, A. Kedia, D. Keitel, J. Kelley-Derzon, J. Kennington, R. Kesharwani, J. S. Key, R. Khadela, S. Khadka, F. Y. Khalili, F. Khan, I. Khan, T. Khanam, M. Khursheed, N. M. Khusid, W. Kiendrebeogo, N. Kijbunchoo, C. Kim, J. C. Kim, K. Kim, M. H. Kim, S. Kim, Y. -M. Kim, C. Kimball, M. Kinley-Hanlon, M. Kinnear, J. S. Kissel, S. Klimenko, A. M. Knee, N. Knust, K. Kobayashi, P. Koch, S. M. Koehlenbeck, G. Koekoek, K. Kohri, K. Kokeyama, S. Koley, P. Kolitsidou, M. Kolstein, K. Komori, A. K. H. Kong, A. Kontos, M. Korobko, R. V. Kossak, X. Kou, A. Koushik, N. Kouvatsos, M. Kovalam, D. B. Kozak, S. L. Kranzhoff, V. Kringel, N. V. Krishnendu, A. Kr\'olak, K. Kruska, G. Kuehn, P. Kuijer, S. Kulkarni, A. Kulur Ramamohan, A. Kumar, Praveen Kumar, Prayush Kumar, Rahul Kumar, Rakesh Kumar, J. Kume, K. Kuns, N. Kuntimaddi, S. Kuroyanagi, N. J. Kurth, S. Kuwahara, K. Kwak, K. Kwan, J. Kwok, G. Lacaille, P. Lagabbe, D. Laghi, S. Lai, A. H. Laity, M. H. Lakkis, E. Lalande, M. Lalleman, P. C. Lalremruati, M. Landry, P. Landry, B. B. Lane, R. N. Lang, J. Lange, B. Lantz, A. La Rana, I. La Rosa, A. Lartaux-Vollard, P. D. Lasky, J. Lawrence, M. N. Lawrence, M. Laxen, A. Lazzarini, C. Lazzaro, P. Leaci, Y. K. Lecoeuche, H. M. Lee, H. W. Lee, K. Lee, R. -K. Lee, R. Lee, S. Lee, Y. Lee, I. N. Legred, J. Lehmann, L. Lehner, M. Le Jean, A. Lema\^itre, M. Lenti, M. Leonardi, M. Lequime, N. Leroy, M. Lesovsky, N. Letendre, M. Lethuillier, S. E. Levin, Y. Levin, K. Leyde, A. K. Y. Li, K. L. Li, T. G. F. Li, X. Li, Z. Li, A. Lihos, C-Y. Lin, C. -Y. Lin, E. T. Lin, F. Lin, H. Lin, L. C. -C. Lin, Y. -C. Lin, F. Linde, S. D. Linker, T. B. Littenberg, A. Liu, G. C. Liu, Jian Liu, F. Llamas Villarreal, J. Llobera-Querol, R. K. L. Lo, J. -P. Locquet, L. T. London, A. Longo, D. Lopez, M. Lopez Portilla, M. Lorenzini, A. Lorenzo-Medina, V. Loriette, M. Lormand, G. Losurdo, T. P. Lott IV, J. D. Lough, H. A. Loughlin, C. O. Lousto, M. J. Lowry, N. Lu, H. L\"uck, D. Lumaca, A. P. Lundgren, A. W. Lussier, L. -T. Ma, S. Ma, M. Ma'arif, R. Macas, A. Macedo, M. MacInnis, R. R. Maciy, D. M. Macleod, I. A. O. MacMillan, A. Macquet, D. Macri, K. Maeda, S. Maenaut, I. Maga\~na Hernandez, S. S. Magare, C. Magazz\`u, R. M. Magee, E. Maggio, R. Maggiore, M. Magnozzi, M. Mahesh, S. Mahesh, M. Maini, S. Majhi, E. Majorana, C. N. Makarem, E. Makelele, J. A. Malaquias-Reis, U. Mali, S. Maliakal, A. Malik, N. Man, V. Mandic, V. Mangano, B. Mannix, G. L. Mansell, G. Mansingh, M. Manske, M. Mantovani, M. Mapelli, F. Marchesoni, D. Mar\'in Pina, F. Marion, S. M\'arka, Z. M\'arka, A. S. Markosyan, A. Markowitz, E. Maros, S. Marsat, F. Martelli, I. W. Martin, R. M. Martin, B. B. Martinez, M. Martinez, V. Martinez, A. Martini, K. Martinovic, J. C. Martins, D. V. Martynov, E. J. Marx, L. Massaro, A. Masserot, M. Masso-Reid, M. Mastrodicasa, S. Mastrogiovanni, T. Matcovich, M. Matiushechkina, M. Matsuyama, N. Mavalvala, N. Maxwell, G. McCarrol, R. McCarthy, D. E. McClelland, S. McCormick, L. McCuller, S. McEachin, C. McElhenny, G. I. McGhee, J. McGinn, K. B. M. McGowan, J. McIver, A. McLeod, T. McRae, D. Meacher, Q. Meijer, A. Melatos, S. Mellaerts, A. Menendez-Vazquez, C. S. Menoni, F. Mera, R. A. Mercer, L. Mereni, K. Merfeld, E. L. Merilh, J. R. M\'erou, J. D. Merritt, M. Merzougui, C. Messenger, C. Messick, M. Meyer-Conde, F. Meylahn, A. Mhaske, A. Miani, H. Miao, I. Michaloliakos, C. Michel, Y. Michimura, H. Middleton, A. L. Miller, S. Miller, M. Millhouse, E. Milotti, V. Milotti, Y. Minenkov, N. Mio, Ll. M. Mir, L. Mirasola, M. Miravet-Ten\'es, C. -A. Miritescu, A. K. Mishra, A. Mishra, C. Mishra, T. Mishra, A. L. Mitchell, J. G. Mitchell, S. Mitra, V. P. Mitrofanov, R. Mittleman, O. Miyakawa, S. Miyamoto, S. Miyoki, G. Mo, L. Mobilia, S. R. P. Mohapatra, S. R. Mohite, M. Molina-Ruiz, C. Mondal, M. Mondin, M. Montani, C. J. Moore, D. Moraru, A. More, S. More, G. Moreno, C. Morgan, S. Morisaki, Y. Moriwaki, G. Morras, A. Moscatello, P. Mourier, B. Mours, C. M. Mow-Lowry, F. Muciaccia, Arunava Mukherjee, D. Mukherjee, Samanwaya Mukherjee, Soma Mukherjee, Subroto Mukherjee, Suvodip Mukherjee, N. Mukund, A. Mullavey, J. Munch, J. Mundi, C. L. Mungioli, W. R. Munn Oberg, Y. Murakami, M. Murakoshi, P. G. Murray, S. Muusse, D. Nabari, S. L. Nadji, A. Nagar, N. Nagarajan, K. N. Nagler, K. Nakagaki, K. Nakamura, H. Nakano, M. Nakano, D. Nandi, V. Napolano, P. Narayan, I. Nardecchia, T. Narikawa, H. Narola, L. Naticchioni, R. K. Nayak, J. Neilson, A. Nelson, T. J. N. Nelson, M. Nery, A. Neunzert, S. Ng, L. Nguyen Quynh, S. A. Nichols, A. B. Nielsen, G. Nieradka, A. Niko, Y. Nishino, A. Nishizawa, S. Nissanke, E. Nitoglia, W. Niu, F. Nocera, M. Norman, C. North, J. Novak, J. F. Nu\~no Siles, L. K. Nuttall, K. Obayashi, J. Oberling, J. O'Dell, M. Oertel, A. Offermans, G. Oganesyan, J. J. Oh, K. Oh, T. O'Hanlon, M. Ohashi, M. Ohkawa, F. Ohme, A. S. Oliveira, R. Oliveri, B. O'Neal, K. Oohara, B. O'Reilly, N. D. Ormsby, M. Orselli, R. O'Shaughnessy, S. O'Shea, Y. Oshima, S. Oshino, S. Ossokine, C. Osthelder, I. Ota, D. J. Ottaway, A. Ouzriat, H. Overmier, B. J. Owen, A. E. Pace, R. Pagano, M. A. Page, A. Pai, A. Pal, S. Pal, M. A. Palaia, M. P\'alfi, P. P. Palma, C. Palomba, P. Palud, H. Pan, J. Pan, K. C. Pan, R. Panai, P. K. Panda, S. Pandey, L. Panebianco, P. T. H. Pang, F. Pannarale, K. A. Pannone, B. C. Pant, F. H. Panther, F. Paoletti, A. Paolone, E. E. Papalexakis, L. Papalini, G. Papigkiotis, A. Paquis, A. Parisi, B. -J. Park, J. Park, W. Parker, G. Pascale, D. Pascucci, A. Pasqualetti, R. Passaquieti, L. Passenger, D. Passuello, O. Patane, D. Pathak, M. Pathak, A. Patra, B. Patricelli, A. S. Patron, K. Paul, S. Paul, E. Payne, T. Pearce, M. Pedraza, R. Pegna, A. Pele, F. E. Pe\~na Arellano, S. Penn, M. D. Penuliar, A. Perego, Z. Pereira, J. J. Perez, C. P\'erigois, G. Perna, A. Perreca, J. Perret, S. Perri\`es, J. W. Perry, D. Pesios, S. Petracca, C. Petrillo, H. P. Pfeiffer, H. Pham, K. A. Pham, K. S. Phukon, H. Phurailatpam, M. Piarulli, L. Piccari, O. J. Piccinni, M. Pichot, M. Piendibene, F. Piergiovanni, L. Pierini, G. Pierra, V. Pierro, M. Pietrzak, M. Pillas, F. Pilo, L. Pinard, I. M. Pinto, M. Pinto, B. J. Piotrzkowski, M. Pirello, M. D. Pitkin, A. Placidi, E. Placidi, M. L. Planas, W. Plastino, R. Poggiani, E. Polini, L. Pompili, J. Poon, E. Porcelli, E. K. Porter, C. Posnansky, R. Poulton, J. Powell, M. Pracchia, B. K. Pradhan, T. Pradier, A. K. Prajapati, K. Prasai, R. Prasanna, P. Prasia, G. Pratten, G. Principe, M. Principe, G. A. Prodi, L. Prokhorov, P. Prosposito, A. Puecher, J. Pullin, M. Punturo, P. Puppo, M. P\"urrer, H. Qi, J. Qin, G. Qu\'em\'ener, V. Quetschke, C. Quigley, P. J. Quinonez, F. J. Raab, S. S. Raabith, G. Raaijmakers, S. Raja, C. Rajan, B. Rajbhandari, K. E. Ramirez, F. A. Ramis Vidal, A. Ramos-Buades, D. Rana, S. Ranjan, K. Ransom, P. Rapagnani, B. Ratto, S. Rawat, A. Ray, V. Raymond, M. Razzano, J. Read, M. Recaman Payo, T. Regimbau, L. Rei, S. Reid, D. H. Reitze, P. Relton, A. I. Renzini, P. Rettegno, B. Revenu, R. Reyes, A. S. Rezaei, F. Ricci, M. Ricci, A. Ricciardone, J. W. Richardson, M. Richardson, A. Rijal, K. Riles, H. K. Riley, S. Rinaldi, J. Rittmeyer, C. Robertson, F. Robinet, M. Robinson, A. Rocchi, L. Rolland, J. G. Rollins, A. E. Romano, R. Romano, A. Romero, I. M. Romero-Shaw, J. H. Romie, S. Ronchini, T. J. Roocke, L. Rosa, T. J. Rosauer, C. A. Rose, D. Rosi\'nska, M. P. Ross, M. Rossello, S. Rowan, S. K. Roy, S. Roy, D. Rozza, P. Ruggi, N. Ruhama, E. Ruiz Morales, K. Ruiz-Rocha, S. Sachdev, T. Sadecki, J. Sadiq, P. Saffarieh, M. R. Sah, S. S. Saha, S. Saha, T. Sainrat, S. Sajith Menon, K. Sakai, M. Sakellariadou, S. Sakon, O. S. Salafia, F. Salces-Carcoba, L. Salconi, M. Saleem, F. Salemi, M. Sall\'e, S. Salvador, A. Sanchez, E. J. Sanchez, J. H. Sanchez, L. E. Sanchez, N. Sanchis-Gual, J. R. Sanders, E. M. S\"anger, F. Santoliquido, T. R. Saravanan, N. Sarin, S. Sasaoka, A. Sasli, P. Sassi, B. Sassolas, H. Satari, B. S. Sathyaprakash, R. Sato, Y. Sato, O. Sauter, R. L. Savage, T. Sawada, H. L. Sawant, S. Sayah, V. Scacco, D. Schaetzl, M. Scheel, A. Schiebelbein, M. G. Schiworski, P. Schmidt, S. Schmidt, R. Schnabel, M. Schneewind, R. M. S. Schofield, K. Schouteden, B. W. Schulte, B. F. Schutz, E. Schwartz, M. Scialpi, J. Scott, S. M. Scott, T. C. Seetharamu, M. Seglar-Arroyo, Y. Sekiguchi, D. Sellers, A. S. Sengupta, D. Sentenac, E. G. Seo, J. W. Seo, V. Sequino, M. Serra, G. Servignat, A. Sevrin, T. Shaffer, U. S. Shah, M. A. Shaikh, L. Shao, A. K. Sharma, P. Sharma, S. Sharma-Chaudhary, M. R. Shaw, P. Shawhan, N. S. Shcheblanov, E. Sheridan, Y. Shikano, M. Shikauchi, K. Shimode, H. Shinkai, J. Shiota, D. H. Shoemaker, D. M. Shoemaker, R. W. Short, S. ShyamSundar, A. Sider, H. Siegel, M. Sieniawska, D. Sigg, L. Silenzi, M. Simmonds, L. P. Singer, A. Singh, D. Singh, M. K. Singh, S. Singh, A. Singha, A. M. Sintes, V. Sipala, V. Skliris, B. J. J. Slagmolen, T. J. Slaven-Blair, J. Smetana, J. R. Smith, L. Smith, R. J. E. Smith, W. J. Smith, J. Soldateschi, K. Somiya, I. Song, K. Soni, S. Soni, V. Sordini, F. Sorrentino, N. Sorrentino, H. Sotani, R. Soulard, A. Southgate, V. Spagnuolo, A. P. Spencer, M. Spera, P. Spinicelli, J. B. Spoon, C. A. Sprague, A. K. Srivastava, F. Stachurski, D. A. Steer, J. Steinlechner, S. Steinlechner, N. Stergioulas, P. Stevens, S. Stevenson, M. StPierre, G. Stratta, M. D. Strong, A. Strunk, R. Sturani, A. L. Stuver, M. Suchenek, S. Sudhagar, N. Sueltmann, L. Suleiman, K. D. Sullivan, L. Sun, S. Sunil, J. Suresh, P. J. Sutton, T. Suzuki, Y. Suzuki, B. L. Swinkels, A. Syx, M. J. Szczepa\'nczyk, P. Szewczyk, M. Tacca, H. Tagoshi, S. C. Tait, H. Takahashi, R. Takahashi, A. Takamori, T. Takase, K. Takatani, H. Takeda, K. Takeshita, C. Talbot, M. Tamaki, N. Tamanini, D. Tanabe, K. Tanaka, S. J. Tanaka, T. Tanaka, D. Tang, S. Tanioka, D. B. Tanner, L. Tao, R. D. Tapia, E. N. Tapia San Mart\'in, R. Tarafder, C. Taranto, A. Taruya, J. D. Tasson, M. Teloi, R. Tenorio, H. Themann, A. Theodoropoulos, M. P. Thirugnanasambandam, L. M. Thomas, M. Thomas, P. Thomas, J. E. Thompson, S. R. Thondapu, K. A. Thorne, E. Thrane, J. Tissino, A. Tiwari, P. Tiwari, S. Tiwari, V. Tiwari, M. R. Todd, A. M. Toivonen, K. Toland, A. E. Tolley, T. Tomaru, K. Tomita, T. Tomura, H. Tong, C. Tong-Yu, A. Toriyama, N. Toropov, A. Torres-Forn\'e, C. I. Torrie, M. Toscani, I. Tosta e Melo, E. Tournefier, A. Trapananti, F. Travasso, G. Traylor, M. Trevor, M. C. Tringali, A. Tripathee, G. Troian, L. Troiano, A. Trovato, L. Trozzo, R. J. Trudeau, T. T. L. Tsang, S. Tsuchida, L. Tsukada, T. Tsutsui, K. Turbang, M. Turconi, C. Turski, H. Ubach, N. Uchikata, T. Uchiyama, R. P. Udall, T. Uehara, M. Uematsu, K. Ueno, S. Ueno, V. Undheim, T. Ushiba, M. Vacatello, H. Vahlbruch, N. Vaidya, G. Vajente, A. Vajpeyi, G. Valdes, J. Valencia, M. Valentini, S. A. Vallejo-Pe\~na, S. Vallero, V. Valsan, N. van Bakel, M. van Beuzekom, M. van Dael, J. F. J. van den Brand, C. Van Den Broeck, D. C. Vander-Hyde, M. van der Sluys, A. Van de Walle, J. van Dongen, K. Vandra, H. van Haevermaet, J. V. van Heijningen, P. Van Hove, M. VanKeuren, J. Vanosky, M. H. P. M. van Putten, Z. van Ranst, N. van Remortel, M. Vardaro, A. F. Vargas, J. J. Varghese, V. Varma, A. Vecchio, G. Vedovato, J. Veitch, P. J. Veitch, S. Venikoudis, J. Venneberg, P. Verdier, D. Verkindt, B. Verma, P. Verma, Y. Verma, S. M. Vermeulen, F. Vetrano, A. Veutro, A. M. Vibhute, A. Vicer\'e, S. Vidyant, A. D. Viets, A. Vijaykumar, A. Vilkha, V. Villa-Ortega, E. T. Vincent, J. -Y. Vinet, S. Viret, A. Virtuoso, S. Vitale, A. Vives, H. Vocca, D. Voigt, E. R. G. von Reis, J. S. A. von Wrangel, S. P. Vyatchanin, L. E. Wade, M. Wade, K. J. Wagner, A. Wajid, M. Walker, G. S. Wallace, L. Wallace, H. Wang, J. Z. Wang, W. H. Wang, Z. Wang, G. Waratkar, J. Warner, M. Was, T. Washimi, N. Y. Washington, D. Watarai, K. E. Wayt, B. R. Weaver, B. Weaver, C. R. Weaving, S. A. Webster, M. Weinert, A. J. Weinstein, R. Weiss, F. Wellmann, L. Wen, P. We{\ss}els, K. Wette, J. T. Whelan, B. F. Whiting, C. Whittle, J. B. Wildberger, O. S. Wilk, D. Wilken, A. T. Wilkin, D. J. Willadsen, K. Willetts, D. Williams, M. J. Williams, N. S. Williams, J. L. Willis, B. Willke, M. Wils, J. Winterflood, C. C. Wipf, G. Woan, J. Woehler, J. K. Wofford, N. E. Wolfe, H. T. Wong, H. W. Y. Wong, I. C. F. Wong, J. L. Wright, M. Wright, C. Wu, D. S. Wu, H. Wu, E. Wuchner, D. M. Wysocki, V. A. Xu, Y. Xu, N. Yadav, H. Yamamoto, K. Yamamoto, T. S. Yamamoto, T. Yamamoto, S. Yamamura, R. Yamazaki, S. Yan, T. Yan, F. W. Yang, F. Yang, K. Z. Yang, Y. Yang, Z. Yarbrough, H. Yasui, S. -W. Yeh, A. B. Yelikar, X. Yin, J. Yokoyama, T. Yokozawa, J. Yoo, H. Yu, S. Yuan, H. Yuzurihara, A. Zadro\.zny, M. Zanolin, M. Zeeshan, T. Zelenova, J. -P. Zendri, M. Zeoli, M. Zerrad, M. Zevin, A. C. Zhang, L. Zhang, R. Zhang, T. Zhang, Y. Zhang, C. Zhao, Yue Zhao, Yuhang Zhao, Y. Zheng, H. Zhong, R. Zhou, X. -J. Zhu, Z. -H. Zhu, A. B. Zimmerman, M. E. Zucker, J. Zweizig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multipolar Electromagnetic Emission of Newborn Magnetar</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09251v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is generally recognized that the electromagnetic multipolar emission from magnetars can be used to explain radiation from Soft Gamma Repeaters (SGRs) or Anomalous X-ray Pulsars (AXPs), but they have little impact on the spindown of magnetars. We here present a comprehensive analytical solution for the neutron star multipolar electromagnetic fields and their associated expected luminosities. We find that for newborn millisecond magnetars, the spin-down luminosity from higher multipolar components can match or even exceed that from the dipole component. Such high-intensity radiation will undoubtedly affect related astrophysical phenomena at the birth of a magnetar. We show that the spin-down luminosity from multipoles can well explain the majority of Gamma-Ray Bursts (GRBs) afterglows, from the plateau starting at several hundred seconds till the normal decay phase lasting for many years. The fitted magnetar parameters for GRB afterglows are all typical values, with spins in the millisecond range and magnetic field strengths in the order of $10^{14} - 10^{15}$ Gauss. Our results in turn, provide support for the hypothesis that GRBs originate from the birth of magnetars with a few millisecond period, thus deepening our understanding of the complex magnetic field structure and the equation of state of magnetars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09251v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Wang, Rahim Moradi, Liang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AT2018fyk: Candidate Tidal Disruption Event by a (Super)massive Black Hole Binary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00894v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The tidal disruption event (TDE) AT2018fyk has unusual X-ray, UV, and optical light curves that decay over the first $\sim$600d, rebrighten, and decay again around 1200d. We explain this behavior as a one-off TDE associated with a massive black hole (BH) \emph{binary}. The sharp drop-offs from $t^{-5/3}$ power laws at around 600d naturally arise when one BH interrupts the debris fallback onto the other BH. The BH mass $M_\bullet$ derived from fitting X-ray spectra with a slim disk accretion model and, independently, from fitting the early UV/optical light curves, is smaller by two orders of magnitude than predicted from the $M_\bullet$--$\sigma_*$ host galaxy relation, suggesting that the debris is accreted onto the secondary, with fallback cut off by the primary. Furthermore, if the rebrightening were associated with the primary, it should occur around 5000d, not the observed 1200d. The secondary's mass and dimensionless spin is $M_{\bullet,{\rm s}}=2.7^{+0.5}_{-1.5} \times 10^5 M_\odot$ and $a_{\bullet,{\rm s}}&gt;0.3$ (X-ray spectral fitting), while the primary's mass is $M_{\bullet,{\rm p}}=10^{7.7\pm0.4}M_\odot$ ($M_\bullet$-$\sigma_*$ relation). An intermediate mass BH secondary is consistent with the observed UV/optical light curve decay, i.e., the secondary's outer accretion disk is too faint to produce a detectable emission floor. The time of the first accretion cutoff constrains the binary separation to be $(6.7\pm 1.2) \times 10^{-3}~{\rm pc}$. X-ray spectral fitting and timing analysis indicate that the hard X-rays arise from a corona above the secondary's disk. The early UV/optical emission, suggesting a super-Eddington phase for the secondary, possibly originates from shocks arising from debris circularization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00894v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad4da3</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>S. Wen, P. G. Jonker, A. J. Levan, D. Li, N. C. Stone, A. I. Zabludoff, Z. Cao, T. Wevers, D. R. Pasham, C. Lewin, E. Kara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The unluckiest star: A spectroscopically confirmed repeated partial tidal disruption event AT 2022dbl</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10895v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The unluckiest star orbits a supermassive black hole elliptically. Every time it reaches the pericenter, it shallowly enters the tidal radius and gets partially tidal disrupted, producing a series of flares. Confirmation of a repeated partial tidal disruption event (pTDE) requires not only evidence to rule out other types of transients, but also proof that only one star is involved, as TDEs from multiple stars can also produce similar flares. In this letter, we report the discovery of a repeated pTDE, AT 2022dbl. In a quiescent galaxy at $z=0.0284$, two separate optical/UV flares have been observed in 2022 and 2024, with no bright X-ray, radio or mid-infrared counterparts. Compared to the first flare, the second flare has a similar blackbody temperature of ~26,000 K, slightly lower peak luminosity, and slower rise and fall phases. Compared to the ZTF TDEs, their blackbody parameters and light curve shapes are all similar. The spectra taken during the second flare show a steeper continuum than the late-time spectra of the previous flare, consistent with a newly risen flare. More importantly, the possibility of two independent TDEs can be largely ruled out because the optical spectra taken around the peak of the two flares exhibit highly similar broad Balmer, N III and possible He II emission lines, especially the extreme ~4100{\AA} emission lines. This represents the first robust spectroscopic evidence for a repeated pTDE, which can soon be verified by observing the third flare, given its short orbital period.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10895v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/ad638e</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zheyu Lin, Ning Jiang, Tinggui Wang, Xu Kong, Dongyue Li, Han He, Yibo Wang, Jiazheng Zhu, Wentao Li, Ji-an Jiang, Avinash Singh, Rishabh Singh Teja, D. K. Sahu, Chichuan Jin, Keiichi Maeda, Shifeng Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining Wind-Driven Accretion Onto Gaia BH3 With Chandra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07602v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Gaia BH3 is the most massive known stellar-origin black hole in the Milky Way, with a mass $M_\bullet \approx 33 \, \rm M_\odot$. Detected from Gaia's astrometry, this black hole is in the mass range of those observed via gravitational waves, whose nature is still highly debated. Hosted in a binary system with a companion giant star that is too far away for Roche-lobe mass transfer, this black hole could nonetheless accrete at low levels due to wind-driven mass-loss from its companion star, thus accreting in advection-dominated accretion flow, or ADAF, mode. Using stellar wind models, we constrain its Eddington ratio in the range $10^{-9} &lt; f_{\rm Edd} &lt; 10^{-7}$, corresponding to radiative efficiencies $5\times10^{-5} &lt; \epsilon &lt; 10^{-3}$, compatible with radiatively inefficient accretion modes. Chandra ACIS-S observed this object and obtained the most sensitive upper bound of its [2-10] keV flux: $F_X &lt; 3.25 \times 10^{-15} \, \rm erg \, s^{-1} \, cm^{-2}$ at $90\%$ confidence level corresponding to $L_{[2-10]}&lt; 2.10 \times 10^{29} \, \rm erg \, s^{-1}$. Using ADAF emission models, we constrained its accretion rate to $f_{\rm Edd}&lt; 4.91 \times 10^{-7}$ at the apastron, in agreement with our theoretical estimate. At the periastron, we expect fluxes $\sim 50$ times larger. Because of the inferred low rates, accretion did not significantly contribute to black hole growth over the system's lifetime. Detecting the electromagnetic emission from Gaia BH3 will be fundamental to informing stellar wind and accretion disk models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07602v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nico Cappelluti, Fabio Pacucci, G\"unther Hasinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quiescent black hole X-ray binaries as multi-messenger sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11981v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The origin of Galactic cosmic rays (CRs) is unknown even though they have traditionally been connected to supernovae based on energetic arguments. In the past decades, Galactic black holes in X-ray binaries (BHXBs) have been proposed as candidate sources of CRs, which revises the CR paradigm. BHXBs launch two relativistic jets during their outbursts, but recent observations suggested that these jets may be launched even during quiescence. A0620-00 is a well-studied object that shows indications of jet emission. We study the simultaneous radio-to-X-ray spectrum of this source that was detected while the source was in quiescence to better constrain the jet dynamics. Because most BHXBs spend their lifetimes in quiescence (qBHXBs), we used the jet dynamics of A0620-00 to study a population of $10^5$ such sources distributed throughout the Galactic disc, and a further 104 sources that are located in the boxy bulge around the Galactic centre. While the contribution to the CR spectrum is suppressed, we find that the cumulative intrinsic emission of qBHXBs from both the boxy bulge and from the Galactic disc adds to the diffuse emission that various facilities detected from radio to TeV gamma rays. We examined the contribution of qBHXBs to the Galactic diffuse emission and investigated the possibility of SKA, INTEGRAL, and CTAO to detect individual sources in the future. Finally, we compare the predicted neutrino flux to the recently presented Galactic diffuse neutrino emission by IceCube.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11981v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitrios Kantzas, Francesca Calore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fragmention in Gravitationally-Unstable Collapsar Disks and Sub-Solar Neutron Star Mergers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07955v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Although stable neutron stars (NS) can in principle exist down to masses Mns ~ 0.1Msun, standard models of stellar core-collapse predict a robust lower limit Mns &gt;~ 1.2Msun, roughly commensurate with the Chandrasekhar mass Mch of the progenitor's iron core (electron fraction Ye ~ 0.5). However, this limit may be circumvented in sufficiently dense neutron-rich environments (Ye &lt;&lt; 0.5) for which Mch ~ Ye^2 is reduced to &lt; Msun. Such physical conditions could arise in the black hole accretion disks formed from the collapse of rapidly-rotating stars ("collapsars"), as a result of gravitational instabilities and cooling-induced fragmentation, similar to models for planet formation in protostellar disks. We confirm that the conditions to form sub-solar mass NS (ssNS) may be marginally satisfied in the outer regions of massive neutrino-cooled collapsar disks. If the disk fragments into multiple ssNS, their subsequent coalescence offers a channel for precipitating sub-solar mass LIGO/Virgo gravitational-wave mergers that does not implicate primordial black holes. The model makes several additional predictions: (1) ~Hz frequency Doppler modulation of the ssNS-merger gravitational wave signals due to the binary's orbital motion in the disk; (2) at least one additional gravitational wave event (coincident within &lt;~ hours), from the coalescence of the ssNS-merger remnant(s) with the central black hole; (3) an associated gamma-ray burst and supernova counterpart, the latter boosted in energy and enriched with r-process elements from the NS merger(s) embedded within the exploding stellar envelope ("kilonovae inside a supernova").</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07955v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brian D. Metzger, Lam Hui, Matteo Cantiello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irradiation effect and binary radio pulsars with giant companions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17178v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Pulsars are neutron stars that rotate rapidly. Most of the pulsars in binary systems tend to spin faster than those in isolation. According to binary evolution theory, radio pulsars in binary systems can have various types of companion stars. However, binary radio pulsars with giant stars, helium stars, and black holes as companions are lacking so far. We aim to investigate the possible parameter space of binary radio pulsars with giant companions. We used the MESA stellar evolution code to consider the effect of irradiation in binary evolution and evolved a series of binary models. We present the potential physical properties of binary radio pulsars with giant star companions in the framework of the classical recycling scenario and the irradiation model. We found that the parameter space of binary radio pulsars with giant companions can be greatly expanded by the effect of irradiation. Moreover, when irradiation is strong enough, submillisecond pulsars might be accompanied by giant companion stars. We also demonstrate a correlation between the timescale of the binary system as a low-mass X-ray binary and the irradiation efficiency. The birthrate problem between millisecond pulsars and low-mass X-ray binaries might not be resolved by the irradiation effect. A more detailed binary population synthesis is necessary. Our findings may offer guidance for observers that wish to locate binary radio pulsars with giant companions or submillisecond pulsars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17178v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunyi Lan, Xiangcun Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical relativity surrogate models for exotic compact objects: the case of head-on mergers of equal-mass Proca stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01395v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present several high-accuracy surrogate models for gravitational-wave signals from equal-mass head-on mergers of Proca stars, computed through the Newman-Penrose scalar $\psi_4$. We also discuss the current state of the model extensions to mergers of Proca stars with different masses, and the particular challenges that these present. The models are divided in two main categories: two-stage and monolithic. In the two-stage models, a dimensional reduction algorithm is applied to embed the data in a reduced feature space, which is then interpolated in terms of the physical parameters. For the monolithic models, a single neural network is trained to predict the waveform from the input physical parameter. Our model displays mismatches below $10^{-3}$ with respect to the original numerical waveforms. Finally, we demonstrate the usage of our model in full Bayesian parameter inference through the accurate recovery of numerical relativity signals injected in zero-noise, together with the analysis of GW190521. For the latter, we observe excellent agreement with existing results that make use of full numerical relativity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01395v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.024004</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 110 (2024) 2, 024004</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Raimon Luna, Miquel Llorens-Monteagudo, Ana Lorenzo-Medina, Juan Calder\'on Bustillo, Nicolas Sanchis-Gual, Alejandro Torres-Forn\'e, Jos\'e A. Font, Carlos A. R. Herdeiro, Eugen Radu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasinormal Modes in Modified Gravity using Physics-Informed Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11583v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we apply a novel approach based on physics-informed neural networks to the computation of quasinormal modes of black hole solutions in modified gravity. In particular, we focus on the case of Einstein-scalar-Gauss-Bonnet theory, with several choices of the coupling function between the scalar field and the Gauss-Bonnet invariant. This type of calculation introduces a number of challenges with respect to the case of General Relativity, mainly due to the extra complexity of the perturbation equations and to the fact that the background solution is known only numerically. The solution of these perturbation equations typically requires sophisticated numerical techniques that are not easy to develop in computational codes. We show that physics-informed neural networks have an accuracy which is comparable to traditional numerical methods in the case of numerical backgrounds, while being very simple to implement. Additionally, the use of GPU parallelization is straightforward thanks to the use of standard machine learning environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11583v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.124064</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 109 (2024) 12, 124064</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Raimon Luna, Daniela D. Doneva, Jos\'e A. Font, Jr-Hua Lien, Stoytcho S. Yazadjiev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Driven Inspirals of Binaries Connected by Cosmic Strings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01758v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider gravitational waves from a pair of monopoles or black holes that are moving non-relativistically and are connected by a cosmic string. Shortly after the binary's formation, the connecting string straightens due the direct coupling of its motion to gravitational radiation. Afterwards, the motion of the binary can be well-approximated by a non-relativistic motion of its components that have an additional constant mutual attraction force due to the tension of the straight string that connects them. The orbit shrinks due to the gravitational radiation backreacting on the binary's components. We find that if the binary's semimajor axis $a\gg \sqrt{R_1 R_2/{\mu}}$, its eccentricity grows on the inspiral's timescale; here $R_1$ and $R_2$ are the gravitational radii of the binary components, and $\mu$ is the dimensionless tension of the string. When the eccentricity is high, it approaches unity super-exponentially. If the binary's components are monopole-antimonopole pair, this leads to the physical collision that would likely destroy the string and annihilate the monopoles when the semimajor axis is still many orders of magnitude greater than the string thickness. If the binary's components are black holes, then the eccentricity reaches its peak when $a\sim \sqrt{R_1 R_2/\mu}$, and then decays according to the standard Peter's formula. The black-hole spins initially become locked to the orbital motion, but then lag behind as the inspiral proceeds. We estimate the string-tension-induced dimensionless spins just prior to the merger and find them to be $\sim\mu^{3/8}\ll 1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01758v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.024074</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 024074 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed Sheta, Yuri Levin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isospectrality in Effective Field Theory Extensions of General Relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12080v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Two universal predictions of general relativity are the propagation of gravitational waves of large momentum along null geodesics and the isospectrality of quasinormal modes in many families of black holes. In extensions of general relativity, these properties are typically lost: quasinormal modes are no longer isospectral and gravitational wave propagation is no longer geodesic and it exhibits birefringence -- polarization-dependent speed. We study these effects in an effective-field-theory extension of general relativity with up to eight-derivative terms and show that there is a unique Lagrangian that has a non-birefringent dispersion relation for gravitational waves and isospectral quasinormal modes in the eikonal limit. We argue that both properties are related through a generalized correspondence between eikonal quasinormal modes and unstable photon-sphere orbits. These properties define a special class of theories that we denote as isospectral effective field theories. We note that the lowest-order isospectral correction to general relativity coincides with the quartic-curvature correction arising from type II string theory, suggesting that isospectrality might be a key feature of quantum gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12080v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo A. Cano, Marina David</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Communicating the gravitational-wave discoveries of the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18638v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA (LVK) Collaboration has made breakthrough discoveries in gravitational-wave astronomy, a new field of astronomy that provides a different means of observing our Universe. Gravitational-wave discoveries are possible thanks to the work of thousands of people from across the globe working together. In this article, we discuss the range of engagement activities used to communicate LVK gravitational-wave discoveries and the stories of the people behind the science using the activities surrounding the release of the third Gravitational Wave Transient Catalog as a case study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18638v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannah Middleton, Christopher P L Berry, Nicolas Arnaud, David Blair, Jacqueline Bondell, Nicolas Bonne, Debarati Chatterjee, Sylvain Chaty, Storm Colloms, Lynn Cominsky, Livia Conti, Isabel Cordero-Carri\'on, Robert Coyne, Zoheyr Doctor, Andreas Freise, Aaron Geller, Jen Gupta, Daniel Holz, William Katzman, David Keitel, Joey Shapiro Key, Nutsinee Kijbunchoo, Carl Knox, Coleman Krawczyk, Ryan N Lang, Shane L Larson, Chris North, Sascha Rieger, Aurore Simonnet, Andrew Spencer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GERry: A Code to Optimise the Hunt for the Electromagnetic Counter-parts to Gravitational Wave Events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18642v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The search for the electromagnetic counterparts to gravitational wave (GW) events has been rapidly gathering pace in recent years thanks to the increasing number and capabilities of both gravitational wave detectors and wide field survey telescopes. Difficulties remain, however, in detecting these counterparts due to their inherent scarcity, faintness and rapidly evolving nature. To find these counterparts, it is important that one optimises the observing strategy for their recovery. This can be difficult due to the large number of potential variables at play. Such follow-up campaigns are also capable of detecting hundreds or potentially thousands of unrelated transients, particularly for GW events with poor localisation. Even if the observations are capable of detecting a counterpart, finding it among the numerous contaminants can prove challenging. Here we present the Gravitational wave Electromagnetic RecovRY code (GERry) to perform detailed analysis and survey-agnostic quantification of observing campaigns attempting to recover electromagnetic counterparts. GERry considers the campaign's spatial, temporal and wavelength coverage, in addition to Galactic extinction and the expected counterpart light curve evolution from the GW 3D localisation volume. It returns quantified statistics that can be used to: determine the probability of having detected the counterpart, identify the most promising sources, and assess and refine strategy. Here we demonstrate the code to look at the performance and parameter space probed by current and upcoming wide-field surveys such as GOTO &amp; VRO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18642v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David O'Neill, Joseph Lyman, Kendall Ackley, Danny Steeghs, Duncan Galloway, Vik Dhillon, Paul O'Brien, Gavin Ramsay, Kanthanakorn Noysena, Rubina Kotak, Rene Breton, Laura Nuttall, Enric Pall\'e, Don Pollacco, Krzysztof Ulaczyk, Martin Dyer, Felipe Jim\'enez-Ibarra, Tom Killestein, Amit Kumar, Lisa Kelsey, Ben Godson, Dan Jarvis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
