<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.HE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.HE</link>
    <description>astro-ph.HE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.HE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 04:00:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of light-mass fermionic dark matter on the equilibrium and stability of white dwarfs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10002v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: White dwarfs (WDs) can be used as laboratories to test strong gravity and high-density regimes, once their equation of state is not so uncertain as the one of neutron stars. This makes them also a useful tool to constrain dark-matter models. In this work, we study dark matter white dwarfs (DMWD) composed of white dwarf matter admixed with fermionic dark matter in a two-fluid general relativistic framework. Dark matter particles are considered to have masses between $0.1-10$ GeV. The equilibrium configurations and stability are derived, showing that the DMWD can be more compact, with masses around 1.3 $M\odot$ and radii around 500 km. The increasing compactness leads to changes in the fundamental modes of radial oscillations ($\sim20\%$ for 0.1 GeV DM), which produce detectable shifts in GW frequencies. The interplay between dark matter and normal matter thus provides a compelling avenue for interpreting deviations in observed WD properties and for placing constraints on DM characteristics through astrophysical observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10002v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. A. Carvalho, J. D. V. Arba\~nil, J. G. Coelho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can stellar physics explain GW231123?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10088v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The gravitational wave event GW231123 detected by the LIGO interferometers during their fourth observing run features two black holes with source-frame masses of $137^{+22}_{-17} M_\odot$ and $103^{+20}_{-52} M_\odot $ -- well within or above the pair-instability black hole mass gap predicted by standard stellar evolution theory. Both black holes are also inferred to be rapidly spinning ($\chi_1 \simeq 0.9$, $\chi_2 \simeq 0.8$). The primary object in GW231123 is the heaviest stellar mass black hole detected to date, which, together with its extreme rotation, raises questions about its astrophysical origin. Accounting for the unusually large spin of $\sim 0.9$ with hierarchical mergers requires some degree of fine tuning. We investigate whether such a massive, highly spinning object could plausibly form from the collapse of a single rotating massive star. We simulate stars with an initial core mass of $160 \rm M_\odot$ -- sufficient to produce BH masses at the upper edge of the 90% credible interval for $m_1$ in GW231123 -- across a range of rotation rates and $^{12}\mathrm{C}(\alpha,\gamma)^{16}\mathrm{O}$ reaction rates. We find that: (i) rotation shifts the pair-instability mass gap to higher masses, introducing a significant ingredient that correlates masses and spins in gravitational wave predictions; and (ii) highly spinning BHs with masses $\gtrsim 150 \rm M_\odot$ can form above the mass gap, implying that stellar evolution alone is sufficient to explain GW231123. Our results suggest that the primary object of GW231123 may be the first directly observed black hole that formed via direct core collapse following the photodisintegration instability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10088v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Djuna Croon, Jeremy Sakstein, Davide Gerosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The X-ray Source Population of the Metal-Rich Globular Cluster NGC 6528</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10105v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the first study of the X-ray sources in one of the most metal-rich globular clusters in the Galaxy, NGC 6528. Using relatively deep (66 ksec) archival imaging from the Chandra X-ray Observatory, we identify 18 sources within the half-light radius of the cluster, all in the range $L_X \sim 10^{31}$-$10^{32}$erg s$^{-1}$ (0.5-7 keV). By combining these data with photometry from the Hubble Space Telescope and other sources, we classify the X-ray sources as a likely mix of cataclysmic variables and active binaries, though one or more of the brighter objects could be a quiescent low-mass X-ray binary. For this cluster, it appears that the X-ray binary-enhancing effects of high metallicity are outweighed by the cluster's advanced dynamical evolution, leading to a relatively modest X-ray source population.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10105v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernard Leal, Kwangmin Oh, Jay Strader, Steve E. Zepf, Kristen Dage, S. Kim, C. Y. Hui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A multi-wavelength view of the multi-messenger sources NGC 1068 and PKS 1502+1061</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-messenger astronomy offers a powerful approach to studying high-energy radiative processes in astrophysical sources. A notable example was seen in 2017, when the IceCube Neutrino Observatory detected a high-energy neutrino event that was found to coincide with a gamma-ray flare from a blazar. Since then, numerous multi-messenger studies combining neutrino and photon data have been conducted, yet the origin of neutrinos from active galactic nuclei (AGN) remains uncertain. In this work, we present the results of an X-ray observing program targeting two AGNs, NGC 1068 and PKS 1502+106. The multi-wavelength dataset includes new observations from NICER and NuSTAR from the observing proposal along with gamma-ray data collected using Fermi-LAT, and one archival observation from Chandra. Additionally, we derive the neutrino fluxes for both AGNs using ten years of IceCube data and neutrino spectra predicted by theoretical models. These results demonstrate the value of combining multi-messenger data in building and constraining theoretical models. They also highlight the importance of testing model predictions against observational data to refine measurements of both the neutrino flux and spectral shape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10194v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Desai, Stefano Marchesi, Justin Vandenbroucke, Indrani Pal, Ke Fang, Dieter Hartmann, Regina Caputo, Marco Ajello, Jessie Thwaites, Kavic R Kumar, Sam Hori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Southern-sky MWA Rapid Two-metre (SMART) pulsar survey -- III. A census of millisecond pulsars at 154 MHz</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10330v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Observations of millisecond pulsars (MSPs) at low radio frequencies play an important role in understanding the Galactic pulsar population and characterising both their emission properties and the effects of the ionised interstellar medium on the received signals. To date, only a relatively small fraction of the known MSP population has been detected at frequencies below 300 MHz, and nearly all previous MSP studies at these frequencies have been conducted with northern telescopes. We present a census of MSPs in the SMART pulsar survey, covering declinations south of +30 deg at a centre frequency of 154 MHz. We detected 40 MSPs, with 11 being the first published detections below 300 MHz. For each detection, we provide coherently-dedispersed full-polarimetric integrated pulse profiles and mean flux densities. We measured significant Faraday rotation measures (RMs) for 25 MSPs, and identified apparent phase-dependent RM variations for three MSPs. Comparison with published profiles at other frequencies supports previous studies suggesting that the pulse component separations of MSPs vary negligibly over a wide frequency range due to their compact magnetospheres. We observe that integrated pulse profiles tend to be more polarised at low frequencies, consistent with depolarisation due to superposed orthogonal polarisation modes. The results of this census will be a valuable resource for planning future MSP monitoring projects at low frequencies, and will also help to improve survey simulations to forecast the detectable MSP population with the SKA-Low.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10330v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. P. Lee, N. D. R. Bhat, B. W. Meyers, S. J. McSweeney, W. van Straten, C. M. Tan, M. Xue, N. A. Swainston, S. M. Ord, G. Sleap, S. E. Tremblay, A. Williams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmark of the Fe XXV R ratio in photoionized plasma during eclipse of Centaurus X-3 with XRISM/Resolve</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10441v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The R ratio is a useful diagnostic of the X-ray emitting astrophysical plasmas defined as the intensity ratio of the forbidden over the inter-combination lines in the K$\alpha$ line complex of He-like ions. The value is altered by excitation processes (electron impact or UV photoexcitation) from the metastable upper level of the forbidden line, thereby constraining the electron density or UV field intensity. The diagnostic has been applied mostly in electron density constraints in collisionally ionized plasmas using low-Z elements as was originally proposed for the Sun (Gabriel &amp; Jordan (1969a, MNRAS, 145, 241)), but it can also be used in photoionized plasmas. To make use of this diagnostic, we need to know its value in the limit of no excitation of metastables (R$_0$), which depends on the element, how the plasmas are formed, how the lines are propagated, and the spectral resolution affecting line blending principally with satellite lines from Li-like ions. We benchmark R$_0$ for photoionized plasmas by comparing calculations using radiative transfer codes and observation data taken with the Resolve X-ray microcalorimter onboard XRISM. We use the Fe XXV He$\alpha$ line complex of the photo-ionized plasma in Centaurus X-3 observed during eclipse, in which the plasma is expected to be in the limit of no metastable excitation. The measured R$ = 0.65 \pm 0.08$ is consistent with the value calculated using xstar for the plasma parameters derived from other line ratios of the spectrum. We conclude that the R ratio diagnostic can be used for high-$Z$ elements such as Fe in photoionized plasmas, which has wide applications in plasmas around compact objects at various scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10441v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuto Mochizuki, Masahiro Tsujimoto, Maurice A. Leutenegger, Liyi Gu, Ralf Ballhausen, Ehud Behar, Paul A. Draghis, Natalie Hell, Pragati Pradhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra-luminous X-ray pulsars as sources of TeV neutrinos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10487v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explored the expected properties of the neutrino emission from accreting neutron stars in X-ray binaries using numerical simulations. The simulations are based on a model in which neutrinos are produced by the decay of charged pions and kaons, generated in inelastic collisions between protons accelerated up to TeV energies in the magnetosphere of a magnetized (B~1E12 G) neutron star and protons of the accretion disc. Our results show that this process can produce strong neutrino emission up to a few tens of TeV when the X-ray luminosity is above ~1E39 erg/s, as in ultra-luminous X-ray (ULX) pulsars. We show that neutrinos from a transient Galactic ULX pulsar with L_x ~ 5E39 erg/s can be detected with kilometre-scale detectors such as IceCube if the source is within about 3-4 kpc. We also derived an upper limit on the neutrino flux from the Galactic ULX pulsar Swift J0243.6+6124 using IceCube data, a result that has not been previously reported. Our findings establish a new benchmark for future astrophysical neutrino observations, critical for interpreting data from current and upcoming instruments with significantly improved sensitivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10487v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Ducci, E. Perinati, P. Romano, S. Vercellone, M. Niko{\l}ajuk, A. Santangelo, M. Sasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracing the Physical Lineage of GRB 211211A: Population Constraints on NS-WD Merger Gamma-Ray Bursts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10551v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The peculiar long gamma-ray burst (GRB) event, GRB 211211A, is known for it is association with a kilonova feature. Whereas most long GRBs are thought to originate in the core collapse of massive stars, the presence of kilonova suggests GRB 211211A was instead produced by a merger of a compact object binary. Building on the interpretation put forward by \citet{Yang2022Natur.612..232Y}--who argue that GRB 211211A was powered by a massive white-dwarf + neutron-star (WD-NS) merger--we adopt this WD-NS scenario as our observationally supported starting point. If the burst truly originates from that channel, its rarity must mirror the formation and merger rate of WD-NS binaries--a rate still largely unexplored in conventional massive-binary population studies. In this letter, we present a qualitative analysis based on binary evolution physics in order to understand the fraction of GRB 211211A in short GRBs (NS-WD/NS-NS fraction). Since the progenitors of massive WD-NS binaries occupy the initial mass function-preferred regime, where the zero-age main-sequence mass range of the assumed WD mass range (1.2-1.4$\,M_\odot$) is comparable to that of NSs, the NS-WD/NS-NS fraction emerging from our standard evolutionary path is expected to be $\sim$14--37\%, far higher than the observed fraction ($\sim5$\%). This discrepancy might imply a large, still-unidentified population of GRB 211211A-like events or an unusual origin of the NS-such as being hypernova-born or accretion-induced-collapse-born. Placing these results in a broader compact-binary context, implications for black-hole systems are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10551v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Tian Xu, Bin-Bin Zhang, Yun-Lang Guo, Xiang-Dong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on the progenitor and explosion of SN 2024ggi in harmony with pre-explosion detection and hydrodynamic simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10573v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Supernova (SN) 2024ggi is a nearby Type II SN discovered by ATLAS, showing early flash-ionization features. The pre-explosion images reveal a red supergiant (RSG) progenitor with an initial mass of 10-17 M$_\odot$. In the present work, we perform detailed hydrodynamic modeling to refine and put robust constraints on the progenitor and explosion parameters of SN 2024ggi. Among the progenitor models in our study, the pre-SN properties of the 11 M$_{\odot}$ match the pre-explosion detected progenitor well. However, we find it difficult to completely rule out the 10 M$_{\odot}$ and 12 M$_{\odot}$ models. Thus, we provide a constraint of 11$^{+1}_{-1}$ M$_{\odot}$ on the initial mass of the progenitor. To match the observed bolometric light curve and velocity evolution of SN 2024ggi, the favored model with an initial mass of 11 M$_{\odot}$ has a pre-SN radius of 800 R$_{\odot}$ and requires an explosion energy of [0.7-0.8]$\times$10$^{51}$ erg, nickel mass of $\lesssim$0.055 M$_{\odot}$, ejecta mass of 9.1 M$_{\odot}$, and an amount of $\sim$ 0.5 M$_{\odot}$ of steady-wind CSM extended up to $\sim1.2\times10^{14}$ cm resulting from an eruptive mass-loss rate of 1.0 M$_{\odot}$ yr$^{-1}$. We also incorporate the accelerated-wind CSM scenario which suggests a mass-loss rate of 1.0$\times10^{-2}$ M$_{\odot}$ yr$^{-1}$ and a CSM mass of $\sim$ 0.7 M$_{\odot}$ extended up to $\sim1.1\times10^{14}$ cm. This mass-loss rate falls within the range constrained observationally. Additionally, due to the constraint of 11$^{+1}_{-1}$ M$_{\odot}$ on the initial mass, the range of pre-SN radius and ejecta mass would be [690-900] R$_{\odot}$, and [8.2-9.6] M$_{\odot}$, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10573v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amar Aryan, Erin Higgins, Matt Nicholl, Ting-Wan Chen, Yu-Hsuan Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arecibo Wow! II: Revised Properties of the Wow! Signal from Archival Ohio SETI Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10657v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Wow! Signal, detected in 1977 by the Ohio State University SETI project, remains one of the most intriguing unexplained radio transients. The most recent significant revision of its properties took place in the late 1990s; however, further advances were limited by readily available data from this event. Here we retrieved and analyzed decades of previously unpublished Ohio SETI observations, enabling the most comprehensive re-evaluation of the properties of the Wow! Signal to date with modern methods. Our results reveal significant revisions to its parameters that may help explain why its source has been so difficult to identify. We refine its potential origin to two adjacent fields centered on the right ascension $\alpha=19^{\mathrm h}25^{\mathrm m}02^{\mathrm s} \pm 3^{\mathrm s}$ or $19^{\mathrm h}27^{\mathrm m}55^{\mathrm s} \pm 3^{\mathrm s}$, and the declination $\delta=-26^{\deg}57' \pm 20'$ (J2000), a location both narrower and slightly displaced from earlier estimates. We measure a higher peak flux density exceeding 250 Jy and a frequency of $1420.726 \pm 0.005$ MHz, implying a galactic source with a substantially higher radial velocity than previously assumed. Our analysis provides additional support for the hypothesis that the Wow! Signal most likely had an astrophysical origin rather than being attributed to radio interference. In particular, we confirm that small, cold HI clouds can produce narrowband signals similar to its detection, which might suggest a common origin. These findings provide the most precise constraints to date on the location, intensity, and frequency of the Wow! Signal and offer a new path to identify its origin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10657v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abel M\'endez, Kevin N. Ortiz Ceballos, Jorge I. Zuluaga, Kelby D. Palencia-Torres, Allison J. Smith, Alondra Cardona Rodr\'iguez, H\'ector Socas-Navarro, David Kipping, Hodari-Sadiki Hubbard-James, Mai Le, Alejandro Rinc\'on-Torres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the Impact of Higher-Order Phase Transitions in Binary Neutron-Star Mergers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10698v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we investigate quark deconfinement in neutrons stars and their mergers, focusing on the effects of higher orders for the phase transition between hadronic and quark matter. The different descriptions we use to describe matter microscopically contain varying particle degrees of freedom, including nucleons, hyperons, Delta baryons, and light and strange quarks. We use tabulated equations of state from the CompOSE database in which the quark deconfinement phase transition is described as being first-order, and then smooth it out by introducing a percolation, replacing the single first-order phase transition with two transitions of second or third order. We then perform binary neutron-star merger simulations using these new equations of st ate, focusing on groups of binaries with the same single-star mass, radius, and tidal deformability, but different equations of state. We go on to discuss differences in their evolution, and the ramifications for interpreting future gravitational wave observations and the potential to learn about dense matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10698v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Hammond, A. Clevinger, M. Albino, V. Dexheimer, S. Bernuzzi, C. Brown, W. Cook, B. Daszuta, J. Fields, E. Grundy, C. Provid\^encia, D. Radice, A. Steiner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Macroscopic approaches to rotating neutron stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10717</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10717v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The macroscopic model for a neutron star (NS) as a perfect liquid drop at equilibrium is extended to rotating systems with a small frequency $\omega $ within the effective-surface (ES) approach. The gradient surface terms of the NS energy density $\cal{E}(\rho)$ [Equation of State] are taken into account along with the volume ones at the leading order of the leptodermic parameter $a/R &lt;&lt; 1$, where $a$ is the ES crust thickness and $R$ is the mean NS radius. The macroscopic NS angular momentum at small frequencies $\omega$ is specified for calculations of the adiabatic moment of inertia (MI) within the Kerr metric coordinate approach in the outer Boyer-Lindquist and inner Hogan forms. The NS MI, $\Theta=\tilde{\Theta}/(1-\cal{G}_{t\varphi})$, was obtained in terms of the statistically averaged MI, $\tilde{\Theta}$, and its time and azimuthal-angle correlation, $\cal{G}_{t\varphi}$, as sums of the volume and surface components. The MI $\Theta$ depends dramatically on its effective radius $R$ because of strong gravitation and surface effects. We found the significant shift of the Schwarzschild radius due to the correlation term $\cal{G}_{t\varphi}$. With this term, the adiabaticity condition fails for the NS J0740+6620, with the mass about $M_\odot$ for a strong gravitation, in contrast to the NS J0030+0451 for smaller mass, and many other NSs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10717v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. A. Uleiev, A. G. Magner, S. P. Maydanyuk, A. Bonasera, H. Zheng, S. N. Fedotkin, A. I. Levon, U. V. Grygoriev, T. Depastas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signature of the explosion mechanism of Type-Ia SNe in substructures of the remnant: the case of Tycho's SNR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10752v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Type-Ia supernovae (SNe), or runaway thermonuclear explosions of white dwarfs (WDs), play a critical role in the chemical evolution of galaxies, and are important cosmological distance indicators due to their 'standardizable' lightcurves. Growing evidence, however, suggests greater diversity in their observed lightcurves (and spectra) than thought previously. This is usually attributed to a variety of WD explosion mechanisms and progenitor system properties, but a direct link between the explosion mechanisms and Type-Ia SN observables remains elusive. Here we present a novel approach to identify explosion mechanisms of Type-Ia SNe, by analyzing the sizes of small-scale turbulent substructures of different elements in their extended ejecta, i.e., in Supernova Remnants (SNRs). Our three-dimensional hydrodynamical models show that substructures in an SNR dominated by iron-group elements may have a typical size different from substructures dominated by intermediate mass elements (e.g., Si, S) in the same SNR. This size difference is governed by the explosion mechanism. Applying this approach to Tycho's SNR, we find that its observed structure is most consistent with the explosion of a sub-Chandrasekhar mass WD via the double-detonation mechanism. Extending this method to other well-characterized SNRs can let us connect the inferred explosion mechanism to the associated historical SNe, which often have spectra reconstructed through light echo observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10752v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soham Mandal, N\'uria Torres-Alb\`a, Carles Badenes, Shazrene Mohamed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radiative Signatures of Magnetic Reconnection: An Approach to Remote Probing of Reconnection Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10768v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic reconnection drives a wide range of astrophysical phenomena, including geomagnetic storms, solar flares, and activity in blazars. However, direct measurement of key reconnection observables remains challenging due to the remote and extreme nature of these environments. While high-energy particle showers observed on Earth are often attributed to reconnection, the underlying mechanisms are not fully understood, and clear diagnostic signatures are lacking. We present a theoretical, data-driven approach for identifying reconnection radiation signatures and enabling remote diagnostics of reconnection in astrophysical settings through radiation spectra. Using particle-in-cell (PIC) simulations of magnetic reconnection, we generate radiation spectra and establish connections between spectral features and the underlying reconnection dynamics. We develop a method to estimate the ratio of the reconnection electric field to the plasmoid magnetic field from spectral data. Analytic calculations show that other parameters can be extracted in the ultra-relativistic reconnection regime, such as the magnetic field or the current sheet width.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10768v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey K. Ermakov, Michael Bussmann, Alexander Debus, Richard Pausch, Ulrich Schramm, Ren\'e Widera, Klaus Steiniger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The explosion jets of the core-collapse supernova remnant Circinus X-1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10843v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose that the recently analyzed opposite rings in the Circinus X-1 (Cir X-1) core collapse supernova (CCSN) remnant resulted from a pair of opposite jets at the final phases of the jet-driven explosion process of the progenitor of Cir X-1. We point out the similarity of the rings in the Cir X-1 CCSN remnant to a ring in the Cygnus Loop CCSN remnant. While the X-ray binary system Cir X-1 actively launches jets, no such activity exists in the Cygnus Loop. In both CCSN remnants, we attribute the rings to jets that are part of the explosion process in the framework of the jittering jets explosion mechanism (JJEM). We also identify such a ring in the CCSN remnant 107.7-5.1, which we also attribute to exploding jets. We conduct three-dimensional hydrodynamical simulations of late jets inside an exploding massive stellar core, and demonstrate the feasibility of this scenario for ring formation. The Cir X-1 CCSN remnant has a large blowout, similar to that of the Cygnus Loop and to a large protrusion in the CCSN remnant G0.9+0.1 . Based on these similarities, we suggest that other exploding jets inflated the blowout of the Cir X-1 nebula, identical to an earlier claim on the formation of the blowout of the Cygnus Loop. We identify a point-symmetric structure in the Cir X-1 CCSN remnant, strengthening the JJEM. This study further demonstrates that the JJEM is a successful explosion mechanism to analyze CCSNe and CCSN remnants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10843v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noam Soker (Technion, Israel), Muhammad Akashi (Technion, Israel)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Foreground and internal free-free absorption in particle-accelerating colliding-wind binaries : Insights from the radio emission of WR 147</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10506v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Radio emission from massive binary systems is generally of composite nature, showing both a thermal emission component from the winds and a non-thermal component from relativistic electrons accelerated in the colliding-wind region. Understanding the processes ruling their radio spectrum is essential to investigate the role of these objects in the production of non-thermal particle populations in our galaxy. Our objective is to explore how the processes at work in particle-accelerating colliding-wind binaries (PACWBs) alter their spectral energy distribution, following a simple phenomenological description. We focus mainly on the role of free-free absorption (FFA) at low frequencies. Our intention is to use WR 147 as a test case, before tentatively extrapolating to a more generic behaviour. We processed recent Karl G. Jansky Very Large Array data, optimised for spectral analysis, combined with older measurements published in the literature at other frequencies. We analysed the radio spectrum considering both a more classical foreground free-free absorption (f-FFA) model and, for the first time, an internal free--free absorption (i-FFA) model. Our results show that the f-FFA model does not reproduce the spectral energy distribution of WR 147 at low frequencies. The i-FFA model is more efficient in providing a more complete description of the SED down to 610 MHz. This model is the only one to account for a change in the spectral index at low frequencies without any exponential drop in flux, as predicted by the f-FFA model. In addition, the upper limit at 150 MHz shows that two turnovers occur in the radio spectrum of WR 147, suggesting the effect of both i-FFA and f-FFA is seen in two regions of the spectrum. (abridged)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10506v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Tasseroul, M. De Becker, A. B Blanco, P. Benaglia, S. del Palacio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Spectrum from the Production of Dark Matter via the freeze-in Mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10665v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Since the first detection of gravitational waves by ground-based interferometers, it has emerged as a novel probe for exploring physics in the early universe. The particle nature of cold dark matter (DM) and its underlying production mechanisms remain long-standing unresolved issues in the field. Notably, if DM is generated through the freeze-in mechanism in the early universe, direct laboratory detection becomes extraordinarily challenging due to its extremely weak coupling with standard model particles. In this study, we calculate the graviton bremsstrahlung process involved in the freeze-in production of dark matter, deriving the gravitational wave spectra for both the conventional freeze-in mechanism and ultraviolet freeze-in scenarios. Our analysis reveals that these spectra exhibit distinct characteristics, though they fall beyond the detection limits of currently proposed gravitational wave experiments. However, advancements in high-frequency gravitational wave detection technologies in the future may offer a means to indirectly probe the ultraviolet freeze-in mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10665v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yonghua Wang, Wei Chao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Forgotten treasures in the HST/FOC UV imaging polarimetric archives of active galactic nuclei -- IV. 5 Orphaned AGNs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10709v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Faint Object Camera (FOC) onboard the Hubble Space Telescope (HST) acquired high-resolution, spatially resolved polarimetric images of nearby Active Galactic Nuclei (AGNs) in the near ultraviolet (near-UV) band. Among the 25 individual targets in the polarized archives, 8 had no published analysis until the beginning of this series of papers. We tackle the last 5 targets in the following. In this paper, we finalize the publication of near-UV imaging polarimetry of AGNs in the HST/FOC archives. We render available spatially resolved polarization maps of the [OIII] emission lines for Mrk 3 and Mrk 78, as well as near-UV continuum polarization maps for Mrk 3, NGC 3862, Cygnus A and 3C 109. We make use of the generalized reduction pipeline presented in the first paper in this series to homogeneously analyze the five remaining polarized observations of AGNs in the FOC archives. In Mrk 3 and Mrk 78, we find a polarization pattern in the narrow-line regions consistent with scattering from an obscured nucleus. For NGC 3862, we confirm marginal UV polarization parallel with the inner radio jet, related to synchrotron emission. In Cygnus A, we report spatially resolved centro-symmetric polarization patterns in both opposite outflows, highlighting the scattering origin of the polarized light. Finally, 3C 109 shows high nuclear polarization, consistent with AGN-dominated emission and parallel with the radio axis, but in tension with polarization arising from dichroic absorption invoked by previous authors. The imaging polarimetry obtained for the narrow-line region and the extended scattering medium surrounding the obscured AGNs is aligned with the predictions of the unified AGN model and demonstrates the power of spatially-resolved polarimetric observation to decipher the complex morphologies at work in AGNs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10709v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thibault Barnouin (Observatoire Astronomique de Strasbourg, Universit\'e de Strasbourg, France), Fr\'ed\'eric Marin (Observatoire Astronomique de Strasbourg, Universit\'e de Strasbourg, France), Enrique Lopez-Rodriguez (Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of South Carolina, USA, Kavli Institute for Particle Astrophysics and Cosmology, Stanford University, USA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Measurement of Supermassive Black Hole Masses: QPE Timing Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11078v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quasi-periodic eruptions (QPEs) are intense repeating soft X-ray bursts with recurrence times about a few hours to a few weeks from galactic nuclei. More and more analyses show that (at least a fraction of) QPEs are the result of collisions between a stellar mass object (SMO, a stellar mass black hole or a main sequence star) and an accretion disk around a supermassive black hole (SMBH) in galactic nuclei. Previous studies have shown the possibility of reconstructing the SMO trajectory from QPE timing data, consequently measuring the SMBH mass from tracing a single SMO. In this paper, we construct a comprehensive Bayesian framework for implementing the QPE timing method, explore the optimal QPE observation strategy for measuring SMBH masses, and forecast the measurement precision expected in the era of multi-target X-ray telescope, Chasing All Transients Constellation Hunters (CATCH). Simulations of CATCH observations of GSN 069 and eRO-QPE2 like QPEs confirm the possible applications of the QPE timing method in precise measurement of SMBH masses (and spins), especially in the lower mass end ($\lesssim 10^7 M_\odot$) where QPEs prevail and relevant dynamical timescales are reasonably short to be measured.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11078v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cong Zhou, Zhen Pan, Ning Jiang, Wen Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of stellar winds on the pair-instability supernova rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07959v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Very massive stars (VMSs, $M_{\star}$ $\geq$ 100 M$_{\odot}$) play a crucial role in several astrophysical processes. At low metallicity, they might collapse directly into black holes, or end their lives as pair-instability supernovae. Recent observational results set an upper limit of $0.7\,{}\mathrm{ yr}^{-1} \,{}\mathrm{ Gpc}^{-3}$ on the rate density of pair-instability supernovae in the nearby Universe. However, most theoretical models predict rates exceeding this limit. Here, we compute new VMS tracks with the MESA code, and use them to analyze the evolution of the (pulsational) pair-instability supernova rate density across cosmic time. We show that stellar wind models accounting for the transition between optically thin and thick winds yield a pair-instability supernova rate $\mathcal{R}_{\mathrm{PISN}}\sim{}0.1$ Gpc$^{-3}$ yr$^{-1}$ at redshift $z\sim{}0$, about two orders of magnitude lower than our previous models. We find that the main contribution to the pair-instability supernova rate comes from stars with metallicity $Z\sim{}0.001-0.002$. Stars with higher metallicities cannot enter the pair-instability supernova regime, even if their zero-age main sequence mass is up to 500 M$_\odot$. The main reason is that VMSs enter the regime for optically thick winds during the main sequence at metallicity as low as $Z\sim{4}\times{}10^{-4}$. This enhances the mass loss rate, quenching the growth of the He core and thus preventing the onset of pair-instability in later evolutionary stages. This result highlights the critical role of mass loss in shaping the final fate of very massive stars and the rate of pair-instability supernovae.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07959v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Simonato, Stefano Torniamenti, Michela Mapelli, Giuliano Iorio, Lumen Boco, Franca De Domenico-Langer, Cecilia Sgalletta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flavor Equilibration of Supernova Neutrinos: Exploring the Dynamics of Slow Modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11588v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Neutrinos experience collective flavor conversion in extreme astrophysical environments such as core-collapse supernovae (CCSNe). One manifestation of collective conversion is slow flavor conversion (SFC), which has recently attracted renewed interest owing to its ubiquity across different regions of the supernova environment. In this study, we systematically examine the evolution of kinematic decoherence in a dense neutrino gas undergoing SFC, considering lepton number asymmetries as large as $30\%$. Our findings show that the neutrino gas asymptotically evolves toward a generic state of coarse-grained flavor equilibration which is constrained by approximate lepton number conservation. The equilibration occurs within a few factors of the inverse vacuum oscillation frequency, $\omega^{-1}$, which corresponds to (anti)neutrinos reaching near flavor equipartition after a few kilometers for typical supernova neutrino energies. Notably, the quasi-steady state of the neutrino number densities can be quantitatively described by the neutrino-antineutrino number density ratio $n_{\bar{\nu}_e}/n_{\nu_e}$ alone. Such a simple estimation opens new opportunities for incorporating SFC into CCSN simulations, particularly in regions where SFC develops on scales much shorter than those of collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11588v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Padilla-Gay, Heng-Hao Chen, Sajad Abbar, Meng-Ru Wu, Zewei Xiong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EP241021a: A catastrophic collapse/merger of compact star binary leading to the formation of a remnant millisecond magnetar?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.12491v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Observations of fast X-ray transients (FXRTs) with the Einstein Probe have successfully led to the discovery of some unusual extragalactic optical transients. EP241021a is a newly discovered FXRT that was featured by a significant bump around ten days in both optical and X-ray bands. This timescale and the exceptionally high peak bolometric luminosity up to $\sim \rm 10^{44}erg~s^{-1}$ of the optical bump make it somewhat similar to fast blue optical transients, but still distinctive from them by its relatively red color. We then suggest that the multi-wavelength bump of EP241021a could represent an explosion-type transient, while the underlying power-law decaying component of the optical and X-ray emission as well as the total radio emission are produced by a moderately relativistic jet. By fitting the observed multi-wavelength light curves, it is found that the explosion ejecta that produce the thermal optical emission can have a mass of $\sim0.03~M_{\odot}$, an expanding velocity of $\sim0.25~c$, and an optical opacity of $\sim12~\rm cm^2g^{-1}$, which was continuously powered by a rapidly rotating and highly magnetized neutron star (NS; i.e., a magnetar). In addition to heating the explosion ejecta, the magnetar also provided the dominant contribution to the observed X-ray rebrightening through the non-thermal emission of its wind. These properties suggest that the explosion may result from a catastrophic collapse/merger of a compact star system, which led to the formation of a millisecond magnetar, and the possible progenitor could be an accreting white dwarf (WD) or a binary consisting of double WDs, double NSs, or a WD and an NS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12491v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guang-Lei Wu, Yun-Wei Yu, Liang-Duan Liu, Zi-Gao Dai, Wei-Hua Lei, Xue-Feng Wu, Dong Xu, Bing Zhang, Jin-Ping Zhu, Yuan-Chuan Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploration of features in the black hole mass spectrum inspired by non-parametric analyses of gravitational wave observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.05929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.05929v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Current gravitational-wave data reveal structures in the mass function of binary compact objects. Properly modelling and deciphering such structures is the ultimate goal of gravitational-wave population analysis: in this context, non-parametric models are a powerful tool to infer the distribution of black holes from gravitational waves without committing to any specific functional form. Here, we aim to quantitatively corroborate the findings of non-parametric methods with parametrised models incorporating the features found in such analyses. We propose two modifications of the currently favoured PowerLaw+Peak model, inspired by non-parametric studies, and use them to analyse the third Gravitational Wave Transient Catalogue. Our analysis marginally supports the existence of two distinct, differently redshift-evolving subpopulations in the black hole primary mass function, and suggests that, to date, we are still unable to robustly assess the shape of the mass ratio distribution for symmetric ($q&gt;0.7$) binaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.05929v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Rinaldi, Yajie Liang, Gabriele Demasi, Michela Mapelli, Walter Del Pozzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RADAR-Radio Afterglow Detection and AI-driven Response: A Federated Framework for Gravitational Wave Event Follow-Up</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14827v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The landmark detection of both gravitational waves (GWs) and electromagnetic (EM) radiation from the binary neutron star merger GW170817 has spurred efforts to streamline the follow-up of GW alerts in current and future observing runs of ground-based GW detectors. Within this context, the radio band of the EM spectrum presents unique challenges. Sensitive radio facilities capable of detecting the faint radio afterglow seen in GW170817, and with sufficient angular resolution, have small fields of view compared to typical GW localization areas. Additionally, theoretical models predict that the radio emission from binary neutron star mergers can evolve over weeks to years, necessitating long-term monitoring to probe the physics of the various post-merger ejecta components. These constraints, combined with limited radio observing resources, make the development of more coordinated follow-up strategies essential -- especially as the next generation of GW detectors promise a dramatic increase in detection rates. Here, we present RADAR, a framework designed to address these challenges by promoting community-driven information sharing, federated data analysis, and system resilience, while integrating AI methods for both GW signal identification and radio data aggregation. We show that it is possible to preserve data rights while sharing models that can help design and/or update follow-up strategies. We demonstrate our approach through a case study of GW170817, and discuss future directions for refinement and broader application.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14827v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Parth Patel, Alessandra Corsi, E. A. Huerta, Kara Merfeld, Victoria Tiki, Zilinghan Li, Tekin Bicer, Kyle Chard, Ryan Chard, Ian T. Foster, Maxime Gonthier, Valerie Hayot-Sasson, Hai Duc Nguyen, Haochen Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enabling Early Transient Discovery in LSST via Difference Imaging with DECam</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22156v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present SLIDE, a pipeline that enables transient discovery in data from the Vera C. Rubin Observatory's Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST), using archival images from the Dark Energy Camera (DECam) as templates for difference imaging. We apply this pipeline to the recently released Data Preview 1 (DP1; the first public release of Rubin commissioning data) and search for transients in the resulting difference images. The image subtraction, photometry extraction, and transient detection are all performed on the Rubin Science Platform. We demonstrate that SLIDE effectively extracts clean photometry by circumventing poor or missing LSST templates. This is especially useful for transient analysis in the early years of LSST, when template coverage will be largely incomplete or when templates may be contaminated by transients present at the time of acquisition. We present multiband light curves for a sample of known transients, along with new transient candidates identified through our search. Finally, we discuss the prospects of applying this pipeline during the main LSST survey.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22156v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yize Dong, Kaylee de Soto, V. Ashley Villar, Anya Nugent, Alex Gagliano, K. Azalee Bostroem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Signatures of Quasi-Periodic Eruptions: LISA Detection Prospects for RX J1301.9+2747</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07961v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One prominent model for quasi-periodic eruptions (QPEs) is that they originate from extreme mass-ratio inspirals (EMRIs) involving stellar-mass objects orbiting around massive black holes and colliding with their accretion disks. We compute the gravitational wave signals from such a model, demonstrating that orbiter-disk interactions result in small frequency shifts and high-frequency tails due to the excitation of non-discrete modes. Interestingly, we show that QPE RX J1301.9+2747 could be detectable by future space-based gravitational wave detectors, provided a moderate eccentricity around $0.25$ and a mass exceeding $35\,M_\odot$ for the orbiter. Moreover, based on this QPE model, we show that the signal-to-noise ratio of the gravitational wave signals from QPEs, if detectable, will be sufficiently high to distinguish such systems from vacuum EMRIs and shed light on the origin of QPEs and environments around massive black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07961v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leif Lui, Alejandro Torres-Orjuela, Rudrani Kar Chowdhury, Lixin Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
