<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.HE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.HE</link>
    <description>astro-ph.HE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.HE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 03:20:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Near-IR Search for Helium in the Superluminous Supernova SN 2024ahr</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01485v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a detailed study of SN 2024ahr, a hydrogen-poor superluminous supernova (SLSN-I), for which we determine a redshift of $z=0.0861$. SN 2024ahr has a peak absolute magnitude of $M_g\approx M_r\approx -21$ mag, rest-frame rise and decline times (50$\%$ of peak) of about 40 and 80 days, respectively, and typical spectroscopic evolution in the optical band. Similarly, modeling of the UV/optical light curves with a magnetar spin-down engine leads to typical parameters: an initial spin period of $\approx 3.3$ ms, a magnetic field strength of $\approx 6\times 10^{13}$ G, and an ejecta mass of $\approx 9.5$ M$_\odot$. Due to its relatively low redshift we obtained a high signal-to-noise ratio near-IR spectrum about 43 rest-frame days post-peak to search for the presence of helium. We do not detect any significant feature at the location of the He I $\,\lambda 2.058$ $\mu$m feature, and place a conservative upper limit of $\sim 0.05$ M$_\odot$ on the mass of helium in the outer ejecta. We detect broad features of Mg I $\,\lambda 1.575$ $\mu$m and a blend of Co II $\,\lambda 2.126$ $\mu$m and Mg II, $\lambda 2.136$ $\mu$m, which are typical of Type Ic SNe, but with higher velocities. Examining the sample of SLSNe-I with NIR spectroscopy, we find that, unlike SN 2024ahr, these events are generally peculiar. This highlights the need for a large sample of prototypical SLSNe-I with NIR spectroscopy to constrain the fraction of progenitors with helium (Ib-like) and without helium (Ic-like) at the time of the explosion, and hence the evolutionary path(s) leading to the rare outcome of SLSNe-I.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01485v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harsh Kumar, Edo Berger, Peter K. Blanchard, Sebastian Gomez, Daichi Hiramatsu, Moira Andrews, K. Azalee Bostroem, Yize Dong, Joseph Farah, Estefania Padilla Gonzalez, D. Andrew Howell, Curtis McCully, Darshana Mehta, Megan Newsome, Aravind P. Ravi, Giacomo Terreran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Line detections in photospheric radius expansion bursts from 4U 1820-303</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01488v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context: NICER (Neutron star Interior Composition ExploreR) is the instrument of choice for the spectral analysis of type I X-ray bursts, as it provides high throughput at X-ray CCD resolution, down to 0.3 keV. Aims: This study investigates whether the energies of absorption lines detected in photospheric radius expansion (PRE) bursts correlate with the inferred blackbody radius. Previous reports suggested such a correlation, attributed to a combination of weaker gravitational redshift and higher blueshifts in bursts with larger radii. Methods: The analysis reexamines four previously studied PRE bursts and examines eight additional bursts from 4U 1820-303, evidencing PRE. Spectral evolution is tracked on the shortest possible timescales (tenth of a second) adopting two parallel continuum descriptions to characterise the photospheric expansion and line evolution. Applying the accretion-enhanced model, maximum blackbody radii of up to $\sim$ 900 km are inferred, with peak bolometric luminosities exceeding the Eddington limit of an Helium accretor. Absorption lines are assessed for significance using Monte Carlo simulations, and spectral lines are characterised using the state-of-art plasma codes available within {\sc{spex}} with a phenomenological continuum. A thorough parameter search explores Doppler shifts to avoid local minima. Results: Several significant (&gt; 99.9%) absorption lines, including the previously reported 2.97 keV line, are detected. While no consistent correlation between line energies and blackbody radii is confirmed, bursts with larger radii exhibit up to four lines and the line strength is higher. The modelling suggests that the observed lines mostly originate from slightly redshifted (almost rest-frame) photo-/collisionally ionised gas in emission. For the burst with the largest PRE, a combination of photo-ionised plasma in both emission and absorption is preferred.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01488v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Barra, D. Barret, C. Pinto, T. Di Salvo, N. Weinberg, S. Guichandut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for continuous gravitational waves from known pulsars in the first part of the fourth LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA observing run</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01495v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Continuous gravitational waves (CWs) emission from neutron stars carries information about their internal structure and equation of state, and it can provide tests of General Relativity. We present a search for CWs from a set of 45 known pulsars in the first part of the fourth LIGO--Virgo--KAGRA observing run, known as O4a. We conducted a targeted search for each pulsar using three independent analysis methods considering the single-harmonic and the dual-harmonic emission models. We find no evidence of a CW signal in O4a data for both models and set upper limits on the signal amplitude and on the ellipticity, which quantifies the asymmetry in the neutron star mass distribution. For the single-harmonic emission model, 29 targets have the upper limit on the amplitude below the theoretical spin-down limit. The lowest upper limit on the amplitude is $6.4\!\times\!10^{-27}$ for the young energetic pulsar J0537-6910, while the lowest constraint on the ellipticity is $8.8\!\times\!10^{-9}$ for the bright nearby millisecond pulsar J0437-4715. Additionally, for a subset of 16 targets we performed a narrowband search that is more robust regarding the emission model, with no evidence of a signal. We also found no evidence of non-standard polarizations as predicted by the Brans-Dicke theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01495v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> The LIGO Scientific Collaboration,  the Virgo Collaboration,  the KAGRA Collaboration, A. G. Abac, R. Abbott, I. Abouelfettouh, F. Acernese, K. Ackley, S. Adhicary, N. Adhikari, R. X. Adhikari, V. K. Adkins, D. Agarwal, M. Agathos, M. Aghaei Abchouyeh, O. D. Aguiar, I. Aguilar, L. Aiello, A. Ain, P. Ajith, T. Akutsu, S. Albanesi, R. A. Alfaidi, A. Al-Jodah, C. All\'en\'e, A. Allocca, S. Al-Shammari, P. A. Altin, S. Alvarez-Lopez, A. Amato, L. Amez-Droz, A. Amorosi, C. Amra, A. Ananyeva, S. B. Anderson, W. G. Anderson, M. Andia, M. Ando, T. Andrade, N. Andres, M. Andr\'es-Carcasona, T. Andri\'c, J. Anglin, S. Ansoldi, J. M. Antelis, S. Antier, M. Aoumi, E. Z. Appavuravther, S. Appert, S. K. Apple, K. Arai, A. Araya, M. C. Araya, J. S. Areeda, L. Argianas, N. Aritomi, F. Armato, N. Arnaud, M. Arogeti, S. M. Aronson, G. Ashton, Y. Aso, M. Assiduo, S. Assis de Souza Melo, S. M. Aston, P. Astone, F. Attadio, F. Aubin, K. AultONeal, G. Avallone, S. Babak, F. Badaracco, C. Badger, S. Bae, S. Bagnasco, E. Bagui, J. G. Baier, L. Baiotti, R. Bajpai, T. Baka, M. Ball, G. Ballardin, S. W. Ballmer, S. Banagiri, B. Banerjee, D. Bankar, P. Baral, J. C. Barayoga, B. C. Barish, D. Barker, P. Barneo, F. Barone, B. Barr, L. Barsotti, M. Barsuglia, D. Barta, A. M. Bartoletti, M. A. Barton, I. Bartos, S. Basak, A. Basalaev, R. Bassiri, A. Basti, D. E. Bates, M. Bawaj, P. Baxi, J. C. Bayley, A. C. Baylor, P. A. Baynard II, M. Bazzan, V. M. Bedakihale, F. Beirnaert, M. Bejger, D. Belardinelli, A. S. Bell, V. Benedetto, W. Benoit, J. D. Bentley, M. Ben Yaala, S. Bera, M. Berbel, F. Bergamin, B. K. Berger, S. Bernuzzi, M. Beroiz, D. Bersanetti, A. Bertolini, J. Betzwieser, D. Beveridge, N. Bevins, R. Bhandare, U. Bhardwaj, R. Bhatt, D. Bhattacharjee, S. Bhaumik, S. Bhowmick, A. Bianchi, I. A. Bilenko, G. Billingsley, A. Binetti, S. Bini, O. Birnholtz, S. Biscoveanu, A. Bisht, M. Bitossi, M. -A. Bizouard, J. K. Blackburn, L. A. Blagg, C. D. Blair, D. G. Blair, F. Bobba, N. Bode, G. Boileau, M. Boldrini, G. N. Bolingbroke, A. Bolliand, L. D. Bonavena, R. Bondarescu, F. Bondu, E. Bonilla, M. S. Bonilla, A. Bonino, R. Bonnand, P. Booker, A. Borchers, V. Boschi, S. Bose, V. Bossilkov, V. Boudart, A. Boudon, A. Bozzi, C. Bradaschia, P. R. Brady, M. Braglia, A. Branch, M. Branchesi, J. Brandt, I. Braun, M. Breschi, T. Briant, A. Brillet, M. Brinkmann, P. Brockill, E. Brockmueller, A. F. Brooks, B. C. Brown, D. D. Brown, M. L. Brozzetti, S. Brunett, G. Bruno, R. Bruntz, J. Bryant, F. Bucci, J. Buchanan, O. Bulashenko, T. Bulik, H. J. Bulten, A. Buonanno, K. Burtnyk, R. Buscicchio, D. Buskulic, C. Buy, R. L. Byer, G. S. Cabourn Davies, G. Cabras, R. Cabrita, V. C\'aceres-Barbosa, L. Cadonati, G. Cagnoli, C. Cahillane, J. Calder\'on Bustillo, T. A. Callister, E. Calloni, J. B. Camp, M. Canepa, G. Caneva Santoro, K. C. Cannon, H. Cao, L. A. Capistran, E. Capocasa, E. Capote, G. Carapella, F. Carbognani, M. Carlassara, J. B. Carlin, M. Carpinelli, G. Carrillo, J. J. Carter, G. Carullo, J. Casanueva Diaz, C. Casentini, S. Y. Castro-Lucas, S. Caudill, M. Cavagli\`a, R. Cavalieri, G. Cella, P. Cerd\'a-Dur\'an, E. Cesarini, W. Chaibi, P. Chakraborty, S. Chalathadka Subrahmanya, J. C. L. Chan, M. Chan, K. Chandra, R. -J. Chang, S. Chao, E. L. Charlton, P. Charlton, E. Chassande-Mottin, C. Chatterjee, Debarati Chatterjee, Deep Chatterjee, M. Chaturvedi, S. Chaty, A. Chen, A. H. -Y. Chen, D. Chen, H. Chen, H. Y. Chen, J. Chen, K. H. Chen, Y. Chen, Yanbei Chen, Yitian Chen, H. P. Cheng, P. Chessa, H. T. Cheung, S. Y. Cheung, F. Chiadini, G. Chiarini, R. Chierici, A. Chincarini, M. L. Chiofalo, A. Chiummo, C. Chou, S. Choudhary, N. Christensen, S. S. Y. Chua, P. Chugh, G. Ciani, P. Ciecielag, M. Cie\'slar, M. Cifaldi, R. Ciolfi, F. Clara, J. A. Clark, J. Clarke, T. A. Clarke, P. Clearwater, S. Clesse, E. Coccia, E. Codazzo, P. -F. Cohadon, S. Colace, M. Colleoni, C. G. Collette, J. Collins, S. Colloms, A. Colombo, M. Colpi, C. M. Compton, G. Connolly, L. Conti, T. R. Corbitt, I. Cordero-Carri\'on, S. Corezzi, N. J. Cornish, A. Corsi, S. Cortese, C. A. Costa, R. Cottingham, M. W. Coughlin, A. Couineaux, J. -P. Coulon, S. T. Countryman, J. -F. Coupechoux, P. Couvares, D. M. Coward, M. J. Cowart, R. Coyne, K. Craig, R. Creed, J. D. E. Creighton, T. D. Creighton, P. Cremonese, A. W. Criswell, J. C. G. Crockett-Gray, S. Crook, R. Crouch, J. Csizmazia, J. R. Cudell, T. J. Cullen, A. Cumming, E. Cuoco, M. Cusinato, P. Dabadie, T. Dal Canton, S. Dall'Osso, S. Dal Pra, G. D\'alya, B. D'Angelo, S. Danilishin, S. D'Antonio, K. Danzmann, K. E. Darroch, L. P. Dartez, A. Dasgupta, S. Datta, V. Dattilo, A. Daumas, N. Davari, I. Dave, A. Davenport, M. Davier, T. F. Davies, D. Davis, L. Davis, M. C. Davis, P. J. Davis, M. Dax, J. De Bolle, M. Deenadayalan, J. Degallaix, M. De Laurentis, S. Del\'eglise, F. De Lillo, D. Dell'Aquila, W. Del Pozzo, F. De Marco, F. De Matteis, V. D'Emilio, N. Demos, T. Dent, A. Depasse, N. DePergola, R. De Pietri, R. De Rosa, C. De Rossi, R. DeSalvo, R. De Simone, A. Dhani, R. Diab, M. C. D\'iaz, M. Di Cesare, G. Dideron, N. A. Didio, T. Dietrich, L. Di Fiore, C. Di Fronzo, M. Di Giovanni, T. Di Girolamo, D. Diksha, A. Di Michele, J. Ding, S. Di Pace, I. Di Palma, F. Di Renzo,  Divyajyoti, A. Dmitriev, Z. Doctor, E. Dohmen, P. P. Doleva, D. Dominguez, L. D'Onofrio, F. Donovan, K. L. Dooley, T. Dooney, S. Doravari, O. Dorosh, M. Drago, J. C. Driggers, J. -G. Ducoin, L. Dunn, U. Dupletsa, D. D'Urso, H. Duval, P. -A. Duverne, S. E. Dwyer, C. Eassa, M. Ebersold, T. Eckhardt, G. Eddolls, B. Edelman, T. B. Edo, O. Edy, A. Effler, J. Eichholz, H. Einsle, M. Eisenmann, R. A. Eisenstein, A. Ejlli, R. M. Eleveld, M. Emma, K. Endo, A. J. Engl, E. Enloe, L. Errico, R. C. Essick, H. Estell\'es, D. Estevez, T. Etzel, M. Evans, T. Evstafyeva, B. E. Ewing, J. M. Ezquiaga, F. Fabrizi, F. Faedi, V. Fafone, S. Fairhurst, A. M. Farah, B. Farr, W. M. Farr, G. Favaro, M. Favata, M. Fays, M. Fazio, J. Feicht, M. M. Fejer, R. Felicetti, E. Fenyvesi, D. L. Ferguson, S. Ferraiuolo, I. Ferrante, T. A. Ferreira, F. Fidecaro, P. Figura, A. Fiori, I. Fiori, M. Fishbach, R. P. Fisher, R. Fittipaldi, V. Fiumara, R. Flaminio, S. M. Fleischer, L. S. Fleming, E. Floden, E. M. Foley, H. Fong, J. A. Font, B. Fornal, P. W. F. Forsyth, K. Franceschetti, N. Franchini, S. Frasca, F. Frasconi, A. Frattale Mascioli, Z. Frei, A. Freise, O. Freitas, R. Frey, W. Frischhertz, P. Fritschel, V. V. Frolov, G. G. Fronz\'e, M. Fuentes-Garcia, S. Fujii, T. Fujimori, P. Fulda, M. Fyffe, B. Gadre, J. R. Gair, S. Galaudage, V. Galdi, H. Gallagher, S. Gallardo, B. Gallego, R. Gamba, A. Gamboa, D. Ganapathy, A. Ganguly, B. Garaventa, J. Garc\'ia-Bellido, C. Garc\'ia N\'u\~nez, C. Garc\'ia-Quir\'os, J. W. Gardner, K. A. Gardner, J. Gargiulo, A. Garron, F. Garufi, C. Gasbarra, B. Gateley, V. Gayathri, G. Gemme, A. Gennai, V. Gennari, J. George, R. George, O. Gerberding, L. Gergely, Archisman Ghosh, Sayantan Ghosh, Shaon Ghosh, Shrobana Ghosh, Suprovo Ghosh, Tathagata Ghosh, L. Giacoppo, J. A. Giaime, K. D. Giardina, D. R. Gibson, D. T. Gibson, C. Gier, P. Giri, F. Gissi, S. Gkaitatzis, J. Glanzer, F. Glotin, J. Godfrey, P. Godwin, N. L. Goebbels, E. Goetz, J. Golomb, S. Gomez Lopez, B. Goncharov, Y. Gong, G. Gonz\'alez, P. Goodarzi, S. Goode, A. W. Goodwin-Jones, M. Gosselin, A. S. G\"ottel, R. Gouaty, D. W. Gould, K. Govorkova, S. Goyal, B. Grace, A. Grado, V. Graham, A. E. Granados, M. Granata, V. Granata, S. Gras, P. Grassia, A. Gray, C. Gray, R. Gray, G. Greco, A. C. Green, S. M. Green, S. R. Green, A. M. Gretarsson, E. M. Gretarsson, D. Griffith, W. L. Griffiths, H. L. Griggs, G. Grignani, A. Grimaldi, C. Grimaud, H. Grote, D. Guerra, D. Guetta, G. M. Guidi, A. R. Guimaraes, H. K. Gulati, F. Gulminelli, A. M. Gunny, H. Guo, W. Guo, Y. Guo, Anchal Gupta, Anuradha Gupta, Ish Gupta, N. C. Gupta, P. Gupta, S. K. Gupta, T. Gupta, N. Gupte, J. Gurs, N. Gutierrez, F. Guzman, H. -Y. H, D. Haba, M. Haberland, S. Haino, E. D. Hall, E. Z. Hamilton, G. Hammond, W. -B. Han, M. Haney, J. Hanks, C. Hanna, M. D. Hannam, O. A. Hannuksela, A. G. Hanselman, H. Hansen, J. Hanson, R. Harada, A. R. Hardison, K. Haris, T. Harmark, J. Harms, G. M. Harry, I. W. Harry, J. Hart, B. Haskell, C. -J. Haster, J. S. Hathaway, K. Haughian, H. Hayakawa, K. Hayama, R. Hayes, A. Heffernan, A. Heidmann, M. C. Heintze, J. Heinze, J. Heinzel, H. Heitmann, F. Hellman, P. Hello, A. F. Helmling-Cornell, G. Hemming, O. Henderson-Sapir, M. Hendry, I. S. Heng, E. Hennes, C. Henshaw, T. Hertog, M. Heurs, A. L. Hewitt, J. Heyns, S. Higginbotham, S. Hild, S. Hill, Y. Himemoto, N. Hirata, C. Hirose, W. C. G. Ho, S. Hoang, S. Hochheim, D. Hofman, N. A. Holland, K. Holley-Bockelmann, Z. J. Holmes, D. E. Holz, L. Honet, C. Hong, J. Hornung, S. Hoshino, J. Hough, S. Hourihane, E. J. Howell, C. G. Hoy, C. A. Hrishikesh, H. -F. Hsieh, C. Hsiung, H. C. Hsu, W. -F. Hsu, P. Hu, Q. Hu, H. Y. Huang, Y. -J. Huang, A. D. Huddart, B. Hughey, D. C. Y. Hui, V. Hui, S. Husa, R. Huxford, T. Huynh-Dinh, L. Iampieri, G. A. Iandolo, M. Ianni, A. Iess, H. Imafuku, K. Inayoshi, Y. Inoue, G. Iorio, M. H. Iqbal, J. Irwin, R. Ishikawa, M. Isi, M. A. Ismail, Y. Itoh, H. Iwanaga, M. Iwaya, B. R. Iyer, V. JaberianHamedan, C. Jacquet, P. -E. Jacquet, S. J. Jadhav, S. P. Jadhav, T. Jain, A. L. James, P. A. James, R. Jamshidi, J. Janquart, K. Janssens, N. N. Janthalur, S. Jaraba, P. Jaranowski, R. Jaume, W. Javed, A. Jennings, W. Jia, J. Jiang, H. Jin, J. Kubisz, C. Johanson, G. R. Johns, N. A. Johnson, M. C. Johnston, R. Johnston, N. Johny, D. H. Jones, D. I. Jones, R. Jones, S. Jose, P. Joshi, L. Ju, K. Jung, J. Junker, V. Juste, T. Kajita, I. Kaku, C. Kalaghatgi, V. Kalogera, M. Kamiizumi, N. Kanda, S. Kandhasamy, G. Kang, J. B. Kanner, S. J. Kapadia, D. P. Kapasi, S. Karat, C. Karathanasis, R. Kashyap, M. Kasprzack, W. Kastaun, T. Kato, E. Katsavounidis, W. Katzman, R. Kaushik, K. Kawabe, R. Kawamoto, A. Kazemi, D. Keitel, J. Kelley-Derzon, J. Kennington, R. Kesharwani, J. S. Key, R. Khadela, S. Khadka, F. Y. Khalili, F. Khan, I. Khan, T. Khanam, M. Khursheed, N. M. Khusid, W. Kiendrebeogo, N. Kijbunchoo, C. Kim, J. C. Kim, K. Kim, M. H. Kim, S. Kim, Y. -M. Kim, C. Kimball, M. Kinley-Hanlon, M. Kinnear, J. S. Kissel, S. Klimenko, A. M. Knee, N. Knust, K. Kobayashi, P. Koch, S. M. Koehlenbeck, G. Koekoek, K. Kohri, K. Kokeyama, S. Koley, P. Kolitsidou, M. Kolstein, K. Komori, A. K. H. Kong, A. Kontos, M. Korobko, R. V. Kossak, X. Kou, A. Koushik, N. Kouvatsos, M. Kovalam, D. B. Kozak, S. L. Kranzhoff, V. Kringel, N. V. Krishnendu, A. Kr\'olak, K. Kruska, G. Kuehn, P. Kuijer, S. Kulkarni, A. Kulur Ramamohan, A. Kumar, Praveen Kumar, Prayush Kumar, Rahul Kumar, Rakesh Kumar, J. Kume, K. Kuns, N. Kuntimaddi, S. Kuroyanagi, N. J. Kurth, S. Kuwahara, K. Kwak, K. Kwan, J. Kwok, G. Lacaille, P. Lagabbe, D. Laghi, S. Lai, A. H. Laity, M. H. Lakkis, E. Lalande, M. Lalleman, P. C. Lalremruati, M. Landry, B. B. Lane, R. N. Lang, J. Lange, B. Lantz, A. La Rana, I. La Rosa, A. Lartaux-Vollard, P. D. Lasky, J. Lawrence, M. N. Lawrence, M. Laxen, A. Lazzarini, C. Lazzaro, P. Leaci, Y. K. Lecoeuche, H. M. Lee, H. W. Lee, K. Lee, R. -K. Lee, R. Lee, S. Lee, Y. Lee, I. N. Legred, J. Lehmann, L. Lehner, M. Le Jean, A. Lema\^itre, M. Lenti, M. Leonardi, M. Lequime, N. Leroy, M. Lesovsky, N. Letendre, M. Lethuillier, S. E. Levin, Y. Levin, K. Leyde, A. K. Y. Li, K. L. Li, T. G. F. Li, X. Li, Z. Li, A. Lihos, C-Y. Lin, C. -Y. Lin, E. T. Lin, F. Lin, H. Lin, L. C. -C. Lin, Y. -C. Lin, F. Linde, S. D. Linker, T. B. Littenberg, A. Liu, G. C. Liu, Jian Liu, F. Llamas Villarreal, J. Llobera-Querol, R. K. L. Lo, J. -P. Locquet, L. T. London, A. Longo, D. Lopez, M. Lopez Portilla, M. Lorenzini, A. Lorenzo-Medina, V. Loriette, M. Lormand, G. Losurdo, T. P. Lott IV, J. D. Lough, H. A. Loughlin, C. O. Lousto, M. J. Lowry, N. Lu, H. L\"uck, D. Lumaca, A. P. Lundgren, A. W. Lussier, L. -T. Ma, S. Ma, M. Ma'arif, R. Macas, A. Macedo, M. MacInnis, R. R. Maciy, D. M. Macleod, I. A. O. MacMillan, A. Macquet, D. Macri, K. Maeda, S. Maenaut, I. Maga\~na Hernandez, S. S. Magare, C. Magazz\`u, R. M. Magee, E. Maggio, R. Maggiore, M. Magnozzi, M. Mahesh, S. Mahesh, M. Maini, S. Majhi, E. Majorana, C. N. Makarem, E. Makelele, J. A. Malaquias-Reis, U. Mali, S. Maliakal, A. Malik, N. Man, V. Mandic, V. Mangano, B. Mannix, G. L. Mansell, G. Mansingh, M. Manske, M. Mantovani, M. Mapelli, F. Marchesoni, D. Mar\'in Pina, F. Marion, S. M\'arka, Z. M\'arka, A. S. Markosyan, A. Markowitz, E. Maros, S. Marsat, F. Martelli, I. W. Martin, R. M. Martin, B. B. Martinez, M. Martinez, V. Martinez, A. Martini, K. Martinovic, J. C. Martins, D. V. Martynov, E. J. Marx, L. Massaro, A. Masserot, M. Masso-Reid, M. Mastrodicasa, S. Mastrogiovanni, T. Matcovich, M. Matiushechkina, M. Matsuyama, N. Mavalvala, N. Maxwell, G. McCarrol, R. McCarthy, D. E. McClelland, S. McCormick, L. McCuller, S. McEachin, C. McElhenny, G. I. McGhee, J. McGinn, K. B. M. McGowan, J. McIver, A. McLeod, T. McRae, D. Meacher, Q. Meijer, A. Melatos, S. Mellaerts, A. Menendez-Vazquez, C. S. Menoni, F. Mera, R. A. Mercer, L. Mereni, K. Merfeld, E. L. Merilh, J. R. M\'erou, J. D. Merritt, M. Merzougui, C. Messenger, C. Messick, Z. Metzler, M. Meyer-Conde, F. Meylahn, A. Mhaske, A. Miani, H. Miao, I. Michaloliakos, C. Michel, Y. Michimura, H. Middleton, A. L. Miller, S. Miller, M. Millhouse, E. Milotti, V. Milotti, Y. Minenkov, N. Mio, Ll. M. Mir, L. Mirasola, M. Miravet-Ten\'es, C. -A. Miritescu, A. K. Mishra, A. Mishra, C. Mishra, T. Mishra, A. L. Mitchell, J. G. Mitchell, S. Mitra, V. P. Mitrofanov, R. Mittleman, O. Miyakawa, S. Miyamoto, S. Miyoki, G. Mo, L. Mobilia, S. R. P. Mohapatra, S. R. Mohite, M. Molina-Ruiz, C. Mondal, M. Mondin, M. Montani, C. J. Moore, D. Moraru, A. More, S. More, G. Moreno, C. Morgan, S. Morisaki, Y. Moriwaki, G. Morras, A. Moscatello, P. Mourier, B. Mours, C. M. Mow-Lowry, F. Muciaccia, Arunava Mukherjee, D. Mukherjee, Samanwaya Mukherjee, Soma Mukherjee, Subroto Mukherjee, Suvodip Mukherjee, N. Mukund, A. Mullavey, J. Munch, J. Mundi, C. L. Mungioli, W. R. Munn Oberg, Y. Murakami, M. Murakoshi, P. G. Murray, S. Muusse, D. Nabari, S. L. Nadji, A. Nagar, N. Nagarajan, K. N. Nagler, K. Nakagaki, K. Nakamura, H. Nakano, M. Nakano, D. Nandi, V. Napolano, P. Narayan, I. Nardecchia, T. Narikawa, H. Narola, L. Naticchioni, R. K. Nayak, J. Neilson, A. Nelson, T. J. N. Nelson, M. Nery, A. Neunzert, S. Ng, L. Nguyen Quynh, S. A. Nichols, A. B. Nielsen, G. Nieradka, A. Niko, Y. Nishino, A. Nishizawa, S. Nissanke, E. Nitoglia, W. Niu, F. Nocera, M. Norman, C. North, J. Novak, J. F. Nu\~no Siles, L. K. Nuttall, K. Obayashi, J. Oberling, J. O'Dell, M. Oertel, A. Offermans, G. Oganesyan, J. J. Oh, K. Oh, T. O'Hanlon, M. Ohashi, M. Ohkawa, F. Ohme, A. S. Oliveira, R. Oliveri, B. O'Neal, K. Oohara, B. O'Reilly, N. D. Ormsby, M. Orselli, R. O'Shaughnessy, S. O'Shea, Y. Oshima, S. Oshino, S. Ossokine, C. Osthelder, I. Ota, D. J. Ottaway, A. Ouzriat, H. Overmier, B. J. Owen, A. E. Pace, R. Pagano, M. A. Page, A. Pai, A. Pal, S. Pal, M. A. Palaia, M. P\'alfi, P. P. Palma, C. Palomba, P. Palud, H. Pan, J. Pan, K. C. Pan, R. Panai, P. K. Panda, S. Pandey, L. Panebianco, P. T. H. Pang, F. Pannarale, K. A. Pannone, B. C. Pant, F. H. Panther, F. Paoletti, A. Paolone, E. E. Papalexakis, L. Papalini, G. Papigkiotis, A. Paquis, A. Parisi, B. -J. Park, J. Park, W. Parker, G. Pascale, D. Pascucci, A. Pasqualetti, R. Passaquieti, L. Passenger, D. Passuello, O. Patane, D. Pathak, M. Pathak, A. Patra, B. Patricelli, A. S. Patron, K. Paul, S. Paul, E. Payne, T. Pearce, M. Pedraza, R. Pegna, A. Pele, F. E. Pe\~na Arellano, S. Penn, M. D. Penuliar, A. Perego, Z. Pereira, J. J. Perez, C. P\'erigois, G. Perna, A. Perreca, J. Perret, S. Perri\`es, J. W. Perry, D. Pesios, S. Petracca, C. Petrillo, H. P. Pfeiffer, H. Pham, K. A. Pham, K. S. Phukon, H. Phurailatpam, M. Piarulli, L. Piccari, O. J. Piccinni, M. Pichot, M. Piendibene, F. Piergiovanni, L. Pierini, G. Pierra, V. Pierro, M. Pietrzak, M. Pillas, F. Pilo, L. Pinard, I. M. Pinto, M. Pinto, B. J. Piotrzkowski, M. Pirello, M. D. Pitkin, A. Placidi, E. Placidi, M. L. Planas, W. Plastino, R. Poggiani, E. Polini, L. Pompili, J. Poon, E. Porcelli, E. K. Porter, C. Posnansky, R. Poulton, J. Powell, M. Pracchia, B. K. Pradhan, T. Pradier, A. K. Prajapati, K. Prasai, R. Prasanna, P. Prasia, G. Pratten, G. Principe, M. Principe, G. A. Prodi, L. Prokhorov, P. Prosposito, A. Puecher, J. Pullin, M. Punturo, P. Puppo, M. P\"urrer, H. Qi, J. Qin, G. Qu\'em\'ener, V. Quetschke, C. Quigley, P. J. Quinonez, F. J. Raab, S. S. Raabith, G. Raaijmakers, S. Raja, C. Rajan, B. Rajbhandari, K. E. Ramirez, F. A. Ramis Vidal, A. Ramos-Buades, D. Rana, S. Ranjan, K. Ransom, P. Rapagnani, B. Ratto, S. Rawat, A. Ray, V. Raymond, M. Razzano, J. Read, M. Recaman Payo, T. Regimbau, L. Rei, S. Reid, D. H. Reitze, P. Relton, A. I. Renzini, P. Rettegno, B. Revenu, R. Reyes, A. S. Rezaei, F. Ricci, M. Ricci, A. Ricciardone, J. W. Richardson, M. Richardson, A. Rijal, K. Riles, H. K. Riley, S. Rinaldi, J. Rittmeyer, C. Robertson, F. Robinet, M. Robinson, A. Rocchi, L. Rolland, J. G. Rollins, A. E. Romano, R. Romano, A. Romero, I. M. Romero-Shaw, J. H. Romie, S. Ronchini, T. J. Roocke, L. Rosa, T. J. Rosauer, C. A. Rose, D. Rosi\'nska, M. P. Ross, M. Rossello, S. Rowan, S. K. Roy, S. Roy, D. Rozza, P. Ruggi, N. Ruhama, E. Ruiz Morales, K. Ruiz-Rocha, S. Sachdev, T. Sadecki, J. Sadiq, P. Saffarieh, M. R. Sah, S. S. Saha, S. Saha, T. Sainrat, S. Sajith Menon, K. Sakai, M. Sakellariadou, S. Sakon, O. S. Salafia, F. Salces-Carcoba, L. Salconi, M. Saleem, F. Salemi, M. Sall\'e, S. Salvador, A. Sanchez, E. J. Sanchez, J. H. Sanchez, L. E. Sanchez, N. Sanchis-Gual, J. R. Sanders, E. M. S\"anger, F. Santoliquido, T. R. Saravanan, N. Sarin, S. Sasaoka, A. Sasli, P. Sassi, B. Sassolas, H. Satari, R. Sato, Y. Sato, O. Sauter, R. L. Savage, T. Sawada, H. L. Sawant, S. Sayah, V. Scacco, D. Schaetzl, M. Scheel, A. Schiebelbein, M. G. Schiworski, P. Schmidt, S. Schmidt, R. Schnabel, M. Schneewind, R. M. S. Schofield, K. Schouteden, B. W. Schulte, B. F. Schutz, E. Schwartz, M. Scialpi, J. Scott, S. M. Scott, T. C. Seetharamu, M. Seglar-Arroyo, Y. Sekiguchi, D. Sellers, A. S. Sengupta, D. Sentenac, E. G. Seo, J. W. Seo, V. Sequino, M. Serra, G. Servignat, A. Sevrin, T. Shaffer, U. S. Shah, M. A. Shaikh, L. Shao, A. K. Sharma, P. Sharma, S. Sharma-Chaudhary, M. R. Shaw, P. Shawhan, N. S. Shcheblanov, E. Sheridan, Y. Shikano, M. Shikauchi, K. Shimode, H. Shinkai, J. Shiota, D. H. Shoemaker, D. M. Shoemaker, R. W. Short, S. ShyamSundar, A. Sider, H. Siegel, M. Sieniawska, D. Sigg, L. Silenzi, M. Simmonds, L. P. Singer, A. Singh, D. Singh, M. K. Singh, S. Singh, A. Singha, A. M. Sintes, V. Sipala, V. Skliris, B. J. J. Slagmolen, T. J. Slaven-Blair, J. Smetana, J. R. Smith, L. Smith, R. J. E. Smith, W. J. Smith, J. Soldateschi, K. Somiya, I. Song, K. Soni, S. Soni, V. Sordini, F. Sorrentino, N. Sorrentino, H. Sotani, R. Soulard, A. Southgate, V. Spagnuolo, A. P. Spencer, M. Spera, P. Spinicelli, J. B. Spoon, C. A. Sprague, A. K. Srivastava, F. Stachurski, D. A. Steer, J. Steinlechner, S. Steinlechner, N. Stergioulas, P. Stevens, M. StPierre, G. Stratta, M. D. Strong, A. Strunk, R. Sturani, A. L. Stuver, M. Suchenek, S. Sudhagar, N. Sueltmann, L. Suleiman, K. D. Sullivan, L. Sun, S. Sunil, J. Suresh, P. J. Sutton, T. Suzuki, Y. Suzuki, B. L. Swinkels, A. Syx, M. J. Szczepa\'nczyk, P. Szewczyk, M. Tacca, H. Tagoshi, S. C. Tait, H. Takahashi, R. Takahashi, A. Takamori, T. Takase, K. Takatani, H. Takeda, K. Takeshita, C. Talbot, M. Tamaki, N. Tamanini, D. Tanabe, K. Tanaka, S. J. Tanaka, T. Tanaka, D. Tang, S. Tanioka, D. B. Tanner, L. Tao, R. D. Tapia, E. N. Tapia San Mart\'in, R. Tarafder, C. Taranto, A. Taruya, J. D. Tasson, M. Teloi, R. Tenorio, H. Themann, A. Theodoropoulos, M. P. Thirugnanasambandam, L. M. Thomas, M. Thomas, P. Thomas, J. E. Thompson, S. R. Thondapu, K. A. Thorne, E. Thrane, J. Tissino, A. Tiwari, P. Tiwari, S. Tiwari, V. Tiwari, M. R. Todd, A. M. Toivonen, K. Toland, A. E. Tolley, T. Tomaru, K. Tomita, T. Tomura, C. Tong-Yu, A. Toriyama, N. Toropov, A. Torres-Forn\'e, C. I. Torrie, M. Toscani, I. Tosta e Melo, E. Tournefier, A. Trapananti, F. Travasso, G. Traylor, M. Trevor, M. C. Tringali, A. Tripathee, G. Troian, L. Troiano, A. Trovato, L. Trozzo, R. J. Trudeau, T. T. L. Tsang, R. Tso, S. Tsuchida, L. Tsukada, T. Tsutsui, K. Turbang, M. Turconi, C. Turski, H. Ubach, T. Uchiyama, R. P. Udall, T. Uehara, M. Uematsu, K. Ueno, S. Ueno, V. Undheim, T. Ushiba, M. Vacatello, H. Vahlbruch, N. Vaidya, G. Vajente, A. Vajpeyi, G. Valdes, J. Valencia, M. Valentini, S. A. Vallejo-Pe\~na, S. Vallero, V. Valsan, N. van Bakel, M. van Beuzekom, M. van Dael, J. F. J. van den Brand, C. Van Den Broeck, D. C. Vander-Hyde, M. van der Sluys, A. Van de Walle, J. van Dongen, K. Vandra, H. van Haevermaet, J. V. van Heijningen, P. Van Hove, M. VanKeuren, J. Vanosky, M. H. P. M. van Putten, Z. van Ranst, N. van Remortel, M. Vardaro, A. F. Vargas, J. J. Varghese, V. Varma, M. Vas\'uth, A. Vecchio, G. Vedovato, J. Veitch, P. J. Veitch, S. Venikoudis, J. Venneberg, P. Verdier, D. Verkindt, B. Verma, P. Verma, Y. Verma, S. M. Vermeulen, F. Vetrano, A. Veutro, A. M. Vibhute, A. Vicer\'e, S. Vidyant, A. D. Viets, A. Vijaykumar, A. Vilkha, V. Villa-Ortega, E. T. Vincent, J. -Y. Vinet, S. Viret, A. Virtuoso, S. Vitale, A. Vives, H. Vocca, D. Voigt, E. R. G. von Reis, J. S. A. von Wrangel, S. P. Vyatchanin, L. E. Wade, M. Wade, K. J. Wagner, A. Wajid, M. Walker, G. S. Wallace, L. Wallace, H. Wang, J. Z. Wang, W. H. Wang, Z. Wang, G. Waratkar, J. Warner, M. Was, T. Washimi, N. Y. Washington, D. Watarai, K. E. Wayt, B. R. Weaver, B. Weaver, C. R. Weaving, S. A. Webster, M. Weinert, A. J. Weinstein, R. Weiss, F. Wellmann, L. Wen, P. We{\ss}els, K. Wette, J. T. Whelan, B. F. Whiting, C. Whittle, J. B. Wildberger, O. S. Wilk, D. Wilken, A. T. Wilkin, D. J. Willadsen, K. Willetts, D. Williams, M. J. Williams, N. S. Williams, J. L. Willis, B. Willke, M. Wils, J. Winterflood, C. C. Wipf, G. Woan, J. Woehler, J. K. Wofford, N. E. Wolfe, H. T. Wong, H. W. Y. Wong, I. C. F. Wong, J. L. Wright, M. Wright, C. Wu, D. S. Wu, H. Wu, E. Wuchner, D. M. Wysocki, V. A. Xu, Y. Xu, N. Yadav, H. Yamamoto, K. Yamamoto, T. S. Yamamoto, T. Yamamoto, S. Yamamura, R. Yamazaki, S. Yan, T. Yan, F. W. Yang, F. Yang, K. Z. Yang, Y. Yang, Z. Yarbrough, H. Yasui, S. -W. Yeh, A. B. Yelikar, X. Yin, J. Yokoyama, T. Yokozawa, J. Yoo, H. Yu, S. Yuan, H. Yuzurihara, A. Zadro\.zny, M. Zanolin, M. Zeeshan, T. Zelenova, J. -P. Zendri, M. Zeoli, M. Zerrad, M. Zevin, A. C. Zhang, L. Zhang, R. Zhang, T. Zhang, Y. Zhang, C. Zhao, Yue Zhao, Yuhang Zhao, Y. Zheng, H. Zhong, R. Zhou, X. -J. Zhu, Z. -H. Zhu, A. B. Zimmerman, M. E. Zucker, J. Zweizig, S. B. Araujo Furlan, Z. Arzoumanian, A. Basu, A. Cassity, I. Cognard, K. Crowter, S. del Palacio, C. M. Espinoza, E. Fonseca, C. M. L. Flynn, G. Gancio, F. Garcia, K. C. Gendreau, D. C. Good, L. Guillemot, S. Guillot, M. J. Keith, L. Kuiper, M. E. Lower, A. G. Lyne, J. W. McKee, B. W. Meyers, J. L. Palfreyman, A. B. Pearlman, G. E. Romero, R. M. Shannon, B. Shaw, I. H. Stairs, B. W. Stappers, C. M. Tan, G. Theureau, M. Thompson, P. Weltevrede, E. Zubieta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SN 2018is: a low-luminosity Type IIP supernova with narrow hydrogen emission lines at early phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01530v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive photometric and spectroscopic study of the Type IIP SN 2018is. The $V$-band luminosity and the expansion velocity at 50 days post-explosion are $-$15.1$\pm$0.2 mag (corrected for A$_V$=1.34 mag) and 1400 km s$^{-1}$, classifying it as a low-luminosity SN II. The recombination phase in the $V$-band is shorter, lasting around 110 days, and exhibits a steeper decline (1.0 mag per 100 days) compared to most other low-luminosity SNe II. Additionally, the optical and near-infrared spectra display hydrogen emission lines that are strikingly narrow, even for this class. The Fe II and Sc II line velocities are at the lower end of the typical range for low-luminosity SNe II. Semi-analytical modelling of the bolometric light curve suggests an ejecta mass of $\sim$8 M$_\odot$, corresponding to a pre-supernova mass of $\sim$9.5 M$_\odot$, and an explosion energy of $\sim$0.40 $\times$ 10$^{51}$ erg. Hydrodynamical modelling further indicates that the progenitor had a zero-age main sequence mass of 9 M$_\odot$, coupled with a low explosion energy of 0.19 $\times$ 10$^{51}$ erg. The nebular spectrum reveals weak [O I] $\lambda\lambda$6300,6364 lines, consistent with a moderate-mass progenitor, while features typical of Fe core-collapse events, such as He I, [C I], and [Fe I], are indiscernible. However, the redder colours and low ratio of Ni to Fe abundance do not support an electron-capture scenario either. As a low-luminosity SN II with an atypically steep decline during the photospheric phase and remarkably narrow emission lines, SN 2018is contributes to the diversity observed within this population.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01530v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Dastidar, K. Misra, S. Valenti, D. J. Sand, A. Pastorello, A. Reguitti, G. Pignata, S. Benetti, S. Bose, A. Gangopadhyay, M. Singh, L. Tomasella, J. E. Andrews, I. Arcavi, C. Ashall, C. Bilinski, K. A. Bostroem, D. A. H. Buckley, G. Cannizzaro, L. Chomiuk, E. Congiu, S. Dong, Y. Dong, N. Elias-Rosa, M. Fraser, C. Gall, M. Gromadzki, D. Hiramatsu, G. Hosseinzadeh, D. A. Howell, E. Y. Hsiao, C. McCully, N. Smith, J. Strader</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compton Scattering of Thermal Disk Radiation with Black Hole Disk Winds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01532v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Galactic black hole (BH) X-ray binaries are known to exhibit episodic outbursts, during which accretion and spectral mode distinctively transition between low/hard and high/soft state. X-ray observations during high/soft state occasionally reveal a pronounced presence of a powerful disk wind in these systems. However, it is unexplored to date how such winds may influence disk emission in that regime.
  In this work, we consider an observational implication by Compton scattering of thermal disk radiation due to accretion disk winds by performing multi-dimensional Monte Carlo simulations in the context of a stratified wind of large solid angle launched over a large radial extent of the disk. Compton-scattered thermal disk spectrum is computed for a different wind property; i.e. wind density and its radial gradient. We find that the intrinsic disk radiation can be significantly down-scattered by winds of moderate-to-high density to the extent that the transmitted spectrum can substantially deviate from the conventional multi-color-disk emission by factor of up to 70\%. We thus claim that the conventional treatment of spectral hardening in the disk atmosphere may be insufficient to fully account for the observed disk continuum in the presence of strong wind scattering.
  It is suggested that the effect of scattering process (by $f_w$) should be incorporated to accurately evaluate an intrinsic disk spectrum besides the conventional hardening (color correction) factor (by $f_c$). We argue that BH spin measurements using thermal continuum-fitting in transient XRBs may well be mildly (if not significantly) altered by such spectral ``contamination".</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01532v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keigo Fukumura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Millihertz Oscillations Near the Innermost Orbit of a Supermassive Black Hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01581v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent discoveries from time-domain surveys are defying our expectations for how matter accretes onto supermassive black holes (SMBHs). The increased rate of short-timescale, repetitive events around SMBHs, including the newly-discovered quasi-periodic eruptions (QPEs), are garnering further interest in stellar-mass companions around SMBHs and the progenitors to mHz frequency gravitational wave events. Here we report the discovery of a highly significant mHz Quasi-Periodic Oscillation (QPO) in an actively accreting SMBH, 1ES 1927+654, which underwent a major optical, UV, and X-ray outburst beginning in 2018. The QPO was first detected in 2022 with a roughly 18-minute period, corresponding to coherent motion on scales of less than 10 gravitational radii, much closer to the SMBH than typical QPEs. The period decreased to 7.1 minutes over two years with a decelerating period evolution ($\ddot{P} &gt; 0$). This evolution has never been seen in SMBH QPOs or high-frequency QPOs in stellar mass black holes. Models invoking orbital decay of a stellar-mass companion struggle to explain the period evolution without stable mass transfer to offset angular momentum losses, while the lack of a direct analog to stellar mass black hole QPOs means that many instability models cannot explain all of the observed properties of the QPO in 1ES 1927+654. Future X-ray monitoring will test these models, and if it is a stellar-mass orbiter, the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA) should detect its low-frequency gravitational wave emission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01581v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Megan Masterson, Erin Kara, Christos Panagiotou, William N. Alston, Joheen Chakraborty, Kevin Burdge, Claudio Ricci, Sibasish Laha, Iair Arcavi, Riccardo Arcodia, S. Bradley Cenko, Andrew C. Fabian, Javier A. Garc\'ia, Margherita Giustini, Adam Ingram, Peter Kosec, Michael Loewenstein, Eileen T. Meyer, Giovanni Miniutti, Ciro Pinto, Ronald A. Remillard, Dev R. Sadaula, Onic I. Shuvo, Benny Trakhtenbrot, Jingyi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy spectrum and mass composition of cosmic rays from Phase I data measured using the Pierre Auger Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01736v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Pierre Auger Observatory concluded its first phase of data taking after seventeen years of operation. The dataset collected by its surface and fluorescence detectors (FD and SD) provides us with the most precise estimates of the energy spectrum and mass composition of ultra-high energy cosmic rays yet available. We present measurements of the depth of shower maximum, the main quantity used to derive species of primary particles, determined either from the direct observation of longitudinal profiles of showers by the FD, or indirectly through the analysis of signals in the SD stations. The energy spectrum of primaries is also determined from both FD and SD measurements, where the former exhibits lower systematic uncertainty in the energy determination while the latter exploits unprecedentedly large exposure. The data for primaries with energy below 1 EeV are also available thanks to the high-elevation telescopes of FD and the denser array of SD, making measurements possible down to 6 PeV and 60 PeV, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01736v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladim\'ir Novotn\'y (for the Pierre Auger Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AT2021aeuk: A Repeating Partial Tidal Disruption Event Candidate in a Narrow-line Seyfert 1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01824v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A black hole (BH) can tear apart a star that ventures within its tidal radius, producing a luminous flare as the stellar debris falls back, known as a tidal disruption event (TDE). While TDEs in quiescent galaxies are relatively well understood, identifying TDEs in active galactic nuclei (AGN) still remains a significant challenge. We present the discovery of AT2021aeuk, a transient exhibiting dual flares within around three years in a narrow-line Seyfert 1 galaxy. Multi-wavelength observations triggered during the second flare in 2023 revealed an extraordinary X-ray V-shaped light curve, strongly anti-correlated with the optical light curve and accompanied by a lag of $\sim$40 days. This behavior is inconsistent with both supernova and pure AGN origins. In addition, a new broad component emerges in the Balmer lines during the second flare, showing a clear reverberation signal to the continuum variation. We propose that the dual-flare may be linked to a repeating partial TDE (rpTDE), where the second flare results from a collision between the TDE stream and the inner accretion disk, triggering an optical flare while simultaneously partially destroying the X-ray corona. However, other mechanisms, such as a stellar-mass BH (sBH) merger within an accretion disk, could produce similar phenomena, which we cannot entirely rule out. The Vera C. Rubin Observatory will be a powerful tool for further investigating the nature of such events in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01824v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingbo Sun, Hengxiao Guo, Minfeng Gu, Ya-Ping Li, Yongjun Chen, D. Gonz\'alez-Buitrago, Jian-Guo Wang, Sha-Sha Li, Hai-Cheng Feng, Dingrong Xiong, Yanan Wang, Qi Yuan, Jun-Jie Jin, Wenda Zhang, Hongping Deng, Minghao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A review of long lasting activities of the central engine of gamma-ray bursts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01857v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gamma-ray bursts are known to display various features on top of their canonical behavior. In this short review, we will describe and discuss two of them: the ultra-long gamma-ray bursts, which are defined by an extreme duration of their prompt phase, and the plateau phase, which is defined by a steady phase of large duration at the start of the afterglow. We will review the main properties of those two phenomena, and will discuss their possible origin, in light of the standard fireball model of gamma-ray bursts. A final section will discuss the future missions which could bring new evidences to the study of those objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01857v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruce Gendre (University of the Virgin Islands,University of Western Australia)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Glitches and glitching clusters in rotation-powered pulsars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01862v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The study of pulsar glitch phenomena serves as a valuable probe into the dynamic properties of matter under extreme high-density conditions, offering insights into the physics within neutron stars. Providing theoretical explanations for the diverse manifestations observed in different pulsars has proven to be a formidable challenge. By analyzing the distribution of glitch sizes and waiting times, along with the evolution of cumulative glitch sizes over time, we have uncovered a long-term clustering phenomenon for pulsar glitches. This perspective allows us to approach the distinct glitch representations in various pulsars from a unified standpoint, connecting the same periodicity of observational data to the randomness. Without relying on specific physical models, we utilized the coefficient of variation to numerically determine optimal clustering numbers and clustering periods for sample pulsars. Our analysis involving 27 pulsars has revealed a clear linear relationship between the glitch cluster period and characteristic age. Of interest, the cumulative distribution of functions of cluster sizes and interval times have the same patterns, which can be synchronously fitted by Gaussian processes. These results may indicate novel understandings of glitches and the resulting processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01862v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad93c9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Astrophysical Journal, 978:49 (13pp), 2025 January 01</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pei-Xin Zhu, Xiao-Ping Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early steep optical decay linked to reverse shock for GRB200131A</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01893v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We observed an optical afterglow of GRB 200131A obtaining the first photometric point 63 s after the satellite trigger. This early observation shows a steep decay, suggesting either internal engine activity or a reverse shock. By fitting this data set, we show that the early data fit well as a reverse shock component of the GRB afterglow modeled as a thin shell expanding into a constant density interstellar matter. The fitting also shows a good agreement with a catalogued Milky Way galactic extinction and leaves only little space for further extinction in the host galaxy. By judging several factors we conclude that the most likely redshift of this GRB is 0.9 +/- 0.1.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01893v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Jel\'inek, Filip Novotn\'y, Sylvio Klose, Bringfried Stecklum, Al\v{z}b\v{e}ta Male\v{n}\'akov\'a, Jan \v{S}trobl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Very high energy cosmic ray particles from the Kerr black hole at the galaxy center</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01899v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Conventional general relativity supplies the notion of a vacuum tension and thus a maximum force $F_{max}=c^4/4G\approx\ 3\times 10^{43}$ Newtons, that is realized for a black hole. In conjunction with the Wilson area rule, we are thus led to the surface confinement of the mass of a black hole analogous to the surface confinement of quarks. The central result of our paper is that PeV scale protons exist on the surface of a Kerr black hole residing at our galactic center that is in concert with the HAWC Collaboration result of a PeVatron at the galactic center.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01899v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Orlando Panella, Simone Pacetti, Giorgio Immirzi, Yogendra N. Srivastava</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astrophysical Black holes: An Explanation for the Galaxy Quenching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00899v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose models of Astrophysical Black holes (ABHs) without event horizons (EHs), as a more viable explanation for the long-term quenching phenomenon in galaxies. At the same time, the short-term quenching is explained here in terms of an efficient feedback expected in the models of stellar-mass astrophysical black holes (StMABHs). We have calculated the radiative flux from the disk in a general spherically symmetric metric background and used it to contrast the distinctive features of the BHs and ABHs scenarios. The nature of the feedbacks arising from accretion onto a BH and an ABH in the `quasar' and `radio' modes are compared and some possible observational signatures of the StMABHs are pointed out.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00899v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jay Verma Trivedi, Pankaj S. Joshi,  Gopal-Krishna, Peter L. Biermann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sub-MHz Radio Background from Ultralight Dark Photon Dark Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01489v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dark photons are a well-motivated candidate for dark matter, but their detection becomes challenging for ultralight masses with both experimental and astrophysical probes. In this work, we propose a new approach to explore this regime through the dark inverse Compton scattering of ultralight dark photons with cosmic ray electrons and positrons. We show this process generates a potentially observable background radiation that is most prominent at frequencies below MHz. We compute this effect using the latest cosmic ray models and radio absorption maps. Comparing it to observations of the Milky Way's radio spectrum from Explorer 43, Radio Astronomy Explorer 2, and the Parker Solar Probe, we place leading constraints on the kinetic mixing of dark photon dark matter for masses $\lesssim 2 \times 10^{-17} \ \rm eV$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01489v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier F. Acevedo, Amit Bhoonah, Kun Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Link Between White Dwarf Pulsars and Polars: Multiwavelength Observations of the 9.36-Minute Period Variable Gaia22ayj</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01490v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: White dwarfs (WDs) are the most abundant compact objects, and recent surveys have suggested that over a third of WDs in accreting binaries host a strong (B $\gtrsim$ 1 MG) magnetic field. However, the origin and evolution of WD magnetism remain under debate. Two WD pulsars, AR Sco and J191213.72-441045.1 (J1912), have been found, which are non-accreting binaries hosting rapidly spinning (1.97-min and 5.30-min, respectively) magnetic WDs. The WD in AR Sco is slowing down on a $P/\dot{P}\approx 5.6\times 10^6$ yr timescale. It is believed they will eventually become polars, accreting systems in which a magnetic WD (B $\approx 10-240$ MG) accretes from a Roche lobe-filling donor spinning in sync with the orbit ($\gtrsim 78$ min). Here, we present multiwavelength data and analysis of Gaia22ayj, which outbursted in March 2022. We find that Gaia22ayj is a magnetic accreting WD that is rapidly spinning down ($P/\dot{P} = 6.1^{+0.3}_{-0.2}\times 10^6$ yr) like WD pulsars, but shows clear evidence of accretion, like polars. Strong linear polarization (40%) is detected in Gaia22ayj; such high levels have only been seen in the WD pulsar AR Sco and demonstrate the WD is magnetic. High speed photometry reveals a 9.36-min period accompanying a high amplitude ($\sim 2$ mag) modulation. We associate this with a WD spin or spin-orbit beat period, not an orbital period as was previously suggested. Fast (60-s) optical spectroscopy reveals a broad ``hump'', reminiscent of cyclotron emission in polars, between 4000-8000 Angstrom. We find an X-ray luminosity of $L_X = 2.7_{-0.8}^{+6.2}\times10^{32} \textrm{ erg s}^{-1}$ in the 0.3-8 keV energy range, while two VLA radio campaigns resulted in a non-detection with a $F_r &lt; 15.8\mu\textrm{Jy}$ 3$ \sigma$ upper limit. The shared properties of both WD pulsars and polars suggest that Gaia22ayj is a missing link between the two classes of magnetic WD binaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01490v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio C. Rodriguez, Kareem El-Badry, Pasi Hakala, Pablo Rodr\'iguez-Gil, Tong Bao, Ilkham Galiullin, Jacob A. Kurlander, Casey J. Law, Ingrid Pelisoli, Matthias R. Schreiber, Kevin Burdge, Ilaria Caiazzo, Jan van Roestel, Paula Szkody, Andrew J. Drake, David A. H. Buckley, Stephen B. Potter, Boris Gaensicke, Kaya Mori, Eric C. Bellm, Shrinivas R. Kulkarni, Thomas A. Prince, Matthew Graham, Mansi M. Kasliwal, Sam Rose, Yashvi Sharma, Tom\'as Ahumada, Shreya Anand, Akke Viitanen, Avery Wold, Tracy X. Chen, Reed Riddle, Roger Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ORACLE: A Real-Time, Hierarchical, Deep-Learning Photometric Classifier for the LSST</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01496v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present ORACLE, the first hierarchical deep-learning model for real-time, context-aware classification of transient and variable astrophysical phenomena. ORACLE is a recurrent neural network with Gated Recurrent Units (GRUs), and has been trained using a custom hierarchical cross-entropy loss function to provide high-confidence classifications along an observationally-driven taxonomy with as little as a single photometric observation. Contextual information for each object, including host galaxy photometric redshift, offset, ellipticity and brightness, is concatenated to the light curve embedding and used to make a final prediction. Training on $\sim$0.5M events from the Extended LSST Astronomical Time-Series Classification Challenge, we achieve a top-level (Transient vs Variable) macro-averaged precision of 0.96 using only 1 day of photometric observations after the first detection in addition to contextual information, for each event; this increases to $&gt;$0.99 once 64 days of the light curve has been obtained, and 0.83 at 1024 days after first detection for 19-way classification (including supernova sub-types, active galactic nuclei, variable stars, microlensing events, and kilonovae). We also compare ORACLE with other state-of-the-art classifiers and report comparable performance for the 19-way classification task, in addition to delivering accurate top-level classifications much earlier. The code and model weights used in this work are publicly available at our associated GitHub repository (https://github.com/uiucsn/ELAsTiCC-Classification).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01496v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ved G. Shah, Alex Gagliano, Konstantin Malanchev, Gautham Narayan, The LSST Dark Energy Science Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximum force conjecture in curved spacetimes of stable self-gravitating matter configurations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01497v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gibbons and Schiller have raised the physically interesting conjecture that forces in general relativity are bounded from above by the mathematically compact relation ${\cal F}\leq c^4/4G$. In the present compact paper we explicitly prove, using the non-linearly coupled Einstein-matter field equations, that the force function ${\cal F}\equiv 4\pi r^2 p(r)$ in {\it stable} self-gravitating horizonless matter configurations is characterized by the upper bound ${\cal F}\leq c^4/G$ [here $p(r)$ is the radial pressure inside the self-gravitating matter configuration].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01497v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D 110, 104040 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shahar Hod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining eV-scale axion-like particle dark matter: insights from the M87 Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01860v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Axion-like particles (ALPs) can account for the observed dark matter (DM) of the Universe and if their masses are at the eV scale, they can decay into infrared, optical and ultraviolet photons with a decay lifetime larger than the age of the Universe. We analyze multi-wavelength data obtained from the central region of Messier 87 (M87) galaxy by several telescopes, such as, Swift, Astrosat, Kanata, Spitzer and International Ultraviolet Explorer in the infrared to ultraviolet frequencies ($\sim 2\times10^{14} \, {\rm Hz} - 3\times10^{15}$ Hz), to constrain the narrow emission lines indicative of the eV scale ALP DM decay. We derive constraints on the ALP coupling to two photons ($g_{a\gamma\gamma}$) for ALP mass range $2 \, {\rm eV} \lesssim m_a \lesssim 20 \, {\rm eV}$, assuming ALPs form the DM in the M87 halo. We find that our bounds on ALP-two-photon coupling can become stronger than the existing ones by an order of magnitude in the ALP mass range $8 \, {\rm eV} \lesssim m_a \lesssim 20 \, {\rm eV}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01860v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpan Kar, Sourov Roy, Pratick Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H$\alpha$-X-ray Surface Brightness Correlation for Filaments in Cooling Flow Clusters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01902v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Massive galaxies in cooling flow clusters display clear evidence of feedback from Active Galactic Nuclei (AGN). Joint X-ray and radio observations have shown that AGN radio jets push aside the surrounding hot gas and form cavities in the hot intracluster medium (ICM). These systems host complex, kiloparsec-scale, multiphase filamentary structures, from warm ionized (10,000 K) to cold molecular ($&lt;$100 K). These striking clumpy filaments are believed to be a natural outcome of thermally unstable cooling from the hot ICM, likely triggered by feedback processes while contributing to feeding the AGN via Chaotic Cold Accretion (CCA). However, the detailed constraints on the formation mechanism of the filaments are still uncertain, and the connection between the different gas phases has to be fully unveiled. By leveraging a sample of seven X-ray bright cooling-flow clusters, we have discovered a tight positive correlation between the X-ray surface brightness and the H$\alpha$ surface brightness of the filaments over two orders of magnitude, as also found in stripped tails.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01902v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valeria Olivares, Adrien Picquenot, Yuanyuan Su, Massimo Gaspari, Marie-Lou Gendron-Marsolais, Fiorella L. Polles, Paul Nulsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QCD Phase Diagram and Astrophysical Implications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01907v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: I make a brief review about the QCD phases and the equation of state inferred from the neutron star data. Along the temperature axis at low baryon density, the QCD phase transition is a smooth crossover, and it is a natural extension of our imagination to postulate a similar crossover along the density axis at low temperature. Even without phase transitions, the inferred thermodynamic properties of neutron star matter turn out to be highly nontrivial already at twice of the nuclear saturation density. I also give some discussions about the substantiation of quark matter by means of the gravitational wave signals including the multi-messenger prospect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01907v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenji Fukushima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-period variations in the intermediate polar RX J2133.7+5107</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01940v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the results of long-term time series photometry on RX J2133.7+5107 (also known as 1RXS J213344.1+510725) obtained at several observatories. Using data taken during 17 years, we determined the current value of the spin period of $570.811470$ seconds with the formal accuracy of $0.000006$ seconds and a spin-up of the white dwarf with a characteristic time of $1.483(1)\times10^5$ years. This is even faster than that reported previously and, if confirmed, makes this object have one of the fastest spin-up timescales of all known intermediate polars. We derived an improved value of the superhump period of the system to be $0^d.280130(1)$. Superhump maxima timings are moving on the phase curve from season to season, showing non-monotonic changes, without a change in superhump period.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01940v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Breus, I. L. Andronov, P. Dubovsky, Y. Kim, J. N. Yoon, K. Petrik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of polarized Fermi-bubble synchrotron and dust emission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.00933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.00933v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The elusive polarized microwave signal from the Fermi bubbles is disentangled from the more extended polarized lobes, which similarly emanate from the Galactic plane but stretch farther west of the bubbles. The projected ~20% synchrotron polarization reveals magnetic fields preferentially parallel to the bubble edges, as expected downstream of a strong shock. The projected ~20% polarization of thermal dust emission is similarly oriented, constraining grain alignment in an extreme environment. We argue that the larger lobes arise from an older Galactic-center, likely supermassive black-hole, outburst.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.00933v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Uri Keshet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AGN flares as counterparts to LIGO/Virgo mergers: No confident causal connection in spatial correlation analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05318</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05318v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The primary formation channel for the stellar-mass Binary Black Holes which have been detected merging by the LIGO-Virgo- KAGRA (LVK) collaboration is yet to be discerned. One of the main reason is that the detection of an Electromagnetic counterpart to such Gravitational Wave (GW) events, which could signpost their formation site, has so far been elusive. Recently, 20 Active Galactic Nuclei flaring activities detected by the Zwicky Transient Facility have been investigated as potential counterparts of GW events by Graham et al. (2023). We present the results of a spatial correlation analysis that involves such events and uses the up-to-date posterior samples of 78 mergers, detected during the third observing run of the LVK collaboration. We apply a likelihood method which takes into account the exact position of the flares within the 3D sky map of the GW events. We place an upper limit of 0.155 at a 90 per cent credibility level on the fraction of the detected coalescences that are physically related to an observed flare, whose posterior probability distribution peaks at a null value. Finally, we show that the typically larger values of the masses of the GW-events, which host at least one flare in their localisation volume, are also consistent with the no-connection hypothesis. This is because of a positive correlation between binary masses and the size of the localisation uncertainties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05318v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae2787</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Niccol\`o Veronesi, Sjoert van Velzen, Elena Maria Rossi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced particle acceleration in a pulsar wind interacting with a companion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18663v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Pulsar winds have been shown to be preferred sites of particle acceleration and high-energy radiation. Numerous studies have been conducted to better characterize the general structure of such relativistic plasmas in isolated systems. However, many pulsars are found in binary systems and there are currently no ab initio models available that would include both the pulsar magnetosphere and the wind of the pulsar in interaction with a spherical companion. We investigate the interaction between a pulsar wind and a companion to probe the rearrangement of the pulsar wind, assess whether it leads to an enhancement of particle acceleration, and predict the high-energy radiative signature that stems from this interaction. We perform two-dimensional equatorial particle-in-cell simulations of an inclined pulsar surrounded by a spherical, unmagnetized, perfectly conducting companion settled in its wind. We find that the presence of the companion significantly alters the structure of the wind. When the companion lies beyond the fast magnetosonic point, a shock is established and the perturbations are advected in a cone behind the companion. We observe an enhancement of particle acceleration due to forced reconnection as the current sheet reaches the companion surface. Hence, high-energy synchrotron radiation is also amplified. The orbital light curves display two broad peaks reaching up to 14 times the high-energy pulsed flux emitted by an isolated pulsar magnetosphere. These effects increase with the growth of the companion size and with the decrease of the pulsar-companion separation. The present study suggests that a pulsar wind interacting with a companion induces a significant enhancement of high-energy radiation that takes the form of an orbital-modulated hollow cone of emission, which should be detectable by galactic-plane surveys, possibly with long-period radio transient counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18663v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202450605</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A, 689, A251 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Valentina Richard-Romei, Beno\^it Cerutti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the propagation of highly-energetic gamma rays in the Galaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08818v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent gamma-ray observations have detected photons up to energies of a few PeV. These highly energetic gamma rays are emitted by the most powerful sources in the Galaxy. Propagating over astrophysical distances, gamma rays might interact with background photons producing electron-positron pairs, then deflected by astrophysical magnetic fields. In turn, these charged particles might scatter through inverse Compton galactic radiation fields, triggering electromagnetic cascades. In this scenario, the characterisation of astrophysical environment in which gamma rays travel, specifically background photons and magnetic fields, is crucial. We explore the impact of propagation effects on observables at Earth by simulating galactic sources emitting gamma rays with energy between $100 \; \text{GeV}$ and $100 \; \text{PeV}$. We analyse the imprint of the galactic environment on observed energy spectra and arrival direction maps, revealing gamma-ray absorption features in the former and ``deflection" of gamma rays in the latter. Specifically, owing to interstellar radiation field spatial distribution and the galactic magnetic field structure, propagation effects on observables are found to be related to the specific gamma-ray source position and to the prompt emission model. Detailed investigations of the propagation effect on galactic gamma rays will improve the robustness of both current and future gamma-ray detections and indirect dark matter searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08818v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaetano Di Marco, Rafael Alves Batista, Miguel \'Angel S\'anchez-Conde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncovering deterministic behavior of black hole IGR J17091-3624: A twin of GRS 1915+105</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17810v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding nonlinear properties in accreting systems, particularly for black holes, from observation is illuminating as they are expected to be general relativistic magnetohydrodynamic flows that are nonlinear. Two features associated with nonlinear systems, used commonly, are chaos, which is deterministic, and random, which is stochastic. The differentiation between chaotic and stochastic systems is often considered to quantify the nonlinear properties of an astrophysical system. The particular emphasis is that data is often noise-contaminated and finite. We examine the dual nature of the black hole X-ray binary IGR J17091-3624, whose behavior has been closely studied in parallel to GRS 1915+105. Certain similarities in the temporal classes of these two objects are explored in literature. However, this has not been the case with their non-linear dynamics: GRS 1915+105 shows signs of determinism and stochasticity both, while IGR J17091-3624 was found to be predominantly stochastic. Here, we confront the inherent challenge of noise contamination faced by previous studies, particularly Poisson noise, which adversely impacts the reliability of non-linear results. We employ several denoising techniques to mitigate noise effects and employ methods like Principal Component Analysis, Singular Value Decomposition, and Correlation Integral to isolate the deterministic signatures. We have found signs of determinism in IGR J17091-3624, thus supporting the hypothesis of it being similar to GRS 1915+105, even as a dynamical system. Our findings not only shed light on the complex nature of IGR J17091-3624 but also pave the way for future research employing noise-reduction techniques to analyze non-linearity in observed dynamical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17810v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anindya Guria, Banibrata Mukhopadhyay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery and Detailed Study of the M31 Classical Nova AT 2023tkw: Evidence for Internal Shocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18215v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a detailed analysis of an extragalactic slow classical nova in M31 exhibiting multiple peaks in its light curve. Spectroscopic and photometric observations were used to investigate the underlying physical processes. Shock-induced heating events resulting in the expansion and contraction of the photosphere are likely responsible for the observed multiple peaks. Deviation of the observed spectrum at the peak from the models also suggests the presence of shocks. The successive peaks occurring at increasing intervals could be due to the series of internal shocks generated near or within the photosphere. Spectral modeling suggests a low-mass white dwarf accreting slowly from a companion star. The ejecta mass, estimated from spectral analysis, is $\sim 10^{-4}\mathrm{M_{\odot}}$, which is typical for a slow nova. We estimate the binary, by comparing the archival HST data and eruption properties with stellar and novae models, to comprise a 0.65 $\mathrm{M_{\odot}}$ primary white dwarf and a K III cool evolved secondary star.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18215v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Judhajeet Basu, Ravi Kumar, G. C. Anupama, Sudhanshu Barway, Peter H. Hauschildt, Shatakshi Chamoli, Vishwajeet Swain, Varun Bhalerao, Viraj R. Karambelkar, Mansi M. Kasliwal, Kaustav K. Das, Igor Andreoni, Avinash Singh, Rishabh S. Teja</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dark Matter Catalyzed Baryon Destruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18472v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: WIMP-type dark matter may have additional interactions that break baryon number, leading to induced nucleon decays which are subject to direct experimental constraints from proton decay experiments. In this work, we analyze the possibility of continuous baryon destruction, deriving strong limits from the dark matter accumulating inside old neutron stars, as such a process leads to excess heat generation. We construct the simplest particle dark matter model that breaks baryon and lepton numbers separately but conserves $B-L$. Virtual exchange by DM particles in this model results in di-nucleon decay via $nn\to n\bar\nu$ and $np\to ne^+$ processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18472v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.023005</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 023005 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yohei Ema, Robert McGehee, Maxim Pospelov, Anupam Ray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A possible evidence of pion condensation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01879v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work demonstrates that once a large number of pion is condensed in a high-energy hadron collision, the gamma-ray spectrum from $\pi^0$ decay takes on a typical broken power-law shape, which has been documented in many astronomical observations, but we have not yet recognized it. We show that this pion condensation is caused by a large number of soft gluons condensed in protons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01879v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Zhu, Yu-Chen Tang, Lei Feng, Feng-yao Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
