<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.HE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.HE</link>
    <description>astro-ph.HE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.HE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 01:43:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Faint supernovae and hyper-runaway white-dwarfs from single He-detonation in double HeCO-white-dwarf mergers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03396v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present three-dimensional hydrodynamical simulations of mergers between low-mass hybrid HeCO white dwarfs (WDs), offering new insights into the diversity of thermonuclear transients. Unlike previously studied mergers involving higher-mass HeCO WDs and CO WDs, where helium detonation often triggers core ignition, our simulations reveal incomplete helium shell detonations in comparable-mass, lower-mass WD pairs. The result is a faint, rapidly evolving transient driven by the ejection of intermediate-mass elements and radioactive isotopes such as $^{48}$Cr and $^{52}$Fe, without significant $^{56}$Ni production. These transients may be detectable in upcoming wide-field surveys and could account for a subset of faint thermonuclear supernovae. Long-term evolution of the merger remnant shows that high-velocity PG-1159-type stars might be formed through this scenario, similar to normal CO-CO white dwarf mergers. This work expands our understanding of white dwarf mergers and their implications for nucleosynthesis and stellar evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03396v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hila Glanz, Hagai B. Perets, Aakash Bhat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Luminous Fast Blue Optical Transients as very massive star core-collapse events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03402v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Luminous Fast Blue Optical Transients (LFBOTs) are rare extragalactic events of unknown origin. Tidal disruptions of white dwarfs by intermediate mass black holes, mergers of black holes and Wolf-Rayet stars, and failed supernovae are among the suggestions. In this paper, we explore the viability of very massive star core-collapse events as the origin of LFBOTs. The appeal of such a model is that the formation of massive black holes via core collapse may yield observational signatures that can match the disparate lines of evidence that point towards both core-collapse and tidal disruption origins for LFBOTs. We explore the formation rate of massive black holes in population synthesis models, and compare the metallicities of their progenitors with the observed metallicities of LFBOT host galaxies. We further examine the composition, mass loss rates and fallback masses of these stars, placing them in the context of LFBOT observations. The formation rate of black holes with mass greater than ~30-40Msol is similar to the observed LFBOT rate. The stars producing these black holes are biased to low metallicity (Z&lt;0.3Zsol), are H and He-poor and have dense circumstellar media. However, some LFBOTs have host galaxies with higher metallicities than predicted, and others have denser environments (plausibly due to late mass loss not captured in the models). We find that long-lived emission from an accretion disc (as implicated in the prototypical LFBOT AT2018cow) can plausibly be produced in these events. We conclude that (very) massive star core-collapse is a plausible explanation for LFBOTs. The preferred progenitors for LFBOTs in this scenario overlap with those predicted to produce super-kilonovae. We therefore suggest that LFBOTs are promising targets to search for super-kilonovae, and that they may contribute non-negligibly to the r-process enrichment of galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03402v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. A. Chrimes, P. G. Jonker, A. J. Levan, A. Mummery</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harnessing the XMM-Newton data: X-ray spectral modelling of 4XMM-DR11 detections and 4XMM-DR11s sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The XMM-Newton X-ray observatory has played a prominent role in astrophysics, conducting precise and thorough observations of the X-ray sky for the past two decades. The most recent iteration of the 4XMM catalogue and one of its latest data releases DR11 mark significant improvements over previous XMM-Newton catalogues, serving as a cornerstone for comprehending the diverse inhabitants of the X-ray sky. We employ detections and spectra extracted from the 4XMM-DR11 catalogue, subjecting them to fitting procedures using simple models. Our study operates within the framework of the XMM2ATHENA project, which focuses on developing state-of-the-art methods that exploit existing XMM-Newton data. We introduce and publicly release four catalogues containing measurements derived from X-ray spectral modelling of sources. The first catalogue encompasses outcomes obtained by fitting an absorbed power law model to all the extracted spectra for individual detections within the 4XMM-DR11 dataset. The second catalogue presents results obtained by fitting both an absorbed power law and an absorbed blackbody model to all unique physical sources listed in the 4XMM-DR11s catalogue, which documents source detection results from overlapping XMM-Newton observations. For the third catalogue we use the five band count rates derived from the pipe line detection of X-ray sources to mimic low resolution spectra to get a rough estimate of the spectral shape (absorbed power-law) of all 4XMM-DR11 detections. In the fourth catalogue, we conduct spectral analyses for the subset of identified sources with extracted spectra, employing various models based on their classification into categories such as AGN, stars, X-ray binaries, and cataclysmic variables. The scientific potential of these catalogues is highlighted by discussing the capabilities of optical and mid-infrared colours for selecting absorbed AGN. (abridged)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03409v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Viitanen, G. Mountrichas, H. Stiele, F. J. Carrera, A. Ruiz, J. Ballet, A. Akylas, A. Corral, M. Freyberg, A. Georgakakis, I. Georgantopoulos, S. Mateos, C. Motch, A. Nebot, H. Tranin, N. Webb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Updated Radio Sigma-D Relation and Distances to the Shell-Like Galactic Supernova Remnants -- IV</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03410v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a new selected sample of 69 Galactic supernova remnants (SNRs) for calibration of radio $\Sigma-D$ relation at 1 GHz. Calibrators with the most reliable distances were selected through an extensive literature search. The calibration is performed using kernel smoothing of the selected sample of calibrators in $\Sigma-D$ plane and an orthogonal offsets fitting procedure. We use the obtained calibration to derive the distances to 164 Galactic SNRs and 27 new detected SNRs/SNR candidates with none or poor distance estimates. The analysis given in this paper confirms the expected predictions from our previous papers that the kernel smoothing method is more reliable for SNR distance calibration than the orthogonal offset fitting method, except for the distance determinations of the very low brightness SNRs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03410v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Uro\v{s}evi\'c, B. Vukoti\'c, M. An{\dj}eli\'c, N. Mladenovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atmospheric pion, kaon, and muon fluxes for sub-orbital experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03428v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cosmic rays interacting with the Earth's atmosphere generate extensive air showers, which produce Cherenkov, fluorescence and radio emissions. These emissions are key signatures for detection by ground-based, sub-orbital, and satellite-based telescopes aiming to study high energy cosmic ray and neutrino events. However, detectors operating at ground and balloon altitudes are also exposed to a background of atmospheric charged particles, primarily pions, kaons, and muons, that can mimic or obscure the signals from astrophysical sources. In this work, we use coupled cascade equations to calculate the atmospheric pion, kaon and muon fluxes reaching detectors at various altitudes. Our analysis focuses on energies above 10 GeV, where the influence of the Earth's magnetic field on particle trajectories is minimal. We provide angular and energy-resolved flux estimates and discuss their relevance as background for extensive air shower detection. Our results are potentially relevant for interpreting data from current and future balloon-borne experiments such as EUSO-SPB2 and for refining trigger and veto strategies in Cherenkov and fluorescence telescopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03428v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diksha Garg, Laksha Pradip Das, Mary Hall Reno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GRMHD modelling of accretion flow around Sagittarius A$^*$ constrained by EHT measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03602v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study low angular momentum, advective accretion flows around a Kerr black hole within the framework of general relativistic magnetohydrodynamics (GRMHD) in the steady state. By solving the full set of GRMHD equations, we aim to provide a comprehensive understanding of the behavior of magnetized plasma in the strong gravity regime near a rotating black hole. The accretion solutions are obtained for a set of input parameters, namely energy (${\cal E}$), angular momentum (${\cal L}$), magnetic flux ($\Phi$), and isorotation parameter ($I$). By systematically varying these parameters, we generate a family of global GRMHD accretion solutions that characterize the physical environment around the black hole. Using this approach, we investigate whether the inferred magnetic field strengths reported by the Event Horizon Telescope (EHT) for Sagittarius A$^*$ at various radii can be reproduced. We find that, for a broad range of parameter values, our model successfully recovers the EHT inferred magnetic field strengths with an accuracy of approximately $10\%$, offering a self-consistent framework for interpreting near-horizon accretion physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03602v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gargi Sen (IITG), Debaprasad Maity (IITG), Santabrata Das (IITG)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VHE $\gamma$-ray observations of bright BL Lacs with the Large-Sized Telescope prototype (LST-1) of the CTAO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03702v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cherenkov Telescope Array Observatory (CTAO) is the next-generation ground-based gamma-ray observatory operating in the energy range from 20 GeV up to 300 TeV, with two sites in La Palma (Spain) and Paranal (Chile). It will consist of telescopes of three sizes, covering different parts of the large energy range. We report on the performance of Large-Sized Telescope prototype (LST-1) in the detection and characterization of extragalactic gamma-ray sources, with a focus on the reconstructed gamma-ray spectra and variability of classical bright BL Lacertae objects, which were observed during the early commissioning phase of the instrument. LST-1 data from known bright gamma-ray blazars - Markarian 421, Markarian 501, 1ES 1959+650, 1ES 0647+250, and PG 1553+113 - were collected between July 10, 2020, and May 23, 2022, covering a zenith angle range of 4 deg to 57 deg. The reconstructed light curves were analyzed using a Bayesian block algorithm to distinguish the different activity phases of each blazar. Simultaneous Fermi-LAT data were utilized to reconstruct the broadband $\gamma$-ray spectra for the sources during each activity phase. High-level reconstructed data in a format compatible with gammapy are provided together with measured light curves and spectral energy distributions (SEDs) for several bright blazars and an interpretation of the observed variability in long and short timescales. Simulations of historical flares are generated to evaluate the sensitivity of LST-1. This work represents the first milestone in monitoring bright BL Lacertae objects with a CTAO telescope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03702v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>The CTAO-LST Project,  :, K. Abe, S. Abe, A. Abhishek, F. Acero, A. Aguasca-Cabot, I. Agudo, C. Alispach, D. Ambrosino, F. Ambrosino, L. A. Antonelli, C. Aramo, A. Arbet-Engels, C. Arcaro, T. T. H. Arnesen, K. Asano, P. Aubert, A. Baktash, M. Balbo, A. Bamba, A. Baquero Larriva, U. Barres de Almeida, J. A. Barrio, L. Barrios Jim\'enez, I. Batkovic, J. Baxter, J. Becerra Gonz\'alez, E. Bernardini, J. Bernete, A. Berti, I. Bezshyiko, C. Bigongiari, E. Bissaldi, O. Blanch, G. Bonnoli, P. Bordas, G. Borkowski, G. Brunelli, A. Bulgarelli, M. Bunse, I. Burelli, L. Burmistrov, M. Cardillo, S. Caroff, A. Carosi, R. Carraro, M. S. Carrasco, F. Cassol, D. Cerasole, G. Ceribella, A. Cervi\~no Cort\'inez, Y. Chai, K. Cheng, A. Chiavassa, M. Chikawa, G. Chon, L. Chytk, G. M. Cicciari, A. Cifuentes, J. L. Contreras, J. Cortina, H. Costantini, M. Dalchenko, P. Da Vela, F. Dazzi, A. De Angelis, M. de Bony de Lavergne, R. Del Burgo, C. Delgado, J. Delgado Mengual, M. Dellaiera, D. della Volpe, B. De Lotto, L. Del Peral, R. de Menezes, G. De Palma, C. D\'iaz, G. Di Marco, A. Di Piano, F. Di Pierr, R. Di Tria, L. Di Venere, R. M. Dominik, D. Dominis Prester, A. Donini, D. Dorner, M. Doro, L. Eisenberger, D. Els\"asser, G. Emery, J. Escudero, V. Fallah Ramazani, F. Ferrarotto, A. Fiasson, L. Foffano, F. Fr\'ias Garc\'ia-Lago, S. Fr\"ose, Y. Fukazawa, S. Gallozzi, R. Garcia L\'opez, S. Garcia Soto, C. Gasbarra, D. Gasparrini, D. Geyer, J. Giesbrecht Paiva, N. Giglietto, F. Giordano, N. Godinovic, T. Gradetzke, R. Grau, D. Green, J. Green, S. Gunji, P. G\"unther, J. Hackfeld, D. Hadasch, A. Hahn, M. Hashizume, T. Hassan, K. Hayashi, L. Heckmann, M. Heller, J. Herrera Llorente, K. Hirotani, D. Hoffmann, D. Horns, J. Houles, M. Hrabovsky, D. Hrupec, D. Hui, M. Iarlori, R. Imazawa, T. Inada, Y. Inome, S. Inoue, K. Ioka, M. Iori, T. Itokawa, A. Iuliano, J. Jahanvi, I. Jimenez Martinez, J. Jimenez Quiles, I. Jorge Rodrigo, J. Jurysek, M. Kagaya, O. Kalashev, V. Karas, H. Katagiri, D. Kerszberg, T. Kiyomoto, Y. Kobayashi, K. Kohri, A. Kong, P. Kornecki, H. Kubo, J. Kushida, B. Lacave, M. Lainez, G. Lamanna, A. Lamastra, L. Lemoigne, M. Linhoff, S. Lombardi, F. Longo, R. L\'opez-Coto, M. L\'opez-Moya, A. L\'opez-Oramas, S. Loporchio, A. Lorini, J. Lozano Bahilo, F. Lucarelli, H. Luciani, P. L. Luque-Escamilla, P. Majumdar, M. Makariev, M. Mallamaci, D. Mandat, M. Manganaro, D. K. Maniadakis, G. Manic\`o, K. Mannheim, S. Marchesi, F. Marini, M. Mariotti, P. Marquez, G. Marsella, J. Mart\'i, O. Martinez, G. Mart\'inez, M. Mart\'inez, A. Mas-Aguilar, M. Massa, G. Maurin, D. Mazin, J. M\'endez-Gallego, S. Menon, E. Mestre Guillen, D. Miceli, T. Miener, J. M. Miranda, R. Mirzoyan, M. Mizote, T. Mizuno, M. Molero Gonzalez, E. Molina, T. Montaruli, A. Moralejo, D. Morcuende, A. Moreno Ramos, A. Morselli, V. Moya, H. Muraishi, S. Nagataki, T. Nakamori, A. Neronov, D. Nieto Casta\~no, M. Nievas Rosillo, L. Nikolic, K. Nishijima, K. Noda, D. Nosek, V. Novotny, S. Nozaki, M. Ohishi, Y. Ohtani, T. Oka, A. Okumura, R. Orito, L. Orsini, J. Otero-Santos, P. Ottanelli, M. Palatiello, G. Panebianco, D. Paneque, F. R. Pantaleo, R. Paoletti, J. M. Paredes, M. Pech, M. Pecimotika, M. Peresano, F. Pfeifle, E. Pietropaolo, M. Pihet, G. Pirola, C. Plard, F. Podobnik, M. Polo, E. Prandini, C. Priyadarshi, M. Prouza, S. Rain\`o, R. Rando, W. Rhode, M. Rib\'o, V. Rizi, G. Rodriguez Fernandez, M. D. Rodr\'iguez Fr\'ias, P. Romano, A. Roy, A. Ruina, E. Ruiz-Velasco, T. Saito, S. Sakurai, D. A. Sanchez, H. Sano, T. \v{S}ari\'c, Y. Sato, F. G. Saturni, V. Savchenko, F. Schiavone, B. Schleicher, F. Schmuckermaier, J. L. Schubert, F. Schussler, T. Schweizer, M. Seglar Arroyo, T. Siegert, G. Silvestri, A. Simongini, J. Sitarek, V. Sliusar, A. Stamerra, J. Stri\v{s}kovi\'c, M. Strzys, Y. Suda, A. Sunny, H. Tajima, M. Takahashi, J. Takata, R. Takeishi, P. H. T. Tam, S. J. Tanaka, D. Tateishi, T. Tavernier, P. Temnikov, Y. Terada, K. Terauchi, T. Terzic, M. Teshima, M. Tluczykont, F. Tokanai, T. Tomura, D. F. Torres, F. Tramonti, P. Travnicek, G. Tripodo, A. Tutone, M. Vacula, J. van Scherpenberg, M. V\'azquez Acosta, S. Ventura, S. Vercellone, G. Verna, I. Viale, A. Vigliano, C. F. Vigorito, E. Visentin, V. Vitale, V. Voitsekhovskyi, G. Voutsinas, I. Vovk, T. Vuillaume, R. Walter, L. Wan, M. Will, J. W\'ojtowicz, T. Yamamoto, R. Yamazaki, Y. Yao, P. K. H. Yeung, T. Yoshida, T. Yoshikoshi, W. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limiting the Yukawa Gravity through the Black Hole Shadows of Sgr A* and M87*</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04210v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently, the \textit{EHT} collaboration unveiled the shadow images of the supermassive black hole (SMBH) M87* and Sgr A*, with angular radii of $42\pm3$\,$\mu$as and $48.7\pm7.0$\,$\mu$as, respectively. These observations are consistent with the shadow of a Kerr black hole in general relativity (GR). Observations of the shadow of SMBHs can be used to test modified gravity theories, including Yukawa gravity, in extremely strong fields. In this paper, we illustrate the shadows of Yukawa black holes, showing that their sizes are significantly influenced by the Yukawa parameters $\lambda$ and $\kappa$. Using the EHT observations of M87* and Sgr A*, we obtain constraints on the Yukawa parameters. For Sgr A*, Keck and VLTI provide different priors on its gravitational radius. The Sgr A* shadow yields $\kappa=-0.04^{+0.09}_{-0.10}$ for $\lambda&gt;1$\,AU with the Keck prior, while $\kappa=-0.08^{+0.09}_{-0.06}$ with the VLTI prior. As $\lambda$ decreases, the constraints weaken, reaching $-0.37&lt;\kappa &lt;0.17$ (Keck prior) and $-0.47&lt;\kappa&lt;0.04$ (VLTI prior) at $\lambda=0.1$\,AU. For M87*, with a mass significantly larger than Sgr A*, this system can only put constraints on $\kappa$ at larger $\lambda$. For $\lambda&gt;1.5\times10^4$\,AU, the \textit{EHT} observation of M87* yields $\kappa=-0.01^{+0.17}_{-0.17}$. No significant deviation from GR is detected in our analysis. Additionally, we explore potential constraints using the next-generation VLBI, like \textit{ngEHT} and the Black Hole Explorer (BHEX), which promise the detection of the second ring of photons. The improved angular resolution and the measurements of the second ring could substantially refine constraints on the Yukawa parameters, enhancing our ability to test deviations from GR in the strong-field regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04210v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.dark.2025.102017</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physics of the Dark Universe, 2025, Volume 49, id.102017</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Tan, Youjun Lu, Kunyu Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latest view of CTA 1 with VERITAS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: CTA 1 is a shell-type supernova remnant (SNR) with a central pulsar wind nebula (PWN), visible at very-high-energy (VHE) from 50 GeV to 100 TeV from a moderately extended emission region. While general consensus concludes the VHE emission originates from relativistic leptons accelerated by the PWN and undergoing inverse Compton scattering, questions remain about electron escape and propagation, as well as the evolutionary stage of this particular PWN. CTA 1 is on the cusp of middle age (~13 kyr) and spatially resolvable at energies visible to imaging atmospheric Cherenkov telescopes (IACTs), such as the Very Energetic Radiation Imaging Telescope Array System (VERITAS) (PSF &lt; 0.1 deg). Therefore, this remnant is an excellent candidate to study lepton propagation and escape between different PWN evolutionary stages. Since the initial VERITAS publication on CTA 1 in 2013, VERITAS has performed new observations, adding to a total exposure of about 120 hours. We have analyzed the entire VERITAS CTA 1 dataset to date and report results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04414v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alisha Chromey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finding Supermassive Black Hole Binary Mergers in Pulsar Timing Array Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04537v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Galaxy observations suggest there is about one merger of supermassive black hole binaries (SMBHB) throughout the observable universe in a year. Here, we introduce the methodology to search for gravitational waves from these events with Pulsar Timing Arrays (PTAs).
  Modelling the inspiral, the merger, the ringdown, and the gravitational wave memory components of the signal in simulated data, we demonstrate a proof of principle for detection and parameter estimation. We study a few representative SMBHB mergers with chirp masses spanning $10^{8} - 10^{10}~M_\odot$ at distances from a few Mpc to 100~Mpc to asses their detectability in PTA observations. Assuming the fixed binary inclination angle of $90^{\circ}$ corresponding to the maximum displacement memory signal, these signals appear distinct for a PTA with 25 pulsars timed for 13 years with 100 ns precision.
  We demonstrate the capabilities of PTAs to constrain chirp masses and distances of detected merging binaries, as well as to place limits. The sky position uncertainties of the order of $1^{\circ}$, which we find in this optimistic example, could potentially enable electromagnetic follow-up and multi-messenger observations of SMBHB mergers. Finally, we show that the measurement uncertainties on the parameters of simulated merging binaries depend weakly on the presence of the gravitational wave background with Hellings-Downs correlations in our simulated data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04537v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sharon Mary Tomson, Boris Goncharov, Rutger van Haasteren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic hydrodynamics simulations of supernova explosions within extragalactic jets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04570v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Jets in active galactic nuclei have to cross significant distances within their host galaxies, meeting large numbers of stars of different masses and evolution stages in their paths. Given enough time, supernova explosions within the jet will eventually happen, and may have a strong impact on its dynamics, potentially triggering powerful non-thermal activity. We carried out a detailed numerical study to explore the dynamics of the interaction between the ejecta of a supernova explosion and a relativistic extragalactic jet. By means of relativistic hydrodynamics simulations using the code RATPENAT, we simulated the jet-ejecta interaction in two different geometries or scenarios: a two-dimensional, axisymmetric simulation, and a three-dimensional one, which includes the orbital velocity of the exploding star. Although initially filling a region much smaller than the jet radius, the ejecta expands and eventually covers most of the jet cross section. The expansion is enhanced as more energy from the jet is converted into kinetic and internal energy of the ejecta, which also favors the ejecta disruption, all this occurring on timescales ~ 10^4 yr. Although a complete numerical convergence of the results is unattainable given the subsonic, turbulent nature of the interaction region, the simulations are consistent in their description of the gross morphological and dynamical properties of the interaction process. At the end of the simulations, the supernova ejecta has already partially mixed with the relativistic jet. The results also suggest that the jet-ejecta interaction may be a non-negligible non-thermal emitter. Moreover, due to efficient mixing, the interaction region can be a potential source of ultra-high-energy cosmic rays of heavy composition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04570v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Longo, M. Perucho, V. Bosch-Ramon, J. M. Mart\'i, G. Fichet de Clairfontaine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Role of Acoustic Instability in Cosmic-Ray Self-Confinement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04635v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the past decades, there has been growing observational and theoretical evidence that cosmic-ray-induced instabilities play an important role in both acceleration and transport of cosmic rays (CRs). For instance, the efficient acceleration of charged particles at supernova remnant shocks requires rapidly growing instabilities, so much so that none of the proposed processes seem sufficient to warrant acceleration to PeV energies. In this work, we investigate whether an acoustic instability triggered by the presence of a CR pressure gradient can lead to significant self-confinement of charged particles in the vicinity of shocks. We validate the expected growth rates and obtain the scale and energy of magnetic field perturbations induced by such system using magnetohydrodynamical simulations. Our results suggest a strong suppression of the diffusion coefficient for particles with Larmor radius around a thousandth of the precursor scale length.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04635v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.22323/1.501.0022</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Capanema, Pasquale Blasi, Emanuele Sobacchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combining the second data release of the European Pulsar Timing Array with low-frequency pulsar data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Low-frequency radio data improve the sensitivity of pulsar timing arrays (PTAs) to propagation effects such as dispersion measure (DM) variations, enabling better noise characterization essential for detecting the stochastic gravitational wave background (GWB). We combined LOFAR (100-200 MHz) and NenuFAR (30-90 MHz) observations with the recent European and Indian PTA release (DR2new+) into a new dataset, DR2low, spanning ~11 years for 12 pulsars. DR2low allows updated noise models, increasing PTA sensitivity to the GWB. Using Libstempo and Enterprise, we applied standard noise models including red noise (RN) and time-variable DM (DMv) as power laws, and performed Bayesian model selection over RN, DMv, and an additional chromatic noise term (CN4). Compared to DR2new+, DR2low improves DM constraints and separates DM and RN contributions. We found that the RN is required in the final model for 10 out of 12 pulsars, compared to only 5 in the DR2new+ dataset. The improved sensitivity to plasma effects provided by DR2low also favors the identification of significant CN4 in eight pulsars, while none showed such evidence in DR2new+. The analysis also reveals unmodelled solar wind effects, particularly near solar conjunction, with residual delays absorbed into the DM component, highlighting the importance of accurately modelling the solar wind in PTA datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04639v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Iraci, A. Chalumeau, C. Tiburzi, J. P. W. Verbiest, A. Possenti, S. C. Susarla, M. A. Krishnakumar, G. M. Shaifullah, J. Antoniadis, M. Bagchi, C. Bassa, R. N. Caballero, B. Cecconi, S. Chen, S. Chowdhury, B. Ciardi, I. Cognard, S. Corbel, S. Desai, D. Deb, J. Girard, A. Golden, J-M. Grie{\ss}meier, L. Guillemot, M. Hoeft, H. Hu, F. Jankowski, G. Janssen, B. C. Joshi, S. Kala, E. Keane, K. Nobelson, A. Konovalenko, I. Kravtsov, M. Kramer, K. Liu, A. Parthasarathy, P. Rana, D. Schwarz, J. Singha, A. Srivastava, K. Takahashi, P. Tarafdar, G. Theureau, O. Ulyanov, C. Vocks, J. Wang, V. Zakharenko, P. Zarka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Converged simulations of the nozzle shock in tidal disruption events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04790v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When debris from a star that experienced a tidal disruption events (TDE) after passing too close to a massive black hole returns to pericenter on the second passage, it is compressed, leading to the formation of nozzle shocks (in the orbital plane) and pancake shocks (perpendicular to the orbital plane). Resolving these shocks is a long-standing problem in the hydrodynamic simulations of parabolic TDEs. Excessive numerical energy dissipation or heating unrealistically expands the stream. In this Letter, we apply adaptive particle refinement to our 3D general relativistic smoothed particle simulations to locally increase the resolution near the pericenter. We achieve resolutions equivalent to $6.55\times10^{11}$ particles, allowing us to converge on the true energy dissipation. We conclude that only $4\times10^{-5}$ of the orbital energy is dissipated in nozzle shocks for a Sun-like star tidally disrupted by a $10^6$ solar-mass black hole, therefore the nozzle shocks are unlikely to be important in the evolution of TDEs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04790v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fangyi Fitz Hu, Ilya Mandel, Rebecca Nealon, Daniel J. Price</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recent observations of PKS 2155-304 with MAGIC and LST-1 in a multi-wavelength context</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04803v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: PKS 2155-304 is a well-known high-frequency peaked BL Lac (HBL) at redshift z=0.116, which has been extensively studied across the electromagnetic spectrum due to its rapid and large-amplitude variability. Several violent outbursts in X-rays and $\gamma$-rays have been observed in the past, with intra-night variability in very-high-energy $\gamma$-rays (VHE; E &gt; 100 GeV) detected down to the minute timescale. The alternation of quiescent and enhanced states, observed with a tentative quasi-periodicity of 1.74 $\pm$ 0.13 years in high-energy (HE; 100 MeV &lt; E &lt; 100 GeV) $\gamma$-rays, makes this source a key target also for ground-based $\gamma$-ray instruments and in particular for the Imaging Atmospheric Cherenkov Telescopes. Its brightness, proximity, and well-determined redshift make this $\gamma$-ray source a prime target for fundamental physics studies, including tests of Lorentz Invariance Violation (LIV), searches for axion-like particles (ALPs), and constraints on the distribution of the extragalactic background light (EBL). In the last two years, PKS 2155-304 has been independently monitored by the Major Atmospheric Gamma-ray Imaging Cherenkov (MAGIC) telescopes and the first Large-Sized Telescope (LST-1) of the Cherenkov Telescope Array Observatory (CTAO) located at the Roque de Los Muchachos Observatory (La Palma, Spain). The observations were carried out at large zenith angles (LZA; ZA &gt; 55{\deg}), and the VHE data have been complemented with simultaneous observations in HE $\gamma$-rays (Fermi-LAT), X-rays (Swift-XRT) and optical wavelengths (ASAS-SN).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04803v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.22323/1.501.0783</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Lisa Nikoli\'c, Gaia Verna, Marina Manganaro, Giacomo Bonnoli, Ivan Agudo, Giuseppe Silvestri, Davide Cerasole, Francesco Schiavone, Franjo Podobnik, Jorge Otero-Santos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint eROSITA and H.E.S.S. analysis of MSH 15-52 using Gammapy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04857v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pulsar wind nebulae (PWNe) are prominent sources in the very-high energy (VHE) gamma-ray sky, constituting the most numerous identified source class in the H.E.S.S. Galactic Plane Survey (HGPS). They are comprised of energetic particles originating from the pulsar and expanding into the surrounding medium. As such, PWNe are of very high scientific interest as PeVatron candidates, objects that could potentially accelerate particles up to PeV energies. Additionally other aspects of their acceleration mechanism are being actively investigated, such as the open question of whether they accelerate not only leptonic but also hadronic particles, and the details of their morphology and particle transport mechanism. As PWNe emit photons over a broad range of the electromagnetic spectrum, multiwavelength (MWL) studies are crucial for the investigation and study of their emission.
  In this vein we present a joint eROSITA X-ray and H.E.S.S. gamma-ray study of the PWN MSH 15-52. We showcase our custom code for integrating the EDR and DR1 eROSITA data into the Gammapy framework, a python package optimised for the analysis of gamma-ray data. We present the first 3D (spatial and spectral) fit to eROSITA data by using Gammapy. We furthermore combine these data with the public H.E.S.S. gamma-ray observations of MSH 15-52, resulting in a joint physical fit of the underlying particle population, and a subsequent discussion of the physical implications of our results. Finally we give an outlook towards future efforts in MWL studies of PWNe and the broader context of MWL data analysis with Gammapy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04857v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.22323/1.501.0637</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PoS(ICRC2025)637</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Katharina Egg, Alison M. W. Mitchell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jet MHD analytical model - framework for radiative transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04949v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We developed the full magnetohydrodynamical analytical jet model that allows accurate reproducing of a transversal and longitudinal structure for a highly collimated relativistic jets. This model can be used as a setup for convenient solution of radiative transfer equations and modelling the total intensity and polarization maps. We show that the analytical fits are in excellent agreement with the numerical solutions of full magnetohydrodynamical equations. Our approach allows setting easily different models for an emitting plasma number density. For example, we show that the equipartition number density ranges from several to tens of percent of a total number density. We show that the Doppler-corrected emissivity distribution behave in such a way that we may expect a limb brightened intensity pattern on a sub-parsec scale and a spine-brightened structure downstream. We reproduce the broken power-law dependence of a jet pressure at its boundary from the jet radius. The corresponding power exponents are in agreement with the parabola-to-cone transition observed directly in nearby sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04949v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. E. Nokhrina, I. N. Pashchenko, V. A. Frolova, R. V. Todorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Line emission search from DM annihilation in the Galactic Center with LST-1</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04977v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dark Matter remains a great mystery in modern physics. Among various candidates, the weakly interacting massive particles (WIMPs) scenario stands out and is under extensive study. The detection of the hypothetical gamma-ray emission from WIMP annihilation could act as a direct probe of electroweak-scale interactions, complementing DM collider searches and other direct DM detection techniques. At very high energies (VHE), WIMP self-annihilation is expected to produce gamma rays together with other Standard Model particles. The galactic center (GC), due to its relative proximity to the Earth and its high expected DM density, is a prime target for monoenergetic line searches. IACTs have placed strong constraints on the DM properties at the GC, with the MAGIC providing the most stringent limits from 20 TeV to 100 TeV, exploiting large zenith angle (LZA) observations. However, the limited field of view (FoV) of the MAGIC telescopes (&lt; 3.5{\deg} ) prevented a detailed study of the extended region around the GC in which an enhanced DM density is expected. The LST-1 of the CTAO, located at the Roque de Los Muchachos Observatory (La Palma, Spain), close to the MAGIC site, has been observing the GC since 2021. With its wide FoV of 4.5{\deg}, LST-1 could contribute significantly to the WIMPs search at the GC. The observations are performed at LZA (ZA &gt; 58{\deg}), which, while required due to the source's low altitude, also optimizes the detection of gamma rays up to 100 TeV and beyond. We present a study of the systematic uncertainties in WIMP line emission searches with LST-1. Our work examines the instrument response functions for LZA observations, background rejection in monoscopic mode, and includes updated results from simulations, highlighting new methods for spectral line searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04977v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.22323/1.501.0462</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Abhishek (on behalf of the CTAO-LST project), Shotaro Abe (on behalf of the CTAO-LST project), Tomohiro Inada (on behalf of the CTAO-LST project), Sofia Ventura (on behalf of the CTAO-LST project), Michele Doro (on behalf of the CTAO-LST project), Masahiro Teshima (on behalf of the CTAO-LST project), Gaia Verna (on behalf of the CTAO-LST project)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed Stochastic-Deterministic Density Functional Theoretic Decomposition of Kubo-Greenwood Conductivities in the Projector Augmented Wave Formalism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03388v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Pairing the accuracy of Kohn-Sham density-functional framework with the efficiency of a stochastic algorithmic approach, mixed stochastic-deterministic Density Functional Theory (mDFT) achieves a favorable computational scaling with system sizes and electronic temperatures. We employ the recently developed mDFT formalism to investigate the dynamic charge-transport properties of systems in the warm dense matter regime. The optical conductivity spectra are computed for single- and multi- component mixtures of carbon, hydrogen, and beryllium using two complementary approaches: Kubo-Greenwood in the mDFT picture and real-time Time-Dependent mDFT. We further devise a decomposition of the Onsager coefficients leading up to the Kubo-Greenwood spectra to exhibit contributions from the deterministic, stochastic, and mixed electronic state transitions at different incident photon energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03388v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vidushi Sharma, Lee A. Collins, Alexander J. White</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biased parameter inference of eccentric, spin-precessing binary black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04332v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While the majority of gravitational wave (GW) events observed by the LIGO and Virgo detectors are consistent with mergers of binary black holes (BBHs) on quasi-circular orbits, some events are also consistent with non-zero orbital eccentricity, indicating that the binaries could have formed via dynamical interactions. Moreover, there may be GW events which show support for spin-precession, eccentricity, or both. In this work, we study the interplay of spins and eccentricity on the parameter estimation of GW signals from BBH mergers. We inject eccentric signals with no spins, aligned spins, and precessing spins using hybrids, TEOBResumS-DALI, and new Numerical Relativity (NR) simulations, respectively, and study the biases in the posteriors of source parameters when these signals are recovered with a quasi-circular precessing-spin waveform model, as opposed to an aligned-spin eccentric waveform model. We find significant biases in the source parameters, such as chirp mass and spin-precession ($\chi_p$), when signals from highly-eccentric BBHs are recovered with a quasi-circular waveform model. Moreover, we find that for signals with both eccentricity and spin-precession effects, Bayes factor calculations confirm that an eccentric, aligned-spin model is preferred over a quasi-circular precessing-spin model. Our study highlights the complex nature of GW signals from eccentric, precessing-spin binaries and the need for readily usable inspiral-merger-ringdown eccentric, spin-precessing waveform models for unbiased parameter estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04332v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Divyajyoti, Isobel M. Romero-Shaw, Vaishak Prasad, Kaushik Paul, Chandra Kant Mishra, Prayush Kumar, Akash Maurya, Michael Boyle, Lawrence E. Kidder, Harald P. Pfeiffer, Mark A. Scheel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing dust torus radius--luminosity relation: An WISE view</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04517v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present measurements of the dusty torus sizes of 51 active galactic nuclei (AGNs) with a redshift of $z&lt;$ 0.8. Our analysis utilizes about 16 years of optical photometric data of 146 AGNs from various time-domain surveys, including ASAS-SN, CRTS, and ZTF, along with 14 years of infrared data in the $W$1 ($\sim$ 3.4 $\mu$m) and $W$2 ($\sim$ 4.6 $\mu$m) bands obtained from the Wide-Field Infrared Survey Explorer (WISE). The estimated dust torus size ranges from 1000 to 3000 days, using both the cross-correlation analysis and lightcurve modeling through `MICA'. The measured lag has been corrected by $(1+z)^{-0.37}$, to account for cosmological time dilation and the torus temperature-gradient scaling. We conduct a linear regression analysis for both the $W$1 and $W$2 bands to examine the radius--luminosity ($R$--$L_{BOL}$) relationship under two conditions: one where the slope is fixed at 0.5 and one where it is allowed to vary. For the fixed slope of 0.5, we find the ratio of R$_{\mathrm{BLR}}$: R$_{W1}$: R$_{W2}$ to be 1: 9: 12, indicating that the torus lies outside the BLR and that its size increases with wavelength. Furthermore, we determine the relationship between torus size and L$_{BOL}$, yielding best-fit slopes of $0.413\pm0.047$ for the $W$1 band and $0.397\pm0.058$ for the $W$2 band. Both slopes are shallower than predicted by the dust radiation equilibrium model. Furthermore, our findings indicate that the torus size systematically decreases as the Eddington ratio increases, a trend that can be explained by the self-shadowing effects of slim disks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04517v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashutosh Tomar, Suvendu Rakshit, Amit Kumar Mandal, Shivangi Pandey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing black hole metrics with binary black hole inspirals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04703v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gravitational wave astronomy has opened an unprecedented window onto tests of gravity and fundamental physics in the strong-field regime. In this study, we examine a series of well-motivated deviations from the classical Kerr solution of General Relativity and employ gravitational wave data to place constraints on possible deviations from the Kerr geometry. The method involves calculating the phase of gravitational waves using the effective one-body formalism and then applying the parameterized post-Einsteinian framework to constrain the parameters appearing in these scenarios beyond General Relativity. The effective one-body method, known for its capability to model complex gravitational waveforms, is used to compute the wave phase, and the post-Einsteinian framework allows for a flexible, model-independent approach to parameter estimation. We demonstrate that gravitational wave data provide evidence supporting the Kerr nature of black holes, showing no significant deviations from General Relativity, thereby affirming its validity within the current observational limits. This work bridges theoretical waveform modeling with observational constraints, providing a pathway to test the no-hair theorem and probe the astrophysical viability of modified black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04703v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Zhao, Swarnim Shashank, Debtroy Das, Cosimo Bambi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The demographics of core-collapse supernovae I. The role of binary evolution and CSM interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04872v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The observational properties of core-collapse supernovae (CC-SNe) are shaped by the envelopes of their progenitors. In massive binary systems, mass-transfer alters the pre-SN structures compared to single stars, leading to a diversity in SN explosions. Aims. We compute the distribution of CC-SN properties based on comprehensive detailed grids of single and binary stellar evolution models. We conduct a grid-based population synthesis to produce a synthetic population of CC-SNe, and compare it to observed SN samples. We also apply various explodability and merger criteria to our models. In line with earlier results, we identify interacting SN progenitors as those stars that undergo CC during or shortly after a Roche-lobe overflow phase. With an interacting binary fraction of 68%, our models predict two-thirds of all CC-SNe to be of Type IIP/L, and 1/3 of Type Ibc, in agreement with recent volume-limited SN surveys. We find that 76% of the Type Ibc SN progenitors took part in a previous binary mass transfer (mostly as mass donor), but also 63% of the Type IIP/L SN progenitors (mostly as mass gainers), yielding a much broader envelope mass distribution than expected from single stars. We find that mass-transfer induced interacting SNe make up ~5% of all CC-SNe, which is close to the observed fractions of Type IIn and Type Ibn SNe. When assuming a disk or toroidal CSM geometry for Type IIn SNe, our models predict a bimodal distribution of the radiated energies, similar to that deduced from observations. While we find the effect of binary evolution on the relative number of Type Ibc and Type IIP/L SNe to be moderate, it leads to lower average ejecta masses in Type Ibc and Type IIb SNe, and can lead to higher pre-SN masses in Type IIP/L SNe than single stars. Binary models are also able to reproduce the number and properties of interacting SNe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04872v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Ercolino, Harim Jin, Norbert Langer, Avishay Gal-Yam, Abel Schootemeijer, Caroline Mannes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The origin of hypervelocity white dwarfs in the merger-disruption of He-CO white dwarfs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17306v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hypervelocity white dwarfs (HVWDs) are stellar remnants moving at speeds exceeding the Milky Way's escape velocity. The origins of the fastest HVWDs are enigmatic, with proposed formation scenarios facing challenges explaining both their extreme velocities and observed properties. Here we report a three-dimensional hydrodynamic simulation of a merger between two hybrid Helium-Carbon-Oxygen white dwarfs (HeCO WDs with masses of 0.69 and 0.62 M$_\odot$). We find that the merger leads to a partial disruption of the secondary WD, coupled with a double-detonation explosion of the primary WD. This launches the remnant core of the secondary WD at a speed of $~2000$ km s$^{-1}$, consistent with observed HVWDs. The low mass of the ejected remnant and its heating from the primary WD's ejecta explain the observed luminosities and temperatures of hot HVWDs, which are otherwise difficult to reconcile with previous models (such as the D6). This discovery establishes a new formation channel for HVWDs and points to a previously unrecognized pathway for producing peculiar Type Ia supernovae and faint explosive transients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17306v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41550-025-02633-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Astronomy, August 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hila Glanz, Hagai B. Perets, Aakash Bhat, Ruediger Pakmor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gamma-Ray Observations of Galaxy Clusters Strongly Constrain Dark Matter Annihilation in Prompt Cusps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14865v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Thermal dark matter models generically include the prompt creation of highly-concentrated dark matter cusps in the early Universe. Recent studies find that these cusps can survive to the present day, as long as they do not fall into extremely dense regions of baryonic structure. In this work, we build models of dark matter annihilation within the prompt cusps that reside in galaxy clusters, showing that they dominate the total $\gamma$-ray annihilation signal. Using 15 years of Fermi-LAT data, we find no evidence for a $\gamma$-ray excess from these sources, and set strong constraints on annihilating dark matter. These constraints generically rule out the thermal annihilation cross-section to the $b\bar{b}$ channel for dark matter masses below $\sim$200~GeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14865v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milena Crnogor\v{c}evi\'c, M. Sten Delos, Nadia Kuritz\'en, Tim Linden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Signatures of Quasi-Periodic Eruptions: LISA Detection Prospects for RX J1301.9+2747</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07961v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: One prominent model for quasi-periodic eruptions (QPEs) is that they originate from extreme mass-ratio inspirals (EMRIs) involving stellar-mass objects orbiting around massive black holes and colliding with their accretion disks. We compute the gravitational wave signals from such a model, demonstrating that orbiter-disk interactions result in small frequency shifts and high-frequency tails due to the excitation of non-discrete modes. Interestingly, we show that QPE RX J1301.9+2747 could be detectable by future space-based gravitational wave detectors, provided a moderate eccentricity around $0.25$ and a mass exceeding $35\,M_\odot$ for the orbiter. Moreover, based on this QPE model, we show that the signal-to-noise ratio of the gravitational wave signals from QPEs, if detectable, will be sufficiently high to distinguish such systems from vacuum EMRIs and shed light on the origin of QPEs and environments around massive black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07961v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leif Lui, Alejandro Torres-Orjuela, Rudrani Kar Chowdhury, Lixin Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Triples as Links between Binary Black Hole Mergers, their Electromagnetic Counterparts, and Galactic Black Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13270v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a formation pathway linking black holes (BHs) observed in gravitational-wave (GW) mergers, wide BH-stellar systems uncovered by Gaia, and accreting low-mass X-ray binaries (LMXBs). In this scenario, a stellar-mass BH binary undergoes isolated binary evolution and merges while hosting a distant, dynamically unimportant tertiary stellar companion. The tertiary becomes relevant only after the merger, when the remnant BH receives a GW recoil kick. Depending on the kick velocity and system configuration, the outcome can be: (i) a bright electromagnetic (EM) counterpart to the GW merger; (ii) an LMXB; (iii) a wide BH-stellar companion resembling the Gaia BH population; or (iv) an unbound, isolated BH. Modeling the three-body dynamics, we find that $\sim 0.02\%$ of LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA (LVK) mergers may be followed by an EM counterpart within $\sim$10 days, produced by tidal disruption of the star by the BH. The flare is likely brightest in the optical-UV and lasts days to weeks; in some cases, partial disruption causes recurring flares with a period of $\sim$2 months. We further estimate that this channel can produce $\sim 1-10\%$ of Gaia BH systems in the Milky Way. This scenario provides the first physically motivated link between GW sources, Gaia BHs, and some X-ray binaries, and predicts a rare but robust pathway for EM counterparts to binary BH mergers, potentially detectable in LVK's O5 run.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13270v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Smadar Naoz, Zoltan Haiman, Eliot Quataert, Liz Holzknecht</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization properties of synchrotron sources from simulations of relativistic magnetohydrodynamic turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.20620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.20620v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The emission from the relativistically hot plasmas of high-energy astrophysical synchrotron sources, pulsar wind nebulae (PWNe) in particular, depends on the level of magnetic fluctuations. Recent observations by the X-ray polarimeter IXPE support the presence of turbulence, with varying conditions even in different regions of a same source. We model such emission, and in particular the degree of linear polarization, by using 3D relativistic magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) turbulence simulations for the first time. Thanks to a novel accelerated version of the ECHO code, a series of 3D relativistic MHD simulations were performed assuming a relativistically hot plasma and various degrees of magnetization, mimicking different conditions encountered in synchrotron sources. Magnetic fluctuations at random directions with respect to a background field were initialized at large scales. After the full development of the turbulent cascade, the statistical properties of the plasma and of the synchrotron emission maps were analyzed. Turbulence rapidly relaxes to a sort of Alfv\'enic equilibrium and a Kolmogorov cascade with a slope of $-5/3$ soon develops, with differences depending on the initial ratio, $\eta$, of magnetic fluctuations over the background field. Dissipation mostly occurs in thin current sheets, where (numerical) reconnection takes place and intermittency and deviation from isotropic Gaussian distributions are observed. Synthetic synchrotron maps and their statistical properties depend on $\eta$ too, approaching analytical estimates for large $\eta$. The integrated degree of linear polarization is found to cover the whole range of observed values in PWNe, and its dependence on the relative amplitude of turbulent fluctuations shows a good agreement with analytical estimates, even in the presence of anisotropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.20620v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Del Zanna, Niccol\`o Bucciantini, Simone Landi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Illuminating dark matter admixed in neutron stars with simultaneous mass-radius constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07767v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate how simultaneous mass and radius measurements of massive neutron stars (NSs) can help constrain properties of dark matter (DM) possibly admixed in them. Within a fermionic DM model that interacts only through gravitation, along with a well-constrained nuclear matter equation of state, we show that the simultaneous mass and radius measurement of PSRJ0740+6620 reduces the uncertainty of DM central energy density by more than 50\% compared to the results obtained from using the two observables independently, while other DM parameters remain unconstrained. Additionally, we find that the DM fraction $f_D$ should be smaller than 2\% when constrained by the observed NS maximum mass alone, and it could be even smaller than 0.3\% with the simultaneous measurement of mass and radius, supporting the conclusion that only a small amount of DM exists in DM admixed neutron stars (DANS).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07767v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/sym17101669</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Symmetry, 17, 1669 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nai-Bo Zhang, Bao-An Li, Jia-Yu Zhang, Wei-Na Shen, Hui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advanced Weights for IXPE Polarization Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07981v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As the Imaging X-ray Polarimetry Explorer (IXPE) measures increasingly faint sources, the need for precise polarimetry extraction becomes paramount. In addition to previously described neural-net (NN) weights, we introduce here point-spread function weights and particle background weights, which can be critical for faint sources. In some cases these can be augmented by time/phase and energy weights. We provide a publicly available analysis tool to incorporate these new weights, validate our method on simulated data, and test it on archival IXPE observations. Together these weights decrease the area of the polarization uncertainty contour by a factor of two compared to baseline IXPE analysis and will be essential for background-limited IXPE observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07981v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack T. Dinsmore, Roger W. Romani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expected Constraints on the Intergalactic Magnetic Field using Gamma-Ray Bursts with the Cherenkov Telescope Array Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.16092v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The InterGalactic Magnetic Field (IGMF), which could permeate the cosmic voids but was never detected so far, is considered a relic of the early Universe. Constraints on its strength $B$ can be derived from its influence on time-delayed very-high-energy photons from Gamma-Ray Bursts (GRBs) in the electromagnetic cascades along their path to the Earth. The present lower limit achieved on its intensity is $10^{-18}\;\mathrm{G}$. In this work, we simulate data from the Cherenkov Telescope Array Observatory (CTAO), accounting for realistic observational constraints, and we apply a joint spectral and temporal fit to characterise the IGMF. GRBs 190114C and 221009A are used as test cases to assess the sensitivity of CTAO. They demonstrate that a broad range of IGMF strengths can be probed with a lower bound as high as $10^{-15}\;\mathrm{G}$. Notably, we show that observations by the CTAO first large telescope, LST-1, already allow us to exclude field strengths up to $3\times 10^{-17}\;\mathrm{G}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.16092v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T\'en\'eman Keita, Renaud Belmont, Thierry Stolarczyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Gaussian Methods for Robust Background Modeling in CALorimetric Electron Telescope (CALET) Gravitational-Wave Searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25893</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25893v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The search for gamma-ray counterparts to gravitational-wave events with the CALET Gamma-ray Burst Monitor (CGBM) requires accurate and robust background modeling. Previous CALET observing runs (O3 and O4) relied on averaged pre/post-event baselines or low-order polynomial fits, approaches that neglect correlated noise, temporal non-stationarity, and the propagation of background uncertainty into derived flux upper limits. These simplifications can lead to reduced sensitivity to faint or atypical transients. In this work, we present a novel Bayesian framework for background estimation based on Gaussian Process (GP) regression and change-point modeling. Our approach captures correlated structures in the detector background, quantifies predictive uncertainties, and propagates them into both detection statistics and Bayesian credible upper limits. We demonstrate, using archival CALET time-tagged event data and simulated signal injections, that our method improves sensitivity to weak short-duration bursts by up to an order of magnitude compared to traditional polynomial fits. This probabilistic background treatment enables a more physically robust interpretation of non-detections and offers a scalable, real-time compatible extension for future joint multi-messenger searches. All codes used in this paper are available at https://github.com/SMALLSCALEDEV/Bayesian-Gaussian-Approach-for-Background-Estimation-in-CALET-GW.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25893v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bisweswar Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EUSO-SPB2 sensitivity to macroscopic dark matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.01152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2104.01152v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Macroscopic dark matter (or macro) provides a broad class of alternative candidates to particle dark matter. These candidates would transfer energy primarily through elastic scattering, and this linear energy deposition would produce observable signals if a macro were to traverse the atmosphere. We study the fluorescence emission produced by a macro passing through the atmosphere. We estimate the sensitivity of EUSO-SPB2 to constrain the two-dimensional parameter space ($\sigma$ vs. $M$), where $M$ is the macro mass and $\sigma$ its cross sectional area.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2104.01152v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas C. Paul (CUNY), Sarah T. Reese (CUNY), Luis A. Anchordoqui (CUNY), Angela V. Olinto (University of Chicago)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leptodermic corrections to the TOV equations and nuclear astrophysics within the effective surface approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04745v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The macroscopic model for a neutron star (NS) as a liquid drop at the equilibrium
  is used to extend the Tolman-Oppenheimer-Volkoff (TOV) equations taking into account the gradient terms
  responsible for the system surface. The parameters of the Schwarzschild metric in the spherical case
  are found with these surface corrections to the known leading (zero) order of the leptodermic approximation
  $a/R&lt;&lt;1$, where $a$ is the NS effective-surface (ES) thickness, and $R$ is the effective NS radius.
  The energy density $\mathcal{E}$ is considered in a general form including the functions of the particle number
  density and of its gradient terms. The macroscopic gravitational component $\Phi(\rho)$ of the energy density
  is taken into account in the simplest form as expansion in powers of $\rho-\overline{\rho} $, where
  $\overline{\rho}$ is the saturation density, up to second order, in terms of its contributions to the
  separation particle energy and incompressibility. Density distributions $\rho$ across the NS ES in the
  normal direction to the ES, which are derived in the simple analytical form at the same leading approximation, was
  used for the derivation of the modified TOV (MTOV) equations by accounting for their NS surface corrections.
  The MTOV equations are analytically solved at first order and the results are compared with the standard
  TOV approach of the zero order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04745v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysa.2025.123239</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nucl.Phys.A 1064 (2025) 123239</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. G. Magner, S. P. Maydanyuk, A. Bonasera, H. Zheng, T. Depastas, A. I. Levon, U. V. Grygoriev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrino production in the central dark-matter spikes of active galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09500v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent multi-messenger observations suggest that high-energy neutrinos may be produced close to central black holes in active galaxies. These regions may host dark-matter (DM) spikes, where the concentration of DM particles is very high. Here we explore the contribution of the DM annihilation to the target photons for the neutrino production, proton-photon interactions, estimate the associated neutrino spectrum and figure out possible future tests of this scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09500v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-025-14848-w</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C 85, 1100 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Polina Kivokurtseva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Fast and the Frame-Dragging: Efficient waveforms for asymmetric-mass eccentric equatorial inspirals into rapidly-spinning black holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09470v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Observations of gravitational-wave signals emitted by compact binary inspirals provide unique insights into their properties, but their analysis requires accurate and efficient waveform models. Intermediate- and extreme-mass-ratio inspirals (I/EMRIs), with mass ratios $q \gtrsim 10^2$, are promising sources for future detectors such as the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA). Modelling waveforms for these asymmetric-mass binaries is challenging, entailing the tracking of many harmonic modes over thousands to millions of cycles. The FastEMRIWaveforms (FEW) modelling framework addresses this need, leveraging precomputation of mode data and interpolation to rapidly compute adiabatic waveforms for eccentric inspirals into zero-spin black holes. In this work, we extend FEW to model eccentric equatorial inspirals into black holes with spin magnitudes $|a| \leq 0.999$. Our model supports eccentricities $e &lt; 0.9$ and semi-latus recta $p &lt; 200$, enabling the generation of long-duration IMRI waveforms, and produces waveforms in $\sim 100$ ms with hardware acceleration. Characterising systematic errors, we estimate that our model attains mismatches of $\sim 10^{-5}$ (for LISA sensitivity) with respect to error-free adiabatic waveforms over most of parameter space. We find that kludge models introduce errors in signal-to-noise ratios (SNRs) as great as $^{+60\%}_{-40\%}$ and induce marginal biases of up to $\sim 1\sigma$ in parameter estimation. We show LISA's horizon redshift for I/EMRI signals varies significantly with $a$, reaching a redshift of $3$ ($15$) for EMRIs (IMRIs) with only minor $(\sim10\%)$ dependence on $e$ for an SNR threshold of 20. For signals with SNR $\sim 50$, spin and eccentricity-at-plunge are measured with uncertainties of $\delta a \sim 10^{-7}$ and $\delta e_f \sim 10^{-5}$. This work advances the state-of-the-art in waveform generation for asymmetric-mass binaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09470v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian E. A. Chapman-Bird, Lorenzo Speri, Zachary Nasipak, Ollie Burke, Michael L. Katz, Alessandro Santini, Shubham Kejriwal, Philip Lynch, Josh Mathews, Hassan Khalvati, Jonathan E. Thompson, Soichiro Isoyama, Scott A. Hughes, Niels Warburton, Alvin J. K. Chua, Maxime Pigou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining Cubic Curvature Corrections to General Relativity with Quasi-Periodic Oscillations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22548v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate observational constraints on cubic curvature corrections to general relativity by analyzing quasi-periodic oscillations (QPOs) in accreting black hole systems. In particular, we study Kerr black hole solution corrected by cubic curvature terms parameterized by $\beta_5$ and $\beta_6$. While $\beta_6$ corresponds to a field-redefinition invariant structure, the $\beta_5$ term can in principle be removed via a field redefinition. Nonetheless, since we work in the frame where the accreting matter minimally couples to the metric, $\beta_5$ is in general present. Utilizing the corrected metric, we compute the QPO frequencies within the relativistic precession framework. Using observational data from GRO J1655$-$40 and a Bayesian analysis, we constrain the coupling parameters to $-12.31&lt;\frac{\beta_5}{(5 M_\odot)^4}&lt;24.15$ and $-1.99&lt;\frac{\beta_6}{(5 M_\odot)^4}&lt;0.30$ at 2-$\sigma$. These bounds improve upon existing constraints from big-bang nucleosynthesis and the speed of gravitational waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22548v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alireza Allahyari, Liang Ma, Shinji Mukohyama, Yi Pang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composition of scalar mesons and their effects on nuclear matter properties in an extended linear sigma model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10049v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It has been argued that the iso-scalar and iso-vector mesons play significant roles in nuclear matter and neutron star structures. We improve the extended linear sigma model with baryons, proposed in our previous work, by introducing the flavor structures constructed from antisymmetric tensors of chiral representations to study these physics. The parameter space of this model is refined with well-reproduced nuclear matter properties at saturation density by the lowest order Lagrangian, ensuring consistency with vacuum results, such as $f_\pi \approx 134 \, \text{MeV}$. The anticipated plateau-like behaviors of the symmetry energy are predicted at intermediate densities, which is crucial for the consistency of GW170817 and the neutron skin thickness of $\text{Pb}^{208}$. Subsequently, neutron star structures are calculated using several parameter sets, and the results for the nuclear matter properties at saturation density align with empirical values. It is found that the neutron star structures are sensitive to the couplings between the iso-vector $a_0$ meson and nucleons and the four-vector meson couplings: small values of both are favorable. Meanwhile, nuclear matter properties at saturation density favor larger values of the latter and are not sensitive to the former. This signifies the statistical significance of neutron star observations when obtaining realistic chiral effective field theories or models at various densities. The parameter set favored by neutron star observations also aligns the behavior of the sound velocity with the conformal limit at high densities relevant to cores of massive stars. It is hoped that the results of this work can guide future studies on the relationship between the microscopic symmetry of strong interactions and macroscopic phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10049v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/p4xz-4ggf</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yao Ma, Yong-Liang Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sub-GeV Right-Handed Neutrino as a Probe of Neutrino Mass Generation in the Minimal Left-Right Symmetric Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15609v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The minimal left-right symmetric model (mLRSM) provides an elegant and testable framework for addressing the origin of neutrino masses. We examine the constraints on the sub-GeV right-handed (RH) neutrino in the type-II seesaw scenario of the mLRSM without left-right mixing, taking limits from collider searches, meson decays, supernovae, neutrinoless double beta ($0\nu\beta\beta$) decay and cosmology. Specifically, we derive the $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay constraints using the advanced effective field theory approach and up-to-date nuclear matrix element calculations. Besides, we update the SN1987A cooling bound with the state-of-the-art simulations, provide new constraints from the energy deposition in the supernova ejecta, and incorporate the stringent RH neutrino lifetime upper limit $\tau\lesssim 0.023\text{ s}$ from the big bang nucleosynthesis. Our results identify the parameter region compatible with all current experimental and observational constraints, where the RH neutrino mass lies between 700 MeV and 1 GeV and the RH $W$ boson mass is slightly below 20 TeV. This region is exclusively probed by the future tonne-scale $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay experiments, providing a unique window to test the mLRSM and the possible origin of neutrino masses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15609v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gang Li, Ying-Ying Li, Sida Lu, Ye-Ling Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A long period transient search method for the Murchison Widefield Array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.06315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.06315v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an automated search method for radio transients on the minute timescale focused on the emerging long period transients (LPTs) in image-plane radio data. The method is tuned for use with the Murchison Widefield Array (MWA) and tested on archival observations from the GaLactic and Extragalactic All-Sky MWA Extended Survey (GLEAM-X) in the 70--300 MHz range. The images are formed from model-subtracted visibilities, before applying three filters to the time series of each pixel in an image, with each filter designed to be sensitive to a different transient behaviour. Due to the nature of radio interferometry and the refraction of the fluctuating ionosphere, the vast majority of candidates at this stage are artefacts which we identify and remove using a set of flagging measures. Of the 336 final candidates, 7 were genuine transients; 1 new LPT, 1 new pulsar, and 5 known pulsars. The performance of the method is analysed by injecting modelled transient pulses into a subset of the observations and applying the method to the result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.06315v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/pasa.2025.10093</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Publications of the Astronomical Society of Australia 42 (2025) e129</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Csan\'ad Horv\'ath, Natasha Hurley-Walker, Samuel J. McSweeney, Timothy J. Galvin, John Morgan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Do plasmoids induce fast magnetic reconnection in well-resolved current sheets in 2D MHD simulations?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01060v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the development of tearing-mode instability using the highest resolution two-dimensional magnetohydrodynamic simulations of reconnecting current sheets on a uniform grid, for Lundquist numbers $10^3 \le S \le 2 \times 10^5$. Although the tearing-mode instability is commonly thought to trigger a plasmoid cascade that enables fast reconnection - i.e., independent of $S$ - our results, in broad agreement with the recent findings of Morillo \&amp; Alexakis (2025), challenge this belief. We demonstrate a Sweet-Parker scaling of the reconnection rate $V_{\text{rec}} \sim S^{-1/2}$ up to Lundquist numbers $S \sim 10^4$. For larger values, plasmoid formation sets in leading to a slight enhancement of the reconnection rate, $V_{\text{rec}} \sim S^{-1/3}$, consistent with the prediction from linear tearing mode induced reconnection, indicating that reconnection remains resistivity dependent, and therefore slow. In our simulations, the plasmoids do not form a cascade of mergers, as they are rapidly advected out of the reconnection layer. Our findings call for the revision of the role of plasmoid formation in 2D high Lundquist number magnetic reconnection. Even if future studies demonstrate that 2D plasmoid-reconnection becomes resistivity-independent at sufficiently large $S$, directly extending those results to 3D astrophysical environments is not justified, as in realistic circumstances, the increase of $S$ also raises the Reynolds number of the outflows, making it essential to account for the dominant role of turbulence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01060v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. H. Vicentin, G. Kowal, E. M. de Gouveia Dal Pino, A. Lazarian</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
