<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.PE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.PE</link>
    <description>q-bio.PE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.PE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 05:00:47 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Population growth on a time varying network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07821v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a population spreading across a finite number of sites. Individuals can move from one site to the other according to a network (oriented links between the sites) that vary periodically over time. On each site, the population experiences a growth rate which is also periodically time varying. Recently, this kind of models have been extensively studied, using various technical tools to derive precise necessary and sufficient conditions on the parameters of the system (ie the local growth rate on each site, the time period and the strength of migration between the sites) for the population to grow. In the present paper, we take a completely different approach: using elementary comparison results between linear systems, we give sufficient condition for the growth of the population This condition is easy to check and can be applied in a broad class of examples. In particular, in the case when all sites are sinks (ie, in the absence of migration, the population become extinct in each site), we prove that when our condition of growth if satisfied, the population grows when the time period is large and for values of the migration strength that are exponentially small with respect to the time period, which answers positively to a conjecture stated by Katriel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07821v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michel Bena\"im, Claude Lobry, Tewfik Sari, Edouard Strickler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computational Approaches of Modelling Human Papillomavirus Transmission and Prevention Strategies: A Systematic Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19235v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Human papillomavirus (HPV) infection is the most common sexually transmitted infection in the world. Persistent oncogenic Human papillomavirus infection has been a leading threat to global health and can lead to serious complications such as cervical cancer. Prevention interventions including vaccination and screening have been proved effective in reducing the risk of HPV-related diseases. In recent decades, computational epidemiology has been serving as a very useful tool to study HPV transmission dynamics and evaluation of prevention strategies. In this paper, we conduct a comprehensive literature review on state-of-the-art computational epidemic models for HPV disease dynamics, transmission dynamics, as well as prevention efforts. We summarise current research trends, identify gaps in the present literature, and identify future research directions with potential in accelerating the containment and/or elimination of HPV infection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19235v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiyi Wang, Shailendra Sawleshwarkar, Mahendra Piraveenan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting institutional punishment in the $N$-person prisoner's dilemma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05884v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The conflict between individual and collective interests makes fostering cooperation in human societies a challenging task, requiring drastic measures such as the establishment of sanctioning institutions. These institutions are costly because they have to be maintained regardless of the presence or absence of offenders. Here we revisit some improvements to the standard $N$-person prisoner's dilemma formulation with institutional punishment in a well-mixed population, namely the elimination of overpunishment, the requirement of a minimum number of contributors to establish the sanctioning institution, and the sharing of its maintenance costs once this minimum number is reached. In addition, we focus on large groups or communities for which sanctioning institutions are ubiquitous. Using the replicator equation framework for an infinite population, we find that by sufficiently fining players who fail to contribute either to the public good or to the sanctioning institution, a population of contributors immune to invasion by these free riders can be established, provided that the contributors are sufficiently numerous. In a finite population, we use finite-size scaling to show that, for some parameter settings, demographic noise helps to fixate the strategy that contributes to the public good but not to the sanctioning institution even for infinitely large populations when, somewhat counterintuitively, its proportion in the initial population vanishes with a small power of the population size.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05884v3</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bianca Y. S. Ishikawa, Jos\'e F. Fontanari</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
