<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.PE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.PE</link>
    <description>q-bio.PE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.PE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 04:01:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Accounting for contact network uncertainty in epidemic inferences with Approximate Bayesian Computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When modeling the dynamics of infectious disease, the incorporation of contact network information allows for the capture of the non-randomness and heterogeneity of realistic contact patterns. Oftentimes, it is assumed that the underlying contact pattern is known with perfect certainty. However, in realistic settings, the observed data often serves as an imperfect proxy of the actual contact patterns in the population. Furthermore, the epidemic in the real world are often not fully observed; event times such as infection and recovery times may be missing. In order to conduct accurate inferences on parameters of contagion spread, it is crucial to incorporate these sources of uncertainty. In this paper, we propose the use of Mixture Density Network compressed ABC (MDN-ABC) to learn informative summary statistics for the available data. This method will allow for Bayesian inference on the epidemic parameters of a contagious process, while accounting for imperfect observations on the epidemic and the contact network. We will demonstrate the use of this method on simulated epidemics and networks, and extend this framework to analyze the spread of Tattoo Skin Disease (TSD) among bottlenose dolphins in Shark Bay, Australia.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02924v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxwell H. Wang, Jukka-Pekka Onnela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Opinion dynamics on biased dynamical networks: beyond rare opinion updating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02913v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Opinion dynamics is of paramount importance as it provides insights into the complex dynamics of opinion propagation and social relationship adjustment. It is assumed in most of the previous works that social relationships evolve much faster than opinions. This is not always true in reality. We propose an analytical approximation to study this issue for arbitrary time scales between opinion adjustment and network evolution. To this end, the coefficient of determination in statistics is introduced and a one-dimensional stable manifold is analytically found, i.e., the most likely trajectory. With the aid of the stable manifold, we further obtain the fate of opinions and the consensus time, i.e., fixation probability and fixation time. We find that for in-group bias, the more likely individuals are to adopt the popular opinion, the less likely the majority opinion takes over the population, i.e., conformity inhibits the domination of popular opinions. This counter-intuitive result can be interpreted from a game perspective, in which in-group bias refers to a coordination game and rewiring probability refers to a rescaling of the selection intensity. Our work proposes an efficient approximation method to foster the understanding of opinion dynamics in dynamical networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02913v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xunlong Wang, Bin Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Escape from a metastable state in non-Markovian population dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03481v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the long-time dynamics in non-Markovian single-population stochastic models, where one or more reactions are modelled as a stochastic process with a fat-tailed non-exponential distribution of waiting times, mimicking long-term memory. We focus on three prototypical examples: genetic switching, population establishment and population extinction, all with non-exponential production rates. The system is studied in two regimes. In the first, the distribution of waiting times has a finite mean. Here, the system approaches a (quasi)stationary steady state at long times, and we develop a general WKB approach for these non-Markovian systems. We derive explicit results for the mean population size and mean escape time from the metastable state of the stochastic dynamics. In this realm, we reveal that for sufficiently strong memory, a memory-induced (meta)stable state can emerge in the system. In the second regime, the waiting time distribution is assumed to have an infinite mean. Here, for bistable systems we find two distinct scaling regimes, separated by an exponentially long time which may strongly depend on the initial conditions of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03481v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ohad Vilk, Michael Assaf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some paradoxes in the Tilman model, how to avoid or accept them</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2101.07082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2101.07082v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In making models for biological systems one expects to grasp the biology and be able to use ones intuition to predict the outcome. This paper is about the discrepancy between what is expected and what is the outcome of the analysis of the model, a paradox. The Tilman model of consumers competing for resources has some aspects that may appear counterintuitive. Within the standard Tilman model for a single consumer and a single resource, when a very efficient consumer rapidly eats all available food, the resource density becomes zero, but if there is no food, how can the consumer survive? The paradox can be resolved by realising that in the short term indeed rapid consumption may lead to starvation and a decline in the consumer population, but in the long term a small resource and consumer density remain. A single consumer living on two essential nutrients leaves the density of the non-limiting nutrient above its critical level, so what is done with the extra food? We explain that the extra food is not consumed, just because it is available, but that in fact the additional food is not consumed at all, because the consumer has no use for it. For a model with two consumer species competing for a single nutrient one of the consumers will eventually disappear, even if the food economics of the surviving one is worse and there is still much food wasted. Both are inherent aspects of the model, and the paradox can be avoided if the difference between the consumer species is small, in which case it will take very long to reach equilibrium. We argue that in general an extended stability analysis, in which not only the asymptotically stable state is considered, but also the unstable steady states and all time scales involved in the transient dynamics, gives more insight in the dynamics involved and thus can help in avoiding apparent contradictions in ecological models, or accepting them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2101.07082v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joost H. J. van Opheusden, Lia Hemerik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upper Bounds on Overshoot in SIR Models with Nonlinear Incidence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.01653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.01653v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We expand the calculation of the upper bound on epidemic overshoot in SIR models to account for nonlinear incidence. We lay out the general procedure and restrictions to perform the calculation analytically. We demonstrate the procedure by working through several examples and also numerically study what happens to the upper bound on overshoot when nonlinear incidence manifests in the form of epidemic dynamics over a contact network. We find that both steeper incidence terms and larger contact heterogeneity can increase the range of communicable diseases at which the overshoot remains a relatively large public health hazard.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.01653v4</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
