<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.PE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.PE</link>
    <description>q-bio.PE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.PE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 04:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Epidemic modelling requires knowledge of the social network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07881v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Compartmental models of epidemics are widely used to forecast the effects of communicable diseases such as COVID-19 and to guide policy. Although it has long been known that such processes take place on social networks, the assumption of random mixing is usually made, which ignores network structure. However, super-spreading events have been found to be power-law distributed, suggesting that the underlying networks may be scale free or at least highly heterogeneous. The random-mixing assumption would then produce an overestimation of the herd-immunity threshold for given $R_0$; and a (more significant) overestimation of $R_0$ itself. These two errors compound each other, and can lead to forecasts greatly overestimating the number of infections. Moreover, if networks are heterogeneous and change in time, multiple waves of infection can occur, which are not predicted by random mixing. A simple SIR model simulated on both Erd\H{o}s-R\'enyi and scale-free networks shows that details of the network structure can be more important than the intrinsic transmissibility of a disease. It is therefore crucial to incorporate network information into standard models of epidemics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07881v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/2632-072X/ad19e0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Complex. 5 (2024) 01LT01</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Johnson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating the Impact of Vaccine Hesitancy on the Allocation of Vital Resources During COVID-19 Pandemic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07971</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07971v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The COVID-19 pandemic highlighted significant challenges in the allocation of vital healthcare resources. Existing epidemiological models, specifically compartmental models, aimed to predict the spread of the COVID-19 virus and its impact on the population, but they overlooked the influence of \ac{VH} on disease dynamics, including the expected number of hospitalizations and fatalities. We propose improvements to the \ac{SEIR} model for COVID-19 by incorporating the influence of vaccination, \ac{VH}, and resource availability on the disease dynamics. We collect publicly available data and perform data analysis to capture \ac{VH} dynamic changes over time and develop scenario paths for \ac{VH}. We simulate the proposed compartmental model for each \ac{VH} path to explain the impacts of public attitudes toward vaccination, the impacts of healthcare resources on patient outcomes, and the timing of vaccination rollout on the progression and severity of the epidemic. Our analysis demonstrates that reducing \ac{VH} improves health outcomes, reinforcing the importance of addressing \ac{VH} to curb the spread of infectious diseases. Our results show that adequate levels of critical healthcare resources are crucial for minimizing fatalities and also highlight the life-saving impact of timely and effective vaccination programs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07971v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hieu Bui, Sandra Eksioglu, Ruben Proano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GTP before ATP: The energy currency at the origin of genes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08744v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Life is an exergonic chemical reaction. Many individual reactions in metabolism entail slightly endergonic processes that are coupled to free energy release, typically as ATP hydrolysis, in order to go forward. ATP is almost always supplied by the rotor-stator ATP synthetase (the ATPase), which harnesses chemiosmotic ion gradients. Because the ATPase is a protein, it arose after the ribosome did. Here we address two questions using comparative physiology: What was the energy currency of metabolism before the origin of the ATPase? How (and why) did ATP come to be the universal energy currency? About 27 percent of a cell's energy budget is consumed as GTP during translation. The universality of GTP-dependence in ribosome function indicates that GTP was the ancestral energy currency of protein synthesis. The use of GTP in translation and ATP in small molecule synthesis are conserved across all lineages, representing energetic compartments that arose in the last universal common ancestor, LUCA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08744v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Natalia Mrnjavac, William F. Martin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Determinants of successful disease control through voluntary quarantine dynamics on social networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.06297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.06297v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the wake of epidemics, quarantine measures are typically recommended by health authorities or governments to help control the spread of the disease. Compared with mandatory quarantine, voluntary quarantine offers individuals the liberty to decide whether to isolate themselves in case of infection exposure, driven by their personal assessment of the trade-off between economic loss and health risks as well as their own sense of social responsibility and concern for public health. To better understand self-motivated health behavior choices under these factors, here we incorporate voluntary quarantine into an endemic disease model -- the susceptible-infected-susceptible (SIS) model -- and perform comprehensive agent-based simulations to characterize the resulting behavior-disease interactions in structured populations. We quantify the conditions under which voluntary quarantine will be an effective intervention measure to mitigate disease burden. Furthermore, we demonstrate how individual decision-making factors, including the level of temptation to refrain from quarantine and the degree of social compassion, impact compliance levels of voluntary quarantines and the consequent collective disease mitigation efforts. We find that successful disease control requires either a sufficiently low level of temptation or a sufficiently high degree of social compassion, such that even complete containment of the epidemic is attainable. In addition to well-mixed populations, our simulation results are applicable to other more realistic social networks of contacts, including spatial lattices, small-world networks, and real social networks. Our work offers new insights into the fundamental social dilemma aspect of disease control through non-pharmaceutical interventions, such as voluntary quarantine and isolation, where the collective outcome of individual decision-making is crucial.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.06297v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simiao Shi, Zhiyuan Wang, Xingru Chen, Feng Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infection-induced Cascading Failures -- Impact and Mitigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.16767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.16767v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Two-layer spreading processes on unidirectionally dependent networks are studied, where the spreading infection of diseases or malware in one layer can trigger cascading failures in another layer and lead to secondary disasters, e.g., disrupting public services, supply chains, or power distribution. We utilize the dynamic message-passing method to devise efficient algorithms for inferring the system states, which allows one to investigate systematically the nature of such complex intertwined spreading processes and evaluate their impact. Based on the dynamic message-passing framework and optimal control, we further develop an effective optimization algorithm for mitigating network failures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.16767v3</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo Li, David Saad</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
