<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.PE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.PE</link>
    <description>q-bio.PE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.PE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2024 02:02:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ages, sizes and (trees within) trees of taxa and of urns, from Yule to today</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14536v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paper written in 1925 by G. Udny Yule that we celebrate in this special issue introduces several novelties and results that we recall in detail.
  First, we discuss Yule (1925)'s main legacies over the past century, focusing on empirical frequency distributions with heavy tails and random tree models for phylogenies. We estimate the year when Yule's work was re-discovered by scientists interested in stochastic processes of population growth (1948) and the year from which it began to be cited (1951, Yule's death). We highlight overlooked aspects of Yule's work (e.g., the Yule process of Yule processes) and correct some common misattributions (e.g., the Yule tree).
  Second, we generalize Yule's results on the average frequency of genera of a given age and size (number of species). We show that his formula also applies to the age $A$ and size $S$ of any randomly chosen genus and that the pairs $(A_i, S_i)$ are equally distributed and independent across genera. This property extends to triples $(H_i, A_i, S_i)$, where $(H_i)$ are the coalescence times of the genus phylogeny, even when species diversification within genera follows any integer-valued process, including species extinctions. Studying $(A, S)$ in this broader context allows us to identify cases where $S$ has a power-law tail distribution, with new applications to urn schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14536v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amaury Lambert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The zero-sum rock-paper-scissors game with non-exponential waiting times</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14581v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Waiting times between successive events play an important role in population dynamics and can vary widely, notably due to environmental conditions. In this work, we focus on the zero-sum rock-paper-scissors (zRPS) model, broadly used to describe cyclic dominance in ecology and biology, with non-Markovian dynamics and study how its survival and fixation properties are affected by interevent times. When the dynamics are Markovian, with exponentially-distributed waiting times, the fate of zRPS games in large well-mixed populations obeys the simple, yet counterintuitive, ``law of the weakest'': the species with the lowest predation-reproduction rate is the most likely to prevail, with a fixation/survival probability asymptotically approaching one. Here, we systematically study how the fixation/survival behavior is influenced by power-law and gamma waiting time distributions, and analyze the deviations from the law of the weakest. Importantly, we determine the phases of the parameter space in which each species dominates, and how these crucially depend on memory and history-dependent interactions. Analytical calculations, which yield nontrivial memory kernels, support our numerical results, shedding light on the evolutionary influence of long waiting times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14581v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ohad Vilk, Mauro Mobilia, Michael Assaf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometry-Induced Competitive Release in a Meta-Population Model for Range Expansions in Disordered Media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15221v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rare evolutionary events, such as the rise to prominence of deleterious mutations, can have drastic impacts on the evolution of growing populations. Heterogeneous environments can reduce the influence of selection on evolutionary outcomes through various mechanisms, including pinning of genetic lineages and of the population fronts. These effects can play significant roles in enabling competitive release of otherwise trapped mutations. In this work we show that environments containing random arrangements of ``hotspot'' patches, where locally abundant resources enhance growth rates equally for all sub-populations, can give rise to massively enriched deleterious mutant clones through an effective reduction of selection efficacy. A geometrical optics description of mutant bubbles, which result from interactions with hotspots, successfully predicts the increase in mutant survival. This prediction requires no fitting parameters and holds well in scenarios of rare mutations and of adaptation from standing variation. In addition, we find that the influence of environmental noise in shaping the fate of rare mutations is maximal near a percolation transition of overlapping discs, beyond which mutant survival decreases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15221v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jimmy Gonzalez Nu\~nez, Daniel A. Beller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Wild Sheep Chase Through an Orchard</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10769v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Orchards are a biologically relevant class of phylogenetic networks as they can describe treelike evolutionary histories augmented with horizontal transfer events. Moreover, the class has attractive mathematical characterizations that can be exploited algorithmically. On the other hand, undirected orchard networks have hardly been studied yet. Here, we prove that deciding whether an undirected, binary phylogenetic network is an orchard -- or equivalently, whether it has an orientation that makes it a rooted orchard -- is NP-hard. For this, we introduce a new characterization of undirected orchards which could be useful for proving positive results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10769v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordan Dempsey, Leo van Iersel, Mark Jones, Yukihiro Murakami, Norbert Zeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A three-state coupled Markov switching model for COVID-19 outbreaks across Quebec based on hospital admissions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.02488v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recurrent COVID-19 outbreaks have placed immense strain on the hospital system in Quebec. We develop a Bayesian three-state coupled Markov switching model to analyze COVID-19 outbreaks across Quebec based on admissions in the 30 largest hospitals. Within each catchment area, we assume the existence of three states for the disease: absence, a new state meant to account for many zeroes in some of the smaller areas, endemic and outbreak. Then we assume the disease switches between the three states in each area through a series of coupled nonhomogeneous hidden Markov chains. Unlike previous approaches, the transition probabilities may depend on covariates and the occurrence of outbreaks in neighboring areas, to account for geographical outbreak spread. Additionally, to prevent rapid switching between endemic and outbreak periods we introduce clone states into the model which enforce minimum endemic and outbreak durations. We make some interesting findings, such as that mobility in retail and recreation venues had a positive association with the development and persistence of new COVID-19 outbreaks in Quebec. Based on model comparison our contributions show promise in improving state estimation retrospectively and in real-time, especially when there are smaller areas and highly spatially synchronized outbreaks. Furthermore, our approach offers new and interesting epidemiological interpretations, such as being able to estimate the effect of covariates on disease extinction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.02488v3</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dirk Douwes-Schultz, Alexandra M. Schmidt, Yannan Shen, David Buckeridge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Good modelling software practices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.21051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.21051v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Frequently in socio-environmental sciences, models are used as tools to represent, understand, project and predict the behaviour of these complex systems. Along the modelling chain, Good Modelling Practices have been evolving that ensure - amongst others - that models are transparent and their results replicable. Whenever such models are represented in software, Good Modelling meet Good Software Practices, such as a tractable development workflow, good code, collaborative development and governance, continuous integration and deployment; and they meet Good Scientific Practices, such as attribution of copyrights and acknowledgement of intellectual property, publication of a software paper and archiving. Too often in existing socio-environmental model software, these practices have been regarded as an add-on to be considered at a later stage only; modellers have shied away from publishing their model as open source out of fear that having to add good practices is too demanding. We here argue for making a habit of following a list of simple and not so simple practices early on in the implementation of the model life cycle. We contextualise cherry-picked and hands-on practices for supporting Good Modelling Practice, and we demonstrate their application in the example context of the Viable North Sea fisheries socio-ecological systems model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.21051v4</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2024.110890</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Ecological Modelling, 498, 110890 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Carsten Lemmen, Philipp Sebastian Sommer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
