<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.PE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.PE</link>
    <description>q-bio.PE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.PE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 05:00:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo-biodiversity effects across scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.22158v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the last decade several attempts have been made to extend biodiversity studies in ways that would allow researchers to explore how biodiversity-ecosystem functioning relationships may change across different spatial and temporal scales. Unfortunately, the studies based on these attempts often overlooked the serious issues that can arise when quantifying biodiversity effects at larger scales, specifically the fact that biodiversity effects measured across space and time can contain trivial effects that are unrelated to the role of biodiversity per se -- or even effects that are non-biological in nature due to being simple artefacts of how properties and entities are counted and quantified. Here we outline and describe three such pseudo-biodiversity effects: Population-level effects, Independence effects, and Arithmetic effects. Population-level effects are those related to temporal changes due to individual species population growth or development, and are thus independent of biodiversity. Independence and Arithmetic effects (which we explore here primarily in a spatial context) arise either as a simple consequence of the fact that not all species are present everywhere -- i.e., species turnover is inevitable at greater spatial scales (Independence effects); or they arise when the purported biodiversity effects measured are a simple byproduct of how mathematical functions behave (Arithmetic effects). Our study demonstrates the necessity of controlling for these trivial artefactual effects if one wishes to meaningfully measure how true biodiversity effects change across spatial and temporal scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.22158v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pradeep Pillai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A nonconservative kinetic framework with logistic growth for modeling the coexistence in a multi-species ecological system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22246</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.22246v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kinetic theory frameworks are widely used for modeling stochastic interacting systems, where the evolution primarily depends on binary interactions. Recently, in this framework the action of the external force field has been introduction in order to gain a more realistic picture of some phenomena. In this paper, we introduce nonconservative kinetic equations where a particular shape external force field acts on the overall system. Then, this framework is used in an ecological context for modeling the evolution of a system composed of two species interacting with a prey-predator mechanism. The linear stability analysis concerned with the coexistence equilibrium point is provided, and a case where a Hopf bifurcations occurs is discussed. Finally, some relevant scenarios are numerically simulated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.22246v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Menale, Carmelo Filippo Munaf\`o, Francesco Oliveri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The effect of dispersal area on the extinction threshold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.22506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.22506v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The survival of populations hinges on their ability to offset local extinctions through new colonizations. The dispersal area ($A$) plays a crucial role in this process, as it determines the probability of finding colonizable vacant sites. We investigated the spatial colonization-extinction dynamics in a lattice model (a contact process), exploring various finite dispersal areas and estimating the extinction threshold $\lambda_E(A)$. Our results revealed a consistent $\lambda_E(A)$ relationship, largely independent of lattice geometry (except for the smallest $A$). This $\lambda_E(A)$ relationship obeyed universal scaling laws within two broad ranges of $A$. The scaling relations suggest considerable selection upon the increase of dispersal area, particularly at low $A$ values. We discuss these findings in the broader context of the evolution of dispersal area.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.22506v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R\'obert Juh\'asz, Igor D. Kov\'acs, Be\'ata Oborny</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bandwidth Selection of Density Estimators over Treespaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.23442v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A kernel density estimator (KDE) is one of the most popular non-parametric density estimators. In this paper we focus on a best bandwidth selection method for use in an analogue of a classical KDE using the tropical symmetric distance, known as a tropical KDE, for use over the space of phylogenetic trees. We propose the likelihood cross validation (LCV) for selecting the bandwidth parameter for the KDE over the space of phylogenetic trees. In this paper, first, we show the explicit optimal solution of the best-fit bandwidth parameter via the LCV for tropical KDE over the space of phylogenetic trees. Then, computational experiments with simulated datasets generated under the multi-species coalescent (MSC) model show that a tropical KDE with the best-fit bandwidth parameter via the LCV perform better than a tropical KDE with an estimated best-fit bandwidth parameter via nearest neighbors in terms of accuracy and computational time. Lastly, we apply our method an empirical data from the Apicomplexa genome.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.23442v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruriko Yoshida, Zhiwen Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a compleat theory of ecosystem size spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00023v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The regularity of ecosystem size spectra is one of the most intriguing and relevant phenomena on our planet. Aquatic size spectra generally show a log-linearly downtrending shape, following a power-law distribution. A constant log-linear slope has been reported for many marine pelagic ecosystems, often being approximately b = -1. Conversely, there are variable trophic-level-biomass relationships (trophic pyramids). The contrasting observations of a constant biomass (M) spectrum slope and highly variable biomass pyramids may be defined as the constant size spectra-variable trophic dynamics paradox. Here, a mass-specific 'predator-prey-efficiency theory of size spectra' (PETS) is presented and discussed. A thorough analysis of available data, literature and models result in the conclusion that most pelagic marine ecosystems are controlled by trophic processes such as resource-limit stress (bottom-up control) and top-down regulation, with a key role of the carrying capacity of large-sized organisms. This has relevant consequences for the prediction and interpretation of size spectra and the context of fisheries, whaling, and the introduction of exotic predators (e.g., lionfish). The complete size spectrum obtained in situ, including living organisms and non-living particles (e.g., for data from LOPC and UVP) is discussed. This paper is intended as a plea for the integration of modeling approaches, to understand and integrate data and processes across communities including bacteria, phytoplankton, fish and mammals, considering the effect of non-organismic particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00023v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ralf Schwamborn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heuristic model on the origin of the homochirality of life</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.11136v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Life demonstrates remarkable homochirality of its major building blocks: nucleic acids, amino acids, sugars, and phospholipids. We propose a mechanism that places the root of life homochirality in the formation of phospholipid bilayer vesicles (liposomes). These liposomes are formed at the water-air interface from Langmuir layers and contain ribose, presumably delivered to Early Earth by carbonaceous meteorites. Although the extraterrestrial ribose was initially racemic, life is homochiral, based on D-ribose and its derivatives. The phospholipid membrane high permeability to D-ribose, combined with the ribose interaction with the bilayer charged phosphate groups, leads to ribose phosphorylation, forming D-ribose-5-phosphate. Once inside, the D-ribose-5-phosphate molecules cannot cross the membrane. The catalytic action of Fe (3+ions) greatly enhances the phosphorylation rate. Overall, this process is enantioselective, substantially favoring the buildup of D-ribose over L-ribose. Through liposome fusion, fission, and self-replication, this eventually leads to the Darwinian evolution of these structures and to the conversion of D-ribose-5-phosphate into complex functional molecules, such as ribozymes and RNA, and eventually into DNA, all of which inherit D-ribose chirality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.11136v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Subbotin, Gennady Fiksel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithms for Reconstructing B Cell Lineages in the Presence of Context-Dependent Somatic Hypermutation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.11693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.11693v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a method for approximating posterior probabilities of phylogenetic trees and reconstructing ancestral sequences under models of sequence evolution with site-dependence, where standard phylogenetic likelihood computations (pruning) fail. Our approach uses a combined data-augmentation and importance sampling scheme. A key advantage of our approach is the ability to leverage existing highly optimized phylogenetic software. We apply our approach to the reconstruction of B cell receptor affinity maturation lineages from high-throughput repertoire sequencing data and evaluate the impact of incorporating site-dependence on the reconstruction accuracy of both trees and ancestral sequences. We show that accounting for context-dependence during inference always improves the estimates of both ancestral sequences and lineage trees on simulated datasets. We also examine the impact of incorporating priors based on VDJ recombination models, and find that they significantly improve ancestral sequence reconstruction in germline-encoded regions, but increase errors in non-templated nucleotides. We propose a modified, piecewise prior to address this demonstrate that it improves empirical reconstruction accuracy. We apply our approach to the analysis of the HIV broadly neutralizing antibodies DH270 and CH235 which are important targets of current vaccine design efforts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.11693v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongkang Li, Kevin J. Wiehe, Scott C. Schmidler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mono- and Polyauxic Growth Kinetics: A Semi-Mechanistic Framework for Complex Biological Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05960v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Kinetic modeling of microbial growth is essential for the design, optimization, and scale-up of industrial bioprocesses. Classical empirical models often lack biologically interpretable parameters or fail to capture complex multiphasic (polyauxic) behaviors, while fully mechanistic models are impractical for systems involving complex substrates and mixed cultures. This study proposes a unified mathematical framework that reformulates the canonical Boltzmann and Gompertz equations into semi-mechanistic forms, explicitly defining the maximum specific reaction rate and lag phase duration. Polyauxic growth is represented as a weighted sum of sigmoidal phases, subject to stringent constraints that ensure parameter identifiability, temporal consistency, and biological plausibility. The methodology integrates a workflow to address nonlinear regression in high-dimensional parameter spaces. A two-stage optimization strategy using Differential Evolution for global search followed by L-BFGS-B for local refinement avoid bias and heuristic parameter initialization. A Charbonnier loss function and the Robust Regression and Outlier Removal procedure are employed to identify and mitigate experimental outliers. Model parsimony is enforced using Akaike (AIC, AICc) and Bayesian (BIC) information criteria to select the optimal number of growth phases and avoid overparameterization. The framework was evaluated using experimental anaerobic digestion datasets, demonstrating that conventional single-phase models can obscure relevant metabolic transitions in co-digestion systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05960v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gustavo Mockaitis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
