<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.flu-dyn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn</link>
    <description>physics.flu-dyn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 02:45:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Bubble dynamics in an inclined Hele-Shaw cell</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13916v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report experimental results on the dynamics of large bubbles in a Hele-Shaw cell subject to various inclination angles with respect to gravity. Low Reynolds number cases are studied by injecting bubbles in an stagnant water/UCON mixture in three different Hele-Shaw cell geometry. The leading order rise speed $v_b$ follows the Taylor-Saffman limit which is inversely proportional to the viscosity $\eta$, but directly proportional to the square of the cell gap $h$ and the effective gravity, accounting for cell tilt angle $\theta$. However, when the cell is inclined more and more, the bubble buoyancy in the cell gap leads to a substantial decrease in the rise speed, as compared to the Taylor-Saffman speed. Buoyancy pushes the bubble towards the top channel wall, whereby a difference between the lubrication film thickness on top of and underneath the rising bubble occurs. We attribute these observations to the loss of symmetry in the channel gap, due to cell inclination. Nonetheless, the top lubrication film is observed to follow the Bretherton scaling, namely, $(\eta v_b/\sigma)^{2/3}$, where $\sigma$ is the liquid surface tension while the bottom film does not exhibit such a scaling. Finally, we illustrate that a model incorporating a friction term to the power balance between buoyancy and viscous dissipation matches well with all experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13916v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevFluids.9.073601</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Fluids, volume 9, issue 7,pages 073601, July 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Monnet, J. John Soundar Jerome, Val\'erie Vidal, Sylvain Joubaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stokes flow of an evolving fluid film with arbitrary shape and topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14025v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dynamics of evolving fluid films in the viscous Stokes limit is relevant to various applications, such as the modeling of lipid bilayers in cells. While the governing equations were formulated by Scriven in 1960, solving for the flow of a deformable viscous surface with arbitrary shape and topology has remained a challenge. In this study, we present a straightforward discrete model based on variational principles to address this long-standing problem. We replace the classical equations, which are expressed with tensor calculus in local coordinate, with a simple coordinate-free, differential-geometric formulation. The formulation provides a fundamental understanding of the underlying mechanics and directly translates to discretization. We construct a discrete analogue of the system using the Onsager variational principle, which, in a smooth context, governs the flow of a viscous medium. In the discrete setting, instead of term-wise discretizing the coordinate-based Stokes equations, we construct a discrete Rayleighian for the system and derive the discrete Stokes equations via the variational principle. This approach results in a stable, structure-preserving variational integrator that solves the system on general manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14025v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cuncheng Zhu, David Saintillan, Albert Chern</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the streamwise velocity variance in the near-wall region of turbulent flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14104v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the behaviour of the streamwise velocity variance in turbulent wall-bounded flows using a DNS database of pipe flow up to $Re_{\tau} \approx 12000$. The analysis of the spanwise spectra in the viscous near-wall region strongly hints to the presence of an overlap layer between the inner- and the outer-scaled spectral ranges, featuring a $k_{\theta}^{-1+\alpha}$ decay (with $k_{\theta}$ the wavenumber in the azimuthal direction, and $\alpha \approx 0.18$), hence shallower than suggested by the classical formulation of the attached-eddy model. The key implication is that the contribution to the streamwise velocity variance from the largest scales of motion (superstructures) slowly declines as $Re_{\tau}^{-\alpha}$, and the integrated variance follows a defect power law of the type $\left&lt; u^2 \right&gt;^+ = A - B \, Re_{\tau}^{-\alpha}$, with constants $A$ and $B$ depending on $y^+$. The DNS data very well support this behaviour, which implies that strict wall scaling is restored in the infinite Reynolds number limit. The extrapolated limit distribution of the streamwise velocity variance features a buffer-layer peak value of $\left&lt; u^2 \right&gt;^+ \approx 12.1$, and an additional outer peak with larger magnitude. The analysis of the velocity spectra also suggests a similar behaviour of the dissipation rate of the streamwise velocity variance at the wall, which is expected to attain a limiting value of about $0.28$, hence slightly exceeding the value $0.25$ which was assumed in previous analyses~\citep{chen_21}. We have found evidence suggesting that the reduced near-wall influence of wall-attached eddies is likely linked to the formation of underlying turbulent Stokes layers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14104v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio Pirozzoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulation Method of Microscale Fluid-Structure Interactions: Diffuse-Resistance-Domain Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Direct numerical simulations (DNS) of microscale fluid-structure interactions (mFSI) in multicomponent multiphase flows pose many challenges such as the thermodynamic consistency of multiphysics couplings, the tracking of moving interfaces, and the dynamics of moving triple-phase contact lines. We propose and validate a generic DNS approach: Diffuse-Resistance-Domain (DRD). It overcomes the above challenges by employing Onsager's principle to formulate dynamic models and combining traditional diffuse-interface models for fluid-fluid interfacial dynamics with a novel implementation of complex fluid-solid interfacial conditions via smooth interpolations of dynamic-resistance coefficients across interfaces. After careful validation by benchmark simulations, we simulated three challenging mFSI problems taken from different fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14291v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Min Gao, Zhihao Li, Xinpeng Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Natural convection in the cytoplasm: Theoretical predictions of buoyancy-driven flows inside a cell</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14385v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The existence of temperature gradients within eukaryotic cells has been postulated as a source of natural convection in the cytoplasm, i.e. bulk fluid motion as a result of temperature-difference-induced density gradients. Recent computations have predicted that a temperature differential of $\Delta T \approx 1$ K between the cell nucleus and the cell membrane could be strong enough to drive significant intracellular material transport. We use numerical computations and theoretical calculations to revisit this problem in order to further understand the impact of temperature gradients on flow generation and advective transport within cells. Surprisingly, our computations yield flows that are an order of magnitude weaker than those obtained previously for the same relative size and position of the nucleus with respect to the cell membrane. To understand this discrepancy, we develop a semi-analytical solution of the convective flow inside a model cell using a bi-spherical coordinate framework, for the case of an axisymmetric cell geometry (i.e. when the displacement of the nucleus from the cell centre is aligned with gravity). We also calculate exact solutions for the flow when the nucleus is located concentrically inside the cell. The results from both theoretical analyses agree with our numerical results, thus providing a robust estimate of the strength of cytoplasmic natural convection and demonstrating that these are much weaker than previously predicted. Finally, we investigate the ability of the aforementioned flows to redistribute solute within a cell. Our calculations reveal that, in all but unrealistic cases, cytoplasmic convection has a negligible contribution toward enhancing the diffusion-dominated mass transfer of cellular material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14385v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1371/journal.pone.0307765</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Nikhil Desai, Weida Liao, Eric Lauga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Turbulent flows over porous and rough substrates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15244</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15244v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Turbulent flows over porous substrates are studied via a systematic exploration of the dependence of the flow properties on the substrate parameters, including permeability $K$, grain pitch $L$, and depth $h$. The study uses direct numerical simulations mainly for staggered-cube substrates with $L^+\approx10$ - $50$, $\sqrt{K}/L\approx0.01$ - $0.25$, and depths from $h=O(L)$ to $h\gg L$, ranging from typical impermeable rough surfaces to deep porous substrates. The results indicate that the permeability has significantly greater relevance than the grain size for the properties of the overlying flow, including the mean-flow slip and the shear across the interface, the drag increase relative to smooth-wall flow, and the statistics and spectra of the overlying turbulence, whereas the direct effect of grain size is only noticeable near the interface as grain-coherent flow fluctuations. The substrate depth also has a significant effect, with shallower substrates suppressing the effective transpiration at the interface. Based on the direct-simulation results, we propose an empirical `equivalent permeability' $K_{eq}^t$, that incorporates this effect and scales well the overlying turbulence for substrates with different depths, permeabilities, etc. Based on this, we propose a conceptual $h^+$-$\sqrt{K^+}$ regime diagram where, for any given substrate topology, turbulence transitions smoothly from that over impermeable rough surfaces with $h=O(L)$ to that over deep porous substrates with $h^+\gtrsim50$, with the latter limit determined by the typical lengthscale of the overlying pressure fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15244v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zengrong Hao, Ricardo Garc\'ia-Mayoral</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empirical large-scale extension of Yakhot's model of strong turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12194v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose an empirical extension of Yakhot's model of strong turbulence [V. Yakhot, Phys. Rev. E 57(2) (1998)] that correctly describes the statistics of longitudinal velocity increments not only in the inertial range but also for larger scales up to the system length scale L. Two additional parameters are introduced to the original equation for the probability density function of velocity increments. These parameters can be motivated by physical arguments and their values are fixed by large scale boundary conditions. The resultant model ensures correct convergence of structure functions at the system length scale, including vanishing slopes at L, and shows good agreement with experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12194v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christoph Renner</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
