<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.flu-dyn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn</link>
    <description>physics.flu-dyn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 04:00:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Second-Order, Variable-Resolution, Weakly-Compressible Smoothed Particle Hydrodynamics Scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20290v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The smoothed particle hydrodynamics (SPH) method has been widely used to simulate incompressible and slightly compressible fluid flows. Adaptive refinement strategies to dynamically increase the resolution of the particles to capture sharp gradients in the flow have also been developed. However, most of the SPH schemes in the literature are not second-order convergent (SOC). Both second-order convergence and adaptive resolution are considered grand challenge problems in the SPH community. In this paper, we propose, for the first time, a second-order convergent (SOC) adaptive refinement strategy along with a SOC weakly-compressible SPH scheme. We employ the method of manufactured solutions to systematically develop the scheme and validate the solver. We demonstrate the order of convergence of the entire scheme using the Taylor-Green vortex problem and then go on to demonstrate the applicability of the method to simulate flow past a circular cylinder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20290v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhinav Muta, Pawan Negi, Prabhu Ramachandran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wind turbine enhancement via Active Flow Control Implementation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20450v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The present research aims to enhance the efficiency of a DTU-10MW Horizontal Axis Wind Turbine (HAWT) via Active Flow Control (AFC) implementation and using Synthetic Jets (SJ). In the initial part of the study the flow around two airfoil sections cut along the wing turbine blade and for a wind speed of 10m/s is simulated using CFD-2D-RANS-K{\omega}-SST turbulence model, in order to obtain the time averaged boundary layer separation point and the associated vortex shedding frequency. This information is used, on a second stage of the paper, to set, in one of these two airfoils where the boundary layer is having an early separation, two of the AFC parameters while optimizing the remaining three. The optimization is performed employing a parametric analysis and demonstrates that a considerable WT power increase can be obtained when managing to reattach the former separated boundary layer. This is further clarified thanks to the energy assessment presented in the final part of the paper. Although the AFC optimization needs to be extended for the rest of the blade sections, the procedure outlined in the present research clarifies the different steps to be followed to optimize the performance of any HAWT under any operating conditions. The Reynolds numbers associated to the respective airfoil sections analyzed in the present manuscript are Re = 14.088 e6 and Re = 14.877 e6, the characteristic length being the corresponding chord length for each airfoil.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20450v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Lahoz, Ahmad Nabhani, Mohammad Saemian, Josep M Bergada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marangoni-driven freezing dynamics of supercooled binary droplets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20555v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solidification of droplets is of great importance to various technological applications, drawing considerable attention from scientists aiming to unravel the fundamental physical mechanisms. In the case of multicomponent droplets undergoing solidification, the emergence of concentration gradients may trigger significant interfacial flows that dominate the freezing dynamics. Here, we experimentally investigate the fascinating snow-globe freezing dynamics of supercooled ethanol-water droplets. We reveal that these unique freezing dynamics are driven by solidification-induced solutal Marangoni flow within the droplets. We quantitatively characterize the concentration-dependent migration and growth dynamics of ice particles, tightly connecting them to the solutal Marangoni effect and the associated convective heat transfer. Moreover, we show that the final wrapping state of droplets can be modulated by the concentration of ethanol. Our findings may pave the way for novel insights into the physicochemical hydrodynamics of multicomponent liquids undergoing phase transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20555v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feng Wang, Hao Zeng, Yihong Du, Xinyu Tang, Chao Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical analysis of stress perturbations from a partially-lubricated viscous gravity current</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20565v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a theoretical investigation into the dynamics of a viscous gravity current subjected to spatially-finite lubrication (i.e., a `slippery patch'). The work is motivated by grounded ice sheets flowing across patches of basal meltwater which reduce the ice-bed frictional coupling, causing perturbations enhancing ice motion, with implications for increased ice flux into the ocean and sea level rise. The flow is characterized by transitions between shear- and extension-dominated dynamics, which necessitates boundary-layer solutions at the transition points. We develop a depth-integrated analytical model of Newtonian flow which concisely reveals fundamental relationships between ice sheet geometry (thickness, surface slope, and slippery patch length) and the magnitude and spatial extent of resulting horizontal deviatoric stresses. This reduced-order analytical model shows good quantitative agreement with numerical simulations using 2-D Newtonian Stokes equations, which are further extended to the case of a non-Newtonian flow. From the reduced-order model, we rationalize that the slippery patch-induced stress perturbations are exponentially-decaying functions of distance upstream away from the patch onset. We also show that the amplitude of the perturbation scales linearly with the surface slope and patch length while the decay lengthscale scales linearly with ice thickness. These fundamental relationships have implications for the response of the Greenland Ice Sheet to the inland expansion of basal meltwater presence over the coming warming decades.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20565v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua H. Rines, Ching-Yao Lai, Yongji Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superposition of system response in modulated turbulent plane Couette flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Traditionally, the response of a turbulent flow to modulated perturbations is expected to be complex. We conduct direct numerical simulations of turbulent Plane Couette flow, the shear flow between two differentially moving plates, to reveal intriguing behaviour in response to a modulation in the velocity of one of the plates: the response of the flow to modulations can be calculated from a superposition of the response to each Fourier mode of the modulation. We fix the shear Reynolds number as $Re_s=3\times10^4$, and measure the propagation of a modulated forcing in the flow close to the resonant frequency of the system. We find that the amplitude and phase response of the flow can be largely captured using models based on laminar flow, regardless of the waveform used to force the flow. Furthermore, we find that linear superposition can effectively describe the flow's response to these perturbations as long as the modulation is smaller than the base flow. Our findings unveil the persistence of linear superposition in a turbulent flow under specific conditions, even when perturbations occur at time-scales closely aligned with the system's characteristic time-scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20639v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wasy Akhtar, Rodolfo Ostilla-Monico</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convection in the active layer speeds up permafrost thaw in coarse grained soils</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20714v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Permafrost thaw is a major concern raised by the ongoing climate change. An understudied phenomenon possibly affecting the pace of permafrost thaw is the onset of convective motions within the active layer caused by the density anomaly of water. Here, we explore the effects of groundwater convection on permafrost thawing using a model that accounts for ice - water phase transitions, coupled with the dynamics of the temperature field transported by the Darcy's flow across a porous matrix. Numerical simulations of this model show that ice thawing in the presence of convection is much faster than in the diffusive case and deepens at a constant velocity proportional to the soil permeability. A scaling argument is able to predict correctly the asymptotic velocity. Since in the convective regime the heat transport is mediated by the coherent motion of thermal plumes across the thawed layer, we find that the depth of the thawing interface becomes highly heterogeneous.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20714v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marta Magnani, Stefano Musacchio, Antonello Provenzale, Guido Boffetta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of turbulence boundary conditions on Spalart-Allmaras RANS simulations for active flow control applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20725v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We assess the suitability of Reynolds-Averaged Navier-Stokes (RANS) simulation using the Spallart-Almaras (SA) turbulence model as a closure in analysing the performance of fluidic Active Flow Control (AFC) applications. In particular, we focus on the optimal set of actuation parameters found by Tousi et al. [1, 2] for a SD7003 airfoil at a Reynolds number Re = 6 e4 and post-stall angle of attack alpha = 14 degrees fitted with a Synthetic Jet Actuator (SJA). The Large Eddy Simulation (LES) presented in that work is taken as the reference to identify the best choice of boundary conditions for the turbulence field nu' at both domain inlet and jet orifice in two-dimensional RANS-SA computations. Although SA-RANS is far less accurate than LES, our findings show that it can still predict macroscopic aggregates such as lift and drag coefficients quite statisfactorily and at a much lower computational cost, provided that turbulence levels of the actuator jet are set to a realistic value. An adequate value of nu'is instrumental in capturing the correct flow behaviour of the reattached boundary layers for close-to-optimal actuated cases. This validates the use of RANS-SA as a reliable and cost-effective simulation method for the preliminary optimisation of SJA parameters in AFC applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20725v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Navid Monshi Tousi, Josep M. Bergada, Fernando Mellibovsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-Scale Horizontal Axis Wind Turbine Aerodynamic Efficiency Optimization using Active Flow Control and Synthetic Jets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20746v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Efficiency increase is seen as one of the main goals in any energy converting device. In this direction, the present study aims to demonstrate that large-scale wind turbines can still be improved in order to generate larger amounts of energy. The research presented in this manuscript consists of two main blocks. Initially, it analyzes via Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) the boundary layer dynamics on a set of pre-determined airfoils cut along the DTU-10MW reference blade by using the 2D URANS k omega SST turbulence model. The aim of this initial stage is to identify the boundary layer separation point, its associated frequency, and peak to peak amplitude for each airfoil cut along the blade, evaluating as well their respective aerodynamic characteristics. The second main goal of the present research consists of implementing the Active Flow Control (AFC) technology and, when employing synthetic jets, to reattach the boundary layer in all airfoils where it is separated. To accomplish this second goal efficiently, the five parameters associated to the AFC implementation performed to each airfoil will be obtained through respective genetic algorithm optimizations. An energy assessment is finally undertaken at each airfoil to validate the respective energy gain obtained. When comparing the net power gain, before and after AFC implementation, generated by each of the airfoils evaluated, net power gains between 23 and 36KW are obtained in all airfoils analyzed, clarifying that the proposed technology is capable of improving the performance of the wind turbines, very likely at any operating condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20746v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmad Nabhani, Navid M Tousi, Marti Coma, Gabriel Bugeda, Josep M Bergada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaporation limited spreading of ethanol on rectangular porous strips: an experimental and theoretical investigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20776v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Wicking is a widely studied process across various natural and artificial systems. A more industrially relevant configuration is when the wicking liquid is allowed to evaporate, such as in the heat pipes and the variants, in order to regulate the operating temperature effectively. We consider a simpler case for investigation where liquid ethanol (kept in a container) climbs onto a thin filter paper oriented vertically and is exposed to laboratory conditions, facilitating mass loss via evaporation, thereby inducing the cooling effect. We use three filter papers having different permeability values and three diagnostics concurrently for each case in order to understand the entire dynamics; these are optical imaging, thermal imaging, and precision weighing scale. Results revealed a steady-state height considerably below Jurin's limit for all the cases, indicating evaporative mass loss as the primary limiting parameter rather than the conventional gravitational effect in such a process. Further, thermal imaging unveiled a non-uniform temperature distribution along the filter paper with a very peculiar temperature inversion near the mid-way of the wicking liquid. We use this feature to improve the Constant Evaporation Model (CEM by Fries et al) by addressing this non-linear behaviour as a consequence of the evaporation rate being a function of the vertical position; we term this newly proposed model Non-Constant Evaporation Model, (NCEM). In the NCEM, we test two different power-law relations for the evaporation rate and both seemingly capture the essential features of this dynamic process. However, both the models do not capture the process completely and further refinement is needed for complete understanding. Since evaporation rate is the limiting factor, we included it in defining two new non-dimensional numbers (Evaporation Height Number, EHN and Evaporation Time Number, ETN).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20776v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rampally Srirama Chandra Murthy, Navneet Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AhmedML: High-Fidelity Computational Fluid Dynamics Dataset for Incompressible, Low-Speed Bluff Body Aerodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20801v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The development of Machine Learning (ML) methods for Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) is currently limited by the lack of openly available training data. This paper presents a new open-source dataset comprising of high fidelity, scale-resolving CFD simulations of 500 geometric variations of the Ahmed Car Body - a simplified car-like shape that exhibits many of the flow topologies that are present on bluff bodies such as road vehicles. The dataset contains simulation results that exhibit a broad set of fundamental flow physics such as geometry and pressure-induced flow separation as well as 3D vortical structures. Each variation of the Ahmed car body were run using a high-fidelity, time-accurate, hybrid Reynolds-Averaged Navier-Stokes (RANS) - Large-Eddy Simulation (LES) turbulence modelling approach using the open-source CFD code OpenFOAM. The dataset contains boundary, volume, geometry, and time-averaged forces/moments in widely used open-source formats. In addition, the OpenFOAM case setup is provided so that others can reproduce or extend the dataset. This represents to the authors knowledge, the first open-source large-scale dataset using high-fidelity CFD methods for the widely used Ahmed car body that is available to freely download with a permissive license (CC-BY-SA).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20801v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neil Ashton, Danielle C. Maddix, Samuel Gundry, Parisa M. Shabestari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A discussion on the critical electric Rayleigh number for AC electrokinetic flow of binary fluids in a divergent microchannel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20803v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electrokinetic (EK) flow is a type of flow driven or manipulated by electric body forces, influenced by various factors such as electric field intensity, electric field form, frequency, electric permittivity/conductivity, fluid viscosity and etc. The diversity of dimensionless control parameters, such as the electric Rayleigh number, complicates the comparison of EK flow stability. Consequently, comparing the performance and cost of micromixers or reactors based on EK flow is challenging, posing an obstacle to their industrial and engineering applications. In this investigation, we theoretically derived a new electric Rayleigh number ($Ra_e$) that quantifies the relationship among electric body forces, fluid viscosity, and ion diffusivity, based on a tanh model of electric conductivity distribution. The calculation results indicate that the new $Ra_e$ exhibits richer variation with the control parameters and better consistency with previous experimental reports. We further conducted experimental studies on the critical electric Rayleigh number ($Ra_{ec}$) of AC EK flow of binary fluids in a divergent microchannel. The experimental variations align well with the theoretical predictions, particularly the existence of an optimal AC frequency and electric conductivity ratio, demonstrating that the tanh model can better elucidate the underlying physics of EK flow. With the new electric Rayleigh number, we found that EK flow in the designed divergent microchannel has a much smaller $Ra_{ec}$ than previously reported, indicating that EK flow is more unstable and thus more suitable for applications in micromixers or reactors in industry and engineering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20803v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinan Pang, Yu Han, Bo Sun, Wei Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Fidelity Bayesian Optimisation of Wind Farm Wake Steering using Wake Models and Large Eddy Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20832v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Improving the power output from wind farms is vital in transitioning to renewable electricity generation. However, in wind farms, wind turbines often operate in the wake of other turbines, leading to a reduction in the wind speed and the resulting power output whilst also increasing fatigue. By using wake steering strategies to control the wake behind each turbine, the total wind farm power output can be increased. To find optimal yaw configurations, typically analytical wake models have been utilised to model the interactions between the wind turbines through the flow field. In this work we show that, for full wind farms, higher-fidelity computational fluid dynamics simulations, in the form of large eddy simulations, are able to find more optimal yaw configurations than analytical wake models. This is because they capture and exploit more of the physics involved in the interactions between the multiple turbine wakes and the atmospheric boundary layer. As large eddy simulations are much more expensive to run than analytical wake models, a multi-fidelity Bayesian optimisation framework is introduced. This implements a multi-fidelity surrogate model, that is able to capture the non-linear relationship between the analytical wake models and the large eddy simulations, and a multi-fidelity acquisition function to determine the configuration and fidelity of each optimisation iteration. This allows for fewer configurations to be evaluated with the more expensive large eddy simulations than a single-fidelity optimisation, whilst producing comparable optimisation results. The same total wind farm power improvements can then be found for a reduced computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20832v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Mole, Sylvain Laizet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Stochastic Precipitating Quasi-Geostrophic Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20886v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Efficient and effective modeling of complex systems, incorporating cloud physics and precipitation, is essential for accurate climate modeling and forecasting. However, simulating these systems is computationally demanding since microphysics has crucial contributions to the dynamics of moisture and precipitation. In this paper, appropriate stochastic models are developed for the phase-transition dynamics of water, focusing on the precipitating quasi-geostrophic (PQG) model as a prototype. By treating the moisture, phase transitions, and latent heat release as integral components of the system, the PQG model constitutes a set of partial differential equations (PDEs) that involve Heaviside nonlinearities due to phase changes of water. Despite systematically characterizing the precipitation physics, expensive iterative algorithms are needed to find a PDE inversion at each numerical integration time step. As a crucial step toward building an effective stochastic model, a computationally efficient Markov jump process is designed to randomly simulate transitions between saturated and unsaturated states that avoids using the expensive iterative solver. The transition rates, which are deterministic, are derived from the physical fields, guaranteeing physical and statistical consistency with nature. Furthermore, to maintain the consistent spatial pattern of precipitation, the stochastic model incorporates an adaptive parameterization that automatically adjusts the transitions based on spatial information. Numerical tests show the stochastic model retains critical properties of the original PQG system while significantly reducing computational demands. It accurately captures observed precipitation patterns, including the spatial distribution and temporal variability of rainfall, alongside reproducing essential dynamic features such as potential vorticity fields and zonal mean flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20886v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nan Chen, Changhong Mou, Leslie M. Smith, Yeyu Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capillary sorting of fiber suspensions by dip coating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20436v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Sorting elongated anisotropic particles, such as fibers, dispersed in suspensions poses significant challenges as they present two characteristic dimensions: length and diameter. Fibers in suspension usually align with the flow, leading to diameter-based filtration when passing through a sieve. Modifying the flow conditions by introducing more mixing so that fibers are arbitrarily oriented can lead to sorting by diameter and length simultaneously, resulting in a lower filtration quality. In this paper, we demonstrate that capillary filtration by dip coating can be utilized to selectively sort fibers by length or by diameter in a controlled manner. Using the withdrawal of a flat substrate from a fiber suspension, we demonstrate that fibers are primarily sorted by their diameters. When considering cylindrical substrates, fibers can be sorted by length under appropriate conditions due to the orientation adopted by the fibers during their entrainment. We report guidelines for designing this filtration process and obtaining good sorting efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20436v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Justin Maddox, Alban Sauret</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical investigation of gravity effects on backdraft phenomena in an enclosure with varying geometries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20449v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, we investigated numerically the backdraft phenomenon under different gravity conditions and 4 openings using Fire Dynamics Simulator (FDS) code. Four different opening geometries are studied under ten different gravity conditions. As demonstrated by an earlier study in our group, backdraft is established under different gravity conditions from 0.1 g to 1 g. The rate at which oxygen reaches an ignition block in the enclosure in the presence of the gravity current plays an important role in the onset of ignition, the subsequent backdraft formation, and the maximum pressure built inside the enclosure before the onset of backdraft. This role also explains why these effects are different under different openings. We observe that the gravity strength affects the ignition time and the onset of backdraft nonlinearly. Moreover, the smoke exiting the enclosure is a precursor for the onset of backdraft, albeit with a short warning, allowing people on the outside to take necessary precautions. The effect of backdraft in the form of heat flow and impact force at the exit is also studied. It is found that the effect of heat flow is more severe than that of impact force.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20449v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vijayananda V. Devananda (North Carolina State University alumni), Tarek Echekki (North Carolina State University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scale locality of information flow in turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20572v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Turbulent fluctuations exhibit universal scaling laws that are independent of large-scale statistics. It is often explained that such universality is caused by the loss of information about large-scale statistics during the cascade process. In our previous study [T. Tanogami and R. Araki, Phys. Rev. Research 6, 013090 (2024)], we applied information thermodynamics to turbulence and proved that information of large-scale turbulent fluctuations is propagated to small scales. As a first step toward understanding how universality emerges at small scales under the influence of the information flow from large scales, here we investigate the scale locality of the information flow for the Sabra shell model. First, we analytically show that the information flow can be decomposed into scale-local and scale-nonlocal parts. Then, we prove that the scale-nonlocal part can be ignored compared to the scale-local part. This result implies that the information transfer from large to small scales occurs mainly through scale-local interactions, which is consistent with the scale locality of the energy cascade.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20572v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomohiro Tanogami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breakthrough-Induced Loop Formation in Evolving Transport Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.08878v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Transport networks, such as vasculature or river networks, provide key functions in organisms and the environment. They usually contain loops whose significance for the stability and robustness of the network is well documented. However, the dynamics of their formation is usually not considered. Such structures often grow in response to the gradient of an external field. During evolution, extending branches compete for the available flux of the field, which leads to effective repulsion between them and screening of the shorter ones. Yet, in remarkably diverse processes, from unstable fluid flows to the canal system of jellyfish, loops suddenly form near the breakthrough when the longest branch reaches the boundary of the system. We provide a physical explanation for this universal behavior. Using a 1D model, we explain that the appearance of effective attractive forces results from the field drop inside the leading finger as it approaches the outlet. Furthermore, we numerically study the interactions between two fingers, including screening in the system and its disappearance near the breakthrough. Finally, we perform simulations of the temporal evolution of the fingers to show how revival and attraction to the longest finger leads to dynamic loop formation. We compare the simulations to the experiments and find that the dynamics of the shorter finger are well reproduced. Our results demonstrate that reconnection is a prevalent phenomenon in systems driven by diffusive fluxes, occurring both when the ratio of the mobility inside the growing structure to the mobility outside is low and near the breakthrough.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.08878v4</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1073/pnas.2401200121</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, vol. 121, no. 29, p. e2401200121, Jul. 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Stanis{\l}aw \.Zukowski, Annemiek Johanna Maria Cornelissen, Florian Osselin, St\'ephane Douady, Piotr Szymczak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unified Framework for Laser-induced Transient Bubble Dynamics within Microchannels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.07105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.07105v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Oscillatory flow in confined spaces is central to understanding physiological flows and rational design of synthetic periodic-actuation based micromachines. Using theory and experiments on oscillating flows generated through a laser-induced cavitation bubble, we associate the dynamic bubble size (fluid velocity) and bubble lifetime to the laser energy supplied - a control parameter in experiments. Employing different channel cross-section shapes, sizes and lengths, we demonstrate the characteristic scales for velocity, time and energy to depend solely on the channel geometry. Contrary to the generally assumed absence of instability in low Reynolds number flows (&lt;1000), we report a momentary flow distortion that originates due to the boundary layer separation near channel walls during flow deceleration. The emergence of distorted laminar states is characterized using two stages. First the conditions for the onset of instabilities is analyzed using the Reynolds number and Womersley number for oscillating flows. Second the growth and the ability of an instability to prevail is analyzed using the convective time scale of the flow. Our findings inform rational design of microsystems leveraging pulsatile flows via cavitation-powered microactuation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.07105v3</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nagaraj Nagalingam, Vikram Korede, Daniel Irimia, Jerry Westerweel, Johan T. Padding, Remco Hartkamp, Huseyin Burak Eral</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WindsorML: High-Fidelity Computational Fluid Dynamics Dataset For Automotive Aerodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19320v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a new open-source high-fidelity dataset for Machine Learning (ML) containing 355 geometric variants of the Windsor body, to help the development and testing of ML surrogate models for external automotive aerodynamics. Each Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) simulation was run with a GPU-native high-fidelity Wall-Modeled Large-Eddy Simulations (WMLES) using a Cartesian immersed-boundary method using more than 280M cells to ensure the greatest possible accuracy. The dataset contains geometry variants that exhibits a wide range of flow characteristics that are representative of those observed on road-cars. The dataset itself contains the 3D time-averaged volume &amp; boundary data as well as the geometry and force &amp; moment coefficients. This paper discusses the validation of the underlying CFD methods as well as contents and structure of the dataset. To the authors knowledge, this represents the first, large-scale high-fidelity CFD dataset for the Windsor body with a permissive open-source license (CC-BY-SA).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19320v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Neil Ashton, Jordan B. Angel, Aditya S. Ghate, Gaetan K. W. Kenway, Man Long Wong, Cetin Kiris, Astrid Walle, Danielle C. Maddix, Gary Page</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spontaneous symmetry breaking in two dimensions under nonequilibrium laminar flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.06390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.06390v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the long-range order in two dimensions where an order parameter is advected by laminar flows such as rotational, shear, and elongational flows. Under these flows, we analyze an ordered state of the $O(N)$ scalar model in the large-$N$ limit. We show that the stability of the ordered state depends on the flow pattern; shear and elongational flows stabilize the long-range order but rotational flow does not. We discuss the physical mechanism underlying our results by connecting static correlations of fluctuations and their dynamics based on the interaction representation used in quantum mechanics. We find that advective transport induces superdiffusion under shear and elongational flows, thereby stabilizing the long-range order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.06390v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuki Minami, Hiroyoshi Nakano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive Parameter Selection in Nudging Based Data Assimilation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18886v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Data assimilation combines (imperfect) knowledge of a flow's physical laws with (noisy, time-lagged, and otherwise imperfect) observations to produce a more accurate prediction of flow statistics. Assimilation by nudging (from 1964), while non-optimal, is easy to implement and its analysis is clear and well-established. Nudging's uniform in time accuracy has even been established under conditions on the nudging parameter $\chi$ and the density of observational locations, $H$, Larios, Rebholz, and Zerfas [1]. One remaining issue is that nudging requires the user to select a key parameter. The conditions required for this parameter, derived through \'a priori (worst case) analysis are severe (Section 2.1 herein) and far beyond those found to be effective in computational experience. One resolution, developed herein, is self-adaptive parameter selection. This report develops, analyzes, tests, and compares two methods of self-adaptation of nudging parameters. One combines analysis and response to local flow behavior. The other is based only on response to flow behavior. The comparison finds both are easily implemented and yield effective values of the nudging parameter much smaller than those of \'a priori analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18886v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aytekin \c{C}{\i}b{\i}k, Rui Fang, William Layton, Farjana Siddiqua</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
