<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.flu-dyn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn</link>
    <description>physics.flu-dyn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2024 04:02:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Group cohesion and passive dynamics of a pair of inertial swimmers with three-dimensional hydrodynamic interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13152v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When swimming animals form cohesive groups, they can reap several benefits. Our understanding of collective animal motion has traditionally been driven by models based on phenomenological behavioral rules, but more recent work has highlighted the critical importance of hydrodynamic interactions among a group of inertial swimmers. To study how hydrodynamic interactions affect group cohesion, we develop a three-dimensional, inviscid, far-field model of a swimmer. In a group of two model swimmers, we observe several dynamical phases, including following, divergence, collision, and cohesion. Our results illustrate when cohesive groups can passively form through hydrodynamic interactions alone, and when other action is needed to maintain cohesion. We find that misalignment between swimmers makes passive cohesion less likely; nevertheless, it is possible for a cohesive group to form through passive hydrodynamic interactions alone. We also find that the geometry of swimmers critically affects the group dynamics due to its role in how swimmers sample the velocity gradient of the flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13152v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Niged Mabrouk, Daniel Floryan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Effect of Liquid Crystal Orientation in the Lipid Layer on Tear Film Thinning and Breakup</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13225v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The human tear film (TF) is thin multilayer fluid film that is critical for clear vision and ocular surface health. Its dynamics are strongly affected by a floating lipid layer and, in health, that layer slows evaporation and helps create a more uniform tear film over the ocular surface. The tear film lipid layer (LL) may have liquid crystalline characteristics and plays important roles in the health of the tear film. Previous models have treated the lipid layer as a Newtonian fluid in extensional flow. We extend previous models to include extensional flow of a thin nematic liquid crystal atop a Newtonian aqueous layer with insoluble surfactant between them. We derive the resulting system of nonlinear partial differential equations for thickness of the LL and aqueous layers, surfactant transport and velocity in the LL. Evaporation is taken into account, and is affected by the LL thickness, internal arrangement of its rod-like molecules, and external conditions. Despite the complexity, this system still represents a significant reduction of the full system. We solve the system numerically via collocation with finite difference discretization in space together with implicit time stepping. We analyze solutions for different internal LL structures and show significant effect of the orientation. Orienting the molecules close to the normal direction to the TF surface results in slower evaporation, and other orientations have an effect on flow, showing that this type of model has promise for predicting TF dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13225v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. J. Taranchuk, R. J. Braun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Feeding of Swimming and Attached Ciliates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13467v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ciliated microorganisms near the base of the aquatic food chain either swim to encounter prey or attach at a substrate and generate feeding currents to capture passing particles. Here, we represent attached and swimming ciliates using a popular spherical model in viscous fluid with slip surface velocity that afford analytical expressions of ciliary flows. We solve an advection-diffusion equation for the concentration of dissolved nutrients, where the P'eclet number (Pe) reflects the ratio of diffusive to advective time scales. For a fixed hydrodynamic power expenditure, we ask what ciliary surface velocities maximize nutrient flux at the microorganism's surface. We find that surface motions that optimize feeding depend on Pe. For freely swimming microorganisms at finite Pe, it is optimal to swim by employing a "treadmill" surface motion, but in the limit of large Pe, there is no difference between this treadmill solution and a symmetric dipolar surface velocity that keeps the organism stationary. For attached microorganisms, the treadmill solution is optimal for feeding at Pe below a critical value, but at larger Pe values, the dipolar surface motion is optimal. We verified these results in open-loop numerical simulations, asymptotic analysis, and using an adjoint-based optimization method. Our findings challenge existing claims that optimal feeding is optimal swimming across all P'eclet numbers, and provide new insights into the prevalence of both attached and swimming solutions in oceanic microorganisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13467v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingyi Liu, Yi Man, John H. Costello, Eva Kanso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marangoni Interfacial Instability Induced by Solute Transfer Across Liquid-Liquid Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13675v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study presents analytical and numerical investigations of Marangoni interfacial instability in a two-liquid-layer system with constant solute transfer across the liquid interface. Previous research has demonstrated that both viscosity ratio and diffusivity ratio can influence the system's hydrodynamic stability via the Marangoni effect, but the distinctions in process and mechanisms are not yet fully understood. To gain insights, we developed a numerical model based on the phase-field method, rigorously validated against linear stability analysis. The parameter space explored encompasses Schmidt number ($Sc \in [0.2, 200]$), Marangoni number ($Ma_c \in [10, 2000]$), Capillary number ($Ca \in [0.01, 1]$), viscosity ratio ($\zeta_\mu \in [0.1, 10]$), and diffusivity ratio ($\zeta_D \in [0.1, 10]$). We identified two key characteristics of Marangoni instability: the self-amplification of triggered Marangoni flows in flow-intensity-unstable case and the oscillation of flow patterns during flow decay in flow-intensity-stable case. Direct numerical simulations incorporating interfacial deformation and nonlinearity confirm that specific conditions, including solute transfer out of a higher viscous or less diffusive layer, amplify and sustain Marangoni interfacial flows. Furthermore, the study highlights the role of interfacial deformation and unequal solute variation in system instability, proposing corresponding instability mechanisms. Notably, traveling waves are observed in the flow-intensity-stable case, correlating with the morphological evolution of convection rolls. These insights contribute to a comprehensive understanding of Marangoni interfacial instability in multicomponent fluids systems, elucidating the mechanisms underlying variations in viscosity and diffusivity ratios across liquid layers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13675v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangwei Li, Dongdong Wan, Mengqi Li, Huanshu Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure gain combustion for gas turbines: Analysis of a fully coupled engine model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14053v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ``Shockless Explosion Combustion" (SEC) concept for gas turbine combustors, introduced in 2014, approximates constant volume combustion (CVC) by harnessing acoustic confinement of autoigniting gas packets. The resulting pressure waves simultaneously transmit combustion energy to a turbine plenum and facilitate the combustor's recharging against an average pressure gain. Challenges in actualizing an SEC-driven gas turbine include i) the creation of charge stratifications for nearly homogeneous autoignition, ii) protecting the turbo components from combustion-induced pressure fluctuations, iii) providing evidence that efficiency gains comparable to those of CVC over deflagrative combustion can be realized, and iv) designing an effective one-way intake valve. This work addresses challenges i)-iii) utilizing computational engine models incorporating a quasi-one-dimensional combustor, zero- and two-dimensional compressor and turbine plena, and quasi-stationary turbo components. Two SEC operational modes are identified which fire at roughly one and two times the combustors' acoustic frequencies. Results for SEC-driven gas turbines with compressor pressure ratios of 6:1 and 20:1 reveal 1.5-fold mean pressure gains across the combustors. Assuming ideally efficient compressors and turbines, efficiency gains over engines with deflagration-based combustors of 30% and 18% are realized, respectively. With absolute values of 52% and 66%, the obtained efficiencies are close to the theoretical Humphrey cycle efficiencies of 54% and 65% for the mentioned pre-compression ratios. Detailed thermodynamic cycle analyses for individual gas parcels suggest that there is room for further efficiency gains through optimized plenum and combustor designs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14053v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rupert Klein, Maikel Nadolski, Christian Zenker, Michael Oevermann, Christian Oliver Paschereit</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prediction of flow and elastic stresses in a viscoelastic turbulent channel flow using convolutional neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14121</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14121v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Neural-network models have been employed to predict the instantaneous flow close to the wall in a viscoelastic turbulent channel flow. The numerical simulation data at the wall is utilized to predict the instantaneous velocity fluctuations and polymeric-stress fluctuations at three different wall-normal positions. Apart from predicting the velocity fluctuations well in a hibernating flow, the neural-network models are also shown to predict the polymeric shear stress and the trace of the polymeric stresses at a given wall-normal location with reasonably good accuracy. These non-intrusive sensing models can be integrated in an experimental setting to construct the polymeric-stress field in turbulent flows, which otherwise may not be directly quantifiable in experimental measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14121v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arivazhagan G. Balasubramanian, Ricardo Vinuesa, Outi Tammisola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The effects of turbulence modeling on dynamic stall</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14172v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A numerical investigation of the flow evolution over a pitching NACA 0012 airfoil incurring in deep dynamic stall phenomena is presented. The experimental data at Reynolds number Re = 135 000 and reduced frequency k = 0.1, provided by Lee and Gerontakos, are compared to numerical simulations using different turbulence models. After a preliminary space and time convergence study, two- and three-dimensional URANS with different turbulence models are explored, highlighting the advantages and the drawbacks. Then, the turbulence-resolving capabilities of hybrid RANS/LES strategies are exploited to recover and better represent the dynamic stall vortex. In detail, Scale-Adaptive Simulations (SAS) and Stress-Blended Eddy Simulations (SBES) are adopted. Furthermore, the LES resolved portion allows a spectral analysis of the force and moment coefficients to investigate the contribution of frequency lower than the pitching one. Finally, a comparison of the proposed approaches with other numerical simulations is given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14172v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giacomo Baldan, Francesco Manara, Gregorio Frassoldati, Alberto Guardone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On h-refined meshless solution to Navier-Stokes problem in porous media: comparing meshless Lattice Boltzman Method with ACM RBF-FD approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14195v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, two mesh-free CFD solvers for pore-scale fluid flow through porous media are considered, namely the Lattice Boltzmann Method with the two relaxation time collision term and the direct Navier-Stokes solver under the artificial compressibility limit. The porous media is built with a regular arrangement of spherical grains with variable radii, which allows control of the porosity. Both solvers use the same h-refined meshless spatial discretization to adequately capture the underlying geometry and the same Radial Basis Function (RBF) method to approximate the involved fields and partial differential operators. First, the results are compared with the data from the literature in terms of drag coefficient and permeability at different porosities achieving excellent agreement with the reported results. Next, the simulations are extended beyond the porosity range reported in the literature using proposed h-refined CFD solvers. The results are supported by convergence and timing analyses and discussions on meshless parameters such as stencil size and refinement settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14195v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dawid Strzelczyk, Miha Rot, Gregor Kosec, Maciej Matyka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning in Viscoelastic Fluids via Energy-Based Kernel Embedding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.14347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.14347v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ability to measure differences in collected data is of fundamental importance for quantitative science and machine learning, motivating the establishment of metrics grounded in physical principles. In this study, we focus on the development of such metrics for viscoelastic fluid flows governed by a large class of linear and nonlinear stress models. To do this, we introduce a kernel function corresponding to a given viscoelastic stress model that implicitly embeds flowfield snapshots into a Reproducing Kernel Hilbert Space (RKHS) whose squared norm equals the total mechanical energy. Working implicitly with lifted representations in the RKHS via the kernel function provides natural and unambiguous metrics for distances and angles between flowfields without the need for hyperparameter tuning. Additionally, we present a solution to the preimage problem for our kernels, enabling accurate reconstruction of flowfields from their RKHS representations. Through numerical experiments on an unsteady viscoelastic lid-driven cavity flow, we demonstrate the utility of our kernels for extracting energetically-dominant coherent structures in viscoelastic flows across a range of Reynolds and Weissenberg numbers. Specifically, the features extracted by Kernel Principal Component Analysis (KPCA) of flowfield snapshots using our kernel functions yield reconstructions with superior accuracy in terms of mechanical energy compared to conventional methods such as ordinary Principal Component Analysis (PCA) with na\"ively-defined state vectors or KPCA with ad-hoc choices of kernel functions. Our findings underscore the importance of principled choices of metrics in both scientific and machine learning investigations of complex fluid systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.14347v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel E. Otto, Cassio M. Oishi, Fabio Amaral, Steven L. Brunton, J. Nathan Kutz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning for climate physics and simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13227v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We discuss the emerging advances and opportunities at the intersection of machine learning (ML) and climate physics, highlighting the use of ML techniques, including supervised, unsupervised, and equation discovery, to accelerate climate knowledge discoveries and simulations. We delineate two distinct yet complementary aspects: (1) ML for climate physics and (2) ML for climate simulations. While physics-free ML-based models, such as ML-based weather forecasting, have demonstrated success when data is abundant and stationary, the physics knowledge and interpretability of ML models become crucial in the small-data/non-stationary regime to ensure generalizability. Given the absence of observations, the long-term future climate falls into the small-data regime. Therefore, ML for climate physics holds a critical role in addressing the challenges of ML for climate simulations. We emphasize the need for collaboration among climate physics, ML theory, and numerical analysis to achieve reliable ML-based models for climate applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13227v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ching-Yao Lai, Pedram Hassanzadeh, Aditi Sheshadri, Maike Sonnewald, Raffaele Ferrari, Venkatramani Balaji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wake structures and performance of wind turbine rotor with harmonic surging motions under laminar and turbulent inflows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.08655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.08655v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study presents a comprehensive numerical analysis of a full-scale horizontal-axis Floating Offshore Wind Turbine (FOWT) subjected to harmonic surging motions under both laminar and turbulent inflow conditions. Utilizing high-fidelity Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) simulations, namely Large-Eddy Simulation (LES) with Actuator Line Model (ALM), this research investigates the rotor performance, wake characteristics, and wake structures of a surging FOWT in detail. The study delves into the influence of varying inflow turbulence intensities, surging settings, and their interplay on the aerodynamic performance and the wake aerodynamics of a FOWT rotor. The results show that, through employing the phase-locking technique, Surging Induced Periodic Coherent Structures (SIPCS) can be identified in the wake of all the surging cases studied, irrespective of the inflow conditions and the surging settings. Additionally, the findings show that the faster wake recovery observed in the surging-laminar cases is not caused by facilitating instability-induced faster wake breakdown, a previously accepted hypothesis. Instead, it is the enhanced advection process resulting from the induction fields of SIPCS that causes the wake to recover faster. The analysis of rotor performance shows that the time-averaged rotor performances are affected by the intricate dynamics arising from the surging motions. With certain surging settings, the time-averaged thrust and the time-averaged power of a surging rotor are found to be simultaneously lower and higher compared to those of a fixed rotor. Furthermore, the study underscores the importance of considering both the magnitude of surging and the rate of surging ($\mathcal{V}$ and $\mathcal{W}$) simultaneously to fully characterize the hysteresis load on a surging rotor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.08655v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>YuanTso Li, Wei Yu, Hamid Sarlak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An experimental evaluation of the interplay between geometry and scale on cross-flow turbine performance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.20616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.20616v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cross-flow turbines harness kinetic energy in wind or moving water. Due to their unsteady fluid dynamics, it can be difficult to predict the interplay between aspects of rotor geometry and turbine performance. This study considers the effects of three geometric parameters: the number of blades, the preset pitch angle, and the chord-to-radius ratio. The relevant fluid dynamics of cross-flow turbines are reviewed, as are prior experimental studies that have investigated these parameters in a more limited manner. Here, 223 unique experiments are conducted across an order of magnitude of diameter-based Reynolds numbers ($\approx 8\!\times\!10^4 - 8\!\times\!10^5$) in which the performance implications of these three geometric parameters are evaluated. In agreement with prior work, maximum performance is generally observed to increase with Reynolds number and decrease with blade count. The broader experimental space clarifies parametric interdependencies; for example, the optimal preset pitch angle is increasingly negative as the chord-to-radius ratio increases. As these experiments vary both the chord-to-radius ratio and blade count, the performance of different rotor geometries with the same solidity (the ratio of total blade chord to rotor circumference) can also be evaluated. Results demonstrate that while solidity can be a poor predictor of maximum performance, across all scales and tested geometries it is an excellent predictor of the tip-speed ratio corresponding to maximum performance. Overall, these results present a uniquely holistic view of relevant geometric considerations for cross-flow turbine rotor design and provide a rich dataset for validation of numerical simulations and reduced-order models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.20616v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aidan Hunt, Benjamin Strom, Gregory Talpey, Hannah Ross, Isabel Scherl, Steven Brunton, Martin Wosnik, Brian Polagye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A quaternion-based mathematical model for geometrically exact dynamic analysis of cantilevered pipe conveying fluid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.06252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.06252v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For the first time, the development of the nonlinear geometrically exact governing equations and corresponding boundary conditions of hanging cantilevered flexible pipes conveying fluid in the framework of the quaternion system is undertaken. Additionally, the linear model is derived from the nonlinear one for the stability analysis. The linear and nonlinear mathematical formulations based on the geometrically exact rotation-based model are also extracted from the current model. The obtained integro-partial differential-algebraic equations are converted to a set of ordinary differential algebraic equations via the Galerkin discretization technique, and the resulting equations are numerically solved to determine the self-excited oscillation behavior of the system in the post-flutter region. The critical flow velocities, time traces, bifurcation diagrams, phase planes, and deformed configurations are compared with those reported based on the geometrically exact rotation-based model. The comparative studies divulge that the present model can successfully capture the stability and dynamic characteristics of the system. An interesting feature of the current ordinary differential-algebraic equations is that their coefficients are time-independent, unlike those of geometrically exact rotation-based equations in the Galerkin form. The results show this feature leads to a remarkable decrease in the computational cost, although the number of equations increases and the nonlinearity becomes stronger. The challenging issues with the numerical solution utilized in this study are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.06252v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amir Mehdi Dehrouyeh-Semnani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bubble departure and sliding in high-pressure flow boiling of water</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12749v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bubble growth, departure and sliding in low-pressure flow boiling has received considerable attention in the past. However, most applications of boiling heat transfer rely on high-pressure flow boiling, for which very little is known, as experimental data are scarce and very difficult to obtain. In this work, we conduct an experiment using high-resolution optical techniques. By combining backlit shadowgraphy and phase-detection imaging, we track bubble shape and physical footprint with high spatial (6 $\mu$m) and temporal (33 $\mu$s) resolution, as well as bubble size and position as bubbles nucleate and slide on top of the heated surface. We show that at pressures above 1 MPa, bubbles grow in a heat-diffusion controlled regime and retain a spherical shape throughout the growth and sliding process. We analytically derive non-dimensional numbers to correlate bubble velocity and liquid velocity throughout the turbulent boundary layer and predict the sliding of bubbles on the surface, solely from physical properties and bubble growth rate. We also show that these non-dimensional solutions can be leveraged to formulate elementary criteria that predict the effect of pressure and flow rate on bubble departure diameter and growth time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12749v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Artyom Kossolapov, Matthew T. Hughes, Bren Phillips, Matteo Bucci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Computation of Large-Scale Statistical Solutions to Incompressible Fluid Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09843v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work presents the development, performance analysis and subsequent optimization of a GPU-based spectral hyperviscosity solver for turbulent flows described by the three dimensional incompressible Navier-Stokes equations. The method solves for the fluid velocity fields directly in Fourier space, eliminating the need to solve a large-scale linear system of equations in order to find the pressure field. Special focus is put on the communication intensive transpose operation required by the fast Fourier transform when using distributed memory parallelism. After multiple iterations of benchmarking and improving the code, the simulation achieves close to optimal performance on the Piz Daint supercomputer cluster, even outperforming the Cray MPI implementation on Piz Daint in its communication routines. This optimal performance enables the computation of large-scale statistical solutions of incompressible fluid flows in three space dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09843v3</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3659914.3659922</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Rohner, Siddhartha Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of Pressure Gradients near the Interface in the Viscous Fingering Instability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.01924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.01924v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The viscous fingering instability, which forms when a less-viscous fluid invades a more-viscous one within a confined geometry, is an iconic system for studying pattern formation. For both miscible and immiscible fluid pairs the growth dynamics change after the initial instability onset and the global structures, typical of late-time growth, are governed by the viscosity ratio. Here we introduce an experimental technique to measure flow throughout the inner and outer fluids. This probes the existence of a new length scale associated with the local pressure gradients around the interface and allows us to compare our results to the predictions of a previously proposed model for late-time finger growth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.01924v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Savannah D. Gowen, Thomas E. Videbaek, Sidney R. Nagel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wave-resolving Voronoi model of Rouse number for sediment entrainment equilibrium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10878v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: To integrate wave and sediment transport modeling, a computationally extensive wave-resolving Voronoi mesh-based simulation has been developed to improve upon heretofore separate sediment and spectral wave modeling. Orbital wave motion-dependent sediment transport and fine structures of the dynamic Rouse number distribution across the seabed were brought into focus. The entirely parallelized wave-resolving hydrodynamic model is demonstrated for nearshore beach waters adjacent to artificial islands in Doha Bay. The nested model was validated with tidal time series for three locations and two seasons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10878v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Lawen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
