<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.flu-dyn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn</link>
    <description>physics.flu-dyn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Mixing of active scalars due to random shock waves in two dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07357v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the mixing of active scalars in two dimensions by the stirring action of stochastically generated shock waves. We use direct numerical simulations (DNS) of the interaction of shock waves with two non-reacting species to analyse the mixing dynamics for different Atwood numbers (At). Unlike passive scalars, the presence of density gradients in active scalars makes the species diffusion nonlinear, introducing a concentration gradient-driven term and a density gradient-driven nonlinear dissipation term in the concentration evolution equation. We show that the direction of the concentration gradient causes the interface across which molecular diffusion occurs to expand outward or inward, even without any stirring action. Shock waves enhance the mixing process by increasing the perimeter of the interface and by sustaining concentration gradients. Negative Atwood number mixtures sustain concentration gradients for longer time than positive Atwood number mixtures due to the so-called nonlinear dissipation terms. We estimate the time till when the action of stirring is dominant over molecular mixing. We also highlight the role of baroclinicity in increasing the interface perimeter in the stirring dominant regime. We compare the stirring effect of shock waves on mixing of passive scalars with active scalars and show that the vorticity generated by baroclinicity is responsible for the folding and stretching of the interface in the case of active scalars. We conclude by showing that lighter mixtures with denser inhomogeneities (At &lt; 0) take longer time to homogenise than the denser mixtures with lighter inhomogeneities (At &gt; 0).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07357v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joaquim P. Jossy, Prateek Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Barchan-barchan dune repulsion investigated at the grain scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07604v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Barchans are eolian dunes of crescent shape found on Earth, Mars and other celestial bodies. Among the different types of barchan-barchan interaction, there is one, known as chasing, in which the dunes remain close but without touching each other. In this paper, we investigate the origins of this barchan-barchan dune repulsion by carrying out grain-scale numerical computations in which a pair of granular heaps is deformed by the fluid flow into barchan dunes that interact with each other. In our simulations, data such as position, velocity and resultant force are computed for each individual particle at each time step, allowing us to measure details of both the fluid and grains that explain the repulsion. We show the trajectories of grains, time-average resultant forces, and mass balances for each dune, and that the downstream barchan shrinks faster than the upstream one, keeping, thus, a relatively high velocity although in the wake of the upstream barchan. In its turn, this fast shrinkage is caused by the flow disturbance, which induces higher erosion on the downstream barchan and its circumvention by grains leaving the upstream dune. Our results help explaining the mechanisms behind the distribution of barchans in dune fields found on Earth and Mars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07604v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1029/2024JF007741</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Geophysical Research: Earth Surface, 129, e2024JF007741, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nicolao Cerqueira Lima, Willian Righi Assis, Carlos Azael Alvarez, Erick de Moraes Franklin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards large eddy simulations of premixed turbulent flames without a combustion model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07668</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07668v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paper aims at assessing a hypothesis that resolution required to evaluate fuel consumption and heat release rates by directly (i.e., without a subgrid model of unresolved influence of small-scale turbulent eddies on the local flame) processing filtered fields of density, temperature, and species mass fractions should be significantly finer than resolution required to directly compute flame surface density by processing the same filtered fields. For this purpose, box filters of various widths are applied to three-dimensional Direct Numerical Simulation data obtained earlier by Dave et al. (Combust. Flame 196 (2018) 386-399) from a statistically one-dimensional and planar, moderately lean H2/air complex-chemistry flame propagating in a box under conditions of sufficiently intense small-scale turbulence (Karlovitz number is larger than unity and a ratio of laminar flame thickness to Kolmogorov length scale is about 20). Results confirm this hypothesis and show that the mean flame surface density and area can be predicted with acceptable accuracy by processing filtered combustion progress variable fields computed using a sufficiently wide filter. Such an approach does not require a model of the influence of subgrid turbulent eddies on flame surface density provided that filter width and laminar flame thickness are of the same order of magnitude. Good performance of this approach is attributed to inability of small-scale (when compared to the thickness) turbulent eddies to substantially change the local flame structure, which, nevertheless, is significantly perturbed by larger turbulent eddies that strain the local flame.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07668v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei N. Lipatnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-informed graph neural networks for flow field estimation in carotid arteries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07110v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hemodynamic quantities are valuable biomedical risk factors for cardiovascular pathology such as atherosclerosis. Non-invasive, in-vivo measurement of these quantities can only be performed using a select number of modalities that are not widely available, such as 4D flow magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). In this work, we create a surrogate model for hemodynamic flow field estimation, powered by machine learning. We train graph neural networks that include priors about the underlying symmetries and physics, limiting the amount of data required for training. This allows us to train the model using moderately-sized, in-vivo 4D flow MRI datasets, instead of large in-silico datasets obtained by computational fluid dynamics (CFD), as is the current standard. We create an efficient, equivariant neural network by combining the popular PointNet++ architecture with group-steerable layers. To incorporate the physics-informed priors, we derive an efficient discretisation scheme for the involved differential operators. We perform extensive experiments in carotid arteries and show that our model can accurately estimate low-noise hemodynamic flow fields in the carotid artery. Moreover, we show how the learned relation between geometry and hemodynamic quantities transfers to 3D vascular models obtained using a different imaging modality than the training data. This shows that physics-informed graph neural networks can be trained using 4D flow MRI data to estimate blood flow in unseen carotid artery geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07110v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Suk, Dieuwertje Alblas, Barbara A. Hutten, Albert Wiegman, Christoph Brune, Pim van Ooij, Jelmer M. Wolterink</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transverse Instability of Stokes Waves at Finite Depth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07169v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A Stokes wave is a traveling free-surface periodic water wave that is constant in the direction transverse to the direction of propagation. In 1981 McLean discovered via numerical methods that Stokes waves are unstable with respect to transverse perturbations. In \cite{CreNguStr} for the case of infinite depth we proved rigorously that the spectrum of the water wave system linearized at small Stokes waves, with respect to transverse perturbations, contains unstable eigenvalues lying approximately on an ellipse. In this paper we consider the case of finite depth and prove that the same spectral instability result holds for all but finitely many values of the depth. The computations and some aspects of the theory are considerably more complicated in the finite depth case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07169v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan P. Creedon, Huy Q. Nguyen, Walter A. Strauss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Thermomechanical Hybrid Incompressible Material Point Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07276v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a novel hybrid incompressible flow/material point method solver for simulating the combustion of flammable solids. Our approach utilizes a sparse grid representation of solid materials in the material point method portion of the solver and a hybrid Eulerian/FLIP solver for the incompressible portion. We utilize these components to simulate the motion of heated air and particulate matter as they interact with flammable solids, causing combustion-related damage. We include a novel particle sampling strategy to increase Eulerian flow accuracy near regions of high temperature. We also support control of the flame front propagation speed and the rate of solid combustion in an artistically directable manner. Solid combustion is modeled with temperature-dependent elastoplastic constitutive modeling. We demonstrate the efficacy of our method on various real-world three-dimensional problems, including a burning match, incense sticks, and a wood log in a fireplace.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07276v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victoria Kala, Jingyu Chen, David Hyde, Alexey Stomakhin, Joseph Teran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven computation of adjoint sensitivities without adjoint solvers: An application to thermoacoustics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11738v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Adjoint methods have been the pillar of gradient-based optimization for decades. They enable the accurate computation of a gradient (sensitivity) of a quantity of interest with respect to all system's parameters in one calculation. When the gradient is embedded in an optimization routine, the quantity of interest can be optimized for the system to have the desired behaviour. Adjoint methods require the system's governing equations and their Jacobian. We propose a computational strategy to infer the adjoint sensitivities from data when the governing equations might be unknown (or partly unknown), and noise might be present. The key component of this strategy is an echo state network, which learns the dynamics of nonlinear regimes with varying parameters, and evolves dynamically via a hidden state. Although the framework is general, we focus on thermoacoustics governed by nonlinear and time-delayed systems. First, we show that a parameter-aware Echo State Network (ESN) infers the parameterized dynamics. Second, we derive the adjoint of the ESN to compute the sensitivity to parameters and initial conditions. Third, we propose the Thermoacoustic Echo State Network (T-ESN), which embeds the physical knowledge in the network architecture. Fourth, we apply the framework to a variety of nonlinear thermoacoustic regimes of a prototypical system. We show that the T-ESN accurately infers the correct adjoint sensitivities of the time-averaged acoustic energy with respect to the flame parameters. The results are robust to noisy data, from periodic, through quasiperiodic, to chaotic regimes. A single network predicts the nonlinear bifurcations on unseen scenarios, and so the inferred adjoint sensitivities are employed to suppress an instability via steepest descent. This work opens new possibilities for gradient-based data-driven design optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11738v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Defne E. Ozan, Luca Magri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An implicit DG solver for incompressible two-phase flows with an artificial compressibility formulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.04580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.04580v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose an implicit Discontinuous Galerkin (DG) discretization for incompressible two-phase flows using an artificial compressibility formulation. The conservative level set (CLS) method is employed in combination with a reinitialization procedure to capture the moving interface. A projection method based on the L-stable TR-BDF2 method is adopted for the time discretization of the Navier-Stokes equations and of the level set method. Adaptive Mesh Refinement (AMR) is employed to enhance the resolution in correspondence of the interface between the two fluids. The effectiveness of the proposed approach is shown in a number of classical benchmarks. A specific analysis on the influence of different choices of the mixture viscosity is also carried out.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.04580v4</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Orlando</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust and accurate simulations of flows over orography using non-conforming meshes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.07759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.07759v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We systematically validate the static local mesh refinement capabilities of a recently proposed IMEX-DG scheme implemented in the framework of the deal.II library. Non-conforming meshes are employed in atmospheric flow simulations to increase the resolution around complex orography. A number of numerical experiments based on classical benchmarks with idealized as well as real orography profiles demonstrate that simulations with the refined mesh are stable for long lead times and no spurious effects arise at the interfaces of mesh regions with different resolutions. Moreover, correct values of the momentum flux are retrieved and the correct large-scale orographic response is established. Hence, large-scale orography-driven flow features can be simulated without loss of accuracy using a much lower total amount of degrees of freedom. In a context of spatial resolutions approaching the hectometric scale in numerical weather prediction models, these results support the use of locally refined, non-conforming meshes as a reliable and effective tool to greatly reduce the dependence of atmospheric models on orographic wave drag parametrizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.07759v4</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Orlando, Tommaso Benacchio, Luca Bonaventura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Onset of Intermittency in Active Turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06950v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent results suggest that highly active, chaotic, non-equilibrium states of living fluids might share much in common with high Reynolds number, inertial turbulence. We now show, by using a hydrodynamical model, the onset of intermittency and the consequent multiscaling of Eulerian and Lagrangian structure functions as a function of the bacterial activity. Our results bridge the worlds of low and high Reynolds number flows as well as open up intriguing possibilities of what makes flows intermittent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06950v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kolluru Venkata Kiran, Kunal Kumar, Anupam Gupta, Rahul Pandit, Samriddhi Sankar Ray</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
