<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.flu-dyn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn</link>
    <description>physics.flu-dyn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 04:00:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the Preprocessing of Physics-informed Neural Networks: How to Better Utilize Data in Fluid Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19923v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs) serve as a flexible alternative for tackling forward and inverse problems in differential equations, displaying impressive advancements in diverse areas of applied mathematics. Despite integrating both data and underlying physics to enrich the neural network's understanding, concerns regarding the effectiveness and practicality of PINNs persist. Over the past few years, extensive efforts in the current literature have been made to enhance this evolving method, by drawing inspiration from both machine learning algorithms and numerical methods. Despite notable progressions in PINNs algorithms, the important and fundamental field of data preprocessing remain unexplored, limiting the applications of PINNs especially in solving inverse problems. Therefore in this paper, a concise yet potent data preprocessing method focusing on data normalization was proposed. By applying a linear transformation to both the data and corresponding equations concurrently, the normalized PINNs approach was evaluated on the task of reconstructing flow fields in three turbulent cases. The results, both qualitatively and quantitatively, illustrate that by adhering to the data preprocessing procedure, PINNs can robustly achieve higher prediction accuracy for all flow quantities through the entire training process, distinctly improving the utilization of limited training data. The proposed normalization method requires zero extra computational cost. Though only verified in Navier-Stokes (NS) equations, this method holds potential for application to various other equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19923v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengfeng Xu, Chang Yan, Zhenxu Sun, Renfang Huang, Dilong Guo, Guowei Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One dimensional models for supercritical and subcritical transitions in rotating convection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19953</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19953v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Numerous study on natural and man made systems including rotating convection report the phenomena of supercritical and subcritical transitions from one state to another with the variation of relevant control parameters. However, the complexity of the rotating convection system even under the idealized Rayleigh-B\'enard geometry, hindered the simplest possible description of these transitions to convection. Here we present an one dimensional description of the stationary subcritical and supercritical transitions to rotating Rayleigh-B\'enard convection both for rigid and free-slip boundary conditions. The analysis of the one dimensional models and performance of three dimensional direct numerical simulations of the system show qualitatively similar results in a wide region of the parameter space. A brief discussion on time dependent convection of overstable origin is also presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19953v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sutapa Mandal, Snehashish Sarkar, Pinaki Pal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Depth from Defocus Technique for High Number Densities and Non-spherical Particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20004</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20004v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Depth from Defocus (DFD) imaging technique for measuring the size and number concentration of particles in a dispersed two-phase flow has up to now been restricted to relatively sparse particle densities and to identifying only spherical particles. The present study examines two advancements to the technique, widening its range of application significantly. The first advancement introduces an image processing procedure which can identify and size particle images which are overlapping. This increases the tolerable number concentration of particles which can be identified and processed within the measurement volume. The second advancement explores the possibility of determining the size and position of non-spherical particles within an observation volume. Both advancements build on recent theoretical work, utilizing not only the gray level of the blurred, out-of-focus images, but also the gradient of the gray level normal to the nominal particle or particle ensemble contour. This gray-level gradient is used to estimate the width of the blur kernel, which is assumed to remain Gaussian.
  These enhancements are experimentally validated using a dedicated apparatus in which particles of known size, shape and degree of overlapping images can be systematically varied. This experimental setup provides benchmark data to quantify the accuracy and limitations of the processing algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20004v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rixin Xua, Zuojie Huanga, Wenchao Gonga, Wu Zhoua, Cameron Tropea</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rise and fall of a multicomponent droplet in a surrounrdfing fluid: simulation study of a bumpy path</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20040v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The coupling between mass transfer and hydrodynamic phenomena in two-phase flow is not necessarily straightforward due to the different effects that can be encountered. The treatment of such coupling is complex and requires particular efforts, especially in the modelling of the interface between phases. In this paper, we consider the case of a droplet composed of two components (one miscible and one immiscible in water) released in a 2D rectangular domain filled with water. Mass transfer occurs between the miscible element and the surrounding water, which leads to a density inversion that directly affects the droplet trajectory through buoyancy. We perform simulations using a ternary Cahn-Hilliard model (implemented in the "phase\_field" model of the TrioCFD code) to capture such coupled phenomena. The Boussinesq approximation for a multicomponent system is used to define the density law and an analytical chemical potential is proposed for the thermodynamic landscape. The effect of the mobility parameter on the flow is highlighted and the results found are in good agreement with the dynamics described from an experimental study of the open literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20040v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mirantsoa Aim\'e Rasolofomanana, Romain Le Tellier, Herv\'e Henry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An enthalpy-based model for the physics of ice crystal icing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20071v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ice crystal icing (ICI) in aircraft engines is a major threat to flight safety. Due to the complex thermodynamic and phase-change conditions involved in ICI, rigorous modelling of the accretion process remains limited. The present study proposes a novel modelling approach based on the physically-observed mixed-phase nature of the accretion layers. The mathematical model, which is derived from the enthalpy change after accretion (the enthalpy model), is compared to an existing pure-phase layer model (the three-layer model). Scaling laws and asymptotic solutions are developed for both models. The onset of ice accretion, the icing layer thickness, and solid ice fraction within the layer are determined by a set of non-dimensional parameters including the Peclet number, the Stefan number, the Biot number, the Melt Ratio, and the evaporative rate. Thresholds for freezing and non-freezing conditions are developed. The asymptotic solutions presents good agreement with numerical solutions at low Peclet numbers. Both the asymptotic and numerical solutions show that, when compared to the three-layer model, the enthalpy model presents a thicker icing layer and a thicker water layer above the substrate due to mixed-phased features and modified Stefan conditions. Modelling in terms of the enthalpy poses significant advantages in the development of numerical methods to complex three-dimensional geometrical and flow configurations. These results improve understanding of the accretion process and provide a novel, rigorous mathematical framework for accurate modelling of ICI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20071v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothy Peters, Josh Shelton, Hui Tang, Philippe Trinh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hydroelectric energy conversion of waste flows through hydro-electronic drag</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20209v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hydraulic energy is a key component of the global energy mix, yet there exists no practical way of harvesting it at small scales, from flows at low Reynolds number. This has triggered the search for alternative hydroelectric conversion methodologies, leading to unconventional proposals based on droplet triboelectricity, water evaporation, osmotic energy or flow-induced ionic Coulomb drag. Yet, these approaches systematically rely on ions as intermediate charge carriers, limiting the achievable power density. Here, we predict that the kinetic energy of small-scale "waste" flows can be directly and efficiently converted into electricity thanks to the hydro-electronic drag effect, by which an ion-free liquid induces an electronic current in the solid wall along which it flows. This effect originates in the fluctuation-induced coupling between fluid motion and electron transport. We develop a non-equilibrium thermodynamic formalism to assess the efficiency of such hydroelectric energy conversion, dubbed hydronic energy. We find that hydronic energy conversion is analogous to thermoelectricity, with the efficiency being controlled by a dimensionless figure of merit. However, in contrast to its thermoelectric analogue, this figure of merit combines independently tunable parameters of the solid and the liquid, and can thus significantly exceed unity. Our findings suggest new strategies for blue energy harvesting without electrochemistry, and for waste flow mitigation in membrane-based filtration processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20209v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baptiste Coquinot, Lyd\'eric Bocquet, Nikita Kavokine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active flow control of a turbulent separation bubble through deep reinforcement learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20295v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The control efficacy of classical periodic forcing and deep reinforcement learning (DRL) is assessed for a turbulent separation bubble (TSB) at $Re_\tau=180$ on the upstream region before separation occurs. The TSB can resemble a separation phenomenon naturally arising in wings, and a successful reduction of the TSB can have practical implications in the reduction of the aviation carbon footprint. We find that the classical zero-net-mas-flux (ZNMF) periodic control is able to reduce the TSB by 15.7%. On the other hand, the DRL-based control achieves 25.3% reduction and provides a smoother control strategy while also being ZNMF. To the best of our knowledge, the current test case is the highest Reynolds-number flow that has been successfully controlled using DRL to this date. In future work, these results will be scaled to well-resolved large-eddy simulation grids. Furthermore, we provide details of our open-source CFD-DRL framework suited for the next generation of exascale computing machines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20295v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernat Font, Francisco Alc\'antara-\'Avila, Jean Rabault, Ricardo Vinuesa, Oriol Lehmkuhl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Taylor and the Trinity Test</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19657v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The atomic bomb uses fission of heavy elements to produce a large amount of energy. It was designed and deployed during World War II by the United States military. The first test of an atomic bomb occurred in July of 1945 in New Mexico and was given the name Trinity; this test was not declassified until 1949. In that year Geoffrey Ingram Taylor released two papers, detailing his process in calculating the energy yield of the atomic bomb from pictures of the Trinity explosion alone. Many scientists made similar calculations concurrently, though Taylor is often accredited with them. Since then many scientists have also attempted a to calculate a yield through various methods. This paper walks through these methods with a focus on Taylor's method -- based on first principles -- as well as redoing the calculations that he performed with modern tools. In this paper we make use of the state-of-the-art computer vision tools to find a more precise measurement of the blast radius, as well as using curve fitting and numerical integration methods. With more precise measurements we are able to follow in Taylor's footstep towards a more accurate approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19657v1</guid>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elizabeth Mone (College of Sciences, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, Georgia), Pranay Seshadri (College of Engineering, Georgia Institute of Technology, Atlanta, Georgia)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Main topics of the NumHyp-2015' discussion session</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19690v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Three main topics were raised in this discussion session, which took place on the 19th of June at the NumHyp-2015 meeting: nonlinear resonance for 1D systems of balance laws, dispersive extensions of standard hyperbolic conservation laws, and the validation of weakly dispersive shallow water wave models. An introductory overview with many bibliographic references is provided for all these topics. Based on kinetic formulation, a numerical strategy that can overcome resonance issues is presented, and a well-balanced (WB) technique for Vlasov-Fokker-Planck equations is outlined. This WB scheme relies on the spectral representation of stationary solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19690v1</guid>
      <category>math.HO</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denys Dutykh, Laurent Gosse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vortical waves in a quantum fluid with vector, axial and helical charges. I. Non-dissipative transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19755v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Due to the spin-orbit coupling, Dirac fermions, submerged in a thermal bath with finite macroscopic vorticity, exhibit a spin polarisation along the direction parallel to the vorticity vector $\boldsymbol{\Omega}$. Due to the symmetries of the Lagrangian for free massless Dirac particles, there are three independent and classically conserved currents corresponding to the vector, axial, and helical charges. The constitutive relations for the charge currents and the stress-energy tensor at thermal equilibrium, derived in the framework of quantum field theory at finite temperature, reveal vorticity-induced contributions that deviate from the perfect fluid form. In this paper, we consider the mode structure of the corresponding hydrodynamical theory and derive collective excitations associated with coherent fluctuations of all three charges. We show that the chirally imbalanced rotating fluid should possess non-reciprocal gapless waves that propagate with different velocities along and opposite to the vorticity vector. We also uncover a strictly unidirectional mode, which we call the Axial Vortical Wave, propagating in the background of the axial charge density. We point out an unexpected instability in the limit of degenerate matter and discuss possible solutions when helicity and axial charge non-conservation is taken into account.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19755v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio Morales-Tejera, Victor E. Ambru\c{s}, Maxim N. Chernodub</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vortical waves in a quantum fluid with vector, axial and helical charges. II. Dissipative effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19756v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the effect of interactions on the local, average polarization of a quantum plasma of massless fermion particles characterized by vector, axial, and helical quantum numbers. Due to the helical and axial vortical effects, perturbations in the vector charge in a rotating plasma can lead to chiral and helical charge transfer along the direction of the vorticity vector. At the same time, interactions between the plasma constituents lead to the dissipation of the helical charge through helicity-violating pair annihilation (HVPA) processes and of the axial charge through the axial anomaly. We will discuss separately a QED-like plasma, in which we ignore background electromagnetic fields and thus the axial charge is roughly conserved, as well as a QCD-like plasma, where instanton effects lead to the violation of the axial charge conservation, even in the absence of background chromomagnetic fields. The non-conservation of helicity and chirality leads to a gapping of the Helical, Axial and mixed, Axial-Helical vortical waves that prevents their infrared modes from propagating. On the other hand, usual dissipative effects, such as charge diffusion, lead to significant damping of ultraviolet modes. We end this paper with a discussion of the regimes where these vortical waves may propagate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19756v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio Morales-Tejera, Victor E. Ambru\c{s}, Maxim N. Chernodub</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bridging Microscopic Dynamics and Hydraulic Permeability in Mechanically-Deformed Nanoporous Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19812v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the field of nanoconfined fluids, there are striking examples of deformation/transport coupling in which mechanical solicitation of the confining host and dynamics of the confined fluid impact each other. While this intriguing behavior can be potentially used for practical applications (e.g. energy storage, phase separation, catalysis), the underlying mechanisms remain to be understood as they challenge existing frameworks. Here, using molecular simulations analyzed through concepts inherent to interfacial fluids, we investigate fluid flow in compliant nanoporous materials subjected to external mechanical stresses. We show that the pore mechanical properties significantly affect fluid flow as they lead to significant pore deformations and different density layering at the interface accounted for by invoking interfacial viscous effects. Despite such poromechanical effects, we show that the thermodynamic properties (i.e. adsorption) can be linked consistently to Darcy's law for the permeability by invoking a pore size definition based on the concept of Gibbs' dividing surface. In particular, regardless of the pore stiffness and applied external stress, all data can be rationalized by accounting for the fluid viscosity and slippage at the interface independent of a specific pore size definition. Using such a formalism, we establish that the intimate relation - derived using the linear response theory - between collective diffusivity and hydraulic permeability remains valid. This allows for linking consistently microscopic dynamics experiments and permeability experiments on fluid flow in compliant nanoporous materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19812v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Schlaich, Matthieu Vandamme, Marie Plazanet, Benoit Coasne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Available potential vorticity and the wave-vortex decomposition for arbitrary stratification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.20269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.20269v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a rotating non-hydrostatic flow with arbitrary stratification and argue that 1) the appropriate form of potential vorticity (PV) for this system is in terms of isopycnal deviation and 2) the decomposition into energetically orthogonal solutions is fundamentally a PV-inversion.
  The new closed-form expression for available potential vorticity (APV) is expressed in terms of isopycnal deviation, following the ideas in Wagner &amp; Young (2015). This form of APV linearizes to quasigeostrophic PV (QGPV) after discarding the nonlinear stretching term and a height nonlinearity, the latter of which is not present in constant stratification. This formulation leads to positive definite definitions of potential enstrophy and total energy expressed in terms of isopycnal deviation, from which the quadratic versions emerge at lowest order. It is exactly these quantities diagonalized by the linear eigenmodes.
  Internal-gravity waves, geostrophic motions, inertial oscillations, and a mean density anomaly form the energetically and enstrophically orthogonal constituents of flow. The complete state of the fluid can be represented in terms of these physically realizeable modes and determined from the derived projection operators using the horizontal velocity and density anomaly. The projection of the fluid state onto the non-hydrostatic wave modes, reveals that one must first account for the PV portion of the flow before recovering the wave solutions.
  We apply the physical insights of the decomposition to a mesoscale eddy showing how strict adherence to adiabatic rearrangement places strong constraints on the vertical structure of such eddies, including a skew towards stronger cyclonic eddies in the upper water-column. Finally, the expression for APV is shown to reproduce the height nonlinearity of shallow-water PV, a well know feature that breaks the cyclone-anticyclone symmetry in QGPV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.20269v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey J. Early, Gerardo Hern\'andez-Due\~nas, Leslie M. Smith, M. -Pascale Lelong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A phase diagram of the pinch-off behavior of impulsively-induced viscoelastic liquid jets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.01364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.01364v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we systematically investigate the behaviors of viscoelastic liquid jets using an impulsive force, particularly in the high velocity and high elasticity regimes. The resulting jets are categorized into two types: (i) pinch-off jets, which break up during elongation after ejection, and (ii) no-pinch-off jets, which either retract to the nozzle after maximum elongation, known as `bungee-jumper jets' or return without elongation after ejection. We then propose criteria to delineate these regions using Reynolds number $Re$ and Weissenberg number $Wi$, reflecting the initial conditions at the jet ejection and the solution's rheological properties, respectively. We find that pinch-off jets occur at $Re \gtrsim 23.4Wi$ in high elasticity regimes ($Wi \gtrsim 10$), and at $Re \gtrsim 250$ in low elasticity regimes ($Wi \lesssim 10$). In addition, we demonstrate that the phase diagram of these behaviors can be rationalized through the focused jet modeling using the finitely extensible non-linear elastic dumbbell model with the Chilcott-Rallison closure approximation (FENE-CR).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.01364v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asuka Hosokawa, Kyota Kamamoto, Hiroya Watanabe, Hiroaki Kusuno, Kazuya U. Kobayashi, Yoshiyuki Tagawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological fluids with boundaries and fractional quantum Hall edge dynamics: A fluid dynamics derivation of the chiral boson action</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.06516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.06516v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the bulk and boundary dynamics of Laughlin states, which are modeled using composite boson theory within a fluid dynamics framework. In this work, we adopt an alternative starting point based on a hydrodynamic action with topological terms, which fleshes out the fluid aspects of the Laughlin state manifestly. For a particular choice of the velocity field, the fluid equation for this action is akin to first-order hydrodynamic equations, supplemented with an additional constitutive equation known as the Hall constraint. When a hard wall boundary is present, one of the topological terms in the fluid action triggers anomaly inflow, indicating the presence of gauge anomaly at the edge. The first-order hydrodynamic equations require a second boundary condition which, in the absence of dissipation, can be either a no-slip or a no-stress condition. We find that the no-slip condition, where the fluid adheres to the wall is incompatible with the chiral edge dynamics. On the other hand, the no-stress condition, which allows the fluid to move along the wall without friction, is consistent with the expected chiral edge dynamics of the Laughlin state. Furthermore, our work derives this modified no-stress boundary condition within a variational principle. This is accomplished by incorporating a chiral boson action within the boundary action that is non-linearly coupled to the edge density, thus systematically extending the edge chiral Luttinger liquid theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.06516v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gustavo M. Monteiro, V. P. Nair, Sriram Ganeshan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potential quantum advantage for simulation of fluid dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.16550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.16550v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Numerical simulation of turbulent fluid dynamics needs to either parameterize turbulence-which introduces large uncertainties-or explicitly resolve the smallest scales-which is prohibitively expensive. Here we provide evidence through analytic bounds and numerical studies that a potential quantum exponential speedup can be achieved to simulate the Navier-Stokes equations governing turbulence using quantum computing. Specifically, we provide a formulation of the lattice Boltzmann equation for which we give evidence that low-order Carleman linearization is much more accurate than previously believed for these systems and that for computationally interesting examples. This is achieved via a combination of reformulating the nonlinearity and accurately linearizing the dynamical equations, effectively trading nonlinearity for additional degrees of freedom that add negligible expense in the quantum solver. Based on this we apply a quantum algorithm for simulating the Carleman-linearized lattice Boltzmann equation and provide evidence that its cost scales logarithmically with system size, compared to polynomial scaling in the best known classical algorithms. This work suggests that an exponential quantum advantage may exist for simulating fluid dynamics, paving the way for simulating nonlinear multiscale transport phenomena in a wide range of disciplines using quantum computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.16550v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangyu Li, Xiaolong Yin, Nathan Wiebe, Jaehun Chun, Gregory K. Schenter, Margaret S. Cheung, Johannes M\"ulmenst\"adt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sample-Efficient and Surrogate-Based Design Optimization of Underwater Vehicle Hulls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.12420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.12420v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Physics simulations like computational fluid dynamics (CFD) are a computational bottleneck in computer-aided design (CAD) optimization processes. To overcome this bottleneck, one requires either an optimization framework that is highly sample-efficient, or a fast data-driven proxy (surrogate model) for long-running simulations. Both approaches have benefits and limitations. Bayesian optimization is often used for sample efficiency, but it solves one specific problem and struggles with transferability; alternatively, surrogate models can offer fast and often more generalizable solutions for CFD problems, but gathering data for and training such models can be computationally demanding. In this work, we leverage recent advances in optimization and artificial intelligence (AI) to explore both of these potential approaches, in the context of designing an optimal unmanned underwater vehicle (UUV) hull. Our study finds that the Bayesian Optimization-Lower Condition Bound (BO-LCB) algorithm is the most sample-efficient optimization framework and has the best convergence behavior of those considered. Subsequently, we show that our DNN-based surrogate model predicts drag force on test data in tight agreement with CFD simulations, with a mean absolute percentage error (MAPE) of 1.85%. Combining these results, we demonstrate a two-orders-of-magnitude speedup (with comparable accuracy) for the design optimization process when the surrogate model is used. To our knowledge, this is the first study applying Bayesian optimization and DNN-based surrogate modeling to the problem of UUV design optimization, and we share our developments as open-source software.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.12420v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harsh Vardhan, David Hyde, Umesh Timalsina, Peter Volgyesi, Janos Sztipanovits</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
