<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.flu-dyn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn</link>
    <description>physics.flu-dyn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 04:00:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 16 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Active flow control over a sphere using a smart morphable skin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.08896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.08896v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dimples on a sphere's surface can lead to significant drag reduction. However, the optimal dimple depth to minimize the drag varies with the Reynolds number ($Re$). In this study, a smart surface-morphing technique is devised that can adjust dimple depth based on the flow conditions to minimize drag across a wide range of $Re$ values. By depressurizing the core of a rigid skeleton enclosed with a thin latex membrane, the dimple depth can be precisely controlled in response to flow velocity changes. A comprehensive series of systematic experiments are performed for Reynolds number range of $6\times10^4 \leq Re \leq 1.3\times10^5$, and dimple depth ratios of $0 \leq k/d \leq 2\times10^{-2}$ using the morphable sphere. It is observed that the dimple depth ratio $k/d$ significantly affects both the onset of the drag crisis and the minimum achievable drag. As $k/d$ increases, the critical Reynolds number for the drag crisis decreases. However, the minimum achievable drag coefficient decreases as $k/d$ increases. By carefully adjusting the $k/d$ to $Re$ using the morphable approach, our experiments show that $C_D$ reductions up to 50 % can be achieved when compared to a smooth counterpart for all the $Re$ considered. For a constant $Re$, drag reduces as $k/d$ increases. However, there is a critical threshold beyond which drag amplification starts to occur. Particle image velocimetry (PIV) reveals a delay in flow separation on the sphere's surface with increasing $k/d$, causing the separation angle to shift downstream. However, when $k/d$ exceeds the critical threshold, flow separation moves upstream, causing an increase in drag. By using the experimental data, a control model is also developed relating optimum $k/d$ with $Re$ to minimize drag. This model also serves as the basis for adaptive drag control of the sphere for a wide range of Reynolds number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.08896v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo Vilumbrales-Garcia, Putu Brahmanda Sudarsana, Anchal Sareen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven discovery of drag-inducing elements on a rough surface through convolutional neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09071v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the influence of surface roughness on drag forces remains a significant challenge in fluid dynamics. This paper presents a convolutional neural network (CNN) that predicts drag solely by the topography of rough surfaces and is capable of discovering spatial patterns linked to drag-inducing structures. A CNN model was developed to analyze spatial information from the topography of a rough surface and predict the roughness function, $\Delta U^+$, obtained from direct numerical simulation. This model enables the prediction of drag from rough surface data alone, which was not possible with previous methods owing to the large number of surface-derived parameters. Additionally, the retention of spatial information by the model enables the creation of a feature map that accentuates critical areas for drag prediction on rough surfaces. By interpreting the feature maps, we show that the developed CNN model is able to discover spatial patterns associated with drag distributions across rough surfaces, even without a direct training on drag distribution data. The analysis of the feature map indicates that, even without flow field information, the CNN model extracts the importance of the flow-directional slope and height of roughness elements as key factors in inducing pressure drag. This study demonstrates that CNN-based drag prediction is grounded in physical principles of fluid dynamics, underscoring the utility of CNNs in both predicting and understanding drag on rough surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09071v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heesoo Shin, Seyed Morteza Habibi Khorasani, Zhaoyu Shi, Jiasheng Yang, Sangseung Lee, Shervin Bagheri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of a fixed downstream cylinder on the flow-induced vibration of an elastically-supported primary cylinder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper numerically investigates the influence of a fixed downstream control cylinder on the flow-induced vibration of an elastically-supported primary cylinder. These two cylinders are situated in a tandem arrangement with small dimensionless centre-to-centre spacing ($L/D$, $L$ is the intermediate spacing, and $D$ is the cylinder diameter). The present two-dimensional (2D) simulations are carried out in the low Reynolds number ($Re$) regime. The primary focus of this study is to reveal the underlying flow physics behind the transition from vortex-induced vibration to galloping in the response of the primary cylinder due to the presence of another fixed downstream cylinder. Two distinct flow field regimes, namely steady flow and alternate attachment regimes, are observed for different $L/D$ and Re values. Depending on the evolution of the near-field flow structures, four different wake patterns - `2S', `2P', `2C', and `aperiodic' - are observed. The corresponding vibration response of the upstream cylinder is characterized as interference galloping and extended vortex-induced vibration. As the $L/D$ ratio increases, the lift enhancement due to flow-induced vibration is seen to be weakened. The detailed correlation between the force generation and the near-wake interactions is investigated. The present findings will augment the understanding of vibration reduction or flow-induced energy harvesting of tandem cylindrical structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09072v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junlei Wang, Shenfang Li, Daniil Yurchenko, Hongjun Zhu, Chandan Bose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-diffusiophoretic propulsion of a spheroidal particle in a shear-thinning fluid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09136v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Shear-thinning viscosity is a non-Newtonian behaviour that active particles often encounter in biological fluids such as blood and mucus. The fundamental question of how this ubiquitous non-Newtonian rheology affects the propulsion of active particles has attracted substantial interest. In particular, spherical Janus particles driven by self-diffusiophresis, a major physico-chemical propulsion mechanism of synthetic active particles, were shown to always swim slower in a shear-thinning fluid than in a Newtonian fluid. In this work, we move beyond the spherical limit to examine the effect of particle eccentricity on self-diffusiophoretic propulsion in a shear-thinning fluid. We use a combination of asymptotic analysis and numerical simulations to show that shear-thinning rheology can enhance self-diffusiophoretic propulsion of a spheroidal particle, in stark contrast to previous findings for the spherical case. A systematic characterization of the dependence of the propulsion speed on the particle's active surface coverage has also uncovered an intriguing feature associated with the propulsion speeds of a pair of complementarily coated particles not previously reported. Symmetry arguments are presented to elucidate how this new feature emerges as a combined effect of anisotropy of the spheroidal geometry and nonlinearity in fluid rheology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09136v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/jfm.2024.350</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Fluid Mechanics, 986, A39 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Guangpu Zhu, Brandon van Gogh, Lailai Zhu, On Shun Pak, Yi Man</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of melting and solidification in the spreading of an impacting water drop</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09143v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The present study reports experiments of water droplet impacting on ice or on a cold metallic substrate, with the aim of understanding the effect of phase change on the impingement process. Both liquid and substrate temperatures are varied, as well as the height of fall. The dimensionless maximum spreading diameter, $\beta_m$, is found to increase with both temperatures as well as with the impact velocity. Furthermore, $\beta_m$ is reduced when solidification, which enhances dissipation, is present, whereas fusion favours the liquid film spreading. These observations are rationalized by extending an existing model of effective viscosity, in which phase change alters the size and shape of the developing viscous boundary layer, thereby modifying the value of $\beta_m$. The use of this correction allows to adapt a scaling law existing for isothermal drop impacts to propose a universal law giving the maximum diameter of an impacting water droplet in the presence of melting or solidification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09143v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wladimir Sarlin, Rodolphe Grivet, Julien Xu, Axel Huerre, Thomas S\'eon, Christophe Josserand</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drag prediction of rough-wall turbulent flow using data-driven regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09256v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Efficient tools for predicting the drag of rough walls in turbulent flows would have a tremendous impact. However, methods for drag prediction rely on experiments or numerical simulations which are costly and time-consuming. Data-driven regression methods have the potential to provide a prediction that is accurate and fast. We assess the performance and limitations of linear regression, kernel methods and neural networks for drag prediction using a database of 1000 homogeneous rough surfaces. Model performance is evaluated using the roughness function obtained at friction-scaled Reynolds number 500. With two trainable parameters, the kernel method can fully account for nonlinear relations between $\Delta U^+$ and surface statistics (roughness height, effective slope, skewness, etc). In contrast, linear regression cannot account for nonlinear correlations and display large errors and high uncertainty. Multilayer perceptron and convolutional neural networks demonstrate performance on par with the kernel method but have orders of magnitude more trainable parameters. For the current database size, the networks' capacity cannot be fully exploited, resulting in reduced generalizability and reliability. Our study provides insight into the appropriateness of different regression models for drag prediction. We also discuss the remaining steps before data-driven methods emerge as useful tools in applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09256v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoyu Shi, Seyed Morteza Habibi Khorasani, Heesoo Shin, Jiasheng Yang, Sangseung Lee, Shervin Bagheri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tip-leakage-flow excited unsteadiness and associated control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09347v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tip leakage flow in turbomachinery inherently generates intense unsteady features, named self-excited unsteadiness, which has not been well understood. A Zonalised LES (ZLES) is employed around a linear cascade, with wall-modelled Large Eddy Simulation (LES) forced to be active in the tip region. The simulation is well validated and demonstrated the advantages of effectively reducing the computational effort while maintaining an equivalent prediction accuracy in the region of interest. The time-averaged and spatial-spectral characteristics of tip leakage vortex (TLV) structures are systematically discussed. The self-excited unsteady processes of TLV include unsteady vortex separation inside the tip gap, the tip leakage jet-mainstream interaction, the primary tip leakage vortex (PTLV) wandering motion and the induced separation near endwall. The Spectral Proper Orthogonal Decomposition (SPOD) is used to examine the dominant frequencies and their coherent structures. It is found that these unsteady features change from a single high-frequency mode to a multiple lower-frequencies mode due to the PTLV breakdown. The SPOD and correlation analyses reveal that the self-excited unsteadiness is mainly induced by the interactions between unsteady vortex separation, tip leakage jet, and mainstream. The associated unsteady fluctuations are convected along the tip leakage jet trajectory, causing the wandering motion of PTLV core. Based on the cause of the investigated unsteadiness, a micro-offset tip design is proposed and validated for effectively suppressing this unsteadiness, and associated turbulence generation and hence pressure fluctuations. This work improves the understanding of tip-leakage-flow dynamics and informs the control of the associated unsteady fluid oscillation and noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09347v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0206385</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yabin Liu, Zhong-Nan Wang, Paul Gary Tucker, Felix M. M\"oller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advection of the image point in probabilistically-reconstructed phase spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09410v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Insufficient reference data is ubiquitous in data-driven computational fluid dynamics, as it is usually too expensive to compute or impossible to observe over long enough times needed for data-driven methods to properly operate out of the sampled range. Ultimately, the lack of data can significantly compromise the fidelity of results computed with data-driven methods or make the data-driven approach inapplicable. In order to challenge this problem, we propose a probabilistic reconstruction method which enriches the hyper-parameterisation approach with ideas underlying the probabilistic-evolutionary approach. We offer to use Advection of the image point (a hyper-parameterisation method) on data sampled from the joint probability distribution of the reference dataset. The idea is to blend together the simplicity of the hyper-parameterisation (HP) method with an extra source of reference data provided through sampling from the joint probability distribution.
  The HP method has been tested on the sea surface temperature and surface relative vorticity computed with the global 1/4-degree and 1/12-degree resolution NEMO model. Our results show that the HP solution (the solution computed with the HP method) in the probabilistically-reconstructed and reduced (in terms of dimensionality) phase space at 1/4-degree resolution is more accurate compared to the 1/4-degree solution computed with NEMO and it is also several orders of magnitude faster to compute than the 1/4-degree run. The proposed method shows encouraging results for the NEMO model and the potential for the use in other operational ocean and ocean-atmospheric models for both deterministic and probabilistic predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09410v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Shevchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A dissipative extension to ideal hydrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09495v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a formulation of special relativistic, dissipative hydrodynamics (SRDHD) derived from the well-established M\"uller- Israel-Stewart (MIS) formalism using an expansion in deviations from ideal behaviour. By re-summing the non-ideal terms, our approach extends the Euler equations of motion for an ideal fluid through a series of additional source terms that capture the effects of bulk viscosity, shear viscosity and heat flux. For efficiency these additional terms are built from purely spatial derivatives of the primitive fluid variables. The series expansion is parametrized by the dissipation strength and timescale coefficients, and is therefore rapidly convergent near the ideal limit. We show, using numerical simulations, that our model reproduces the dissipative fluid behaviour of other formulations. As our formulation is designed to avoid the numerical stiffness issues that arise in the traditional MIS formalism for fast relaxation timescales, it is roughly an order of magnitude faster than standard methods near the ideal limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09495v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcus J. Hatton, Ian Hawke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caustic formation in a non-Gaussian model for turbulent aerosols</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.10689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.10689v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Caustics in the dynamics of heavy particles in turbulence accelerate particle collisions. The rate $\mathscr{J}$ at which these singularities form depends sensitively on the Stokes number St, the non-dimensional inertia parameter. Exact results for this sensitive dependence have been obtained using Gaussian statistical models for turbulent aerosols. However, direct numerical simulations of heavy particles in turbulence yield much larger caustic-formation rates than predicted by the Gaussian theory. In order to understand possible mechanisms explaining this difference, we analyse a non-Gaussian statistical model for caustic formation in the limit of small St. We show that at small St, $\mathscr{J}$ depends sensitively on the tails of the distribution of Lagrangian fluid-velocity gradients. This explains why different authors obtained different St-dependencies of $\mathscr{J}$ in numerical-simulation studies. The most-likely gradient fluctuation that induces caustics at small St, by contrast, is the same in the non-Gaussian and Gaussian models. Direct-numerical simulation results for particles in turbulence show that the optimal fluctuation is similar, but not identical, to that obtained by the model calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.10689v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevFluids.9.024302</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Fluids 9, 024302 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>J. Meibohm, L. Sundberg, B. Mehlig, K. Gustavsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spheres and fibres in turbulent flows at various Reynolds numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07986v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We perform fully coupled numerical simulations using immersed boundary methods of finite-size spheres and fibres suspended in a turbulent flow for a range of Taylor Reynolds numbers $12.8&lt;Re_\lambda&lt;442$ and solid mass fractions $0\leq M\leq1$. Both spheres and fibres reduce the turbulence intensity with respect to the single-phase flow at all Reynolds numbers, with fibres causing a more significant reduction than the spheres. The particles' effect on the anomalous dissipation tends to vanish as $Re \to \infty$. A scale-by-scale analysis shows that both particle shapes provide a "spectral shortcut" to the flow, but the shortcut extends further into the dissipative range in the case of fibres. Multifractal spectra of the near-particle dissipation show that spheres enhance dissipation in two-dimensional sheets, and fibres enhance the dissipation in structures with a dimension greater than one and less than two. In addition, we show that spheres suppress vortical flow structures, whereas fibres produce structures which completely overcome the turbulent vortex stretching behaviour in their vicinity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07986v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ianto Cannon, Stefano Olivieri, Marco E. Rosti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slender vortex filaments in the Boussinesq Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00460v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A model for the motion of slender vortex filaments is extended to include the effect of gravity. The model, initially introduced by Callegari and Ting (SIAM, J. of App. Math., (1978), vol. 35, pp. 148-175), is based on a matched asymptotic expansion in which the outer solution, given by the Biot-Savart law, is matched with the inner solution derived from the Navier-Stokes equations. Building on recent work by Harikrishnan et al (Phys. of Fluids, (2023), vol. 35) the Boussinesq approximation is applied such that the density variations only enter in the gravity term. However, unlike Harikrishnan et al. (2023) the density variation enters at a lower order in the asymptotic expansion, and thus has a more significant impact on the self-induced velocity of the vortex filament. In this regime, which corresponds to the regime studied by Chang and Smith (J. of Fl. Mech., (2018), vol. 857), the effect of gravity is given by an alteration of the core constant, which couples the motion of the filament to the motion within the vortical core, in addition to a change in the compatability conditions (evolution equations) which determine the leading order azimuthal and tangential velocity fields in the vortex core. The results are used to explain certain properties of bouyant vortex rings, as well as qualitatively explore the impact of gravity on tornado type atmospheric vorticies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00460v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0205028</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physics of Fluids 1 May 2024; 36 (5): 056604</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marie Rodal, Daniel Margerit, Rupert Klein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The atomizing pulsed jet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01959v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Direct Numerical Simulations of the injection of a pulsed round liquid jet in a stagnant gas are performed. The Reynolds and Weber numbers and the density ratio are sufficiently large for reaching a complex high-speed atomization regime. The Weber number based on grid size is small, an indication that the simulations are very well resolved. Computations are performed using octree adaptive mesh refinement using the Basilisk free-code platform, down to a specified minimum grid size $\Delta$. Qualitative analysis of the flow and its topology reveal a complex structure of ligaments, sheets, droplets and bubbles that evolve and interact through impacts, ligament breakup, sheet rupture and engulfment of air bubbles in the liquid. A rich gallery of images of entangled structures is produced. Most processes occurring in this type of atomization are reproduced in detail, except at the instant of thin sheet perforation or breakup. We analyze drop statistics, showing that as the grid resolution is increased, the small-scale part of the distribution does not converge, and contains a large number of droplets close in order of magnitude to the minimum grid size with a significant peak at $d = 3\Delta$ . This non-convergence arises from the numerical sheet breakup effect, in which the interface becomes rough just before it breaks. The rough appearance of the interface is associated to a high-wavenumber oscillation of the curvature. To recover convergence, we apply the controlled "manifold death" numerical procedure, in which thin sheets are detected, and then pierced by fiat before they reach a set critical thickness $h_c$ that is always larger than $6 \Delta$. This allows convergence of the droplet frequency above a certain critical diameter $d_c$ above and close to $h_c$. A unimodal distribution is observed in the converged range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01959v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yash Kulkarni, Cesar Pairetti, Rapha\"el Villiers, St\'ephane Popinet, St\'ephane Zaleski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A multiscale and multicriteria Generative Adversarial Network to synthesize 1-dimensional turbulent fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.16580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.16580v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article introduces a new Neural Network stochastic model to generate a 1-dimensional stochastic field with turbulent velocity statistics. Both the model architecture and training procedure ground on the Kolmogorov and Obukhov statistical theories of fully developed turbulence, so guaranteeing descriptions of 1) energy distribution, 2) energy cascade and 3) intermittency across scales in agreement with experimental observations. The model is a Generative Adversarial Network with multiple multiscale optimization criteria. First, we use three physics-based criteria: the variance, skewness and flatness of the increments of the generated field that retrieve respectively the turbulent energy distribution, energy cascade and intermittency across scales. Second, the Generative Adversarial Network criterion, based on reproducing statistical distributions, is used on segments of different length of the generated field. Furthermore, to mimic multiscale decompositions frequently used in turbulence's studies, the model architecture is fully convolutional with kernel sizes varying along the multiple layers of the model. To train our model we use turbulent velocity signals from grid turbulence at Modane wind tunnel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.16580v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/2632-2153/ad43b3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Machine Learning: Science and Technology, 2024, 5 (2), pp.025032.</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Granero-Belinchon (ODYSSEY, IMT Atlantique - MEE, Lab-STICC_OSE), Manuel Cabeza Gallucci (IMT Atlantique - MEE, UBA, IMT Atlantique)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
