<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.flu-dyn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn</link>
    <description>physics.flu-dyn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 02:32:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>High-speed micro-actuation in a supersonic dual-stream jet flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08403v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Supersonic shear layers experience instabilities that generate significant adverse effects; in complex configurations, these instabilities have global impacts as they foster compounding complications with other independent flow features. We consider the flow near the exit of a dual-stream rectangular nozzle, in which the supersonic core and sonic bypass streams mix downstream of a splitter plate trailing edge (SPTE) just above an adjacent deck representative of a wing surface. Active flow control is explored to alleviate the prominent tone associated with vortices shed at the SPTE; these vortices also initiate an unsteady shock system that affects the entire flow field through a shock-induced separation and the downstream evolution of plume shear layers. Resolvent analysis is performed on the baseline flow. The identified optimal location guides the placement of steady-blowing micro-jet actuators. A Navier--Stokes-based parametric study is carried out to consider various actuation angles and locations. Since the resolvent analysis fundamentally investigates the input-output dynamics of a system, it is also utilized to uncover actuation-induced changes in the forcing-response dynamics. Spectral analysis shows that the baseline flow fluctuating energy is concentrated in the shedding instability. Actuating at optimal angles based on location disperses this energy into various flow features; this affects the shedding itself, and the structure and unsteadiness of the shock system and thus the response of the deck and nozzle wall boundary layers and the plume. The resolvent analysis indicates, and Navier-Stokes solutions confirm, that favorable control is obtained by either indirectly or directly mitigating the baseline instability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08403v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Melissa Yeung, Datta V. Gaitonde, Yiyang Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving the measurement of air-water flow properties using remote distance sensing technology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08466v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, there has been an increasing research interest in the application of remote sensing technology to highly aerated flows, which is because this technology holds the ultimate promise to enable safe and accurate measurements of real-word air-water flows in natural and human made environments. Despite the increasing number of publications, some fundamental questions, such as ``what do we measure'' or ``what can we measure'', have not been answered conclusively. In this study, we hypothesize that laser distance sensors are able to measure the concentration of entrapped air, which we demonstrate using two seminal air-water flow types, namely a submerged hydraulic jump and flows down a stepped spillway. By converting our free-surface signals into time series of instantaneous air concentrations, we also show that a dual laser triangulation setup enables the extraction of basic air-water flow parameters of the upper flow region, comprising interface count rates, interfacial velocities, and turbulence levels, while we acknowledge that some sensor characteristics, such as beam diameters, can lead to measurement biases. Overall, this study represents a major advancement in the remote measurement of air-water flow properties. Future collective research effort is required to overcome remaining challenges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08466v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1061/JHEND8/HYENG-14074</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Hydraulic Engineering (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Kramer, Daniel B. Bung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A geometrical Green-Naghdi type system for dispersive-like waves in prismatic channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08625v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a one dimensional fully nonlinear model for surface waves in channels accounting for dispersive effects strictly related to multi-dimensional hydrostatic processes related to geometrical variations, namely to the bathymetry.
  Our model generalizes and improves those proposed by Chassagne et al. 2018 and 2019, as well as Quezada de Luna et al JFM 2021.
  The new model is obtained as an approximation of the hyperbolic shallow water equations under some hypotheses on the anisotropy of the propagation. For historical reasons the new model is referred to as geometrical Green-Naghdi type (gGN) system. The gGN system is fully nonlinear and weakly dispersive. It is endowed with an exact energy conservation law, and admits several types of exact travelling wave solutions. We analyze the propagation properties compare them to those of Chassagne et al. JFM 2019, including a characterization of undular bores via the analogy by Lemoine. Finally the system is recast in two useful forms appropriate for its numerical approximations, whose properties are discussed. Our results allow to further confirm the existence of these dispersive processes (highlighted in Chassagne et al JFM 2019) having a fully hydrostatic nature and modelled by the 2D hyperbolic nonlinear shallow water simulations. Finally, the numerical fully validate the new gGN model proposed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08625v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergey Gavrilyuk, Mario Ricchiuto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuation-driven dynamics of liquid nano-threads with external hydrodynamic perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08705v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Instability and rupture dynamics of a liquid nano-thread, subjected to external hydrodynamic perturbations, are captured by a stochastic lubrication equation (SLE) incorporating thermal fluctuations via Gaussian white noise. Linear instability analysis of the SLE is conducted to derive the spectra and distribution functions of thermal capillary waves influenced by external perturbations and thermal fluctuations. The SLE is also solved numerically using a second-order finite difference method with a correlated noise model. Both theoretical and numerical solutions, validated through molecular dynamics, indicate that surface tension forces due to specific external perturbations overcome the random effects of thermal fluctuations, determining both the thermal capillary waves and the evolution of perturbation growth. The results also show two distinct regimes: (i) the hydrodynamic regime, where external perturbations dominate, leading to uniform ruptures, and (ii) the thermal-fluctuation regime, where external perturbations are surpassed by thermal fluctuations, resulting in non-uniform ruptures. The transition between these regimes, modelled by a criterion developed from the linear instability theory, exhibits a strong dependence on the amplitudes and wavenumbers of the external perturbations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08705v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhao Zhang, Chengxi Zhao, Ting Si</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aerodynamic equilibria and flight stability of plates at intermediate Reynolds numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The passive flight of a thin wing or plate is an archetypal problem in flow-structure interactions at intermediate Reynolds numbers. This seemingly simple aerodynamic system displays an impressive variety of steady and unsteady motions that are familiar from fluttering leaves, tumbling seeds and gliding paper planes. Here, we explore the space of flight behaviors using a nonlinear dynamical model rooted in a quasi-steady description of the fluid forces. Efficient characterization is achieved by identification of the key dimensionless parameters, assessment of the steady equilibrium states, and linear analysis of their stability. The structure and organization of the stable and unstable flight equilibria proves to be complex, and seemingly related factors such as mass and buoyancy-corrected weight play distinct roles in determining the eventual flight patterns. The nonlinear model successfully reproduces previously documented unsteady states such as fluttering and tumbling while also predicting new types of motions, and the linear analysis accurately accounts for the stability of steady states such as gliding and diving. While the conditions for dynamic stability seem to lack tidy formulas that apply universally, we identify relations that hold in certain regimes and which offer mechanistic interpretations. The generality of the model and the richness of its solution space suggest implications for small-scale aerodynamics and related applications in biological and robotic flight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08864v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olivia Pomerenk, Leif Ristroph</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nanoscale Surfactant Transport: Bridging Molecular and Continuum Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08327v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Surfactant transport is central to a diverse range of natural phenomena, and for many practical applications in physics and engineering. Surprisingly, this process remains relatively poorly understood at the molecular scale. This study investigates the mechanism behind the transport of surfactant monolayers on flat and curved liquid vapor interfaces using nonequilibrium molecular dynamics simulations, which are compared with the continuum transport model. This approach not only provides fresh molecular level insight into surfactant dynamics, but also confirms the nanoscale mechanism of the lateral migration of surfactant molecules along a thin film that continuously deforms as surfactants spread. By connecting the continuum model where the long wave approximations prevail, to the molecular details where such approximations break down, we establish that the transport equation preserves substantial accuracy in capturing the underlying physics. Moreover, the relative importance of the different mechanisms of the transport process are identified. Consequently, we derive a novel, exact molecular equation for surfactant transport along a deforming surface. Finally, our findings demonstrate that the spreading of surfactants at the molecular scale adheres to expected scaling laws and aligns well with experimental observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08327v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Rizwanur Rahman, James P. Ewen, Li Shen, D. M. Heyes, Daniele Dini, E. R. Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tailoring the first law of thermodynamics for convective flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08649v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Equilibrium thermodynamics is grounded in the law of energy conservation, with a specific focus on how systems exchange energy with their environment during transitions between equilibrium states. These transitions are typically characterized by quantities such as heat absorption and the work needed to alter the system's volume. This study is inspired by the potential to develop an analogous, straightforward thermodynamic description for systems that are out of equilibrium. Here, we explore the global energy exchanges that occur during transitions between these nonequilibrium states. We study a system with heat flow and an external (gravity) field that exhibits macroscopic motion, such as Rayleigh-B\'enard convection. We show that the formula for system's energy exchange has the same form as in equilibrium. It opens the possibility of describing out-of-equilibrium systems using a few simple laws similar to equilibrium thermodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08649v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karol Makuch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying optimal location for control of thermoacoustic instability through statistical analysis of saddle point trajectories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.14261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.14261v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a framework of Lagrangian Coherent Structures (LCS) to enable passive open-loop control of tonal sound generated during thermoacoustic instability. Experiments were performed in a laboratory-scale bluff-body stabilized turbulent combustor in the state of thermoacoustic instability. We use dynamic mode decomposition (DMD) on the flow-field to identify dynamical regions where the acoustic frequency is dominant. We find that the separating shear layer from the backward-facing step of the combustor envelops a cylindrical vortex in the outer recirculation zone (ORZ), which eventually impinging on the top wall of the combustor during thermoacoustic instability. We track the saddle points in this shear layer emerging from the backward facing step over several acoustic cycles. A passive control strategy is then developed by injecting a steady stream of secondary air targeting the identified optimal location where the saddle points spend a majority of their time in a statistical sense.
  After implementing the control action, the resultant flow-field is also analysed using LCS to understand the key differences in flow dynamics. We find that the shear layer emerging from the dump plane is deflected in a direction almost parallel to the axis of the combustor after the control action. This deflection in turn prevents the shear layer from enveloping the vortex and impinging on the combustor walls, resulting in a drastic reduction in the amplitude of the sound produced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.14261v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. P. Premchand, Abin Krishnan, Manikandan Raghunathan, Midhun Raghunath, Reeja K. V., R. I. Sujith, Vineeth Nair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Developing the next generation of dual-tip phase-detection probes for air-water flow experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06009v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Self-aeration is a fascinating phenomenon that commonly occurs in high Froude-number flows in natural or human made environments. The most common air-water flow measurement instrument to characterize such flows is the intrusive dual-tip phase-detection needle probe, which identifies phase changes around the needle tips due to a change of resistivity (phase-detection conductivity probe) or light refraction (phase-detection fiber optical probe). Phase-detection conductivity probes are typically custom made for research purposes, with current design dating back to the 1980ies. In the present study, the next generation of dual-tip conductivity probes is developed and validated against a state-of-the-art system. The novel probe design comprises two main features, including (1) a printed circuit board of the sensor's electrodes and (2) a detachable sensor head. These features offer many advantages over the classical needle-type design. For example, the circuit boards can be manufactured with high precision and the sensor head can be easily replaced in case of damage or deterioration. As such, it is anticipated that this relatively cheap and robust design will enable a better repeatability of air-water flow experiments, combined with an enhanced accessibility for the air-water flow research community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06009v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Kramer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
