<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.flu-dyn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn</link>
    <description>physics.flu-dyn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 01:49:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Computational Efficiency in DSMC Simulations of Vacuum Gas Dynamics with a Fixed Number of Particles per Cell</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01589v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The present study addresses the challenge of enhancing computational efficiency without compromising accuracy in numerical simulations of vacuum gas dynamics using the direct simulation Monte Carlo (DSMC) method. A technique termed "fixed particle per cell (FPPC)" was employed, which enforces a fixed number of simulator particles across all computational cells. The proposed technique eliminates the need for real-time adjustment of particle weights during simulation, reducing calculation time. Using the SPARTA solver, simulations of rarefied gas flow in a micromixer and rarefied supersonic airflow around a cylinder were conducted to validate the proposed technique. Results demonstrate that applying the FPPC technique effectively reduces computational costs while yielding results comparable to conventional DSMC implementations. Additionally, the application of local grid refinement coupled with the FPPC technique was investigated. The results show that integrating local grid refinement with the FPPC technique enables accurate prediction of flow behaviour in regions with significant gradients. These findings highlight the efficacy of the proposed technique in improving the accuracy and efficiency of numerical simulations of complex vacuum gas dynamics at a reduced computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01589v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1402-4896/ad5a46</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Moslem Sabouri, Ramin Zakeri, Amin Ebrahimi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical method for the magnetic vector potential in incompressible magnetohydrodynamic flows and the conservation properties of magnetic helicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01605v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Analyzing magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) flows requires accurate predictions of the Lorentz force and energy conversion. Total energy, cross-helicity, and magnetic helicity can be used to investigate energy conservation properties in inviscid MHD flows. However, the conservation property of magnetic helicity has not been fully clarified using the magnetic vector potential equation. This study presents a numerical method to simultaneously relax magnetic vector and electric potentials for incompressible MHD flows using a conservative finite difference scheme that discretely conserves total energy. First, it was proven that the transport equations of total energy, cross-helicity, and magnetic helicity can be discretely derived from the equations of momentum, magnetic flux density, and magnetic vector potential, thereby elucidating the conservation properties of these quantities. Subsequently, five models for steady and unsteady problems were analyzed to verify the accuracy and convergence of the proposed numerical method. Additionally, the computational approach involving the magnetic vector and electric potentials was validated. A comparison of the calculated results with exact solutions in the analysis of one- and two-dimensional flow models and Hartmann flow further validated the numerical method. Unsteady analyses of two- and three-dimensional decaying vortices were performed. The ideal periodic inviscid MHD flow exhibited good conservation properties for total energy and cross-helicity. Magnetic helicity was discretely preserved even in three-dimensional flow. Furthermore, in viscous flow, the attenuation trends of total energy, cross-helicity, and magnetic helicity aligned with the exact solution. The numerical method accurately captured the decay trends of energy. Thus, the proposed method can facilitate the investigation of energy conservation and conversion in compressible MHD flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01605v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hideki Yanaoka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of diffusion flames under shear flow: Taylor dispersion and the formation of flame streets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01610v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Diffusion flame streets, observed in non-premixed micro-combustion devices, align parallel to a shear flow. They are observed to occur in mixtures with high Lewis number ($Le$) fuels, provided that the flow Reynolds number, or the Peclet number $Pe$, exceeds a critical value. The underlying mechanisms behind these observations have not yet been fully understood. In the present paper, we identify the coupling between diffusive-thermal instabilities and Taylor dispersion as a mechanism which is able to explain the experimental observations above. The explanation is largely based on the fact that Taylor dispersion enhances all diffusion processes in the flow direction, leading effectively to anisotropic diffusion with an effective (flow-dependent) Lewis number in the flow direction which is proportional to $1/Le$ for $Pe\gg 1$. Validation of the identified mechanism is demonstrated within a simple model by investigating the stability of a planar diffusion flame established parallel to a plane Poiseuille flow in a narrow channel. A linear stability analysis, leading to an eigenvalue problem solved numerically, shows that cellular (or finite wavelength) instabilities emerge for high Lewis number fuels when the Peclet number exceeds a critical value. Furthermore, for Peclet numbers below this critical value, longwave instabilities with or without time oscillations are obtained. Stability regime diagrams are presented for illustrative cases in a $Le$-$Pe$ plane where various instability domains are identified. Finally, the linear analysis is supported and complemented by time dependent numerical simulations, describing the evolution of unstable diffusion flames. The simulations demonstrate the existence of stable cellular structures and show that the longwave instabilities are conducive to flame extinction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01610v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.combustflame.2023.113003</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Combust. Flame (2023) 257, 113003</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Prabakaran Rajamanickam, Aiden Kelly, Joel Daou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NeurIPS 2024 ML4CFD Competition: Harnessing Machine Learning for Computational Fluid Dynamics in Airfoil Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The integration of machine learning (ML) techniques for addressing intricate physics problems is increasingly recognized as a promising avenue for expediting simulations. However, assessing ML-derived physical models poses a significant challenge for their adoption within industrial contexts. This competition is designed to promote the development of innovative ML approaches for tackling physical challenges, leveraging our recently introduced unified evaluation framework known as Learning Industrial Physical Simulations (LIPS). Building upon the preliminary edition held from November 2023 to March 2024, this iteration centers on a task fundamental to a well-established physical application: airfoil design simulation, utilizing our proposed AirfRANS dataset. The competition evaluates solutions based on various criteria encompassing ML accuracy, computational efficiency, Out-Of-Distribution performance, and adherence to physical principles. Notably, this competition represents a pioneering effort in exploring ML-driven surrogate methods aimed at optimizing the trade-off between computational efficiency and accuracy in physical simulations. Hosted on the Codabench platform, the competition offers online training and evaluation for all participating solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01641v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mouadh Yagoubi, David Danan, Milad Leyli-abadi, Jean-Patrick Brunet, Jocelyn Ahmed Mazari, Florent Bonnet, maroua gmati, Asma Farjallah, Paola Cinnella, Patrick Gallinari, Marc Schoenauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-field modeling of dendritic growth with gas bubbles in the solidification of binary alloys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01651v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, a phase-field model is developed for the dendritic growth with gas bubbles in the solidification of binary alloys. In this model, a total free energy for the complex gas-liquid-dendrite system is proposed through considering the interactions of gas bubbles, liquid melt and solid dendrites, and it can reduce to the energy for gas-liquid flows in the region far from the solid phase, while degenerate to the energy for thermosolutal dendritic growth when the gas bubble disappears. The governing equations are usually obtained by minimizing the total free energy, but here some modifications are made to improve the capacity of the conservative phase-field equation for gas bubbles and convection-diffusion equation for solute transfer. Additionally, through the asymptotic analysis of the thin-interface limit, the present general phase-field model for alloy solidification can match the corresponding free boundary problem, and it is identical to the commonly used models under a specific choice of model parameters. Furthermore, to describe the fluid flow, the incompressible Navier-Stokes equations are adopted in the entire domain including gas, liquid, and solid regions, where the fluid-structure interaction is considered by a simple diffuse-interface method. To test the present phase-field model, the lattice Boltzmann method is used to study several problems of gas-liquid flows, dendritic growth as well as the solidification in presence of gas bubbles, and a good performance of the present model for such complex problems is observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01651v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengjie Zhan, Zhenhua Chai, Dongke Sun, Baochang Shi, Shaoning Geng, Ping Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Triad Interactions and Evolving Turbulence -- Part 2: Implications for Practical Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01652v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate how momentum and kinetic energy is transferred between Fourier components (the so-called triad interactions) in measured turbulent flow fields with finite spatial and temporal resolution. We consider the effect of finite, digitally sampled velocity records on the triad interactions and find that Fourier components may interact within a broadened frequency window (finite overlap widths), as compared to the usual integrals over infinite ranges where Fourier components interact by overlapping Dirac delta functions. We also see how the finite domain (temporal and/or spatial) of velocity records has a significant effect on the efficiency of the triad interactions and thereby on the shape and development of measured velocity power spectra. These finite spatial/temporal domains thus influence the measured spatial and temporal development of turbulence, the possibility for non-local interactions and hence also non-equilibrium turbulence, e.g. fractal grid generated turbulence. Finally, we quote results from other companion papers that report results from laboratory and numerical experiments of the time development of velocity power spectra in a turbulent jet flow into which a single or a couple of Fourier modes are injected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01652v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Preben Buchhave, Clara Velte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A thermodynamically consistent phase-field lattice Boltzmann method for two-phase electrohydrodynamic flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01654v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we aim to develop a phase-field based lattice Boltzmann (LB) method for simulating two-phase electrohydrodynamics (EHD) flows, which allows for different properties (densities, viscosities, conductivity and permittivity) of each phase while maintaining thermodynamic consistency. To this end, we first present a theoretical analysis on the two-phase EHD flows by using the Onsager's variational principle, which is an extension of Rayleigh's principle of least energy dissipation and, naturally, guarantees thermodynamic consistency. It shows that the governing equations of the model include the hydrodynamic equations, Cahn-Hilliard equation coupled with additional electrical effect, and the full Poisson-Nernst-Planck electrokinetic equations. After that, a coupled lattice Boltzmann (LB) scheme is constructed for simulating two-phase EHD flows. In particular, in order to handle two-phase EHD flows with a relatively larger electric permittivity ratio, we also introduce a delicately designed discrete forcing term into the LB equation for electrostatic field. Moreover, some numerical examples including two-phase EHD flows in planar layers and charge diffusion of a Gaussian bell are simulated with the developed LB method. It is shown that our numerical scheme shares a second-order convergence rate in space in predicting electric potential and charge density. Finally, we used the current model to simulate the deformation of a droplet under an electric field and the dynamics of droplet detachment in reversed electrowetting. Our numerical results align well with the theoretic solutions, and the available experimental/numerical data, demonstrating that the proposed method is feasible for simulating two-phase EHD flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01654v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fang Xiong, Lei Wang, Jiangxu Huang, Kang Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unification theory of instabilities of visco-diffusive swirling flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01706v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A universal theoretical model of instabilities in swirling flows occurring in nature or industrial processes is developed. This model encompasses various open and confined flows including spiral Couette flow, spiral Poiseuille flow, and baroclinic Couette flow, which results from the combination of differential rotation and baroclinic convection due to radial heating and natural gravity. Utilizing short-wavelength local analysis, the model generalizes previous results from numerical simulations and linear stability analysis of specific flows. A general criterion for instability is derived, incorporating viscous dissipation and thermal diffusion, thereby extending and uniting existing criteria (Rayleigh for centrifugally-driven flows, L\"udwieg-Eckhoff-Leibovich-Stewartson for isothermal spiraling flows, and Goldreich-Schubert-Fricke for non-isothermal azimuthal flows).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01706v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleg N. Kirillov, Innocent Mutabazi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lift generation on a sphere through asymmetric roughness using active surface morphing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01748v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates a novel phenomenon of lift generation around a sphere by pneumatically manipulating its surface topology with an asymmetric roughness distribution. A comprehensive series of systematic experiments were conducted for Reynolds numbers ($Re = U_{\infty} d/\nu$, where $U_{\infty}$ is the fluid velocity, $d$ is the sphere diameter, and $\nu$ is the fluid kinematic viscosity) ranging from $6\times10^4$ to $1.3\times10^5$, and dimple depth ratios ($k/d$, where $k$ is the dimple depth) from $0$ to $1\times10^{-2}$ using a smart morphable sphere with one smooth and one dimpled side. The findings show that an asymmetrically rough sphere can generate lift forces up to 80\% of the drag, comparable to those produced by the Magnus Effect. The dimple depth ratio affects both the $Re$ at which lift generation begins and the maximum lift coefficient ($C_L$) achievable. The optimal $k/d$ for maximum lift varies with $Re$: deeper dimples are needed at low $Re$, while shallower dimples are more effective at high $Re$. For a fixed $Re$, increasing $k/d$ monotonically increases lift until a critical $k/d$ is reached, beyond which lift decreases. Particle Image Velocimetry (PIV) revealed that dimples delay flow separation on the rough side while the smooth side remains unchanged, resulting in asymmetric boundary layer separation, leading to wake deflection and lift generation. Beyond the critical $k/d$, the flow separation location moved upstream, increasing the size of the rear wake, reducing wake deflection, and thus decreasing lift. Overall, this study establishes the foundation for wake control over bluff bodies and paves the way for real-time manoeuvring applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01748v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo Vilumbrales-Garcia, Putu Brahmanda Sudarsana, Anchal Sareen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mass crystals and cage effect in vorticity crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02001v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the motion of tiny heavy inertial particles advected by a two dimensional inviscid fluid flow composed of $N$ identical point vortices regularly placed on a ring, and forming a crystal. In the limit of weak particle inertia, we show asymptotically that, in the reference frame of the crystal, inertial particles have $N$ asymptotically stable equilibrium positions located outside the crystal. In addition to these "satellite" attracting points, we observe that for $N \ge 3$ the center of the ring is a stable equilibrium position for inertial particles. This creates a kind of cage effect, where inclusions slowly drift towards the center under the effect of the surrounding vortices. This cage effect is observed to persist even at large Stokes numbers, in contrast with the satellite attracting points that vanish when the Stokes number is above some critical value.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02001v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-R\'egis Angilella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetics of Rayleigh-Taylor instability in van der Waals fluid: the influence of compressibility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02139v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Early studies on Rayleigh-Taylor instability (RTI) primarily relied on the Navier-Stokes (NS) model. As research progresses, it becomes increasingly evident that the kinetic information that the NS model failed to capture is of great value for identifying and even controlling the RTI process; simultaneously, the lack of analysis techniques for complex physical fields results in a significant waste of data information. In addition, early RTI studies mainly focused on the incompressible case and the weakly compressible case. In the case of strong compressibility, the density of the fluid from the upper layer (originally heavy fluid) may become smaller than that of the surrounding (originally light) fluid, thus invalidating the early method of distinguishing light and heavy fluids based on density. In this paper, tracer particles are incorporated into a single-fluid discrete Boltzmann method (DBM) model that considers the van der Waals potential. By using tracer particles to label the matter-particle sources, a careful study of the matter-mixing and energy-mixing processes of the RTI evolution is realized in the single-fluid framework. The effects of compressibility on the evolution of RTI are examined mainly through the analysis of bubble and spike velocities, the ratio of area occupied by heavy fluid, and various entropy generation rates of the system. It is demonstrated that: (1) compressibility has a suppressive effect on the spike velocity, and this suppressive impact diminishes as the Atwood number ($At$) increases. The influence of compressibility on bubble velocity shows a staged behavior with increasing $At$. (2) The impact of compressibility on the entropy production rate associated with the heat flow (${{\dot{S}}_{NOEF}}$) is related to the stages of RTI evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02139v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie Chen, Aiguo Xu, Yudong Zhang, Dawei Chen, Zhihua Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How turbulence increases the bubble-particle collision rate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02234v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the effect of turbulence on collisions between a finite-size bubble and small inertial particles based on interface-resolved simulations. Our results show that the interaction with the flow field around the bubble remains the dominant effect. Nonlinear dependencies in this process can enhance the turbulent collision rate by up to 100\% compared to quiescent flow. Fluctuations in the bubble slip velocity during the interaction with the particle additionally increase the collision rate. We present a frozen-turbulence model that captures the relevant effects providing a physically consistent framework to model collisions of small inertial particles with finite-sized objects in turbulence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02234v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linfeng Jiang, Dominik Krug</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hypersonic Boundary Layer Transition and Heat Loading</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02311v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hypersonic boundary layer transition using high-order methods for direct numerical simulations (DNS) is largely unexplored, although a few references exist in the literature. Experimental data in the hypersonic regime are scarce, while almost all existing hypersonic codes have low-order accuracy, which could lead to erroneous results in long-time integration and at high Reynolds numbers. Here, we focus on the transition from laminar to turbulent flow, where the Nusselt number may be five times or higher than the Nusselt number in the turbulent regime. The hypersonic flow regime must be modeled accurately using realistic chemistry to predict heat flux on the surface correctly. In this study, we simulate hypersonic boundary layer transition on a flat plate to compute the thermal and shear stresses on the wall. The domain is initialized with a laminar Blasius solution of compressible boundary layer equations. The transition to turbulence is induced using suction and blowing from a thin strip on the wall. Sponge regions are defined at the inflow and outflow boundaries to eliminate the solution contamination due to the reflections of the boundary conditions. In the spanwise direction, periodic boundary conditions are imposed. The numerical method applied here is a sixth-order compact finite difference in the interior of the domain coupled with a fourth-order Runge-Kutta time-stepping scheme for a structured Cartesian grid using staggered variables. The base finite difference code can perform simulations of non-equilibrium hypersonic flows. The numerical scheme is stabilized using the approximate deconvolution model (ADM) and artificial diffusion coefficients. We investigated the effect of non-equilibrium chemistry on the non-linear instability growth with hypersonic boundary layers. We also quantify thermal loads during the boundary layer laminar to turbulent transition for Mach number 10.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02311v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmad Peyvan, Luis Bravo, Anindya Ghoshal, Olaf Marxen, George Karniadakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermoelectric magnetohydrodynamic flow in a liquid metal-infused trench</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02470v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive a mathematical model for steady, unidirectional, thermoelectric magnetohydrodynamic (TEMHD) flow of liquid lithium along a solid metal trench, subject to an imposed heat flux. We use a finite-element method implemented in COMSOL Multiphysics to solve the problem numerically, demonstrating how the fluid velocity, induced magnetic field and temperature change depending on the key physical and geometrical parameters. The observed flow structures are elucidated by using the method of matched asymptotic expansions to obtain approximate solutions in the limit where the Hartmann number is large and the trench walls are thin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02470v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliver George Bond, Peter Denis Howell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tayler-Spruit dynamo in stably stratified rotating fluids: Application to proto-magnetars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01775</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01775v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The formation of highly magnetized young neutron stars, called magnetars, is still a strongly debated question. A promising scenario invokes the amplification of the magnetic field by the Tayler-Spruit dynamo in a proto-neutron star (PNS) spun up by fallback. Barr\`ere et al. 2023 supports this scenario by demonstrating that this dynamo can generate magnetar-like magnetic fields in stably stratified Boussinesq models of a PNS interior. To further investigate the Tayler-Spruit dynamo, we perform 3D-MHD numerical simulations with the MagIC code varying the ratio between the Brunt-V\"ais\"al\"a frequency and the rotation rate. We first demonstrate that a self-sustained dynamo process can be maintained for a Brunt-V\"ais\"al\"a frequency about 4 times higher than the angular rotation frequency. The generated magnetic fields and angular momentum transport follow the analytical scaling laws of Fuller et al. 2019, which confirms our previous results. We also report for the first time the existence of an intermittent Tayler-Spruit dynamo. For a typical PNS Brunt-V\"ais\"al\"a frequency of $10^{3}\,{\rm s}^{-1}$, the axisymmetric toroidal and dipolar magnetic fields range between $1.2\times 10^{15}-2\times 10^{16}\,{\rm G}$ and $1.4\times 10^{13}-3\times 10^{15}\,{\rm G}$, for rotation periods of $1-10\,{\rm ms}$. Thus, our results provide numerical evidence that our scenario can explain the formation of magnetars. As the Tayler-Spruit dynamo is often invoked for the angular momentum transport in stellar radiative zones, our results are also of particular importance in this field and we provide a calibration of the Fuller et al.'s prescription based on our simulations, with a dimensionless normalisation factor of the order of $10^{-2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01775v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Barr\`ere, J\'er\^ome Guilet, Rapha\"el Raynaud, Alexis Reboul-Salze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rotational dynamics of a disk in a thin film of weakly nematic fluid subject to linear friction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02267v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dynamics at low Reynolds numbers experiences recent revival in the fields of biophysics and active matter. While in bulk isotropic fluids it is exhaustively studied, this is less so in anisotropic fluids and in confined situations. Here, we combine the latter two by studying the rotation of a disk-like inclusion in a uniaxially anisotropy, globally oriented, incompressible two-dimensional fluid film. In terms of a perturbative expansion in parameters that quantify anisotropies in viscosity and in additional linear friction with a supporting substrate or other type of confinement, we derive analytical expressions for the resulting hydrodynamic flow and pressure fields as well as for the resistance and mobility coefficients of the rotating disk. It turns out that, in contrast to translational motion, the solutions remain well-behaved also in the absence of the additional linear friction. Comparison with results from finite-element simulations show very good agreement with those from our analytical calculations. Besides applications to describe technological systems, for instance, in the area of microfluidics and thin cells of aligned nematic liquid crystals, our solutions are important for quantitative theoretical approaches to fluid membranes and thin films in general featuring a preferred direction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02267v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdallah Daddi-Moussa-Ider, Elsen Tjhung, Marc Pradas, Thomas Richter, Andreas M. Menzel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Boussinesq stability analysis of natural-convection gaseous flow on inclined hot plates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.06571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.06571v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The buoyancy-driven boundary-layer flow that develops over a semi-infinite inclined hot plate is known to become unstable at a finite distance from the leading edge, characterized by a critical value of the Grashof number Gr based on the local boundary-layer thickness. The nature of the resulting instability depends on the inclination angle $\phi$, measured from the vertical direction. For values of $\phi$ below a critical value $\phi_c$ the instability is characterized by the appearance of spanwise traveling waves, whereas for $\phi&gt;\phi_c$ the bifurcated flow displays G\"ortler-like streamwise vortices. The Boussinesq approximation, employed in previous linear stability analyses, ceases to be valid for gaseous flow when the wall-to-ambient temperature ratio $\Theta_w$ is not close to unity. The corresponding non-Boussinesq analysis is presented here, accounting also for the variation with temperature of the different transport properties. A temporal stability analysis including nonparallel effects of the base flow is used to determine curves of neutral stability, which are then employed to delineate the dependences of the critical Grashof number and of its associated wave length on the inclination angle $\phi$ and on the temperature ratio $\Theta_w$ for the two instability modes, giving quantitative information of interest for configurations with $\Theta_w-1\sim 1$. The analysis provides in particular the predicted dependence of the crossover inclination angle $\phi_c$ on $\Theta_w$, indicating that for gaseous flow with $\Theta_w-1\sim 1$ spanwise traveling waves are predominant over a range of inclination angles $0 \le \phi \le \phi_c$ that is significantly wider than that predicted in the Boussinesq approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.06571v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ijheatmasstransfer.2017.02.010</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Int. J. Heat Mass Transf. (2017) 109, 949-957</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Prabakaran Rajamanickam, Wilfried Coenen, Antonio L. S\'anchez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of thermal expansion on Taylor dispersion-controlled diffusion flames</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.00877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.00877v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A theoretical analysis is developed to investigate the effects of gas expansion due to heat release on unsteady diffusion flames evolving in a pipe flow in which the mixing of reactants is controlled by Taylor's dispersion processes thereby extending a previously developed theory based on the thermo-diffusive model. It is first shown that at times larger than radial diffusion times, the pressure gradient induced by the gas expansion is, in the first approximation, small in comparison with the prevailing pressure gradient driving the flow, indicating that corrections to the background velocity profile are small. The corrections to the velocity components along with the leading-order mixing variables such as the concentrations, temperature and density are solved for a Burke-Schumann flame. Due to the dependence of the effective Taylor diffusion coefficients on the gas density, quantitative and sometimes qualitative departures in predictions from the thermo-diffusive model are observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.00877v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1080/13647830.2021.1985618</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Combust. Theory Model. 26 (2022) 50-66</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Prabakaran Rajamanickam, Adam D. Weiss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transition to turbulence via moving fronts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.08829v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Directed percolation (DP), a universality class of continuous phase transitions, has recently been established as a possible route to turbulence in subcritical wall-bounded flows. In canonical straight pipe or planar flows, the transition occurs via discrete large-scale turbulent structures, known as puffs in pipe flow or bands in planar flows, which either self-replicate or laminarize. However, these processes might not be universal to all subcritical shear flows. Here, we design a numerical experiment that eliminates discrete structures in plane Couette flow and show that it follows a different, simpler transition scenario: turbulence proliferates via expanding fronts and decays via spontaneous creation of laminar zones. We map this phase transition onto a stochastic one-variable system. The level of turbulent fluctuations dictates whether moving-front transition is discontinuous, or continuous and within the DP universality class, with profound implications for other hydrodynamic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.08829v3</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.264002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 264002 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S\'ebastien Gom\'e, Ali\'enor Rivi\`ere, Laurette S. Tuckerman, Dwight Barkley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fourier neural operator for large eddy simulation of compressible Rayleigh-Taylor turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05834v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Fourier neural operator (FNO) framework is applied to the large eddy simulation (LES) of three-dimensional compressible Rayleigh-Taylor (RT) turbulence with miscible fluids at Atwood number $A_t=0.5$, stratification parameter $Sr=1.0$, and Reynolds numbers $Re=10000$ and 30000. The FNO model is first used for predicting three-dimensional compressible turbulence. The different magnitudes of physical fields are normalized using root mean square values for an easier training of FNO models. In the \emph{a posteriori} tests, the FNO model outperforms the velocity gradient model (VGM), the dynamic Smagorinsky model (DSM), and implicit large eddy simulation (ILES) in predicting various statistical quantities and instantaneous structures, and is particularly superior to traditional LES methods in predicting temperature fields and velocity divergence. Moreover, the computational efficiency of the FNO model is much higher than that of traditional LES methods. FNO models trained with short-time, low Reynolds number data exhibit a good generalization performance on longer-time predictions and higher Reynolds numbers in the \emph{a posteriori} tests.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05834v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tengfei Luo (Leon), Zhijie Li (Leon), Zelong Yuan (Leon), Wenhui Peng (Leon), Tianyuan Liu (Leon),  Liangzhu (Leon),  Wang, Jianchun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling and simulations of high-density two-phase flows using projection-based Cahn-Hilliard Navier-Stokes equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17933v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurately modeling the dynamics of high-density ratio ($\mathcal{O}(10^5)$) two-phase flows is important for many applications in material science and manufacturing. In this work, we consider numerical simulations of molten metal undergoing microgravity oscillations. Accurate simulation of the oscillation dynamics allows us to characterize the interplay between the two fluids' surface tension and density ratio, which is an important consideration for terrestrial manufacturing applications. We present a projection-based computational framework for solving a thermodynamically-consistent Cahn-Hilliard Navier-Stokes equations for two-phase flows under these large density ratios. A modified version of the pressure-decoupled solver based on the Helmholtz-Hodge decomposition presented in Khanwale et al. [$\textit{A projection-based, semi-implicit time-stepping approach for the Cahn-Hilliard Navier-Stokes equations on adaptive octree meshes.}$, Journal of Computational Physics 475 (2023): 111874] is used. We present a comprehensive convergence study to investigate the effect of mesh resolution, time-step, and interfacial thickness on droplet-shape oscillations. We deploy our framework to predict the oscillation behavior of three physical systems exhibiting very large density ratios ($10^4-10^5:1$) that have previously never been performed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17933v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Rabeh, Makrand A. Khanwale, Jonghyun Lee, Baskar Ganapathysubramanian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2.5D turbulence in shear-thinning jets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01038v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The dimensional transition in turbulent jets of a shear-thinning fluid is studied via direct numerical simulations. Our findings reveal that under vertical confinement, the flow exhibits a unique mixed-dimensional (or 2.5D) state, where large-scale two-dimensional and small-scale three-dimensional structures coexist. This transition from three-dimensional turbulence near the inlet to two-dimensional dynamics downstream is dictated by the level of confinement: weak confinement guarantees turbulence to remain three-dimensional, whereas strong confinement forces the transition to two-dimensions; the mixed-dimensional state is observed for moderate confinement and it emerges as soon as flow scales are larger than the vertical length. In this scenario, we observed that the mixed-dimensional state is an overall more energetic state and it shows a multi-cascade process, where the direct cascade of energy at small scales and the direct cascade of enstrophy at large scales coexist. The results provide insights into the complex dynamics of confined turbulent flows, relevant in both natural and industrial settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01038v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Amor, Giovanni Soligo, Andrea Mazzino, Marco Edoardo Rosti</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
