<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.flu-dyn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn</link>
    <description>physics.flu-dyn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 04:00:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Turbulent heat transfer in open-channel flows with a thermally-conductive porous wall</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08962v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Results of direct numerical simulations (DNS) of porous-wall turbulent flows in open channels with conjugate heat transfer are reported in this work. For the conductive porous walls considered here, the change in heat transfer is not monotonic. The heat flux initially decreases when going from a conductive smooth wall to slightly porous walls. In this initial porous-wall turbulence regime, the near-wall flow remains smooth-wall like and the heat transfer is dominated by molecular diffusion. As such, a reduction of the more favorably conducting solid material diminishes the overall heat transfer performance. Beyond a certain level of permeability however, the near-wall flow transitions to the K-H-like regime marked by the presence of cross-stream rollers, and the heat flux undergoes an increasing trend until it eventually surpasses that of smooth-wall turbulence. Neglecting the thermal behavior of the solid material can therefore result in overestimation of any gains in heat transfer. Additionally, thermal performance is assessed in terms of the Reynolds analogy breakdown, which is the disparity between the fractional increases in the Stanton number, $St$, and the fractional increases in the skin-friction coefficient, $C_f$, relative to smooth-wall flow. Similar to rough walls, the breakdown is unfavorable for porous walls. The unfavorable breakdown in Reynolds analogy is due to growing dissimilarities between the transfer of momentum and heat in the vicinity of the porous wall as it becomes more permeable. Turbulent sweep and ejection type events contribute more significantly to momentum transfer across the permeable surface than they do to heat transfer. However, unlike for rough walls, a saturation limit for heat transfer is not observed for the porous walls considered here. How much of a maximum increase in heat transfer can be achieved is something that remains to be determined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08962v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seyed Morteza Habibi Khorasani, Geert Brethouwer, Shervin Bagheri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Based Machine Learning Closures and Wall Models for Hypersonic Transition-Continuum Boundary Layer Predictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08986v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modeling rarefied hypersonic flows remains a fundamental challenge due to the breakdown of classical continuum assumptions in the transition-continuum regime, where the Knudsen number ranges from approximately 0.1 to 10. Conventional Navier-Stokes-Fourier (NSF) models with empirical slip-wall boundary conditions fail to accurately predict nonequilibrium effects such as velocity slip, temperature jump, and shock structure deviations. We develop a physics-constrained machine learning framework that augments transport models and boundary conditions to extend the applicability of continuum solvers in nonequilibrium hypersonic regimes. We employ deep learning PDE models (DPMs) for the viscous stress and heat flux embedded in the governing PDEs and trained via adjoint-based optimization. We evaluate these for two-dimensional supersonic flat-plate flows across a range of Mach and Knudsen numbers. Additionally, we introduce a wall model based on a mixture of skewed Gaussian approximations of the particle velocity distribution function. This wall model replaces empirical slip conditions with physically informed, data-driven boundary conditions for the streamwise velocity and wall temperature. Our results show that a trace-free anisotropic viscosity model, paired with the skewed-Gaussian distribution function wall model, achieves significantly improved accuracy, particularly at high-Mach and high-Knudsen number regimes. Strategies such as parallel training across multiple Knudsen numbers and inclusion of high-Mach data during training are shown to enhance model generalization. Increasing model complexity yields diminishing returns for out-of-sample cases, underscoring the need to balance degrees of freedom and overfitting. This work establishes data-driven, physics-consistent strategies for improving hypersonic flow modeling for regimes in which conventional continuum approaches are invalid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08986v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashish S. Nair, Narendra Singh, Marco Panesi, Justin Sirignano, Jonathan F. MacArt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wavy optimal flows for heat transfer in channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We compute incompressible two-dimensional fluid flows that maximize the rate of heat transfer from the walls of a straight channel given a specified flow input power $Pe^{2}$, where $Pe$ is the P\'{e}clet number. We use the Broyden-Fletcher-Goldfarb-Shanno (BFGS) algorithm together with an adjoint method to compute gradients. The optimal flows are approximately unidirectional up to a critical $Pe \approx 2^{12}$. Above this value the flows assume wavy patterns characterized by finger-like protrusions emanating from both the top and bottom walls of the channel. The rate of heat transfer for these wavy flows is 3% to 30% greater than that of the previously identified unidirectional optima for $2^{13} \leq Pe \leq 2^{17}$. The wavy flows have a much smaller flux through the channel than the unidirectional flows, with regions of slow-moving fluid at nearly homogeneous temperature interspersed with serpentine regions of fast-moving fluid. Consequently, the area of the interface between hot and cold fluid is increased.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09027v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivani Prabala, Silas Alben</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluid Dynamical Pathways of Airborne Transmission while Waiting in a Line</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09065v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Waiting in a line (or a queue) is an important, often unavoidable social interaction that occurs frequently in public spaces. Despite its wide prevalence and rich parametric variability, few studies have addressed the risks of airborne transmission while waiting in a line. Here we use a combination of scaled down laboratory experiments and direct numerical simulations (DNS) to assess the flow patterns and infection risks in a simplified waiting line setting. We observed the presence of fluid dynamical countercurrents, due to the competing effects of line kinematics and thermal gradients, which can either heighten or suppress the risks of transmission. Depending on the walking speed, an intermediate ambient temperature range can potentially heighten the infection risks by allowing the breath plume to linger in the air for extended durations; however, colder and warmer ambients both suppress the spread. The current guideline of increasing physical separation has limited impact on reducing transmission in the waiting line setting. The present work highlights the need for updated transmission mitigation guidelines that go beyond the simplicity of the six feet rule in social interactions where physical separation, duration of interaction, and periodicity of movements are factors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09065v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruixi Lou, Milo van Mooy, Gabriel A Tarditti, Rodolfo Ostilla Monico, Varghese Mathai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vorticity dynamics and drag for flows over a sphere and a prolate spheroid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09096v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The connection between the drag and vorticity dynamics for viscous flow over a bluff body is explored using the Josephson-Anderson (J-A) relation for classical fluids. The instantaneous rate of work on the fluid, associated with the drag force, is related to the vorticity flux across the streamlines of a background potential flow. The vorticity transport itself is examined by aid of the Huggins vorticity flux tensor. The analysis is performed for three flows: flow over a sphere at Reynolds numbers $Re=\{200,3700\}$ and flow over a prolate spheroid at $Re=3000$ and $20^{\circ}$ incidence. In these flows, the vorticity transport shifts the flow away and towards the ideal potential flow, with a net balance towards the former effect thus making an appreciably contribution to the drag. The J-A relation is first demonstrated for the flow over a sphere at $Re=200$. The drag is related to the viscous flux of azimuthal vorticity from the wall into the fluid and the advection of vorticity by the shear layer. In the wake, the azimuthal vorticity is advected towards the wake centerline and is annihilated by viscous effects, which contributes a reduction to drag. The analysis of the flow over a sphere at $Re=3700$ is reported for the impulsively started and stationary stages, with emphasis on the effects of unsteady separation and turbulent transport in the wake. The turbulent flux in the wake enhances the transport of mean azimuthal vorticity towards the wake centerline, and is the driver of the recovery of enthalpy downstream. The drag force for a prolate spheroid is mostly due to the transport of vorticity along the separated boundary layers. Primary and secondary separation contribute oppositely to the drag force, while the large-scale vortices only re-distribute vorticity. A mechanism for secondary separation is proposed based on the theory of vortex-induced separation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09096v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Du, Tamer A. Zaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Size Amplification of Jet Drops due to Insoluble Surfactants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09189v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the effect of insoluble surfactant on jet drop formation by bubble bursting. We demonstrate quantitative agreement on the jet velocity and drop size between laboratory experiments and numerical simulations by using the measured surface tension dependence on surfactant concentration as the equation of state for the simulations. We demonstrate that surfactants increase the drop size for bubbles without precursor capillary waves, which is opposite in trend to bubbles with precursor capillary waves, due to the effect of Marangoni stresses on the focusing of the collapsing cavity.
  *Jun Eshima and Tristan Aur\'egan contributed equally to this work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09189v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Eshima, Tristan Aur\'egan, Palas Kumar Farsoiya, St\'ephane Popinet, Howard A. Stone, Luc Deike</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WellPINN: Accurate Well Representation for Transient Fluid Pressure Diffusion in Subsurface Reservoirs with Physics-Informed Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09330v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate representation of wells is essential for reliable reservoir characterization and simulation of operational scenarios in subsurface flow models. Physics-informed neural networks (PINNs) have recently emerged as a promising method for reservoir modeling, offering seamless integration of monitoring data and governing physical equations. However, existing PINN-based studies face major challenges in capturing fluid pressure near wells, particularly during the early stage after injection begins. To address this, we propose WellPINN, a modeling workflow that combines the outputs of multiple sequentially trained PINN models to accurately represent wells. This workflow iteratively approximates the radius of the equivalent well to match the actual well dimensions by decomposing the domain into stepwise shrinking subdomains with a simultaneously reducing equivalent well radius. Our results demonstrate that sequential training of superimposing networks around the pumping well is the first workflow that focuses on accurate inference of fluid pressure from pumping rates throughout the entire injection period, significantly advancing the potential of PINNs for inverse modeling and operational scenario simulations. All data and code for this paper will be made openly available at https://github.com/linuswalter/WellPINN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09330v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linus Walter (Global Change Research Group, Department of Civil and Environmental Engineering), Qingkai Kong (Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, Livermore, USA), Sara Hanson-Hedgecock (Global Change Research Group), V\'ictor Vilarrasa (Global Change Research Group)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Informed Neural Networks for Estimating Convective Heat Transfer in Jet Impingement Cooling: A Comparison with Conjugate Heat Transfer Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09356v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Efficient cooling is vital for the performance and reliability of modern systems such as electronics, nuclear reactors, and industrial equipment. Jet impingement cooling is widely used for its high local heat transfer rates. Accurate estimation of convective heat transfer coefficient (CHTC) is essential for design, simulation, and control of thermal systems. However, estimating spatially varying CHTCs from limited and noisy temperature data poses a challenging inverse problem. This study presents a physics-informed neural network (PINN) framework to estimate both averaged and spatially varying CHTCs at the fluid-solid interface in a jet impingement setup at Reynolds number 5000. The model uses sparse and noisy temperature data from within the solid and embeds the transient heat conduction equation along with boundary and initial conditions into its loss function. This enables inference of unknown boundary parameters without explicit modeling of the fluid domain. Validation is performed using synthetic temperature data from high-fidelity conjugate heat transfer (CHT) simulations. The framework is tested under various additive Gaussian noise levels (up to 30 percent) and sampling rates 0.25 to 4.0 per second. For noise levels up to 10% and sampling rates of 0.5 per second or higher, estimated CHTCs match CHT-derived benchmarks with relative errors below 8 percent. Even under high-noise scenarios, the framework maintains predictive accuracy when time resolution is sufficient. These results highlight the method's robustness to noise and sparse data, offering a scalable alternative to traditional inverse methods, experimental measurements, or full CHT modeling for estimating boundary thermal parameters in real-world cooling applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09356v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arijit Hazra, Prahar Sarkar, Sourav Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computational Aerothermal Framework and Analysis of Stetson Mach 6 Blunt Cone</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09368v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurately predicting aerothermal behavior is paramount for the effective design of hypersonic vehicles, as aerodynamic heating plays a pivotal role in influencing performance metrics and structural integrity. This study introduces a computational aerothermal framework and analyzes a blunt cone subjected to Mach 6 conditions, drawing inspiration from Stetson foundational experimental work published in 1983. While the findings offer significant insights into the phenomena at play, the study highlights an urgent necessity for integrating chemical kinetics to comprehensively capture non-equilibrium effects, thereby enhancing the predictive accuracy of computational fluid dynamics (CFD) simulations. This research implements a one-way coupling method between CFD simulations and heat conduction analysis, facilitating a thorough investigation of surface heat transfer characteristics. The numerical results elucidate discrete roughness elements' impact on surface heating and fluid dynamics within high-speed airflow. Furthermore, the investigation underscores the critical importance of accounting for non-equilibrium thermochemical effects in aerothermal modeling to bolster the accuracy of high-enthalpy flow simulations. By refining predictive computational tools and deepening understanding of hypersonic aerothermal mechanisms, this research lays a robust groundwork for future experimental and computational endeavors, significantly contributing to advancing high-speed flight applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09368v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arturo Rodriguez, Piyush Kumar, Cesar Diaz-Caraveo, Richard O. Adansi, Luis F. Rodriguez, Vineeth Vijaya Kumar, Vinod Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TrajectoryFlowNet: Hybrid Lagrangian-Eulerian learning of flow field and trajectories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09621v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The process of flows carrying particles is highly complex, traditionally tackled by solving the Navier-Stokes equations. Although different numerical and experimental techniques have been developed, these approaches demand a deep understanding of the underlying physics and \textcolor{black}{are frequently associated with high computational costs}. Machine learning offers a novel alternative, learning predictive patterns directly from data, thus bypassing the need for explicit physical modeling. Nonetheless, pure data-driven methods can sometimes lack interpretability and physical consistency. By integrating physics principles into machine learning, this gap can be bridged and the above problems can be solved. In this context, we have proposed TrajectoryFlowNet for flow and particle tracking. Our approach combines the flexibility of data-driven learning with the rigorousness of physics-based constraints, aiming to achieve both accuracy and efficiency. The salient features of our model include its ability to handle complex flow patterns with moving boundaries, predict the trajectories of all particles in the domain, and ensure physical consistency throughout the predictions based only on sparse trajectories. To validate our method, we have conducted several numerical and experimental cases across a range of flow scenarios. These experiments demonstrate the model's effectiveness in capturing the intricate dynamics of particle-laden flows, advancing precise particle tracking and flow field inversion in various real-world problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09621v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingdi Wan, Hongping Wang, Bo Liu, Guowei He, Yang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A sharp and conservative method for modeling interfacial flows with insoluble surfactants in the framework of a geometric volume-of-fluid approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09680v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Insoluble surfactants adsorbed at liquid-liquid or gas-liquid interfaces alter interfacial tension, leading to variations in the normal stress jump and generating tangential Marangoni stresses that can dramatically affect the flow dynamics. We develop a three-dimensional, sharp and conservative numerical method for modeling insoluble surfactant-laden interfacial flows within a volume-of-fluid framework. This method contrasts with diffusive transport algorithms commonly employed in the Eulerian framework. The proposed method preserves the zero-thickness property of the interface, ensures accurate calculation of the surfactant concentration, and robustly handles complex topological changes. The interface evolution is captured using a geometrical volume-of-fluid method, with surfactant mass sharply stored at the reconstructed interface. The advection term in the surfactant transport equation is discretized implicitly in conjunction with the geometrical advection of the volume fraction of one of the fluids, thereby eliminating numerical inconsistencies arising from discrepancies between the actual and computed interface areas. Additionally, the diffusion term is discretized along the reconstructed interface, preventing artificial diffusion normal to the zero-thickness interface. Benchmark tests demonstrate that the proposed method achieves higher accuracy and faster convergence compared to existing diffusive approaches. Finally, we apply the method to investigate the interaction of a surfactant-laden rising bubble with a vertical wall, revealing a transition from near-wall bouncing to migration away from the wall as the surfactant concentration increases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09680v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Han Xue, Jacques Magnaudet, Jie Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak Detonations Revisited: Uncovering Its General Nature Using Autoignitive Reaction Wave Concept</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10022v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Weak detonations have remained experimentally elusive since their theoretical prediction, with previous realization attempts requiring either pathological detonations or Zeldovich spontaneous waves. Here, we demonstrate that stable weak detonations are naturally achieved through supersonic autoignitive reaction waves a recently proposed concept describing inherently stable reaction waves determined by inflow velocity conditions and autoignition characteristics. We establish the mathematical equivalence between autoignitive reaction waves and classical Rayleigh flow, proving that supersonic autoignitive reaction waves are indeed weak detonations. The underlying thermodynamic structure reveals Legendre conjugate variables linking normalized enthalpy and fuel consumption. Unlike previous approaches, our universal realization conditions require only that inlet velocity exceed the Chapman-Jouguet velocity and autoignition criteria be met applicable to any reactive system without specialized chemistry. This framework transforms weak detonations from theoretical curiosities to practically achievable phenomena, opening new possibilities for applications in supersonic combustion systems and astrophysical phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10022v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youhi Morii, Kaoru Maruta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On physical consistency of HLL-type Riemann solvers for ideal MHD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10420v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Approximate Riemann solvers are widely used for solving hyperbolic conservation laws, including those of magnetohydrodynamics (MHD). However, due to the nonlinearity and complexity of MHD, obtaining accurate and robust numerical solutions to MHD equations is non-trivial, and it may be challenging for an approximate MHD Riemann solver to preserve the positivity of scalar variables, particularly when the plasma beta is low. As we have identified that the inconsistency between the numerically calculated magnetic field and magnetic energy may be responsible for the loss of positivity of scalar variables, we propose a physical consistency condition and implement it in HLL-type MHD Riemann solvers, thus alleviating the erroneous magnetic field solutions breaking scalar positivity. In addition, (I) for the HLLC-type scheme, we have designed a revised two-state approximation, specifically reducing numerical error in magnetic field solutions, and (II) for the HLLD-type scheme, we replace the constant total pressure assumption by a three-state assumption for the intermediate thermal energy, which is more consistent with our other assumptions. The proposed schemes perform better in numerical examples with low plasma \b{eta}. Moreover, we explained the energy error introduced during time integration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10420v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Zhang, Andrea Lani, Stefaan Poedts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imprints of turbulence on heterogeneous deposition of adhesive particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.10480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.10480v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present direct numerical simulations (DNS) of particle deposition in a turbulent channel flow, incorporating a viscoelastic soft-sphere collision model with temperature-dependent van der Waals adhesion. Particle-wall contact is governed by an adhesion number that varies with temperature, enabling exploration of a wide range of deposition behaviors. Deposition is strongly heterogeneous, especially for inertial particles, where rolling and sliding enhance nonuniformity. Spanwise radial distribution functions reveal that deposited particles form streaks with characteristic spacing set by near-wall two-point velocity correlations. A clustering metric confirms that high-inertia, low-adhesion particles deposit in elongated, anisotropic patterns due to spanwise migration driven by velocity fluctuations. Finally, it is shown that this heterogeneity in deposition leads to localized wall wear rates exceeding ten times the mean, with the most severe wear associated with particles that are carried to the wall in clusters by sweep events.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.10480v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max P. Herzog, Jesse Capecelatro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Static and dynamic ordering of magnetic repelling particles under confinement: disks vs bars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08816v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explored experimentally the self-organization at rest and the compression dynamics of a two-dimensional array of magnetic repelling particles, using two particle geometries, namely, disks and rectangular bars. Despite the non-contact interaction, typical static features of granular materials are observed for both particle shapes: pile formation with an angle of repose and pressure saturation (Janssen-like effect), which can be explained by considering the magnetically-induced torques that generate friction between particles and confining walls. Particle shape effects are mainly observed during compression: while disks rearrange increasing the hexagonal ordering, bars augment their orientational ordering forming larger non-contact force chains; however, in both cases, the resistance to compression rises continuously, in contrast with the fluctuating compression dynamics (stick-slip motion or periodic oscillations) that characterizes granular systems with inter-particle contacts. The continuous response to compression, and the reduction of particle wear due to non-contact interactions, are desirable features in designing magnetic granular dampers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08816v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Aguilar-Gonz\'alez, L. F. Elizondo-Aguilera, Y. D. Sobral, F. Pacheco-V\'azquez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating Three-dimensional Turbulence with Physics-informed Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.08972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.08972v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Turbulent fluid flows are among the most computationally demanding problems in science, requiring enormous computational resources that become prohibitive at high flow speeds. Physics-informed neural networks (PINNs) represent a radically different approach that trains neural networks directly from physical equations rather than data, offering the potential for continuous, mesh-free solutions. Here we show that appropriately designed PINNs can successfully simulate fully turbulent flows in both two and three dimensions, directly learning solutions to the fundamental fluid equations without traditional computational grids or training data. Our approach combines several algorithmic innovations including adaptive network architectures, causal training, and advanced optimization methods to overcome the inherent challenges of learning chaotic dynamics. Through rigorous validation on challenging turbulence problems, we demonstrate that PINNs accurately reproduce key flow statistics including energy spectra, kinetic energy, enstrophy, and Reynolds stresses. Our results demonstrate that neural equation solvers can handle complex chaotic systems, opening new possibilities for continuous turbulence modeling that transcends traditional computational limitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.08972v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sifan Wang, Shyam Sankaran, Panos Stinis, Paris Perdikaris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of Shock-Capturing with Bound-Preserving Limiters for the Nonlinearly Stable Flux Reconstruction Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09131v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nonlinearly stable flux reconstruction (NSFR) combines the key properties of provable nonlinear stability with the increased time step from energy-stable flux reconstruction. The NSFR scheme has been successfully applied to unsteady compressible flows. Through the use of a bound-preserving limiter, positivity of thermodynamic quantities is preserved, and this enables the extension of NSFR to hyperbolic conservation laws. We extend the limiter of Zhang and Shu [1] to ensure robustness for the proposed scheme. The limiter is modified to consider the minimum density and pressure at the solution nodes when determining the value to scale the solution. The modifications are thoroughly tested with a suite of test cases. In addition to these modifications, this paper conducts a thorough investigation into the shock-capturing capabilities of the NSFR scheme and the advantages it presents over standard discontinuous Galerkin (DG) methods, where, on select variants of the flux reconstruction (FR) scheme, essentially oscillation-free solutions are demonstrated. Various parameters of the scheme are extensively tested and analyzed through several 1D and 2D compressible Euler tests that verify the high-order accuracy, entropy stability, time step advantage and shock-capturing capabilities of the NSFR scheme. These parameters include the two-point flux, quadrature nodes and the strength of the FR parameter. In addition to investigating the impact of the various two-point fluxes, this paper also presents numerical studies to determine the CFL condition required to maintain positivity for the two-point flux of choice. The investigation yields insightful results for all parameters, with the results pertaining to the type of FR scheme being of special interest. The tests showcase increased robustness, time step advantages and oscillation/overshoot mitigation when employing a stronger FR parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09131v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sai Shruthi Srinivasan, Siva Nadarajah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmark stress tests for flow past a cylinder at higher Reynolds numbers using EMAC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09274v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a test problem for Navier-Stokes solvers based on the flow around a cylinder at Reynolds numbers 500 and 1000, where the solution is observed to be periodic when the problem is sufficiently resolved. Computing the resulting flow is a challenge, even for exactly divergence-free discretization methods, when the scheme does not include sufficient numerical dissipation. We examine the performance of the energy, momentum and angular momentum conserving (EMAC) formulation of the Navier-Stokes equations. This incorporates more physical conservation into the finite element method even when the numerical solution is not exactly divergence-free. Consequently, it has a chance to outperform standard methods, especially for long-time simulations. We find that for lowest-order Taylor-Hood elements, EMAC outperforms the standard convective formulations. However, for higher-order elements, EMAC can become unstable on under-resolved meshes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09274v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henry von Wahl, Leo G. Rebholz, L. Ridgway Scott</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear projection-based model order reduction with machine learning regression for closure error modeling in the latent space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00634v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A significant advancement in nonlinear projection-based model order reduction (PMOR) is presented through a highly effective methodology. This methodology employs Gaussian process regression (GPR) and radial basis function (RBF) interpolation for closure error modeling in the latent space, offering notable gains in efficiency and expanding the scope of PMOR. Moving beyond the limitations of deep artificial neural networks (ANNs), previously used for this task, this approach provides crucial advantages in terms of interpretability and a reduced demand for extensive training data. The capabilities of GPR and RBFs are showcased in two demanding applications: a two-dimensional parametric inviscid Burgers problem, featuring propagating shocks across the entire computational domain, and a complex three-dimensional turbulent flow simulation around an Ahmed body. The results demonstrate that this innovative approach preserves accuracy and achieves substantial improvements in efficiency and interpretability when contrasted with traditional PMOR and ANN-based closure modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00634v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Ares de Parga, Radek Tezaur, Carlos G. Hern\'andez, Charbel Farhat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fokker-Planck approach to wave turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.08484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.08484v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Kolmogorov-Zakharov stationary states for weak wave turbulence involve solving a leading-order kinetic equation. Recent calculations of higher-order corrections to this kinetic equation using the Martin-Siggia-Rose path integral are reconsidered in terms of stationary states of a Fokker-Planck Hamiltonian. A non-perturbative relation closely related to the quantum mechanical Ehrenfest theorem is introduced and used to express the kinetic equation in terms of divergences of two-point expectation values in the limit of zero dissipation. Similar equations are associated to divergences in higher-order cumulants. It is additionally shown that the ordinary thermal equilibrium state is not actually a stationary state of the Fokker-Planck Hamiltonian, and a non-linear modification of dissipation is considered to remedy this.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.08484v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Schubring</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constructing Extreme Heatwave Storylines with Differentiable Climate Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.10660v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding the plausible upper bounds of extreme weather events is essential for risk assessment in a warming climate. Existing methods, based on large ensembles of physics-based models, are often computationally expensive or lack the fidelity needed to simulate rare, high-impact extremes. Here, we present a novel framework that leverages a differentiable hybrid climate model, NeuralGCM, to optimize initial conditions and generate physically consistent worst-case heatwave trajectories. Applied to the 2021 Pacific Northwest heatwave, our method produces heatwave intensity up to 3.7 $^\circ$C above the most extreme member of a 75-member ensemble. These trajectories feature intensified atmospheric blocking and amplified Rossby wave patterns-hallmarks of severe heat events. Our results demonstrate that differentiable climate models can efficiently explore the upper tails of event likelihoods, providing a powerful new approach for constructing targeted storylines of extreme weather under climate change.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.10660v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Whittaker, Alejandro Di Luca</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
