<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.flu-dyn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn</link>
    <description>physics.flu-dyn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Eddy population based model for the wall-pressure spectrum at high Reynolds number</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23098v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Wall-pressure fluctuations beneath turbulent boundary layers drive noise and structural fatigue through interactions between fluid and structural modes. Conventional predictive models for the spectrum--such as the widely accepted Goody model--fail to capture the energetic growth in the subconvective regime that occurs at high Reynolds number, while at the same time over-predicting the variance.
  To address these shortcomings, two semi-empirical models are proposed for the wall-pressure spectrum in canonical turbulent boundary layers, pipes and channels for friction Reynolds numbers $\delta^+$ ranging from 180 to 47 000.
  The models are based on consideration of two eddy populations that broadly represent the contributions to the wall pressure fluctuations from inner-scale motions and outer-scale motions.
  The first model expresses the premultiplied spectrum as the sum of two overlapping log-normal populations: an inner-scaled term that is $\delta^+$-invariant and an outer-scaled term whose amplitude broadens smoothly with $\delta^+$. Calibrated against large-eddy simulations, direct numerical simulations, and recent high-$\delta^+$ pipe data, it reproduces the convective ridge and the emergence of a sub-convective ridge at large $\delta^+$.
  The second model, developed around newly-available pipe data, uses theoretical arguments to prescribe the spectral shapes of the inner and outer populations. By embedding the $\delta^+$ dependence in smooth asymptotic functions, it yields a formulation that varies continuously with $\delta^+$.
  Both models capture the full spectrum and the logarithmic growth of its variance, laying the groundwork for more accurate engineering predictions of wall-pressure fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23098v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan M. O. Massey, Alexander J. Smits, Beverley J. McKeon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extensional rheology of dilute suspensions of spheres in polymeric liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23114v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The extensional rheology of dilute suspensions of spheres in viscoelastic or polymeric liquids is studied computationally. At low polymer concentration (c) and Deborah number (De), a wake of highly stretched polymers forms downstream of the particles due to larger local velocity gradients than the imposed flow, indicated by a positive deviation in local De. This increases the suspension's extensional viscosity with time and De for De less than 0.5. When De exceeds 0.5 (the coil-stretch transition), the fully stretched polymers from the far field collapse in regions with lower local velocity gradients around the particle's stagnation points, reducing suspension viscosity relative to the polymer-only liquid. The interaction between local flow and polymers intensifies with increasing c. Highly stretched polymers impede local flow, reducing local De, while it increases in regions with collapsed polymers. Initially, increasing c aligns local De and polymer stretch with far-field values, diminishing particle-polymer interaction effects. However, beyond a certain c, a new mechanism emerges. At low c, fluid three particle radii upstream exhibits increased local De, stretching polymers beyond their undisturbed state. As c increases, this deviation becomes negative, collapsing polymers and resulting in increasingly negative stress from particle-polymer interactions at large De and time. At high c, this negative interaction stress scales as c squared, surpassing the linear increase in polymer stress, making dilute sphere suspensions more effective at reducing the viscosity of viscoelastic liquids at larger De and c.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23114v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arjun Sharma, Donald L. Koch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From vortices to forces - a data-driven framework for unsteady lift generation in three-dimensional vortex-dominated flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23131v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Time-varying flow-induced forces on bodies immersed in fluid flows play a key role across a range of natural and engineered systems, from biological locomotion to propulsion and energy-harvesting devices. These transient forces often arise from complex, dynamic vortex interactions and can either enhance or degrade system performance. However, establishing a clear causal link between vortex structures and force transients remains challenging, especially in high-Reynolds number nominally three-dimensional flows. In this study, we investigate the unsteady lift generation on a rotor blade that is impulsively started with a span-based Reynolds number of 25,500. The lift history from this direct-numerical simulation reveals distinct early-time extrema associated with rapidly evolving flow structures, including the formation, evolution, and breakdown of leading-edge and tip vortices. To quantify the influence of these vortical structures on the lift transients, we apply the force partitioning method (FPM) that quantifies the surface pressure forces induced by vortex-associated effects. Two metrics - $Q$-strength and vortex proximity - are derived from FPM to provide a quantitative assessment of the influence of vortices on the lift force. This analysis confirms and extends qualitative insights from prior studies, and offers a simple-to-apply data-enabled framework for attributing unsteady forces to specific flow features, with potential applications in the design and control of systems where unsteady aerodynamic forces play a central role.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23131v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suryansh Prakhar, Jung-Hee Seo, Rajat Mittal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuating interfaces in barotropic beta-plane turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23493v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Zonal jets manifest themselves as bands with sharp interfaces in the vorticity configuration. We develop an algorithm to track these fluctuating vorticity interfaces and systematically investigate their characteristic spatio-temporal behavior. While the interfacial height fluctuations are typically sub-Gaussian, the corresponding $\textit{fluctuation speeds}$ exhibit wider, heavy-tailed distributions reflecting the influence of lateral dispersion induced by the zonal velocity profile along the interfacial contours. The temporal evolution of these fluctuations is further characterized through their power spectrum displaying scale invariance in the frequency domain. The sharp, dense, shock-like features present in the time series of the $\textit{height}$ field suggest a possible lacking of differentiability. We confirm this by calculating the moments of the time-increments of the interfacial height fluctuations. Finally, the fractal nature of these boundaries is investigated systematically through a multifractal approach, revealing the non-trivial, complex statistics of interfaces in such geophysical, turbulent flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23493v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sandip Sahoo, Samriddhi Sankar Ray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Viscosity variation in fluid flows across scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23532v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A wide range of natural and engineered fluid flows exhibit spatial or temporal viscosity variations, spanning scales from microbial locomotion to planetary mantle convection. These variations introduce qualitatively new physical mechanisms absent in constant-viscosity flows. This review surveys such phenomena across scales. In low Reynolds number (Stokes) flows, viscosity gradients couple translation and rotation, enabling novel particle responses to uniform forcing-- mechanisms that microorganisms may exploit. In shear flows, viscosity variation alters base flow profiles and breaks symmetries, modifying stability and transition dynamics. At high Reynolds numbers, stratification fundamentally changes the singular perturbation structure governing energy production, enhancing or suppressing canonical instabilities and introducing new ones. Viscosity variation also affects nonnormal growth and nonlinear interactions that drive transition to turbulence. While laminar and fully developed turbulence have been extensively studied, transitional processes remain poorly understood in variable-viscosity flows. In turbulent regimes, viscosity variation impacts jets, wall-bounded flows, and mixing layers. At geophysical scales, incorporating eddy viscosity stratification in climate models may improve predictions, while in Earth's mantle, viscosity contrasts drive large-scale convection and geological evolution. Particle-laden flows, common across contexts, can generate effective viscosity stratification through inhomogeneous loading. Throughout, we highlight cases where viscosity variation alters flow behavior qualitatively, and point to open questions. This review aims to guide graduate students and researchers toward tractable, cross-disciplinary problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23532v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arjun Sharma, Ritabrata Thakur, Sharath Jose, Rama Govindarajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wake Stabilization and Force Modulation via Surface Dimples on an Airfoil at Low-Reynolds-Numbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23564v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the effect of surface dimples on the unsteady aerodynamics of a National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics airfoil (NACA0012) at a chord-based Reynolds numbers of $Re_c = 5300$ and $10{,}000$ using direct numerical simulations. Dimples were placed on the suction side at non-dimensional chordwise locations of $l_D/c = 0.035$ and $0.35$, and the flow response was studied at a fixed angle of attack $\alpha = 5^\circ$. At $Re_c = 5300$, dimples placed at $l_D/c = 0.35$ reduced lift and drag fluctuations by $26.5\%$ and $33.3\%$, respectively, with minimal change in mean forces. At $Re_c = 10{,}000$, the same configuration led to a seven-fold increase in force fluctuations, while the mean remained unchanged. The smooth airfoil exhibited irregular, aperiodic force signals at this $Re_c$, whereas the dimpled case showed highly periodic behavior, indicating wake stabilization. Flow visualizations revealed that dimples generate streamwise vortices within the boundary layer. These vortices are found to have a stabilizing effect on wake dynamics at $Re_c = 5300$, reducing vortex breakdown and enhancing the coherence of wake structures. Spectral Proper Orthogonal Decomposition (SPOD) showed that dimples redistribute modal energy depending on Reynolds number: at low $Re_c$, they reduce broadband content and suppress unsteadiness, while at high $Re_c$, they amplify dominant shedding modes and broaden the spectral energy distribution. These results demonstrate that dimples can passively modulate unsteady forces and wake dynamics for a flow over a streamlined body, either suppressing or enhancing flow instabilities depending on the regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23564v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Putu Brahmanda Sudarsana, Jagmohan Singh, Anchal Sareen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CFDagent: A Language-Guided, Zero-Shot Multi-Agent System for Complex Flow Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23693v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce CFDagent, a zero-shot, multi-agent system that enables fully autonomous computational fluid dynamics (CFD) simulations from natural language prompts. CFDagent integrates three specialized LLM-driven agents: (i) the Preprocessing Agent that generates 3D geometries from textual or visual inputs using a hybrid text-to-3D diffusion model (Point-E) and automatically meshes the geometries; (ii) the Solver Agent that configures and executes an immersed boundary flow solver; and (iii) the Postprocessing Agent that analyzes and visualizes the results, including multimodal renderings. These agents are interactively guided by GPT-4o via conversational prompts, enabling intuitive and user-friendly interaction. We validate CFDagent by reproducing canonical sphere flows at Reynolds numbers of 100 and 300 using three distinct inputs: a simple text prompt (i.e., "sphere"), an image-based input, and a standard sphere model. The computed drag and lift coefficients from meshes produced by each input approach closely match available data. The proposed system enables synthesization of flow simulations and photorealistic visualizations for complex geometries. Through extensive tests on canonical and realistic scenarios, we demonstrate the robustness, versatility, and practical applicability of CFDagent. By bridging generative AI with high-fidelity simulations, CFDagent significantly lowers barriers to expert-level CFD, unlocking broad opportunities in education, scientific research, and practical engineering applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23693v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoyue Xu, Long Wang, Chunyu Wang, Yixin Chen, Qingyong Luo, Hua-Dong Yao, Shizhao Wang, Guowei He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fully Coupled Implicit Hydro-Mechanical Multiphase Flow Simulation in Deformable Porous Media Using DEM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.17100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.17100v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Knowledge of the underlying mechanisms of multiphase flow dynamics in porous media is crucial for optimizing subsurface engineering applications like geological carbon sequestration. However, studying the micro-mechanisms of multiphase fluid--grain interactions in the laboratory is challenging due to the difficulty in obtaining mechanical data such as force and displacement. Transitional discrete element method models coupled with pore networks offer insights into these interactions but struggle with accurate pressure prediction during pore expansion from fracturing and efficient simulation during the slow drainage of compressible fluids. To address these limitations, we develop an advanced two-way coupled hydro-mechanical discrete element method model that accurately and efficiently captures fluid--fluid and fluid--grain interactions in deformable porous media. Our model integrates an unconditionally stable implicit finite volume approach, enabling significant timesteps for advancing fluids. A pressure-volume iteration scheme dynamically balances injection-induced pressure buildup with substantial pore structure deformation, while flow front-advancing criteria precisely locate the fluid--fluid interface and adaptively refine timesteps, particularly when capillary effects block potential flow paths. The model is validated against benchmark Hele-Shaw experiments in both rigid and deformable porous media, providing quantitative insights into the micro-mechanisms governing multiphase flow. For the first time, grain-scale inputs such as viscous and capillary pressures, energies, contact forces, and flow resistances are utilized to provide a detailed understanding of micro-scale fluid--fluid and fluid--grain flow patterns and their transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.17100v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quanwei Dai, Kang Duan, Chung-Yee Kwok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Longitudinal vortices in unsteady Taylor-Couette flow: solution to a 60-year-old mystery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15232v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Applying a sufficiently rapid start-stop to the outer cylinder of the Couette-Taylor system, structures approximately aligned with the axis were recorded in the classic work of Coles (1965). These short-lived rolls are oriented perpendicular to the classic Taylor-vortex rolls. In this work we report numerical observation of this instability, guided by a more recent experimental observation. The instability is shown to be related to an inflection in the azimuthal velocity profile, a finding consistent with the experimental observations of its emergence during the deceleration phase. Despite the transient nature of start-stop experiments, we show that the instability can be linked to that of the oscillating boundary layer problem of Stokes. There are several reasons why the instability may have remained elusive, both for experimental observation and intrinsic to the idealized system. We look in more detail at dependence on the radius ratio for the Taylor-Couette system and find that, in the case where the size of the rolls scales with the gap width, for radius ratios any lower than that used by Coles, R_i/R_o=0.874, the instability is quickly overrun by axisymmetric rolls of Gortler type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15232v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ashley P. Willis, Michael J. Burin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of the sheared flow velocity profile on impedance eduction in a 2D duct</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.10129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.10129v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Impedance eduction methods are the current standard approach to access the impedance of acoustic liner under sheared grazing flow. The dedicated facilities for these methods consists on a waveguide with rectangular cross-section, which implies in a sheared grazing flow. A current debate in the literature is the effect of this sheared flow in the impedance eduction methods. We assess the impact of the flow profile shape on acoustic propagation in a two-dimensional duct within the typical operating range of impedance eduction facilities. Firstly, a numerical experiment is proposed in which the Pridmore--Brown equation is assumed to represent the true physical behaviour, and is used with both simplified flow profiles commonly used in the literature and a realistic representation of a turbulent boundary layer using a van Driest universal law of the wall model. The data from these numerical experiments are then used with a traditional impedance eduction process, and the resulting variation in obtained impedances are investigated. Secondly, we apply a less-traditional impedance eduction method that incorporates the sheared velocity profile to data obtained from real-world experiments. The results suggest that the Ingard--Myers boundary condition remains a good approximation to a realistic boundary layer profile, such as the universal law of the wall, at least in the two-dimensional case. However, it is also shown that the simplified flow profiles often used in the literature can lead to significant deviations from the results obtained using a realistic velocity distribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.10129v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas A Bonomo, Edward J Brambley, Julio A Cordioli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On buoyancy in disperse two-phase flow and its impact on well-posedness of two-fluid models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.21602v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Maxey &amp; Riley's (Phys. Fluids, vol. 26, 1983, 883) analytical solution for the flow around a small sphere at low particle Reynolds number tells us that the fluid-particle interaction force decomposes into a contribution from the local flow disturbance caused by the particle's boundary -- consisting of the drag, Faxen, virtual-mass, and history forces -- and another contribution from the stress of the background flow, termed generalized-buoyancy force. There is also a consensus that, for general disperse two-phase flow, the interfacial force density, resulting from averaging the fluid's and particles' equations of motion, decomposes in a likewise manner. However, there has been a long-standing controversy about the physical closure separating the generalized-buoyancy from the interfacial force density, especially whether or not pseudo-stresses, such as the Reynolds stress, should be attributed to the background flow. Furthermore, most existing propositions for this closure involve small-particle approximations. Here, we show that all existing buoyancy closures are mathematically inconsistent with at least one of three simple thought experiments designed to determine the roles of pseudo-stresses and small-particle approximations. We then derive the unique closure consistent with these thought experiments. It fully incorporates all pseudo-stresses, requires no approximation, and is supported by particle-resolved numerical simulations. Remarkably, it exhibits a low-pass filter property, attenuating buoyancy at short wavelengths, that prevents it from causing Hadamard instabilities, constituting a first-principle-based solution to the long-standing ill-posedness problem of two-fluid models. When employing the derived closure, even very simplistic two-fluid models are hyperbolic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.21602v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Zhu, Yulan Chen, Katharina Tholen, Zhiguo He, Thomas P\"ahtz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pinning mediated coalescence-induced lateral droplet motion on nanotextured superhydrophobic surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22547v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Droplets coalescing on a superhydrophobic surface exhibit coalescence-induced droplet jumping. However, water vapor condensing on a superhydrophobic surface can result in simultaneous formation of condensate droplets with two distinct wetting states, cassie state (CS) and partially wetting (PW) state. Droplets in PW state exhibit high contact angle but are connected to the substrate though a thin liquid condensate column. Coalescence between CS and PW droplets has been recently identified as a possible mechanism for generating droplets exhibiting in-plane roaming motion during dropwise condensation on nanotextured superhydrophobic surfaces. Here, we systematically investigate this phenomenon through experiments on coalescence between sessile droplets in CS and PW state on a nanostructured superhydrophobic surface endowed with a micro-scale hydrophilic spot. Here, a sessile droplet carefully placed on the hydrophilic spot simulates the PW state. Overall, our investigations demonstrate that when a CS droplet coalesces with a PW droplet pinned to a hydrophilic defect, the interaction generates substantial in-plane momentum. We find that when the coalescing CS and PW droplets are nearly of the same size and about ~3 to ~3.5 times the size of the hydrophilic spot pinning the PW droplet, the vertical momentum generation is nearly completely suppressed, and the resulting maxima in in-plane momentum results in detachment of merged droplet from hydrophilic spot and its subsequent in-plane motion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22547v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raushan Kumar, Gopal Chandra Pal, Chander Shekhar Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the impact of the turbulent grazing flow development on the acoustic response of an acoustic liner</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.22714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.22714v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The interaction between acoustic waves and turbulent grazing flow over an acoustic liner is investigated using Lattice-Boltzmann Very-Large-Eddy simulations. A single-degree-of-freedom liner with 11 streamwise-aligned cavities is studied in a grazing flow impedance tube. The conditions replicate reference experiments from the Federal University of Santa Catarina. The influence of grazing flow (with a centerline Mach of 0.32), acoustic wave amplitude, frequency, and propagation direction relative to the mean flow is analysed. Impedance is computed using both the in-situ and the mode-matching methods. The in-situ method reveals strong spatial variations; however, averaged values throughout the sample show minimal differences between upstream and downstream propagating waves, in contrast to the mode-matching method. Flow analyses reveal that the orifices displace the flow away from the face sheet, with this effect amplified by acoustic waves and dependent on the wave propagation direction. Consequently, the boundary layer displacement thickness (${\delta}$*) increases along the streamwise direction compared to a smooth wall and exhibits localised humps downstream of each orifice. The growth of ${\delta}$* alters the flow dynamics within the orifices by weakening the shear layer at downstream positions. This influences the acoustic-induced mass flow rate through the orifices, suggesting that acoustic energy is dissipated differently along the liner. The role of near-wall flow features highlights the need to consider a spatially evolving turbulent flow when studying the acoustic-flow interaction and measuring impedance. The spatial development of the turbulent flow may also partly explain the upstream-downstream impedance differences, as current eduction methods do not account for it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.22714v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angelo Paduano, Francesco Scarano, Julio Cordioli, Damiano Casalino, Francesco Avallone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RG approach to the inviscid limit for shell models of turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04659v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider an initial value problem for shell models that mimic turbulent velocity fluctuations over a geometric sequence of scales. Our goal is to study the convergence of solutions in the inviscid (more generally, vanishing regularization) limit and explain the universality of both the limiting solutions and the convergence process. We develop a renormalization group (RG) formalism representing this limit as dynamics in a space of flow maps. For the dyadic shell model, the RG dynamics has a fixed-point attractor, which determines universal limiting solutions. Deviations from the limiting solutions are also universal and given by a leading eigenmode (eigenvalue and eigenvector) of the linearized RG operator. Application to the Gledzer shell model reveals the RG attractor in the form of a closed invariant curve, while the Sabra shell model yields chaotic RG dynamics. An important consequence of the RG formalism is the understanding of the different roles of symmetry-preserving (canonical) and symmetry-breaking (e.g. viscous) regularizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04659v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexei A. Mailybaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
