<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.flu-dyn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn</link>
    <description>physics.flu-dyn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 05:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Operator Learning for Reconstructing Flow Fields from Sparse Measurements: an Energy Transformer Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08339v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Machine learning methods have shown great success in various scientific areas, including fluid mechanics. However, reconstruction problems, where full velocity fields must be recovered from partial observations, remain challenging. In this paper, we propose a novel operator learning framework for solving reconstruction problems by using the Energy Transformer (ET), an architecture inspired by associative memory models. We formulate reconstruction as a mapping from incomplete observed data to full reconstructed fields. The method is validated on three fluid mechanics examples using diverse types of data: (1) unsteady 2D vortex street in flow past a cylinder using simulation data; (2) high-speed under-expanded impinging supersonic jets impingement using Schlieren imaging; and (3) 3D turbulent jet flow using particle tracking. The results demonstrate the ability of ET to accurately reconstruct complex flow fields from highly incomplete data (90\% missing), even for noisy experimental measurements, with fast training and inference on a single GPU. This work provides a promising new direction for tackling reconstruction problems in fluid mechanics and other areas in mechanics, geophysics, weather prediction, and beyond.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08339v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qian Zhang, Dmitry Krotov, George Em Karniadakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoronaryHemodynamics: An Automated Simulation Framework for Coronary Artery Hemodynamics Using OpenFOAM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08340v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: CoronaryHemodynamics is a comprehensive simulation package developed on the OpenFOAM platform, designed specifically for coronary artery hemodynamics analysis. The package integrates a complete suite of tools for simulation preparation, including automatic case setup, boundary condition configuration, computational domain meshing, and a CFD solver. It fully supports MPI parallelization, leveraging the native parallel computing capabilities of OpenFOAM. The package implements Windkessel boundary conditions at the aorta outlet and all coronary vessel outlets, with outlet parameters automatically derived from physiological metrics such as heart rate, systolic blood pressure, and myocardial volume. At the aorta inlet, a parabolic flow profile is applied based on the input flow rate waveform. CoronaryHemodynamics supports both steady-state and transient solvers, enabling the simulation of various flow conditions. Flow rate and pressure data are recorded at all boundaries during the simulation, and outputs such as wall shear stress, pressure fields, and velocity fields are automatically stored for detailed post-processing and analysis. By automating critical aspects of the simulation pipeline and integrating physiological boundary conditions, CoronaryHemodynamics offers an efficient and robust framework to study coronary hemodynamics in both research and clinical applications. The package can be found at https://github.com/alundilong/CoronaryHemodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08340v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yijin Mao, Yuwen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermoelectrically Elevated Hydrogel Evaporation for Personal Cooling under Extreme Heat Stress</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08342v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hydrogel evaporative cooling has recently emerged as an appealing strategy for personal cooling. However, with the increasing prevalence of extreme heat events featuring high temperatures (above 40$^{\circ}$C) and relative humidity (RH$&gt; 30\%$), hydrogel alone may not achieve thermal comfort under most conditions, as it must be maintained at a sufficiently high temperature-often exceeding the skin comfort temperature ($\sim$35.8$^{\circ}$C)-to achieve effective evaporation in hot, humid environments. This study integrates thermoelectric devices (TEDs) with hydrogels to create a personal cooling solution suited to extreme heat. TEDs pump heat away from the skin, maintaining it at a comfortable temperature, while simultaneously raising the temperature of a hydrogel layer positioned on top of the TEDs to enhance its evaporation rate. The TED-hydrogel tandem device outperforms TEDs or hydrogel alone in extreme conditions (up to 55$^{\circ}$C and RH$&gt; 30\%$). Furthermore, the active temperature control enabled by the TEDs allows the system to adapt to varying thermal loads and environmental conditions. With a manageable hydrogel and battery weight, this cooling system can operate for over six hours. These results demonstrate the potential of hybrid evaporative and thermoelectric cooling as an efficient, adaptable, and sustainable personal cooling solution to combat extreme heat.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08342v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Pei, Tianshi Feng, Robert Chambers, Shengqiang Cai, Renkun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Turbulent Plume from Wildland Fire in Sheared Boundary Layer Flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08343v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Background. Smoke plumes from wildland fires are significant hazards, impacting public health and facilitating fire spotting. In crossflow conditions, typically characterized by vertical shear within the planetary boundary layer, smoke plumes bend downstream of the fire. This bending confines the plume within the boundary layer, delaying its dispersion and increasing fire spotting risks. Aims. This study aims to investigate the bending height of smoke plumes influenced by a sheared crossflow and stratified atmospheric conditions, providing insights into smoke dispersion and fire behavior. Methods. Radar observations from a prescribed fire experiment reveal a large-scale billow-like vorticity pair associated with plume bending. Large Eddy Simulations (LES) in the CM1 model are used to replicate these observations. Key Results. A scaling analysis estimates the plume bending height by incorporating a modified Byram's convective number to account for sheared crossflow. The bending height increases with higher fire intensity, more unstable stratification, and weaker crossflow shear. Simulated results align well with the scaling analysis, highlighting the significance of shear and stratification in plume dynamics. Conclusions. Plume bending height is strongly influenced by fire intensity, atmospheric stratification, and crossflow shear. Incorporating these factors improves our understanding of smoke plume behavior. Implications. The findings enhance smoke dispersion modeling and risk assessment for fire spotting, aiding in the development of strategies to mitigate wildfire impacts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08343v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie Sun, Kevin Speer, Bryan Quaife, Ming Cai, David Schvartzman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A study of pendular liquid bridge between two equal solid spheres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08344v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pendular liquid bridges with concave meridian between two equal rigid spheres are mathematically studied emphasizing on some less analyzed facts in the literature. Discrepancies from numerical solution of the Young-Laplace equation are examined among typical simplifying approximations as well as a few curve-fitting formulas. The separation distance between spheres is shown to play an important role in pendular ring formation via capillary condensation for a given relative humidity as well as the strength of subsequent capillary forces. For most practical situations, the toroidal approximation could be reasonably accurate (especially with diminishing separation distance) and can provide valuable mathematical insights at least in a qualitative sense with its relatively simple analytical formulas. Using the elliptic meridional profile generally offers more accurate approximations, but with so complicated analytical formulas that it would limit its convenience for practical applications. With a few examples, the present study shows that curve-fitting formulas cannot be perfect and by their approximative nature would always leave rooms for improvements; therefore, care should be taken to avoid undesirable errors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08344v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Q Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry-Breaking of Turbulent Flow in Periodic Porous Media at Intermediate Porosities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08350v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel discovery of a symmetry-breaking effect in porous media with porosity between 0.8-0.9, which we are referring to as the intermediate porosity flow regime. Using large eddy simulation, we studied how heat transfer and turbulent convection occurs within these materials at a microscopic level. We observed symmetry-breaking in porous structures made of regularly spaced circular cylinders, a common design in heat exchangers, immediately following the laminar to turbulent flow transition between Reynolds numbers of 37 and 100. Asymmetric patterns persisted up to Reynolds numbers of 1,000. The initial breakdown of symmetry occurs through a Hopf bifurcation, creating an oscillating flow pattern as shear layers interact around the solid obstacles. When the flow becomes turbulent, random variations in the timing of vortex oscillations (caused by the secondary instability) create asymmetric distributions of fluid velocity and temperature throughout the porous space. This leads to the formation of alternating channels with high and low velocity fluid flow. At the macroscale level, this loss of symmetry creates residual transverse drag force components and asymmetric heat flux distribution on the solid obstacle surfaces. Interestingly, the oscillating flow pattern promotes attached flow on the circular cylinder surfaces, which enhances heat transfer from the cylinders to the fluid. We observe that this secondary flow instability is the primary mechanism of enhanced turbulent heat flux from porous media with circular cylinders compared to those with square cylinders.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08350v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vishal Srikanth, Andrey V Kuznetsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytic Solution of the N-Dimensional Incompressible Navier-Stokes Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08353v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents an analytic solution of the incompressible Navier-Stokes equations as recurrence relations for the solution's derivatives, addressing the Clay Mathematics Institute's Millennium Prize problem on Navier-Stokes existence and smoothness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08353v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathan Strange</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Duty-cycle actuation for drag reduction of deep dynamic stall: Insights from linear stability analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08414</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08414v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A flow control framework based on linear stability analysis is proposed focusing on reducing the aerodynamic drag due to dynamic stall through a finite-window temporal actuation. The methodology is applied on a periodically plunging SD7003 airfoil.Finite-time Lyapunov exponent (FTLE) fields reveal a saddle point near the airfoil leading edge, where a shear layer forms and feeds a dynamic stall vortex (DSV). A local stability analysis conducted at this saddle point identifies a Kelvin-Helmholtz instability, and the most unstable eigenvalue frequencies remain constant when the variation in the effective angle of attack is minimal. The findings from the FTLE fields and the stability analysis are used to inform the position and finite duty cycle of a periodic blowing and suction actuation applied in a wall-resolved large eddy simulation (LES). The present framework reduces the actuation duty cycle by 77.5% during the airfoil plunging motion, while maintaining the same performance as a continuous actuation throughout the entire cycle. The LES results demonstrate that disturbances from the stability-analysis-informed actuation modify the leading-edge dynamics, preventing the formation of the coherent DSV and significantly reducing the drag.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08414v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Feitosa de Souza, William Roberto Wolf, Maryam Safari, Chi-An Yeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytical and Numerical Study of a Convection-Diffusion-Reaction-Source Problem in Multilayered Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08489v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, a thermal energy transfer problem in a one-dimensional multilayer body is theoretically analyzed, considering diffusion, advection, internal heat generation or loss linearly dependent on temperature in each layer, as well as heat generation due to external sources. Additionally, the thermal contact resistance at the interfaces between each pair of materials is taken into account. The problem is mathematically modeled, and explicit analytical solutions are derived using Fourier techniques. A convergent finite difference scheme is also formulated to simulate specific cases. The solution is consistent with previous results. A numerical example is provided, demonstrating the coherence between the obtained results and the physical behavior of the problem. This work was recently published for a two-layer body; the generalization to m-layer bodies allows for conclusions that enhance the theoretical understanding of heat transfer in multilayer materials and may contribute to improving the thermal design of multilayer engineering systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08489v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ijthermalsci.2025.109690</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Thermal Sciences 211 (2025), 109690</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Guillermo Federico Umbricht, Domingo Alberto Tarzia, Diana Rubio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of pressure gradient histories on skin friction and mean flow of high Reynolds number turbulent boundary layers over smooth and rough walls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08642v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Experiments are conducted over smooth and rough walls to explore the influence of pressure gradient histories on skin friction and mean flow of turbulent boundary layers. Different pressure gradient histories are imposed on the boundary layer through an aerofoil mounted in the freestream. Hot-wire measurements are taken at different freestream velocities downstream of the aerofoil where the flow has locally recovered to zero pressure gradient but retains the history effects. Direct skin friction measurements are also made using oil film interferometry for smooth walls and a floating element drag balance for rough walls. The friction Reynolds number, $Re_\tau$, varies between $3000$ and $27000$, depending both on the surface conditions and the freestream velocity ensuring sufficient scale separation. Results align with previous findings, showing that adverse pressure gradients just upstream of the measurement location increase wake strength and reduce the local skin friction while favourable pressure gradients suppress the wake and increase skin friction. The roughness length scale, $y_0$, remains constant across different pressure gradient histories for rough wall boundary layers. Inspired by previous works, a new correlation is proposed to infer skin friction based on the mean flow. The difference in skin friction between an arbitrary pressure gradient history and zero pressure gradient condition can be predicted using only the local wake strength parameter ($\Pi$), and the variations in wake strength for different histories are related to a weighted integral of the pressure gradient history normalised by local quantities. This allows us to develop a general correlation that can be used to infer skin friction for turbulent boundary layers experiencing arbitrary pressure-gradient histories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08642v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Preskett, Marco Virgilio, Prateek Jaiswal, Bharathram Ganapathisubramani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimized CFD modelling and validation of radiation section of an industrial top-fired steam methane reforming furnace</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08660v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The present study proposes an optimized computational fluid dynamics (CFD) modelling framework to provide a complete and accurate representation of combustion and heat transfer phenomena in the radiation section of an industrial top-fired steam methane reforming (SMR) furnace containing 64 reforming tubes, 30 burners and 3 flue-gas tunnels. The framework combines fully-coupled appropriate furnace-side models with a 1-D reforming process-side model. Experimental measurements are conducted in terms of outlet temperatures at the flue-gas tunnels, point-wise temperature distributions at the panel walls, and inside the reforming tube collectors which are placed at the refinery plant of Petronor. The final results are compared with the experimental data for validation purpose. The proposed fully coupled 3-D CFD modeling framework, which utilizes a detailed chemical-kinetic combustion mechanism, reproduces well basic flow features including pre-mixed combustion process, downward movement of flue-gas in association with large recirculation zones, radiative heat transfer to the reforming tubes, composition profiles along the reaction core of the reforming tubes, temperature non-uniformities, and fluctuating characteristics of heat flux. The reported non-uniform heat and temperature distributions might be optimized by means of the operating parameters in order to avoid a negative impact on furnace balancing and performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08660v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.compchemeng.2021.107504</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Computers and Chemical Engineering 155 (2021) 107504</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mustafa Tutar, Cihat Emre \"Ust\"un, Jose Miguel Campillo-Robles, Raquel Fuente, Silvia Cibri\'an, Ignacio Arzua, Arturo Fern\'andez, Gabriel A. L\'opez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mutual Interactions Between a Thin Flexible Panel and Supersonic Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08875</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08875v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper discusses the mutual interactions between a thin flexible aluminum plate and supersonic flow using two-dimensional (2D) numerical simulations. Calculations are performed using an open source library, SU2, that solves partial differential equations governing fluid and structural dynamics. The configuration considered in this research effort is based on an experiment in which a thin flexible panel of 1.02 mm with a 50.8 mm overhang at the outer edge of a backward facing step is exposed to Mach 2 flow. The computational framework was first validated against measurements for both the initial transients of 10 ms and the fully started conditions at 0.4 s. Then, numerical studies were performed to analyze the fluid-structure interactions at 4 different Mach numbers between 0.5 and 3. The flow behavior revealed distinct phenomena, including shear layer separation for subsonic and transonic flows, and a fully enclosed recirculation region under the overhang in supersonic cases. The time-averaged flow field identified potential temperature hotspots during the initial transients, which intensified as time evolved. For Mach 0.50, the amplitude of the thin panel oscillations increased as the flow transitioned from transient to steady-state conditions. In the transonic case (M = 0.95), the oscillation amplitude became significantly larger, potentially leading to resonant behavior and structural failure (we did not model failure). However, in the supersonic cases, the oscillations stabilized and were sustained after the initial transients. The research quantitatively identifies the influence of the Mach number on the fluid-structure interaction phenomena, which affect pressure loads and the development of thermal hotspots, which are crucial elements in engineering design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08875v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Himakar Ganti, Luis Bravo, Anindya Ghosal, Prashant Khare</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Helicity effect on turbulent passive and active scalar diffusivities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08879v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Turbulent flows are known to produce enhanced effective magnetic and passive scalar diffusivities, which can fairly accurately be determined with numerical methods. It is now known that, if the flow is also helical, the effective magnetic diffusivity is reduced relative to the nonhelical value. Neither the usual second-order correlation approximation nor the various $\tau$ approaches have been able to capture this. Here we show that the helicity effect on the turbulent passive scalar diffusivity works in the opposite sense and leads to an enhancement. This effect has not previously been seen. We have also demonstrated that the correlation time of the turbulent velocity field increases by the kinetic helicity. This is a key point in the theoretical interpretation of the obtained numerical results. Simulations in which helicity is being produced self-consistently by stratified rotating turbulence, resulted in a turbulent passive scalar diffusivity that was found to be decreasing with increasing rotation rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08879v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Axel Brandenburg, Petri J. K\"apyl\"a, Igor Rogachevskii, Nobumitsu Yokoi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On idealized models of turbulent condensation in clouds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08968v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Various microphysical models attempt to explain the occurrence of broad droplet size distributions (DSD) in clouds through approximate representations of the stochastic droplet growth by condensation in a turbulent environment. This work analyzes specific idealized models, where the variability of droplet growth conditions arises primarily from variability in the turbulent vertical velocity of the air carrying these droplets. Examples are the stochastic eddy hopping model operating in adiabatic parcels and certain types of DNS-like models. We show that such models produce droplet size statistics that are spatially inhomogeneous along the vertical direction, causing the predicted DSD to depend on the DSD spatial sampling scale $\Delta$. In these models, $\Delta$ is implicitly related to the spatial extent of the droplets turbulent diffusion (approximated by Brownian-like excursions) and thus grows like $t^{1/2}$. This leads to spurious continuous DSD broadening, as the growth in time (also like $t^{1/2}$) of the standard deviation of droplet squared radius arises essentially from the growth of the sampling scale $\Delta$. Also, the DSDs predicted by the models discussed here are not necessarily locally broad (in the sense that large and small droplets might not be well-mixed in sufficiently small volumes) and thus do not necessarily indicate enhanced probabilities of gravity-induced droplet coagulation. In the effort to build a firm physical basis for subgrid parametrizations, this study presents a framework to explain the merits and limitations of idealized models, indicating how to assess and use them wisely as a subgrid representation of turbulent condensation in large-eddy simulations of clouds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08968v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. C. Abade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimising branched fluidic networks: A unifying approach including laminar and turbulent flows, rough walls, and non-Newtonian fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08999v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Power minimisation in branched fluidic networks has gained significant attention in biology and engineering. The optimal network is defined by channel radii that minimise the sum of viscous dissipation and the volumetric energetic cost of the fluid. For limit cases including laminar flows, high Reynolds number turbulence, or smooth channel approximations, optimal solutions are known. However, no single optimisation approach captures these limit cases. Furthermore, realistic fluidic networks exhibit intermediate points in the parameter space that can hardly be optimised. Here, we present a unifying optimisation approach based on the Darcy friction factor, which has been determined for a wide range of flow regimes and fluid models. We optimise fluidic networks for the entire parameter space: Laminar and turbulent flows, including networks that exhibit both flow types; Non-Newtonian fluid models (power-law, Bingham, and Herschel-Bulkley); and Networks with arbitrary wall roughness, including non-uniform relative roughness. The optimal channel radii are presented analytically and graphically. Finally, the parameter $x$ in the optimisation relationship $Q\propto R^x$ was approximated as a function of the Reynolds number, revealing that previously-determined values of $x$ hardly apply to realistic turbulent flows. Our approach can be extended to other configurations for which the friction factor is known, such as different channel curvatures or wall slip conditions, enabling optimisation of a wide range of fluidic networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08999v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Siemen Smink, Rob Hagmeijer, Cornelis Henricus Venner, Claas Willem Visser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unsupervised neural-implicit laser absorption tomography for quantitative imaging of unsteady flames</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08337v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel neural-implicit approach to laser absorption tomography (LAT) with experimental verification. A coordinate neural network is used to represent thermochemical state variables as continuous functions of space and time. Unlike most existing neural methods for LAT, which rely on prior simulations and supervised training, our approach is based solely on LAT measurements, utilizing a differentiable observation operator with line parameters provided in standard spectroscopy database formats. Although reconstructing scalar fields from multi-beam absorbance data is an inherently ill-posed, nonlinear inverse problem, our continuous space-time parameterization supports physics-inspired regularization strategies and enables physics-informed data assimilation. Synthetic and experimental tests are conducted to validate the method, demonstrating robust performance and reproducibility. We show that our neural-implicit approach to LAT can capture the dominant spatial modes of an unsteady flame from very sparse measurement data, indicating its potential to reveal combustion instabilities in measurement domains with minimal optical access.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08337v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph P. Molnar, Jiangnan Xia, Rui Zhang, Samuel J. Grauer, Chang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geomorphodynamics, evolution, and ecology of vertical roots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08367v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The roots of some coastal and wetland trees grow peculiar vertical protrusions, the function of which remains unclear. Here, using computational simulations based on first-principles fluid and sedimentation dynamics, we argue that the protrusions work together to create an elevated patch of sediment downstream of the tree, thereby creating its own fertile flood-protected breeding grounds for the seedlings. In our simulations, we vary the vertical root diameter, root spacing and total root area and show that there is an optimal vertical root spacing that depends on root thickness. Next, we quantify and discuss the cooperative effects between adjacent vertical root patches. Lastly, by varying vertical root spacing of a patch of trees, we estimate a maximal vegetation density for which vertical root production has a beneficial geomorphological response. Our hypothesis suggests that vertical roots, such as the "knee roots" of baldcypress trees, have an important role in shaping riparian geomorphology and community structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08367v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3389/fpls.2023.1102491</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Frontiers in Plant Science 14 (2023): 1102491</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Martin Heidelman, Dervis Can Vural</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-informed neural networks for phase-resolved data assimilation and prediction of nonlinear ocean waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08430v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The assimilation and prediction of phase-resolved surface gravity waves are critical challenges in ocean science and engineering. Potential flow theory (PFT) has been widely employed to develop wave models and numerical techniques for wave prediction. However, traditional wave prediction methods are often limited. For example, most simplified wave models have a limited ability to capture strong wave nonlinearity, while fully nonlinear PFT solvers often fail to meet the speed requirements of engineering applications. This computational inefficiency also hinders the development of effective data assimilation techniques, which are required to reconstruct spatial wave information from sparse measurements to initialize the wave prediction. To address these challenges, we propose a novel solver method that leverages physics-informed neural networks (PINNs) that parameterize PFT solutions as neural networks. This provides a computationally inexpensive way to assimilate and predict wave data. The proposed PINN framework is validated through comparisons with analytical linear PFT solutions and experimental data collected in a laboratory wave flume. The results demonstrate that our approach accurately captures and predicts irregular, nonlinear, and dispersive wave surface dynamics. Moreover, the PINN can infer the fully nonlinear velocity potential throughout the entire fluid volume solely from surface elevation measurements, enabling the calculation of fluid velocities that are difficult to measure experimentally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08430v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Svenja Ehlers, Norbert Hoffmann, Tianning Tang, Adrian H. Callaghan, Rui Cao, Enrique M. Padilla, Yuxin Fang, Merten Stender</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay between tidal flows and magnetic fields in nonlinear simulations of stellar and planetary convective envelopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08722v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stars and planets in close systems are magnetised but the influence of magnetic fields on their tidal responses (and vice versa) and dissipation rates has not been well explored. We present exploratory nonlinear magnetohydrodynamical (MHD) simulations of tidally-excited inertial waves in convective envelopes. These waves probably provide the dominant contribution to tidal dissipation in several astrophysical settings, including tidal circularisation of solar-type binary stars and hot Jupiters, and orbital migration of the moons of Jupiter and Saturn. We model convective envelopes as incompressible magnetised fluids in spherical shells harbouring an initially (rotationally-aligned) dipolar magnetic field. We find that depending on its strength (quantified by its Lehnert number Le) and the magnetic Prandtl number Pm, the magnetic field can either deeply modify the tidal response or be substantially altered by tidal flows. Simulations with small Le exhibit strong tidally-generated differential rotation (zonal flows) for sufficiently large tidal amplitudes, such that both the amplitude and topology of the initial magnetic field are tidally impacted. In contrast, strong magnetic fields can inhibit these zonal flows through large-scale magnetic torques, and by Maxwell stresses arising from magneto-rotational instability, which we identify and characterise in our simulations, along with the role of torsional Alfv\'en waves. Without tidally-driven zonal flows, the resulting tidal dissipation is close to the linear predictions. We quantify the transition Le as a function of Pm, finding it to be comparable to realistic values found in solar-like stars, such that we predict complex interactions between tidal flows and magnetic fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08722v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aur\'elie Astoul, Adrian J. Barker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MeshMask: Physics-Based Simulations with Masked Graph Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08738v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a novel masked pre-training technique for graph neural networks (GNNs) applied to computational fluid dynamics (CFD) problems. By randomly masking up to 40\% of input mesh nodes during pre-training, we force the model to learn robust representations of complex fluid dynamics. We pair this masking strategy with an asymmetric encoder-decoder architecture and gated multi-layer perceptrons to further enhance performance. The proposed method achieves state-of-the-art results on seven CFD datasets, including a new challenging dataset of 3D intracranial aneurysm simulations with over 250,000 nodes per mesh. Moreover, it significantly improves model performance and training efficiency across such diverse range of fluid simulation tasks. We demonstrate improvements of up to 60\% in long-term prediction accuracy compared to previous best models, while maintaining similar computational costs. Notably, our approach enables effective pre-training on multiple datasets simultaneously, significantly reducing the time and data required to achieve high performance on new tasks. Through extensive ablation studies, we provide insights into the optimal masking ratio, architectural choices, and training strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08738v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Garnier, Vincent Lannelongue, Jonathan Viquerat, Elie Hachem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calculus with combinatorial differential forms for fluid flow analysis in porous and fractured media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08996v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The fabric of porous and fractured media contains solid regions (grains) and voids. The space conducting fluids is a system of connected voids with variable geometries. Relative to the grain sizes, the voids can be voluminous with three comparable large extensions, narrow expansive with two comparable large extensions and one smaller extension, and thin long with one comparable large extension and two smaller extensions. The widely used representation of void spaces by systems of spheres connected by cylinders (pore network models) is an acceptable approximation for some special cases, but not for most porous and fractured media. We propose a flexible method for modelling such media by mapping their measured fabric's characteristics - void and grain volume distributions and shapes - onto polyhedral tessellations of space. The map assigns voluminous voids and grains to polyhedrons (3D), narrow expansive voids to some polyhedral faces (2D), and thin long voids to some polyhedral edges (1D), as dictated by experimental data. The analysis of transport through such discrete structures with components of different dimensions is performed by a novel mathematical method, which uses combinatorial differential forms to represent physical properties and their fluxes, as well as structure-preserving operators on such forms to formulate the conservation laws exactly and directly in matrix form, ready for computation. The method allows for individual material properties, such as conductivity, to be assigned to voids of all dimensions, so that the three types of voids are suitably represented. Publicly available XCT images of four different rocks are used to test the method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08996v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changhao Liu, Kiprian Berbatov, Majid Sedighi, Andrey P. Jivkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alfv\'en waves at low magnetic Reynolds number: Transitions between diffusion, dispersive Alfv\'en waves and nonlinear propagation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04276v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper seeks whether Alfv\'en waves (AW) can be produced in laboratory-scale liquid metal experiments, \emph{i.e.} at low-magnetic Reynolds Number ($R\!m$). AW are incompressible waves propagating along magnetic fields typically found geo and astrophysical systems. Until now, only faint linear waves have been experimentally produced in liquid metals because of the large magnetic dissipation they undergo when $R\!m\ll1$. Yet, controlling laboratory AW could emulate such far remote processes as anomalous heating in the solar corona, oscillations of the Earth inner core or turbulence in the solar wind. To answer this question, we force AW with an AC electric current in a liquid metal channel in a transverse magnetic field. We derive a wave-bearing extension of the usual low$-R\!m$ MHD approximation to identify two linear regimes: The purely diffusive regime exists when $N_\omega$, the ratio of the oscillation period to the timescale of diffusive two-dimensionalisation by the Lorentz force, is small. The propagative regime is governed by the ratio of the forcing period to the AW propagation timescale which, we call the Jameson number $J\!a$ after Jameson (1964), JFM. In this regime, AW are dissipative and dispersive as they propagate more slowly where velocity gradients are higher. Both regimes are recovered in the FLOWCUBE experiment, in excellent agreement with the model up to $J\!a \lesssim 0.85$ but near the $J\!a=1$ resonance, high amplitude waves become clearly nonlinear. Hence, in electrically driving AW, we were able to produce some of the propagative, diffusive and nonlinear processes of astro and geophysical AW.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04276v4</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samy Lalloz, Laurent Davoust, Fran\c{c}ois Debray, Alban Poth\'erat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wall-resolved large eddy simulations of a pitching airfoil incurring in deep dynamic stall</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12036v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study investigates the flow evolution around a sinusoidal pitching NACA 0012 airfoil, defined by the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics (NACA), undergoing deep dynamic stall using a wall-resolved large eddy simulation (LES) approach. Numerical results are assessed against experimental data from Lee and Gerontakos (2004) at Reynolds number Re = 135 000 and reduced frequency k = 0.1. A comprehensive analysis of the computational model span size is presented, highlighting the requirement for a span-to-chord ratio of at least one to correctly capture the dynamic stall vortex physics in the downstroke phase. Furthermore, a comparative assessment with state-of-the-art Reynolds-Averaged Navier-Stokes (RANS), hybrid RANS/LES, and the experimental data is carried out. All the numerical models concur to the same flow behavior and exhibit similar differences with the experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12036v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giacomo Baldan, Alberto Guardone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lateral migration and bouncing of a deformable bubble rising near a vertical wall. Part 1. Moderately inertial regimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17912v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The buoyancy-driven motion of a deformable bubble rising near a vertical hydrophilic wall is studied numerically. We focus on moderately inertial regimes in which the bubble undergoes low-to-moderate deformations and would rise in a straight line in the absence of the wall. Three different types of near-wall motion are observed, depending on the buoyancy-to-viscous and buoyancy-to-capillary force ratios defining the Galilei ($Ga$) and Bond ($Bo$) numbers of the system, respectively. For low enough $Ga$ or large enough $Bo$, bubbles consistently migrate away from the wall. Conversely, for large enough $Ga$ and low enough $Bo$, they perform periodic near-wall bounces. At intermediate $Ga$ and $Bo$, they are first attracted to the wall down to a certain critical distance, and then perform bounces with a decreasing amplitude before stabilizing at this critical separation. Periodic bounces are accompanied by the shedding of a pair of streamwise vortices in the wake, the formation of which is governed by the near-wall shear resulting from the no-slip condition. These vortices provide a repulsive force that overcomes the viscous resistance of the fluid to the departing motion, making the bubble capable of returning to the region where it is attracted again to the wall. Although periodic, the shedding/regeneration cycle of these vortices is highly asymmetric with respect to the lateral bubble displacements, vortices being shed when the gap left between the bubble and the wall reaches its maximum, and reborn only when this gap comes back to its minimum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17912v3</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/jfm.2024.865</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Fluid Mech. 998 (2024) A8</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pengyu Shi, Jie Zhang, Jacques Magnaudet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A front-tracking immersed-boundary framework for simulating Lagrangian melting problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20244</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.20244v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In so-called Lagrangian melting problems, a solid immersed in a fluid medium is free to rotate and translate in tandem with its phase-change from solid to liquid. Such configurations may be classified as a fluid-solid interaction (FSI) problem coupled to phase-change. Our present work proposes a numerical method capable of simulating these Lagrangian melting problems and adopts a front-tracking immersed-boundary (IB) method. We use the moving least squares IB framework, a well-established method for simulating a diverse range of FSI problems and extend this framework to accommodate melting by additionally imposing the Stefan condition at the interface. In the spirit of canonical front-tracking methods, the immersed solid is represented by a discrete triangulated mesh which is separate from the Eulerian mesh in which the governing flow equations are solved. A known requirement for these methods is the need for comparable Eulerian and Lagrangian grid spacings to stabilise interpolation and spreading operations between the two grids. For a melting object, this requirement is inevitably violated unless interventional remeshing is introduced. Our work therefore presents a novel dynamic remeshing procedure to overcome this. The remeshing is based on a gradual coarsening of the triangulated Lagrangian mesh and amounts to a negligible computational burden per timestep owing to the incremental and local nature of its operations, making it a scalable approach. Moreover, the coarsening is coupled to a volume-conserving smoothing procedure detailed by Kuprat et al. (2001), ensuring a zero net volume change in the remeshing step to machine precision. This added feature makes our present method highly specialised to the study of melting problems, where precise measurements of the melting solid's volume is often the primary predictive quantity of interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.20244v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Zhong, Christopher J. Howland, Detlef Lohse, Roberto Verzicco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ZipGAN: Super-Resolution-based Generative Adversarial Network Framework for Data Compression of Direct Numerical Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14150v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The advancement of high-performance computing has enabled the generation of large direct numerical simulation (DNS) datasets of turbulent flows, driving the need for efficient compression/decompression techniques that reduce storage demands while maintaining fidelity. Traditional methods, such as the discrete wavelet transform, cannot achieve compression ratios of 8 or higher for complex turbulent flows without introducing significant encoding/decoding errors. On the other hand, a super-resolution-based generative adversarial network (SR-GAN), called ZipGAN, can accurately reconstruct fine-scale features, preserving velocity gradients and structural details, even at a compression ratio of 512, thanks to the more efficient representation of the data in compact latent space. Additional benefits are ascribed to adversarial training. The high GAN training time is significantly reduced with a progressive transfer learning approach and, once trained, they can be applied independently of the Reynolds number. It is demonstrated that ZipGAN can enhance dataset temporal resolution without additional simulation overhead by generating high-quality intermediate fields from compressed snapshots. The ZipGAN discriminator can reliably evaluate the quality of decoded fields, ensuring fidelity even in the absence of original DNS fields. Hence, ZipGAN compression/decompression method presents a highly efficient and scalable alternative for large-scale DNS storage and transfer, offering substantial advantages over the DWT methods in terms of compression efficiency, reconstruction fidelity, and temporal resolution enhancement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14150v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ludovico Nista, Christoph D. K. Schumann, Fabian Fr\"ode, Mohamed Gowely, Temistocle Grenga, Jonathan F. MacArt, Antonio Attili, Heinz Pitsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A stochastic model for the turbulent ocean heat flux under Arctic sea ice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.11815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2108.11815v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The physics of planetary climate features a variety of complex systems that are challenging to model as they feature turbulent flows. A key example is the heat flux from the upper ocean to the underside of sea ice which provides a key contribution to the evolution of the Arctic sea ice cover. Here, we develop a model of the turbulent ice-ocean heat flux using coupled ordinary stochastic differential equations to model fluctuations in the vertical velocity and temperature in the Arctic mixed layer. All the parameters in the model are determined from observational data. A detailed comparison between the model results and measurements made during the Surface Heat Budget of the Arctic Ocean (SHEBA) project reveals that the model is able to capture the probability density functions (PDFs) of velocity, temperature and heat flux fluctuations. Furthermore, we show that the temperature in the upper layer of the Arctic ocean can be treated as a passive scalar during the whole year of SHEBA measurements. The stochastic model developed here provides a computationally inexpensive way to compute an observationally consistent PDF of this heat flux, and has implications for its parametrization in regional and global climate models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2108.11815v3</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Srikanth Toppaladoddi, Andrew J. Wells</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum collision circuit, quantum invariants and quantum phase estimation procedure for fluid dynamic lattice gas automata</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07362v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Lattice Gas Cellular Automata (LGCA) is a classical numerical method widely known and applied to simulate several physical phenomena. In this paper, we study the translation of LGCA on quantum computers (QC) using computational basis encoding (CBE), developing methods for different purposes. In particular, we clarify and discuss some fundamental limitations and advantages in using CBE and quantum walk as streaming procedure. Using quantum walks affect the possible encoding of classical states in quantum orthogonal states, feature linked to the unitarity of collision and to the possibility of getting a quantum advantage. Then, we give efficient procedures for optimizing collisional quantum circuits, based on the classical features of the model. This is applied specifically to fluid dynamic LGCA. Alongside, a new collision circuit for a 1-dimensional model is proposed. We address the important point of invariants in LGCA providing a method for finding how many invariants appear in their QC formulation. Quantum invariants outnumber the classical expectations, proving the necessity of further research. Lastly, we prove the validity of a method for retrieving any quantity of interest based on quantum phase estimation (QPE).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07362v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CG</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niccolo Fonio, Pierre Sagaut, Giuseppe Di Molfetta</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
