<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.flu-dyn updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn</link>
    <description>physics.flu-dyn updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.flu-dyn" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 05:00:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic subgrid-scale LES model for turbulent non-Newtonian flows: A priori and a posteriori analyses of Burgers turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09687v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large Eddy Simulation (LES) of turbulent non-Newtonian flows involves two additional closures, namely the Non-Newtonian SubGrid-Scale (NNSGS) stress tensor and filtered viscosity. Here, dynamic closures are proposed for NNSGS, eliminating the need for model calibration. In addition, for the primary evaluation of LES closures, two canonical case studies are designed by the extension of Newtonian forced Burgers turbulence to include power-law viscosity rheology. The characteristics of the proposed non-Newtonian turbulence are studied carefully using direct numerical simulation. For instance, it is revealed that the shear-thinning effect intensifies the small-scale motions and elevates the energy spectrum function at high wave-numbers. The subsequent a priori and a posteriori studies manifest that the NNSGS modeling is important for the present test cases. The omission of this term results in the under-prediction of kinetic energy due to the substantial backscatter effect of NNSGS. The proposed dynamic Smagorinsky based closure is recommended, based on the correlation coefficient measure in the a priori tests and the energy spectrum function in the a posteriori tests, for LES of turbulence at high shear-thinning rheology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09687v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jnnfm.2021.104615</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Non-Newtonian Fluid Mechanics Journal of Non-Newtonian Fluid Mechanics, Volume 295, September 2021, 104615</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>E. Amani, A. Ahmadpour, M. J. Aghajari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Novel mixed approximate deconvolution subgrid-scale models for large-eddy simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09697v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Approximate Deconvolution (AD) has emerged as a promising closure for Large-Eddy Simulation (LES) in complex multi-physics flows, where the conventional pure Dynamic Eddy-Viscosity (DEV) models experience issues. In this research, we propose novel improved mixed hard-deconvolution or secondary-regularization models and compare their performance with the existing standard mixed AD-DEV and penalty-term regularizations. For this aim, five consistency criteria, based on the properties of the modeled sub-filter-scale stress in limit conditions, are introduced for the first time. It is proved that the conventional hard-deconvolution models do not adhere to a couple of important primary criteria. Furthermore, through a priori and a posteriori analyses of Burgers turbulence and turbulent channel flow, it is manifested that the inconsistency with the primary criteria can result in larger modeling errors, the over-prediction and pile-up of kinetic energy in eddies of a length scale between the explicit filter width and grid size, and even the solution instability. On the other hand, the favorable characteristics of the new mixed models, in terms of the consistency criteria, significantly improve the accuracy of the predictions, the solution stability, and even the computational cost, particularly for one of the new models called mixed Alternative-DEV (A-DEV).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09697v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0221814</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physics of Fluids 36, 085188 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ehsan Amani, Mohammad Bagher Molaei, Morteza Ghorbani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry aware Reynolds Averaged Navier Stokes turbulence models with equivariant neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09769v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate and generalizable Reynolds-averaged Navier-Stokes (RANS) models for turbulent flows rely on effective closures. We introduce tensor-based, symmetry aware closures using equivariant neural networks (ENNs) and present an algorithm for enforcing algebraic contraction relations among tensor components. The modeling approach builds on the structure tensor framework introduced by Kassinos and Reynolds to learn closures in the rapid distortion theory setting. Experiments show that ENNs can effectively learn relationships involving high-order tensors, meeting or exceeding the performance of existing models in tasks such as predicting the rapid pressure-strain correlation. Our results show that ENNs provide a physically consistent alternative to classical tensor basis models, enabling end-to-end learning of unclosed terms in RANS and fast exploration of model dependencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09769v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aaron Miller, Sahil Kommalapati, Robert Moser, Petros Koumoutsakos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mitigating numerical dissipation in simulations of subsonic turbulent flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09806v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) simulations of subsonic (Mach number~$&lt;1$) turbulence are crucial to our understanding of several processes including oceanic and atmospheric flows, the amplification of magnetic fields in the early universe, accretion discs, and stratified flows in stars. In this work, we demonstrate that conventional numerical schemes are excessively dissipative in this low-Mach regime. We demonstrate that a new numerical scheme (termed `USM-BK' and implemented in the FLASH MHD code) reduces the dissipation of kinetic and magnetic energy, constrains the divergence of magnetic field to zero close to machine precision, and resolves smaller-scale structure than other, more conventional schemes, and hence, is the most accurate for simulations of low-Mach turbulent flows among the schemes compared in this work. We first compare several numerical schemes/solvers, including Split-Roe, Split-Bouchut, USM-Roe, USM-HLLC, USM-HLLD, and the new USM-BK, on a simple vortex problem. We then compare the schemes/solvers in simulations of the turbulent dynamo and show that the choice of scheme affects the growth rate, saturation level, and viscous and resistive dissipation scale of the dynamo. We also measure the numerical kinematic Reynolds number (Re) and magnetic Reynolds number (Rm) of our otherwise ideal MHD flows, and show that the new USM-BK scheme provides the highest Re and comparable Rm amongst all the schemes compared.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09806v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Watt, Christoph Federrath, Claudius Birke, Christian Klingenberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven modeling of multiscale phenomena with applications to fluid turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09847v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This letter introduces a novel data driven framework for constructing accurate and general equivariant models of multiscale phenomena which does not rely on specific assumptions about the underlying physics. This framework is illustrated using incompressible fluid turbulence as an example that is representative, practically important, reasonably simple, and exceedingly well studied. We use direct numerical simulations of freely decaying turbulence in two spatial dimensions to infer an effective field theory comprising explicit, interpretable evolution equations for both the large (resolved) and small (modeled) scales. The resulting closed system of equations is capable of accurately describing the effect of small scales, including backscatter -- the flow of energy from small to large scales, which is particularly pronounced in two dimensions -- which is an outstanding challenge that, to our knowledge, no existing alternative successfully tackles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09847v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brandon Choi, Matteo Ugliotti, Mateo Reynoso, Daniel R. Gurevich, Roman O. Grigoriev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergent series of Stokes wave of arbitrary height in deep water via machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09927v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Permanent gravity waves propagating in deep water, spanning amplitudes from infinitesimal to their theoretical limiting values, remain a classical yet challenging problem due to its inherent nonlinear complexities. Traditional analytical and numerical methods encounter substantial difficulties near the limiting wave condition due to singularities at sharp wave crests. In this study, we propose a novel hybrid framework combining the homotopy analysis method (HAM) with machine learning (ML) to efficiently compute convergent series solutions of Stokes waves in deep water for arbitrary wave amplitudes from small to theoretical limiting values, which show excellent agreement with established benchmarks. We introduce a neural network trained using only 20 representative cases whose series solution are given by means of HAM, which can rapidly predict series solutions across arbitrary steepness levels, substantially improving computational efficiency. Additionally, we develop a neural network to gain the inverse mapping from the conformal coordinates $(\theta, r)$ to the physical coordinates $(x,y)$, facilitating explicit and intuitive representations of series solutions in physical plane. This HAM-ML hybrid framework represents a powerful and efficient approach to compute convergent series in a whole range of physical parameters for water waves with arbitrary wave height including even limiting waves. In this way we establish a new paradigm to quickly obtain convergent series solutions of complex nonlinear systems for a whole range of physical parameters, thereby significantly broadening the scope of series solutions that can be easily gained by means of HAM even for highly nonlinear problems in science and engineering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09927v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chong Lin, Shijun Liao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freezing dynamics of the ferrofluid droplet in a uniform magnetic field using the lattice Boltzmann flux solver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10257v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, an enthalpy-based lattice Boltzmann flux solver is developed to simulate the freezing dynamics of a ferrofluid droplet under a uniform magnetic field. The accuracy and robustness of the solver are first validated through three benchmark tests: conductive freezing, static droplet freezing, and ferrofluid droplet deformation. The solver is then employed to investigate the influence of a uniform magnetic field on the freezing behavior of ferrofluid droplets, with particular emphasis on the overall freezing process, heat transfer characteristics, and freezing duration. The results reveal that the uniform magnetic field affects the freezing dynamics primarily by altering the droplet morphology. Under a vertically oriented magnetic field, the droplet elongates along the field direction, which increases the thermal resistance and consequently prolongs the freezing time. Conversely, a horizontally uniform magnetic field flattens the droplet, reducing the thermal resistance and thus shortening the freezing time. These findings provide new physical insight into magnetic-field-induced modulation of the freezing process in ferrofluid systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10257v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinxiang Zhou, Liming Yang, Yaping Wang, Jie Wu, Xiaodong Niu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-similar scaling of variable-density Rayleigh-Taylor turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10512v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dynamics of self-similar Rayleigh-Taylor (RT) mixing layers are investigated across a broad range of Atwood and Reynolds numbers using the statistically stationary Rayleigh-Taylor (SRT) flow configuration - a computational framework that enables simulation of self-similar RT flows at reduced cost compared to conventional temporally growing mixing layers. Normalizations are developed for all dominant non-transport terms in the continuity, mixed mass, and turbulent kinetic energy budgets in terms of the input parameters: the mixing layer height $h$, gravitational acceleration $g$, and fluid densities $\rho_H$ and $\rho_L$. Most normalized quantities collapse well across the parameter space. In some cases, variations in the Atwood number $A$ (or equivalently, the density ratio $R$) lead to consistent integral magnitudes but spatially shifted profiles. These shifts are primarily related to a division by density and are similarly observed in the analytical solution of the one-dimensional variable-density diffusion problem. The analysis introduces a reference density for the mixed mass, examines trends in Favre-averaged statistics, and derives a scaling law for the growth rate of the mixing layer. For height definitions encompassing the full extent of the layer, the conventional growth parameter, $\alpha = \dot{h}^2/4Agh$, varies with Atwood number. Our analysis leads to an alternative formulation using an effective Atwood number, $A^*= (\ln R)/2$, that is consistent with the scaling proposed by Belen'kii &amp; Fradkin (Trudy FIAN, vol. 29, 1965, pp. 207-238). The corresponding growth parameter, $\alpha^*=\dot{h}^2/4A^*gh$, remains nearly constant across all Atwood numbers considered, offering a unified scaling for variable-density RT flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10512v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chian Yeh Goh, Daniel Brito Matehuala, Guillaume Blanquart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-organisation through layering of $\beta$-plane like turbulence in plasmas and geophysical fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10438v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Staircase formation and layering is studied in simplified, potential vorticity conserving models of plasmas and geophysical fluids, by investigating turbulent self-organisation and nonlinear saturation with different mechanisms of free energy production -- forcing or linear instability -- and with standard or modified zonal flow responses. To this end, staircase formation in both the standard and modified Charney-Hasegawa-Mima equations with stochastic forcing, along with two different simple instability driven models -- one from a plasma and from a geophysical context -- are studied and compared. In these studies, it is observed that $\beta$-plane turbulence that does not distinguish between zonal and non-zonal perturbations (i.e., standard zonal response) gradually forms large-scale, elliptic zonal structures that merge progressively, regardless of whether it is driven by forcing (though it should be slow enough to allow wave couplings) or by the baroclinic instability, using for example a two-layer model. Conversely, the plasma system, with its modified zonal response, can rapidly form straight, stationary jets of well-defined size, again regardless of the way it is driven: by stochastic forcing or by the dissipative drift instability. Furthermore, the instability-driven plasma system exhibits a phase transition between a zonal flow dominated state and an eddy dominated state. In both states, saturation is possible without large-scale friction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10438v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. L. Guillon, G. Dif-Pradalier, Y. Sarazin, D. W. Hughes, \"O. D. G\"urcan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning parameter-dependent shear viscosity from data, with application to sea and land ice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10452v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Complex physical systems which exhibit fluid-like behavior are often modeled as non-Newtonian fluids. A crucial element of a non-Newtonian model is the rheology, which relates inner stresses with strain-rates. We propose a framework for inferring rheological models from data that represents the fluid's effective viscosity with a neural network. By writing the rheological law in terms of tensor invariants and tailoring the network's properties, the inferred model satisfies key physical and mathematical properties, such as isotropic frame-indifference and existence of a convex potential of dissipation. Within this framework, we propose two approaches to learning a fluid's rheology: 1) a standard regression that fits the rheological model to stress data and 2) a PDE-constrained optimization method that infers rheological models from velocity data. For the latter approach, we combine finite element and machine learning libraries. We demonstrate the accuracy and robustness of our method on land and sea ice rheologies which also depend on external parameters. For land ice, we infer the temperature-dependent Glen's law and, for sea ice, the concentration-dependent shear component of the viscous-plastic model. For these two models, we explore the effects of large data errors. Finally, we infer an unknown concentration-dependent model that reproduces Lagrangian ice floe simulation data. Our method discovers a rheology that generalizes well outside of the training dataset and exhibits both shear-thickening and thinning behaviors depending on the concentrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10452v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gonzalo G. de Diego, Georg Stadler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pore-scale imaging of hydrogen and methane storage in fractured aquifer rock: The impact of gas type on relative permeability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14122v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Underground hydrogen storage in saline aquifers is a potential solution for seasonal renewable energy storage. Among potential storage sites, facilities used for underground natural gas storage have advantages, including well-characterized cyclical injection-withdrawal behavior and partially reusable infrastructure. However, the differences between hydrogen-brine and natural gas-brine flow, particularly through fractures in the reservoir and the sealing caprock, remain unclear due to the complexity of two-phase flow. Therefore, we investigate fracture relative permeability for hydrogen versus methane (natural gas) and nitrogen (commonly used in laboratories). Steady-state relative permeability experiments were conducted at 10 MPa on fractured carbonate rock from the Loenhout natural gas storage in Belgium, where gas flows through {\textmu}m-to-mm scale fractures. Our results reveal that the hydrogen exhibits similar relative permeability curves to methane, but both are significantly lower than those measured for nitrogen. This implies that nitrogen cannot reliably serve as a proxy for hydrogen at typical reservoir pressures. The low relative permeabilities for hydrogen and methane indicate strong fluid phase interference, which traditional relative permeability models fail to capture. This is supported by our observation of periodic pressure fluctuations associated with intermittent fluid connectivity for hydrogen and methane. In conclusion, our findings suggest that the fundamental flow properties of fractured rocks are complex but relatively similar for hydrogen and natural gas. This is an important insight for predictive modeling of the conversion of Loenhout and similar natural gas storage facilities, which is crucial to evaluate their hydrogen storage efficiency and integrity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14122v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.advwatres.2025.105109</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advances in Water Resources 2025, 206, 105109</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sojwal Manoorkar, G\"ulce Kalyoncu, Hamdi Omar, Soetkin Barbaix, Dominique Ceursters, Maxime Latinis, Stefanie Van Offenwert, Tom Bultreys</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well-posedness of the Euler equations in a stably stratified ocean in isopycnal coordinates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13263v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article is concerned with the well-posedness of the incompressible Euler equations describing a stably stratified ocean, reformulated in isopycnal coordinates. Our motivation for using this reformulation is twofold: first, its quasi-2D structure renders some parts of the analysis easier. Second, it closes a gap between the analysis performed in the paper by Bianchini and Duch{\^e}ne in 2022 in isopycnal coordinates, with shear velocity but with a regularizing term, and the analysis performed in the paper by Desjardins, Lannes, Saut in 2020 in Eulerian coordinates, without any regularizing term but without shear velocity. Our main result is a local well-posedness result in Sobolev spaces on the system in isopycnal coordinates, with shear velocity, without any regularizing term. The time of existence that we obtain is uniform with respect to the size $\epsilon$ of the perturbation, and boils down to the large time $1/\epsilon$ with the assumptions of the paper by Desjardins, Lannes, Saut in 2020. With additional assumptions, it is also uniform in the shallow-water parameter. The main difficulty consists in transposing to the isopycnal reformulation the symmetric structure of the system which is more straightforward in Eulerian coordinates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13263v4</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Th\'eo Fradin (IMB)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-level, high-resolution ocean modeling at all scales with Oceananigans</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14148v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We describe the user interface, governing equations, and numerical methods underpinning the community ocean modeling software called "Oceananigans". Oceananigans development has been lead by the Climate Modeling Alliance to build a trainable climate model with quantifiable uncertainty. Oceananigans is written in the Julia programming language, which, like similar recent efforts based on modern programming languages, distinguishes it from usual software based on Fortran. Oceananigans can efficiently simulate all scales of ocean motion, ranging from millimeter-scale turbulence in a small box to planetary-scale ocean circulation. Oceananigans design combines (i) a basic structured finite volume algorithm (ii) optimized for high-resolution simulations on GPUs which is (iii) exposed behind a high-level, programmable user interface. This design negotiates a dual mandate for highest-possible performance (to support state-of-the-art applications) and enhanced accessibility (to facilitate adoption and development). The dual mandate aims ultimately to accelerate the progress of Earth system science. Achieving this aim, however, requires a substantial and sustained increase in the collective effort of Oceananigans development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14148v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregory L. Wagner, Simone Silvestri, Navid C. Constantinou, Ali Ramadhan, Jean-Michel Campin, Chris Hill, Tomas Chor, Jago Strong-Wright, Xin Kai Lee, Francis Poulin, Andre Souza, Keaton J. Burns, Siddhartha Bishnu, John Marshall, Raffaele Ferrari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving the robustness of the immersed interface method through regularized velocity reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.03929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.03929v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Robust, broadly applicable fluid-structure interaction (FSI) algorithms remain a challenge for computational mechanics. In previous work, we introduced an immersed interface method (IIM) for discrete surfaces and an extension based on an immersed Lagrangia-Eulerian (ILE) coupling strategy for modeling FSI involving complex geometries. The ability of the method to sharply resolve stress discontinuities induced by singular immersed boundary forces in the presence of low-regularity geometrical representations makes it a compelling choice for three-dimensional modeling of complex geometries in diverse engineering applications. Although the IIM we previously introduced offers many desirable advantages, it also imposes a restrictive mesh factor ratio, requiring the surface mesh to be coarser than the fluid grid to ensure stability. This is because when the mesh factor ratio constraint is not satisfied, parts of the structure motion are not controlled by the discrete FSI system. This constraint can significantly increase computational costs, particularly in applications involving multiscale geometries with highly localized complexity or fine-scale features. To address this limitation, we devise a stabilization strategy for the velocity restriction operator inspired by Tikhonov regularization. This study demonstrates that using a stabilized velocity restriction operator in IIM enables a broader range of structure-to-fluid grid-size ratios without compromising accuracy or altering the flow dynamics. This advancement significantly broadens the applicability of the method to real-world FSI problems involving complex geometries and dynamic conditions, offering a robust and practical solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.03929v3</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Sun, Ebrahim M. Kolahdouz, Boyce E. Griffith</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
