<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-fin.PM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.PM</link>
    <description>q-fin.PM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-fin.PM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 04:00:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Semiparametric Dynamic Copula Models for Portfolio Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12266v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The mean-variance portfolio model, based on the risk-return trade-off for optimal asset allocation, remains foundational in portfolio optimization. However, its reliance on restrictive assumptions about asset return distributions limits its applicability to real-world data. Parametric copula structures provide a novel way to overcome these limitations by accounting for asymmetry, heavy tails, and time-varying dependencies. Existing methods have been shown to rely on fixed or static dependence structures, thus overlooking the dynamic nature of the financial market. In this study, a semiparametric model is proposed that combines non-parametrically estimated copulas with parametrically estimated marginals to allow all parameters to dynamically evolve over time. A novel framework was developed that integrates time-varying dependence modeling with flexible empirical beta copula structures. Marginal distributions were modeled using the Skewed Generalized T family. This effectively captures asymmetry and heavy tails and makes the model suitable for predictive inferences in real world scenarios. Furthermore, the model was applied to rolling windows of financial returns from the USA, India and Hong Kong economies to understand the influence of dynamic market conditions. The approach addresses the limitations of models that rely on parametric assumptions. By accounting for asymmetry, heavy tails, and cross-correlated asset prices, the proposed method offers a robust solution for optimizing diverse portfolios in an interconnected financial market. Through adaptive modeling, it allows for better management of risk and return across varying economic conditions, leading to more efficient asset allocation and improved portfolio performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12266v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PM</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Savita Pareek, Sujit K. Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal portfolios in continuous time: a model-free approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11881v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We provide a simple and straightforward approach to a continuous-time version of Cover's universal portfolio strategies within the model-free context of F\"ollmer's pathwise It\^o calculus. We establish the existence of the universal portfolio strategy and prove that its portfolio value process is the average of all values of constant rebalanced strategies. This result relies on a systematic comparison between two alternative descriptions of self-financing trading strategies within pathwise It\^o calculus. We moreover provide a comparison result for the performance and the realized volatility and variance of constant rebalanced portfolio strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11881v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.PM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiyue Han, Alexander Schied</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Black-Litterman</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18822v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Black-Litterman model is a framework for incorporating forward-looking expert views in a portfolio optimization problem. Existing work focuses almost exclusively on single-period problems with the forecast horizon matching that of the investor. We consider a generalization where the investor trades dynamically and views can be over horizons that differ from the investor. By exploiting the underlying graphical structure relating the asset prices and views, we derive the conditional distribution of asset returns when the price process is geometric Brownian motion, and show that it can be written in terms of a multi-dimensional Brownian bridge. The components of the Brownian bridge are dependent one-dimensional Brownian bridges with hitting times that are determined by the statistics of the price process and views. The new price process is an affine factor model with the conditional log-price process playing the role of a vector of factors. We derive an explicit expression for the optimal dynamic investment policy and analyze the hedging demand for changes in the new covariate. More generally, the paper shows that Bayesian graphical models are a natural framework for incorporating complex information structures in the Black-Litterman model. The connection between Brownian motion conditional on noisy observations of its terminal value and multi-dimensional Brownian bridge is novel and of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18822v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anas Abdelhakmi, Andrew Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
