<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DC</link>
    <description>cs.DC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 14:30:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Vec-LUT: Vector Table Lookup for Parallel Ultra-Low-Bit LLM Inference on Edge Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06443v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) are increasingly deployed on edge devices. To meet strict resource constraints, real-world deployment has pushed LLM quantization from 8-bit to 4-bit, 2-bit, and now 1.58-bit. Combined with lookup table (LUT)-based inference, CPUs run these ultra-low-bit LLMs even faster than NPUs, opening new opportunities for ubiquitous on-device intelligence.
  However, this paper identifies that LUT-based inference underutilizes memory bandwidth during parallel inference, which is required for prefilling, test-time scaling, and other multi-token scenarios. The root cause is the scalar LUT paradigm, which performs repetitive and non-contiguous memory accesses for each token.
  To solve the issue, we propose vector LUT, a new lookup paradigm that constructs a unified LUT across parallel tokens, and performs a single $1 \rightarrow N$ lookup per index. To realize it efficiently, we further introduce (1) Vector LUT-Centric Tensor Layout, and (2) Cache-Aware Streamed Lookup techniques. Evaluations on 5 edge devices across 3 LLMs show that Vec-LUT outperforms state-of-the-art baselines by up to $4.2\times$. Our implementation is integrated into llama.cpp. The code is available at https://github.com/Cipherxzc/vlut.cpp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06443v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangyu Li, Chengyu Yin, Weijun Wang, Jianyu Wei, Ting Cao, Yunxin Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable-MoE: Lyapunov-based Token Routing for Distributed Mixture-of-Experts Training over Edge Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06784v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The sparse activation mechanism of mixture of experts (MoE) model empowers edge intelligence with enhanced training efficiency and reduced computational resource consumption. However, traditional token routing in distributed MoE training faces significant challenges in resource-constrained edge networks characterized by heterogeneous computing capabilities and stochastic token arrivals, which inevitably suffer from workload backlog, resource inefficiency, and performance degradation. To address this issue, we propose a novel Lyapunov-based token routing framework for distributed MoE training over resource-heterogeneous edge networks, termed Stable-MoE. Specifically, we formulate a stochastic optimization problem to maximize both system throughput and gating consistency via optimizing the token routing strategy and computational resource allocation, while ensuring long-term stability of both token and energy queues at the edge devices. Using the Lyapunov optimization, we transform the intractable long-term optimization problem into tractable per-slot subproblems by enabling online decision-making of token routing and computation frequency utilization without the knowledge of future system states. Experimental results on the SVHN and CIFAR-100 datasets demonstrate that Stable-MoE outperforms the baselines with at least 40% and 5% gains in system throughput and test accuracy, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06784v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Long Shi, Bingyan Ou, Kang Wei, Weihao Zhu, Zhe Wang, Zhiyong Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cloud Revolution: Tracing the Origins and Rise of Cloud Computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06800v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The history behind the development of cloud computing is more than several decades of technological progress in the fields of virtualization, distributed systems, and high-speed networking, but its current application is much broader than the underlying technologies that made it possible. This paper reexamines the historical evolution of the field, including the initial ideas of resource sharing and utility-based computing approaches and the development of hyperscale data centers and modern globally federated cloud ecosystems. We also analyze the technological and economic forces and point to the way cloud platforms altered the organizational computing habits, decreasing the entrance-level to the data-intensive and computation-heavy apps. The study also takes into account the ongoing limitations which have come with the large-scale adoption of clouds which include exposure to security due to the weaknesses in configuration, particular establishment regulations, and structural reliance on the single vendors. Lastly, we address some of the new trends that are transforming the cloud environment, including the convergence of edge and cloud infrastructure, the increased prominence of AI-optimised architectures and the initial adoption of quantum computing services. Collectively, the developments above describe an emerging but quickly changing paradigm with its future direction being determined by a strike of balancing between scalability, openness, and trust.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06800v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deepa Gurung, S M Zia Ur Rashid, Zain ul Abdeen, Suman Rath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing video analytics inference pipelines: a case study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07009v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cost-effective and scalable video analytics are essential for precision livestock monitoring, where high-resolution footage and near-real-time monitoring needs from commercial farms generates substantial computational workloads. This paper presents a comprehensive case study on optimizing a poultry welfare monitoring system through system-level improvements across detection, tracking, clustering, and behavioral analysis modules. We introduce a set of optimizations, including multi-level parallelization, Optimizing code with substituting CPU code with GPU-accelerated code, vectorized clustering, and memory-efficient post-processing. Evaluated on real-world farm video footage, these changes deliver up to a 2x speedup across pipelines without compromising model accuracy. Our findings highlight practical strategies for building high-throughput, low-latency video inference systems that reduce infrastructure demands in agricultural and smart sensing deployments as well as other large-scale video analytics applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07009v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saeid Ghafouri, Yuming Ding, Katerine Diaz Chito, Jes\'us Martinez del Rinc\'on, Niamh O'Connell, Hans Vandierendonck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PIR-DSN: A Decentralized Storage Network Supporting Private Information Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07189v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Decentralized Storage Networks (DSNs) are emerging as a foundational infrastructure for Web 3.0, offering global peer-to-peer storage. However, a critical vulnerability persists: user privacy during file retrieval remains largely unaddressed, risking the exposure of sensitive information. To overcome this, we introduce PIR-DSN, the first DSN protocol to integrate Private Information Retrieval (PIR) for both single and multi-server settings. Our key innovations include a novel secure mapping method that transforms sparse file identifiers into compact integer indexes, enabling both public verifiability of file operations and efficient private retrieval. Furthermore, PIR-DSN guarantees Byzantine-robust private retrieval through file replication across multiple miners. We implement and rigorously evaluate PIR-DSN against three prominent industrial DSN systems. Experimental results demonstrate that PIR-DSN achieves comparable overhead for file upload and deletion. While PIR inherently introduces an additional computational cost leading to higher retrieval latency, PIR-DSN maintains comparable throughput. These findings underscore PIR-DSN's practical viability for privacy-sensitive applications within DSN environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07189v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahao Zhang, Minghui Xu, Hechuan Guo, Xiuzhen Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ContinuumConductor : Decentralized Process Mining on the Edge-Cloud Continuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07280v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Process mining traditionally assumes centralized event data collection and analysis. However, modern Industrial Internet of Things systems increasingly operate over distributed, resource-constrained edge-cloud infrastructures. This paper proposes a structured approach for decentralizing process mining by enabling event data to be mined directly within the IoT systems edge-cloud continuum. We introduce ContinuumConductor a layered decision framework that guides when to perform process mining tasks such as preprocessing, correlation, and discovery centrally or decentrally. Thus, enabling privacy, responsive and resource-efficient process mining. For each step in the process mining pipeline, we analyze the trade-offs of decentralization versus centralization across these layers and propose decision criteria. We demonstrate ContinuumConductor at a real-world use-case of process optimazition in inland ports. Our contributions lay the foundation for computing-aware process mining in cyber-physical and IIoT systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07280v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hendrik Reiter, Janick Edinger, Martin Kabierski, Agnes Koschmider, Olaf Landsiedel, Arvid Lepsien, Xixi Lu, Andrea Marrella, Estefania Serral, Stefan Schulte, Florian Tschorsch, Matthias Weidlich, Wilhelm Hasselbring</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Venus: An Efficient Edge Memory-and-Retrieval System for VLM-based Online Video Understanding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07344v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vision-language models (VLMs) have demonstrated impressive multimodal comprehension capabilities and are being deployed in an increasing number of online video understanding applications. While recent efforts extensively explore advancing VLMs' reasoning power in these cases, deployment constraints are overlooked, leading to overwhelming system overhead in real-world deployments. To address that, we propose Venus, an on-device memory-and-retrieval system for efficient online video understanding. Venus proposes an edge-cloud disaggregated architecture that sinks memory construction and keyframe retrieval from cloud to edge, operating in two stages. In the ingestion stage, Venus continuously processes streaming edge videos via scene segmentation and clustering, where the selected keyframes are embedded with a multimodal embedding model to build a hierarchical memory for efficient storage and retrieval. In the querying stage, Venus indexes incoming queries from memory, and employs a threshold-based progressive sampling algorithm for keyframe selection that enhances diversity and adaptively balances system cost and reasoning accuracy. Our extensive evaluation shows that Venus achieves a 15x-131x speedup in total response latency compared to state-of-the-art methods, enabling real-time responses within seconds while maintaining comparable or even superior reasoning accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07344v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shengyuan Ye, Bei Ouyang, Tianyi Qian, Liekang Zeng, Mu Yuan, Xiaowen Chu, Weijie Hong, Xu Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Communication-Efficient Serving for Video Diffusion Models with Latent Parallelism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07350v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Video diffusion models (VDMs) perform attention computation over the 3D spatio-temporal domain. Compared to large language models (LLMs) processing 1D sequences, their memory consumption scales cubically, necessitating parallel serving across multiple GPUs. Traditional parallelism strategies partition the computational graph, requiring frequent high-dimensional activation transfers that create severe communication bottlenecks. To tackle this issue, we exploit the local spatio-temporal dependencies inherent in the diffusion denoising process and propose Latent Parallelism (LP), the first parallelism strategy tailored for VDM serving. \textcolor{black}{LP decomposes the global denoising problem into parallelizable sub-problems by dynamically rotating the partitioning dimensions (temporal, height, and width) within the compact latent space across diffusion timesteps, substantially reducing the communication overhead compared to prevailing parallelism strategies.} To ensure generation quality, we design a patch-aligned overlapping partition strategy that matches partition boundaries with visual patches and a position-aware latent reconstruction mechanism for smooth stitching. Experiments on three benchmarks demonstrate that LP reduces communication overhead by up to 97\% over baseline methods while maintaining comparable generation quality. As a non-intrusive plug-in paradigm, LP can be seamlessly integrated with existing parallelism strategies, enabling efficient and scalable video generation services.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07350v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyuan Wu, Shuai Wang, Li Chen, Kaihui Gao, Dan Li, Yanyu Ren, Qiming Zhang, Yong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Otus Supercomputer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07401v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Otus is a high-performance computing cluster that was launched in 2025 and is operated by the Paderborn Center for Parallel Computing (PC2) at Paderborn University in Germany. The system is part of the National High Performance Computing (NHR) initiative. Otus complements the previous supercomputer Noctua 2, offering approximately twice the computing power while retaining the three node types that were characteristic of Noctua 2: 1) CPU compute nodes with different memory capacities, 2) high-end GPU nodes, and 3) HPC-grade FPGA nodes. On the Top500 list, which ranks the 500 most powerful supercomputers in the world, Otus is in position 164 with the CPU partition and in position 255 with the GPU partition (June 2025). On the Green500 list, ranking the 500 most energy-efficient supercomputers in the world, Otus is in position 5 with the GPU partition (June 2025).
  This article provides a comprehensive overview of the system in terms of its hardware, software, system integration, and its overall integration into the data center building to ensure energy-efficient operation. The article aims to provide unique insights for scientists using the system and for other centers operating HPC clusters. The article will be continuously updated to reflect the latest system setup and measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07401v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sadaf Ehtesabi, Manoar Hossain, Tobias Kenter, Andreas Krawinkel, Holger Nitsche, Lukas Ostermann, Christian Plessl, Heinrich Riebler, Stefan Rohde, Robert Schade, Michael Schwarz, Jens Simon, Nils Winnwa, Alex Wiens, Xin Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bandwidth-Aware Network Topology Optimization for Decentralized Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07536v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Network topology is critical for efficient parameter synchronization in distributed learning over networks. However, most existing studies do not account for bandwidth limitations in network topology design. In this paper, we propose a bandwidth-aware network topology optimization framework to maximize consensus speed under edge cardinality constraints. For heterogeneous bandwidth scenarios, we introduce a maximum bandwidth allocation strategy for the edges to ensure efficient communication among nodes. By reformulating the problem into an equivalent Mixed-Integer SDP problem, we leverage a computationally efficient ADMM-based method to obtain topologies that yield the maximum consensus speed. Within the ADMM substep, we adopt the conjugate gradient method to efficiently solve large-scale linear equations to achieve better scalability. Experimental results demonstrate that the resulting network topologies outperform the benchmark topologies in terms of consensus speed, and reduce the training time required for decentralized learning tasks on real-world datasets to achieve the target test accuracy, exhibiting speedups of more than $1.11\times$ and $1.21\times$ for homogeneous and heterogeneous bandwidth settings, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07536v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yipeng Shen, Zehan Zhu, Yan Huang, Changzhi Yan, Cheng Zhuo, Jinming Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Performance Analyzer for a Public Cloud's ML-Augmented VM Allocator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07750v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many operational cloud systems use one or more machine learning models that help them achieve better efficiency and performance. But operators do not have tools to help them understand how each model and the interaction between them affect the end-to-end system performance. SANJESH is such a tool. SANJESH supports a diverse set of performance-related queries which we answer through a bi-level optimization. We invent novel mechanisms to solve this optimization more quickly. These techniques allow us to solve an optimization which prior work failed to solve even after $24$ hours.
  As a proof of concept, we apply SANJESH to an example production system that uses multiple ML models to optimize virtual machine (VM) placement. These models impact how many servers the operators uses to host VMs and the frequency with which it has to live-migrate them because the servers run out of resources. SANJESH finds scenarios where these models cause $~4\times$ worse performance than what simulation-based approaches detect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07750v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roozbeh Bostandoost, Pooria Namyar, Siva Kesava Reddy Kakarla, Ryan Beckett, Santiago Segarra, Eli Cortez, Ankur Mallick, Kevin Hsieh, Rodrigo Fonseca, Mohammad Hajiesmaili, Behnaz Arzani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Designing Co-operation in Systems of Hierarchical, Multi-objective Schedulers for Stream Processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07792v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stream processing is a computing paradigm that supports real-time data processing for a wide variety of applications. At Meta, it's used across the company for various tasks such as deriving product insights, providing and improving user services, and enabling AI at scale for our ever-growing user base. Meta's current stream processing framework supports processing TerraBytes(TBs) of data in mere seconds. This is enabled by our efficient schedulers and multi-layered infrastructure, which allocate workloads across various compute resources, working together in hierarchies across various parts of the infrastructure. But with the ever growing complexity of applications, and user needs, areas of the infrastructure that previously required minimal load balancing, now must be made more robust and proactive to application load. In our work we explore how to build and design such a system that focuses on load balancing over key compute resources and properties of these applications. We also showcase how to integrate new schedulers into the hierarchy of the existing ones, allowing multiple schedulers to work together and perform load balancing, at their infrastructure level, effectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07792v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Animesh Dangwal, Yufeng Jiang, Charlie Arnold, Jun Fan, Mohamed Bassem, Aish Rajagopal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying the Carbon Reduction of DAG Workloads: A Job Shop Scheduling Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07799v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Carbon-aware schedulers aim to reduce the operational carbon footprint of data centers by running flexible workloads during periods of low carbon intensity. Most schedulers treat workloads as single monolithic tasks, ignoring that many jobs, like video encoding or offline inference, consist of smaller tasks with specific dependencies and resource needs; however, knowledge of this structure enables opportunities for greater carbon efficiency.
  We quantify the maximum benefit of a dependency-aware approach for batch workloads. We model the problem as a flexible job-shop scheduling variant and use an offline solver to compute upper bounds on carbon and energy savings. Results show up to $25\%$ lower carbon emissions on average without increasing the optimal makespan (total job completion time) compared to a makespan-only baseline. Although in heterogeneous server setup, these schedules may use more energy than energy-optimal ones. Our results also show that allowing twice the optimal makespan nearly doubles the carbon savings, underscoring the tension between carbon, energy, and makespan. We also highlight key factors such as job structure and server count influence the achievable carbon reductions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07799v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roozbeh Bostandoost, Adam Lechowicz, Walid A. Hanafy, Prashant Shenoy, Mohammad Hajiesmaili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A-3PO: Accelerating Asynchronous LLM Training with Staleness-aware Proximal Policy Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06547v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Decoupled loss has been a successful reinforcement learning (RL) algorithm to deal with the high data staleness under the asynchronous RL setting. Decoupled loss improves coupled-loss style of algorithms' (e.g., PPO, GRPO) learning stability by introducing a proximal policy to decouple the off-policy corrections (importance weight) from the controlling policy updates (trust region). However, the proximal policy requires an extra forward pass through the network at each training step, creating a computational bottleneck for large language models. We observe that since the proximal policy only serves as a trust region anchor between the behavior and target policies, we can approximate it through simple interpolation without explicit computation. We call this approach A-3PO (APproximated Proximal Policy Optimization). A-3PO eliminates this overhead, reducing training time by 18% while maintaining comparable performance. Code &amp; off-the-shelf example are available at: https://github.com/inclusionAI/AReaL/blob/main/docs/algorithms/prox_approx.md</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06547v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaocan Li, Shiliang Wu, Zheng Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Chunked-Object Pattern for Multi-Region Large Payload Storage in Managed NoSQL Databases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.06852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.06852v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many managed key-value and NoSQL databases - such as Amazon DynamoDB, Azure Cosmos DB, and Google Cloud Firestore - enforce strict maximum item sizes (e.g., 400 KB in DynamoDB). This constraint imposes significant architectural challenges for applications requiring low-latency, multi-region access to objects that exceed these limits. The standard industry recommendation is to offload payloads to object storage (e.g., Amazon S3) while retaining a pointer in the database. While cost-efficient, this "pointer pattern" introduces network overhead and exposes applications to non-deterministic replication lag between the database and the object store, creating race conditions in active-active architectures.
  This paper presents a "chunked-object" pattern that persists large logical entities as sets of ordered chunks within the database itself. We precisely define the pattern and provide a reference implementation using Amazon DynamoDB Global Tables. The design generalizes to any key-value store with per-item size limits and multi-region replication. We evaluate the approach using telemetry from a production system processing over 200,000 transactions per hour. Results demonstrate that the chunked-object pattern eliminates cross-system replication lag hazards and reduces p99 cross-region time-to-consistency for 1 MB payloads by keeping data and metadata within a single consistency domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.06852v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manideep Reddy Chinthareddy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DCO: Dynamic Cache Orchestration for LLM Accelerators through Predictive Management</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07312v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rapid adoption of large language models (LLMs) is pushing AI accelerators toward increasingly powerful and specialized designs. Instead of further complicating software development with deeply hierarchical scratchpad memories (SPMs) and their asynchronous management, we investigate the opposite point of the design spectrum: a multi-core AI accelerator equipped with a shared system-level cache and application-aware management policies, which keeps the programming effort modest. Our approach exploits dataflow information available in the software stack to guide cache replacement (including dead-block prediction), in concert with bypass decisions and mechanisms that alleviate cache thrashing.
  We assess the proposal using a cycle-accurate simulator and observe substantial performance gains (up to 1.80x speedup) compared with conventional cache architectures. In addition, we build and validate an analytical model that takes into account the actual overlapping behaviors to extend the measurement results of our policies to real-world larger-scale workloads. Experiment results show that when functioning together, our bypassing and thrashing mitigation strategies can handle scenarios both with and without inter-core data sharing and achieve remarkable speedups.
  Finally, we implement the design in RTL and the area of our design is $\mathbf{0.064mm^2}$ with 15nm process, which can run at 2 GHz clock frequency. Our findings explore the potential of the shared cache design to assist the development of future AI accelerator systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07312v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongchun Zhou, Chengtao Lai, Yuhang Gu, Wei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Adaptive Multi-Layered Honeynet Architecture for Threat Behavior Analysis via Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.07827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.07827v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The escalating sophistication and variety of cyber threats have rendered static honeypots inadequate, necessitating adaptive, intelligence-driven deception. In this work, ADLAH is introduced: an Adaptive Deep Learning Anomaly Detection Honeynet designed to maximize high-fidelity threat intelligence while minimizing cost through autonomous orchestration of infrastructure. The principal contribution is offered as an end-to-end architectural blueprint and vision for an AI-driven deception platform. Feasibility is evidenced by a functional prototype of the central decision mechanism, in which a reinforcement learning (RL) agent determines, in real time, when sessions should be escalated from low-interaction sensor nodes to dynamically provisioned, high-interaction honeypots. Because sufficient live data were unavailable, field-scale validation is not claimed; instead, design trade-offs and limitations are detailed, and a rigorous roadmap toward empirical evaluation at scale is provided. Beyond selective escalation and anomaly detection, the architecture pursues automated extraction, clustering, and versioning of bot attack chains, a core capability motivated by the empirical observation that exposed services are dominated by automated traffic. Together, these elements delineate a practical path toward cost-efficient capture of high-value adversary behavior, systematic bot versioning, and the production of actionable threat intelligence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.07827v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Johannes M\"oller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Redox: Improving I/O Efficiency of Model Training Through File Redirection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16280v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes Redox, a training data management system designed to achieve high I/O efficiency. The key insight is a new observation of file redirection: for model training, when training data in one file is requested, the system has the flexibility to return the data of another file. Based on this property, Redox starts with a bold design principle that chunks of data files are always read from disk in batch, and once loaded, all files in the chunk will be consumed without being loaded again. We propose efficient local and distributed file read protocol based on this principle that both minimizes the wasted data read and enables opportunistic prefetch from remote node. Moreover, we analyze file redirection's impact on randomness, and show that it has little effects on training efficiency. Experimental results indicate that Redox significantly accelerates data fetching in training, achieving up to a 4.57x improvement in end-to-end training compared to PyTorch.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16280v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuhao Li, Xuanhua Shi, Yunfei Zhao, Yongluan Zhou, Yusheng Hua, Xuehai Qian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aurora: Architecting Argonne's First Exascale Supercomputer for Accelerated Scientific Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08207v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Aurora is Argonne National Laboratory's pioneering Exascale supercomputer, designed to accelerate scientific discovery with cutting-edge architectural innovations. Key new technologies include the Intel(TM) Xeon(TM) Data Center GPU Max Series (code-named Sapphire Rapids) with support for High Bandwidth Memory (HBM), alongside the Intel(TM) Data Center GPU Max Series (code-named Ponte Vecchio) on each compute node. Aurora also integrates the Distributed Asynchronous Object Storage (DAOS), a novel exascale storage solution, and leverages Intel's oneAPI programming environment. This paper presents an in-depth exploration of Aurora's node architecture, the HPE Slingshot interconnect, the supporting software ecosystem, and DAOS. We provide insights into standard benchmark performance and applications readiness efforts via Aurora's Early Science Program and the Exascale Computing Project.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08207v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William E. Allcock, Benjamin S. Allen, James Anchell, Victor Anisimov, Thomas Applencourt, Abhishek Bagusetty, Ramesh Balakrishnan, Riccardo Balin, Solomon Bekele, Colleen Bertoni, Cyrus Blackworth, Renzo Bustamante, Kevin Canada, John Carrier, Christopher Chan-nui, Lance C. Cheney, Taylor Childers, Paul Coffman, Susan Coghlan, Tanima Dey, Michael D'Mello, Ashok Emani, Murali Emani, Kyle G. Felker, Sam Foreman, Olivier Franza, Longfei Gao, Marta Garc\'ia, Mar\'ia Garzar\'an, Balazs Gerofi, Yasaman Ghadar, Subrata Goswami, Neha Gupta, Kevin Harms, V\"ain\"o Hatanp\"a\"a, Brian Holland, Carissa Holohan, Brian Homerding, Khalid Hossain, Xue Hu, Louise Huot, Huda Ibeid, Joseph A. Insley, Sai Jayanthi, Hong Jiang, Wei Jiang, Xiao-Yong Jin, Jeongnim Kim, Christopher Knight, Panagiotis Kourdis, Kalyan Kumaran, JaeHyuk Kwack, Janghaeng Lee, Ti Leggett, Ben Lenard, Chris Lewis, Nevin Liber, Johann Lombardi, Raymond M. Loy, Ye Luo, Bethany Lusch, Nilakantan Mahadevan, Beth Markey, Victor A. Mateevitsi, Gordon McPheeters, Ryan Milner, Jerome Mitchell, Vitali A. Morozov, Servesh Muralidharan, Tom Musta, Mrigendra Nagar, Vikram Narayana, Marieme Ngom, Anthony-Trung Nguyen, Nathan Nichols, Aditya Nishtala, James C. Osborn, Michael E. Papka, Scott Parker, Saumil S. Patel, Julia Piotrowska, Adrian C. Pope, Sucheta Raghunanda, Esteban Rangel, Paul M. Rich, Katherine M. Riley, Silvio Rizzi, Kris Rowe, Varuni Sastry, Adam Scovel, Filippo Simini, Haritha Siddabathuni Som, Patrick Steinbrecher, Rick Stevens, Xinmin Tian, Peter Upton, Thomas Uram, Archit K. Vasan, \'Alvaro V\'azquez-Mayagoitia, Kaushik Velusamy, Brice Videau, Venkatram Vishwanath, Brian Whitney, Timothy J. Williams, Michael Woodacre, Sam Zeltner, Chuanjun Zhang, Gengbin Zheng, Huihuo Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From GPUs to RRAMs: Distributed In-Memory Primal-Dual Hybrid Gradient Method for Solving Large-Scale Linear Optimization Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21137v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The exponential growth of computational workloads is surpassing the capabilities of conventional architectures, which are constrained by fundamental limits. In-memory computing (IMC) with RRAM provides a promising alternative by providing analog computations with significant gains in latency and energy use. However, existing algorithms developed for conventional architectures do not translate to IMC, particularly for constrained optimization problems where frequent matrix reprogramming remains cost-prohibitive for IMC applications. Here we present a distributed in-memory primal-dual hybrid gradient (PDHG) method, specifically co-designed for arrays of RRAM devices. Our approach minimizes costly write cycles, incorporates robustness against device non-idealities, and leverages a symmetric block-matrix formulation to unify operations across distributed crossbars. We integrate a physics-based simulation framework called MELISO+ to evaluate performance under realistic device conditions. Benchmarking against GPU-accelerated solvers on large-scale linear programs demonstrates that our RRAM-based solver achieves comparable accuracy with up to three orders of magnitude reductions in energy consumption and latency. These results demonstrate the first PDHG-based LP solver implemented on RRAMs, showcasing the transformative potential of algorithm-hardware co-design for solving large-scale optimization through distributed in-memory computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21137v3</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huynh Q. N. Vo, Md Tawsif Rahman Chowdhury, Paritosh Ramanan, Gozde Tutuncuoglu, Junchi Yang, Feng Qiu, Murat Yildirim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elastic Data Transfer Optimization with Hybrid Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06159v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Modern scientific data acquisition generates petabytes of data that must be transferred to geographically distant computing clusters. Conventional tools either rely on preconfigured sessions, which are difficult to tune for users without domain expertise, or they adaptively optimize only concurrency while ignoring other important parameters. We present \name, an adaptive data transfer method that jointly considers multiple parameters. Our solution incorporates heuristic-based parallelism, infinite pipelining, and a deep reinforcement learning based concurrency optimizer. To make agent training practical, we introduce a lightweight network simulator that reduces training time to less than four minutes and provides a $2750\times$ speedup compared to online training. Experimental evaluation shows that \name consistently outperforms existing methods across diverse datasets, achieving up to 9.5x higher throughput compared to state-of-the-art solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06159v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rasman Mubtasim Swargo, Md Arifuzzaman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combining Serverless and High-Performance Computing Paradigms to support ML Data-Intensive Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12185v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Data is found everywhere, from health and human infrastructure to the surge of sensors and the proliferation of internet-connected devices. To meet this challenge, the data engineering field has expanded significantly in recent years in both research and industry. Traditionally, data engineering, Machine Learning, and AI workloads have been run on large clusters within data center environments, requiring substantial investment in hardware and maintenance. With the rise of the public cloud, it is now possible to run large applications across nodes without owning or maintaining hardware. Serverless functions such as AWS Lambda provide horizontal scaling and precise billing without the hassle of managing traditional cloud infrastructure. However, when processing large datasets, users often rely on external storage options that are significantly slower than direct communication typical of HPC clusters. We introduce Cylon, a high-performance distributed data frame solution that has shown promising results for data processing using Python. We describe how we took inspiration from the FMI library and designed a serverless communicator to tackle communication and performance issues associated with serverless functions. With our design, we demonstrate that the performance of AWS Lambda falls below one percent of strong scaling experiments compared to serverful AWS (EC2) and HPCs based on implementing direct communication via NAT Traversal TCP Hole Punching.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12185v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mills Staylor, Arup Kumar Sarker, Gregor von Laszewski, Geoffrey Fox, Yue Cheng, Judy Fox</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Are Bus-Mounted Edge Servers Feasible?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05543v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Placement of edge servers is the prerequisite of provisioning edge computing services for Internet of Vehicles (IoV). Fixed-site edge servers at Road Side Units (RSUs) or base stations are able to offer basic service coverage for end users, i.e., vehicles on road. However, the server locations and capacity are fixed after deployment, rendering their inefficiency in handling spationtemporal user dynamics. Mobile servers such as buses, on the other hand, have the potential of adding computation elasticity to such system. To this end, this paper studies the feasibility of bus-mounted edge servers based on real traces. First, we investigate the coverage of the buses and base stations using the Shanghai bus/taxi/Telecom datasets, which shows a great potential of bus-based edge servers as they cover a great portion of geographic area and demand points. Next, we build a mathematical model and design a simple greedy heuristic algorithm to select a limited number of buses that maximizes the coverage of demand points, i.e., with a limited purchase budget. We perform trace-driven simulations to verify the performance of the proposed bus selection algorithm. The results show that our approach effectively handles the dynamic user demand under realistic constraints such as server capacity and purchase quantity. Thus, we claim: bus-mounted edge servers for vehicular networks in urban areas are feasible, beneficial, and valuable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05543v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuezhi Li, Jiancong He, Ming Xie, Xuyang Chen, Le Chang, Li Jiang, Gui Gui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SDT-GNN: Streaming-based Distributed Training Framework for Graph Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02300v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, distributed GNN training frameworks, such as DistDGL and PyG, have been developed to enable training GNN models on large graphs by leveraging multiple GPUs in a distributed manner. Despite these advances, their memory requirements are still excessively high, thereby hindering GNN training on large graphs using commodity workstations. In this paper, we propose SDT-GNN, a streaming-based distributed GNN training framework. Unlike the existing frameworks that load the entire graph in memory, it takes a stream of edges as input for graph partitioning to reduce the memory requirement for partitioning. It also enables distributed GNN training even when the aggregated memory size of GPUs is smaller than the size of the graph and feature data. Furthermore, to improve the quality of partitioning, we propose SPRING, a novel streaming partitioning algorithm for distributed GNN training. We demonstrate the effectiveness and efficiency of SDT-GNN on seven large public datasets. SDT-GNN has up to 95% less memory footprint than DistDGL and PyG without sacrificing the prediction accuracy. SPRING also outperforms state-of-the-art streaming partitioning algorithms significantly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02300v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Huang, Weipeng Zhuo, Minh Phu Vuong, Shiju Li, Jongryool Kim, Bradley Rees, Chul-Ho Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
