<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT</link>
    <description>math.GT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 May 2024 04:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A construction of homotopically non-trivial embedded spheres for hyperplane arrangements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the notion of locally consistent system of half-spaces for a real hyperplane arrangement. We embed a sphere in the complexified complement by shifting the real unit sphere into the imaginary direction indicated by the half-spaces. We then prove that the sphere is homotopically trivial if and only if the system of half-spaces is globally consistent. To prove its non-triviality, we compute the twisted intersection number of the sphere with a specific, explicitly constructed twisted Borel-Moore cycle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20010v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahiko Yoshinaga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast Algorithm for Multiplication on the Skein Algebra of One-hole Torus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20159v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Kauffman bracket skein algebra of a surface is a generalization of the Jones polynomial invariant for links and plays a principal role in the Witten-Reshetikhin- Turaev topological quantum field theory. However, the multiplicative structure of the skein algebra is not well understood, with a priori exponential complexity. We consider the case of one-hole torus, and provide a polynomial algorithm for computing multiplication of any two skein elements. Some closed form formulas for multiplication of curves with low crossing number are also given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20159v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sike Wang, Helen Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bandwidth and focal radius with positive isotropic curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20129v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates quantitative metric inequalities for manifolds with positive isotropic curvature (PIC). Our results include upper bounds on the bandwidth and focal radius of hypersurfaces in PIC manifolds, contingent on boundary convexities and Betti numbers. The proof is based on exploiting the spectral properties of a twisted de Rham-Hodge operator on manifolds with boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20129v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsz-Kiu Aaron Chow, Jingze Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embedding calculus and grope cobordism of knots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.05120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2010.05120v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that embedding calculus invariants $ev_n$ are surjective for long knots in an arbitrary $3$-manifold. This solves some remaining open cases of Goodwillie--Klein--Weiss connectivity estimates, and at the same time confirms one half of the conjecture that for classical knots $ev_n$ are universal additive Vassiliev invariants over the integers. In addition, we give a sufficient condition for this conjecture to hold over a coefficient group, which is by recent results of Boavida de Brito and Horel fulfilled for the rationals and for the $p$-adic integers in a range. Therefore, embedding calculus invariants are strictly more powerful than the Kontsevich integral.
  Furthermore, our work shows they are more computable as well. Namely, the main theorem computes the first possibly non-vanishing invariant $ev_n$ of a knot which is grope cobordant to the unknot to be precisely equal to the equivalence class of the underlying decorated tree of the grope in the associated graph complex. Actually, our techniques apply beyond dimension $3$, offering a description of the layers in embedding calculus for long knots in a manifold of any dimension, and suggesting that certain generalised gropes realise the corresponding graph complex classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2010.05120v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Danica Kosanovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisted local wild mapping class groups: configuration spaces, fission trees and complex braids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.12695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.12695v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Following the completion of the algebraic construction of the Poisson wild character varieties (B.--Yamakawa, 2015) one can consider their natural deformations, generalising both the mapping class group actions on the usual (tame) character varieties, and the G-braid groups already known to occur in the wild/irregular setting. Here we study these wild mapping class groups in the case of arbitrary formal structure in type A. As we will recall, this story is most naturally phrased in terms of admissible deformations of wild Riemann surfaces. The main results are: 1) the construction of configuration spaces containing all possible local deformations, 2) the definition of a combinatorial object, the ``fission forest'', of any wild Riemann surface and a proof that it gives a sharp parameterisation of all the admissible deformation classes. As an application of 1), by considering basic examples, we show that the braid groups of all the complex reflection groups known as the generalised symmetric groups appear as wild mapping class groups. As an application of 2), we compute the dimensions of all the (global) moduli spaces of type A wild Riemann surfaces (in fixed admissible deformation classes), a generalisation of the famous ``Riemann's count'' of the dimensions of the moduli spaces of compact Riemann surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.12695v5</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Boalch, Jean Dou\c{c}ot, Gabriele Rembado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological 5d $\mathcal {N} = 2$ Gauge Theory: Novel Floer Homologies, their Dualities, and an $A_\infty$-category of Three-Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.18302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.18302v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show how one can define novel gauge-theoretic Floer homologies of four, three and two-manifolds from the physics of a certain topologically-twisted 5d ${\cal N}=2$ gauge theory via its supersymmetric quantum mechanics interpretation. They are associated with Vafa-Witten, Hitchin and $G_{\mathbb{C}}$-BF configurations on the four, three and two-manifolds, respectively. We also show how one can define novel symplectic Floer homologies of Hitchin spaces, which in turn will allow us to derive novel Atiyah-Floer correspondences that relate our gauge-theoretic Floer homologies to symplectic intersection Floer homologies of Higgs bundles. Furthermore, topological invariance and 5d "S-duality" suggest a web of relations and a Langlands duality amongst these novel Floer homologies and their loop/toroidal group generalizations. Last but not least, via a 2d gauged Landau-Ginzburg model interpretation of the 5d theory, we derive, from the soliton string theory that it defines and the 5d partition function, a Fukaya-Seidel type $A_\infty$-category of Hitchin configurations on three-manifolds and its novel Atiyah-Floer correspondence. Our work therefore furnishes purely physical proofs and generalizations of the mathematical conjectures of Haydys [1], Abouzaid-Manolescu [2], and Bousseau [3], and more.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.18302v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arif Er, Zhi-Cong Ong, Meng-Chwan Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-commutative divergence and the Turaev cobracket</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16566v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The divergence map, an important ingredient in the algebraic description of the Turaev cobracket on a connected oriented compact surface with boundary, is reformulated in the context of non-commutative geometry using a flat connection on the space of 1-forms on a formally smooth associative algebra. We then extend this construction to the case of associative algebras with any finite cohomological dimension, which allows us to give a similar algebraic description of the Turaev cobracket on a closed surface. We also look into a relation between the Satoh trace and the divergence map on a free Lie algebra via geometry over Lie operad.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16566v4</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Toyo Taniguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on the finitely generated fixed subgroup property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12824v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study when a group of form $G\times\mathbb{Z}^m (m\geq 1)$ has the finitely generated fixed subgroup property of automorphisms ($\rm{FGFP}_a$), by using the BNS-invariant, and provide some partial answers and non-trivial examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12824v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jialin Lei, Jiming Ma, Qiang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Salter's question on the image of the Burau representation of $B_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.16607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.16607v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In 1974, Birman posed the question of under what conditions a matrix with Laurent polynomial entries is in the image of the Burau representation. In 1984, Squier observed that the matrices in the image are contained in a unitary group. In 2021, Salter formulated a specific question: whether the central quotient of the Burau image group is the central quotient of a certain subgroup of the unitary group. We solve this question negatively in the simplest nontrivial case, $n=3$, algorithmically constructing a counterexample.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.16607v3</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donsung Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
