<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT</link>
    <description>math.GT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 04:00:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Real monopoles and a spectral sequence from Khovanov homology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00152v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a based link $(K,p)$, we define a "tilde"-version $\tilde{HMR}(K,p)$ of real monopole Floer homology and prove an unoriented skein exact triangle. We show the Euler characteristic of $\tilde{HMR}(K,p)$ is equal to Miyazawa's invariant $|deg(K)|$ arXiv:2312.02041 and examine some examples. Further, we construct a spectral sequence over $\mathbb{F}_2$ abutting to $\tilde{HMR}(K,p)$, whose $E_2$ page is the reduced Khovanov homology $Khr(\overline{K})$ of the mirror link $\overline{K}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00152v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiakai Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>McDuff's secondary class and the Euler class of foliated sphere bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00896v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Tsuboi proved that the Calabi invariant of the closed disk transgresses to the Euler class of foliated circle bundles and suggested looking for its higher-dimensional analog. In this paper, we construct a cohomology class of the group of volume-preserving diffeomorphisms of a real-cohomologically acyclic manifold with sphere boundary, which is closely related to McDuff's secondary class, and prove that this cohomology class transgresses to the Euler class of foliated sphere bundles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00896v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuhei Maruyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of generalized Alexander quandles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01074v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to provide a new characterization of isomorphism classes of generalized Alexander quandles in terms of the underlying groups and their automorphisms. This extends the previous result [4, Theorem 1.4]. Additionally, we compute the number of generalized Alexander quandles up to quandle isomorphism arising from groups up to order 127 and their group automorphisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01074v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akihiro Higashitani, Seiichi Kamada, Jin Kosaka, Hirotake Kurihara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Primitive Feynman diagrams and the rational Goussarov--Habiro Lie algebra of string links</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Goussarov-Habiro's theory of clasper surgeries defines a filtration of the monoid of string links $L(m)$ on $m$ strands, in a way that geometrically realizes the Feynman diagrams appearing in low-dimensional and quantum topology. Concretely, $L(m)$ is filtered by $C_n$-equivalence, for $n\geq 1$, which is defined via local moves that can be seen as higher crossing changes. The graded object associated to the Goussarov-Habiro filtration is the Goussarov-Habiro Lie algebra of string links $\mathcal{L} L(m)$. We give a concrete presentation, in terms of primitive Feynman (tree) diagrams and relations ($\text{1T}$, $\text{AS}$, $\text{IHX}$, $\text{STU}^2$), of the rational Goussarov-Habiro Lie algebra $\mathcal{L} L(m)_{\mathbb{Q}}$. To that end, we investigate cycles in graphs of forests: flip graphs associated to forest diagrams and their $\text{STU}$ relations. As an application, we give an alternative diagrammatic proof of Massuyeau's rational version of the Goussarov-Habiro conjecture for string links, which relates indistinguishability under finite type invariants of degree $&lt;n$ and $C_n$-equivalence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01093v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Dular</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivariant Seiberg-Witten theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00642v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce and study equivariant Seiberg-Witten invariants for $4$-manifolds equipped with a smooth action of a finite group $G$. Our invariants come in two types: cohomological, valued in the group cohomology of $G$ and $K$-theoretic, valued in the representation ring of $G$. We establish basic properties of the invariants such as wall-crossing and vanishing of the invariants for $G$-invariant positive scalar curvature metrics. We establish a relation between the equivariant Seiberg-Witten invariants and families Seiberg-Witten invariants. Sufficient conditions are found under which equivariant transversality can be achieved leading to smooth moduli spaces on which $G$ acts. In the zero-dimensional case this yields a further invariant of the $G$-action valued in a refinement of the Burnside ring of $G$. We prove localisation formulas in cohomology and $K$-theory, relating the equivariant Seiberg-Witten invariants to moduli spaces of $G$-invariant solutions. We give an explicit formula for the invariants for holomorphic group actions on K\"ahler surfaces. We also prove a gluing formula for the invariants of equivariant connected sums. Various applications and consequences of the theory are considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00642v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Baraglia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural characterizations and Obstructions to Planar-Rips complexes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01082v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given a scale parameter $r&gt;0$, the Vietoris-Rips complex of $X \subset \mathbb{R}^2$ (referred to as planar-Rips complex) under the usual Euclidean metric is a (finite) simplicial complex whose simplices are subsets of $X$ with diameter at most $r$. This paper focuses on characterizing the simplicial complexes that can or cannot be realized as planar-Rips complexes. Building on the prior work of Adamszek et al., we classify, up to simplicial isomorphism, all $n$-dimensional pseudomanifolds and weak-pseudomanifolds that admit a planar-Rips structure, and further characterize two-dimensional, pure, and closed planar-Rips complexes. Additionally, the notion of obstructions to planar-Rips complexes has been introduced, laying the groundwork for algorithmic approaches to identifying forbidden planar-Rips structures. We also explore the correlations between planar-Rips complexes and the class of intersection graphs called disk graphs, establishing a natural isomorphism between the two classes. Parallelly, our findings on planar-Rips complexes have been consolidated in terms of unit disk graphs for interested readers, depicting the significance of the topological and algebraic approaches. Several structural and geometric properties of planar-Rips complexes have been derived that are of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01082v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vinay Sipani, Ramesh Kasilingam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the topology of loops of contactomorphisms and Legendrians in non-orderable manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01148</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01148v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the global topology of the space $\mathcal L$ of loops of contactomorphisms of a non-orderable closed contact manifold $(M^{2n+1}, \alpha)$. We filter $\mathcal L$ by a quantitative measure of the ``positivity'' of the loops and describe the topology of $\mathcal L$ in terms of the subspaces of the filtration. In particular, we show that the homotopy groups of $\mathcal L$ are subgroups of the homotopy groups of the subspace of positive loops $\mathcal L^+$. We obtain analogous results for the space of loops of Legendrian submanifolds in $(M^{2n+1}, \alpha)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01148v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis Hern\'andez-Corbato, Javier Mart\'inez-Aguinaga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graphs for torus actions on oriented manifolds with isolated fixed points and classification in dimension 6</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.10190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.10190v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let a torus act on a compact oriented manifold $M$ with isolated fixed points, with an additional mild assumption that its isotropy submanifolds are orientable. We associate a signed labeled multigraph encoding the fixed point data (weights and signs at fixed points and isotropy submanifolds) of the manifold. We study operations on $M$ and its multigraph, (self) connected sum and blow up, etc. When the circle group acts on a 6-dimensional $M$, we classify such a multigraph by proving that we can convert it into the empty graph by successively applying two types of operations. In particular, this classifies the fixed point data of any such manifold. We prove this by showing that for any such manifold, we can successively take equivariant connected sums at fixed points with itself, $\mathbb{CP}^3$, and 6-dimensional analogue $Z_1$ and $Z_2$ of the Hirzebruch surfaces (and these with opposite orientations) to a fixed point free action on a compact oriented 6-manifold. We also classify a multigraph for a torus action on a 4-dimensional $M$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.10190v3</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donghoon Jang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A formula to evaluate type A webs and link polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.12169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.12169v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a closed formula to evaluate exterior webs (also called MOY webs) and the associated Reshetikhin-Turaev link polynomials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.12169v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4310/ARKIV.2024.v62.n1.a5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Ark. Mat. 62 (2024), no. 1, 83-101</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Abel Lacabanne, Daniel Tubbenhauer, Pedro Vaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Links in orthoplicial Apollonian packings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.03089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.03089v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish a connection between Apollonian packings and knot theory. We introduce new representations of links realized in the tangency graph of the regular crystallographic sphere packings. Particularly, we prove that any algebraic link can be realized in the cubic section of the orthoplicial Apollonian packing. We use these representations to improve the upper bound on the ball number of an infinite family of alternating algebraic links. Furthermore, the later allow us to reinterpret the correspondence of rational tangles and rational numbers and to reveal geometrically primitive solutions for the Diophantine equation $x^4 + y^4 + z^4 = 2t^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.03089v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge L. Ram\'irez Alfons\'in, Iv\'an Rasskin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bavard duality for the relative Gromov seminorm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.02149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.02149v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The relative Gromov seminorm is a finer invariant than stable commutator length where a relative homology class is fixed. We show a duality result between bounded cohomology and the relative Gromov seminorm, analogously to Bavard duality for scl. We give an application to computations of scl in graphs of groups. We also explain how our duality result can be given a purely algebraic interpretation via a relative version of the Hopf formula. Moreover, we show that this leads to a natural generalisation of a result of Calegari on a connection between scl and the rotation quasimorphism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.02149v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexis Marchand</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Core groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.02048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.02048v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The core group of a classical link was introduced independently by A.J. Kelly in 1991 and M. Wada in 1992. It is a link invariant defined by a presentation involving the arcs and crossings of a diagram, related to Wirtinger's presentation of the fundamental group of a link complement. Two close relatives of the core group are defined by presentations involving regions rather than arcs; one of them is related to Dehn's presentation of a link group. The definitions are extended to virtual link diagrams and properties of the resulting invariants are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.02048v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel S. Silver, Lorenzo Traldi, Susan G. Williams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Bonahon-Wong-Yang volume conjecture for the four-puncture sphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.13151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.13151v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute the Bonahon-Wong-Yang quantum invariant for self-diffeomorphisms of the four-puncture sphere explicitly, based on the representation theory of the Checkov-Fock algebra. As an application of the computation, we verify the volume conjecture proposed by Bonahon-Wong-Yang for the four puncture sphere bundles with some technical conditions. Together with the one-puncture torus bundles, this is the first family of examples for which the conjecture is verified providing evidence for the conjecture</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.13151v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tushar Pandey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the mapping class group action on the homology of surface covers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16322v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\phi \in {\rm Mod}(\Sigma)$ be an arbitrary element of the mapping class group of a closed orientable surface $\Sigma$ of genus at least $2$. For any characteristic cover $\widetilde{\Sigma} \to \Sigma$ one can consider the linear subspace ${\rm H}_1^{f.o.}(\widetilde{\Sigma}, \mathbb{Q})^\phi \subseteq {\rm H}_1(\widetilde{\Sigma}, \mathbb{Q})$ consisting of all homology classes with finite $\phi$-orbit. We prove that $\dim {\rm H}_1^{f.o.}(\widetilde{\Sigma}, \mathbb{Q})^\phi$ can be arbitrary large for any fixed $\phi \in {\rm Mod}(\Sigma)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16322v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Spiridonov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Naturality of ${\rm SL}_3$ quantum trace maps for surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2104.06286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2104.06286v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fock-Goncharov's moduli spaces $\mathscr{X}_{{\rm PGL}_3,\frak{S}}$ of framed ${\rm PGL}_3$-local systems on punctured surfaces $\frak{S}$ provide prominent examples of cluster $\mathscr{X}$-varieties and higher Teichm\"uller spaces. In a previous paper of the author (arXiv:2011.14765), building on the works of others, the so-called ${\rm SL}_3$ quantum trace map is constructed for each triangulable punctured surface $\frak{S}$ and an ideal triangulation $\Delta$ of $\frak{S}$, as a homomorphism from the stated ${\rm SL}_3$-skein algebra of the surface to a quantum torus algebra that deforms the ring of Laurent polynomials in the cube-roots of the cluster coordinate variables for the cluster $\mathscr{X}$-chart for $\mathscr{X}_{{\rm PGL}_3,\frak{S}}$ associated to $\Delta$. We develop quantum mutation maps between special subalgebras of the cube-root quantum torus algebras for different triangulations and show that the ${\rm SL}_3$ quantum trace maps are natural, in the sense that they are compatible under these quantum mutation maps. As an application, the quantum ${\rm SL}_3$-${\rm PGL}_3$ duality map constructed in the previous paper is shown to be independent of the choice of an ideal triangulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2104.06286v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4171/QT/214</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hyun Kyu Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Circle actions on six dimensional oriented manifolds with isolated fixed points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2108.07560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2108.07560v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let the circle group act on a 6-dimensional compact oriented manifold $M$ with isolated fixed points. The fixed point data of $M$ is the collection of signs and weights at the fixed points. To classify such a manifold $M$, the fixed point data is an essential information. Under an assumption that each isotropy submanifold is orientable, we classify the fixed point data of $M$, by showing that we can convert it to the empty collection by performing a combination of a number of types of operations. We do so by proving that we can successively take equivariant connected sums of $M$ at fixed points with $S^6$, $\mathbb{CP}^3$, and 6-dimensional analogue $Z_1$ and $Z_2$ of the Hirzebruch surfaces (and these with opposite orientations), to a fixed point free action on a compact oriented 6-manifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2108.07560v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donghoon Jang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete subgroups with finite Bowen-Margulis-Sullivan measure in higher rank</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.00610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.00610v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a connected semisimple real algebraic group and $\Gamma&lt;G$ be its Zariski dense discrete subgroup. We prove that if $\Gamma\backslash G$ admits any finite Bowen-Margulis-Sullivan measure, then $\Gamma$ is virtually a product of higher rank lattices and discrete subgroups of rank one factors of $G$. This may be viewed as a measure-theoretic analogue of classification of convex cocompact actions by Kleiner-Leeb and Quint, which was conjectured by Corlette in 1994. The key ingredients in our proof are the product structure of leafwise measures and the high entropy method of Einsiedler-Katok-Lindenstrauss. In a companion paper jointly with Edwards and Oh, we use this result to show that the bottom of the $L^2$ spectrum has no atom in any infinite volume quotient of a higher rank simple algebraic group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.00610v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikolaj Fraczyk, Minju Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Information Geometry of UMAP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.01237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.01237v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Although UMAP was derived from Category Theory observations, its underlying mechanisms may be clarified using Information Geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.01237v5</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Kolpakov, Aidan Rocke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular Legendrian unknot links and relative Ginzburg algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03330v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We associate to a quiver and a subquiver $(Q,F)$ a stopped Weinstein manifold $X$ whose Legendrian attaching link is a singular Legendrian unknot link $\varLambda$. We prove that the relative Ginzburg algebra of $(Q,F)$ is quasi-isomorphic to the Chekanov--Eliashberg dg-algebra of $\varLambda$. It follows that the Chekanov--Eliashberg dg-algebra of $\varLambda$ relative to its boundary dg-subalgebra, and the Orlov functor associated to the partially wrapped Fukaya category of $X$ both admit a strong relative smooth Calabi--Yau structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03330v2</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johan Asplund</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-hyperbolic 3-manifolds and 3D field theories for 2D Virasoro minimal models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.16377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.16377v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Using 3D-3D correspondence, we construct 3D dual bulk field theories for general Virasoro minimal models $M(P,Q)$. These theories correspond to Seifert fiber spaces $S^2 ((P,P-R),(Q,S),(3,1))$ with two integers $(R,S)$ satisfying $PS-QR =1$. In the unitary case, where $|P-Q|=1$, the bulk theory has a mass gap and flows to a unitary topological field theory (TQFT) in the IR, which is expected to support the chiral Virasoro minimal model at the boundary under an appropriate boundary condition. For the non-unitary case, where $|P-Q|&gt;1$, the bulk theory flows to a 3D $\mathcal{N}=4$ rank-0 superconformal field theory, whose topologically twisted theory supports the chiral minimal model at the boundary. We also provide a concrete field theory description of the 3D bulk theory using $T[SU(2)]$ theories. Our proposals are supported by various consistency checks using 3D-3D relations and direct computations of various partition functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.16377v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongmin Gang, Heesu Kang, Seongmin Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
