<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT</link>
    <description>math.GT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 02:49:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Adding a suitable unknot to any link equates bridge number and meridional rank</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10642v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given any link $L\subseteq S^3$, we show that it is possible to embed an unknot $U$ in its complement so that the link $L\cup U$ satisfies the Meridional Rank Conjecture (MRC). The bridge numbers in our construction fit into the equality $\beta(L\cup U)=2\beta(L)-1=\text{rank}(\pi_1(S^3\backslash (L\cup U)))$. In addition, we prove the MRC for new infinite families of links and distinguish them from previously settled cases through an application of bridge distance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10642v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan Blair, Alexandra Kjuchukova, Ella Pfaff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A criterion for virtual Euler class one</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $M$ be an oriented closed hyperbolic $3$--manifold. Suppose that $w$ is a rational second cohomology class of $M$ with dual Thurston norm $1$. Upon the existence of certain nonvanishing Alexander polynomials, the author shows that the pullback of $w$ to some finite cover of $M$ is the real Euler class of some transversely oriented taut foliation on that cover. As application, the author constructs examples with first Betti number either $2$ or $3$, and partial examples with any first Betti number at least $4$, supporting Yazdi's virtual Euler class one conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11492v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Large-Color Expansion Derived from the Universal Invariant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11569v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The colored Jones polynomial associated to a knot admits an expansion of knot invariants known as the large-color expansion or Melvin-Morton-Rozansky expansion. We will show how this expansion can be derived from the universal invariant arising from a Hopf algebra $\mathbb{D}$, as introduced by Bar-Natan and Van der Veen. We utilize a Mathematica implementation to compute the universal invariant $\mathbf{Z}_{\mathbb{D}}(\mathcal{K})$ up to a certain order for a given knot $\mathcal{K}$, allowing for experimental verification of our theoretical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11569v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boudewijn Bosch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Vol-Det Conjecture for highly twisted alternating links</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11711v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Vol-Det Conjecture, formulated by Champanerkar, Kofman and Purcell, states that there exists a specific inequality connecting the hyperbolic volume of an alternating link and its determinant. Among the classes of links for which this conjecture holds are all knots with at most 16 crossings, 2-bridge links, and links that are closures of 3-strand braids. In the present paper, Burton's bound on the number of crossings for which the Vol-Det Conjecture holds is improved for links with more than eight twists. In addition, Stoimenow's inequalities between hyperbolic volumes and determinants are improved for alternating and alternating arborescent links with more than eight twists.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11711v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Egorov, Andrei Vesnin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reorienting quandle orbits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11763v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by knot theory, it is natural to define the orientation-reversal of a quandle orbit by inverting all the translations given by elements of that orbit. In this short note we observe that this natural notion is unsuited to medial quandles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11763v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Traldi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contact Geometry of the Restricted Three-Body Problem on $\mathbb{S}^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10885v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the contact geometry of the connected components of the energy hypersurface, in the symmetric restricted 3-body problem on $\mathbb{S}^2$, for a specific type of motion of the primaries. In particular, we show that these components are of contact type for all energies below the first critical value and slightly above it. We prove that these components, suitably compactified using a Moser-type regularization are contactomorphic to $R\mathbb{P}^3$ with its unique tight contact structure or to the connected sum of two copies of it, depending on the value of the energy. We exploit Taubes' solution of the Weinstein conjecture in dimension three, to infer the existence of periodic orbits in all these cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10885v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kursat Yilmaz, Alessandro Arsie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Structure in Multi-agent Systems Using Geometric Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11142v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work investigates the self-organization of multi-agent systems into closed trajectories, a common requirement in unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) surveillance tasks. In such scenarios, smooth, unbiased control signals save energy and mitigate mechanical strain. We propose a decentralized control system architecture that produces a globally stable emergent structure from local observations only; there is no requirement for agents to share a global plan or follow prescribed trajectories. Central to our approach is the formulation of an injective virtual embedding induced by rotations from the actual agent positions. This embedding serves as a structure-preserving map around which all agent stabilize their relative positions and permits the use of well-established linear control techniques. We construct the embedding such that it is topologically equivalent to the desired trajectory (i.e., a homeomorphism), thereby preserving the stability characteristics. We demonstrate the versatility of this approach through implementation on a swarm of Quanser QDrone quadcopters. Results demonstrate the quadcopters self-organize into the desired trajectory while maintaining even separation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11142v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitria Silveria, Kleber Cabral, Peter Jardine, Sidney Givigi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computations of Stable Multiplicities in the Cohomology of Configuration Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11337v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We describe an algorithm to compute the stable multiplicity of a family of irreducible representations in the cohomology of ordered configuration space of the plane. Using this algorithm, we compute the stable multiplicities of all families of irreducibles given by Young diagrams with $23$ boxes or less up to cohomological degree $50$. In particular, this determines the stable cohomology in cohomological degrees $0 \leq i \leq 11$. We prove related qualitative results and formulate some conjectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11337v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emil Geisler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partially Hyperbolic Dynamics with Quasi-isometric Center</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11836v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the class of partially hyperbolic diffeomorphisms on a closed 3-manifold with quasi-isometric center. Under the non-wandering condition, we prove that the diffeomorphisms are accessible if there is no $su$-torus. As a consequence, volume-preserving diffeomorphisms in this context are ergodic in the absence of $su$-tori, thereby confirming the Hertz-Hertz-Ures Ergodicity Conjecture for this class.
  We show the existence of transitive Anosov flows on a closed 3-manifold admitting a non-wandering partially hyperbolic diffeomorphism with quasi-isometric center and fundamental group of exponential growth. Furthermore, we provide a complete classification of these diffeomorphisms, showing they fall into two categories: skew products and discretized Anosov flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11836v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziqiang Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Marked Length Spectrum Rigidity for Surface Amalgams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.09968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.09968v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we show that simple, thick negatively curved two-dimensional P-manifolds, a large class of surface amalgams, are marked length spectrum rigid. That is, if two piecewise negatively curved Riemannian metrics (satisfying certain smoothness conditions) on a simple, thick two-dimensional P-manifold assign the same lengths to all closed geodesics, then they differ by an isometry up to isotopy. Our main theorem is a natural generalization of Croke and Otal's celebrated results about marked length spectrum rigidity of negatively curved surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.09968v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yandi Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representations of braid groups via cyclic covers of the sphere: Zariski closure and arithmeticity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.10401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.10401v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $d \geq 2$ and $n\geq 3$ be two natural numbers. Given any sequence $\kappa=(k_1,\dots,k_n) \in \mathbb{Z}^n$ such that $\gcd(k_1,\dots,k_n,d)=1$, we consider the family of Riemann surfaces obtained from the plane curves defined by $y^d=\prod_{i=1}^n(x-b_i)^{k_i}$, where $\{b_1,\dots,b_n\}$ are $n$ distinct points in $\mathbb{C}$. The monodromy of the cohomology of the fibers of this family provides us with a representation of the pure braid group $\mathrm{PB}_n$ into some symplectic group. By restricting to a specific subspace in the cohomology of the fibers, we obtain a representation $\rho_d$ of $\mathrm{PB}_n$ into a linear algebraic group defined over $\mathbb{Q}$. In a sense, $\rho_d$ is primitive with respect to the parameters $d$ and $\kappa$. The first main result of this paper is a criterion for the Zariski closure of the image of $\rho_d$ to be maximal, and the second main result is a criterion for the image to be an arithmetic lattice in the target group. The latter generalizes previous results of Venkataramana and gives an answer to a question by McMullen.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.10401v3</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabrielle Menet, Duc-Manh Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivariant Double-Slice Genus, Stabilization, and Equivariant Stabilization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17062v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we define the equivariant double-slice genus and equivariant super-slice genus of a strongly invertible knot. We prove lower bounds for both the equivariant double-slice genus and the equivariant super-slice genus. Using these bounds we find a family of knots which are double-slice and equivariantly slice, but have equivariant double-slice genus at least $n$. Using this result, we construct unknotted symmetric 2-spheres which do not bound symmetric 3-balls. Additionally, using double-slice and super-slice genera we find effective lower bounds for 1-handle stabilization distance and identify a possible method for using equivariant double-slice and super-slice genera to bound symmetric 1-handle stabilization distance for symmetric surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17062v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Malcolm Gabbard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributive quandle and detecting causality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04477v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: I investigated the capability of a specific type of quandle, quandle whose operation satisfying that $(a_1*b_1)*(a_2*b_2)=(a_1*a_2)*(b_1*b_2)$, to detect causality in (2+1)-dimensional globally hyperbolic spacetime by determining if they can distinguishe the connected sum of two Hopf links with an infinite series of relevant three-component links constructed by Allen and Swenberg in 2020, who suggested that any link invariant must be able to distinguish those links for them to detect causality in the given setting. I show that these quandles fail to do so as long as $a\sim b\Leftrightarrow a*b=a$ defines an equivalence relation on the quandle with * be its operation. The Alexander quandles is an example that this result can apply to.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04477v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongxu Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Closed Formula for the Interleaving Distance of Rectangle Persistence Modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01430v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We give formulas for calculating the interleaving distance between rectangle persistence modules that depend solely on the geometry of the underlying rectangles. Moreover, we extend our results to calculate the bottleneck distance for rectangle decomposable persistence modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01430v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mehmet Ali Batan, Claudia Landi, Mehmetcik Pamuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thurston norm for coherent right-angled Artin groups via $L^2$-invariants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02516v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We define a new notion of splitting complexity for a group $G$ along a non-trivial integral character $\phi \in H^1(G; \mathbb{Z})$. If $G$ is a one-ended coherent right-angled Artin group, we show that the splitting complexity along an epimorphism $\phi \colon G \to \mathbb{Z}$ equals the $L^2$-Euler characteristic of the kernel of $\phi$. This allows us to define a Thurston-type semi-norm $\| \cdot \|_T \colon H^1(G ; \mathbb{R}) \to \mathbb{R}$ that measures the splitting complexity of integral characters. Our main tool is Friedl--L\"{u}ck's $L^2$-polytope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02516v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Monika Kudlinska</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
