<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT</link>
    <description>math.GT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 04:00:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>From disc patterns in the plane to character varieties of knot groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13829v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by an experimental study of groups generated by reflections in planar patterns of tangent circles, we describe some methods for constructing and studying representation spaces of holonomy groups of infinite covolume hyperbolic $3$-manifolds that arise from unknotting tunnels of links. We include full descriptions of our computational methods, which were guided by simplicity and generality rather than by being particularly efficient in special cases. This makes them easy for non-experts to understand and implement to produce visualisations that can suggest conjectures and support algebraic calculations in the character variety. Throughout, we have tried to make the exposition clear and understandable for graduate students in geometric topology and related fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13829v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Elzenaar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Knots not detected by any trace</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14172v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The first and last named authors have demonstrated the existence of knots for which every integral slope is non-characterizing. In this short note, we extend this result in two ways. There exists a knot that shares for every integer n the same n-trace with infinitely many mutually distinct knots. Moreover, every knot is concordant to a knot that is not detected by any of its traces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14172v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenneth L. Baker, Marc Kegel, Kimihiko Motegi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A convenient category of cubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13663v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We claim that the cube category whose morphisms are the interval-preserving monotone functions between finite Boolean lattices is a convenient general-purpose site for cubical sets. This category is the largest possible concrete Eilenberg-Zilber variant excluding the reversals and diagonals. The category admits as monoidal generators all functions between the singleton and two-element ordinals and all monotone surjections from finite Boolean lattices to the two-element ordinal. Consequently, morphisms in the minimal symmetric monoidal variant of the cube category containing coconnections of one kind can be characterized as the interval-preserving semilattice homomorphisms between finite Boolean lattices. There exists a model structure on our variant of cubical sets that is at once Quillen equivalent to and left induced from the classical model structure on simplicial sets along triangulation. This model structure is proper and hence its fibrations interpret Martin-Lof dependent types.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13663v1</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanjeevi Krishnan, Emily Rudman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the topology of manifolds with positive intermediate curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13815v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We formulate a conjecture relating the topology of a manifold's universal cover with the existence of metrics with positive $m$-intermediate curvature. We prove the result for manifolds of dimension $n\in\{3,4,5\}$ and for most choices of $m$ when $n=6$. As a corollary, we show that a closed, aspherical 6-manifold cannot admit a metric with positive $4$-intermediate curvature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13815v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liam Mazurowski, Tongrui Wang, Xuan Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Connectivity of Coxeter group Morse boundaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14085v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the connectivity of Morse boundaries of Coxeter groups. We define two conditions on the defining graph of a Coxeter group: wide-avoidant and wide-spherical-avoidant. We show that wide-spherical-avoidant, one-ended, affine-free Coxeter groups have connected and locally connected Morse boundaries. On the other hand, one-ended Coxeter groups that are not wide-avoidant and not wide have disconnected Morse boundary. For the right-angled case, we get a full characterization: a one-ended right-angled Coxeter group has connected, non-empty Morse boundary if and only if it is wide-avoidant. Along the way we characterize Morse geodesic rays in affine-free Coxeter groups as those that spend uniformly bounded time in cosets of wide special subgroups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14085v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Cordes, Ivan Levcovitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Torres-type formulas for link signatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.02347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.02347v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the limits of the multivariable signature function $\sigma_L$ of a $\mu$-component link $L$ as some variable tends to $1$ via two different approaches: a three-dimensional and a four-dimensional one. The first uses the definition of $\sigma_L$ by generalized Seifert surfaces and forms. The second relies on a new extension of $\sigma_L$ from its usual domain $(S^1\setminus\{1\})^\mu$ to the full torus $\mathbb{T}^\mu$ together with a Torres-type formula for $\sigma_L$, results which are of independent interest. Among several consequences, we obtain new estimates on the value of the Levine-Tristram signature of a link close to $1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.02347v5</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Cimasoni, Maciej Markiewicz, Wojciech Politarczyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limiting Sets for Digital Cones and Suspensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.07365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.07365v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cone and suspension constructions have been introduced in digital topology, modeled on those of classical topology. For digital cones and suspensions, and for some related digital images, we find (m, n)-limiting sets; especially (0, 0)-limiting (freezing) sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.07365v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laurence Boxer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A lower bound on end-periodic stretch factors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17389</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17389v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given an end-periodic homeomorphism $f: S \to S$ we give a lower bound on the Handel--Miller stretch factor of $f$ in terms of the core characteristic of $f$, which is a measure of topological complexity for an end-periodic homeomorphism. We also show that this bound is asymptotically sharp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17389v4</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marissa Loving, Chenxi Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irrationality of the Length Spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03461</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03461v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is a classical result of Dal'Bo that the length spectrum of a non-elementary Fuchsian group is non-arithmetic, namely, it generates a dense additive subgroup of $\mathbb{R}$. In this note we observe the following extension of this fact: a non-elementary Fuchsian group contains two elements whose lengths are linearly independent over $\mathbb{Q}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03461v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Peterzil, Guy Sapire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Cohen--Lyndon property in non-metric small-cancellation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.20288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.20288v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that the Cohen--Lyndon property holds for all non-metric small-cancellation quotients. This generalises the analogous result from the metric small-cancellation setting, and answers a question asked by Lyndon in 1966 and by Wall in his 1979 problem list.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.20288v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Macarena Arenas, Karol Duda</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
