<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT</link>
    <description>math.GT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 04:00:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Volumes of end-periodic mapping tori</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14244</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14244v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this expository paper, we provide an intuition and illustration-driven overview of two recent results that tie the dynamics of certain homeomorphisms of infinite-type surfaces, called end-periodic homeomorphisms, to the geometry of their associated (compactified) mapping tori. These results are analogues of a theorem of Brock in the finite-type setting for mapping tori of pseudo-Anosov homeomorphisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14244v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marissa Loving</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing Khovanov homology of tangles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14398v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The computation of Khovanov homology for tangles has significant potential applications, yet explicit computational studies remain limited. In this work, we present a method for computing the Khovanov homology of tangles via an arc reduction approach, and we derive the Poincar\'e polynomial for simple tangles. Furthermore, we compute the Poincar\'e polynomials of tangles with at most three crossings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14398v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li Shen, Jian Liu, Guo-Wei Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Khovanov homology of tangles: algorithm and computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14404v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Knot, link, and tangle theory is crucial in both mathematical theory and practical application, including quantum physics, molecular biology, and structural chemistry. Unlike knots and links, tangles impose more relaxed constraints, allowing the presence of arcs, which makes them particularly valuable for broader applications. Although Khovanov homology for knots and links has been extensively studied, its computation for tangles remains largely unexplored. In our recent work, we provide a topological quantum field theory (TQFT) construction for the Khovanov homology of tangles, offering a more concrete method for its computation. The primary contribution of this work is a comprehensive approach to the computation of the Khovanov homology of tangles, offering both a detailed computation procedure and a practical guide for implementing algorithms through codes to facilitate the calculation. This contribution paves the way for further studies and applications of Khovanov homology in the context of tangles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14404v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li Shen, Jian Liu, Guo-Wei Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All Tied Up: A First Look At Modern Yo-Yo and Knot Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14462v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modern Yo-Yo play has developed into a sophisticated international subculture, featuring elite competition and intricate tricks. Despite this, no systematic knot-theoretic treatment has yet been applied to the numerous string configurations realised in contemporary Yo-Yo play. This paper takes initial steps in addressing this gap, recalling fundamental results from knot theory and embeddings to develop a methodology for classifying string arrangements, known as `mounts', in both beginner and advanced single Yo-Yo play. We classify a range of mounts according to the knots they form under appropriate post-processing procedures and identify Yo-Yo maneuvers that correspond to Reidemeister moves. Furthermore, we analyse the impact of certain mounts on the writhe of their diagrammatic projections and introduce operations to facilitate discussion of composite mounts. This work seeks to initiate a dialogue between Yo-Yo practitioners and knot theorists, fostering further advancements in high-level Yo-Yo play and enabling novel physical realisations of knots, links, braids, surgeries, and other topological transformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14462v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Hamblin, Victor M. Calo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The lengths of 3-cocycles of the 7-dihedral and the octahedral quandles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We determine the lengths of certain 3-cocycles of the 7-dihedral and the octahedral quandles. As a consequence, we show that both of the 2-twist-spun $5_{2}$-knot and the 4-twist-spun trefoil have the triple point number eight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14612v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayumu Inoue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Almost-concordance of knots in aspherical 3-manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14638v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study topological concordance modulo local knotting, or almost-concordance, of knots in 3-manifolds $M\neq S^3$. A. Levine, Celoria (arXiv:1602.05476v4), and Friedl-Nagel-Orson-Powell (arXiv:1611.09114v2) conjecture that, absent the presence of an embedded dual 2-sphere, any free homotopy class $x$ of knots in $M$ contains infinitely many concordance classes modulo the action of the concordance group of knots in $S^3$ by local knotting. We develop a method for confirming this conjecture for any nontrivial class $x$ in any aspherical $M$ and provide computations that prove the conjecture in a large family of open cases. Our technique employs an extension of Milnor's link invariants to knots and links in non-simply-connected 3-manifolds (arXiv:2310.10918v2). We exhibit a large family of examples where, in a precise sense, we maximize the number of almost-concordance classes distinguished by these invariants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14638v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan Stees</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fibering of double twist knots via the adjoint hyperbolic torsion polynomial</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14731v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a hyperbolic knot $K$ in $S^3$, the adjoint hyperbolic torsion polynomial $\mathcal T^{\mathrm{Ad}}_K(t) \in \mathbb C[t^{\pm 1}]$ is defined as a normalization of the twisted Alexander polynomial of $K$ associated with the $\mathrm{SL}_3(\mathbb C)$-representation obtained by composing the holonomy representation of $K$ with the adjoint action of $\mathrm{SL}_2(\mathbb C)$ on its Lie algebra $\mathfrak{sl}_2(\mathbb C)$. In this paper we consider the adjoint hyperbolic torsion polynomial for a two-parameter family of rational knots called double twist knots, and show that $\mathcal T^{\mathrm{Ad}}_K(t)$ determines the genus and fibering of this family by using algebraic integers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14731v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anh T. Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric components of representation spaces via robust families of submanifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14842v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce robust families of submanifolds for a linear Lie group $G$. We show that they give rise to geometric subspaces of the representation space ${\rm Hom}(\Gamma,G)$. As an application, we give a unified short proof of results of Beyrer and Kassel and of Benoist and Koszul about the existence of higher Teichm\"uller components for $G={\rm SO}(p,q+1),{\rm SL}(p+1,\mathbb{R})$. Being based on very general principles, our approach might be suited for finding geometric components in various ${\rm Hom}(\Gamma,G)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14842v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele Viaggi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$c_{\rm eff}$ from Resurgence at the Stokes Line</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.10112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.10112v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent papers [1,2], a new method to cross the natural boundary has been proposed, and applied to Mordell-Borel integrals arising in the study of Chern-Simons theory, based on decompositions into {\it resurgent cyclic orbits}. Resurgent analysis on the Stokes line leads to a unique transseries decomposition in terms of unary false theta functions, which can be continued across the natural boundary to produce dual $q$-series whose integer-valued coefficients enumerate BPS states. This constitutes a deeper new manifestation of resurgence in quantum field theoretic path integrals. In this paper we show that the algebraic structure of the {\it resurgent cyclic orbits}, combined with just the leading term of the $q$-series, completely determines the large order rate of growth of the dual $q$-series coefficients. The essential exponent of this asymptotic growth has a Cardy-like interpretation [10] of an effective central charge in a 3 dimensional quantum field theory with $\mathcal{N}=2$ supersymmetry related to the Chern-Simons theory through the $3d$-$3d$ correspondence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.10112v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Griffen Adams, Ovidiu Costin, Gerald V. Dunne, Sergei Gukov, O\u{g}uz \"Oner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small Scale Index Theory, Scalar Curvature, and Gromov's Simplicial Norms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14791v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article, we study the topological complexity of manifolds with a lower scalar curvature bound. We introduce a small-scale index theorem to establish an upper bound on Gromov's simplicial norm of the Poincar\'e dual of the $\hat{A}$-class for Riemannian manifolds satisfying a scalar curvature lower bound. This result can be considered as a topological finiteness theorem for manifolds with a lower scalar curvature bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14791v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiaochu Ma, Guoliang Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral gap with polynomial rate for Weil-Petersson random surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14874v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that there is a constant $c&gt;0$ such that a genus $g$ closed hyperbolic surface, sampled at random from the moduli space $\mathcal{M}_{g}$ with respect to the Weil-Petersson probability measure, has Laplacian spectral gap at least $\frac{1}{4}-O\left(\frac{1}{g^{c}}\right)$ with probability tending to $1$ as $g\to\infty$. This extends and gives a new proof of a recent result of Anantharaman and Monk proved in the series of works [2,3,5,4,6].
  Our approach adapts the polynomial method for the strong convergence of random matrices, introduced by Chen, Garza-Vargas, Tropp and van Handel [19], and its generalization to the strong convergence of surface groups by Magee, Puder and van Handel [41], to the Laplacian on Weil-Petersson random hyperbolic surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14874v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Will Hide, Davide Macera, Joe Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigidity of Kleinian groups via self-joinings: measure theoretic criterion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.03552v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $n, m\ge 2$. Let $\Gamma&lt;\text{SO}^\circ(n+1,1)$ be a Zariski dense convex cocompact subgroup and $\Lambda\subset\mathbb{S}^n$ be its limit set. Let $\rho : \Gamma \to \text{SO}^\circ(m+1,1)$ be a Zariski dense convex cocompact faithful representation and $f:\Lambda\to \mathbb{S}^{m}$ the $\rho$-boundary map. Let $$\Lambda_f:= \bigcup \left\{ C \cap \Lambda : \begin{matrix} C \subset \mathbb{S}^n \text{ is a circle such that} \\ f(C \cap \Lambda) \text{ is contained in a proper sphere } \text{in } \mathbb{S}^m \end{matrix} \right\}.$$ When there exists at least one $\Lambda$-doubly stable circle in $\mathbb{S}^n$ (e.g., $\Omega=\mathbb{S}^n-\Lambda$ is disconnected), we prove the following dichotomy: $$\text{either}\quad \Lambda_f= \Lambda \quad \text{ or } \quad \mathcal{H}^{\delta}(\Lambda_f) =0,$$ where $\mathcal{H}^\delta$ is the Hausdorff measure of dimension $\delta=\dim_H \Lambda$. Moreover, in the former case, we have $n=m$ and $\rho$ is a conjugation by a M\"obius transformation on $\mathbb{S}^n$. Our proof uses ergodic theory for directional diagonal flows and conformal measure theory of discrete subgroups of higher rank semisimple Lie groups, applied to the self-joining subgroup $\Gamma_\rho=(\operatorname{id} \times \rho)(\Gamma) &lt; \text{SO}^\circ(n+1,1)\times \text{SO}^\circ(m+1,1)$. We also obtain an analogous theorem for any divergence-type subgroup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.03552v5</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongryul M. Kim, Hee Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small symplectic caps and embeddings of homology balls in the complex projective plane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.16207v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a handlebody construction of small symplectic caps, and hence of small closed symplectic 4-manifolds. We use this to construct handlebody descriptions of symplectic embeddings of rational homology balls in $\mathbb{C}\mathrm{P}^2$, and thereby provide the first examples of (infinitely many) symplectic handlebody decompositions of a closed symplectic 4-manifold. Our constructions provide a new topological interpretation of almost toric fibrations of $\mathbb{C}\mathrm{P}^2$ in terms of symplectic handlebody decompositions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.16207v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John B. Etnyre, Hyunki Min, Lisa Piccirillo, Agniva Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A lower bound on volumes of end-periodic mapping tori</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.03279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.03279v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide a lower bound on the volume of the compactified mapping torus of a strongly irreducible end-periodic homeomorphism f. This result, together with work of Field, Kim, Leininger, and Loving, shows that the volume of the compactified mapping torus of f is comparable to the translation length of f on a connected component of the pants graph, extending work of Brock in the finite-type setting on volumes of mapping tori of pseudo-Anosov homeomorphisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.03279v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elizabeth Field, Autumn Kent, Christopher Leininger, Marissa Loving</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-simple systoles on random hyperbolic surfaces for large genus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.16447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.16447v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the asymptotic behavior of the non-simple systole, which is the length of a shortest non-simple closed geodesic, on a random closed hyperbolic surface on the moduli space $\mathcal{M}_g$ of Riemann surfaces of genus $g$ endowed with the Weil-Petersson measure. We show that as the genus $g$ goes to infinity, the non-simple systole of a generic hyperbolic surface in $\mathcal{M}_g$ behaves exactly like $\log g$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.16447v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxin He, Yang Shen, Yunhui Wu, Yuhao Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Arithmeticity and commensurability of links in thickened surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00490v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The family of right-angled tiling links consists of links built from regular 4-valent tilings of constant-curvature surfaces that contain one or two types of tiles. The complements of these links admit complete hyperbolic structures and contain two totally geodesic checkerboard surfaces that meet at right angles. In this paper, we give a complete characterization of which right-angled tiling links are arithmetic, and which are pairwise commensurable. The arithmeticity classification exploits symmetry arguments and the combinatorial geometry of Coxeter polyhedra. The commensurability classification relies on identifying the canonical decompositions of the link complements, in addition to number-theoretic data from invariant trace fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00490v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Futer, Rose Kaplan-Kelly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contact surgery numbers of projective spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05032v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We classify all contact projective spaces with contact surgery number one. In particular, this implies that there exist infinitely many non-isotopic contact structures on the real projective 3-space which cannot be obtained by a single rational contact surgery from the standard tight contact 3-sphere.
  Large parts of our proofs deal with a detailed analysis of Gompf's $\Gamma$-invariant of tangential 2-plane fields on 3-manifolds. From our main result we also deduce that the $\Gamma$-invariant of a tangential 2-plane field on the real projective 3-space only depends on its $d_3$-invariant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05032v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Kegel, Monika Yadav</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The CN matrix of a pure braid projection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08659v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The CN matrix of an $n$-braid projection $B$ is an $n \times n$ matrix such that each $(i,j)$ entry indicates the number of crossings between $i^{th}$ and $j^{th}$ strands of $B$. In this paper, several patterns of an $n \times n$ matrix to be a CN matrix are discussed, and the CN matrix of a pure 6-braid projection is characterized. As an application, the OU matrix of a pure 6-braid diagram and the crossing matrix of a positive pure 6-braid are also characterized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08659v3</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuko Ozawa, Ayaka Shimizu, Yoshiro Yaguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lie algebras and the (co)homology of configuration spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14909v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We survey decades of research identifying the (co)homology of configuration spaces with Lie algebra (co)homology. The different routes to this one proto-theorem offer genuinely different explanations of its truth, and we attempt to convey some sense of the conceptual core of each perspective. We close with a list of problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14909v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Knudsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H\"older continuous mappings, differential forms and the Heisenberg groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11506v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop analysis of H\"older continuous mappings with applications to geometry and topology of the Heisenberg groups. We cover the theory of distributional Jacobians of H\"older continuous mappings and pullbacks of differential forms under H\"older continuous mappings. That includes versions of the change of variables formula and the Stokes theorem for H\"older continuous mappings. The main applications are in the setting of the Heisenberg groups, where we provide a simple proof of a generalization of the Gromov non-embedding theorem, and new results about the H\"older homotopy groups of the Heisenberg groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11506v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Haj{\l}asz, Jacob Mirra, Armin Schikorra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Manifold structures on highly connected Poincar\'e complexes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23228v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper constructs numerous examples of highly connected Poincar\'{e} complexes, each homotopy equivalent to a topological manifold yet not homotopy equivalent to any smooth manifold. Furthermore, we determine the homotopy type of any closed $2k$-connected framed $(4k+2)$-manifold with Kervaire invariant one for $k=7,15,31$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23228v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
