<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT</link>
    <description>math.GT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 04:00:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Constructions of and Bounds on the Toric Mosaic Number</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02265v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Knot mosaics were introduced by Kauffman and Lomonaco in the context of quantum knots, but have since been studied for their own right. A classical knot mosaic is formed on a square grid. In this work, we identify opposite edges of the square to form mosaics on the surface of a torus. We provide two algorithms for efficiently constructing toric mosaics of torus knots, providing upper bounds for the toric mosaic number. Using these results and a computer search, we provide a census of known toric mosaic numbers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02265v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kendall Heiney, Margaret Kipe, Samantha Pezzimenti, Kaelyn Pontes, Luc Ta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surgeries between lens spaces of type $L(n,1)$ and the Heegaard Floer $d$-invariant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02325v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a $d$-invariant surgery formula for $L$-space knots that provides an effective tool for studying surgeries between lens spaces. Using this formula, we classify distance one surgeries between lens spaces of the form $L(n,1)$. This classification has direct applications to band surgeries between torus links $T(2,n)$, with connections to DNA topology. In particular, we show that chirally cosmetic banding of torus links can possibly occur only when $n=1,5,9$ or $10$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02325v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongtao Wu, Jingling Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent version of Drinfeld's associator equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02549v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The works of Alekseev and Torossian [AT] and Alekseev, Enriquez, and Torossian [AET] show that any solution of Drinfeld's associator equations gives rise to a solution of the Kashiwara-Vergne equations in an explicit way. We introduce a weak version of Drinfeld's associator equations that we call the emergent version of the original equations. It is shown that solutions to the resulting linearized emergent Drinfeld's equations still lead to solutions to the linearized Kashiwara-Vergne equations.
  The emergent Drinfeld equations arise within a natural topological context of emergent braids, which we discuss. Our results are adjacent to the results of Bar-Natan, Dancso, Hogan, Liu and Scherich [BDHLS] on the relationship between emergent tangles and the Goldman-Turaev Lie bialgebra. We hope that in time our results will play a role in relating several bodies of work, on Drinfeld associators, Kashiwara-Vergne equations, and on expansions for classical tangles, for w-tangles, and for the Goldman-Turaev Lie bialgebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02549v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusuke Kuno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A spanning tree model for Khovanov homology, Rasmussen's s-invariant and exotic discs in the $4$-ball</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02625v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The checkerboard coloring of knot diagrams offers a graph-theoretical approach to address topological questions. Champanerkar and Kofman defined a complex generated by the spanning trees of a graph obtained from the checkerboard coloring whose homology is the reduced Khovanov homology. Notably, the differential in their chain complex was not explicitly defined. We explicitly define the combinatorial form of the differential within the spanning tree complex. We additionally provide a description of Rasmussen's $s$-invariant within the context of the spanning tree complex. Applying our techniques, we identify a new infinite family of knots where each of them bounds a set of exotic discs within the 4-ball.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02625v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aninda Banerjee, Apratim Chakraborty, Swarup Kumar Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuous two-valued discrete-time dynamical systems and actions of two-valued groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02635v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study continuous 2-valued dynamical systems with discrete time (dynamics) on $\mathbb{C}$. The main question addressed is whether a 2-valued dynamics can be defined by the action of a 2-valued group. We construct a class of strongly invertible continuous 2-valued dynamics on $\mathbb{C}$ such that none of these dynamics can be given by the action of any 2-valued group. We also construct an example of a continuous 2-valued dynamics on $\mathbb{C}$ that is not strongly invertible but can be defined by the action of a 2-valued group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02635v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantin M. Posadskiy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pivoting technique for the circle homeomorphism group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02788v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We adapt Gou{\"e}zel's pivoting technique to the circle homeomorphism group. As an application, we give different proofs of Gilabert Vio's probabilistic Tits alternative and Malicet's exponential synchronization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02788v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Inhyeok Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nu-invariants of extra-twisted connected sums</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2010.16367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2010.16367v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyse the possible ways of gluing twisted products of circles with asymptotically cylindrical Calabi-Yau manifolds to produce manifolds with holonomy G_2, thus generalising the twisted connected sum construction of Kovalev and Corti, Haskins, Nordstr\"om, Pacini. We then express the extended nu-invariant of Crowley, Goette, and Nordstr\"om arXiv:1505.02734 in terms of fixpoint and gluing contributions, which include different types of (generalised) Dedekind sums. Surprisingly, the calculations involve some non-trivial number-theoretical arguments connected with special values of the Dedekind eta-function and the theory of complex multiplication. One consequence of our computations is that there exist compact G_2-manifolds that are not G_2-nullbordant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2010.16367v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Goette, Johannes Nordstr\"om, Don Zagier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of tight contact structures on some Seifert fibered manifolds: I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.09490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.09490v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We classify tight contact structures with zero Giroux torsion on some Seifert-fibered manifolds with four exceptional fibers. We get the lower bound by constructing contact structures using Legendrian surgery. We use convex surface theory to obtain the upper bound.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.09490v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tanushree Shah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagrammatic representations of 3-periodic entanglements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14254v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Diagrams enable the use of various algebraic and geometric tools for analysing and classifying knots. In this paper we introduce a new diagrammatic representation of triply periodic entangled structures (TP tangles), which are embeddings of simple curves in $\mathbb{R}^3$ that are invariant under translations along three non-coplanar axes. As such, these entanglements can be seen as preimages of links embedded in the 3-torus $\mathbb{T}^3 = \mathbb{S}^1 \times \mathbb{S}^1 \times \mathbb{S}^1$ in its universal cover $\mathbb{R}^3$, where two non-isotopic links in $\mathbb{T}^3$ may possess the same TP tangle preimage. We consider the equivalence of TP tangles in $\mathbb{R}^3$ through the use of diagrams representing links in $\mathbb{T}^3$. These diagrams require additional moves beyond the classical Reidemeister moves, which we define and show that they preserve ambient isotopies of links in $\mathbb{T}^3$. The final definition of a tridiagram of a link in $\mathbb{T}^3$ allows us to then consider additional notions of equivalence relating non-isotopic links in $\mathbb{T}^3$ that possess the same TP tangle preimage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14254v4</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.topol.2025.109346</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Topology and its Applications 368 (2025) 109346</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Toky Andriamanalina, Myfanwy E. Evans, Sonia Mahmoudi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative cubulation of relative strict hyperbolization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.14946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.14946v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that many relatively hyperbolic groups obtained by relative strict hyperbolization admit a cocompact action on a CAT(0) cubical complex. Under suitable assumptions on the peripheral subgroups, these groups are residually finite and even virtually special. We include some applications to the theory of manifolds, such as the construction of new non-positively curved Riemannian manifolds with residually finite fundamental group, and the existence of non-triangulable aspherical manifolds with virtually special fundamental group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.14946v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1112/jlms.70093</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Groves, Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Lafont, Jason Fox Manning, Lorenzo Ruffoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coarse group theoretic study on stable mixed commutator length</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.08618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.08618v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $G$ be a group and $N$ a normal subgroup of $G$. We study the large scale behavior, not the exact values themselves, of the stable mixed commutator length $scl_{G,N}$ on the mixed commutator subgroup $[G,N]$; when $N=G$, $scl_{G,N}$ equals the stable commutator length $scl_G$ on the commutator subgroup $[G,G]$. For this purpose, we regard $scl_{G,N}$ not only as a function from $[G,N]$ to $\mathbb{R}_{\geq 0}$, but as a bi-invariant metric function $d^+_{scl_{G,N}}$ from $[G,N]\times [G,N]$ to $\mathbb{R}_{\geq 0}$. Our main focus is coarse group theoretic structures of $([G,N],d^+_{scl_{G,N}})$. Our preliminary result (the absolute version) connects, via the Bavard duality, $([G,N],d^+_{scl_{G,N}})$ and the quotient vector space of the space of $G$-invariant quasimorphisms on $N$ over one of such homomorphisms. In particular, we prove that the dimension of this vector space equals the asymptotic dimension of $([G,N],d^+_{scl_{G,N}})$.
  Our main result is the comparative version: we connect the coarse kernel, formulated by Leitner and Vigolo, of the coarse homomorphism $\iota_{G,N}\colon ([G,N],d^+_{scl_{G,N}})\to ([G,N],d^+_{scl_{G}})$; $y\mapsto y$, and a certain quotient vector space $W(G,N)$ of the space of invariant quasimorphisms. Assume that $N=[G,G]$ and that $W(G,N)$ is finite dimensional with dimension $\ell$. Then we prove that the coarse kernel of $\iota_{G,N}$ is isomorphic to $\mathbb{Z}^{\ell}$ as a coarse group. In contrast to the absolute version, the space $W(G,N)$ is finite dimensional in many cases, including all $(G,N)$ with finitely generated $G$ and nilpotent $G/N$. As an application of our result, given a group homomorphism $\varphi\colon G\to H$ between finitely generated groups, we define an $\mathbb{R}$-linear map `inside' the groups, which is dual to the naturally defined $\mathbb{R}$-linear map from $W(H,[H,H])$ to $W(G,[G,G])$ induced by $\varphi$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.08618v4</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Morimichi Kawasaki, Mitsuaki Kimura, Shuhei Maruyama, Takahiro Matsushita, Masato Mimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strongly adapted contact geometry of Anosov 3-flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21208v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide a 3 dimensional contact geometric characterization of Anosov 3-flows based on interactions with Reeb dynamics. We investigate basic properties of the space of the resulting geometries and in particular show that such space is homotopy equivalent to the space of Anosov 3-flows. A technical theorem on the asymptotic synchronization of adapted norms is proved, which can be of broader interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21208v3</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11784-025-01180-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Fixed Point Theory Appl. 27, 37 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Surena Hozoori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Poincar\'e Surgery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20052v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We exhibit a homotopy theoretic proof of the Fundamental Theorem of Poincar\'e surgery in the simply connected case. We also deduce the Poincar\'e transversality exact sequence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20052v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John R. Klein</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
