<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.GT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT</link>
    <description>math.GT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.GT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 05:01:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo-Anosov flows, hyperbolic geometry, and the curve graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11595v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Starting with a pseudo-Anosov flow $\varphi$ on a closed hyperbolic $3$-manifold $M$ and an embedded surface $S \subset M$ that is (almost) transverse to $\varphi$, we relate the hyperbolic geometry of $M$ (e.g. volume, circumference, short geodesics) to dynamical invariants of $\varphi$ encoded by the curve graph of $S$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11595v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junzhi Huang, Samuel J. Taylor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A partial classification of 3-dimensional clasp number two, genus two fibered knots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The 3-dimensional clasp number $cl(K)$ of a knot $K$ is the minimum number of clasp singularities of clasp disk, a singular immersed disk bounding $K$ whose singular set consists of only clasp singularities. We give a classification of clasp number two, genus two fibered knots under the assumption that they admit a clasp disk of certain type which we call of type II.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11612v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tetsuya Ito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A resistance invariant of special alternating links</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12226v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a new numerical invariant for special, reduced, alternating diagrams of oriented knots and links, defined in terms of the Laplacian matrix of the associated Tait graph. For a special alternating diagram, the Laplacian encodes both the combinatorics of the checkerboard graph and the crossing signs. While its spectrum depends on the chosen diagram, we show that a specific quadratic trace expression involving the Laplacian and its Moore-Penrose pseudoinverse is invariant under flype moves. The invariant admits an interpretation in terms of total effective resistance of the associated weighted graph viewed as an electrical network. Explicit computations for pairs of flype-related diagrams demonstrate that, although the Laplacian characteristic polynomials differ, the invariant FP coincides. Values for several prime alternating knots are provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12226v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michal Jablonowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-contractible loops of Legendrian tori from families of knots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11538v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the unit cotangent bundle of $\mathbb{R}^3$, we consider loops of Legendrian tori arising as families of the unit conormal bundles of smooth knots in $\mathbb{R}^3$. In this paper, using the cord algebra of knots, we give a topological method to compute the monodromy on the Legendrian contact homology in degree $0$ induced by those loops. As an application, we obtain an infinite family of non-contractible loops of Legendrian tori which are contractible in the space of smoothly embedded tori.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11538v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yukihiro Okamoto, Mari\'an Poppr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The higher connectivity at infinity of mapping class groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12191v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The higher connectivity at infinity for mapping class groups of surfaces with boundary components and punctures is understood with the exceptions of the mapping class groups for the closed surfaces of genus 3 and 4. In this paper we prove a general simply connected at infinity result for finitely presented groups that implies all mapping class groups of closed surfaces of genus $\geq 3$ are simply connected at infinity. As these groups are duality groups the Proper Hurewicz Theorem implies that they are $(n-2)$-connected at infinity where $n$ is the dimension of the group. Combining this result with earlier work we give a complete list of all mapping class groups and their connectivity at infinity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12191v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Mihalik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On real algebraic realization of round fold maps of codimension $-1$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12211v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The canonical projections of the unit spheres are generalized to special generic maps and round fold maps, for example. They are generalizations from the viewpoint of singularity theory of differentiable maps and these maps restrict the topologies and the differentiable structures of the manifolds.
  We are concerned with round fold maps, defined as smooth maps locally represented as the product map of a Morse function and the identity map on a smooth manifold, and maps with singular value sets being concentric spheres. A bit different from differential topology, we are concerned with real algebraic geometric aspects of these maps. We discuss real algebraic realization of round fold maps of codimension $-1$ as our new work. Real algebraic realization of these maps is of fundamental and important studies in real algebraic geometry and a new study recently developing mainly due to the author.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12211v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoki Kitazawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A short proof of the Patak-Tancer theorem on non-embeddability of $k$-complexes in $2k$-manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.14010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2106.14010v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In 2019 P. Patak and M. Tancer obtained the following higher-dimensional generalization of the Heawood inequality on embeddings of graphs into surfaces. We present a short well-structured proof accessible to non-specialists in the field. Let $\Delta_n^k$ be the union of $k$-dimensional faces of the $n$-dimensional simplex.
  Theorem. (a) If $\Delta_n^k$ PL embeds into the connected sum of $g$ copies of the Cartesian product $S^k\times S^k$ of two $k$-dimensional spheres, then $g\ge\dfrac{n-2k-1}{k+2}$.
  (b) If $\Delta_n^k$ PL embeds into a closed $(k-1)$-connected PL $2k$-manifold $M$, then $(-1)^k(\chi(M)-2)\ge\dfrac{n-2k-1}{k+1}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2106.14010v4</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Kogan, A. Skopenkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cobordism maps in Khovanov homology and singular instanton homology I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.12095v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Khovanov homology and singular instanton Floer homology are both functorial with respect to link cobordisms. Although the two homology groups are related by a spectral sequence, direct correspondence between the cobordism maps has not been rigorously established. In this paper, we define a cobordism map on the instanton cube complex as a filtered chain map, and prove that it recovers the cobordism maps both in Khovanov homology and singular instanton theory. In a sequel paper, we further extend this cobordism map to immersed cobordisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12095v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hayato Imori, Taketo Sano, Kouki Sato, Masaki Taniguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vassiliev invariants for virtual knotoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20269v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce the 0-smoothing invariant $\mathcal{F}$ of virtual knotoids constructed from local modification at classical crossings, which take values in a free $\mathbb Z$-module generated by non-oriented flat virtual knotoids. We prove that $\mathcal{F}$ is a Vassiliev invariant of order one. It was observed by Henrich that smoothing invariant she constructed for virtual knots provides less information than the gluing invariant. We demonstrate the same property for the 0-smoothing invariant of virtual knotoids: $\mathcal{F}$ provides less information than the gluing invariant introduced by Petit. To prove this result, we use the extension of the singular based matrix invariant originally introduced by Turaev for singular virtual strings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20269v3</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siqi Ding, Xiaobo Jin, Fengchun Lei, Fengling Li, Andrei Vesnin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dehn Twist Action for Quantum Representations of Mapping Class Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.16020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.16020v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We calculate the Dehn twist action on the spaces of conformal blocks of a not necessarily semisimple modular category. In particular, we give the order of the Dehn twists under the mapping class group representations of closed surfaces. For Dehn twists about non-separating simple closed curves, we prove that this order is the order of the ribbon twist, thereby generalizing a result that De Renzi-Gainutdinov-Geer-Patureau-Mirand-Runkel obtained for the small quantum group. In the separating case, we express the order using the order of the ribbon twist on monoidal powers of the canonical end. As an application, we prove that the Johnson kernels of the mapping class groups act trivially if and only if for the canonical end the ribbon twist and double braiding with itself are trivial. We give a similar result for the visibility of the Torelli groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.16020v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Top. 18(3), 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lukas M\"uller, Lukas Woike</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum invariants arising from $U_h\mathfrak{sl}(2|1)$ are q-holonomic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12882v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that the quantum invariants arising from typical representations of the quantum group $U_h\mathfrak{sl}(2|1)$ are q-holonomic. In particular, this implies the existence of an underlying field theory for which this family of invariants are partition functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12882v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jennifer Brown, Nathan Geer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The asymptoticity of extremal length in Teichm\"uller space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06314</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06314v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the asymptotic behavior of extremal length along Teichm\"uller rays. Specifically, we determine the limit of extremal length along a Teichm\"uller ray and obtain an explicit expression for this limit, which complements a related formula established by Cormac Walsh. Building on this result and Kerckhoff's formula, we establish a formula for the limiting Teichm\"uller distance between two points moving along arbitrary pairs of Teichm\"uller rays. Furthermore, we derive a necessary and sufficient condition for two Teichm\"uller rays to be asymptotic. Finally, by shifting the initial points of the Teichm\"uller rays along their associated Teichm\"uller geodesics, we show that the minimum of the limiting Teichm\"uller distance coincides with the detour metric between the endpoints of the rays on the horofunction boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06314v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhiyang Lyu, Yi Qi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
