<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 02:44:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Pooling Solvent Mixtures for Solvation Free Energy Predictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01982v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Solvation free energy is an important design parameter in reaction kinetics and separation processes, making it a critical property to predict during process development. In previous research, directed message passing neural networks (D-MPNN) have successfully been used to predict solvation free energies and enthalpies in organic solvents. However, solvent mixtures provide greater flexibility for optimizing solvent interactions than monosolvents. This work aims to extend our previous models to mixtures. To handle mixtures in a permutation invariant manner we propose a pooling function; MolPool. With this pooling function, the machine learning models can learn and predict properties for an arbitrary number of molecules. The novel SolProp-mix software that applies MolPool to D-MPNN was compared to state-of-the-art architectures for predicting mixture properties and validated with our new database of COSMOtherm calculations; BinarySolv-QM. To improve predictions towards experimental accuracy, the network was then fine-tuned on experimental data in monosolvents. To demonstrate the benefit of this transfer learning methodology, experimental datasets of solvation free energies in binary (BinarySolv-Exp) and ternary (TernarySolv-Exp) solvent mixtures were compiled from data on vapor-liquid equilibria and activity coefficients. The neural network performed better than COSMOtherm calculations with an MAE of 0.25 kcal/mol and an RMSE of 0.37 kcal/mol for non-aqueous mixed solvents. Additionally, the ability to capture trends for a varying mixture composition was validated successfully. Our model's ability to accurately predict mixture properties from the combination of in silico data and pure component experimental data is promising given the scarcity of experimental data for mixtures in many fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01982v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roel J. Leenhouts, Nathan Morgan, Emad Al Ibrahim, William H. Green, Florence H. Vermeire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra low-cost fabrication of homogeneous alginate hydrogel microspheres in symmetry designed microfluidic device</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02404v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we present a two-stage method for fabricating monodisperse alginate hydrogel microspheres using a symmetrically designed flow-focusing microfluidic device. One of the flow-focusing junctions generates alginate hydrogel droplets without the addition of surfactants, while the other junction introduces corn oil with acetic acid, which facilitates the solidification of the homogeneous alginate hydrogel droplets and prevents coalescence. These hydrogel microspheres can be easily separated from the oil phase using an oscillation state, eliminating the need for a demulsifier. This microfluidic system for hydrogel microsphere formation is notable for its simplicity, ease of fabrication, and user-friendliness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02404v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qing Qin, Yu Zhang, Yubei Wei,  Jinnuo,  Lv, Meiling Tian, Yuanyuan Sun,  Xingjian,  Huang, Jianglin Li,  Yifeng,  Su, Xiaoliang Xiang, Xing Hu, Zhizhi Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Designing Optically Addressable Nitrogen-Vacancy Centers in Ultra-Small Nanodiamonds: Insights from First-Principles Calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01976</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01976v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultrasmall nanodiamonds (USNDs) are promising platforms for fluorescent and quantum sensing applications. Here we present first-principles electronic structure calculations of color centers in USNDs, specifically the nitrogen-vacancy (NV-) and we investigate their optical addressability as a function of the surface termination. We consider both isolated nanoparticles and arrays of USNDs with different degrees of packing, and we include quantum vibronic effects in our analysis, using stochastic methods. We find that the NV in USNDs can be stabilized in a negative charge state if the nanoparticles are terminated by fluorine, hydroxyl, and ether. While fluorine terminations can be used for fluorescent bio-tags, we suggest that hydroxyl and ether terminations are beneficial for quantum sensing applications. We also find that the NV- can be stabilized in arrays of USNDs when inter-particle separations are larger than the diameter of the nanoparticle. Interestingly, the phonon renormalizations of single-particle energy levels found in arrays contribute to the charge stability of negatively charged NV centers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01976v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpan Kundu, Francesco Martinelli, Giulia Galli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sublayers Editing of Covalent MAX Phase for Nanolaminated Early Transition Metal Compounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02157</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02157v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two-dimensional transition metal carbides and nitrides (MXenes) have gained popularity in fields such as energy storage, catalysis, and electromagnetic interference due to their diverse elemental compositions and variable surface terminations (T). Generally, the synthesis of MXene materials involves etching the weak M-A metallic bonds in the ternary layered transition metal carbides and nitrides (MAX phase) using HF acid or Lewis acid molten salts, while the strong M-X covalent bonds preserve the two-dimensional framework structure of MXenes. On the other hand, the MAX phase material family also includes a significant class of members where the A site is occupied by non-metal main group elements (such as sulfur and phosphorus), in which both M-A and M-X are covalent bond-type sublayers. The aforementioned etching methods cannot be used to synthesize MXene materials from these parent phases. In this work, we discovered that the covalent bond-type M-A and M-X sublayers exhibit different reactivity with some inorganic materials in a high-temperature molten state. By utilizing this difference in reactivity, we can structurally modify these covalent sublayers, allowing for the substitution of elements at the X site (from B to Se, S, P, C) and converting non-metal A site atoms in non-van der Waals (non-vdW) MAX phases into surface atoms in vdW layered materials. This results in a family of early transition metal Xide chalcogenides (TMXCs) that exhibit lattice characteristics of both MXenes and transition metal chalcogenides. Using electron-donor chemical scissors, these TMXC layered materials can be further exfoliated into monolayer nanosheets. The atomic configurations of each atom in these monolayer TMXCs are the same as those of conventional MXenes, but the oxidation states of the M-site atoms can be regulated by both X-site atoms and intercalated cations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02157v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziqian Li, Ke Chen, Xudong Wang, Kan Luo, Lei Lei, Mian Li, Kun Liang, Degao Wang, Shiyu Du, Zhifang Chai, Qing Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurements and simulations of rate coefficients for the deuterated forms of the H2 + + H2 and H3 + + H2 reactive systems at low temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02206v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rate coefficients of various isotopic variations of the H2+ + H2 and H3+ + H2 reactions in the 10-250 K temperature range were measured using a cryogenic 22 pole radio frequency ion trap. The processes involving diatomic ions were found to behave close to the Langevin rate, whereas temperature-dependent rate coefficients were obtained for the four isotopic exchange processes with triatomic ions. Fitting the experimental data using a chemical code allowed us in specific cases to constrain rate coefficients that were not directly measured in the ion trap. The reported rate coefficients suggest a more efficient hydrogenation of deuterated H3+ forms than usually assumed in astrochemical models, which might affect deuteration rates in warmer environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02206v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202451757</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Jim\'enez-Redondo, Olli Sipil\"a, Pavol Jusko, Paola Caselli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensitive Low-Recoil VUV 1+1$'$ REMPI Detection of ND$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02330v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In molecular beam scattering experiments, an important technique for measuring product energy and angular distributions is velocity map imaging following photoionization. For studies with cold molecular beams, the resolution is often limited by the product detection process. When state-selective ionization detection is used, excess photon energy can transfer to kinetic energy in the molecular ion-electron pair, resulting in measurable cation recoil. With advanced molecular beam technology, velocity spreads as small as a few m/s are possible. Thus, a suitable product detection scheme must be not only sensitive, state-selective, and background-free, it must also produce less cation recoil than the velocity spread of the molecular beams. To date this has only been possible with the NO molecule. Our goal here is to extend this low-recoil capability to fully deuterated ammonia, ND$_3$. We present a resonance-enhanced multi-photon ionization (REMPI) detection scheme for ND$_3$, that imparts sufficiently low ion recoil, allowing, for the first time, high-resolution imaging of ND$_3$ products in a cold ND$_3$-HD scattering experiment. The first step of the 1+1$'$ REMPI scheme requires vacuum ultra-violet (VUV) photons of ~160 nm, which are generated through four-wave-mixing in Xe. We varied the wavelength of the second, ionization step between 434 and 458 nm, exciting ND$_3$ to a wide range of autoionizing neutral states. By velocity mapping the resulting photoelectrons, it was possible to fully chart the ion recoil across this range with vibrational resolution for the final ionic states. Additionally, rotational resolution in the photoionization dynamics was achieved for selected excitation energies near one of the vibrational thresholds. Many of the peaks in the spectrum of autoionizing Rydberg states are assigned to specific Rydberg series using a simple Rydberg formula model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02330v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.jpca.4c06253</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Stach E. J. Kuijpers, Panagiotis Kalaitzis, Evangelia Sakkoula, Sebastiaan Y. T. van de Meerakker, Timothy P. Softley, David H. Parker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perspective: Time irreversibility in systems observed at coarse resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02675v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A broken time-reversal symmetry, i.e. broken detailed balance, is central to non-equilibrium physics and is a prerequisite for life. However, it turns out to be quite challenging to unambiguously define and quantify time-reversal symmetry (and violations thereof) in practice, that is, from observations. Measurements on complex systems have a finite resolution and generally probe low-dimensional projections of the underlying dynamics, which are well known to introduce memory. In situations where many microscopic states become "lumped" onto the same observable "state" or when introducing "reaction coordinates" to reduce the dimensionality of data, signatures of a broken time-reversal symmetry in the microscopic dynamics become distorted or masked. In this perspective we highlight why in defining and discussing time-reversal symmetry, and quantifying its violations, the precise underlying assumptions on the microscopic dynamics, the coarse graining, and further reductions, are not a technical detail. These assumptions decide whether the conclusions that are drawn are physically sound or inconsistent. We summarize recent findings in the field and reflect upon key challenges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02675v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cai Dieball, Alja\v{z} Godec</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-Heterogeneity of the F\"orster Radius from Dipole Orientational Dynamics Impacts Single-Molecule FRET Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09883v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: F\"orster resonance energy transfer (FRET) is a quantum mechanical phenomenon involving the non-radiative transfer of energy between coupled electric dipoles. Due to the strong dependence of FRET on the distance between the dipoles, it is frequently used as a ``molecular ruler" in biology, chemistry, and physics. This is done by placing dipolar molecules called dyes on molecules of interest. In time-resolved confocal single-molecule FRET (smFRET) experiments, the joint distribution of the FRET efficiency and the donor fluorescence lifetime can reveal underlying molecular conformational dynamics via deviation from their theoretical F\"orster relationship. This deviation is referred to as a dynamic shift. Quantifying the dynamic shift caused by the motion of the fluorescent dyes is essential to decoupling the dynamics of the studied molecules and the dyes. We develop novel Langevin models for the dye linker dynamics, including rotational dynamics, based on first principle physics and proper dye linker chemistry to match accessible volumes predicted by molecular dynamics simulations. By simulating the dyes' stochastic translational and rotational dynamics, we show that the observed dynamic shift can largely be attributed to the mutual orientational dynamics of the electric dipole moments associated with the dyes, not their accessible volume. Our models provide the most up-to-date and accurate estimation of FRET.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09883v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Frost, Keisha Cook, Hugo Sanabria</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bending, breaking, and reconnecting of the electrical double layers at heterogeneous electrodes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01339v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In electrochemical systems, the structure of electrical double layers (EDLs) near electrode surfaces is crucial for energy conversion and storage functions. While the electrodes in real-world systems are usually heterogeneous, to date the investigation of EDLs is mainly limited to flat model solid surfaces. To bridge this gap, here we image the EDL structure of an ionic liquid-based electrolyte at a heterogeneous graphite electrode using our recently developed electrochemical 3D atomic force microscopy. These interfaces feature the formation of thin, nanoscale adlayer/cluster domains that closely mimic the early-stage solid-electrolyte interphases in many battery systems. We observe multiple discrete layers in the EDL near the flat electrode, which restructures at the heterogeneous interphase sites. Depending on the local size of the interphase clusters, the EDLs exhibit bending, breaking, and/or reconnecting behaviors, likely due to the combined steric and long-range interaction effects. These results shed light on the fundamental structure and reconfiguration mechanism of EDLs at heterogeneous interfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01339v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qian Ai, Lalith Krishna Samanth Bonagiri, Kaustubh S. Panse, Jaehyeon Kim, Shan Zhou, Yingjie Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpolation and differentiation of alchemical degrees of freedom in machine learning interatomic potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10746v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Machine learning interatomic potentials (MLIPs) have become a workhorse of modern atomistic simulations, and recently published universal MLIPs, pre-trained on large datasets, have demonstrated remarkable accuracy and generalizability. However, the computational cost of MLIPs limits their applicability to chemically disordered systems requiring large simulation cells or to sample-intensive statistical methods. Here, we report the use of continuous and differentiable alchemical degrees of freedom in atomistic materials simulations, exploiting the fact that graph neural network MLIPs represent discrete elements as real-valued tensors. The proposed method introduces alchemical atoms with corresponding weights into the input graph, alongside modifications to the message-passing and readout mechanisms of MLIPs, and allows smooth interpolation between the compositional states of materials. The end-to-end differentiability of MLIPs enables efficient calculation of the gradient of energy with respect to the compositional weights. With this modification, we propose methodologies for optimizing the composition of solid solutions towards target macroscopic properties, characterizing order and disorder in multicomponent oxides, and conducting alchemical free energy simulations to quantify the free energy of vacancy formation and composition changes. The approach offers an avenue for extending the capabilities of universal MLIPs in the modeling of compositional disorder and characterizing the phase stability of complex materials systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10746v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juno Nam, Jiayu Peng, Rafael G\'omez-Bombarelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal bound states and resonances with Coulomb plus short-range potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06011</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06011v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study charged particles in three dimensions interacting via a short-range potential in addition to the Coulomb potential. When the Bohr radius and the scattering length are much larger than the potential range, low-energy physics of the system becomes independent from details of the short-range potential. We develop the zero-range theory to describe such universal physics in terms of the Bohr radius and the scattering length by generalizing the Bethe-Peierls boundary condition, which is then applied to two charged particles to reveal their bound states and resonances. Infinite resonances are found for a repulsive Coulomb potential, one of which turns into a bound state with increasing inverse scattering length, whereas infinite bound states exist for an attractive Coulomb potential with no resonances at any scattering length. The zero-range theory is also applied to three equally charged particles at infinite scattering length under the variational Born-Oppenheimer approximation. We find that the effective potential between two heavy particles induced by a light particle is an inverse-square attraction at distances shorter than the Bohr radius, leading to infinite deep bound states, whereas shallow ones successively turn into resonances with increasing Coulomb repulsion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06011v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.110.064001</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. C 110, 064001 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shunta Mochizuki, Yusuke Nishida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling scale-up of particle coating by atomic layer deposition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13116v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Atomic layer deposition (ALD) is a promising technique to functionalize particle surfaces for energy applications including energy storage, catalysis, and decarbonization. In this work, we present a set of models of ALD particle coating to explore the transition from lab scale to manufacturing. Our models encompass the main particle coating manufacturing approaches including rotary bed, fluidized bed, and continuously vibrating reactors. These models provide key metrics, such as throughput and precursor utilization, required to evaluate the scalability of ALD manufacturing approaches and their feasibility in the context of energy applications. Our results show that designs that force the precursor to flow through fluidized particles transition faster to a transport-limited regime where throughput is maximized. They also exhibit higher precursor utilization. In the context of continuous processes, our models indicate that it is possible to achieve self-extinguishing processes with almost 100% precursor utilization. A comparison with past experimental results of ALD in fluidized bed reactors shows excellent qualitative and quantitative agreement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13116v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angel Yanguas-Gil, Jeffrey W. Elam</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
