<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 04:00:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Photon correlation time-asymmetry and dynamical coherence in multichromophoric systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16892v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate polarization-filtered two-photon correlations for the light emitted by a multichromophoric system undergoing excitation transport under realistic exciton-phonon interactions, and subject to continuous incoherent illumination. We show that for a biomolecular aggregate, such as the Fenna-Matthews Olson (FMO) photosynthetic complex, time-asymmetries in the cross-correlations of photons corresponding to different polarizations can be exploited to probe both quantum coherent transport mechanisms and steady-state coherence properties, which are not witnessed by zero-delay correlations. A classical bound on correlation asymmetry is obtained, which FMO is shown to violate using exact numerical calculations. Our analysis indicates that the dominant contributions to time-asymmetry in such photon cross-correlations are population to coherence transfer for Frenkel-Exciton models. Our results therefore put forward photon correlation asymmetry as a promising approach to investigate coherent contributions to excited-stated dynamics in molecular aggregates and other many-site quantum emitters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16892v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charlie Nation, Hallmann Oskar Gestsson, Alexandra Olaya-Castro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HEroBM: a deep equivariant graph neural network for universal backmapping from coarse-grained to all-atom representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Molecular simulations have assumed a paramount role in the fields of chemistry, biology, and material sciences, being able to capture the intricate dynamic properties of systems. Within this realm, coarse-grained (CG) techniques have emerged as invaluable tools to sample large-scale systems and reach extended timescales by simplifying system representation. However, CG approaches come with a trade-off: they sacrifice atomistic details that might hold significant relevance in deciphering the investigated process. Therefore, a recommended approach is to identify key CG conformations and process them using backmapping methods, which retrieve atomistic coordinates. Currently, rule-based methods yield subpar geometries and rely on energy relaxation, resulting in less-than-optimal outcomes. Conversely, machine learning techniques offer higher accuracy but are either limited in transferability between systems or tied to specific CG mappings. In this work, we introduce HEroBM, a dynamic and scalable method that employs deep equivariant graph neural networks and a hierarchical approach to achieve high-resolution backmapping. HEroBM handles any type of CG mapping, offering a versatile and efficient protocol for reconstructing atomistic structures with high accuracy. Focused on local principles, HEroBM spans the entire chemical space and is transferable to systems of varying sizes. We illustrate the versatility of our framework through diverse biological systems, including a complex real-case scenario. Here, our end-to-end backmapping approach accurately generates the atomistic coordinates of a G protein-coupled receptor bound to an organic small molecule within a cholesterol/phospholipid bilayer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16911v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Angioletti, Stefano Raniolo, Vittorio Limongelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive atomic basis sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16942v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Atomic basis sets are widely employed within quantum mechanics based simulations of matter. We introduce a machine learning model that adapts the basis set to the local chemical environment of each atom, prior to the start of self consistent field (SCF) calculations. In particular, as a proof of principle and because of their historic popularity, we have studied the Gaussian type orbitals from the Pople basis set, i.e. the STO-3G, 3-21G, 6-31G and 6-31G*. We adapt the basis by scaling the variance of the radial Gaussian functions leading to contraction or expansion of the atomic orbitals.A data set of optimal scaling factors for C, H, O, N and F were obtained by variational minimization of the Hartree-Fock (HF) energy of the smallest 2500 organic molecules from the QM9 database. Kernel ridge regression based machine learning (ML) prediction errors of the change in scaling decay rapidly with training set size, typically reaching less than 1 % for training set size 2000. Overall, we find systematically lower variance, and consequently the larger training efficiencies, when going from hydrogen to carbon to nitrogen to oxygen. Using the scaled basis functions obtained from the ML model, we conducted HF calculations for the subsequent 30'000 molecules in QM9. In comparison to the corresponding default Pople basis set results we observed improved energetics in up to 99 % of all cases. With respect to the larger basis set 6-311G(2df,2pd), atomization energy errors are lowered on average by ~31, 107, 11, and 11 kcal/mol for STO-3G, 3-21G, 6-31G and 6-31G*, respectively -- with negligible computational overhead. We illustrate the high transferability of adaptive basis sets for larger out-of-domain molecules relevant to addiction, diabetes, pain, aging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16942v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Danish Khan, Maximilian L. Ach, O. Anatole von Lilienfeld</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolving the size and charge of small particles: a predictive model of nanopore mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17115v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The movement of small particles and molecules through membranes is widespread and has far-reaching implications. Consequently, the development of mathematical models is essential for understanding these processes on a micro level, leading to deeper insights. In this endeavour, we suggested a model based on a set of empirical equations to predict the transport of substances through a solid-state nanopore and the associated signals generated during their translocation. This model establishes analytical relationships between the ionic current and electrical double-layer potential observed during ana-lyte translocation and their size, charge, and mobility in an electrolyte solution. This framework allows for rapid interpretation and prediction of the nanopore system's behaviour and provides a means for quantitatively determining the physical properties of molecular analytes. To illustrate the analyt-ical capability of this model, ceria nanoparticles were investigated while undergoing oxidation or reduction within an original nanopore device. The re-sults obtained were found to be in good agreement with predictions from physicochemical methods. This developed approach and model possess transfer-able utility to various porous materials, thereby expediting research efforts in membrane characterization and the advancement of nano- and ultrafiltra-tion or electrodialysis technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17115v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Bearden, Tigran M. Abramyan, Dmitry Gil, Jessica Johnson, Anton Murashko, Sergei Makaev, David Mai, Alexander Baranchikov, Vladimir Ivanov, Vladimir Reukov, Guigen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Converging TDDFT calculations in 5 iterations with minimal auxiliary preconditioning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17133v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Eigenvalue problems and linear systems of equations involving large symmetric matrices are commonly solved in quantum chemistry using Krylov space methods, such as the Davidson algorithm. The preconditioner is a key component of Krylov space methods that accelerates convergence by improving the quality of new guesses at each iteration. We systematically design a new preconditioner for time-dependent density functional theory (TDDFT) calculations based on the recently introduced TDDFT-ris semiempirical model by re-tuning the empirical scaling factor and the angular momenta of a minimal auxiliary basis. The final preconditioner produced includes up to $d$-functions in the auxiliary basis and is named "rid". The rid preconditioner converges excitation energies and polarizabilities in 5-6 iterations on average, a factor of 2-3 faster than the conventional diagonal preconditioner, without changing the converged results. Thus, the rid preconditioner is a broadly applicable and efficient preconditioner for TDDFT calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17133v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zehao Zhou, Shane M. Parker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isotope effect in the Morse approximation of the ground state term of hydrogen molecule nH2, n = 1-7. Herzberg anomaly and anharmonicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17328v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The influence of the reduced mass on the results of the approximation by the Morse function of the ground electronic state term potential U(r) of hydrogen molecule nH2 for seven symmetrical isotopologues n = 1-7 is investigated. For each isotopologue, two alternative model solutions of the Schroedinger equation are obtained, namely, M1(r) and M2(r) functions, which differ by the selection of the primary fitting parameters in the Morse approximation. The U(r) - M(r) functions are shown to clearly visualize the differences between the shapes of the potential at its approximation. The concept of systematic deviation of Morse functions from the real potential is introduced. This deviation is always present in the approximation of simple terms, for which U(r) curve lies between M1(r) and M2(r) without crossings. In case of nH2, for M1(r) the systematic monotonous deviation increases, reaching 1700-2770 cm-1 (for 7H2-1H2) at the level of the asymptote. For M2(r) the systematic deviation decreases at larger distances: it is dome-shaped with a maximum of ca. 1500 cm-1 in the upper part of the term, after which it falls to zero. The M2(r) curves for different isotopologues diverge by less than 20 cm-1. There are also anomalies, where M1(r) and M2(r) cross U(r), called "Herzberg anomaly". For example, at around r = 1.08 A the U(r) - M2(r) function shows anomalous negative values ranging from -125 cm-1 (for 1H2) to -142 cm-1 (for 7H2). The diagnostic value of Herzberg anomaly and anharmonicities for various isotopologues is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17328v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gleb S. Denisov, Edem R. Chakalov, Peter M. Tolstoy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vibrational coherences in half-broadband 2D electronic spectroscopy: spectral filtering to identify excited state displacements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17362v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vibrational coherences in ultrafast pump-probe (PP) and 2D electronic spectroscopy (2DES) provide insight into the excited state dynamics of molecules. Femtosecond coherence spectra (FCS) and 2D beat maps yield information about displacements of excited state surfaces for key vibrational modes. Half-broadband 2DES (HB2DES) uses a PP configuration with a white light continuum probe to extend the detection range and resolve vibrational coherences in the excited state absorption (ESA). However, interpretation of these spectra is difficult as they are strongly dependent on the spectrum of the pump laser and the relative displacement of the excited states along the vibrational coordinates. We demonstrate the impact of these convoluting factors for a model based upon cresyl violet. Careful consideration of the position of the pump spectrum can be a powerful tool in resolving the ESA coherences to gain insights into excited state displacements. The paper also highlights the need for caution in considering the spectral window of the pulse when interpreting these spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17362v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dale Green, Giovanni Bressan, Ismael A. Heisler, Stephen R. Meech, Garth A. Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enzymatic Aggregation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17026v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce an autocatalytic aggregation model in which the rate at which two clusters merge to form a cluster is controlled by the presence of a third "enzymatic" cluster whose mass must equal to the mass of one of the reaction partners. The enzyme is unaffected by the joining event and is available to either participate in or catalyze subsequent reactions. This model is meant to mimic the self-replicating reactions that occur in models for the origin of life. We solve the kinetics of enzymatic aggregation in the model with mass-independent rates and show that the total cluster density decays as $t^{-1/3}$, while the density of clusters of any fixed mass decays as $t^{-2/3}$. These behaviors contrast with the corresponding $t^{-1}$ and $t^{-2}$ scalings for classic aggregation. We extend our model to mass-dependent reaction rates, to situations where only "magic" mass clusters can catalyze reactions, and to include steady monomer input.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17026v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. L. Krapivsky, S. Redner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultralow-Power Single-Sensor-Based E-Nose System Powered by Duty Cycling and Deep Learning for Real-Time Gas Identification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17130v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study presents a novel, ultralow-power single-sensor-based electronic nose (e-nose) system for real-time gas identification, distinguishing itself from conventional sensor-array-based e-nose systems whose power consumption and cost increase with the number of sensors. Our system employs a single metal oxide semiconductor (MOS) sensor built on a suspended 1D nanoheater, driven by duty cycling-characterized by repeated pulsed power inputs. The sensor's ultrafast thermal response, enabled by its small size, effectively decouples the effects of temperature and surface charge exchange on the MOS nanomaterial's conductivity. This provides distinct sensing signals that alternate between responses coupled with and decoupled from the thermally enhanced conductivity, all within a single time domain during duty cycling. The magnitude and ratio of these dual responses vary depending on the gas type and concentration, facilitating the early-stage gas identification of five gas types within 30 s via a convolutional neural network (classification accuracy = 93.9%, concentration regression error = 19.8%). Additionally, the duty-cycling mode significantly reduces power consumption by up to 90%, lowering it to 160 $\mu$W to heat the sensor to 250$^\circ$C. Manufactured using only wafer-level batch microfabrication processes, this innovative e-nose system promises the facile implementation of battery-driven, long-term, and cost-effective IoT monitoring systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17130v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taejung Kim, Yonggi Kim, Wootaek Cho, Jong-Hyun Kwak, Jeonghoon Cho, Youjang Pyeon, Jae Joon Kim, Heungjoo Shin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the Boson Peaks in Amorphous Phase-Change Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17226v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Boson peak is a universal phenomenon in amorphous solids. It can be observed as an anomalous contribution to the low-temperature heat capacity over the Debye model. Amorphous phase-change materials (PCMs) such as Ge-Sb-Te are a family of poor glass formers with fast crystallization kinetics, being of interest for phase-change memory applications. So far, whether Boson peaks exist in PCMs is unknown and, if they do, their relevance to PCM properties is unclear. Here, we investigate the thermodynamic properties of the pseudo-binary compositions on the tie-line between Ge15Te85 and Ge15Sb85 from a few Kelvins to the liquidus temperatures. Our results demonstrate the evidence of the pronounced Boson peaks in heat capacity below 10 K in the amorphous phase of all compositions. By fitting the data using the Debye model combined with the Einstein model, we can extract the characteristic parameters of the Boson peaks and attribute their origin to the excess vibrational modes of dynamic defects in the amorphous solids. We find that these parameters correlate almost linearly with the Sb-content of the alloys, despite the nonmonotonic behaviors in glass forming abilities. A larger contribution of excess vibrational modes correlates with a larger width of enthalpy relaxation below the glass transition temperature Tg. In a broader context, we show that the correlations of the characteristic parameters of the Boson peaks with Tg and kinetic fragility, vary according to the type of bonding. Specifically, metallic glasses and conventional covalent glasses exhibit distinct patterns of dependence, whereas PCMs manifest characteristics that lie in between. A deeper understanding of the Boson peaks in PCMs holds the promise to enable predictions of material properties at higher temperatures based on features observed in low-temperature heat capacity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17226v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jens Moesgaard, Tomoki Fujita, Shuai Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
