<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 04:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>SmileyLlama: Modifying Large Language Models for Directed Chemical Space Exploration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02231v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Here we show that a Large Language Model (LLM) can serve as a foundation model for a Chemical Language Model (CLM) which performs at or above the level of CLMs trained solely on chemical SMILES string data. Using supervised fine-tuning (SFT) and direct preference optimization (DPO) on the open-source Llama LLM, we demonstrate that we can train an LLM to respond to prompts such as generating molecules with properties of interest to drug development. This overall framework allows an LLM to not just be a chatbot client for chemistry and materials tasks, but can be adapted to speak more directly as a CLM which can generate molecules with user-specified properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02231v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph M. Cavanagh, Kunyang Sun, Andrew Gritsevskiy, Dorian Bagni, Thomas D. Bannister, Teresa Head-Gordon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SDSPT2s: SDSPT2 with Selection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02367v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As an approximation to SDSCI [static-dynamic-static (SDS) configuration interaction (CI), a minimal MRCI; Theor. Chem. Acc. 133, 1481 (2014)], SDSPT2 [Mol. Phys. 115, 2696 (2017)] is a CI-like multireference (MR) second-order perturbation theory (PT2) that treats single and multiple roots on an equal footing. This feature permits the use of configuration selection over a large complete active space (CAS) $P$ to end up with a much reduced reference space $\tilde{P}$, which is connected only with a portion ($\tilde{Q}_1$) of the full first-order interacting space $Q$ connected to $P$. The effective interacting $\tilde{Q}$ space can further be truncated by an integral-based cutoff threshold. With marginal loss of accuracy, the selection-truncation procedure, along with an efficient evaluation and storage of internal contraction coefficients, renders SDSPT2s (SDSPT2 with selection) applicable to systems that cannot be handled by the parent CAS-based SDSPT2, as demonstrated by several challenging showcases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02367v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yibo Lei, Yang Guo, Bingbing Suo, Wenjian Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-consistent approach to the dynamics of excitation energy transfer in multichromophoric systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Computationally tractable and reliable, albeit approximate, methods for studying exciton transport in molecular aggregates immersed in structured bosonic environments have been actively developed. Going beyond the lowest-order (Born) approximation for the memory kernel of the generalized quantum master equation typically results in complicated and possibly divergent expressions. Starting from the memory kernel in the Born approximation, and recognizing the quantum master equation as the Dyson equation of the Green's functions theory, we formulate the self-consistent Born approximation to resum the memory-kernel perturbation series in powers of the exciton-environment interaction. Our formulation is in the Liouville space and frequency domain, and handles arbitrary exciton-environment spectral densities. In a molecular dimer coupled to an overdamped oscillator environment, we conclude that the self-consistent cycle significantly improves the Born-approximation energy-transfer dynamics. The dynamics in the self-consistent Born approximation agree well with solutions of hierarchical equations of motion over a wide range of parameters, including the most challenging regimes of strong exciton-environment interactions, slow environments, and low temperatures. This is rationalized by analytical considerations of coherence-dephasing dynamics in the pure-dephasing model. We find that the self-consistent Born approximation is good (poor) at describing energy transfer modulated by an underdamped vibration resonant (off-resonant) with the exciton energy gap. Nevertheless, it reasonably describes exciton dynamics in the seven-site model of the Fenna-Matthews-Olson complex in a realistic environment comprising both an overdamped continuum and underdamped vibrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02496v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Veljko Jankovi\'c, Tom\'a\v{s} Man\v{c}al</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Vibrational States of Methanol (12D)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02505</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02505v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Full-dimensional (12D) vibrational states of the methanol molecule (CH$_3$OH) have been computed using the GENIUSH-Smolyak approach and the potential energy surface from Qu and Bowman (2013). All vibrational energies are converged better than 0.5 cm$^{-1}$ with respect to the basis and grid size up to the first overtone of the CO stretch, ca. 2000 cm$^{-1}$ beyond the zero-point vibrational energy. About seventy torsion-vibration states are reported and assigned. The computed vibrational energies agree with the available experimental data within less than a few cm$^{-1}$ in most cases, which confirms the good accuracy of the potential energy surface. The computations are carried out using curvilinear normal coordinates with the option of path-following coefficients which minimize the coupling of the small- and large-amplitude motions. It is important to ensure tight numerical fulfilment of the $C_{3\mathrm{v}}$(M) molecular symmetry for every geometry and coefficient set used to define the curvilinear normal coordinates along the torsional coordinate to obtain a faithful description of degeneracy in this floppy system. The reported values may provide a computational reference for fundamental spectroscopy, astrochemistry, and for the search of the proton-to-electron mass ratio variation using the methanol molecule.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02505v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.jctc.4c00647</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ayaki Sunaga, Gustavo Avila, Edit Matyus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semiclassical instanton theory for reaction rates at any temperature: How a rigorous real-time derivation solves the crossover temperature problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02820v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Instanton theory relates the rate constant for tunneling through a barrier to the periodic classical trajectory on the upturned potential energy surface whose period is $\tau=\hbar /(k_{\mathrm{B}}T)$. Unfortunately, the standard theory is only applicable below the "crossover temperature", where the periodic orbit first appears. This paper presents a rigorous semiclassical ($\hbar\to0$) theory for the rate that is valid at any temperature. The theory is derived by combining Bleistein's method for generating uniform asymptotic expansions with a real-time modification of Richardson's flux-correlation function derivation of instanton theory. The resulting theory smoothly connects the instanton result at low temperature to the parabolic correction to Eyring transition state theory at high-temperature. Although the derivation involves real time, the final theory only involves imaginary-time (thermal) properties, consistent with the standard theory. Therefore, it is no more difficult to compute than the standard theory. The theory is illustrated with application to model systems, where it is shown to give excellent numerical results. Finally, the first-principles approach taken here results in a number of advantages over previous attempts to extend the imaginary free-energy formulation of instanton theory. In addition to producing a theory that is a smooth (continuously differentiable) function of temperature, the derivation also naturally incorporates hyperasymptotic (i.e.~multi-orbit) terms, and provides a framework for further extensions of the theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02820v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph E. Lawrence</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approaching the Lower Temporal Limit of Laser-Produced Plasma Sources for Table-Top Soft X-ray NEXAFS Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02280v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The increasing popularity of time-resolved X-ray absorption measurements for understanding dynamics in molecular and material systems has led to many advances in table-top sources for pulsed X-rays. We report on a table top laser-produced plasma (LPP) source that can perform soft X-ray (SXR), near edge X-ray absorption fine structure (NEXAFS) measurements using a laser source with 23 ps pulse duration. The spectrometer's key specifications, such as brilliance, resolution, and stability, are characterized against the more commonly used longer-pulse-duration LPP sources. The 23 ps laser produced approximately an order of magnitude weaker SXR flux than the 8 ns laser for a higher power density due to the smaller total energy absorbed by the plasma. The increased repetition rate and an implemented self-referencing scheme still allowed for high-resolution, synchrotron-like NEXAFS measurements of Si3N4 and TiO2 thin films with 2.5 minute acquisition times. It was observed that degradation of the gas jet nozzle led to long-term instability of the source, which can be remediated using alternative nozzle designs. This work demonstrates the feasibility of achieving higher temporal resolution in future time-resolved X-ray absorption measurements using table-top laser-produced plasma sources</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02280v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Danika Nimlos, Alejandro Arellano, Scott Kevin Cushing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Partition Function Estimator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02538v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a simple estimator that allows to calculate the absolute value of a system's partition function from a finite sampling of its canonical ensemble. The estimator utilizes a volume correction term to compensate the effect that the finite sampling cannot cover the whole configuration space. As a proof of concept, the estimator is applied to calculate the partition function for several model systems, and the results are compared with the numerically exact solutions. Excellent agreement is found, demonstrating that a solution for an efficient calculation of partition functions is possible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02538v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying-Chih Chiang, Frank Otto, Jonathan W. Essex</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practical techniques for high precision measurements on near-term quantum hardware: a Case Study in Molecular Energy Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02575v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Achieving high-precision measurements on near-term quantum devices is critical for advancing quantum computing applications. In this paper, we explore several practical techniques to enhance measurement accuracy using randomized measurements, focusing on minimizing shot overhead, circuit overhead, measurement noise, and time-dependent measurement noise. Our approach leverages locally biased random measurements to reduce shot overhead, in addition to repeated settings and parallel quantum detector tomography to reduce circuit overhead and mitigate measurement noise. Additionally, we employ a blended scheduling technique to mitigate time-dependent measurement noise. We demonstrate the effectiveness of these techniques through a case study on the molecular energy estimation of the BODIPY molecule using the Hartree-Fock state on an IBM Eagle r3 computer, showcasing significant improvements in measurement precision. These strategies pave the way for more reliable and accurate quantum computations, particularly in applications requiring precise molecular energy calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02575v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keijo Korhonen, Hetta Vappula, Adam Glos, Marco Cattaneo, Zolt\'an Zimbor\'as, Elsi-Mari Borrelli, Matteo A. C. Rossi, Guillermo Garc\'ia-P\'erez, Daniel Cavalcanti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complete and Efficient Covariants for 3D Point Configurations with Application to Learning Molecular Quantum Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02730v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: When modeling physical properties of molecules with machine learning, it is desirable to incorporate $SO(3)$-covariance. While such models based on low body order features are not complete, we formulate and prove general completeness properties for higher order methods, and show that $6k-5$ of these features are enough for up to $k$ atoms. We also find that the Clebsch--Gordan operations commonly used in these methods can be replaced by matrix multiplications without sacrificing completeness, lowering the scaling from $O(l^6)$ to $O(l^3)$ in the degree of the features. We apply this to quantum chemistry, but the proposed methods are generally applicable for problems involving 3D point configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02730v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hartmut Maennel, Oliver T. Unke, Klaus-Robert M\"uller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Doping-Induced Enhancement of Hydrogen Evolution at MoS2 Electrodes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02749v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Rate theory and DFT calculations of hydrogen evolution reaction (HER) on MoS2 with Co, Ni and Pt impurities show the significance of dihydrogen (H2*) complex where both hydrogen atoms are interacting with the surface. Stabilization of such a complex affects the competing Volmer-Heyrovsky (direct H2 release) and Volmer-Tafel (H2* intermediate) pathways. The resulting evolution proceeds with a very small overpotential for all dopants ($\eta$ = 0.1 to 0.2 V) at 25% edge substitution, significantly reduced from the already low $\eta$ = 0.27 V for the undoped edge. At full edge substitution, Co-MoS2 remains highly active ($\eta$ = 0.18 V) while Ni- and Pt-MoS2 are deactivated ($\eta$ = 0.4 to 0.5 V) due to unfavorable interaction with H2*. Instead of the single S-vacancy, the site of intrinsic activity in the basal plane was found to be the undercoordinated central Mo-atom in threefold S-vacancy configurations, enabling hydrogen evolution with $\eta$ = 0.52 V via a H2* intermediate. The impurity atoms interact favorably with the intrinsic sulfur vacancies on the basal plane, stabilizing but simultaneously deactivating the triple vacancy configuration. The calculated shifts in overpotential are consistent with reported measurements, and the dependence on doping level may explain variations in experimental observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02749v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/cphc.202400349</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Sander {\O}. Hanslin, Hannes J\'onsson, Jaakko Akola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous propagators and the particle-particle channel: Hedin's equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07062</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07062v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hedin's equations provide an elegant route to compute the exact one-body Green's function (or propagator) via the self-consistent iteration of a set of non-linear equations.
  Its first-order approximation, known as $GW$, corresponds to a resummation of ring diagrams and has shown to be extremely successful in physics and chemistry. Systematic improvement is possible, although challenging, via the introduction of vertex corrections.
  Considering anomalous propagators and an external pairing potential, we derive a new self-consistent set of closed equations equivalent to the famous Hedin equations but having as a first-order approximation the particle-particle (pp) $T$-matrix approximation where one performs a resummation of the ladder diagrams.
  This pp version of Hedin's equations offers a way to go systematically beyond the $T$-matrix approximation by accounting for low-order pp vertex corrections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07062v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Marie, Pina Romaniello, Pierre-Fran\c{c}ois Loos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine-Learning-Based Construction of Molecular Potential and Its Application in Exploring the Deep-Lying-Orbital Effect in High-Order Harmonic Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12627v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Creating soft-Coulomb-type (SC) molecular potential within single-active-electron approximation (SAE) is essential since it allows solving time-dependent Schr\"odinger equations with fewer computational resources compared to other multielectron methods. The current available SC potentials can accurately reproduce the energy of the highest occupied molecular orbital (HOMO), which is sufficient for analyzing nonlinear effects in laser-molecule interactions like high-order harmonic generation (HHG). However, recent discoveries of significant effects of deep-lying molecular orbitals call for more precise potentials to analyze them. In this study, we present a fast and accurate method based on machine learning to construct SC potentials that simultaneously reproduce various molecular features, including energies, symmetries, and dipole moments of HOMO, HOMO-1, and HOMO-2. We use this ML model to create SC SAE potentials of the HCN molecule and then comprehensively analyze the fingerprints of lower-lying orbitals in HHG spectra emitted during the H-CN stretching. Our findings reveal that HOMO-1 plays a role in forming the second HHG plateau. Additionally, as the H-C distance increases, the plateau structure and the smoothness of HHG spectra are altered due to the redistribution of orbital electron density. These results are in line with other experimental and theoretical studies. Lastly, the machine learning approach using deconvolution and convolution neural networks in the present study is so general that it can be applied to construct molecular potential for other molecules and molecular dynamic processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12627v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duong D. Hoang-Trong, Khang Tran, Doan-An Trieu, Quan-Hao Truong, Kim-Ngan H. Nguyen, Cam-Tu Le, DinhDuy Vu, Ngoc-Hung Phan, Ngoc-Ty Nguyen, Van-Hoang Le, Ngoc-Loan Phan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
