<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2024 01:24:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Insights into Polymer Electrolyte Stability and Reaction Pathways: A first-principle calculations study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07229v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the electrochemical behavior and decomposition pathways of four monomers, namely PMC, PMC-OH, PeMC-OH, and DEO-EA, which are potential candidates for polymer electrolytes in solid-state batteries. Density functional theory calculations were employed to determine the oxidation and reduction potentials of these monomers near different ions (Li+, TFSI-, and LiTFSI) and their corresponding reorganization energies. The results reveal notable sensitivity of the monomers to reduction in a Li+ rich regime and to oxidation in a TFSI- rich regime. Additionally, the decomposition pathways of the monomers were investigated, focusing on the cleavage of CO bonds. The findings provide insights into the stability and reactivity of these monomers in various electrochemical environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07229v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazem Zhour, Andreas Heuer, Diddo Diddens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coupling Between Local and Global Oscillations in Palladium-Catalysed Methane Oxidation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07374v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The interplay between order and disorder is crucial across various fields, especially in understanding oscillatory phenomena. Periodic oscillations are frequently observed in heterogeneous catalysis, yet their underlying mechanisms need deeper exploration. Here, we investigate how periodic oscillations arise during methane oxidation catalysed by palladium nanoparticles (Pd NPs), utilizing a suite of complementary operando techniques across various spatial scales. We found that reaction intensity and collective dynamic modes can be tuned by the reactant gas-flow rate. At lower gas-flow rates, we observed periodic facet reconstruction of Pd NPs correlated with repeated bubbling behaviour at the Pd/PdO interface, without evident global oscillatory responses. Conversely, at higher gas-flow rates, Pd NPs undergo chaotic transformations between metallic and oxidized states, resulting in overall oscillation. Integrating our observations at different gas-flow rates, we attributed the emergence of global oscillation to thermal coupling regulated by gas flow and connected local and global dynamics through a weak synchronization mechanism. This work demonstrates the correlations between open surfaces and interfaces, chaos and regularity, and dissipative processes and coupling behaviour. Our findings offer critical insights into the complexity behind catalytic oscillations and provide guidance for modulating oscillatory behaviours in catalytic processes, with significant implications for both science and industry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07374v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxiong Hu, Jianyu Hu, Mengzhao Sun, Aowen Li, Shucheng Shi, P. J. Hu, Wu Zhou, Marc-Georg Willinger, Dan Zhou, Zhi Liu, Xi Liu, Wei-Xue Li, Zhu-Jun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Force Fields for Deep Eutectic Mixtures: Application to Structure and 2D-Infrared Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07638v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Parametrizing energy functions for ionic systems can be challenging. Here, the total energy function for an eutectic system consisting of water, SCN$^-$, K$^+$ and acetamide is improved vis-a-vis experimentally measured properties. Given the importance of electrostatic interactions, two different types of models are considered: the first (model M0) uses atom-centered multipole whereas the other two (models M1 and M2) are based on fluctuating minimal distributed charges (fMDCM) that respond to geometrical changes of SCN$^-$. The Lennard-Jones parameters of the anion are adjusted to best reproduce experimentally known hydration free energies and densities which are matched to within a few percent for the final models irrespective of the electrostatic model. Molecular dynamics simulations of the eutectic mixtures with varying water content (between 0% and 100%) yield radial distribution functions and frequency correlation functions for the CN-stretch vibration. Comparison with experiments indicate that models based on fMDCM are considerably more consistent that those using multipoles. Computed viscosities from models M1 and M2 are within 30% of measured values and their change with increasing water content is consistent with experiments. This is not the case for model M0.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07638v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai T\"opfer, Eric Boittier, Michael Devereux, Andrea Pasti, Peter Hamm, Markus Meuwly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predictions of the interfacial free energy along the coexistence line from single-state calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07469v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The calculation of the interfacial free energy between two thermodynamic phases is crucial across different fields including materials science, chemistry, and condensed matter physics. This study delves into a thermodynamic approach to predict interfacial free energy along a coexistence line. For that purpose, we utilize Gibbs-Cahn integration method to accurately determine the interfacial free energy along various coexistence conditions, relying solely on data obtained from a single-state interfacial free energy calculation at given conditions of pressure and temperature. Unlike traditional methods that require individual measurements at each thermodynamic state, this approach significantly reduces computational demand and enhances efficiency. The integration scheme requires the computation of the excess interfacial energy (by means of unbiased NVT computer simulations in which the two phases involved coexist) at different points along the coexistence line, for later use this information as an input in our calculations. We apply this method for the Lennard-Jones and mW water model for the case of the liquid-solid interface, as well as Lennard-Jones and TIP4P/2005 models for liquid-vapor interfaces. Our results highlight the accuracy and effectiveness of this thermodynamic integration route for estimating the interfacial free energy along a coexistence line.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07469v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ignacio Sanchez-Burgos, Pablo Montero de Hijes, Eduardo Sanz, Carlos Vega, Jorge R. Espinosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Quantum States and Peaked Molecular Wave Functions: Curse or Blessing?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07625v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The field of neural quantum states has recently experienced a tremendous progress, making them a competitive tool of computational quantum many-body physics. However, their largest achievements to date mostly concern interacting spin systems, while their utility for quantum chemistry remains yet to be demonstrated. Two main complications are the peaked structure of the molecular wave functions, which impedes sampling, and large number of terms in second quantised Hamiltonians, which hinders scaling to larger molecule sizes. In this paper we address these issues jointly and argue that the peaked structure might actually be key to drastically more efficient calculations. Specifically, we introduce a novel algorithm for autoregressive sampling without replacement and a procedure to calculate a computationally cheaper surrogate for the local energy. We complement them with a custom modification of the stochastic reconfiguration optimisation technique and a highly optimised GPU implementation. As a result, our calculations require substantially less resources and exhibit more than order of magnitude speedup compared to the previous works. On a single GPU we study molecules comprising up to 118 qubits and outperform the ``golden standard'' CCSD(T) benchmark in Hilbert spaces of $\sim 10^{15}$ Slater determinants, which is orders of magnitude larger than what was previously achieved. We believe that our work underscores the prospect of NQS for challenging quantum chemistry calculations and serves as a favourable ground for the future method development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07625v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksei Malyshev, Markus Schmitt, A. I. Lvovsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpolating many-body wave functions for accelerated molecular dynamics on the near-exact electronic surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11097v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: While there have been many developments in computational probes of both strongly-correlated molecular systems and machine-learning accelerated molecular dynamics, there remains a significant gap in capabilities in simulating accurate non-local electronic structure over timescales on which atoms move. We develop an approach to bridge these fields with a practical interpolation scheme for the correlated many-electron state through the space of atomic configurations, whilst avoiding the exponential complexity of these underlying electronic states. With a small number of accurate correlated wave functions as a training set, we demonstrate provable convergence to near-exact potential energy surfaces for subsequent dynamics with propagation of a valid many-body wave function and inference of its variational energy whilst retaining a mean-field computational scaling. This represents a profoundly different paradigm to the direct interpolation of potential energy surfaces in established machine-learning approaches. We combine this with modern electronic structure approaches to systematically resolve molecular dynamics trajectories and converge thermodynamic quantities with a high-throughput of several million interpolated wave functions with explicit validation of their accuracy from only a few numerically exact quantum chemical calculations. We also highlight the comparison to traditional machine-learned potentials or dynamics on mean-field surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11097v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yannic Rath, George H. Booth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Influence of (n-1)d Subvalence Correlation and of Spin-Orbit Coupling on Chalcogen Bonding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.05338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.05338v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article presents a comprehensive computational investigation into chalcogen bonding interactions, focusing specifically on elucidating the role of subvalence (n$-$1)d and (n$-$1)sp correlation. The incorporation of inner-shell (n$-$1)d correlation leads to a decrease in interaction energies for chalcogen-bonded systems (at least those studied herein), contradicting the observations regarding halogen bonding documented by Kesharwani et al. in \textit{J. Phys. Chem. A}, \textbf{2018}, 122 (8), 2184-2197. The significance of (n$-$1)sp subvalence correlation appears to be lower by an order of magnitude. Notably, among the various components of interaction energies computed at the PNO-LCCSD(T) or DF-CCSD levels, we identify the PNO-LMP2 or DF-MP2 component of the (n$-$1)d correlation as predominant. Furthermore, we delve into the impact of second-order spin-orbit coupling (SOC2) on these interactions. Specifically, for the Te complexes, SOC2 effects rival (n$-$1)d correlation in importance; for the Se complexes, SOC2 is much less important. Generally, SOC2 stabilizes monomers more than dimers, resulting in reduced binding of the latter. Notably, at equilibrium and stretched geometries, SOC2 and (n$-$1)d destabilize the complex; however, at compressed geometries, they exhibit opposing effects, with (n$-$1)d becoming stabilizing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.05338v3</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1039/D4CP01877J</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Nisha Mehta, Jan M. L. Martin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the exact limits of the real-time equation-of-motion coupled cluster cumulant Green's functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00989</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00989v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we analyze the properties of the recently proposed real-time equation-of-motion coupled-cluster (RT-EOM-CC) cumulant Green's function approach [J. Chem. Phys. 2020, 152, 174113]. We specifically focus on identifying the limitations of the original time-dependent coupled cluster (TDCC) ansatz and propose an enhanced double TDCC ansatz ensuring the exactness in the expansion limit. Additionally, we introduce a practical cluster-analysis-based approach for characterizing the peaks in the computed spectral function from the RT-EOM-CC cumulant Green's function approach, which is particularly useful for the assignments of satellite peaks when many-body effects dominate the spectra. Our preliminary numerical tests focus on reproducing, approximating, and characterizing the exact impurity Green's function of the three-site and four-site single impurity Anderson models using the RT-EOM-CC cumulant Green's function approach. The numerical tests allow us to have a direct comparison between the RT-EOM-CC cumulant Green's function approach and other Green's function approaches in the numerical exact limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00989v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo Peng, Himadri Pathak, Ajay Panyala, Fernando D. Vila, John J. Rehr, Karol Kowalski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty-Aware Liquid State Modeling from Experimental Scattering Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00236v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This dissertation is founded on the central notion that structural correlations in dense fluids, such as dense gases, liquids, and glasses, are directly related to fundamental interatomic forces. This relationship was identified early in the development of statistical theories of fluids through the mathematical formulations of Gibbs in the 1910s. However, it took nearly 80 years before practical implementations of structure-based theories became widely used for interpreting and understanding the atomic structures of fluids from experimental X-ray and neutron scattering data. The breakthrough in successfully applying structure-potential relations is largely attributed to the advancements in molecular mechanics simulations and the enhancement of computational resources. Despite advancements in understanding the relationship between structure and interatomic forces, a significant gap remains. Current techniques for interpreting experimental scattering measurements are widely used, yet there is little evidence that they yield physically accurate predictions for interatomic forces. In fact, it is generally assumed that these methods produce interatomic forces that poorly model the atomistic and thermodynamic behavior of fluids, rendering them unreliable and non-transferable. This thesis aims to address these limitations by refining the statistical theory, computational methods, and philosophical approach to structure-based analyses, thereby developing more robust and accurate techniques for characterizing structure-potential relationships.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00236v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brennon L. Shanks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral topological light for detecting robust enantio-sensitive observables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.10932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.10932v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The topological response of matter to electromagnetic fields is a property in high demand in materials design and metrology due to its robustness against noise and decoherence, stimulating recent advances in ultrafast photonics. Embedding topological properties into the enantio-sensitive optical response of chiral molecules could therefore enhance the efficiency and robustness of chiral optical discrimination. Here we achieve such a topological embedding by introducing the concept of chiral topological light~-- a light beam which displays chirality locally, with an azimuthal distribution of its handedness described globally by a topological charge. The topological charge is mapped onto the azimuthal intensity modulation of the non-linear optical response, where enantio-sensitivity is encoded into its spatial rotation. The spatial rotation is robust against intensity fluctuations and imperfect local polarization states of the driving field. Our theoretical results show that chiral topological light enables detection of percentage-level enantiomeric excesses in randomly oriented mixtures of chiral molecules, opening a way to new, extremely sensitive and robust chiro-optical spectroscopies with attosecond time resolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.10932v4</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41566-024-01499-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Nicola Mayer, David Ayuso, Piero Decleva, Margarita Khokhlova, Emilio Pisanty, Misha Ivanov, Olga Smirnova</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
