<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Discovering deposition process regimes: leveraging unsupervised learning for process insights, surrogate modeling, and sensitivity analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18444v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work introduces a comprehensive approach utilizing data-driven methods to elucidate the deposition process regimes in Chemical Vapor Deposition (CVD) reactors and the interplay of physical mechanism that dominate in each one of them. Through this work, we address three key objectives. Firstly, our methodology relies on process outcomes, derived by a detailed CFD model, to identify clusters of "outcomes" corresponding to distinct process regimes, wherein the relative influence of input variables undergoes notable shifts. This phenomenon is experimentally validated through Arrhenius plot analysis, affirming the efficacy of our approach. Secondly, we demonstrate the development of an efficient surrogate model, based on Polynomial Chaos Expansion (PCE), that maintains accuracy, facilitating streamlined computational analyses. Finally, as a result of PCE, sensitivity analysis is made possible by means of Sobol' indices, that quantify the impact of process inputs across identified regimes. The insights gained from our analysis contribute to the formulation of hypotheses regarding phenomena occurring beyond the transition regime. Notably, the significance of temperature even in the diffusion-limited regime, as evidenced by the Arrhenius plot, suggests activation of gas phase reactions at elevated temperatures. Importantly, our proposed methods yield insights that align with experimental observations and theoretical principles, aiding decision-making in process design and optimization. By circumventing the need for costly and time-consuming experiments, our approach offers a pragmatic pathway towards enhanced process efficiency. Moreover, this study underscores the potential of data-driven computational methods for innovating reactor design paradigms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18444v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geremy Loacham\'in Suntaxi, Paris Papavasileiou, Eleni D. Koronaki, Dimitrios G. Giovanis, Georgios Gakis, Ioannis G. Aviziotis, Martin Kathrein, Gabriele Pozzetti, Christoph Czettl, St\'ephane P. A. Bordas, Andreas G. Boudouvis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective phase diffusion for spin phase evolution under random nonlinear magnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18514v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The general theoretical description of spin self-diffusion under nonlinear gradient is proposed, which extends the effective phase diffusion method for linear gradient field. Based on the phase diffusion, the proposed method reveals the general features of phase evolutions in non-nonlinear gradient fields. There are three types of phase evolutions: phase diffusion, float phase evolution, and shift based on the starting position. For spin diffusion near the origin of the nonlinear field, these three phase evolutions significantly affect the NMR signal. The traditional methods have difficulties in handling these three-phase evolutions. Notably, the phase from float phase evolution is missed or misplaced in traditional methods, which leads to incorrect NMR signal attenuation or phase shift. The method here shows that the diffusing and float phase evolutions come from the first and second derivatives of the gradient field. Based on these three phase evolutions, the phase variance and corresponding NMR signal attenuation are obtained, demonstrated by calculating the phase diffusions under the parabolic and cubic fields. The results indicate that signal attenuation obeys Gaussian attenuation for a short time, then changes to Lorentzian or Mittag Leffler function attenuations when time increases, significantly different from Gaussian attenuation. For spins starting diffusion far away from the origin, the signal attenuation is Gaussian, but the float phase still has an important effect on the total phase shift of even-order gradient fields, which could be used to measure the diffusion coefficient directly. Random walk simulations are performed, which support the obtained theoretical results. The obtained general theoretical expressions can handle random order nonlinear gradient field. The results could help develop advanced experimental techniques for NMR and MRI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18514v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guoxing Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design and Implementation of a New Apparatus for Astrochemistry: Kinetic Measurements of the CH + OCS Reaction and Frequency Comb Spectroscopy in a Cold Uniform Supersonic Flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18814v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the development of a new astrochemical research tool HILTRAC, the Highly Instrumented Low Temperature ReAction Chamber. The instrument is based on a pulsed form of the CRESU (Cin\'etique de R\'eaction en \'Ecoulement Supersonique Uniforme, meaning reaction kinetics in a uniform supersonic flow) apparatus, with the aim of collecting kinetics and spectroscopic information on gas phase chemical reactions important in interstellar space or planetary atmospheres. We discuss the apparatus design and its flexibility, the implementation of pulsed laser photolysis followed by laser induced fluorescence (PLP-LIF), and the first implementation of direct infrared frequency comb spectroscopy (DFCS) coupled to the uniform supersonic flow. Achievable flow temperatures range from 32(3) - 111(9) K, characterising a total of five Laval nozzles for use with N2 and Ar buffer gases by pressure impact measurements. These results were further validated using LIF and DFCS measurements of the CH radical and OCS, respectively. Spectroscopic constants and linelists for OCS are reported for the 1001 band near $2890 - 2940 cm^{-1}$ for both $OC^{32}S$ and $OC^{34}S$, measured using DFCS. Additional peaks in the spectrum are tentatively assigned to the OCS-Ar complex. The first reaction rate coefficients for the CH + OCS reaction measured between 32(3) K and 58(5) K are reported. The reaction rate coefficient at 32(3) K was measured to be $3.9(4) \times 10^{10} cm^3 molecule^{-1} s^{-1}$ and the reaction was found to exhibit no observable temperature dependence over this low temperature range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18814v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel I. Lucas, Th\'eo Guillaume, Dwayne E. Heard, Julia H. Lehman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Screening and antiscreening effects in endohedral nanotubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently we investigated from first principles screening properties in systems where small molecules, characterized by a finite electronic dipole moment, are encapsulated into different nanocages. The most relevant result was the observation of an antiscreening effect in alkali-halide nanocages characterized by ionic bonds. Here we extend the study to another class of nanostructures, the nanotubes. Using first-principles techniques based on the Density Functional Theory, we studied the properties of endohedral nanotubes obtained by encapsulation of a water molecule or a linear HF molecule. A detailed analysis of the effective dipole moment of the complexes and of the electronic charge distribution suggests that screening effects crucially depend not only on the nature of the intramolecular bonds but also on the size and the shape of the nanotubes, and on the specific encapsulated molecule. As observed in endohedral nanocages, screening is maximum in covalent-bond carbon nanotubes, while it is reduced in partially-ionic nanotubes and an antiscreening effect is observed in some ionic nanotubes. However in this case the scenario is more complex than in corresponding ionic nanocages. In fact the specific geometric structure of alkali-halide nanotubes turns out to be crucial for determining the screening/antiscreening behavior: while nanotubes with octagonal transversal section can exhibit an antiscreening effect, which quantitatively depends on the number of layers in the longitudinal direction, instead nanotubes with dodecagonal section are always characterized by a reduction of the total dipole moment, so that a screening behavior is observed. Our results therefore show that, even in nanotube structures, in principle one can tune the dipole moment and generate electrostatic fields at the nanoscale without the aid of external potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18864v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pier Luigi Silvestrelli, Matteo Tessarolo, Abdolvahab Seif, Alberto Ambrosetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Donnan equilibrium in charged slit-pores from a hybrid nonequilibrium Molecular Dynamics / Monte Carlo method with ions and solvent exchange</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18957v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ion partitioning between different compartments (\emph{e.g.} a porous material and a bulk solution reservoir), known as Donnan equilibrium, plays a fundamental role in various contexts such as energy, environment, or water treatment. The linearized Poisson-Boltzmann (PB) equation, capturing the thermal motion of the ions with mean-field electrostatic interactions, is practically useful to understand and predict ion partitioning, despite its limited applicability to conditions of low salt concentrations and surface charge densities. Here, we investigate the Donnan equilibrium of coarse-grained dilute electrolytes confined in charged slit-pores in equilibrium with a reservoir of ions and solvent. We introduce and use an extension to confined systems of a recently developed hybrid nonequilibrium molecular dynamics / grand canonical Monte Carlo simulation method ("H4D"), which enhances the efficiency of solvent and ion-pair exchange via a fourth spatial dimension. We show that the validity range of linearized PB theory to predict the Donnan equilibrium of dilute electrolytes can be extended to highly charged pores, by simply considering \textit{renormalized} surface charge densities. We compare with simulations of implicit solvent models of electrolytes and show that in the low salt concentrations and thin electric double layer limit considered here, an explicit solvent has a limited effect on the Donnan equilibrium and that the main limitations of the analytical predictions are not due to the breakdown of the mean-field description, but rather to the charge renormalization approximation, because it only focuses on the behavior far from the surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18957v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeongmin Kim, Benjamin Rotenberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Tunneling Could Enable Proton Transfer Reactions on Titan</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19195v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The surface of Titan, Saturn's largest moon, is rich in organics and is often suggested to model early Earth environments. Titan's surface is cold, at a temperature of approximately 90 K, which prohibits most thermally activated chemical reactions. However, quantum effects become more important at low temperatures and reactions that are classically prohibited can often proceed through quantum mechanical pathways. Using path integral molecular dynamics simulations, we investigate nuclear quantum effects on the thermodynamics of model proton transfer reactions in liquid ethane. We find that proton transfer can occur at Titan surface conditions through quantum tunneling. Consequently, we estimate that nuclear quantum effects can enhance reaction rates by many orders of magnitude. Our results suggest that nuclear quantum effects could facilitate prebiotic chemistry on Titan, and quantum effects should be considered in future investigations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19195v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henry W. Longo, Richard C. Remsing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Nirmala indices based entropy measures for the complex structure of ruthenium bipyridine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18441v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A numerical parameter, known as a topological index, is employed to represent the molecular structure of a compound by considering its graph-theoretical properties. In the study of quantitative structure-activity relationships (QSAR) and quantitative structure-property relationships (QSPR), topological indices are used to predict the physicochemical properties of chemical compounds. Graph entropies have evolved as information-theoretic tools to investigate the structural information of a molecular graph. In this study, we compute the Nirmala index, the first and second inverse Nirmala index of the complex structure of ruthenium bipyridine, with the help of its M-polynomial. Furthermore, entropy measures for the complex structure of ruthenium bipyridine are computed using Shannon's entropy model. The comparison between the Nirmala indices and their associated entropy measures is presented through numerical computation. The correlation between the Nirmala indices and associated entropy measurements is then examined using a regression model. Finally, it is shown that the structural characteristics and properties of the complex structure of ruthenium bipyridine will be predicted by Nirmala indices-based entropy measures rather than the Nirmala indices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18441v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. M. Nagesh, Muhammad Kamran Siddiqui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>"Stumbling-to-Fetters" mechanism and Virginia Creeper model in hydrogel for designing bionic cardiovascular system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18445v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Manufacturing hydrogels with identical electrochemical properties are typically riddled with unresolved inquiries and challenges. Here, we utilized ultra-light graphene flakes to trace the influence of convection phenomena during reactions on hydrogels' formation and structural non-uniformity, elucidating its mechanisms. Furthermore, we confirmed that an external electric field induced the orientation of functional groups of hydrogels along the direction of this field, revealing the mechanism of its influence on the structural non-uniformity and electrochemical properties of hydrogels. Additionally, we discovered that ion diffusion was "Stumbling-to-Fetters" by the functional groups on the polymer chains within the hydrogel, unveiling this mechanism and developing the Virginia Creeper (VC) model for hydrogels. We demonstrated the scalability and application of the VC model. Furthermore, we proposed a molecular-ion diffusion and current decay equation to describe the electrochemical properties of hydrogels. As an application of the VC model, we developed a bionic cardiovascular system and proved its potential to seamlessly interface with living organisms and generate bio-like bioelectricity. Our findings provide novel insights into triboelectricity and guidance for producing hydrogels with identical electrochemical properties, and offer a new pathway for bioelectric generation and the design of new hydrogel devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18445v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanqing Dai (Academy for Engineering and Technology, Fudan University, Shanghai, China), Wenqing Dai (School of Materials Science and Engineering, Shanghai Jiao Tong University, Shanghai, China), Yuanyuan Chen (Institute for Electric Light Sources, Fudan University, Shanghai, China), Wanlu Zhang (Institute for Electric Light Sources, Fudan University, Shanghai, China), Yimeng Wang (School of Science and Engineering, University of Dundee, Dundee, United Kingdom), Ruiqian Guo (Academy for Engineering and Technology, Fudan University, Shanghai, China, Institute for Electric Light Sources, Fudan University, Shanghai, China), Guoqi Zhang (Department of Microelectronics, Delft University of Technology, Delft, Netherlands)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automatic Forward Model Parameterization with Bayesian Inference of Conformational Populations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18532v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To quantify how well theoretical predictions of structural ensembles agree with experimental measurements, we depend on the accuracy of forward models. These models are computational frameworks that generate observable quantities from molecular configurations based on empirical relationships linking specific molecular properties to experimental measurements. Bayesian Inference of Conformational Populations (BICePs) is a reweighting algorithm that reconciles simulated ensembles with ensemble-averaged experimental observations, even when such observations are sparse and/or noisy. This is achieved by sampling the posterior distribution of conformational populations under experimental restraints as well as sampling the posterior distribution of uncertainties due to random and systematic error. In this study, we enhance the algorithm for the refinement of empirical forward model (FM) parameters. We introduce and evaluate two novel methods for optimizing FM parameters. The first method treats FM parameters as nuisance parameters, integrating over them in the full posterior distribution. The second method employs variational minimization of a quantity called the BICePs score that reports the free energy of `turning on` the experimental restraints. This technique, coupled with improved likelihood functions for handling experimental outliers, facilitates force field validation and optimization, as illustrated in recent studies (Raddi et al. 2023, 2024). Using this approach, we refine parameters that modulate the Karplus relation, crucial for accurate predictions of J-coupling constants based on dihedral angles between interacting nuclei. We validate this approach first with a toy model system, and then for human ubiquitin, predicting six sets of Karplus parameters. This approach, which does not rely on predetermined parameters, enhances predictive accuracy and can be used for many applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18532v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert M. Raddi, Tim Marshall, Vincent A. Voelz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards an exact electronic quantum many-body treatment of Kondo correlation in magnetic impurities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18709v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Kondo effect is a prototypical quantum phenomenon arising from the interaction between localized electrons in a magnetic impurity and itinerant electrons in a metallic host. Although it has served as the testing ground for quantum many-body methods for decades, the precise description of Kondo physics with material specificity remains challenging. Here, we present a systematic ab initio approach to converge towards an exact zero-temperature electronic treatment of Kondo correlations. Across a series of 3d transition metals, we extract Kondo temperatures matching the subtle experimental trends, with an accuracy far exceeding that of standard models. We further obtain microscopic insight into the origin of these trends. More broadly, we demonstrate the possibility to start from fully ab initio many-body simulations and push towards the realm of converged predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18709v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianyu Zhu, Linqing Peng, Huanchen Zhai, Zhi-Hao Cui, Garnet Kin-Lic Chan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stoichiometric reconstruction of the Al$_{2}$O$_{3}$(0001) surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19263v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Macroscopic properties of materials stem from fundamental atomic-scale details, yet for insulators, resolving surface structures remains a challenge. The basal (0001) plane of ${\alpha}$-Al$_{2}$O$_{3}$ was imaged with noncontact atomic force microscopy with an atomically-defined tip apex. The surface forms a complex $({\sqrt31} {\times} {\sqrt31})R{\pm}9{\deg}$ reconstruction. The lateral positions of the individual O and Al surface atoms come directly from experiment; how these connect to the underlying crystal bulk was determined based on computational modeling. Before the restructuring, the surface Al atoms assume an unfavorable, threefold planar coordination; the reconstruction allows a rehybridization with subsurface O that leads to a substantial energy gain. The reconstructed surface remains stoichiometric, Al$_{2}$O$_{3}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19263v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johanna I. H\"utner, Andrea Conti, David Kugler, Florian Mittendorfer, Georg Kresse, Michael Schmid, Ulrike Diebold, Jan Balajka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ion Correlation-Driven Hysteretic Adhesion and Repulsion between Opposing Polyelectrolyte Brushes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19329v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Surface interactions mediated by polyelectrolyte (PE) brushes has been of great significance in biotechnology and nanotechnology including lubrication of skeletal joints, protein-coated surfaces, and stabilization of nanoparticles. The addition of salt ions is an important tool to modulate the morphology and mechanical properties of PE brushes. In this work, the electrostatic correlation augmented self-consistent field theory we previously developed is applied to investigate the interactions between opposing PE brushes in a mixture of 1:1 and 3:1 salt solutions. Our theory predicts that adding a small amount of trivalent ions can lead to a hysteretic feature of the force profile: repulsion in the compression and adhesion in the separation. Coexistence of two collapsed modes of PE brushes induced by strong ion correlations can be obtained, clearly elucidating the molecular origin of the hysteretic force. Furthermore, trivalent ions with larger radius induce less pronounced ion correlation, leading to stronger repulsion in the compression and weaker adhesion in the separation. Our results are in good agreement with the experiments reported by Tirrell group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19329v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Duan, Rui Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Symmetry in Thermally-Assisted-Occupation Density Functional Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09187v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For electronic systems with multi-reference (MR) character, Kohn-Sham density functional theory (KS-DFT) with the conventional exchange-correlation (xc) energy functionals can lead to incorrect spin densities and related properties. For example, for H2 dissociation, the spin-restricted and spin-unrestricted solutions obtained with the same xc energy functional in KS-DFT can be distinctly different, yielding the unphysical spin-symmetry breaking effects in the spin-unrestricted solutions. Recently, thermally-assisted-occupation density functional theory (TAO-DFT) has been shown to resolve the aforementioned spin-symmetry breaking, when the fictitious temperature is properly chosen. In this work, a response theory based on TAO-DFT is developed to demonstrate that TAO-DFT with a sufficiently large fictitious temperature can always resolve the unphysical spin-symmetry breaking in MR systems. To further support this, TAO-DFT calculations with various fictitious temperatures are performed for the dissociation of H2, N2, He2, and Ne2 as well as the twisted ethylene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09187v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Yang Wang, Jeng-Da Chai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A multigrain-multilayer astrochemical model with variable desorption energy for surface species</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13011</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13011v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Context. Interstellar surface chemistry is a complex process that occurs in icy layers accumulated onto grains of different sizes. Efficiency of surface processes often depends on the immediate environment of adsorbed molecules. Aims. We investigate how gas-grain chemistry changes when surface molecule desorption is made explicitly dependent to the molecular binding energy, which is modified, depending on the properties of the surface. Methods. Molecular binding energy changes gradually for three different environments - bare grain, where polar, water-dominated ices and non-polar, carbon monoxide-dominated ices. In addition to diffusion, evaporation and chemical desorption, photodesorption was also made binding energy-dependent, in line with experimental results. These phenomena occur in a collapsing prestellar core model that considers five grain sizes with ices arranged into four layers. Results. Efficient chemical desorption from bare grains significantly delays ice accumulation. Easier surface diffusion of molecules on non-polar ices promotes the production of carbon dioxide and other species. Conclusions. The composition of interstellar ices is regulated by several binding-energy dependent desorption mechanisms. Their actions overlap in time and space, which explains the ubiquitous proportions of major ice components (water and carbon oxides), observed to be similar in all directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13011v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juris Kalv\=ans, Aija Kalni\c{n}a, Kristaps Veitners</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
