<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 04:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Transparent and heat-insulation bionic hydrogel-based smart window system for long-term cooling and waste heat collection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23213v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the energy crisis and climate warming, the position of a new generation of smart windows is becoming increasingly important, and materials or systems that can have high blocking of near-infrared (NIR) and ultraviolet (UV) and high transmittance of visible light (VIS) are needed. Currently, it is difficult for smart heat-insulation materials to achieve high transmittance of VIS, good UV isolation, outstanding cooling and thermal insulation, and excellent waste heat collection. Here, we design a novel composite hydrogel to achieve an average 92% VIS transmittance, efficient UV absorption , 11 Celsius degree of thermal insulation, and sensing properties. Interestingly, we designed a transparent heat insulation system with this composite hydrogel to obtain about 22 Celsius degree of the record-breaking insulation performance for 168 hours, waste heat collection and reutilization, and temperature sensing. Our findings provide new ideas and possibilities for designing transparent and heat-insulation smart window systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23213v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qianwang Ye, Hanqing Dai, Yukun Yan, Liwei Wang, Xinlin Du, Yimeng Wang, Zhile Han, Wanlu Zhang, Ruiqian Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of water models for structure prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23446v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Describing the interactions of water molecules is one of the most common, yet critical, tasks in molecular dynamics simulations. Because of its unique properties, hundreds of attempts have been made to construct an ideal interaction potential model for water. In various studies, the models have been evaluated based on their ability to reproduce different properties of water. This work focuses on the atomic-scale structure in the liquid phase of water. Forty-four classical water potential models are compared to identify those that can accurately describe the structure in alignment with experimental results. In addition to some older models that are still popular today, new or re-parametrized classical models using effective pair-additive potentials that have appeared in recent years are examined. Molecular dynamics simulations were performed over a wide range of temperatures and the resulting trajectories were used to calculate the partial radial distribution functions. The total scattering structure factors were compared with data from neutron and X-ray diffraction experiments. Our analysis indicates that models with more than four interaction sites, as well as flexible or polarizable models with higher computational requirements, do not provide a significant advantage in accurately describing the structure. On the other hand, recent three-site models have made considerable progress in this area, although the best agreement with experimental data over the entire temperature range was achieved with four-site, TIP4P-type models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23446v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B\'alint Socz\'o, Ildik\'o Pethes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Simulations of Charge and Exciton Transfer in Multi-mode Models using Engineered Reservoirs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22729v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum simulation offers a route to study open-system molecular dynamics in non-perturbative regimes by programming the interactions among electronic, vibrational, and environmental degrees of freedom on similar energy scales. Trapped-ion systems possess this capability, with their native spins, phonons, and tunable dissipation integrated within a single platform. Here, we demonstrate an open-system quantum simulation of charge and exciton transfer in a multi-mode linear vibronic coupling model (LVCM). Employing tailored spin-phonon interactions alongside reservoir engineering techniques, we emulate a system with two dissipative vibrational modes coupled to donor and acceptor electronic sites and follow its excitation transfer in real time. We continuously drive the system from the charge transfer (CT) regime to the vibrationally assisted exciton transfer (VAET) regime by tuning the vibronic coupling strengths. We find that degenerate modes enhance CT and VAET rates at large energy gaps, while non-degenerate modes activate slow-mode pathways that reduce the energy-gap dependence, thus enlarging the window for efficient transfer. These results show that the presence of just one additional vibration reshapes non-perturbative quantum excitation transfer. Our work also establishes a scalable route to simulating chemically relevant, many-mode vibronic processes with engineered environments, guiding the design of next-generation organic photovoltaics and molecular electronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22729v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Visal So, Midhuna Duraisamy Suganthi, Mingjian Zhu, Abhishek Menon, George Tomaras, Roman Zhuravel, Han Pu, Peter G. Wolynes, Jos\'e N. Onuchic, Guido Pagano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Excited State Population and Coherence via Adiabatic Tunneling Ionization and Excitation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22833v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Tunneling ionization followed by strong-field excitation leads to important ultrafast phenomena such as charge migration and lasing. Recent theoretical developments suggest that the population of the ionic excited state can be greatly enhanced due to the complex interplay between tunneling and excitation. In this Letter, using an adiabatic approach for both tunneling and excitation, semi-analytical solutions are derived for the population and coherence of a two-level ionic system. This approach removes the strong-field dressing, revealing novel sub-half-cycle processes for excited state population and coherence buildup. It predicts that the excited state population is enhanced by an order of magnitude, independent of the laser wavelength, while coherence amplitude can be boosted by over four orders of magnitude for a multi-cycle pulse. For a single-cycle pulse, it suggests that coherence amplitude decreases rapidly as the wavelength increases. This work introduces a novel framework for generating and controlling the electronic excited state and coherence using intense laser pulses, with applications in strong-field control of chemistry and lasing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22833v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chi-Hong Yuen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Descriptor Is All You Need: Accurate Machine Learning of Nonadiabatic Coupling Vectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23344v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nonadiabatic couplings (NACs) play a crucial role in modeling photochemical and photophysical processes with methods such as the widely used fewest-switches surface hopping (FSSH). There is therefore a strong incentive to machine learn NACs for accelerating simulations. However, this is challenging due to NACs' vectorial, double-valued character and the singularity near a conical intersection seam. For the first time, we design NAC-specific descriptors based on our domain expertise and show that they allow learning NACs with never-before-reported accuracy of $R^2$ exceeding 0.99. The key to success is also our new ML phase-correction procedure. We demonstrate the efficiency and robustness of our approach on a prototypical example of fully ML-driven FSSH simulations of fulvene targeting the SA-2-CASSCF(6,6) electronic structure level. This ML-FSSH dynamics leads to an accurate description of $S_1$ decay while reducing error bars by allowing the execution of a large ensemble of trajectories. Our implementations are available in open-source MLatom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23344v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakub Martinka, Lina Zhang, Yi-Fan Hou, Miko{\l}aj Martyka, Ji\v{r}\'i Pittner, Mario Barbatti, Pavlo O. Dral</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revolutionising Antibacterial Warfare: Machine Learning and Molecular Dynamics Unveiling Potential Gram-Negative Bacteria Inhibitors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23356v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Diseases caused by bacteria have been a threat to human civilisation for centuries. Despite the availability of numerous antibacterial drugs today, bacterial diseases continue to pose life-threatening challenges. The credit for this goes to Gram-Negative bacteria, which have developed multi-drug resistant properties towards \b{eta}-lactams, chloramphenicols, fluoroquinolones, tetracyclines, carbapenems, and macrolide antibiotics. V arious mechanisms of bacterial defence contribute to drug resistance, with Multi-Drug Efflux Pumps and Enzymatic degradation being the major ones. An effective approach to cope with this resistance is to target and inhibit the activity of efflux pumps and esterases. Even though various Efflux Pump Inhibitors and Esterase resistant macrolide drugs have been proposed in the literature, none of them has achieved FDA approval due to several side effects. This research has provided valuable insights into the mechanism of drug resistance by RND efflux pump and Erythromycin esterase. A handful of potential efflux pump inhibitors have been predicted through machine learning and molecular dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23356v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pritish Joshi, Niladri Patra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin polarized enantio-sensitive multipolar photoelectron currents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23460v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Photoelectron circular dichroism (PECD) manifests as a forward-backward asymmetry of electron emission in the direction orthogonal to the light polarization plane via one-photon ionization of chiral molecules with circularly polarized light. Multi-polar `PECD' currents, i.e., currents resolved along multiple directions, have also been predicted using two mutually-orthogonal linearly polarized light with carrier frequencies $\omega$ and $2\omega$. These currents arise from the interference between the one- and two-photon transitions. Here, we will show that photoelectron spin detection reveals enantio-sensitive multi-polar currents already in the one-photon regime since the two axes can be marked by the photoelectron momentum $\unitvec{k}$ and spin-detection axis $\unitvec{s}$. Specifically, we consider one-photon ionization of an isotropic ensemble of randomly oriented chiral molecules via circularly polarized light and show that the resulting spin-resolved current has three components whose magnitudes are comparable and can be larger than PECD: (i) a spin-polarization vortex in the plane of light polarization that rotates in opposite directions for opposite enantiomers, (ii) either a spin-sink or source in the plane of light polarization for opposite enantiomers, and (iii) a spin analog of photoelectron vortex dichroism (\href{https://journals.aps.org/prl/abstract/10.1103/PhysRevLett.129.233201}{Phys. Rev. Lett. \textbf{129}, 233201, 2022}) wherein the detected photoelectron spin encodes molecular chirality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23460v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Caesar M. Flores, Stefanos Carlstr Carlstrom, Serguei Patchkovskii, Andres F. Ordonez, Olga Smirnova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alchemical diastereomers from antisymmetric alchemical perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.16409v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The leading order Hellmann-Feynman term in the energy difference between any two iso-electronic systems is exact up to third order for the averaged reference Hamiltonian because even-order contributions cancel out. This finding holds for {any} iso-electronic compound pair (dubbed `alchemical diastereomers'), regardless of differences in configuration, composition, or energy. As a result, first order relative energy estimates for all possible iso-electronic alchemical diastereomer pairs, derived from a given averaged reference Hamiltonian, require only ${O}(1)$ self-consistent field cycles. We discuss the relation to the Verlet algorithm, alchemical harmonic approximation (AHA) [\textit{J. Chem. Phys.}\textbf{162}, 044101 (2025)], relative properties such as forces, ionization potential or electron affinities, and Levy's formula for relative energies among iso-electronic systems that uses the averaged electron density of the two systems [\textit{J. Chem. Phys.} \textbf{70}, 1573 (1979)]. Numerical estimates accurately reflect trends in the charge-neutral iso-electronic diatomic molecule series with 14 protons (N$_2$, CO, BF, BeNe, LiNa, HeMg, HAl), with systematically increasing errors. Using alchemical Hellmann-Feynman derivatives for toluene, we demonstrate the concept's broader applicability by estimating relative energies for all 36 possible alchemical diastereomer pairs from vertical iso-electronic charge-neutral antisymmetric BN doping of toluene's aromatic ring, with mean absolute errors of a few milli-Hartrees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.16409v3</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>O. Anatole von Lilienfeld, Giorgio Domenichini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PropMolFlow: Property-guided Molecule Generation with Geometry-Complete Flow Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21469v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Molecule generation is advancing rapidly in chemical discovery and drug design. Flow matching methods have recently set the state of the art (SOTA) in unconditional molecule generation, surpassing score-based diffusion models. However, diffusion models still lead in property-guided generation. In this work, we introduce PropMolFlow, a novel approach for property-guided molecule generation based on geometry-complete SE(3)-equivariant flow matching. Integrating five different property embedding methods with a Gaussian expansion of scalar properties, PropMolFlow achieves competitive performance against previous SOTA diffusion models in conditional molecule generation across various properties while preserving the stability and validity of the generated molecules, consistent with its unconditional counterpart. Additionally, it enables faster inference with significantly fewer time steps compared to baseline models. We highlight the importance of validating the properties of generated molecules through DFT calculations performed at the same level of theory as the training data. Specifically, our analysis identifies properties that require DFT validation and others where a pretrained SE(3) geometric vector perceptron regressors provide sufficiently accurate predictions on generated molecules. Furthermore, we introduce a new property metric to assess the model's ability to propose molecules with underrepresented property values, assessing its capacity for out-of-distribution generalization. Our findings reveal shortcomings in existing structural metrics, which mistakenly validate open-shell molecules or molecules with invalid valence-charge configurations, underscoring the need for improved evaluation frameworks. Overall, this work paves the way for developing targeted property-guided generation methods, enhancing the design of molecular generative models for diverse applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21469v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Zeng, Jirui Jin, George Karypis, Mark Transtrum, Ellad B. Tadmor, Richard G. Hennig, Adrian Roitberg, Stefano Martiniani, Mingjie Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine-Learned Potentials for Solvation Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.22402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.22402v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Solvent environments play a central role in determining molecular structure, energetics, reactivity, and interfacial phenomena. However, modeling solvation from first principles remains difficult due to the complex interplay of interactions and unfavorable computational scaling of first-principles treatment with system size. Machine-learned potentials (MLPs) have recently emerged as efficient surrogates for quantum chemistry methods, offering first-principles accuracy at greatly reduced computational cost. MLPs approximate the underlying potential energy surface, enabling efficient computation of energies and forces in solvated systems, and are capable of accounting for effects such as hydrogen bonding, long-range polarization, and conformational changes. This review surveys the development and application of MLPs in solvation modeling. We summarize the theoretical basis of MLP-based energy and force predictions and present a classification of MLPs based on training targets, model types, and design choices related to architectures, descriptors, and training protocols. Integration into established solvation workflows is discussed, with case studies spanning small molecules, interfaces, and reactive systems. We conclude by outlining open challenges and future directions toward transferable, robust, and physically grounded MLPs for solvation-aware atomistic modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.22402v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roopshree Banchode, Surajit Das, Shampa Raghunathan, Raghunathan Ramakrishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding and Mitigating Distribution Shifts For Machine Learning Force Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.08674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.08674v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Machine Learning Force Fields (MLFFs) are a promising alternative to expensive ab initio quantum mechanical molecular simulations. Given the diversity of chemical spaces that are of interest and the cost of generating new data, it is important to understand how MLFFs generalize beyond their training distributions. In order to characterize and better understand distribution shifts in MLFFs, we conduct diagnostic experiments on chemical datasets, revealing common shifts that pose significant challenges, even for large foundation models trained on extensive data. Based on these observations, we hypothesize that current supervised training methods inadequately regularize MLFFs, resulting in overfitting and learning poor representations of out-of-distribution systems. We then propose two new methods as initial steps for mitigating distribution shifts for MLFFs. Our methods focus on test-time refinement strategies that incur minimal computational cost and do not use expensive ab initio reference labels. The first strategy, based on spectral graph theory, modifies the edges of test graphs to align with graph structures seen during training. Our second strategy improves representations for out-of-distribution systems at test-time by taking gradient steps using an auxiliary objective, such as a cheap physical prior. Our test-time refinement strategies significantly reduce errors on out-of-distribution systems, suggesting that MLFFs are capable of and can move towards modeling diverse chemical spaces, but are not being effectively trained to do so. Our experiments establish clear benchmarks for evaluating the generalization capabilities of the next generation of MLFFs. Our code is available at https://tkreiman.github.io/projects/mlff_distribution_shifts/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.08674v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Kreiman, Aditi S. Krishnapriyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regional chemical potential analysis for material surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04053v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a local regional chemical potential (RCP) analysis method based on an energy window scheme to quantitatively estimate the selectivity of atomic and molecular adsorption on surfaces, as well as the strength of chemical bonding forces between a probe tip and a surface in atomic force microscopy (AFM) measurements. In particular, focusing on the local picture of covalent bonding, we use a simple H$_2$ molecular model to demonstrate a clear relationship between chemical bonding forces and the local RCP. Moreover, density functional theory calculations on molecular systems and diamond C(001) surfaces reveal that the local RCP at the surfaces successfully visualizes electron-donating regions such as dangling bonds and double bonds. These results suggest that the local RCP can serve as an effective measure to analyze high-resolution non-contact or near-contact AFM images enhanced by chemical bonding forces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04053v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahiro Fukuda, Masato Senami, Yoshiaki Sugimoto, Taisuke Ozaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learned Free-Energy Functionals from Pair-Correlation Matching for Dynamical Density Functional Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09543v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Classical density functional theory (cDFT) and dynamical density functional theory (DDFT) are modern statistical mechanical theories for modeling many-body colloidal systems at the one-body density level. The theories hinge on knowing the excess free-energy accurately, which is however not feasible for most practical applications. Dijkman et al. [Phys. Rev. Lett. 134, 056103 (2025)] recently showed how a neural excess free-energy functional for cDFT can be learned from bulk simulations via pair-correlation matching. In this article, we demonstrate how this same functional can be applied to DDFT, without any retraining, to simulate non-equilibrium overdamped dynamics of inhomogeneous densities. We evaluate this on a 3D Lennard-Jones system with planar geometry under various complex external potentials and observe good agreement of the dynamical densities with those from expensive Brownian dynamic simulations, up to the limit of the adiabatic approximation. We further develop and apply an extension of DDFT based on gradient flows, to a grand-canonical system modeled after breakthrough gas adsorption studies, finding similarly good agreement. Our results demonstrate a practical route for leveraging learned free-energy functionals in DDFT, paving the way for accurate and efficient modeling of many-body non-equilibrium systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09543v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karnik Ram, Jacobus Dijkman, Ren\'e van Roij, Jan-Willem van de Meent, Bernd Ensing, Max Welling, Daniel Cremers</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
