<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 05:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction of Polymer of Intrinsic Microporosity PIM-1 with explosive analytes at the molecular level: Combined experiment and computational modelling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13938v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work investigates the molecular-level interactions of a fluorescent microporous polymer (PIM-1) with nitroaromatic explosives, in the context of thin film explosive sensors. Thin films of the PIM-1 were exposed to 2,4-dinitrotoluene (DNT) and 2,4,6-trinitrotoluene (TNT), and their steady-state absorption and emission spectra measured. For comparison, the response of PIM-1 to non-explosive molecules such as benzene (BN) was also explored. Complementary electronic-structure calculations were used to predict absorption and emission spectra and to determine binding energies for the PIM-1-analyte complexes. The calculations agree well with experiment and reveal that association of nitroaromatic analyte molecules with PIM-1 alters the energy levels and the arrangements of frontier orbitals, indicating significant molecular interactions. Calculations show that the electronic properties and photo-excited electron transfer can be described by interaction with a single repeat unit of the polymer. The molecular binding, however, involves interaction with at least three repeat units, with the DNT or TNT molecule binding into a pocket in the contorted structure of the microporous polymer. Together, the experimental and theoretical results demonstrate that PIM-1 is a promising platform for selective nitroaromatic detection and provide molecular design principles that could improve sensitivity and selectivity in future sensor materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13938v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salam Mohammed, Edward B. Ogugu, Ramakant Sharma, Dominic Taylor, Graeme Cooke, Neil McKeown, Glib Baryshnikov, Hans {\AA}gren, Ifor D. W. Samuel, Graham A. Turnbull</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple charge transfer driven complex reaction dynamics: covalent bonding meets van der Waals interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14201v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The details of multiple charge transfer within or among molecules (including the accompanying molecular structure evolution and energy distribution) are typically not accessible on a single molecule level in experiments targeting complex condensed chemical or biological systems. In order to gather such detailed insight, small prototype systems that cover the essence of such processes need to be identified and investigated. Here, we employ a small system consisting of a combination of covalent and van der Waals bonds for our studies, namely N2Ar dimers. We use synchrotron radiation to site-selectively enable the charge transfer processes and perform a coincidence measurement of the resulting electrons and ions. In combination with ab initio calculations, this approach enables a step-by-step tracking of the charge transfer and fragmentation dynamics. We find that ultrafast structural evolution of the dimer can trigger a second CT, thereby opening complex reaction pathways, in which electrons transfer back and forth between Ar and N2, and nonadiabatic transitions occur twice through conical intersections. These results demonstrate that multiple CT-induced transitions, particularly in such a simple dimer system, provide benchmark insights into the mechanisms of nonadiabatic reactions in complex natural systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14201v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruichao Dong, Xiaoqing Hu, Owen Dennis McGinnis, Xincheng Wang, Yikang Zhang, Aha Chen, Andreas Pier, Alexander Tsertsvadze, Huanyu Ma, Jinze Feng, Jessica Weiherer, Laura Sommerlad, Madeleine Schmidt, Niklas Melzer, Noah Kraft, Sina Marie Jacob, Zhenjie Shen, Noelle Walsh, Jianguo Wang, Reinhard D\"orner, Kiyoshi Ueda, Yong Wu, Florian Trinter, Till Jahnke, Yuhai Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recent advances in stimulus-assisted nanoprecipitation for nanoparticle synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14627v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nanoprecipitation, the rapid solvent-displacement route to nanoscale phase separation, has matured from a simple batch operation into a versatile platform for nanomaterial synthesis. This review synthesizes recent progress in stimulus-assisted nanoprecipitation, wherein externally applied triggers (ultrasonic, electrical, supergravity, thermal, chemical, and photonic/other stimuli) are integrated with contemporary mixing technologies (batch, flash, microfluidic, membrane and high-shear reactors) to decouple and selectively control over nucleation, growth kinetics, and assembly processes. These methods allow for the precise tuning of the size, morphology, stability and functionality of nanoparticles (NPs), thereby broadening their applications in drug delivery, catalysis and materials science. We distill mechanistic principles by which each stimulus alters local supersaturation, chain mobility, interfacial instabilities, or droplet/film microreactor dynamics, and compare advantages and limitations by surveying research works from recent years. We also explore the potential development trends of multiscale coupling models, design rules for stimulus-compatible continuous reactors, and adoption of data-driven optimization frameworks to expand the capabilities of nanoprecipitation for advanced nanomaterial design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14627v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingbo Li, Junhao Cai, Yawen Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of Quantum Confinement inside a Viral Capsid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13768v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Classical computational methods, such as molecular dynamics and Monte Carlo simulations, have long been the standard for modeling viral structure and function. However, these approaches may overlook crucial quantum phenomena that operate at the nanoscale, particularly within the highly-compacted genetic material of the viral capsid. The confined, high-density environment of genetic material within the capsid strongly suggests that quantum confinement effects play a significant, yet unexplored, role in viral processes. This study introduces a novel quantum approach using Supersymmetric Quantum Mechanics (SQM) to investigate the quantum confinement effects on viruses. In this paper, the viral capsid environment is modeled using the Pariacoto virus, a model system well-suited for this analysis due to its specific structural properties. The findings reveal that quantum effects are not merely marginal but essential for understanding key processes inside the capsid, providing new insights beyond the scope of classical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13768v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elso Drigo Filho, Regina Maria Ricotta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated Prediction of Thermodynamic Properties via Bayesian Free-Energy Reconstruction from Molecular Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14655v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate free-energy calculations are essential for predicting thermodynamic properties and phase stability, but existing methods are limited: phonon-based approaches neglect anharmonicity and liquids, while molecular dynamics (MD) is computationally demanding, neglects low-temperature quantum effects, and often requires manual planning and post-processing of simulations. We present a unified workflow that reconstructs the Helmholtz free-energy surface from MD data using Gaussian Process Regression (GPR), augmented with zero-point energy corrections from harmonic/quasi-harmonic theory. The framework propagates statistical uncertainties, mitigates finite-size effects, and employs active learning to optimize sampling in the volume-temperature space. It applies seamlessly to both crystalline and liquid phases. We demonstrate the methodology by computing heat capacities, thermal expansion, isothermal and adiabatic bulk moduli, and melting properties for nine elemental FCC and BCC metals using 20 classical and machine-learned interatomic potentials, with all predictions accompanied by quantified confidence intervals. Automated, general, and uncertainty-aware, the workflow advances high-throughput thermodynamics and provides a systematic benchmark for interatomic potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14655v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.cocom.2025.e01163</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Computational Condensed Matter 45 (2025) e01163</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ekaterina Spirande (Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology, Dolgoprudny, Russia, Digital Materials LLC, Odintsovo, Russia, Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology, Moscow, Russia), Timofei Miryashkin (Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology, Moscow, Russia), Andrei Kolmakov (Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology, Dolgoprudny, Russia, Digital Materials LLC, Odintsovo, Russia), Alexander Shapeev (Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology, Moscow, Russia, Digital Materials LLC, Odintsovo, Russia)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Random Determinants to the Ground State</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.14734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.14734v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate quantum many-body calculations often depend on reliable reference states or good human-designed ans\"atze, yet these sources of knowledge can become unreliable in hard problems like strongly correlated systems. We introduce the Trimmed Configuration Interaction (TrimCI) method, a prior-knowledge-free algorithm that builds accurate ground states directly from random Slater determinants. TrimCI iteratively expands the variational space and trims away unimportant states, allowing a random initial core to self-refine into an accurate approximation of exact ground state. Across challenging benchmarks, TrimCI achieves state-of-the-art accuracy with strikingly efficiency gains of several orders of magnitude. For [4Fe-4S] cluster, it matches recent quantum computing results with $10^6$-fold fewer determinants and CPU-hours. For the nitrogenase P-cluster, it matches selected-CI accuracy using $10^5$-fold fewer determinants. For $8\times8$ Hubbard model, it recovers over $99\%$ of the ground-state energy using only $10^{-28}$ of the Hilbert space. In some regimes, TrimCI attains orders-of-magnitude higher accuracy than AFQMC method. These results demonstrate that high-accuracy many-body ground states can be discovered directly from random determinants, establishing TrimCI as a prior-knowledge-free, accurate and highly efficient framework for quantum many-body systems. The compact explicit wavefunctions it produces further enable direct and rapid evaluation of observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.14734v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Zhang, Matthew Otten</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LOCAL: A Locality-based Active Learning Framework for Predicting the Stability of Dual-Atom Catalysts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19445v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Dual-atom catalysts supported on nitrogen-doped graphene (DAC/NG) are emerging as a family of promising catalysts that can overcome intrinsic limitations of single-atom catalysts. However, comprehensive assessment of their structural stability is prohibitively demanding due to a vast local configurational space. Here we introduce LOCAL, a locality-based framework that combines graph convolutional networks with active learning to efficiently predict DAC/NG stability by leveraging chemically intuitive locality quantified by crystal orbital Hamilton population analysis. We demonstrate the effectiveness of LOCAL over a comprehensive dataset of 611,648 DAC/NG structures, achieving a test mean absolute error of 0.15~eV while invoking density functional theory calculations for only 16,704 structures (2.7\% of the dataset). Thus, LOCAL enables efficient and accurate construction of phase diagrams for DAC/NG across diverse compositions reciprocally validated with experimentally synthesized configurations for representative systems. Our framework composes an essential methodology for accelerating the discovery and optimization of high-performance complex catalysts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19445v4</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Yin, Jiangshan He, Runze Li, Dingsheng Wang, Hai Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A direct approach to computing the non-interacting kinetic energy functional</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00321v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The non-interacting kinetic energy functional, $T_{KS}(\rho)$, plays a fundamental role in Density Functional Theory (DFT), but its explicit form remains unknown for arbitrary $N$-representable densities. Although it can, in principle, be evaluated by solving a constrained optimization problem, the associated adjoint problem is not always well-posed; moreover, even when it is, the corresponding adjoint operator may be singular. To the best of our knowledge, none of the existing approaches in the literature precisely determines the non-interacting kinetic energy functional for a given $N$-representable electron density, $\rho$. In this work, we present a variational framework for computing an extension of $T_{KS}(\rho)$ using an exact trigonometric reparametrization of the density that eliminates the need for an adjoint equation. We present a proof-of-concept numerical validation of the variational principle for the special case of one-dimensional Kohn-Sham systems. Our method, however, is general and provides a systematic foundation for computing $T_{KS}(\rho)$ in higher dimensions too, paving the way for improved kinetic energy functionals in DFT.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00321v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dharamveer Kumar, Amuthan A. Ramabathiran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance of Automatic Active Space Selection for Electronic Excitation Energies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05732v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Computation of electronic spectra is one of the most important applications of methods capturing static electron correlation, including complete-active-space self-consistent field (CASSCF) and post-CASSCF theories. Performance of these techniques critically depends on the active space construction, both in terms of accuracy and computational effort. In this work we benchmark the performance of automatic active space construction, as implemented in the Active Space Finder software, for the computation of electronic excitation energies. The multi-step procedure constructs meaningful molecular orbitals and selects the most suitable active space based on information from more approximate correlated calculations. It aims to tackle a key difficulty in computing excitation energies with CASSCF: choosing active spaces that are balanced for several electronic states. The Active Space Finder is tested with several established data sets of small and medium-sized molecules and shows encouraging results. We evaluate multiple setting configurations and provide practical recommendations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05732v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reza G. Shirazi, Alexander Zech, Peter Pinski, Vladimir V. Rybkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slater-Condon Rules and Spin-Orbit Couplings: 2-(2-(2,5-Dimethoxybenzylidene)hydrazineyl)-4-(trifluoromethyl)thiazole a test case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12924v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Light-atom chromophores can display properties often associated with heavy-atom compounds, such as intersystem crossing leading to phosphorescence and singlet oxygen generation, yet their use remains comparatively underexplored. Here, we report the synthesis of HM610, a derivative of the benzylidenehydrazinylthiazole light-atom chromophore backbone. Spin-orbit couplings (SOCs), computed with the sf-X2C-S-TDDFT method, follow Slater-Condon rules and predict moderate values. Trajectory surface hopping simulations further illustrate the role of dynamical effects in promoting ISC, yet these results together establish that HM610 has only limited potential as a triplet sensitizer without further structural modification, such as heavy atom substitution. Based on the benchmarked (TD)DFT protocol, a computational set studying six systematic analogues allowed us to study the influence of electron-donating (-OMe) and electron-withdrawing (-CF3) substituents on the common backbone, revealing the impact of substitution on the geometry and photophysics of light-atom analogues of HM610 and paving the way for future studies where the introduction of heavy atoms and their impact on triplet sensitization by this family of chromophores can be probed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12924v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsomega.5c10359</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hasnain Mehmood, Tashfeen Akhtar, Jes\'us Espinosa-Romero, Mauricio Maldonado-Dom\'inguez, Jakub Vi\v{s}\v{n}\'ak, Mirza Wasif Baig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Local Point-Group-Symmetry Order in Complex Particle Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12665v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Crystals and other condensed phases are defined primarily by their inherent symmetries, which play a crucial role in dictating their structural properties. In crystallization studies, local order parameters (OPs) that describe bond orientational order are widely employed to investigate crystal formation. Despite their utility, these traditional metrics do not directly quantify symmetry, an important aspect for understanding the development of order during crystallization. To address this gap, we introduce a new set of OPs, called Point Group Order Parameters (PGOPs), designed to continuously quantify point group symmetry order. We demonstrate the strength and utility of PGOP in detecting order across different crystalline systems and compare its performance to commonly used bond-orientational order metrics. PGOP calculations for all non-infinite point groups are implemented in the open-source package SPATULA (Symmetry Pattern Analysis Toolkit for Understanding Local Arrangements), written in parallelized C++ with a Python interface. The code is publicly available on GitHub.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12665v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Domagoj Fijan, Maria R. Ward Rashidi, Sharon C. Glotzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Global Spacetime Optimization Approach to the Real-Space Time-Dependent Schr\"odinger Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12983v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The time-dependent Schr\"odinger equation (TDSE) in real space is fundamental to understanding the dynamics of many-electron quantum systems, with applications ranging from quantum chemistry to condensed matter physics and materials science. However, solving the TDSE for complex fermionic systems remains a significant challenge, particularly due to the need to capture the time-evolving many-body correlations, while the antisymmetric nature of fermionic wavefunctions complicates the function space in which these solutions must be represented. We propose a general-purpose neural network framework for solving the real-space TDSE, Fermionic Antisymmetric Spatio-Temporal Network, which treats time as an explicit input alongside spatial coordinates, enabling a unified spatiotemporal representation of complex, antisymmetric wavefunctions for fermionic systems. This approach formulates the TDSE as a global optimization problem, avoiding step-by-step propagation and supporting highly parallelizable training. The method is demonstrated on four benchmark problems: a 1D harmonic oscillator, interacting fermions in a time-dependent harmonic trap, 3D hydrogen orbital dynamics, and a laser-driven H$_2$ molecule, achieving excellent agreement with reference solutions across all cases. These results confirm our method's scalability, accuracy, and flexibility across various dimensions and interaction regimes, while demonstrating its ability to accurately simulate long-time dynamics in complex systems. Our framework offers a highly expressive alternative to traditional basis-dependent or mean-field methods, opening new possibilities for ab initio simulations of time-dependent quantum systems, with applications in quantum dynamics, molecular control, and ultrafast spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12983v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enze Hou, Yuzhi Liu, Lei Wang, Han Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
