<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 04:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of Three-Body Effects on Halogen Bonding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17619v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct a new noncovalent benchmark dataset 3BXB that combines halogen-bonded bimolecular complexes from the SH250 dataset [Kriz and Rezac, Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys. 2022, 24, 14794] with a third interacting partner, either H$_2$O or CH$_4$. The reference total and three-body interaction energies are computed at the CCSD(T) level. To shed light on the physical origins of binding and cooperativity in complexes of this kind, several symmetry-adapted perturbation theory (SAPT)-based energy decompositions were performed for both pairwise additive and nonadditive terms. We found that the two-body attractions in the 3BXB complexes are dominated by either electrostatics or dispersion, while the three-body effect is dominated by induction and can be either attractive or repulsive. An accurate recovery of reference interaction energies is attained by the wavefunction-based two-body SAPT variants including the $\delta$MP2 correction, combined with the SAPT(DFT) estimates of nonadditive induction and first-order exchange and any estimate of nonadditive dispersion. The values for the latter term are sometimes quite inconsistent between different approaches; fortunately, nonadditive dispersion is a relatively minor effect for complexes studied here, and all reasonable estimates lead to total interaction energies of similar accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17619v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sharon A. Ochieng, Konrad Patkowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating the interplay of dipolar and quadrupolar interactions in NMR by spin dynamic mean-field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17720v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The simulation of nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) experiments is a notoriously difficult task, if many spins participate in the dynamics. The recently established dynamic mean-field theory for high-temperature spin systems (spinDMFT) represents an efficient yet accurate method to deal with this scenario. SpinDMFT reduces a complex lattice system to a time-dependent single-site problem, which can be solved numerically with small computational effort. Since the approach retains local quantum degrees of freedom, a quadrupolar term can be exactly incorporated. This allows us to study the interplay of dipolar and quadrupolar interactions for any parameter range, i.e., without the need for a perturbative treatment. We highlight the relevance of local quantum effects by a comparison with the classical analogue system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17720v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timo Gr\"a{\ss}er, G\"otz S. Uhrig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shot-Efficient ADAPT-VQE via Reused Pauli Measurements and Variance-Based Shot Allocation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16879v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Adaptive Variational Quantum Eigensolver (ADAPT-VQE) is a promising approach for quantum algorithms in the Noisy Intermediate-Scale Quantum (NISQ) era, offering advantages over traditional VQE methods by reducing circuit depth and mitigating challenges in classical optimization. However, a major challenge in ADAPT-VQE is the high quantum measurement (shot) overhead required for circuit parameter optimization and operator selection. In this work, we propose two integrated strategies to reduce the shot requirements in ADAPT-VQE. First, we reuse Pauli measurement outcomes obtained during VQE parameter optimization in the subsequent operator selection step of the next ADAPT-VQE iteration, which involves operator gradient measurements. Second, we apply variance-based shot allocation to both Hamiltonian and operator gradient measurements. Our numerical results demonstrate that each method, individually and in combination, significantly reduces the number of shots needed to achieve chemical accuracy while maintaining result fidelity across the studied molecular systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16879v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Azhar Ikhtiarudin, Gagus Ketut Sunnardianto, Fadjar Fathurrahman, Mohammad Kemal Agusta, Hermawan Kresno Dipojono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speed of sound in dense simple liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16967v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The speed of sound of simple dense fluids is shown to exhibit a pronounced freezing temperature scaling of the form $c_{\rm s}/v_{\rm T}\simeq \sqrt{\gamma} +\alpha (T_{\rm fr}/T)^{\beta}$, where $c_s$ is the speed of sound, $v_{\rm T}$ is the characteristic thermal velocity, $\gamma$ is the ideal gas heat capacity ratio, $T$ is the temperature, $T_{\rm fr}$ is the freezing temperature, and $\alpha$ and $\beta$ are dimensionless parameters. For the Lennard-Jones fluid we get $\gamma=5/3$, $\alpha\simeq 7$ with a weak temperature dependence, and $\beta = 1/3$. Similar scaling works in several real liquids, such as argon, krypton, xenon, nitrogen, and methane. In this case, $\alpha$ and $\beta$ are substance-dependent fitting parameters. A comparison between the prediction of this freezing temperature scaling and a recent experimental measurement of the speed of sound in methane under conditions of planetary interiors is presented and discussed. The results provide a simple practical tool to estimate the speed of sound in regimes where no experimental data are yet available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16967v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/5dtk-4x7m</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review E 111, 065423 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sergey Khrapak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Beatings in Optical Cavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17339v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cavity polaritons, quasiparticles formed by coherent light-matter coupling, are at the heart of fundamental concepts of quantum optics. The quintessential signature of this coherent coupling is the Rabi oscillation, which results from the neglect of the counter-rotating-wave (CRW) effect in the weak-coupling regime. The goal of this letter is to predict resonant beatings that envelop the Rabi oscillation on the second or higher excitation manifold. These polariton beatings arise from the CRW term in the Dicke or Pauli-Fierz model and are directly correlated with the asymmetry in polariton eigenenergies. Our findings highlight the relevance of the CRW effect even in the weak-coupling regime, offer novel perspectives about coherent polariton dynamics, and shed new light on experiments of coupled quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17339v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ishaan Ganti, Jianshu Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>pH-dependent interfacial rheology of polymer membranes assembled at liquid-liquid interfaces using hydrogen bonds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17355v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Self-assembly of polymers at liquid interfaces using non-covalent interactions has emerged as a promising technique to reversibly produce self-healing membranes. Besides the assembly process, it is also crucial to control the mechanical properties of these membranes. Here, we measure the interfacial rheological properties of PMAA-PPO (polymethacrylic acidpolypropylene oxide) polymer membranes assembled using hydrogen bonds at liquid-oil interfaces. Varying the pH enables us to modify the degree of ionization of the PMAA chains, and hence their ability to establish hydrogen interactions with PPO. Frequency sweeps of the interfacial layers show a crossover between a viscous regime at low frequencies and an elastic regime at high frequencies. The crossover elastic modulus decreases by half after one hour of the experiment over the pH range investigated, which can be accounted for by a decrease of the layer thickness as pH increases. Furthermore we find that the crossover frequency varies exponentially with the degree of ionization of PMAA. To account for these observations, we propose a simple picture where the short PPO chains behave as non-covalent cross-linkers that bridge several PMAA chains. The dissociation rate and hence the crossover frequency are controlled by the number of PO units per PPO chain involved in the hydrogen bonds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17355v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julien Dupr\'e de Baubigny (SIMM), Corentin Tregouet (SIMM), Elena N. Govorun (SIMM), Mathilde Reyssat (SIMM), Patrick Perrin (SIMM), Nad\`ege Pantoustier (SIMM), Thomas Salez (LOMA), C\'ecile Monteux (SIMM)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reasoning-Driven Retrosynthesis Prediction with Large Language Models via Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17448v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Retrosynthesis planning, essential in organic synthesis and drug discovery, has greatly benefited from recent AI-driven advancements. Nevertheless, existing methods frequently face limitations in both applicability and explainability. Traditional graph-based and sequence-to-sequence models often lack generalized chemical knowledge, leading to predictions that are neither consistently accurate nor easily explainable. To address these challenges, we introduce RetroDFM-R, a reasoning-based large language model (LLM) designed specifically for chemical retrosynthesis. Leveraging large-scale reinforcement learning guided by chemically verifiable rewards, RetroDFM-R significantly enhances prediction accuracy and explainability. Comprehensive evaluations demonstrate that RetroDFM-R significantly outperforms state-of-the-art methods, achieving a top-1 accuracy of 65.0% on the USPTO-50K benchmark. Double-blind human assessments further validate the chemical plausibility and practical utility of RetroDFM-R's predictions. RetroDFM-R also accurately predicts multistep retrosynthetic routes reported in the literature for both real-world drug molecules and perovskite materials. Crucially, the model's explicit reasoning process provides human-interpretable insights, thereby enhancing trust and practical value in real-world retrosynthesis applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17448v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Situo Zhang, Hanqi Li, Lu Chen, Zihan Zhao, Xuanze Lin, Zichen Zhu, Bo Chen, Xin Chen, Kai Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scattering Angle Dependence of Fano Resonance Profiles in Cold Atomic Collisions Analyzed with the Complex Valued $w$ Parameter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17674v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The scattering angle dependence of Fano resonance profiles in cold atomic collisions has been theoretically studied. A complex-valued parameter $ w $ with an analytical formula describing the asymmetry of the resonance profile is proposed as a new development from previous work on electron resonance scattering from atoms [F. Koike, J. Phys. $\mathbf{B10}$, 2883 (1977)]. It serves as the general formulation which leads to the angle-dependence of Fano's $ q $ parameter. Calculations for the case of cold elastic collisions of hydrogen atoms with krypton atoms have been accomplished. The strong angle dependence of the resonance profile asymmetry in the differential scattering cross section due to the interference with non-resonant partial waves is demonstrated. The scattering angle dependence of the resonance profile and thus the newly proposed asymmetry parameter is highly sensitive to the inter-atomic interaction potentials. This is likely to prove useful for the study of interaction potentials themselves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17674v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tanmay Singh, Raj Aryan Singh, Fumihiro Koike, Masatomi Iizawa, Yoshiro Azuma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light-Induced Persistent Electronic Chirality in Achiral Molecules Probed with Time-Resolved Electronic Circular Dichroism Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16986v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Chiral systems exhibit unique properties traditionally linked to their asymmetric spatial arrangement. Recently, multiple laser pulses were shown to induce purely electronic chiral states without altering the nuclear configuration. Here, we propose and numerically demonstrate a simpler realization of light-induced electronic chirality that is long-lived and occurs well before the onset of nuclear motion and decoherence. A single monochromatic circularly-polarized laser pulse is shown to induce electronic chiral currents in an oriented achiral molecule. Using state-of-the-art ab initio theory, we analyze this effect and relate the chiral currents to induced magnetic dipole moments, detectable via attosecond time-resolved electronic circular dichroism (TR-ECD) spectroscopy, also known as transient absorption ECD. The resulting chiral electronic wavepacket oscillates rapidly in handedness at harmonics of the pump laser's carrier frequency, and the currents persist after the pulse ends. We establish a chiral molecular-current analogue to high harmonic generation, and demonstrate attosecond transient chirality control with potential impact on spintronics and reaction dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16986v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Torsha Moitra, Lukas Konecny, Marius Kadek, Ofer Neufeld, Angel Rubio, Michal Repisky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Hierarchical Models for Quantitative Estimates for Performance metrics applied to Saddle Search Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13621v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Rigorous performance evaluation is essential for developing robust algorithms for high-throughput computational chemistry. Traditional benchmarking, however, often struggles to account for system-specific variability, making it difficult to form actionable conclusions. We present a Bayesian hierarchical modeling framework that rigorously quantifies performance metrics and their uncertainty, enabling a nuanced comparison of algorithmic strategies. We apply this framework to analyze the Dimer method, comparing Conjugate Gradient (CG) and L-BFGS rotation optimizers, with and without the removal of external rotations, across a benchmark of 500 molecular systems. Our analysis confirms that CG offers higher overall robustness than L-BFGS in this context. While the theoretically-motivated removal of external rotations led to higher computational cost (&gt;40% more energy and force calls) for most systems in this set, our models also reveal a subtle interplay, hinting that this feature may improve the reliability of the L-BFGS optimizer. Rather than identifying a single superior method, our findings support the design of adaptive "chain of methods" workflows. This work showcases how a robust statistical paradigm can move beyond simple performance rankings to inform the intelligent, context-dependent application of computational chemistry methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13621v3</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rohit Goswami (Science Institute and Faculty of Physical Sciences, University of Iceland, Reykjav\'ik, Iceland, Department of Mechanical and Materials Engineering, Queen's University, Kingston, Ontario, Canada)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A reduced cost equation of motion coupled cluster method for excited states based on state-specific natural orbitals: Theory, Implementation, Benchmark</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16894v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a reduced-cost equation-of-motion coupled-cluster method for excited states, built on a new state-specific frozen natural orbital (SS-FNO) framework. This approach enables systematic and controllable truncation of the virtual spaces, significantly reducing computational demands while maintaining high accuracy. The method allows black-box application via two adjustable thresholds and includes a perturbative correction that compensates for truncation errors. We have tested the performance of both CIS(D) and ADC(2) methods in generating appropriate natural orbitals for excited states. Benchmarking on valence, Rydberg, and charge-transfer excited states demonstrates excellent agreement with canonical EE-EOM-CCSD results, with mean absolute deviations typically below 0.02 eV when ADC(2) natural orbitals with perturbative corrections are applied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16894v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amrita Manna, Achintya Kumar Dutta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular Quantum Control Algorithm Design by Reinforcement Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11839v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Precision measurements of molecules offer an unparalleled paradigm to probe physics beyond the Standard Model. The rich internal structure within these molecules makes them exquisite sensors for detecting fundamental symmetry violations, local position invariance, and dark matter. While trapping and control of diatomic and a few very simple polyatomic molecules have been experimentally demonstrated, leveraging the complex rovibrational structure of more general polyatomics demands the development of robust and efficient quantum control schemes. In this study, we present reinforcement-learning quantum-logic spectroscopy (RL-QLS), a general, reinforcement-learning-designed, quantum logic approach to prepare molecular ions in single, pure quantum states. The reinforcement learning agent optimizes the pulse sequence, each followed by a projective measurement, and probabilistically manipulates the collapse of the quantum system to a single state. The performance of the control algorithm is numerically demonstrated for the polyatomic molecule H$_3$O$^+$ with 130 thermally populated eigenstates and degenerate transitions within inversion doublets, where quantum Markov decision process modeling and a physics-informed reward function play a key role, as well as for CaH$^+$ under the disturbance of environmental thermal radiation. The developed theoretical framework cohesively integrates techniques from quantum chemistry, AMO physics, and artificial intelligence, and we expect that the results can be readily implemented for quantum control of polyatomic molecular ions with densely populated structures, thereby enabling new experimental tests of fundamental theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11839v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anastasia Pipi, Xuecheng Tao, Arianna Wu, Prineha Narang, David R. Leibrandt</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
