<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 01:23:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Instanton Theory for Nonadiabatic Tunneling through Near-Barrier Crossings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01151v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many reactions in chemistry and biology involve multiple electronic states, rendering them nonadiabatic in nature. These reactions can be formally described using Fermi's golden rule (FGR) in the weak-coupling limit. Nonadiabatic instanton theory presents a semiclassical approximation to FGR, which is directly applicable to molecular systems. However, there are cases where the theory has not yet been formulated. For instance, in many real-world reactions including spin-crossover or proton-coupled electron transfer, the crossing occurs near a barrier on a diabatic state. This scenario gives rise to competing nonadiabatic reaction pathways, some of which involve tunneling through a diabatic barrier while simultaneously switching electronic states. To date, no rate theory is available for describing tunneling via these unconventional pathways. Here we extend instanton theory to model this class of processes, which we term the ``non-convex'' regime. Benchmark tests on model systems show that the rates predicted by instanton theory are in excellent agreement with quantum-mechanical FGR calculations. Furthermore, the method offers new insights into multi-step tunneling reactions and the competition between sequential and concerted nonadiabatic tunneling pathways.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01151v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyan Ye, Eric R. Heller, Dong H. Zhang, Jeremy O. Richardson, Wei Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing aqueous interfaces with spin defects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01220v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the physical and chemical properties of aqueous interfaces is important in diverse fields of science, ranging from biology and chemistry to materials science. In spite of crucial progress in surface sensitive spectroscopic techniques over the past decades, the microscopic properties of aqueous interfaces remain difficult to measure. Here we explore the use of noise spectroscopy to characterize interfacial properties, specifically of quantum sensors hosted in two-dimensional materials in contact with water. We combine molecular dynamics simulations of water/graphene interfaces and the calculations of the spin dynamics of an NV-like color center, and we investigate the impact of interfacial water and simple ions on the decoherence time of the defect. We show that the Hahn echo coherence time of the NV center is sensitive to motional narrowing and to the hydrogen bonding arrangement and the dynamical properties of water and ions at the interface. We present results as a function of the liquid temperature, strength of the water-surface interaction, and for varied mono-valent and di-valent ions, highlighting the broad applicability of near-surface qubits to gain insight into the properties of aqueous interfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01220v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alfonso Castillo, Gustavo R. Perez-Lemus, Mykyta Onizhuk, Giulia Galli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overview of Topics in Electrocatalysis for Sustainability: Reactions, Electrocatalysts, Degradation, and Mitigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01311v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Electrocatalysis provides an avenue for transitioning the global energy dependence from fossil fuels to renewable energy sources. While electrocatalytic reactions are being used for several decades, recently, there is a growing interest for electrocatalytic reactions that are useful from sustainability perspective. The wide industrial applications of these sustainable electrocatalytic processes is largely limited by the degradation of the electrocatalysts. This review begins with an introduction to such reactions, followed by a detailed discussion of the electrocatalysts. Finally we describe the processes that are responsible for the degradation of electrocatalytic activity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01311v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Varada Purohit, Avdhoot Datar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Large Language Model for Chemistry and Retrosynthesis Predictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01444v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Large language models (LLM) have achieved impressive progress across a broad range of general-purpose tasks, but their effectiveness in chemistry remains limited due to scarce domain-specific datasets and the demand for precise symbolic and structural reasoning. Here we introduce ECNU-ChemGPT(name after East China Normal University), a chemistry-specialized LLM engineered for deep chemical knowledge understanding and accurate retrosynthetic route planning. Our approach is distinguished by four key strategies: structured prompt-based knowledge distillation from authoritative chemistry textbooks to construct a high-quality question-answering dataset; domain-specific prompt engineering using curated chemical keywords, combined with LLMs APIs for data derivation and knowledge distillation; large-scale fine-tuning on a meticulously cleaned and enriched Pistachio reaction dataset to enhance retrosynthesis prediction accuracy; and integration of BrainGPT, a dynamic multi-model scheduling framework that enables task-specific invocation of multiple specialized models trained for diverse chemistry-related tasks. ECNU-ChemGPT exhibits superior performance on chemistry question-answering and retrosynthetic planning benchmarks, outperforming leading general-purpose models-including Deepseek-R1, Qwen-2.5, and GPT-4o. In retrosynthesis, it achieves a Top-1 accuracy of 68.3% on the USPTO_50K dataset and successfully reconstructed 13 complete experimental pathways for real-world drug molecules from medicinal chemistry journals. These results underscore the effectiveness of domain-adapted fine-tuning combined with dynamic multi-model task scheduling, providing a scalable and robust solution for chemical knowledge question answering and retrosynthetic planning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01444v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yueqing Zhang, Wentao Liu, Yan Zhang, Danyang Xiong, Jihang Zhai, Hao Hao, YuCheng Gu, HaiBo Yang, Shuanhu Gao, Lianrui Hu, Aimin Zhou, Xiao He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning prediction of a chemical reaction over 8 decades of energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01793v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent progress in machine learning has sparked increased interest in utilizing this technology to predict the outcomes of chemical reactions. The ultimate aim of such endeavors is to develop a universal model that can predict products for any chemical reaction given reactants and physical conditions. In pursuit of ever more universal chemical predictors, machine learning models for atom-diatom and diatom-diatom reactions have been developed, yet no such models exist for termolecular reactions. Accordingly, we introduce neural networks trained to predict opacity functions of atom recombination reactions. Our models predict the recombination of Sr$^+$ + Cs + Cs $\rightarrow$ SrCs$^+$ + Cs and Sr$^+$ + Cs + Cs $\rightarrow$ Cs$_2$ + Sr$^+$ over multiple orders of magnitude of energy, yielding overall results with a relative error $\lesssim 10\%$. Even far beyond the range of energies seen during training, our models predict the atom recombination reaction rate accurately. As a result, the machine is capable of learning the physics behind the atom recombination reaction dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01793v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Julian, Jes\'us P\'erez-R\'ios</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Attosecond Control and Measurement of Chiral Photoionisation Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01906v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many chirality-sensitive light-matter interactions are governed by chiral electron dynamics. Therefore, the development of advanced technologies harnessing chiral phenomena would critically benefit from measuring and controlling chiral electron dynamics on their natural attosecond time scales. Such endeavors have so far been hampered by the lack of characterized circularly polarized attosecond pulses, an obstacle that has recently been overcome (Han et al. Optica 10 (2023) 1044-1052, Han et al. Nature Physics 19 (2023) 230-236). In this article, we introduce chiroptical spectroscopy with attosecond pulses and demonstrate attosecond coherent control over photoelectron circular dichroism (PECD) (Goetz et al. Physical Review Letters 122 (2019) 013204, Goetz et al. arXiv:2104.07522), as well as the measurement of chiral asymmetries in the forward-backward and angle-resolved photoionisation delays of chiral molecules. We show that co-rotating attosecond and near-infrared pulses can nearly double the PECD and even change its sign compared to single-photon ionisation. We demonstrate that chiral photoionisation delays depend on both polar and azimuthal angles of photoemission in the light-propagation frame, requiring three-dimensional momentum resolution. We measure forward-backward chiral-sensitive delays of up to 120 as and polar-angle-resolved photoionisation delays up to 240 as, which include an asymmmetry of $\sim$60 as originating from chirality in the continuum-continuum transitions. Attosecond chiroptical spectroscopy opens the door to quantitatively understanding and controlling the dynamics of chiral molecules on the electronic time scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01906v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meng Han, Jia-Bao Ji, Alexander Blech, R. Esteban Goetz, Corbin Allison, Loren Greenman, Christiane P. Koch, Hans Jakob W\"orner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TeO2-BaO-Bi2O3 tellurite optical glasses II. -- Linear and non-linear optical and magneto-optical properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01258v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The present study investigates the linear and non-linear optical and magneto-optical properties of TeO$_2$-BaO-Bi$_2$O$_3$ (TeBaBi) glasses prepared by the conventional melt-quenching technique at 900 {\deg}C. Prepared glass composition ranges across the whole glass-forming-ability (GFA) region focusing on mutual substitution trends of constituent oxides, where TeO$_2$: 55-85 mol.%, BaO: 10-35 mol.%, Bi$_2$O$_3$: 5-15 mol.%. Studied glasses exhibit high values of linear ($n_{632} \approx$ 1.922-2.084) and non-linear refractive index ($n_2\approx$1.63-3.45$\times10^{-11}$ esu), Verdet constant ($V_{632} \approx$ 26.7-45.3 radT$^{-1}$m$^{-1}$) and optical band gap energy ($E_g \approx$ 3.1-3.6 eV). The introduction of TeO$_2$ and Bi$_2$O$_3$ results in increase of both linear/non-linear refractive index and Verdet constant, with a more pronounced influence of Bi$_2$O$_3$. Measured spectral dispersion of refractive index and Verdet constant were used for estimation of magneto-optic anomaly parameter ($\gamma \approx$ 0.71-0.92), which may be used for theoretical modelling of magneto-optic response in diamagnetic TeBaBi glasses. Additionally, the properties of the prepared TeBaBi glasses were directly compared to those of the TeO$_2$-ZnO-BaO glass system, which was prepared and characterized under similar experimental conditions. The compositional dependence of the refractive index in both glass systems was described using multilinear regression analysis, demonstrating high correlation and uniformity of estimation across the entire GFA region. This makes them highly promising for precise dispersion engineering and construction of optical devices operating from visible to mid-infrared spectral region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01258v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Hrabovsk\'y, Jaden R. Love, Luk\'a\v{s} St\v{r}i\v{z}\'ik, Takayuki Ishibashi, Stefan Zollner, Martin Veis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative flow-based warm start of the variational quantum eigensolver</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01726v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hybrid quantum-classical algorithms like the variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) show promise for quantum simulations on near-term quantum devices, but are often limited by complex objective functions and expensive optimization procedures. Here, we propose Flow-VQE, a generative framework leveraging conditional normalizing flows with parameterized quantum circuits to efficiently generate high-quality variational parameters. By embedding a generative model into the VQE optimization loop through preference-based training, Flow-VQE enables quantum gradient-free optimization and offers a systematic approach for parameter transfer, accelerating convergence across related problems through warm-started optimization. We compare Flow-VQE to a number of standard benchmarks through numerical simulations on molecular systems, including hydrogen chains, water, ammonia, and benzene. We find that Flow-VQE outperforms baseline optimization algorithms, achieving computational accuracy with fewer circuit evaluations (improvements range from modest to more than two orders of magnitude) and, when used to warm-start the optimization of new systems, accelerates subsequent fine-tuning by up to 50-fold compared with Hartree--Fock initialization. Therefore, we believe Flow-VQE can become a pragmatic and versatile paradigm for leveraging generative modeling to reduce the costs of variational quantum algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01726v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hang Zou, Martin Rahm, Anton Frisk Kockum, Simon Olsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analyzing Common Electronic Structure Theory Algorithms for Distributed Quantum Computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01902v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To move towards the utility era of quantum computing, many corporations have posed distributed quantum computing (DQC) as a framework for scaling the current generation of devices for practical applications. One of these applications is quantum chemistry, also known as electronic structure theory, which has been poised as a "killer application" of quantum computing, To this end, we analyze five electronic structure methods, found in common packages such as Tequila and ffsim, which can be easily interfaced with the Qiskit Circuit Cutting addon. Herein, we provide insights into cutting these algorithms using local operations (LO) to determine their aptitude for distribution. The key findings of our work are that many of these algorithms cannot be efficiently parallelized using LO, and new methods must be developed to apply electronic structure theory within a DQC framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01902v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grier M. Jones, Hans-Arno Jacobsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A comprehensive theory for relativistic polaritonic chemistry: a four components ab initio treatment of molecular systems coupled to quantum fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12757v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a new ab initio approach to study molecules containing heavy atoms strongly interacting with quantum fields in optical devices. The theory has been derived from the relativistic quantum electrodynamics (QED) introducing the approximations needed to provide a formalism suitable for relativistic quantum chemistry. This framework represents the ideal starting point to extend the main quantum chemistry methods to relativistic polaritonic. The Polaritonic Dirac Hartree Fock (Pol-DHF) approach is the first method we propose based on this theory. Pol-DHF allows for the simulation of field induced effects on the ground and excited state properties of heavy transition metals molecular complexes. The method is able to include not only the effects of the photons, but can in principle be extended also to include explicit interactions with positrons. Application of Pol-DHF to three metal hydrides shows that the magnitude of both polaritonic and relativistic effects can be comparable when relativistic effects are getting more important. Due to an accurate description of spin-orbit coupling, the method is able to reproduce polaritonic effects happening at the crossing between singlet and triplet potential energy surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12757v4</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Thiam, Riccardo Rossi, Henrik Koch, Leonardo Belpassi, Enrico Ronca</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-eddy simulation of turbulent spray flames: Effects of scalar correlation and enthalpy reduction in flamelet modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.01045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.01045v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Numerical modeling of turbulent spray combustion provides a promising tool for advanced engine design. In spray flames, the droplet evaporation not only reduces the ambient gas temperature, but also influences flame structure by generating substantial local fluctuations of the mixture fraction $\widetilde{Z}$ and progress variable $\widetilde{c}$. These two scalars, conventionally assumed independent in flamelet models, exhibit significant correlations arising from the coupling among evaporation, turbulent mixing and chemical reactions. This study proposes a six-dimensional flamelet-generated manifolds (FGM) method, considering the evaporation-induced specific enthalpy reduction and scalar correlation. A novel joint presumed probability density function (PDF) method is derived using the copula theory, achieving rapid grid convergence and good feasibility. Large-eddy simulation (LES) is performed on the Sydney ethanol turbulent spray flames (EtF1, EtF4 and EtF7), which feature different ethanol mass flow rates and jet Reynolds numbers. Both gas and liquid phase statistics show good agreement with experimental data across the three flames. The incorporation of specific enthalpy reduction and scalar correlation in FGM modeling improves gas temperature predictions, along with enhanced liquid-phase prediction through refined gas-field resolution. The correlation coefficient of $\widetilde{Z}$ and $\widetilde{c}$ is found to be a competing result of local evaporation and combustion, since evaporation elevates $\widetilde{Z}$ and dilutes reaction products, whereas chemical reactions enhance $\widetilde{c}$ fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.01045v5</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dong Wang, Min Zhang, Ruixin Yang, Zhi X. Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aitomia: Your Intelligent Assistant for AI-Driven Atomistic and Quantum Chemical Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08195v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We have developed Aitomia - a platform powered by AI to assist in performing AI-driven atomistic and quantum chemical (QC) simulations. This evolving intelligent assistant platform is equipped with chatbots and AI agents to help experts and guide non-experts in setting up and running the atomistic simulations, monitoring their computation status, analyzing the simulation results, and summarizing them for the user in text and graphical forms. We achieve these goals by exploiting open-source large language models (LLMs, original and fine-tuned), rule-based agents, and a retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) system. Aitomia leverages the versatility of our MLatom ecosystem, supporting AI-enhanced computational chemistry tasks ranging from ground- to excited-state calculations such as geometry optimizations, thermochemistry, and spectra calculations. Aitomia is the first intelligent assistant publicly accessible online on a cloud computing platform for atomistic simulations of broad scope (Aitomistic Hub at https://aitomistic.xyz), while it may also be deployed locally as described at http://mlatom.com/aitomia. Aitomia is expected to lower the barrier to performing atomistic simulations, democratizing simulations, and accelerating research and development in the relevant fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08195v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinming Hu, Hassan Nawaz, Yuting Rui, Lijie Chi, Arif Ullah, Pavlo O. Dral</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
