<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 04:00:36 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Vibrational corrections to molecular properties including relativistic corrections at the level of the Zeroth-Order Regular Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12412v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The vibrational averaging module of the Dalton Project was extended to work also with the Amsterdam Density Functional (ADF) program, making it possible to calculate vibrational corrections to properties and at the same time include a treatment of relativistic effects for heavier atoms at the level of the Zeroth-Order Regular Approximation (ZORA). To illustrate the importance of the relativistic contributions, zero-point vibrational corrections were calculated for the electric field gradient tensor and the two NMR parameters, the isotropic shielding and the spin-spin coupling constants (SSCC), of selected mercury compounds. For all three properties, the vibrational corrected values performed closest to experimental values, and the magnitudes of the corrections depended on the level of relativity and the basis set in the calculation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12412v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louise M{\o}ller Jessen, Ronan Gleeson, Lars Hemmingsen, Stephan P. A. Sauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic Radial Correlation Energy Density Components</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12580v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The components of the radial correlation energy density are calculated and analyzed for the atoms from He to Ar. The components include the nucleus-electron potential correlation energy density, the kinetic correlation energy density and the electron-electron potential correlation energy density. The necessary correlated one and two-electron density matrices are obtained from the Extrapolated-Full-Configuration-Interaction (exFCI) wave function where the reference wave function is restricted Hartree-Fock (RHF) or restricted open-shell Hartree-Fock (ROHF) depending on whether the atom is closed or open-shell. The accuracy associated with integrating the HF and exFCI energy density components, and the correlation energy density components, is evaluated on the SG-1 and SG-2 atomic grids. The SG-1 grid provides atomic energies that are accurate to about 1 kJ mol$^{-1}$, with the exception of the kinetic energy. The SG-2 grid is required for the analysis of atomic kinetic energies and more subtle energetic effects. There is also a significant amount of integration error cancellation in the correlation energy densities. The radial correlation energy densities display notable shell structure, and there is a substantial difference between the $\alpha$ and $\beta$-electron correlation energy densities for the open-shell atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12580v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ibrahim E. Awad, Abd Al-Aziz A. Abu-Saleh, Gurleen Cheema, Joshua W. Hollett, Raymond A. Poirier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oxygen vacancy formation in ZnSeTe blue quantum dot light-emitting diodes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12598v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advancements have led to the development of bright and heavy metal-free blue-emitting quantum dot light-emitting diodes (QLEDs). However, consensus understanding of their distinct photophysical and electroluminescent dynamics remains elusive. This work correlates the chemical and electronic changes occurring in a QLED during operation using depth-resolved and operando techniques. The results indicate that oxygen vacancy forms in the ZnMgO layer during operation, with important implications on the charge injection and electrochemical dynamics. Taken together, the results suggest a causal relationship between oxygen vacancy formation and operational degradation of the blue-emitting ZnSeTe-based QLEDs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12598v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shaun Tan, Sujin Park, Seung-Gu Choi, Oliver J. Tye, Ruiqi Zhang, Jonah R. Horowitz, Heejae Chung, Vladimir Bulovi\'c, Jeonghun Kwak, Jin-Wook Lee, Taehyung Kim, Moungi G. Bawendi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extension of the Jordan-Wigner mapping to nonorthogonal spin orbitals for quantum computing application to valence bond approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12680v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum computing offers a promising platform to address the computational challenges inherent in quantum chemistry, and particularly in valence bond (VB) methods, which are chemically appealing but suffer from high computational cost due to the use of nonorthogonal orbitals. While various fermionic-to-spin mappings exist for orthonormal spin orbitals, such as the widely used Jordan-Wigner transformations, an analogous framework for nonorthogonal spin orbitals remains undeveloped. In this work, we propose an alternative Jordan-Wigner-type mapping tailored for the nonorthogonal case, with the goal of enabling efficient quantum simulations of VB-type wavefunctions. Our approach paves the way towards the development of chemically interpretable and computationally feasible valence bond algorithms on near-term quantum devices. An initial theoretical analysis and a preliminary application demonstrate the feasibility of this encoding and its potential for extending the applicability of VB methods to larger and more complex systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12680v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/bs.aiq.2025.07.007</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advances in Quantum Chemistry, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alessia Marruzzo, Mos\`e Casalegno, Piero Macchi, Fabio Mascherpa, Bernardino Tirri, Guido Raos, Alessandro Genoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure dependent structure of neat liquid methanol, CH3OH: molecular dynamics simulations with various united atom type potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12834v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Molecular dynamics computer simulations have been conducted on neat liquid methanol, using three different united atom (three site) interatomic potentials: TraPPE [J. Phys. Chem. B 105, 3093 (2001)], UAM-I [J. Mol. Liq. 323, 114576 (2021)] and OPLS/2016 [J. Chem. Phys. 145, 034508 (2016)]. The effects of pressure, between 1 bar and 6 kbar, have been evaluated on total scattering structure factors, partial radial distribution functions, as well as on collective characteristics such as ring size distributions and cluster size distributions. Agreement with experimental density is nearly quantitative for all the three force fields, and major trends observed for recent pressure dependent neutron diffraction data are reproduced qualitatively. The OPLS/2016 force field, in general, generates properties that are markedly different from results originating from the other potentials. Pressure effects are hardly noticeable on most partial radial distribution functions and on the distribution of the number of hydrogen bonded neighbours. On the other hand, collective structural properties, like cluster- and ring size distributions exhibit significant changes with increasing pressure: larger clusters become more numerous, whereas the number of cyclic clusters, i.e., rings, decrease. The self-diffusion coefficient decreases with increasing pressure, and the same is valid for the average lifetime of hydrogen bonds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12834v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Imre Bak\'o, L\'aszl\'o Pusztai, Orest Pizio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Attosecond-resolved probing of recolliding electron wave packets in liquids and aqueous solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12872v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-harmonic spectroscopy (HHS) in liquids promises real-time access to ultrafast electronic dynamics in the native environment of chemical and biological processes. While electron recollision has been established as the dominant mechanism of high-harmonic generation (HHG) in liquids, resolving the underlying electron dynamics has remained elusive. Here we demonstrate attosecond-resolved measurements of recolliding electron wave packets, extending HHS from neat liquids to aqueous solutions. Using phase-controlled two-colour fields, we observe a linear scaling of the two-colour delay that maximizes even-harmonic emission with photon energy, yielding slopes of 208+/-55 as/eV in ethanol and 124+/-42 as/eV in water, the latter matching ab initio simulations (125+/-48 as/eV). In aqueous salt solutions, we uncover interference minima whose appearance depends on solute type and concentration, arising from destructive interference between solute and solvent emission. By measuring the relative phase of solvent and solute HHG, we retrieve a variation of electron transit time by 113+/-32 as/eV, consistent with our neat-liquid results. These findings establish HHS as a powerful attosecond-resolved probe of electron dynamics in disordered media, opening transformative opportunities for studying ultrafast processes such as energy transfer, charge migration, and proton dynamics in liquids and solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12872v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angana Mondal, Nicolas Tancogne-Dejean, George Trenins, Sona Achotian, Meng Han, Tadas Balciunas, Zhong Yin, Angel Rubio, Mariana Rossi, Ofer Neufeld, Hans Jakob W\"orner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formalizing dimensional analysis using the Lean theorem prover</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13142v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dimensional analysis is fundamental to the formulation and validation of physical laws, ensuring that equations are dimensionally homogeneous and scientifically meaningful. In this work, we use Lean 4 to formalize the mathematics of dimensional analysis. We define physical dimensions as mappings from base dimensions to exponents, prove that they form an Abelian group under multiplication, and implement derived dimensions and dimensional homogeneity theorems. Building on this foundation, we introduce a definition of physical variables that combines numeric values with dimensions, extend the framework to incorporate SI base units and fundamental constants, and implement the Buckingham Pi Theorem. Finally, we demonstrate the approach on an example: the Lennard-Jones potential, where our framework enforces dimensional consistency and enables formal proofs of physical properties such as zero-energy separation and the force law. This work establishes a reusable, formally verified framework for dimensional analysis in Lean, providing a foundation for future libraries in formalized science and a pathway toward scientific computing environments with built-in guarantees of dimensional correctness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13142v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxwell P. Bobbin, Colin Jones, John Velkey, Tyler R. Josephson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying Local Point-Group-Symmetry Order in Complex Particle Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12665v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Crystals and other condensed phases are defined primarily by their inherent symmetries, which play a crucial role in dictating their structural properties. In crystallization studies, local order parameters (OPs) that describe bond orientational order are widely employed to investigate crystal formation. Despite their utility, these traditional metrics do not directly quantify symmetry, an important aspect for understanding the development of order during crystallization. To address this gap, we introduce a new set of OPs, called Point Group Order Parameters (PGOPs), designed to continuously quantify point group symmetry order. We demonstrate the strength and utility of PGOP in detecting order across different crystalline systems and compare its performance to commonly used bond-orientational order metrics. PGOP calculations for all non-infinite point groups are implemented in the open-source package SPATULA (Symmetry Pattern Analysis Toolkit for Understanding Local Arrangements), written in parallelized C++ with a Python interface. The code is publicly available on GitHub.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12665v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Domagoj Fijan, Maria R. Ward Rashidi, Sharon C. Glotzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmic dust as a prerequisite for the formation of complex organic molecules in space?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12967v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In cold, dense astrophysical environments dust grains are mixed with molecular ices. Chemistry in those dust/ice mixtures is determined by diffusion and reaction of molecules and radicals. However, investigations of diffusion of astrophysically relevant radicals and molecules across the surface and through the pores of cosmic dust grains and of surface reactions consequent to such diffusion is largely uncharted territory. This paper presents results of a study of a solid-state reaction of two molecular species, CO2 and NH3, separated by a layer of porous silicate grain aggregates, analogues of cosmic dust. The experiments demonstrate that the presence of the dust layer was necessary for a pure thermal CO2 + 2NH3 reaction to proceed, leading to the formation of ammonium carbamate (NH4+NH2COO-), an ionic solid containing a complex organic moiety of prebiotic interest recently detected in a protoplanetary disk. This result speaks for: (i) efficient diffusion of molecules on/within cosmic dust, (ii) an underestimated role for surface catalysis in the astrochemistry of cosmic dust, and (iii) potentially efficient dust-promoted chemistry in warm cosmic environments, such as protostellar envelopes and protoplanetary disks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12967v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Potapov, Kilian Pollok, Falko Langenhorst, Martin McCoustra, Robin T. Garrod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explaining Principles of Tip-Enhanced Raman Images with Ab Initio Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13075v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Tip-enhanced Raman spectroscopy (TERS) is a powerful method for imaging vibrational motion and chemically characterizing surface-bound systems. Theoretical simulations of TERS images often consider systems in isolation, ignoring any substrate support, such as metallic surfaces. Here, we show that this omission leads to deviations from experimentally measured data through simulations with a new finite-field formulation of first-principles simulation of TERS spectra that can address extended, periodic systems. We show that TERS images of tetracyanoethylene on Ag(100) and defective MoS$_2$ monolayers calculated using isolated molecules or cluster models are qualitatively different from those calculated when accounting for the periodicity of the substrate. For Mg(II)-porphine on Ag(100), a system for which a direct experimental comparison is possible, these simulations prove to be crucial for explaining the spatial variation of TERS intensity patterns and allow us to uncover fundamental principles of TERS spectroscopy. We explain how and why surface interactions affect images of out-of-plane vibrational modes much more than those of in-plane modes, providing an important tool for the future interpretation of these images in more complex systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13075v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krystof Brezina, Yair Litman, Mariana Rossi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cyclic Variational Quantum Eigensolver: Escaping Barren Plateaus through Staircase Descent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13096v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the Cyclic Variational Quantum Eigensolver (CVQE), a hardware-efficient framework for accurate ground-state quantum simulation on noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices. CVQE departs from conventional VQE by incorporating a measurement-driven feedback cycle: Slater determinants with significant sampling probability are iteratively added to the reference superposition, while a fixed entangler (e.g., single-layer UCCSD) is reused throughout. This adaptive reference growth systematically enlarges the variational space in most promising directions, avoiding manual ansatz or operator-pool design, costly searches, and preserving compile-once circuits. The strategy parallels multi-reference methods in quantum chemistry, while remaining fully automated on quantum hardware. Remarkably, CVQE exhibits a distinctive staircase-like descent pattern, where successive energy drops sharply signal efficient escape from barren plateaus. Benchmarks show that CVQE consistently maintains chemical precision across correlation regimes, outperforms fixed UCCSD by several orders of magnitude, and achieves favorable accuracy-cost trade-offs compared to the Selected Configuration Interaction. These results position CVQE as a scalable, interpretable, and resource-efficient paradigm for near-term quantum simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13096v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Zhang, Ayush Asthana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Key Physics of Ice Premelting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.13221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.13221v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A disordered quasi-liquid layer of water is thought to cover the ice surface, but many issues, such as its onset temperature, its thickness, or its actual relation to bulk liquid water have been a matter of unsettled controversy for more than a century. In this perspective article, current computer simulations and experimental results are discussed under the light of a suitable theoretical framework. It is found that using a combination of wetting physics, the theory of intermolecular forces, statistical mechanics and out of equilibrium physics a large number of conflicting results can be reconciled and collected into a consistent description of the ice surface. This helps understand the crucial role of surface properties in a range of important applications, from the enigmatic structure of snow crystals to the slipperiness of ice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.13221v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis G. MacDowell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A foundation machine learning potential with polarizable long-range interactions for materials modelling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13820v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Long-range interactions are essential determinants of chemical system behaviour across diverse environments. We present a foundation framework that integrates explicit polarizable long-range physics with an equivariant graph neural network potential. It employs a physically motivated polarizable charge equilibration scheme that directly optimizes electrostatic interaction energies rather than partial charges. The foundation model, trained across the periodic table up to Pu, demonstrates strong performance across key materials modelling challenges. It effectively captures long-range interactions that are challenging for traditional message-passing mechanisms and accurately reproduces polarization effects under external electric fields. We have applied the model to mechanical properties, ionic diffusivity in solid-state electrolytes, ferroelectric phase transitions, and reactive dynamics at electrode-electrolyte interfaces, highlighting the model's capacity to balance accuracy and computational efficiency. Furthermore, we show that as a foundation model, it can be efficiently finetuned to achieve high-level accuracy for specific challenging systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13820v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rongzhi Gao, ChiYung Yam, Jianjun Mao, Shuguang Chen, GuanHua Chen, Ziyang Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High efficiency quantification of $^{90}$Sr contamination in cow milk after a nuclear accident</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07123v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Monitoring $^{90}$Sr contamination in milk following a nuclear accident is critical due to its radiotoxicity and calcium-mimicking behaviour, leading to accumulation in bones and teeth. This study presents a high-efficiency protocol for quantifying$^{90}$Sr in cow milk by integrating freeze-drying, high-temperature calcination, ion exchange chromatography and liquid scintillation spectroscopy (LSC). The method was validated using reference milk samples with 0.45~Bq/mL of $^{90}$Sr, achieving a chemical yield of 100 $\pm$ 2\%, ensuring near-complete recovery and accurate quantification.
  The minimum detectable activity (MDA) was estimated at 0.33 Bq/L under optimal conditions, demonstrating the protocol's sensitivity for low-level detection. A comparative analysis with existing methods centrifugation-based approaches and Dowex resin techniques revealed that our protocol outperforms in both strontium recovery and organic matter elimination. Alternative methods showed lower recovery rates (68 $\pm$ 2\% for Gu\'erin's method, 65 $\pm$6\% for Dowex resin) and suffered from procedural drawbacks, such as incomplete organic matter removal.
  Applying this methodology to compare samples from certified laboratories confirmed its robustness, with liquid scintillation spectroscopy radioactivity values doubling after 14 days, consistent with secular equilibrium between $^{90}$Sr and $^{90}$Y. While the protocol is optimized for milk, future research should explore its applicability to other food matrices. The high yield, reliability, and ease of implementation position this method as an effective tool for nuclear emergency response and routine radiological monitoring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07123v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Q. Rogliardo, A. Kanellakopoulos, H. Corcelle, M. Fedel, M. Zsely-Schaffter, G. Triscone, S. Pallada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-informed machine learning for combustion: A review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03347v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Physics-informed machine learning (PIML) represents an emerging paradigm that integrates various forms of physical knowledge into machine learning (ML) components, thereby enhancing the physical consistency of ML models compared to purely data-driven paradigms. The field of combustion, characterized by a rich foundation of physical laws and abundant data, is undergoing a transformation due to PIML. This paper aims to provide a comprehensive overview of PIML for combustion, systematically outlining fundamental principles, significant contributions, key advancements, and available resources. The application of PIML in combustion is categorized into three domains: combustion chemical kinetics, combustion reacting flows, and other combustion-related problems. Additionally, current challenges, potential solutions, and practical guidelines for researchers and engineers will be discussed. A primary focus of this review is to demonstrate how combustion laws can be integrated into ML, either through soft or hard constraints, via loss functions or representation models, and within coordinate-to-variable or field-to-field paradigms. This paper shows that PIML offers a unified framework linking physics, model, and data in combustion--integrating physical knowledge in model-to-data simulation and reconstruction tasks, as well as data-to-model modeling tasks--resulting in enhanced data, improved physical models, and more reliable ML models. PIML for combustion presents significant opportunities for both the combustion and ML communities, encouraging greater collaboration and cross-disciplinary engagement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03347v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahao Wu, Xutun Wang, Yuxin Wu, Guihua Zhang, Jiayue Liu, Xin Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Network Assisted Fermionic Compression Encoding: A Lossy-QSCI Framework for Resource-Efficient Ground-State Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17846</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17846v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum computing promises to revolutionize many-body simulations for quantum chemistry, but its potential is constrained by limited qubits and noise in current devices. In this work, we introduce the Lossy Quantum Selected Configuration Interaction (Lossy-QSCI) framework, which combines a lossy subspace Hamiltonian preparation pipeline with a generic QSCI selection process. This framework integrates a chemistry-inspired lossy Random Linear Encoder (Chemical-RLE) with a neural network-assisted Fermionic Expectation Decoder (NN-FED). The RLE leverages fermionic number conservation to compress quantum states, reducing qubit requirements to O(N log M) for M spin orbitals and N electrons, while preserving crucial ground state information and enabling self-consistent configuration recovery. NN-FED, powered by a neural network trained with minimal data, efficiently decodes these compressed states, overcoming the measurement challenges common in the approaches of the traditional QSCI and its variants. Through iterative quantum sampling and classical post-processing, our hybrid method refines ground state estimates with high efficiency. This framework offers a resource-efficient pathway for ground-state simulations on near-term noisy hardware and could inspire resource-efficient extensions to future devices by minimizing qubit overhead.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17846v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/9x8b-4j41</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yu-cheng Chen, Ronin Wu, M. H. Cheng, Min-Hsiu Hsieh</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
