<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 02:49:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing the Computational Efficiency of the DoNOF Program through a New Orbital Sorting Scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents a novel approach to distribute orbitals into subspaces within electron-pairing-based natural orbital functionals (NOFs). This approach modifies the coupling between weakly and strongly occupied orbitals by applying an alternating orbital sorting strategy. In contrast to the previous orbital sorting that enforced electron pairing within subspaces of contiguous orbitals, the new approach provides greater flexibility, enabling a calculation scheme where the size of the subspaces can be gradually expanded. As a consequence, one can start using subspaces of only one weakly occupied orbital (perfect pairing) and progressively enlarge their size by incorporating more weakly occupied orbitals (extended pairing) up to the maximum size allowed by the basis set. In this way, the alternate orbital sorting allows solving first a simpler problem with small subspaces and leverage its orbital solution for the more intensive problem with larger subspaces, thereby reducing the overall computational cost and improving convergence, as we observed in the DoNOF program. The efficiency provided by the new sorting approach has been validated through benchmark calculations in H2O, H2O2, and NH3. In particular, we compared three strategies: i) solving directly the calculation with the largest subspaces (one-shot strategy), as was usually done before this work, ii) starting with perfect pairing and stepwise increasing the number of orbitals in the subspaces one by one until reaching the maximum size (incremental strategy), and iii) starting with perfect pairing and transitioning directly to the maximum subspace size (two-step strategy). Our results show that the two-step approach emerges as the most effective strategy, achieving the lowest computational cost while maintaining high accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01786v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Elodie Boutou, Juan Felipe Huan Lew-Yee, Jose Maria Mercero, Mario Piris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational path sampling of rare dynamical events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01852v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article reviews the concepts and methods of variational path sampling. These methods allow computational studies of rare events in systems driven arbitrarily far from equilibrium. Based upon a statistical mechanics of trajectory space and leveraging the theory of large deviations, they provide a perspective with which dynamical phenomena can be studied with the same types of ensemble reweighting ideas that have been used for static equilibrium properties. Applications to chemical, material, and biophysical systems are highlighted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01852v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya N. Singh, Avishek Das, David T. Limmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional fluorescence spectroscopy with quantum entangled photons and time- and frequency-resolved two-photon coincidence detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02073v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent theoretical studies in quantum spectroscopy have emphasized the potential of non-classical correlations in entangled photon pairs for selectively targeting specific nonlinear optical processes in nonlinear optical responses. However, because of the extremely low intensity of the nonlinear optical signal generated by irradiating molecules with entangled photon pairs, time-resolved spectroscopic measurements using entangled photons have yet to be experimentally implemented. In this paper, we theoretically propose a quantum spectroscopy measurement employing a time-resolved fluorescence approach that aligns with the capabilities of current photon detection technologies. The proposed quantum spectroscopy affords two remarkable advantages over conventional two-dimensional electronic spectroscopy. First, it enables the acquisition of two-dimensional spectra without requiring control over multiple pulsed lasers. Second, it reduces the complexity of the spectra because the spectroscopic signal is contingent upon the nonlinear optical process of spontaneous emission. These advantages are similar to those achieved in a previous study [Fujihashi et al., J. Chem. Phys. 160, 104201 (2024)]. However, our approach achieves sufficient signal intensities that can be readily detected using existing photon detection technologies, thereby rendering it a practicable. Our findings will potentially facilitate the first experimental real-time observation of dynamic processes in molecular systems using quantum entangled photon pairs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02073v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuta Fujihashi, Ozora Iso, Ryosuke Shimizu, Akihito Ishizaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular Pseudorotation in Phthalocyanines as a Tool for Magnetic Field Control at the Nanoscale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02169v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Metal phthalocyanines, a highly versatile class of aromatic, planar, macrocyclic molecules with a chelated central metal ion, are topical objects of ongoing research and particularly interesting due to their magnetic properties. However, while current focus lies almost exclusively on spin-Zeeman-related effects, the high symmetry of the molecule and its circular shape suggests the exploitation of light-induced excitation of twofold degenerate vibrational states in order to generate, switch and manipulate magnetic fields at the nanoscale. The underlying mechanism is a molecular pseudorotation that can be triggered by infrared pulses and gives rise to a quantized, small but controllable magnetic dipole moment. We investigate the optical stimulation of vibrationally-induced molecular magnetism and estimate changes in the magnetic shielding constants for confirmation by future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02169v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/jacs.4c01915</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Am. Chem. Soc. 146, 14620-14632 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Raphael Wilhelmer, Matthias Diez, Johannes K. Krondorfer, Andreas W. Hauser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excited States of the Uniform Electron Gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02378</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02378v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The uniform electron gas (UEG) is a cornerstone of density-functional theory (DFT) and the foundation of the local-density approximation (LDA), one of the most successful approximations in DFT. In this work, we extend the concept of UEG by introducing excited-state UEGs, systems characterized by a gap at the Fermi surface created by the excitation of electrons near the Fermi level. We report closed-form expressions of the reduced kinetic and exchange energies of these excited-state UEGs as functions of the density and the gap. Additionally, we derive the leading term of the correlation energy in the high-density limit. By incorporating an additional variable representing the degree of excitation into the UEG paradigm, the present work introduces a new framework for constructing local and semi-local state-specific functionals for excited states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02378v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre-Fran\c{c}ois Loos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Reactions on the Solid-Liquid Interface With Next Generation Extended Lagrangian Quantum-Based Molecular Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02429v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we demonstrate how extended Lagrangian Born-Oppenheimer quantum-based molecular dynamics (XL-BOMD) can be used to simulate heterogeneous electrocatalytic reactions. In particular, we apply our framework to study the oxygen reduction reaction (ORR) mechanism on nitrogen-doped graphene in an aqueous solution. The electronic ground state and total energy of XL-BOMD are stabilized through nuclear and electronic equations of motion assisted by an integral kernel updated with low-rank approximations. A species charge analysis reveals that the XL-BOMD simulations can be used to detect electron transfer between the catalyst surface and the solvated molecular oxygen mediated by water molecules, resulting in the molecular dissociation of O$_2$. Simulations of the ORR under high electrochemical biases contribute to a larger body of work elucidating an outer-sphere ORR mechanism in which reduction occurs through water networks without direct adsorption of molecular oxygen.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02429v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rae A. Corrigan Grove, Kevin G. Kleiner, Joshua D. Finkelstein, Ivana Gonzales, Michael E. Wall, Travis E. L. Jones, Anders M. N. Niklasson, Christian F. A. Negre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precision measurement of the last bound states in H$_2$ and determination of the H + H scattering length</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01877v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The binding energies of the five bound rotational levels $J=0-4$ in the highest vibrational level $v=14$ in the X$^1\Sigma_g^+$ ground electronic state of H$_2$ were measured in a three-step ultraviolet-laser experiment. Two-photon UV-photolysis of H$_2$S produced population in these high-lying bound states, that were subsequently interrogated at high precision via Doppler-free spectroscopy of the F$^1\Sigma_g^+$ - X$^1\Sigma_g^+$ system. A third UV-laser was used for detection through auto-ionizing resonances. The experimentally determined binding energies were found to be in excellent agreement with calculations based on non-adiabatic perturbation theory, also including relativistic and quantum electrodynamical contributions. The $s$-wave scattering length of the H + H system is derived from the binding energy of the last bound $J=0$ level via a direct semi-empirical approach, yielding a value of $a_s$ = 0.2724(5) $a_0$, in good agreement with a result from a previously followed theoretical approach. The subtle effect of the $m\alpha^4$ relativity contribution to $a_s$ was found to be significant. In a similar manner a value for the $p$-wave scattering volume is determined via the $J=1$ binding energy yielding $a_p$ = -134.0000(6) $a_0^3$. The binding energy of the last bound state in H$_2$, the ($v=14$, $J=4$) level, is determined at 0.023(4) cm$^{-1}$, in good agreement with calculation. The effect of the hyperfine substructure caused by the two hydrogen atoms at large internuclear separation, giving rise to three distinct dissociation limits, is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01877v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. -F. Lai, W. Ubachs, M. Beyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of Molecular Structure in Defining the Dynamical Landscape of Deep Eutectic Solvents at Nanoscale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02120v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The molecular dynamics of deep eutectic solvents (DESs) are complex, characterized by nanoscale spatial and temporal heterogeneity. Understanding these dynamics is crucial for tailoring transport properties like diffusion, viscosity and ionic conductivity. Molecular diffusion in DESs stems from transient caging and translation jumps, necessitating an understanding of how molecular structure regulates these processes. This study explores the influence of alkyl chain length on the nanoscopic dynamics of alkylamide-lithium perchlorate based DESs using quasielastic neutron scattering (QENS) and molecular dynamics (MD) simulations. QENS results show that, despite its shorter chain length and lighter mass, acetamide (ACM) exhibited the lowest mobility among the alkylamides, including propanamide (PRM) and butyramide (BUT). Detailed analysis of QENS data reveals that long-range jump diffusion is fastest in ACM and slowest in BUT, essentially due to their differences in molecular size, mass and also enhanced complexation in longer alkyl chain molecules. However, the localized dynamics follows an unusual trend, where PRM is the fastest and ACM is the slowest. Despite greater flexibility in BUT, the slower caged dynamics impedes its localized motion. These findings highlight the interplay between alkyl chain length and DES dynamics, emphasizing role of molecular structure in governing transport properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02120v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Rinesh, H. Srinivasan, V. K. Sharma, V. Garc\'ia Sakai, S. Mitra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instrumental distortions in quantum optimal control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02198v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum optimal control methods, such as gradient ascent pulse engineering (GRAPE), are used for precise manipulation of quantum states. Many of those methods were pioneered in magnetic resonance spectroscopy where instrumental distortions are often negligible. However, that is not the case elsewhere: the usual gallimaufry of cables, resonators, modulators, splitters, filters, and amplifiers can and would distort control signals. Those distortions may be non-linear, their inverse functions may be ill-defined and unstable; they may even vary from one day to the next, and across the sample.
  Here we introduce the response-aware gradient ascent pulse engineering (RAW-GRAPE) framework, which accounts for any cascade of differentiable distortions directly within the GRAPE optimisation loop, does not require response function inversion, and produces control sequences that are resilient to user-specified distortion cascades with user-specified parameter ensembles.
  The framework is implemented into the optimal control module supplied with versions 2.10 and later of the open-source Spinach library; the user needs to provide function handles returning the actions by the distortions and, optionally, parameter ensembles for those actions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02198v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Uluk Rasulov, Ilya Kuprov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast laser synthesis of zeolites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02292v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Research has demonstrated that zeolite nucleation and growth can be controlled by fine-tuning chemical composition, temperature, and pressure, resulting in structures with diverse porosities and functionalities. Nevertheless, current energy delivery methods lack the finesse required to operate on the femto- and picosecond timescales of silica polymerisation and depolymerisation, limiting their ability to direct synthesis with high precision. To overcome this limitation, we introduce an ultrafast laser synthesis technique capable of delivering energy at these timescales with unprecedented spatiotemporal precision. Unlike conventional or emerging approaches, this method bypasses the need for specific temperature and pressure settings, as nucleation and growth are governed by dynamic phenomena arising from nonlinear light-matter interactions, such as convective flows, cavitation bubbles, plasma formation, and shock waves. These processes can be initiated, paused, and resumed within fractions of a second, effectively freezing structures at any stage of self-assembly. Using this approach, we traced the entire nucleation and growth pathway of laser-synthesized TPA-silicate-1 zeolites, from early oligomer formation to fully developed crystals. The unprecedented spatiotemporal control of this technique unlocks new avenues for manipulating reaction pathways and exploring the vast configurational space of zeolites.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02292v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sezin Galioglu, Mehdi Hagverdiyev, Meryem M. Do\u{g}an, \"Ozg\"un Yavuz, \"U. Seleme Nizam, Ghaith Makey, Aladin Choura, Mesut La\c{c}in, Burcu Akata Kur\c{c}, Parviz Elahi, F. \"Omer Ilday, Serim Ilday</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuation Dissipation Relations for the Non-Reciprocal Cahn-Hilliard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02524v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent results demonstrate how deviations from equilibrium fluctuation-dissipation theorem can be quantified for active field theories by deriving exact fluctuations dissipation relations that involve the entropy production [M. K. Johnsrud and R. Golestanian, arXiv:2409.14977]. Here we develop and employ diagrammatic tools to perform perturbative calculations for a paradigmatic active field theory, the Non-Reciprocal Cahn-Hilliard (NRCH) model. We obtain analytical results, which serve as an illustration of how to implement the recently developed framework to active field theories, and help to illuminate the specific non-equilibrium characteristics of the NRCH field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02524v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Kj{\o}llesdal Johnsrud, Ramin Golestanian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Protons accumulate at the graphene-water interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04487v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Water's ability to autoionize into hydroxide and hydronium ions profoundly influences surface properties, rendering interfaces either basic or acidic. While it is well-established that protons show an affinity to the air-water interface, a critical knowledge gap exists in technologically relevant surfaces like the graphene-water interface. Here we use machine learning-based simulations with first-principles accuracy to unravel the behavior of the hydroxide and hydronium ions at the graphene-water interface. Our findings reveal that protons accumulate at the graphene-water interface, with the hydronium ion predominantly residing in the first contact layer of water. In contrast, the hydroxide ion exhibits a bimodal distribution, found both near the surface and towards the interior layers. Analysis of the underlying electronic structure reveals local polarization effects, resulting in counterintuitive charge rearrangement. Proton propensity to the graphene-water interface challenges the interpretation of surface experiments and is expected to have far-reaching consequences for ion conductivity, interfacial reactivity, and proton-mediated processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04487v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xavier R. Advincula, Kara D. Fong, Angelos Michaelides, Christoph Schran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>State Selective Preparation and Nondestructive Detection of Trapped ${\rm O}_2^+$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14832v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The ability to prepare molecular ions in selected quantum states enables studies in areas such as chemistry, metrology, spectroscopy, quantum information, and precision measurements. Here, we demonstrate $(2+1)$ resonance-enhanced multiphoton ionization (REMPI) of oxygen, both in a molecular beam and in an ion trap. The two-photon transition in the REMPI spectrum is rotationally resolved, allowing ionization from a selected rovibrational state of O$_2$. Fits to this spectrum determine spectroscopic parameters of the O$_2$ $d\,^1\Pi_g$ state and resolve a discrepancy in the literature regarding its band origin. The trapped molecular ions are cooled by co-trapped atomic ions. Fluorescence mass spectrometry nondestructively demonstrates the presence of the photoionized O$_2^+$. We discuss strategies for maximizing the fraction of ions produced in the ground rovibrational state. For $(2+1)$ REMPI through the $d\,^1\Pi_g$ state, we show that the Q(1) transition is preferred for neutral O$_2$ at rotational temperatures below 50~K, while the O(3) transition is more suitable at higher temperatures. The combination of state-selective loading and nondestructive detection of trapped molecular ions has applications in optical clocks, tests of fundamental physics, and control of chemical reactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14832v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0244447</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 162, 054203 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ambesh Pratik Singh, Michael Mitchell, Will Henshon, Addison Hartman, Annika Lunstad, Boran Kuzhan, David Hanneke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOLPIPx: an end-to-end differentiable package for permutationally invariant polynomials in Python and Rust</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17011</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17011v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we present MOLPIPx, a versatile library designed to seamlessly integrate Permutationally Invariant Polynomials (PIPs) with modern machine learning frameworks, enabling the efficient development of linear models, neural networks, and Gaussian process models. These methodologies are widely employed for parameterizing potential energy surfaces across diverse molecular systems. MOLPIPx leverages two powerful automatic differentiation engines -JAX and EnzymeAD-Rust- to facilitate the efficient computation of energy gradients and higher-order derivatives, which are essential for tasks such as force field development and dynamic simulations. MOLPIPx is available at https://github.com/ChemAI-Lab/molpipx.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17011v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel S. Drehwald, Asma Jamali, Rodrigo A. Vargas-Hern\'andez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Laser-induced alignment of nanoparticles and macromolecules for single-particle-imaging applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.05870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.05870v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Laser-induced alignment of particles and molecules was long envisioned to support three-dimensional structure determination using "single-molecule diffraction" with x-ray free-electron lasers [PRL 92, 198102 (2004)]. However, the alignment of isolated macromolecules has not yet been demonstrated, also because quantitative modeling is very expensive. We computationally demonstrated that the alignment of nanorods and proteins is possible with standard laser technology. We performed a comprehensive analysis on the dependence of the degree of alignment on molecular properties and experimental details, e.g., particle temperature and laser-pulse energy. Considering the polarizability anisotropy of about 150,000 proteins, our analysis revealed that most of these proteins can be aligned using realistic experimental parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.05870v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/jacs.4c15679</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Muhamed Amin, Jean-Michel Hartmann, Amit K. Samanta, Jochen K\"upper</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
