<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 02:02:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging MMW-MMW Double Resonance Spectroscopy to Understand the Pure Rotational Spectrum of Glycidaldehyde and 17 of Its Vibrationally Excited States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22865v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Broadband measurements of glycidaldehyde in the frequency ranges 75-170 and 500-750 GHz were recorded to extend previous analyses of its pure rotational spectrum in the microwave region. The rotational parameters of the ground vibrational states for the main isotopologue and the three singly 13C-substituted isotopologues were considerably improved, and additional higher-order parameters were determined. To identify new vibrationally excited states in the dense and convoluted spectrum, an updated version of the double-modulation double-resonance spectroscopy technique was used. Connecting transitions with a shared energy level into series and expanding these via Loomis-Wood plots proved to be a powerful method, which allowed the identification of 11 new vibrationally excited states in addition to the already known aldehyde torsions, v21 = 1 to v21 = 6. Interactions between several vibrational states were observed, and three interacting systems were treated successfully. Rotational transitions of glycidaldehyde were searched for in the imaging spectral line survey ReMoCA obtained with the Atacama Large Millimeter/submillimeter Array (ALMA) toward the high-mass star-forming region Sgr B2(N). The observed spectra were modeled under the assumption of local thermodynamic equilibrium (LTE). Glycidaldehyde, an oxirane derivative, was not detected toward Sgr B2(N2b). The upper limit on its column density implies that it is at least six times less abundant than oxirane in this source.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22865v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsearthspacechem.4c00360</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Luis Bonah, Jean-Claude Guillemin, Arnaud Belloche, Sven Thorwirth, Holger S. P. M\"uller, Stephan Schlemmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Many-Body Linear Algebra, Hamiltonian Moments, and a Coupled Cluster Inspired Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22908v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a general strategy to develop quantum many-body approximations of primitives in linear algebra algorithms. As a practical example, we introduce a coupled-cluster inspired framework to produce approximate Hamiltonian moments, and demonstrate its application in various linear algebra algorithms for ground state estimation. Through numerical examples, we illustrate the difference between the ground-state energies arising from quantum many-body linear algebra and those from the analogous many-body perturbation theory. Our results support the general idea of designing quantum many-body approximations outside of perturbation theory, providing a route to new algorithms and approximations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22908v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuhang Ai, Huanchen Zhai, Johannes T\"olle, Garnet Kin-Lic Chan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extending ring polymer molecular dynamics rate theory to reactions with non-separable reactants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22964v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The ring polymer molecular dynamics (RPMD) rate theory is an efficient and accurate method for estimating rate coefficients of chemical reactions affected by nuclear quantum effects. The commonly used RPMD treatment of gas-phase bimolecular reactions adopts two dividing surfaces, one at the transition state and another in the reactant asymptote, where the partition function of the separated reactants can be readily obtained. With some exceptions, however, this strategy is difficult to implement for processes on surfaces or in liquids, because the reactants are often strongly coupled with the extended medium (surface or solvent) and thus non-separable. Under such circumstances, the RPMD rate theory with a single dividing surface is better suited, but most implementations are constrained to Cartesian forms of the reaction coordinate. Here, we present a more general RPMD implementation, which are free of the aforementioned shortcomings. This approach is demonstrated in four representative reactions, including the gas phase H + H2 exchange reaction, gas phase CH3NC isomerization, H recombinative desorption from Pt(111), and NO desorption from Pd(111). This implementation offers a unified treatment of both unimolecular and bimolecular reactions and represents a promising way to accurately predict gas-phase and surface reaction rates on the same footing. It can also be readily applied to more complex systems, such as those in liquids, heterogeneous systems, and proteins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22964v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Li, Liang Zhang, Bin Jiang, Hua Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A low-cost four-component relativistic coupled cluster linear response theory based on perturbation sensitive natural spinors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23144v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an efficient implementation of four-component linear response coupled cluster singles and doubles (4c-LRCCSD) theory that enables accurate and computationally efficient calculation of polarizabilities for systems containing heavy elements. We have observed that the frozen natural spinor (FNS)-based truncation scheme is not suitable for linear response properties, as it leads to larger errors in static and dynamic polarizability values. In this work, we have introduced a "perturbation-sensitive" density to construct the natural spinor basis, termed FNS++. Using FNS++, we achieve excellent accuracy when compared to experimental data and other theoretical results, even after truncating nearly 70% of the total virtual spinors. We also present pilot applications of 4c-LRCCSD with a canonical basis to calculate the polarizability spectra of 3d transition metals. By employing the FNS++-based 4c-LRCCSD, we have been able to compute polarizabilities for systems with over 1200 virtual spinors, maintaining low computational cost and excellent accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23144v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudipta Chakraborty, Amrita Manna, T. Daniel Crawford, Achintya Kumar Dutta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Invariant Bases for Atomistic Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23515v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The representation of atomic configurations for machine learning models has led to the development of numerous descriptors, often to describe the local environment of atoms. However, many of these representations are incomplete and/or functionally dependent. Incomplete descriptor sets are unable to represent all meaningful changes in the atomic environment. Complete constructions of atomic environment descriptors, on the other hand, often suffer from a high degree of functional dependence, where some descriptors can be written as functions of the others. These redundant descriptors do not provide additional power to discriminate between different atomic environments and increase the computational burden. By employing techniques from the pattern recognition literature to existing atomistic representations, we remove descriptors that are functions of other descriptors to produce the smallest possible set that satisfies completeness. We apply this in two ways: first we refine an existing description, the Atomistic Cluster Expansion. We show that this yields a more efficient subset of descriptors. Second, we augment an incomplete construction based on a scalar neural network, yielding a new message-passing network architecture that can recognize up to 5-body patterns in each neuron by taking advantage of an optimal set of Cartesian tensor invariants. This architecture shows strong accuracy on state-of-the-art benchmarks while retaining low computational cost. Our results not only yield improved models, but point the way to classes of invariant bases that minimize cost while maximizing expressivity for a host of applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23515v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alice E. A. Allen, Emily Shinkle, Roxana Bujack, Nicholas Lubbers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performing Path Integral Molecular Dynamics Using Artificial Intelligence Enhanced Molecular Simulation Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23728v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study employed an artificial intelligence-enhanced molecular simulation framework to enable efficient Path Integral Molecular Dynamics (PIMD) simulations. Owing to its modular architecture and high-throughput capabilities, the framework effectively mitigates the computational complexity and resource-intensive limitations associated with conventional PIMD approaches. By integrating machine learning force fields (MLFFs) into the framework, we rigorously tested its performance through two representative cases: a small-molecule reaction system (double proton transfer in formic acid dimer) and a bulk-phase transition system (water-ice phase transformation). Computational results demonstrate that the proposed framework achieves accelerated PIMD simulations while preserving quantum mechanical accuracy. These findings show that nuclear quantum effects can be captured for complex molecular systems, using relatively low computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23728v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Fan, Maodong Li, Sihao Yuan, Zhaoxin Xie, Dechin Chen, Yi Isaac Yang, Yi Qin Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Molecular Quantum electro-Dynamics Research Group in Budapest</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23942</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23942v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article briefly overviews the scientific activities of the Molecular Quantum (electro-)Dynamics (MQD) Research Group in Budapest. Since its foundation in 2016, the MQD group has worked on molecular spectroscopy and molecular physics topics with primary applications and relevance to high-resolution and precision spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23942v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edit Matyus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H2-roaming dynamics in the formation of H3+ following two-photon double ionization of ethanol and aminoethanol</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24018v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Roaming reactions involving a neutral fragment of a molecule that transiently wanders around another fragment before forming a new bond are intriguing and peculiar pathways for molecular rearrangement. Such reactions can occur for example upon double ionization of small organic molecules, and have recently sparked much scientific interest. We have studied the dynamics of the H$_2$-roaming reaction leading to the formation of H$_3^+$ after two-photon double ionization of ethanol and 2-aminoethanol, using an XUV-UV pump-probe scheme. For ethanol, we find dynamics similar to previous studies employing different pump-probe schemes, indicating the independence of the observed dynamics from the method of ionization and the photon energy of the disruptive probe pulse. Surprisingly, we do not observe a kinetic isotope effect in ethanol-D$_6$, in contrast to previous experiments on methanol where such an effect was observed. This distinction indicates fundamental differences in the energetics of the reaction pathways as compared to the methanol molecule. The larger number of possible roaming pathways compared to methanol complicates the analysis considerably. In contrast to previous studies, we additionally analyze a broad range of dissociative ionization products, which feature distinct dynamics from that of H$_{3}^{+}$ and allow initial insight into the action of the disruptive UV-probe pulse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24018v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41598-024-84531-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci. Rep. 15, 3201 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Aaron Ngai, Sebastian Hartweg, Jakob D. Asmussen, Bj\"orn Bastian, Matteo Bonanomi, Carlo Callegari, Miltcho Danailov, Michele di Fraia, Raimund Feifel, Sarang Dev Ganeshamandiram, Sivarama Krishnan, Aaron LaForge, Friedemann Landmesser, Ltaief Ben Ltaief, Moritz Michelbach, Nitish Pal, Oksana Plekan, Nicolas Rendler, Lorenzo Raimondi, Fabian Richter, Audrey Scognamiglio, Tobias Sixt, Richard J. Squibb, Katrin Dulitz, Frank Stienkemeier, Marcel Mudrich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Deep Learning Framework for the Electronic Structure of Water: Towards a Universal Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24050v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurately modeling the electronic structure of water across scales, from individual molecules to bulk liquid, remains a grand challenge. Traditional computational methods face a critical trade-off between computational cost and efficiency. We present an enhanced machine-learning Deep Kohn-Sham (DeePKS) method for improved electronic structure, DeePKS-ES, that overcomes this dilemma. By incorporating the Hamiltonian matrix and their eigenvalues and eigenvectors into the loss function, we establish a universal model for water systems, which can reproduce high-level hybrid functional (HSE06) electronic properties from inexpensive generalized gradient approximation (PBE) calculations. Validated across molecular clusters and liquid-phase simulations, our approach reliably predicts key electronic structure properties such as band gaps and density of states, as well as total energy and atomic forces. This work bridges quantum-mechanical precision with scalable computation, offering transformative opportunities for modeling aqueous systems in catalysis, climate science, and energy storage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24050v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyuan Liang, Renxi Liu, Mohan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal machine learning with large language embedding model for polymer property prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22962v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Contemporary large language models (LLMs), such as GPT-4 and Llama, have harnessed extensive computational power and diverse text corpora to achieve remarkable proficiency in interpreting and generating domain-specific content, including materials science. To leverage the domain knowledge embedded within these models, we propose a simple yet effective multimodal architecture, PolyLLMem, which integrates text embeddings generated by Llama 3 with molecular structure embeddings derived from Uni-Mol, for polymer properties prediction tasks. In our model, Low-rank adaptation (LoRA) layers were also incorporated during the property prediction tasks to refine the embeddings based on our limited polymer dataset, thereby enhancing their chemical relevance for polymer SMILES representation. This balanced fusion of fine-tuned textual and structural information enables PolyLLMem to accurately predict a variety of polymer properties despite the scarcity of training data. Its performance is comparable to, and in some cases exceeds, that of graph-based models, as well as transformer-based models that typically require pretraining on millions of polymer samples. These findings demonstrate that LLM, such as Llama, can effectively capture chemical information encoded in polymer PSMILES, and underscore the efficacy of multimodal fusion of LLM embeddings and molecular structure embeddings in overcoming data scarcity and accelerating the discovery of advanced polymeric materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22962v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianren Zhang, Dai-Bei Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coupling molecular spin qubits with 2D magnets for coherent magnon manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnonics is an emerging field widely considered as a paradigm shift in information technology that uses spin waves for data storage, processing and transmission. However, the coherent control of spin waves in 2D magnets still remains a challenge. Herein, we investigate the interplay between molecular spins and magnons in hybrid heterostructures formed by [CpTi(cot)] and VOPc spin qubits deposited on the surface of the air-stable 2D van der Waals ferromagnet CrSBr using first principles. Our results show that different molecular rotation configurations significantly impact on qubit relaxation time and alter the magnon spectra of the underlying 2D magnet, allowing the chemical coherent control of spin waves in this material. We predict the feasibility of an ultrafast magnon-qubit interface with minimized decoherence, where exchange coupling plays a crucial role. This work opens new avenues for hybrid quantum magnonics, enabling selective tailoring through a versatile chemical approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23401v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sourav Dey, Gonzalo Rivero-Carracedo, Andrei Shumilin, Carlos Gonzalez-Ballestero, Jos\'e J. Baldov\'i</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of the delocalized charge distribution in trapped ion-atom collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23690v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the study of ion-atom interactions, the ion often remain trapped during the experiments. However, the effects of the trapping potential of the ion on ion-neutral interactions remain largely unexplored. Although trap-assisted ion-neutral complex formation has been experimentally studied and described by applying semiclassical theories where the ion is treated as a point charge particle, the potential effect of a delocalized charge distribution of a confined ion due to its quantum mechanical wavefunction has not been considered. To remedy this, in the present theoretical work we substitute the point charge of the ion with a delocalized charged distribution according to its motional ground state in the trap. Our results show that the trapping frequency and hence the spatial extension of the ion's ground-state wavefunction drastically affects the elastic and transport cross sections in interactions with neutral atoms. Stimulated by these results, we propose experimental procedures to verify the effects of the delocalize charge distribution in ion-atom interactions via measuring the heating rate of the ion due to the energy transfer in atomic collisions. Our novel approach brings new possibilities for investigating ion-neutral systems and, through them, new perspectives on ionic polarons and potentially a better understanding of trap-induced losses in ion-neutral experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23690v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiren Shi, Michael Drewsen, Jes\'us P\'erez-R\'ios</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Force-Free Molecular Dynamics Through Autoregressive Equivariant Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23794v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations play a crucial role in scientific research. Yet their computational cost often limits the timescales and system sizes that can be explored. Most data-driven efforts have been focused on reducing the computational cost of accurate interatomic forces required for solving the equations of motion. Despite their success, however, these machine learning interatomic potentials (MLIPs) are still bound to small time-steps. In this work, we introduce TrajCast, a transferable and data-efficient framework based on autoregressive equivariant message passing networks that directly updates atomic positions and velocities lifting the constraints imposed by traditional numerical integration. We benchmark our framework across various systems, including a small molecule, crystalline material, and bulk liquid, demonstrating excellent agreement with reference MD simulations for structural, dynamical, and energetic properties. Depending on the system, TrajCast allows for forecast intervals up to $30\times$ larger than traditional MD time-steps, generating over 15 ns of trajectory data per day for a solid with more than 4,000 atoms. By enabling efficient large-scale simulations over extended timescales, TrajCast can accelerate materials discovery and explore physical phenomena beyond the reach of traditional simulations and experiments. An open-source implementation of TrajCast is accessible under https://github.com/IBM/trajcast.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23794v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian L. Thiemann, Thiago Resch\"utzegger, Massimiliano Esposito, Tseden Taddese, Juan D. Olarte-Plata, Fausto Martelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>He-Mg compounds and helium-driven nonmetal transition in metallic magnesium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23874</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23874v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The polymorphism and mechanism of helium compounds is crucial for understanding the physical and chemical nature of He-bearing materials under pressures. Here, we predict two new types of He-bearing compounds, MgHe and MgnHe (n = 6, 8, 10, 15, 18), being formed above 750 GPa by unbiased ab initio structure search. An unexpected bandgap is opened up in MgHe at as low as around 200 GPa. This is the first case of noble gas driven metal-nonmetal transition in all elements. The same mechanism is demonstrated also being applicable to other metallic elements, and making beryllium transform into a non-metallic state, a triumph that is impossible otherwise. Furthermore, the stability of the simple cubic phase of Mg (Mg-sc) is greatly enhanced by mixing with He, which lowers the critical pressure of pure Mg-sc from about 1.1 TPa down to 750 GPa to form ordered substitutional alloying phase of MgnHe on a simple cubic lattice of Mg. This is the first report on Mg-based noble gas substitutional alloy, in sharp contrast to the conventional wisdom that He preferring interstitial sites. The observed striking influences of He demonstrate the rich physics and chemistry of He-bearing compounds under ultra-high pressures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23874v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.214102</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 214102 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Y. S. Huang, H. X. Song, Q. D. Hao, X. L. Pan, D. Wang, H. Wang, Y. F. Wang, Y. Sun, Hua Y. Geng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chemically Tuning Room Temperature Pulsed Optically Detected Magnetic Resonance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24341v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Optical detection of magnetic resonance enables spin-based quantum sensing with high spatial resolution and sensitivity-even at room temperature-as exemplified by solid-state defects. Molecular systems provide a complementary, chemically tunable, platform for room-temperature optically detected magnetic resonance (ODMR)-based quantum sensing. A critical parameter governing sensing sensitivity is the optical contrast-i.e., the difference in emission between two spin states. In state-of-the-art solid-state defects such as the nitrogen-vacancy center in diamond, this contrast is approximately 30%. Here, capitalizing on chemical tunability, we show that room-temperature ODMR contrasts of 40% can be achieved in molecules. Using a nitrogen-substituted analogue of pentacene (6,13-diazapentacene), we enhance contrast compared to pentacene and, by determining the triplet kinetics through time-dependent pulsed ODMR, show how this arises from accelerated anisotropic intersystem crossing. Furthermore, we translate high-contrast room-temperature pulsed ODMR to self-assembled nanocrystals. Overall, our findings highlight the synthetic handles available to optically readable molecular spins and the opportunities to capitalize on chemical tunability for room-temperature quantum sensing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24341v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sarah K. Mann, Angus Cowley-Semple, Emma Bryan, Ziqiu Huang, Sandrine Heutz, Max Attwood, Sam L. Bayliss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The structure and topology of an amorphous metal-organic framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24367</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24367v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Amorphous metal-organic frameworks are an important emerging materials class that combine the attractive physical properties of the amorphous state with the versatility of metal-organic framework (MOF) chemistry. The structures of amorphous MOFs have largely been inferred by drawing analogies to crystalline polymorphs and inorganic glasses, but ultimately the validity of such structural models has been challenging to establish either experimentally or computationally. Here we use a unified data-driven approach, combining experimental scattering data and active machine learning for interatomic potentials, to determine the structure of an amorphous zeolitic imidazolate framework (a-ZIF) -- the canonical amorphous MOF. Our results reveal clear differences between the structure of a-ZIF and that of other amorphous tetrahedral networks, allowing us to invalidate the long-standing assumption that these inorganic and hybrid glasses are topologically equivalent. To this end, we introduce a systematic notation for the network topology of amorphous solids, building a bridge to the successful use of topology analysis in crystalline MOFs and to materials informatics. Our work provides insights into the structure and topology of the archetypal amorphous MOF and opens up new avenues for modelling and understanding amorphous framework materials more generally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24367v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas C. Nicholas, Daniel F. Thomas du Toit, Louise A. M. Rosset, Davide M. Proserpio, Andrew L. Goodwin, Volker L. Deringer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elastic and Inelastic Electron Scattering Cross Sections of Trichlorofluoromethane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03171v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Differential elastic electron scattering cross sections of trichlorofluoromethane $\mathrm{(CCl_3F)}$ were measured for the first time over a broad energy range spanning 30 eV to 800 eV in the angular range of 20$^\circ$ to 150$^\circ$. The experimental results were compared with calculations using the IAM-SCAR+I model. Satisfactory agreements between both data sets were found for electron energies above 200 eV within experimental uncertainties, whereas significant deviations of up to 100% were observed at electron energies below 60 eV. In addition to the measurements of differential elastic scattering cross sections, total inelastic scattering cross sections of $\mathrm{CCl_3F}$ were calculated using the spherical complex optical potential (SCOP) model. These calculations closely match experimental total ionization cross sections available in the literature for energies below 50 eV. The sum of the experimental total elastic and the theoretical total inelastic scattering cross sections align very well with the total electron scattering cross sections of $\mathrm{CCl_3F}$ measured by other groups across the entire energy range (30 eV to 800 eV), demonstrating the consistency among these three cross sections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03171v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.111.022809</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 111, 022809 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mareike Dinger, Yeunsoo Park, Woon Yong Baek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A generalized valence bond model for the quantum mechanics of bonding in sulfur compounds, a new view of hypervalency</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23593</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23593v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A model for the bonding of hypervalent molecules containing sulfur is presented using generalized valence bond wavefunctions. To delineate the model from more commonly used DFT and delocalized wavefunctions, we present detailed comparisons to these other methods. The result is a new concept of local transferable bonding in hypervalent molecules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23593v3</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert B. Murphy, Richard P. Messmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Breakdown of broken-symmetry approach to exchange interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01019v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Broken-symmetry (BS) approaches are widely employed to evaluate Heisenberg exchange parameters, primarily in combination with DFT calculations. For many magnetic materials, BS-DFT calculations give reasonable estimations of exchange parameters, although systematic failures have also been reported. While the latter were attributed to deficiencies of approximate exchange-correlation functional, we prove here by treating a simple model system that the broken-symmetry methodology has serious problems. Detailed analysis clarifies the intrinsic issue with the broken-symmetry treatment of low-spin states. It shows, in particular, that the error in the BS calculation of exchange parameter scales with the degree of covalency between the magnetic and the bridging orbitals. This is due to the constraint on the form of multiconfigurational state imposed by the BS determinant, a feature common to other single-reference methods too. As a possible tool to overcome this intrinsic drawback of single-determinant BS approaches, we propose their extension to a minimal multiconfigurational version.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01019v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoya Iwahara, Zhishuo Huang, Akseli Mansikkam\"aki, Liviu F. Chibotaru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-linear and non-empirical double hybrid density functional</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22661v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a non-linear and non-empirical (nLanE) double hybrid density functional derived from an accurate interpolation of the adiabatic connection in density functional theory, incorporating the correct asymptotic expansions. By bridging the second-order perturbative weak correlation limit with the fully interacting limit from the semi-local SCAN functional, nLanE-SCAN is free of fitted parameters while providing improved energetic predictions compared to SCAN for moderately and strongly correlated systems alike. It delivers accurate predictions for atomic total energies and multiple reaction datasets from the GMTKN55 benchmark while significantly outperforming traditional linear hybrids and double hybrids for non-covalent interactions without requiring dispersion corrections. Due to the exact constraints at the weak correlation limit, nLanE-SCAN has reduced delocalization errors as evident through SIE4x4 and bond dissociations of H\(_2^+\) and He\(_2^+\). Its proper asymptotic behavior ensures stability in strongly correlated systems, improving H\(_2\) and N\(_2\) bond dissociation profiles compared to conventional functionals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22661v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Danish Khan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open reaction-diffusion systems: bridging probabilistic theory and simulations across scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07119v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Reaction-diffusion processes are the foundational model for a diverse range of complex systems, ranging from biochemical reactions to social agent-based phenomena. The underlying dynamics of these systems occur at the individual particle/agent level, and in realistic applications, they often display interaction with their environment through energy or material exchange with a reservoir. This requires intricate mathematical considerations, especially in the case of material exchange since the varying number of particles/agents results in ``on-the-fly'' modification of the system dimension. In this work, we first overview the probabilistic description of reaction-diffusion processes at the particle level, which readily handles varying number of particles. We then extend this model to consistently incorporate interactions with macroscopic material reservoirs. Based on the resulting expressions, we bridge the probabilistic description with macroscopic concentration-based descriptions for linear and nonlinear reaction-diffusion systems, as well as for an archetypal open reaction-diffusion system. Using these mathematical bridges across scales, we finally develop numerical schemes for open reaction-diffusion systems, which we implement in two illustrative examples. This work establishes a methodological workflow to bridge particle-based probabilistic descriptions with macroscopic concentration-based descriptions of reaction-diffusion in open settings, laying the foundations for a multiscale theoretical framework upon which to construct theory and simulation schemes that are consistent across scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07119v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mauricio J. del Razo, Margarita Kostr\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy Windows Augmented Plane Waves (EWAPW)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.11926</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.11926v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work we present a new basis set for electronic structure calculations of crystalline solids aimed at applications to Density Functional Theory (DFT) methods. In this construction, Energy Windows Augmented Plane Waves (EWAPW), we take advantage of the fact that most DFT calculations use a convergence loop in order to obtain the eigenstates of a final Kohn Sham (KS) Hamiltonian matrix - that is iterate solve the KS equations till the eigenstates of the KS Hamiltonian matrix also give the appropriate electron density needed to obtain the KS potential needed for that KS Hamiltonian matrix. Here we propose that, for the basis used at each step of the iteration, we use the previous eigenstate basis, in the interstitial region, but augmented inside the Muffin Tin (MT) sphere with the solution to the spherically averaged KS Hamiltonian for the linearization energy of the energy window of the energy of that eigenstate. Indeed, to reduce the number of times the spherically averaged KS potential needs to be solved inside the MT spheres it is advantageous to use energy windows and solve the spherically averaged KS Hamiltonian inside the MT region only once per window (at the linearization energy relevant to that window) so that the spherically averaged KS Hamiltonian needs only be solved a small number of times per iteration of the solution of the KS equations. For practical applications it is reasonable to have on the order of ten to one hundred windows. This method combines the implicit energy dependence of the basis of methods such as Projected Augmented Wave functions (PAW) with the ability of the basis set to adjust to the solid state (rather then atomic) environment which is similar to basis sets such as Linearized Augmented Plane Waves (LAPW).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.11926v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Garry Goldstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy functionals and equilibrium states in mixed quantum-classical dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18587v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The computational challenges posed by many-particle quantum systems are often overcome by mixed quantum-classical (MQC) models in which certain degrees of freedom are treated as classical while others are retained as quantum. One of the fundamental questions raised by this hybrid picture involves the characterization of the information associated to MQC systems. Based on the theory of dynamical invariants in Hamiltonian systems, here we propose a family of hybrid entropy functionals that consistently specialize to the usual R\'enyi and Shannon entropies. Upon considering the MQC Ehrenfest model for the dynamics of quantum and classical probabilities, we apply the hybrid Shannon entropy to characterize equilibrium configurations for simple Hamiltonians. The present construction also applies beyond Ehrenfest dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18587v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cesare Tronci, David Mart\'inez-Crespo, Fran\c{c}ois Gay-Balmaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on new vector boson mediated electron-nucleus interactions from spectroscopy of polar diatomic molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.08210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.08210v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A measurement of parity violation in the hyperfine structure of $^{138}$Ba$^{19}$F [E. Altunta\c{s} et al. Phys. Rev. Lett. 120, 142501 (2018)] is reinterpreted with electronic structure calculations in terms of beyond Standard Model vector boson mediated electron-nucleus interactions. Our results set constraints on previously unexplored, new boson mediated axial vector-vector nucleus-electron interactions. Similar bounds are obtained by analyzing the atomic parity violation experiment with $^{133}$Cs. Moreover, we show that future experiments with cold heavy diatomic molecules like $^{225}$RaF can improve the present sensitivity to axial vector-vector nucleus-electron and nucleon-nucleus interactions by up to five orders of magnitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.08210v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantin Gaul, Lei Cong, Dmitry Budker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mathematical crystal chemistry II: Random search for ionic crystals and analysis on oxide crystals registered in ICSD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20273v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Mathematical crystal chemistry views crystal structures as the optimal solutions of mathematical optimization problem formalizing inorganic structural chemistry. This paper introduces the minimum and maximum atomic radii depending on the types of geometrical constraints, extending the concept of effective atomic sizes. These radii define permissible interatomic distances instead of interatomic forces, constraining feasible types and connections of coordination polyhedra. The definition shows the aspect that crystal structures are packings of atomic spheres. Additionally, creatability functions for geometrical constraints, which give a choice of creatable types of geometrical constraints depending on the spatial order of atoms, are implemented to guide randomly generated structures toward optimal solutions. The framework identifies unique optimal solutions corresponding to the structures of spinel, pyrochlore ($\alpha$ and $\beta$), pyroxene, quadruple perovskite, cuprate superconductor $\mathrm{YBa}_2 \mathrm{Cu}_3 \mathrm{O}_{7-x}$, and iron-based superconductor $\mathrm{LaFeAsO}$. Notably, up to $95\%$ of oxide crystal structure types in Inorganic Crystal Structure Database align with the optimal solutions preserving experimental structures despite the discretized feasible atomic radii. These findings highlight the role of mathematical optimization problem as a theoretical foundation for mathematical crystal chemistry, enabling efficient structure prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20273v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryotaro Koshoji</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
