<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 02:50:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Response Selected Configuration Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02949v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we extend selected configuration interaction (SCI) methods beyond energies and expectation values by introducing a linear response (LR) framework for molecular response properties. Existing SCI approaches are capable of approximating the energy of the full configuration interaction (FCI) wave function with high accuracy but at a much lower cost. However, conventional determinant selection will, by design, mainly select determinants that are expected to improve energies, and this can lead to the omission of many determinants that are important for wave function response. We address this by introducing two new selection criteria motivated by linear response theory. Using these extended determinant selection criteria, we demonstrate that LR-SCI can systematically converge toward the FCI limit for static polarizabilities. Using a damped LR formulation, we compute the water K-edge X-ray absorption spectrum in active spaces up to (10e, 58o). Finally, we use LR-SCI to compute NMR spin-spin coupling constants for water, where we find that accuracy beyond that offered by CCSDT can be achieved. Overall, LR-SCI offers a promising route to compute response properties with near-FCI accuracy to systems beyond the reach of exact FCI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02949v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Reinholdt, Erik Kjellgren, Jacob Kongsted</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrochemical insights into manganese-cobalt doped $\alpha-Fe_2O_3$ nanomaterial for cholesterol detection: A comparative approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03114v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Herein, a self-assembled hierarchical structure of hematite ($\alpha$-$Fe_2O_3$) was synthesized via a one-pot hydrothermal method. Subsequently, the nanomaterial was doped to get $M_{x}Fe_{2-x}O_3$ (M = Mn-Co; x = 0.01, 0.05, 0.1) at precise concentrations. The electrode was fabricated by coating the resulting nanocomposite onto a Nickel Foam (NF) substrate. The electrochemical characterization demonstrated the excellent performance of cobalt-doped $\alpha$-$Fe_2O_3$, among which, $Co_0.05Fe_0.95O_3$ (CF5) exhibited superior performance, showing a two-fold increase in sensitivity of 1364.2 $\mu$A.m$M^{-1}$.$cm^{-2}$ $(\pm 0.03, n = 3)$ in 0.5 M KOH, a Limit of Detection (LOD) of $\sim 0.17 mM$, and a Limit of Quantification (LOQ) of {\sim}0.58 mM. Density Functional Theory (DFT) was performed to understand the doping prompting in the reduced bandgap. The fabricated electrode displayed a rapid response time of 2 s and demonstrated 95% stability, excellent reproducibility, and selectivity, as confirmed by tests with several interfering species. A comprehensive evaluation of the electrode's performance using human blood serum highlighted its robustness and reliability for cholesterol detection in clinical settings, making it a promising tool for clinical and pharmaceutical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03114v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1039/D5RA04373E</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>RSC Adv., 2025, 15, 34176-34190</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sushmitha S, Subhasmita Ray, Lavanya Rao, Mahesha P Nayak, Karel Carva, Badekai Ramachandra Bhat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Any type of spectroscopy can be efficiently simulated on a quantum computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02784v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spectroscopy is the most important method for probing the structure of molecules. However, predicting molecular spectra on classical computers is computationally expensive, with the most accurate methods having a cost that grows exponentially with molecule size. Quantum computers have been shown to simulate simple types of optical spectroscopy efficiently -- with a cost polynomial in molecule size -- using methods such as time-dependent simulations of photoinduced wavepackets. Here, we show that any type of spectroscopy can be efficiently simulated on a quantum computer using a time-domain approach, including spectroscopies of any order, any frequency range, and involving both electric and magnetic transitions. Our method works by computing any spectroscopic correlation function based on the corresponding double-sided Feynman diagram, the canonical description of spectroscopic interactions. The approach can be used to simulate spectroscopy of both closed and open molecular systems using both digital and analog quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02784v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liam P. Flew, Ivan Kassal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global approximations to the error function of real argument for vectorized computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05068v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The error function of real argument can be uniformly approximated to a given accuracy by a single closed-form expression for the whole variable range either in terms of addition, multiplication, division, and square root operations only, or also using the exponential function. The coefficients have been tabulated for up to 128-bit precision. Tests of a computer code implementation using the standard single- and double-precision floating-point arithmetic show good performance and vectorizability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05068v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitri N. Laikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaging nuclei by smashing them at high energies: how are their shapes revealed after destruction?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16071v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: High-energy nuclear collisions have recently emerged as a promising ``imaging-by-smashing'' approach that may reveal the intrinsic shapes of atomic nuclei. Here, I outline a conceptual framework for this technique, explaining how nuclear shapes are encoded during quark-gluon plasma formation and evolution, and how they can be decoded from final-state particle distributions. I highlight the method's potential to advance our understanding of both nuclear structure and quark-gluon plasma physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16071v4</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rept.Prog.Phys. 88 (2025) 9, 092301</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jiangyong Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
