<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 02:40:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Software Package for Generating Robust and Accurate Potentials using the Moment Tensor Potential Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12433v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the Plan for Robust and Accurate Potentials (PRAPs), a software package for training and using moment tensor potentials (MTPs) in concert with the Machine Learned Interatomic Potentials (MLIP) software package. PRAPs provides an automated workflow to train MTPs using active learning procedures, and a variety of utilities to ease and improve workflows when utilizing the MLIP software. PRAPs was originally developed in the context of crystal structure prediction, in which one calculates convex hulls and predicts low energy metastable and thermodynamically stable structures, but the potentials PRAPs develops are not limited to such applications. PRAPs produces two potentials, one capable of rough estimates of the energies, forces and stresses of almost any chemical structure in the specified compositional space -- the Robust Potential -- and a second potential intended to provide more accurate descriptions of ground state and metastable structures -- the Accurate Potential. We also present a Python library, mliputils, designed to assist users in working with the chemical structural files used by the MLIP package.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12433v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Josiah Roberts, Biswas Rijal, Simon Divilov, Jon-Paul Maria, William G. Fahrenholtz, Douglas E. Wolfe, Donald W. Brenner, Stefano Curtarolo, Eva Zurek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LibppRPA: An Open-Source Library for Particle-Particle Random Phase Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12515v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The accurate description of electron correlation and excitation energies remains a fundamental challenge in quantum chemistry. The particle-particle random phase approximation (ppRPA) has emerged as a promising method for capturing a broad range of excited-state properties. However, the implementation of ppRPA has been largely limited to in-house software, restricting its accessibility and usability. In this work, we present LibppRPA, an open-source and lightweight Python library designed for efficient and flexible ppRPA calculations of (1) electronic excitation energy and its associated analytical gradients and (2) the ground state correlation energy, and its associated analytical gradients. LibppRPA enables seamless integration with existing quantum chemistry packages, such as PySCF, by utilizing occupation numbers, molecular orbital coefficients, and three-center electron repulsion integrals. We implement both direct diagonalization and the iterative Davidson algorithm for solving the ppRPA equations, as well as active-space approximations, allowing users to balance accuracy and computational efficiency. We demonstrate the performance of LibppRPA through benchmark calculations on singlet-triplet gaps, double excitations, charge-transfer excitations, and valence/Rydberg excitations, showcasing its reliability across diverse molecular systems. The library provides a robust platform for studying electronic excitations and offers new opportunities for future developments in electronic structure theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12515v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jincheng Yu, Jiachen Li, Chaoqun Zhang, Tianyu Zhu, Weitao Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanisms of inductively coupled BCl3-plasma interaction with the GaN surfaceMechanisms of inductively coupled BCl3-plasma interaction with the GaN surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12569</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12569v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consideration is given to inductively coupled BCl3-plasma (ICP) treatment of the GaN surface, which is a promising technique to get the low resistance ohmic contacts in GaN-based transistors. In some cases, BCl3 plasma treatment results in ohmic contact degradation because BClx radicals tend to form a polymer thin film BxCly on the surface. In the present work, the mechanisms of BCl3 plasma interaction with the GaN surface are considered. Threshold ion energies of reactive ion etching for polymer BxCly and semiconductor GaN, respectively, are estimated using numerical plasma modeling. It has been demonstrated that a plasma treatment regime without polymer deposition and reactive etching is possible when an ion energy is in the range ~32-60 eV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12569v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Uspekhi Prikladnoi Fiziki 6, 381 (2018)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Anton Kobelev, Nikolay Andrianov, Yuri Barsukov, Alexander Smirnov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended dissipaton theory for higher-order bath couplings and application to non-Condon spectroscopy with anharmonicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we develop an extended dissipaton theory that generalizes the environmental couplings beyond the conventional linear and quadratic forms, enabling the treatment of arbitrary order of bath couplings. Applying this theoretical framework to the condensed-phase non-Condon spectroscopy, we demonstrate the interplay of anharmonicity, non-Condon and solvent effects on optical spectra. Precise simulations are carried out with high efficiency on linear absorption spectra involving the above mentioned correlated effects. We exhibit how an anharmonic potential modulates the vibronic feature, offering insights into the role of nonlinear environmental couplings in spectroscopic signatures and exemplifying the success of the extended dissipaton formalism as an exact and efficient method for higher-order bath couplings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12584v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zi-Fan Zhu, Yu Su, Yao Wang, Rui-Xue Xu, YiJing Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling real-time chemical shifts in the ultrafast regime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13079v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Traditional x-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS) relies upon a direct mapping between the photoelectron binding energies and the local chemical environment, which is well-characterized by an electrostatic partial charges model for systems in equilibrium. However, the extension of this technique to out-of-equilibrium systems has been hampered by the lack of x-ray sources capable of accessing multiple atomic sites with high spectral and temporal resolution, as well as the lack of simple theoretical procedures to interpret the observed signals. In this work we employ multi-site XPS with a narrowband femtosecond x-ray probe to unravel different ultrafast dissociation processes of a polyatomic molecule, fluoromethane (CH$_{3}$F). We show that XPS can follow the cleavage of both the C-F and C-H bonds in real time, despite these channels lying close in binding energy. Additionally, we apply the partial charges model to describe these dynamics, and verify this extension with both advanced ab-initio calculations and experimental data. These results enable the application of this technique to out-of-equilibrium systems of higher complexity, by correlating real-time information from multiple atomic sites and interpreting the measurements through a viable theoretical modelling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13079v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel E. Rivas, Lorenzo Paoloni, Rebecca Boll, Alberto De Fanis, Ana Mart\'inez Guti\'errez, Tommaso Mazza, Sol\`ene Oberli, Oliver Alexander, Andr\'e Al-Haddad, Thomas M. Baumann, Christoph Bostedt, Simon Dold, Gianluca Geloni, Markus Ilchen, Dooshaye Moonshiram, Daniel Rolles, Artem Rudenko, Philipp Schmidt, Svitozar Serkez, Sergey Usenko, \'Angel Mart\'in Pend\'as, Michael Meyer, Jes\'us Gonz\'alez-V\'azquez, Antonio Pic\'on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combining Molecular Dynamics and Experimental Methods for the Parametrization of Binary Carbonate-Based Electrolytes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13225v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modelling the ionic transport in battery cells requires precise parametrization of the involved electrolytes. For carbonate-based electrolytes, however, the evaluation of their parameters suffers from interphase effects between the bulk electrolyte and the Li metal electrode, commonly present in the usual electrochemical polarization experiments. In this work, we combine measurements on conductivity and concentration cells with molecular dynamic simulations, avoiding these difficulties and thus, allowing for a more accurate determination of the parameters. We determine the conductivity, the transference number, the thermodynamic factor and the salt diffusion coefficient for three different electrolytes, i.e mixtures of ethylene carbonate (EC), ethyl methyl carbonate (EMC), methyl propionate (MP), dimethyl carbonate (DMC) and propylene carbonate (PC), containing LiPF$_6$ at various concentrations and temperatures. In order to validate the simulated transference numbers, we employ electrophoretic Nuclear Magnetic Resonance spectroscopy (eNMR).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13225v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1149/1945-7111/add381</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of The Electrochemical Society 172 (2025) 050523</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Lehnert, Martin Lorenz, Maria Fernanda Juarez, Max Schammer, Maryam Nojabaee, Monika Sch\"onhoff, Birger Horstmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Space Electronic Structure Theory: From Diatomic Lambda-Doubling to Macroscopic Einstein-de Haas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13448v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: $\Lambda$-doubling of diatomic molecules is a subtle microscopic phenomenon that has long attracted the attention of experimental groups, insofar as rotation of molecular $\textit{nuclei}$ induces small energetic changes in the (degenerate) $\textit{electronic}$ state. A direct description of such a phenomenon clearly requires going beyond the Born-Oppenheimer approximation. Here we show that a phase space theory previously developed to capture electronic momentum and model vibrational circular dichroism -- and which we have postulated should also describe the Einstein-de Haas effect, a macroscopic manifestation of angular momentum conservation -- is also able to recover the $\Lambda$-doubling energy splitting (or $\Lambda$-splitting) of the NO molecule nearly quantitatively. The key observation is that, by parameterizing the electronic Hamiltonian in terms of both nuclear position ($\mathbf{X}$) and nuclear momentum ($\mathbf{P}$), a phase space method yields potential energy surfaces that explicitly include the electron-rotation coupling and correctly conserve angular momentum (which we show is essential to capture $\Lambda-$doubling). The data presented in this manuscript offers another small glimpse into the rich physics that one can learn from investigating phase space potential energy surfaces $E_{PS}(\mathbf{X},\mathbf{P})$ as a function of both nuclear position and momentum, all at a computational cost comparable to standard Born-Oppenheimer electronic structure calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13448v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linqing Peng, Tian Qiu, Nadine Bradbury, Xuezhi Bian, Mansi Bhati, Robert Littlejohn, Nathanael M. Kidwell, Joseph E. Subotnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DoNOF 2.0: A modern Open-Source Electronic Structure Program for Natural Orbital Functionals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13550v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we present the second version of the Donostia Natural Orbital Functional Software, an open-source program for natural orbital functional calculations. The new release incorporates improved optimization algorithms, capabilities for excited-state computations, support for ab initio molecular dynamics, and integration with the libcint library. DoNOF 2.0 also extends its property toolbox by enabling the evaluation of nonlinear optical responses, including static polarizabilities and higher-order hyperpolarizabilities via a finite-field Romberg-Richardson scheme. Program Summary [Title: DoNOF; Developer's repository link: http://github.com/DoNOF/; Program's Manual link: https://donof.readthedocs.io/; Licensing provisions: GPLv3; Programming language: Fortran; additional implementations available in Python (PyNOF) and Julia (DoNOF.jl); Multinode capability: Support for distributed execution through a hybrid OpenMPI and OpenMP implementation]</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13550v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Felipe Huan Lew-Yee, Ion Mitxelena, Jorge M. del Campo, and Mario Piris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine-Learned Electrostatic Potentials for Accurate Hydration Free Energy Calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13579v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Free energy calculations are widely used tools in computational chemistry, but their dependence on the assignment of partial charges during force field parametrization reduces their accuracy and reproducibility. In this work, we highlight the direct connection between the low accuracy of AM1-BCC charges on polar species and the poor accuracy of corresponding hydration free energy calculations. We then propose an XGBoost regressor trained on atomic descriptors to rapidly predict charges obtained with high-fidelity density functional theory calculations at PBE0-D3(BJ)/def2-TZVP level. The more accurate electrostatic description results in more reliable free energy calculations than those obtained with semi-empirical AM1-BCC charges. Finally, we leverage this predictive model in combination with a 1 ns gas-phase molecular dynamics simulation to propose the Boltzmann Percentile method for assigning charges representative of the conformational ensemble of a molecule. Charges obtained with this method are robust to different input conformations, and the resulting free energies, calculated on a subset of the FreeSolv dataset, show a root mean squared error of 1.69 kcal/mol against the 3.05 kcal/mol obtained with semi-empirical charges as well as a significantly better ranking. Our method is easily integrable in the traditional workflow and requires the same computational resources. These two aspects make it a realistic tool for enhancing already expensive free energy calculations, and more in general, molecular dynamics simulations in condensed phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13579v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathias Hilfiker, Leonardo Medrano Sandonas, Alexandre Tkatchenko, Ola Engkvist, Marco Kl\"ahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Quantum Advantage in Chemistry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13657v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Molecular simulations are widely regarded as leading candidates to demonstrate quantum advantage--defined as the point at which quantum methods surpass classical approaches in either accuracy or scale. Yet the qubit counts and error rates required to realize such an advantage remain uncertain; resource estimates for ground-state electronic structure span orders of magnitude, and no quantum-native method has been validated at a commercially relevant scale. Here we address this uncertainty by executing the iterative qubit coupled-cluster (iQCC) algorithm, designed for fault-tolerant quantum hardware, at unprecedented scale using a quantum solver on classical processors, enabling simulations of transition organo-metallic complexes requiring hundreds of logical qubits and millions of entangling gates. Using this approach, we compute the lowest triplet excited state (T$_1$) energies of Ir(III) and Pt(II) phosphorescent organometallic compounds and show that iQCC achieves the lowest mean absolute error (0.05 eV) and highest R$^2$ (0.94) relative to experiment, outperforming leading classical methods. We find these systems remain classically tractable up to $\sim$200 logical qubits, establishing the threshold at which quantum advantage in computational chemistry may emerge and clarifying resource requirements for future quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13657v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Scott N. Genin, Ohyun Kwon, Seyyed Mehdi Hosseini Jenab, Seon-Jeong Lim, Taehyung Kim, Tae-Gon Kim, Rami Gherib, Angela F. Harper, Ilya G. Ryabinkin, Michael G. Helander</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry Dilemmas in Quantum Computing for Chemistry: A Comprehensive Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12097v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Symmetry adaptation, universality, and gate efficiency are central but often competing requirements in quantum algorithms for electronic structure and many-body physics. For example, fully symmetry-adapted universal operator pools typically generate long and deep quantum circuits, gate-efficient universal operator pools generally break symmetries, and gate-efficient fully symmetry-adapted operator pools may not be universal. In this work, we analyze such symmetry dilemmas both theoretically and numerically. On the theory side, we prove that the popular, gate-efficient operator pool consisting of singlet spin-adapted singles and perfect-pairing doubles is not universal when spatial symmetry is enforced. To demonstrate the strengths and weaknesses of the three types of pools, we perform numerical simulations using an adaptive algorithm paired with operator pools that are (i) fully symmetry-adapted and universal, (ii) fully symmetry-adapted and non-universal, and (iii) breaking a single symmetry and are universal. Our numerical simulations encompass three physically relevant scenarios in which the target state is (i) the global ground state, (ii) the ground state crossed by a state differing in multiple symmetry properties, and (iii) the ground state crossed by a state differing in a single symmetry property. Our results show when symmetry-breaking but universal pools can be used safely, when enforcing at least one distinguishing symmetry suffices, and when a particular symmetry must be rigorously preserved to avoid variational collapse. Together, the formal and numerical analysis provides a practical guide for designing and benchmarking symmetry-adapted operator pools that balance universality, resource requirements, and robust state targeting in quantum simulations for chemistry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12097v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilias Magoulas, Muhan Zhang, Francesco A. Evangelista</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous power generation and cooling using semiconductor-sensitized thermal cells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12114v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This manuscript reports a semiconductor-sensitized thermal cell (STC) that converts ambient heat into electrical power while simultaneously reducing its own temperature under isothermal conditions. Using a printable semiconductor--electrolyte architecture, we fabricate $4\,\mathrm{cm} \times 4\,\mathrm{cm}$ devices that generate up to approximately $0.2\,\mathrm{mW}$ at temperatures of $40$--$55\,^\circ\mathrm{C}$. During continuous discharge, the STC exhibits a transient temperature decrease followed by thermal equilibration with the environment. In contrast, periodic on--off discharge produces sustained cooling of approximately $1\,^\circ\mathrm{C}$ relative to a non-discharging reference. Notably, parallel integration of four STCs yields a nonlinear enhancement of cooling (approximately $5\,^\circ\mathrm{C}$) without a corresponding increase in electrical output. The observed behavior can be understood within a macroscopic energy-balance framework, in which time modulation of electrochemical heat consumption prevents the establishment of thermal steady state. These results demonstrate sustained isothermal cooling induced by heat-to-electricity conversion at practical device scales, and highlight semiconductor-sensitized thermal cells as a platform for coupled energy harvesting and thermal management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12114v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atsushi Hayashida, Hitoshi Saito, Yang Chunxiang, Taiga Nishii, Motokazu Ishihara, Yuta Nakamura, Kento Sunaga, Sachiko Matsushita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photoelectron chiral dichroism induced by lasers without helicity via chiral hole wave-packets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12412v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Photoelectron circular dichroism (PECD) is a method where randomly oriented chiral molecules are photoionized due to irradiation by circularly-polarized lasers, yielding large chiral signals in the photoelectron momentum distribution. Recently, PECD was explored with polarization-tailored light such as bi-chromatic and non-collinear drivers, which still produces significant chiral signals. Yet, all known PECD configurations to date exhibit non-zero time-local chirality. That is, they are driven by an intrinsically helical light source. Nonetheless, 'chiral' light can also be non-helical if its chirality manifests on longer timescales (e.g. an optical centrifuge). It remains unknown whether PECD can arise from non-helical coherent light. Here we predict that PECD indeed emerges from non-helical light by employing a train of linearly-polarized intense laser pulses with a rotating polarization axis, which are phase-coherent and time-delayed. We find strong PECD in the model chiral molecule CBrClFH under a wide parameter regime that can be optimized up to ~8% by tuning delays between pulses, suggesting quantum interference. We directly show that the physical mechanism for this type of PECD differs from the standard case, relying on a chiral hole attosecond wave-packet evolving in the molecule, induced by the first linear pulse. Our work shows that multiple mechanisms can give rise to PECD on longer timescales and provides a novel approach for ultrafast chirality spectroscopy and coherent chiral wave-packet manipulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12412v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gal Bouskila, Avner Fleischer, Ofer Neufeld</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking massive multiplexing in whispering gallery mode biosensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.12421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.12421v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate, label-free quantification of multiple analytes in complex biological media remains a major challenge due to limited multiplexing, signal cross-correlations, and inconsistency across sensor samples and measurement runs. We introduce a multiplexed whispering-gallery-mode (WGM) biosensing framework that overcomes these barriers by jointly advancing photonic integration and data analytics. Our glass-chip platform enables massive, parallelized and flexible multiplexing of &gt;10000 microresonators organized into up to 100 sensing channels, with universal and modular chip design and detection hardware, while maintaining loaded Q-factors of 10^6. Our novel hybrid deep-learning framework BioCCF that integrates domain adaptation with cross-channel fusion enables harmonization of responses across sensing chips and extraction of nonlinear correlations in complex mixtures. Using a highly heterogeneous dataset comprising over 200 hours of sensing data acquired from nine chips with different channel configurations, biological replicates, and repeated regeneration cycles, we demonstrate recalibration-free identification of solution (99.3\% accuracy) and quantification of immunoglobulin G components with relative prediction error of 10^-4 under 5 min. The affordability and modularity of the platform enable distributed data acquisition and aggregation into shared repositories, providing a pathway toward continuously improving model generalization, cross-validation and a scalable, community-driven paradigm for biosensing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.12421v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Saetchnikov, Elina Tcherniavskaia, Andreas Ostendorf, Anton Saetchnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic Theory of a Fluctuation-Induced Dynamical Crossover in Supercooled Liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13082v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Mean-field theories of the glass transition predict a phase transition to a dynamically arrested state, yet no such transition is observed in experiments or simulations of finite-dimensional systems. We resolve this long-standing discrepancy by incorporating critical dynamical fluctuations into a microscopic mode-coupling framework. We show that these fluctuations round off the mean-field singularity and restore ergodicity at all finite densities (or temperatures) without invoking activated dynamics or facilitation. The resulting effective theory describes the order parameter as a stochastic process with self-induced, annealed disorder, determined self-consistently at the mean-field level. In the $\beta$-relaxation regime it reduces to stochastic beta-relaxation theory, thereby unifying mode-coupling and replica-based approaches beyond mean-field. All parameters of the stochastic $\beta$-relaxation theory are fixed by the static structure, enabling parameter-free predictions that extend mean-field theory into finite dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13082v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Corentin C. L. Laudicina, Liesbeth M. C. Janssen, Grzegorz Szamel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of the $\beta$-Relaxation Beyond Mode-Coupling Theory: A Microscopic Treatment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13092v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a systematic extension of mode-coupling theory (MCT) that incorporates critical dynamical fluctuations. Starting from a microscopic diagrammatic theory, we identify dominant classes of divergent diagrams near the mode-coupling transition and show that the corresponding asymptotic series dominates the mean-field below an upper critical dimension $d_c=8$. To resum these divergences, we construct a mapping to a stochastic dynamical process in which the order parameter evolves under random spatiotemporal fields. This reformulation provides a controlled, fully dynamical derivation of an effective theory for the $\beta$-relaxation which remarkably coincides with stochastic beta-relaxation theory [T. Rizzo, EPL 106, 56003 (2014)]. All coupling constants of the latter theory are expressed microscopically in terms of the liquid static structure factor and are computed for the paradigmatic hard-sphere system. The analysis demonstrates that fluctuations alone restore ergodicity and replace the putative mean-field transition by a smooth crossover. Our results establish a predictive framework for structural relaxation beyond mean-field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13092v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Corentin C. L. Laudicina, Liesbeth M. C. Janssen, Grzegorz Szamel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Animate Droplets: Active, Adaptive, and Autonomous</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13425v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Droplets, sub-millilitre liquid volumes with at least one interface, have traditionally served as compartments for storing, transporting, and delivering materials. Beyond familiar applications in food, coatings, and consumer goods, they find cutting-edge use in energy storage, sensing, and tissue engineering. The next frontier is their integration into animate matter, emerging materials defined by their levels of activity, adaptiveness, and autonomy. Easy to produce and dispense or print into complex structures, and with enormous chemical versatility, droplets are ideal building blocks for animate matter. In this Perspective, we outline a roadmap for advancing animacy in droplets and call for a more concerted effort to integrate novel mechanisms for motility, sensing, and decision-making into droplet design. Although research on active droplets spans more than a century, achieving true autonomy, where droplets process multiple stimuli and respond without external control, remains a central challenge. We hope to inspire interdisciplinary collaboration towards applications in consumer goods, microfluidics, adaptive optics, tissue engineering, and soft robotics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13425v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joe Forth, Robert Malinowski, Giorgio Volpe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High Resolution Overtone Spectroscopy of HNC$^+$ and HCN$^+$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.13476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.13476v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Rotationally resolved spectra of the HNC$^+$ and HCN$^+$ molecular ions have been recorded in the spectral range between 6200 and 6800 \rcm\ using a cryogenic ion trap instrument. The rovibrational transitions were probed using two different action spectroscopy schemes, namely laser-induced reaction (LIR) and leak-out spectroscopy (LOS). Various vibrational bands of HNC$^+$ and HCN$^+$ were measured with high resolution for the first time. For HNC$^+$, the $\text{X}~^2\Sigma^+~(20^00)-(00^00)$ overtone band was recorded using LIR, while LOS was used to probe the $\text{X}~^2\Pi~(000)^1-(210)^0\mu$ combination band and the $\text{X}~^2\Pi~(000)^1-\text{A}~^2\Sigma^+~(10^00)$ vibronic band of HCN$^+$. Spectroscopic constants, band origins and radiative lifetimes for the observed states have been determined. The effective fit for the HCN$^+$ spectra revealed the presence of strong vibrational couplings leading to perturbations of the rovibrational levels of the excited states. The two action spectroscopy schemes are compared and their potential use to explore ion-molecule interactions is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.13476v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.saa.2025.127359</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Jim\'enez-Redondo, Chiara Schleif, Julianna Palot\'as, J\'anos Sarka, Hayley Bunn, Petr Dohnal, Paola Caselli, Pavol Jusko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum simulation of CO$_2$ chemisorption in an amine-functionalized metal-organic framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17453</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17453v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We perform a series of calculations using simulated QPUs, accelerated by the NVIDIA CUDA-Q platform, focusing on a molecular analog of an amine-functionalized metal-organic framework (MOF), a promising class of materials for CO$_2$ capture. The variational quantum eigensolver (VQE) technique is employed, utilizing both the unitary coupled-cluster method with singles and doubles (UCCSD) and adaptive ans\"atze within active spaces extracted from the larger material system. We explore active spaces of (6e,6o), (8e,8o), and (10e,10o), corresponding to 12, 16, and 20 qubits, respectively, and simulate them using CUDA-Q's GPU-accelerated state-vector simulator. Gate fusion is shown to decrease circuit evaluation time by 2-3$\times$, while parameter shift decreases the number of epochs required for variational convergence. The ADAPT-VQE method decreases both the number of epochs required for convergence and reduces the number of circuit parameters across all active spaces, at the cost of an increased number of circuit evaluations. Combining ADAPT-VQE with the 1- and 2-electron integrals from a CASSCF calculation recovers more correlation energy, at the cost of increased computational time. The CO$_2$ binding energy is computed, and we observe and discuss how increasing the active space size can lead to uneven recovery of correlation energy, making the predicted binding energies variable, even positive (\textit{i.e.}, energetically unfavorable) in some instances. This can be partially remedied by using an alternative approach to computing the binding energy that more evenly spreads the active space. This work explores the application of VQE to a novel material system using simulated QPUs and provides some insight into various consideration when performing these types of calculations, ultimately highlighting the challenges of studying chemisorption on near-term quantum machines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17453v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan R. Owens, Marwa H. Farag, Pooja Rao, Annarita Giani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PropMolFlow: Property-Guided Molecule Generation with Geometry-Complete Flow Matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21469v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Molecule generation is advancing rapidly in chemical discovery and drug design. Flow matching methods have recently set the state of the art (SOTA) in unconditional molecule generation, surpassing score-based diffusion models. However, diffusion models still lead in property-guided generation. In this work, we introduce PropMolFlow, an approach for property-guided molecule generation based on geometry-complete SE(3)-equivariant flow matching. Integrating five different property embedding methods with a Gaussian expansion of scalar properties, PropMolFlow achieves competitive performance against previous SOTA diffusion models in conditional molecule generation while maintaining high structural stability and validity. Additionally, it enables faster sampling speed with fewer time steps compared to baseline models. We highlight the importance of validating the properties of generated molecules through DFT calculations. Furthermore, we introduce a task to assess the model's ability to propose molecules with underrepresented property values, assessing its capacity for out-of-distribution generalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21469v4</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Zeng, Jirui Jin, Connor Ambrose, George Karypis, Mark Transtrum, Ellad B. Tadmor, Richard G. Hennig, Adrian Roitberg, Stefano Martiniani, Mingjie Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insights into Symmetry and Substitution Patterns Governing Singlet-Triplet Energy Gap in the Chemical Space of Azaphenalenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08235v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Molecules that violate Hund's rule by exhibiting an inverted singlet-triplet gap (STG), where the first excited singlet (S$_1$) lies below the triplet (T$_1$), are rare but hold great promise as efficient fifth-generation light emitters. Azaphenalenes (APs) represent one of the few known molecular classes capable of such inversion of the S$_1$/T$_1$ energy ordering, yet a systematic exploration of all unique APs is lacking. Here, we investigate 104 distinct APs and classify them based on their adherence to or deviation from Hund's rule using S$_1$-T$_1$ gaps computed with the second-order coupled-cluster method employing the Laplace transform (L-CC2). To capture substitution-dependent pseudo-Jahn-Teller distortions that are inadequately described by MP2 and DFT methods, we employ focal-point extrapolation scheme to obtain near-CCSD(T)/cc-pVTZ-quality geometries. We find three APs to undergo $D_{\rm 3h} \rightarrow C_{\rm 3h}$ and ten to show $C_{\rm 2v}\rightarrow C_{\rm s}$ symmetry lowering, leading to a total of 117 configurations of 104 unique APs. Our study identifies top candidates with inverted STGs, revealing how substitution and symmetry-lowering modulate these gaps to uncover new stable AP cores that provide promising targets for designing molecular light-emitters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08235v4</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atreyee Majumdar, Raghunathan Ramakrishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near surface concentration profile of sheared semi-dilute polymer solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.05960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.05960v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Controlling the structure of polymer solutions near a solid surface is crucial for many industrial processes, as it significantly impacts solution flow and influences slip at the interface. To date, only a few techniques have been developed to experimentally investigate this type of interface at the nanometric scale of solid/liquid interaction. In this study, we probe the interface between a smooth sapphire surface and a semi-diluted polystyrene solution, using neutron reflectivity. A special setup for flow measurements under shear has been designed and optimized. Our results show that, at rest, polymer chains are globally depleted from the solid surface. Contrary to common assumptions, some polystyrene chains do adsorb onto the wall. Under flow conditions, we experimentally demonstrate that the depletion layer remains stable, a finding that has been hypothesized but only vaguely confirmed in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.05960v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.langmuir.4c04005</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Langmuir 41(3), 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Suzanne Lafon, Tiago Outerelo-Corvo, Marion Grzelka, Arnaud H\'elary, Philipp Gutfreund, Liliane L\'eger, Alexis Chennevi\`ere, Fr\'ed\'eric Restagno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical signatures of coherence in molecular dimers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13435</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13435v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We calculate experimentally measurable signatures of quantum correlations in a coupled molecular dimer that strongly interacts with its vibrational environment. We investigate intensity and mode-resolved photon coincidences for different relative orientations of such dimers, and observe spatio-temporal correlations for various configurations. We find that projective measurements can produce cooperative signatures even when emitters are arranged orthogonal to each other. To model effects of vibrational environments that are present in realistic experimental situations, we use the polaron framework. Further, we also account for the effects of finite instrument response, varying temperature, and presence of static disorder. We analyse the effect of disorder in both dimer orientation and measurement direction and find that photon coincidences remain well-resolvable using state-of-the-art detectors. This work enhances our understanding of cooperative emission from two coupled emitters and offers direction for future experiments on probing their coherent dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13435v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0281761</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 163, 204103 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Priyankar Banerjee, Adam Burgess, Julian Wiercinski, Moritz Cygorek, Erik M. Gauger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reduced Density Matrices and Phase-Space Distributions in Thermofield Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21302v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Thermofield dynamics (TFD) is a powerful framework to account for thermal effects in a wavefunction setting, and has been extensively used in physics and quantum optics. TFD relies on a duplicated state space and creates a correlated two-mode thermal state via a Bogoliubov transformation acting on the vacuum state. However, a very useful variant of TFD uses the vacuum state as initial condition and transfers the Bogoliubov transformation into the propagator. This variant, referred to here as the inverse Bogoliubov transformation (iBT) variant, has recently been applied to vibronic coupling problems and coupled-oscillator Hamiltonians in a chemistry context, where the method is combined with efficient tensor network methods for high-dimensional quantum propagation. In the iBT/TFD representation, the mode expectation values are clearly defined and easy to calculate, but the thermalized reduced particle distributions such as the reduced 1-particle densities or Wigner distributions are highly non-trivial due to the Bogoliubov back-transformation of the original thermal TFD wavefunction. Here we derive formal expressions for the reduced 1-particle density matrix (1-RDM) that uses the correlations between the real and tilde modes encoded in the associated reduced 2-particle density matrix (2-RDM). We apply this formalism to define the 1-RDM and the Wigner distributions in the special case of a thermal harmonic oscillator. Moreover, we discuss several approximate schemes that can be extended to higher-dimensional distributions. These methods are demonstrated for the thermal reduced 1-particle density of an anharmonic oscillator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21302v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bartosz B{\l}asiak, Dominik Brey, Rocco Martinazzo, Irene Burghardt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excitation Amplitude Sampling for Low Variance Electronic Structure on Quantum Computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15438v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We combine classical heuristics with partial shadow tomography to enable efficient protocols for extracting information from correlated ab initio electronic systems encoded on quantum devices. By proposing the use of a correlation energy functional and sampling of a polynomial set of excitation amplitudes of the quantum state, we can demonstrate an almost two order of magnitude reduction in required number of shots for a given statistical error in the energy estimate, as well as observing a linear scaling to accessible system sizes. Furthermore, we find a high-degree of noise resilience of these estimators on real quantum devices, with up to an order of magnitude increase in the tolerated noise compared to traditional techniques. While these approaches are expected to break down asymptotically, we find strong evidence that these large system arguments do not prevent algorithmic advantage from these simple protocols in many systems of interest. We further extend this to consider the extraction of beyond-energetic properties by mapping to a coupled cluster surrogate model, as well as a natural combination within a quantum embedding framework. This embedding framework avoids the unstable self-consistent requirements of previous approaches, enabling application of quantum solvers to realistic correlated materials science, where we demonstrate the volume-dependence of the spin gap of Nickel Oxide.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15438v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Connor Lenihan, Oliver J. Backhouse, Basil Ibrahim, Tom W. A. Montgomery, Phalgun Lolur, M. J. Bhaseen, George H. Booth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modification of adhesion between microparticles and engineered silicon surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13887v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A key challenge in performing experiments with microparticles is controlling their adhesion to substrates. For example, levitation of a microparticle initially resting on a surface requires overcoming the surface adhesion forces to deliver the microparticle into a mechanical potential acting as a trap. By engineering the surface of silicon substrates, we aim to decrease the adhesion force between a metallic microparticle and the silicon surface. To this end, we investigate different methods of surface engineering that are based on chemical, physical, or physio-chemical modifications of the surface of silicon. We give quantitative results on the detachment force, finding a correlation between the water contact angle and the mean detachment force, indicating that hydrophobic surfaces are desired for low microparticle adhesion. We develop surface preparations decreasing the mean detachment force by more than a factor of three compared to an untreated silicon surface. Our results will enable reliable levitation of microparticles and are relevant for experiments requiring low adhesion between microparticles and a surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13887v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0297664</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Appl. Phys. 138, 225304 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Resare, Somiya Islam Soke, Witlef Wieczorek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shoot from the HIP: Hessian Interatomic Potentials without derivatives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21624v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fundamental tasks in computational chemistry, from transition state search to vibrational analysis, rely on molecular Hessians, which are the second derivatives of the potential energy. Yet, Hessians are computationally expensive to calculate and scale poorly with system size, with both quantum mechanical methods and neural networks. In this work, we demonstrate that Hessians can be predicted directly from a deep learning model, without relying on automatic differentiation or finite differences. We observe that one can construct SE(3)-equivariant, symmetric Hessians from irreducible representations (irrep) features up to degree $l$=2 computed during message passing in graph neural networks. This makes HIP Hessians one to two orders of magnitude faster, more accurate, more memory efficient, easier to train, and enables more favorable scaling with system size. We validate our predictions across a wide range of downstream tasks, demonstrating consistently superior performance for transition state search, accelerated geometry optimization, zero-point energy corrections, and vibrational analysis benchmarks. We open-source the HIP codebase and model weights to enable further development of the direct prediction of Hessians at https://github.com/BurgerAndreas/hip</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21624v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Burger, Luca Thiede, Nikolaj R{\o}nne, Varinia Bernales, Nandita Vijaykumar, Tejs Vegge, Arghya Bhowmik, Alan Aspuru-Guzik</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
