<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.chem-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph</link>
    <description>physics.chem-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.chem-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 05:00:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Kohn-Sham density encoding rescues coupled cluster theory for strongly correlated molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06149v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Coupled cluster theory with a Kohn-Sham reference (KS-CC) can dramatically outperform its Hartree-Fock counterpart for strongly correlated systems, but the origin of these improvements has remained unclear. Here we demonstrate that these improvements arise from differences in the one-particle density matrix that are encoded into the non-canonical Fock matrix and not from the nature of the KS orbitals, as is commonly assumed. Equipped with this insight, KS-CCSD(T) can be leveraged to achieve near-chemical-accuracy for electronic and thermochemical properties of transition-metal dimers and main-group compounds. Most strikingly, KS-CCSD(T) qualitatively recovers the entire Cr$_2$ potential energy surface, a notorious failure case for HF-CCSD(T) and single-reference density functional theory. We further introduce a density difference diagnostic that identifies multireference character and guides practitioners toward rational selections of optimal references at mean-field cost. These results establish KS-CCSD(T) as a practical route to treat strong correlation within the "gold standard" framework, and this has immediate implications for machine learning potential development and materials research, areas that heavily rely on KS-DFT for model-parameter fitting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06149v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdulrahman Y. Zamani, Barbaro Zulueta, Andrew M. Ricciuti, John A. Keith, Kevin Carter-Fenk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematic incorporation of nuclear quantum effects into atomistic simulations by smoothed trajectory analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06725v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nuclear quantum effects (NQEs) play an essential role in many atomistic systems, yet their explicit inclusion in molecular simulations remains challenging. Path-integral molecular dynamics (PIMD) provides a rigorous framework for incorporating NQEs, but its practical applicability is often limited by the slow and strongly system-dependent convergence with respect to the number of beads. Here we introduce path-integral generalized smoothed trajectory analysis (PIGSTA), a post-processing framework for the systematic incorporation of NQEs into atomistic simulations, using either classical or path-integral molecular dynamics trajectories. By applying analytically defined convolution kernels to simulation trajectories, PIGSTA corrects the frequency-dependent discretization error associated with a finite number of beads, without modifying the underlying dynamics. For harmonic systems, PIGSTA recovers the exact quantum-mechanical limit at any bead number, whereas standard PIMD becomes exact only in the infinite-bead limit. More generally, the method significantly improves the convergence of thermodynamic and structural observables at finite bead numbers and provides an internal, reference-free diagnostic of bead-number convergence based on the consistency of energy and force estimators. We assess PIGSTA for ambient liquid water and for the Zundel cation at ultralow temperature, representing a particularly demanding case for bead-number convergence. In both systems, PIGSTA reproduces the converged PIMD limit and enables physically consistent results at reduced bead numbers when convergence criteria are satisfied. Owing to its post-processing nature and negligible additional computational cost, PIGSTA offers a practical and broadly applicable approach for incorporating NQEs into atomistic simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06725v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Ad\'am Madar\'asz, Bence Bal\'azs M\'esz\'aros, J\'anos Daru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Molecular origin of 31P-NMR chemical shifts of phosphate groups with bivalent counter ions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06753v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The electrostatic interactions of phosphate groups and counter ions critically affect the structure, function and reactivity of DNA or RNA. We present a joint experimental-theoretical investigation of dimethyl phosphate (DMP-) in aqueous solution, an established model system of the sugar-phosphate backbone. Utilizing 31P-NMR spectroscopy as probe of phosphate-ion association, variations of Mg2+ and Ca2+ content exhibit a systematic shielding of the 31P chemical shift ({\delta}iso(31P)) with moderate temperature dependence. Enhanced sampling molecular dynamics (MD) and ab initio (GIAO-DF-LMP2) level of theory are used to reveal the microscopic mechanism. Simulations are performed for a configurational ensemble of DMP-ion geometries and their first solvation shells, demonstrating (i) the spatial convergence of changes of the nuclear shielding constant {\sigma}iso(31P), (ii) the intramolecular geometric origin of short-timescale {\sigma}iso(31P) fluctuations and (iii) an average shift of {\sigma}iso(31P) of about 3-5 ppm upon contact ion pair formation with Mg2+ or Ca2+ ions. A quantitative analysis of {\delta}iso(31P) for varying ion content and temperature allows us to extract the temperature-dependent fraction of the contact ion pair species, indicating that solvent separated or free ion pairs are the energetically preferred species. The results impose boundary conditions for improvements of phosphate ion force fields and establish the interactions underlying the changes of {\delta}iso(31P).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06753v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leo Christanell, Karl-Jakob K\"onig, Julian Holzinger, Anne K. Sch\"utz, Benjamin P. Fingerhut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mimyria: Machine learned vibrational spectroscopy for aqueous systems made simple</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06760v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vibrational spectroscopy provides a powerful connection between molecular dynamics (MD) simulations and experiment, but its routine use in condensed-phase systems remains limited. We introduce mimyria, a modular and automated framework that orchestrates electronic-structure reference calculations, trains atom-resolved machine-learning response models, and generates IR and Raman spectra from MD trajectories within a unified workflow. We introduce the polarizability gradient tensor (PGT) as a novel atom-resolved machine-learning target property for Raman spectroscopy, complementing the established atomic polar tensor (APT) for IR spectroscopy. As a necessary prerequisite, we demonstrate how both PGTs and APTs can accurately be computed from electronic-structure theory, validate them across formally equivalent derivative formulations, and thereby benchmark their numerical consistency. We then employ machine learning as an efficient surrogate to represent the validated APT and PGT response functions on aqueous benchmark systems. We validate the trained models directly at the level of the spectrum against explicit ab initio reference calculations and find that IR and Raman spectra converge with surprisingly small training sets. Moreover, spectral agreement improves more rapidly than the root-mean-square error (RMSE). While RMSE is straightforward to compute, statistically converged reference spectra are generally impractical to obtain, motivating the need to relate model-level errors to observable-level accuracy. By connecting these complementary error measures, we provide practical guidelines and early-stopping criteria for achieving sufficient spectral fidelity. By integrating response-tensor learning, automated training, and spectral-domain validation into a unified workflow, mimyria enables data-efficient and quantitatively reliable vibrational spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06760v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Schienbein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Artificial Intelligence for Direct Prediction of Molecular Dynamics Across Chemical Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16301v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Molecular dynamics (MD) is a powerful tool for exploring the behavior of atomistic systems, but its reliance on sequential numerical integration limits simulation efficiency. We present a novel neural network architecture, MDtrajNet, and a pre-trained foundational model, MDtrajNet-1, that directly generates MD trajectories across chemical space, bypassing force calculations and integration. MDtrajNet combines equivariant neural networks with a transformer-based architecture to achieve strong accuracy and transferability in predicting long-time trajectories. This approach accelerates simulations by up to two orders of magnitude and yields better accuracy than MD propagated with established machine-learning interatomic potentials trained on the same data. Remarkably, the errors of the trajectories generated by MDtrajNet-1 for various seen and even unseen small-sized molecular systems are close to those of the conventional ab initio MD. The current limitations of MDtrajNet-1 are attributed to the relatively small size of the chemical space in its training data; however, even for bigger, unseen systems, MDtrajNet-1 provides a good starting point for fine-tuning and obtaining system-specific models. The architecture's flexible design supports diverse application scenarios, including different statistical ensembles, boundary conditions, and interaction types. By overcoming the intrinsic speed barrier of conventional MD, MDtrajNet opens new frontiers in efficient and scalable atomistic simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16301v3</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fuchun Ge, Yuxinxin Chen, Pavlo O. Dral</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extracting Many-Body Quantum Resources within One-Body Reduced Density Matrix Functional Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12596v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum Fisher information (QFI) is a central concept in quantum sciences used to quantify the ultimate precision limit of parameter estimation, detect quantum phase transitions, witness genuine multipartite entanglement, or probe nonlocality. Despite this widespread range of applications, computing the QFI value of quantum many-body systems is, in general, a very demanding task. Here we combine ideas from functional theories and quantum information to develop a novel functional framework for the QFI of fermionic and bosonic ground states. By relying upon the constrained-search approach, we demonstrate that the QFI matricial values can universally be determined by the one-body reduced density matrix (1-RDM), avoiding thus the use of exponentially large wave functions. Furthermore, we show that QFI functionals can be determined from the universal 1-RDM functional by calculating its derivatives with respect to the coupling strengths, becoming thus the generating functional of the QFI. We showcase our approach with the Bose-Hubbard model and present exact analytical and numerical QFI functionals. Our results provide the first connection between the one-body reduced density matrix functional theory and the quantum Fisher information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12596v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.L012052</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 6, L012052 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Carlos L. Benavides-Riveros, Tomasz Wasak, Alessio Recati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Negative Energetic Elasticity in Polymer Chains: Crossovers among Random, Self-Avoiding, and Neighbor-Avoiding Walks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14992v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Negative energetic elasticity in gels challenges the conventional understanding of gel elasticity; despite extensive research, a concise explanation remains elusive. In this study, we use the weakly self-avoiding walk (the Domb-Joyce model; DJ model) and interacting self-avoiding walk (ISAW) to investigate the emergence of negative energetic elasticity in polymer chains. Using exact enumeration, we show that both the DJ model and ISAW exhibit negative energetic elasticity, which is caused by effective soft-repulsive interactions between polymer segments. Moreover, we find that a universal scaling law for the internal energy of both models, with a common exponent of $7/4$, holds consistently across both random-walk-self-avoiding-walk and self-avoiding-walk-neighbor-avoiding-walk crossovers. These findings suggest that negative energetic elasticity is a fundamental and universal property of polymer networks and chains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14992v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/pzk3-t3s5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 112, 025406 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nobu C. Shirai, Naoyuki Sakumichi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field theories and quantum methods for stochastic reaction-diffusion systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13377v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Complex systems are composed of many particles or agents that move and interact with one another. The underlying mathematical framework to model many of these systems must incorporate the spatial transport of particles and their interactions, as well as changes to their copy numbers, all of which can be formulated in terms of stochastic reaction-diffusion processes. The probabilistic representation of these processes is complex because of combinatorial aspects arising due to nonlinear interactions and varying particle numbers. This review presents the main field theory representations of stochastic reaction-diffusion systems, which handle these issues `under-the-hood'. First, we focus on bringing techniques familiar to theoretical physicists -- such as second quantization, Fock space, and path integrals -- back into the classical domain of reaction-diffusion systems. We demonstrate how various field theory representations can all be unified under a single basis-independent representation. We then extend existing quantum-based methods and notation to work directly on the level of the unifying representation, and we illustrate how they can be used to consistently obtain previous known results, such as numerical discretizations and relations between model parameters at multiple scales. Throughout the work, we contextualize how these representations mirror well-known models of chemical physics depending on their spatial resolution, as well as the corresponding macroscopic limits. The framework presented here may find applications in a diverse set of scientific fields, including physical chemistry, theoretical ecology, epidemiology, game theory and socio-economical models of complex systems. The presentation is done in a self-contained educational and unifying manner such that it can be followed by researchers across several fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13377v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/9qlw-gyd7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rev. Mod. Phys. 98, 015001 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mauricio J. del Razo, Tommaso Lamma, Wout Merbis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Room-Temperature Ferrotoroidic Material Exhibiting Magnetic Semiconductor Properties with Superhigh Hole Mobility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09327v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The design and fabrication of room-temperature ferrotoroidic materials and magnetic semiconductors are recognized worldwide as a great challenge, and of both theoretical and practical importance in the field of condensed matter physics and information storage. Reported herein are ferrotoroidic crystal powder and film formed by supramolecular self-assembly based on uranyl and cyclodextrin, with the Curie temperature above room temperature. Experimental measurements and calculations demonstrate spontaneous vortex-like alignment of magnetic moments and furthermore a macroscopic long-range arrangement in the crystal, which breaks simultaneously space-inversion and time-reversal symmetries, exhibiting strong superexchange, spin-orbit coupling as well as anomalous Hall effect (AHE). The electrical measurements show the film with a superhigh carrier mobility of 3200 cm2*V-1*s-1 and a Hall resistivity as high as 0.32 mV*A-1*cm at room temperature. This work is expected to pave greatly the applied research on new-generation magnetoresistive random access memory (MRAM), especially as flexible material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09327v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianyuan Qi, Shijie Xiong, Beining Ma, Xinghai Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
