<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI</link>
    <description>cs.SI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 04:00:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling the Italian and English Telegram Conspiracy Spheres through Message Forwarding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18602v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Telegram has grown into a significant platform for news and information sharing, favored for its anonymity and minimal moderation. This openness, however, makes it vulnerable to misinformation and conspiracy theories. In this study, we explore the dynamics of conspiratorial narrative dissemination within Telegram, focusing on Italian and English landscapes. In particular, we leverage the mechanism of message forwarding within Telegram and collect two extensive datasets through snowball strategy. We adopt a network-based approach and build the Italian and English Telegram networks to reveal their respective communities. By employing topic modeling, we uncover distinct narratives and dynamics of misinformation spread. Results highlight differences between Italian and English conspiracy landscapes, with Italian discourse involving assorted conspiracy theories and alternative news sources intertwined with legitimate news sources, whereas English discourse is characterized by a more focused approach on specific narratives such as QAnon and political conspiracies. Finally, we show that our methodology exhibits robustness across initial seed selections, suggesting broader applicability. This study contributes to understanding information and misinformation spread on Italian and English Telegram ecosystems through the mechanism of message forwarding</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18602v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Alvisi, Serena Tardelli, Maurizio Tesconi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Winning the Social Media Influence Battle: Uncertainty-Aware Opinions to Understand and Spread True Information via Competitive Influence Maximization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18826v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Competitive Influence Maximization (CIM) involves entities competing to maximize influence in online social networks (OSNs). Current Deep Reinforcement Learning (DRL) methods in CIM rely on simplistic binary opinion models (i.e., an opinion is represented by either 0 or 1) and often overlook the complexity of user behaviors and prior knowledge. We propose a novel DRL-based framework that enhances CIM analysis by integrating Subjective Logic (SL) to accommodate uncertain opinions, user behaviors, and preferences. This approach targets the mitigation of false information by effectively propagating true information. By modeling two competitive agents, one spreading true information and the other spreading false information, we capture the strategic interplay essential to CIM. Our framework utilizes an uncertainty-based opinion model (UOM) to assess the impact on information quality in OSNs, emphasizing the importance of user behavior alongside network topology in selecting influential seed nodes. Extensive experiments demonstrate that our approach significantly outperforms state-of-the-art methods, achieving faster and more influential results (i.e., outperforming over 20%) under realistic network conditions. Moreover, our method shows robust performance in partially observable networks, effectively doubling the performance when users are predisposed to disbelieve true information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18826v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Zhang, Lance M. Kaplan, Audun J{\o}sang, Dong Hyun. Jeong, Feng Chen, Jin-Hee Cho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Utilizing Large Language Models to Identify Reddit Users Considering Vaping Cessation for Digital Interventions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17607v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The widespread adoption of social media platforms globally not only enhances users' connectivity and communication but also emerges as a vital channel for the dissemination of health-related information, thereby establishing social media data as an invaluable organic data resource for public health research. The surge in popularity of vaping or e-cigarette use in the United States and other countries has caused an outbreak of e-cigarette and vaping use-associated lung injury (EVALI), leading to hospitalizations and fatalities in 2019, highlighting the urgency to comprehend vaping behaviors and develop effective strategies for cession. In this study, we extracted a sample dataset from one vaping sub-community on Reddit to analyze users' quit vaping intentions. Leveraging large language models including both the latest GPT-4 and traditional BERT-based language models for sentence-level quit-vaping intention prediction tasks, this study compares the outcomes of these models against human annotations. Notably, when compared to human evaluators, GPT-4 model demonstrates superior consistency in adhering to annotation guidelines and processes, showcasing advanced capabilities to detect nuanced user quit-vaping intentions that human evaluators might overlook. These preliminary findings emphasize the potential of GPT-4 in enhancing the accuracy and reliability of social media data analysis, especially in identifying subtle users' intentions that may elude human detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17607v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sai Krishna Revanth Vuruma, Dezhi Wu, Saborny Sen Gupta, Lucas Aust, Valerie Lookingbill, Caleb Henry, Yang Ren, Erin Kasson, Li-Shiun Chen, Patricia Cavazos-Rehg, Dian Hu, Ming Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction Event Forecasting in Multi-Relational Recursive HyperGraphs: A Temporal Point Process Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17943v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modeling the dynamics of interacting entities using an evolving graph is an essential problem in fields such as financial networks and e-commerce. Traditional approaches focus primarily on pairwise interactions, limiting their ability to capture the complexity of real-world interactions involving multiple entities and their intricate relationship structures. This work addresses the problem of forecasting higher-order interaction events in multi-relational recursive hypergraphs. This is done using a dynamic graph representation learning framework that can capture complex relationships involving multiple entities. The proposed model, \textit{Relational Recursive Hyperedge Temporal Point Process} (RRHyperTPP) uses an encoder that learns a dynamic node representation based on the historical interaction patterns and then a hyperedge link prediction based decoder to model the event's occurrence. These learned representations are then used for downstream tasks involving forecasting the type and time of interactions. The main challenge in learning from hyperedge events is that the number of possible hyperedges grows exponentially with the number of nodes in the network. This will make the computation of negative log-likelihood of the temporal point process expensive, as the calculation of survival function requires a summation over all possible hyperedges. In our work, we use noise contrastive estimation to learn the parameters of our model, and we have experimentally shown that our models perform better than previous state-of-the-art methods for interaction forecasting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17943v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tony Gracious, Ambedkar Dukkipati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hiding from Facebook: An Encryption Protocol resistant to Correlation Attacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18817v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In many social networks, one publishes information that one wants to reveal (e.g., the photograph of some friends) together with information that may lead to privacy breaches (e.g., the name of these people). One might want to hide this sensitive information by encrypting it and sharing the decryption key only with trusted people, but this might not be enough. If the cipher associated to a face is always the same, correlation between the output of a face recognition system and the cipher can give useful clues and help train recognizers to identify untagged instances of the face. We refer to these as "correlation attacks".
  In this paper we present a coding system that attempts to counter correlation attacks by associating to each instance of a face a different encryption of the same tag in such a way that the correlation between different instances is minimal.
  In addition, we present a key distribution code that allows only the owner of the images to encode the tags, but allows a group of trusted friends to decode them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18817v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen-Da Liu, Simone Santini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The dynamics of leadership and success in software development teams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18833v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: From science to industry, teamwork plays a crucial role in knowledge production and innovation. Most studies consider teams as static groups of individuals, thereby failing to capture how the micro-dynamics of collaborative processes and organizational changes determine team success. Here, we leverage fine-grained temporal data on software development teams to gain insights into the dynamics of online collaborative projects. Our analysis reveals an uneven workload distribution in teams, with stronger heterogeneity correlated with higher success, and the early emergence of a lead developer carrying out the majority of work. Moreover, we find that a sizeable fraction of projects experience a change of lead developer, with such a transition being more likely in projects led by inexperienced users. Finally, we show that leadership change is associated with faster success growth, in particular for the least successful projects. Our work contributes to a deeper understanding of the link between team evolution and success in collaborative processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18833v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Betti, Luca Gallo, Johannes Wachs, Federico Battiston</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-Language-Model-Powered Agent-Based Framework for Misinformation and Disinformation Research: Opportunities and Open Challenges</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07545v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article presents the affordances that Generative Artificial Intelligence can have in misinformation and disinformation contexts, major threats to our digitalized society. We present a research framework to generate customized agent-based social networks for disinformation simulations that would enable understanding and evaluating the phenomena whilst discussing open challenges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07545v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/MSEC.2024.3380511</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Security &amp; Privacy, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Javier Pastor-Galindo, Pantaleone Nespoli, Jos\'e A. Ruip\'erez-Valiente</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HierCas: Hierarchical Temporal Graph Attention Networks for Popularity Prediction in Information Cascades</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.13219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.13219v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Information cascade popularity prediction is critical for many applications, including but not limited to identifying fake news and accurate recommendations. Traditional feature-based methods heavily rely on handcrafted features, which are domain-specific and lack generalizability to new domains. To address this problem, researchers have turned to neural network-based approaches. However, most existing methods follow a sampling-based modeling approach, potentially losing continuous dynamic information that emerges during the information diffusion process. In this paper, we propose Hierarchical Temporal Graph Attention Networks for cascade popularity prediction (HierCas), which operates on the entire cascade graph by a dynamic graph modeling approach. By leveraging time-aware node embedding, graph attention mechanisms, and hierarchical pooling structures, HierCas effectively captures the popularity trend implicit in the complex cascade. Extensive experiments conducted on two real-world datasets in different scenarios demonstrate that our HierCas significantly outperforms the state-of-the-art approaches. We have released our code at https://github.com/Daisy-zzz/HierCas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.13219v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhizhen Zhang, Xiaohui Xie, Yishuo Zhang, Lanshan Zhang, Yong Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comparative Study on Enhancing Prediction in Social Network Advertisement through Data Augmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.13812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.13812v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the ever-evolving landscape of social network advertising, the volume and accuracy of data play a critical role in the performance of predictive models. However, the development of robust predictive algorithms is often hampered by the limited size and potential bias present in real-world datasets. This study presents and explores a generative augmentation framework of social network advertising data. Our framework explores three generative models for data augmentation - Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs), Variational Autoencoders (VAEs), and Gaussian Mixture Models (GMMs) - to enrich data availability and diversity in the context of social network advertising analytics effectiveness. By performing synthetic extensions of the feature space, we find that through data augmentation, the performance of various classifiers has been quantitatively improved. Furthermore, we compare the relative performance gains brought by each data augmentation technique, providing insights for practitioners to select appropriate techniques to enhance model performance. This paper contributes to the literature by showing that synthetic data augmentation alleviates the limitations imposed by small or imbalanced datasets in the field of social network advertising. At the same time, this article also provides a comparative perspective on the practicality of different data augmentation methods, thereby guiding practitioners to choose appropriate techniques to enhance model performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.13812v3</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qikai Yang, Panfeng Li, Xinhe Xu, Zhicheng Ding, Wenjing Zhou, Yi Nian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restructuring Graph for Higher Homophily via Adaptive Spectral Clustering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.02386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.02386v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: While a growing body of literature has been studying new Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) that work on both homophilic and heterophilic graphs, little has been done on adapting classical GNNs to less-homophilic graphs. Although the ability to handle less-homophilic graphs is restricted, classical GNNs still stand out in several nice properties such as efficiency, simplicity, and explainability. In this work, we propose a novel graph restructuring method that can be integrated into any type of GNNs, including classical GNNs, to leverage the benefits of existing GNNs while alleviating their limitations. Our contribution is threefold: a) learning the weight of pseudo-eigenvectors for an adaptive spectral clustering that aligns well with known node labels, b) proposing a new density-aware homophilic metric that is robust to label imbalance, and c) reconstructing the adjacency matrix based on the result of adaptive spectral clustering to maximize the homophilic scores. The experimental results show that our graph restructuring method can significantly boost the performance of six classical GNNs by an average of 25% on less-homophilic graphs. The boosted performance is comparable to state-of-the-art methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.02386v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shouheng Li, Dongwoo Kim, Qing Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Temporal Point Process for Forecasting Higher Order and Directional Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.12210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.12210v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Real-world systems are made of interacting entities that evolve with time. Creating models that can forecast interactions by learning the dynamics of entities is an important problem in numerous fields. Earlier works used dynamic graph models to achieve this. However, real-world interactions are more complex than pairwise, as they involve more than two entities, and many of these higher-order interactions have directional components. Examples of these can be seen in communication networks such as email exchanges that involve a sender, and multiple recipients, citation networks, where authors draw upon the work of others, and so on. In this paper, we solve the problem of higher-order directed interaction forecasting by proposing a deep neural network-based model \textit{Directed HyperNode Temporal Point Process} for directed hyperedge event forecasting, as hyperedge provides a native framework for modeling relationships among the variable number of nodes. Our proposed technique reduces the search space by initially forecasting the nodes at which events will be observed and then forecasting hyperedge sizes and adjacency vectors for the nodes observing events. Based on these, it generates candidate hyperedges, which are then used by a hyperedge predictor to identify the ground truth. To demonstrate the efficiency of our model, we curated five datasets and conducted an extensive empirical study. We believe that this is the first work that solves the problem of forecasting higher-order directional interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.12210v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tony Gracious, Arman Gupta, Ambedkar Dukkipati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Supervised Temporal Graph learning with Temporal and Structural Intensity Alignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.07491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.07491v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Temporal graph learning aims to generate high-quality representations for graph-based tasks with dynamic information, which has recently garnered increasing attention. In contrast to static graphs, temporal graphs are typically organized as node interaction sequences over continuous time rather than an adjacency matrix. Most temporal graph learning methods model current interactions by incorporating historical neighborhood. However, such methods only consider first-order temporal information while disregarding crucial high-order structural information, resulting in suboptimal performance. To address this issue, we propose a self-supervised method called S2T for temporal graph learning, which extracts both temporal and structural information to learn more informative node representations. Notably, the initial node representations combine first-order temporal and high-order structural information differently to calculate two conditional intensities. An alignment loss is then introduced to optimize the node representations, narrowing the gap between the two intensities and making them more informative. Concretely, in addition to modeling temporal information using historical neighbor sequences, we further consider structural knowledge at both local and global levels. At the local level, we generate structural intensity by aggregating features from high-order neighbor sequences. At the global level, a global representation is generated based on all nodes to adjust the structural intensity according to the active statuses on different nodes. Extensive experiments demonstrate that the proposed model S2T achieves at most 10.13% performance improvement compared with the state-of-the-art competitors on several datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.07491v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TNNLS.2024.3386168</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Meng Liu, Ke Liang, Yawei Zhao, Wenxuan Tu, Sihang Zhou, Xinbiao Gan, Xinwang Liu, Kunlun He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Displacing Science</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16839v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Over the past century, the focus of scientific practices has shifted from purely intellectual exploration to problem-solving, leading to uneven development in scientific knowledge. Our analysis of 41 million research articles over the past six decades reveals this trend of uneven development, with atypical papers representing complementary innovation becoming the majority and displacement papers representing substitutive innovation decreasing to the minority. While AI can enhance human memory capacity, it may not necessarily accelerate progress in canonical concepts without changing the agenda of science and its organization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16839v5</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linzhuo Li, Yiling Lin, Lingfei Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
