<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI</link>
    <description>cs.SI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 07:11:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>TikTok and the Art of Personalization: Investigating Exploration and Exploitation on Social Media Feeds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12410v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recommendation algorithms for social media feeds often function as black boxes from the perspective of users. We aim to detect whether social media feed recommendations are personalized to users, and to characterize the factors contributing to personalization in these feeds. We introduce a general framework to examine a set of social media feed recommendations for a user as a timeline. We label items in the timeline as the result of exploration vs. exploitation of the user's interests on the part of the recommendation algorithm and introduce a set of metrics to capture the extent of personalization across user timelines. We apply our framework to a real TikTok dataset and validate our results using a baseline generated from automated TikTok bots, as well as a randomized baseline. We also investigate the extent to which factors such as video viewing duration, liking, and following drive the personalization of content on TikTok. Our results demonstrate that our framework produces intuitive and explainable results, and can be used to audit and understand personalization in social media feeds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12410v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karan Vombatkere, Sepehr Mousavi, Savvas Zannettou, Franziska Roesner, Krishna P. Gummadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Community detection by spectral methods in multi-layer networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12540v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Community detection in multi-layer networks is a crucial problem in network analysis. In this paper, we analyze the performance of two spectral clustering algorithms for community detection within the multi-layer degree-corrected stochastic block model (MLDCSBM) framework. One algorithm is based on the sum of adjacency matrices, while the other utilizes the debiased sum of squared adjacency matrices. We establish consistency results for community detection using these methods under MLDCSBM as the size of the network and/or the number of layers increases. Our theorems demonstrate the advantages of utilizing multiple layers for community detection. Moreover, our analysis indicates that spectral clustering with the debiased sum of squared adjacency matrices is generally superior to spectral clustering with the sum of adjacency matrices. Numerical simulations confirm that our algorithm, employing the debiased sum of squared adjacency matrices, surpasses existing methods for community detection in multi-layer networks. Finally, the analysis of several real-world multi-layer networks yields meaningful insights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12540v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huan Qing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of Malicious Agents in Social Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12619</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12619v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Social learning is a non-Bayesian framework for distributed hypothesis testing aimed at learning the true state of the environment. Traditionally, the agents are assumed to receive observations conditioned on the same true state, although it is also possible to examine the case of heterogeneous models across the graph. One important special case is when heterogeneity is caused by the presence of malicious agents whose goal is to move the agents towards a wrong hypothesis. In this work, we propose an algorithm that allows to discover the true state of every individual agent based on the sequence of their beliefs. In so doing, the methodology is also able to locate malicious behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12619v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valentina Shumovskaia, Mert Kayaalp, Ali H. Sayed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electioneering the Network: Dynamic Multi-Step Adversarial Attacks for Community Canvassing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12399v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The problem of online social network manipulation for community canvassing is of real concern in today's world. Motivated by the study of voter models, opinion and polarization dynamics on networks, we model community canvassing as a dynamic process over a network enabled via gradient-based attacks on GNNs. Existing attacks on GNNs are all single-step and do not account for the dynamic cascading nature of information diffusion in networks. We consider the realistic scenario where an adversary uses a GNN as a proxy to predict and manipulate voter preferences, especially uncertain voters. Gradient-based attacks on the GNN inform the adversary of strategic manipulations that can be made to proselytize targeted voters. In particular, we explore $\textit{minimum budget attacks for community canvassing}$ (MBACC). We show that the MBACC problem is NP-Hard and propose Dynamic Multi-Step Adversarial Community Canvassing (MAC) to address it. MAC makes dynamic local decisions based on the heuristic of low budget and high second-order influence to convert and perturb target voters. MAC is a dynamic multi-step attack that discovers low-budget and high-influence targets from which efficient cascading attacks can happen. We evaluate MAC against single-step baselines on the MBACC problem with multiple underlying networks and GNN models. Our experiments show the superiority of MAC which is able to discover efficient multi-hop attacks for adversarial community canvassing. Our code implementation and data is available at https://github.com/saurabhsharma1993/mac.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12399v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saurabh Sharma, Ambuj SIngh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The SIS process on Erd\"os-R\'enyi graphs: determining the infected fraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12560v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The SIS process on a graph poses many challenges. An important problem is to identify characteristics of the metastable behaviour. Existing mean-field methods (such as Heterogeneous Mean Field and the N-intertwined Mean Field Approximation) overestimate the metastable infected fraction, because they ignore correlations. Especially in sparse graphs, this leads to serious inaccuracies. We propose quenched and annealed methods incorporating correlations and giving significantly more accurate approximations. We use the Erd\"os-R\'enyi graph as a test case, but the methods can be generalized easily. Our methods are computationally very friendly and can be applied to fairly large graphs, in contrast with some other second-order mean field approximations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12560v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>O. S. Awolude, E. Cator, H. Don</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NewsCaption: Named-Entity aware Captioning for Out-of-Context Media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12618v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With the increasing influence of social media, online misinformation has grown to become a societal issue. The motivation for our work comes from the threat caused by cheapfakes, where an unaltered image is described using a news caption in a new but false-context. The main challenge in detecting such out-of-context multimedia is the unavailability of large-scale datasets. Several detection methods employ randomly selected captions to generate out-of-context training inputs. However, these randomly matched captions are not truly representative of out-of-context scenarios due to inconsistencies between the image description and the matched caption. We aim to address these limitations by introducing a novel task of out-of-context caption generation. In this work, we propose a new method that generates a realistic out-of-context caption given visual and textual context. We also demonstrate that the semantics of the generated captions can be controlled using the textual context. We also evaluate our method against several baselines and our method improves over the image captioning baseline by 6.2% BLUE-4, 2.96% CiDEr, 11.5% ROUGE, and 7.3% METEOR</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12618v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anurag Singh, Shivangi Aneja</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social bots sour activist sentiment without eroding engagement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12904v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Social media platforms have witnessed a substantial increase in social bot activity, significantly affecting online discourse. Our study explores the dynamic nature of bot engagement related to Extinction Rebellion climate change protests from 18 November 2019 to 10 December 2019. We find that bots exert a greater influence on human behavior than vice versa during heated online periods. To assess the causal impact of human-bot communication, we compared communication histories between human users who directly interacted with bots and matched human users who did not. Our findings demonstrate a consistent negative impact of bot interactions on subsequent human sentiment, with exposed users displaying significantly more negative sentiment than their counterparts. Furthermore, the nature of bot interaction influences human tweeting activity and the sentiment towards protests. Political astroturfing bots increase activity, whereas other bots decrease it. Sentiment changes towards protests depend on the user's original support level, indicating targeted manipulation. However, bot interactions do not change activists' engagement towards protests. Despite the seemingly minor impact of individual bot encounters, the cumulative effect is profound due to the large volume of bot communication. Our findings underscore the importance of unrestricted access to social media data for studying the prevalence and influence of social bots, as with new technological advancements distinguishing between bots and humans becomes nearly impossible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12904v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linda Li, Orsolya Vasarhelyi, Balazs Vedres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Individual differences in knowledge network navigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.10036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.10036v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: With the rapid accumulation of online information, efficient web navigation has grown vital yet challenging. To create an easily navigable cyberspace catering to diverse demographics, understanding how people navigate differently is paramount. While previous research has unveiled individual differences in spatial navigation, such differences in knowledge space navigation remain sparse. To bridge this gap, we conducted an online experiment where participants played a navigation game on Wikipedia and completed personal information questionnaires. Our analysis shows that age negatively affects knowledge space navigation performance, while multilingualism enhances it. Under time pressure, participants' performance improves across trials and males outperform females, an effect not observed in games without time pressure. In our experiment, successful route-finding is usually not related to abilities of innovative exploration of routes. Our results underline the importance of age, multilingualism and time constraint in the knowledge space navigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.10036v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manran Zhu, Taha Yasseri, J\'anos Kert\'esz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Graph is Worth $K$ Words: Euclideanizing Graph using Pure Transformer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.02464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.02464v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Can we model non-Euclidean graphs as pure language or even Euclidean vectors while retaining their inherent information? The non-Euclidean property have posed a long term challenge in graph modeling. Despite recent GNN and Graphformer efforts encoding graphs as Euclidean vectors, recovering original graph from the vectors remains a challenge. We introduce GraphsGPT, featuring a Graph2Seq encoder that transforms non-Euclidean graphs into learnable graph words in a Euclidean space, along with a GraphGPT decoder that reconstructs the original graph from graph words to ensure information equivalence. We pretrain GraphsGPT on 100M molecules and yield some interesting findings: (1) Pretrained Graph2Seq excels in graph representation learning, achieving state-of-the-art results on 8/9 graph classification and regression tasks. (2) Pretrained GraphGPT serves as a strong graph generator, demonstrated by its ability to perform both unconditional and conditional graph generation. (3) Graph2Seq+GraphGPT enables effective graph mixup in the Euclidean space, overcoming previously known non-Euclidean challenge. (4) Our proposed novel edge-centric GPT pretraining task is effective in graph fields, underscoring its success in both representation and generation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.02464v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhangyang Gao, Daize Dong, Cheng Tan, Jun Xia, Bozhen Hu, Stan Z. Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incorporating Higher-order Structural Information for Graph Clustering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11087v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Clustering holds profound significance in data mining. In recent years, graph convolutional network (GCN) has emerged as a powerful tool for deep clustering, integrating both graph structural information and node attributes. However, most existing methods ignore the higher-order structural information of the graph. Evidently, nodes within the same cluster can establish distant connections. Besides, recent deep clustering methods usually apply a self-supervised module to monitor the training process of their model, focusing solely on node attributes without paying attention to graph structure. In this paper, we propose a novel graph clustering network to make full use of graph structural information. To capture the higher-order structural information, we design a graph mutual infomax module, effectively maximizing mutual information between graph-level and node-level representations, and employ a trinary self-supervised module that includes modularity as a structural constraint. Our proposed model outperforms many state-of-the-art methods on various datasets, demonstrating its superiority.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11087v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>DASFAA 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Qiankun Li, Haobing Liu, Ruobing Jiang, Tingting Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
