<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI</link>
    <description>cs.SI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 05:02:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Political Ads on News and Media Websites During the 2024 U.S. Elections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02886</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02886v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Building on recent work studying content in the online advertising ecosystem, including our own prior study of political ads on the web during the 2020 U.S. elections, we analyze political ad content appearing on websites leading up to and during the 2024 U.S. elections. Crawling a set of 745 news and media websites several times from three different U.S. locations (Atlanta, Seattle, and Los Angeles), we collect a dataset of over 15000 ads, including (at least) 315 political ads, and we analyze it quantitatively and qualitatively. Among our findings: a prevalence of clickbait political news ads, echoing prior work; a seemingly new emphasis (compared to 2020) on voting safety and eligibility ads, particularly in Atlanta; and non-election related political ads around the Israel-Palestine conflict, particularly in Seattle. We join prior work in calling for more oversight and transparency of political-related ads on the web. Our dataset is available at https://ad-archive.cs.washington.edu.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02886v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emi Yoshikawa, Franziska Roesner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics and Inequalities in Digital Social Networks: A Computational and Sociological Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02887</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02887v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Digital networks have profoundly transformed the ways in which individuals interact, exchange information, and establish connections, leading to the emergence of phenomena such as virality, misinformation cascades, and online polarization. This review conducts a thorough examination of the micro-macro linkages within digital social networks, analyzing how individual actions like liking, sharing, and commenting coalesce into broader systemic patterns and how these interactions are influenced by algorithmic mediation. Utilizing a multidisciplinary literature base, this study explores the interaction among user behaviors, network structures, and platform algorithms that intensify biases, strengthen homophily, and foster echo chambers. We delve into crucial dynamics including the scalability's impact on weak tie propagation, the amplification effects on influencers, and the rise of digital inequalities, employing both theoretical and empirical approaches. By synthesizing insights from sociology, network theory, and computational social science, this paper underscores the necessity for novel frameworks that integrate algorithmic processes into established micro-macro models. The conclusion presents practical strategies aimed at promoting fairer digital networks through decentralized architectures, algorithmic fairness, and improved digital inclusion, tackling significant challenges such as polarization and misinformation within networked societies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02887v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pengjia Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Political Biases on X before the 2025 German Federal Election</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02888v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study examines whether German X users would see politically balanced news feeds if they followed comparable leading politicians from each federal parliamentary party of Germany. We address this question using an algorithmic audit tool [1] and all publicly available posts published by 436 German politicians on X. We find that the default feed of X showed more content from far-right AfD than from other political parties. We analyze potential factors influencing feed content and the resulting political non-representativeness of X. Our findings suggest that engagement measures and unknown factors related to party affiliation contribute to the overrepresentation of extremes of the German political party spectrum in the default algorithmic feed of X.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02888v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5281/zenodo.14880275</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tabia Tanzin Prama, Chhandak Bagchi, Vishal Kalakonnavar, Paul Krau{\ss}, Przemyslaw A. Grabowicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Cascade Failures in Interdependent Urban Infrastructure Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02890v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cascading failures (CF) entail component breakdowns spreading through infrastructure networks, causing system-wide collapse. Predicting CFs is of great importance for infrastructure stability and urban function. Despite extensive research on CFs in single networks such as electricity and road networks, interdependencies among diverse infrastructures remain overlooked, and capturing intra-infrastructure CF dynamics amid complex evolutions poses challenges. To address these gaps, we introduce the \textbf{I}ntegrated \textbf{I}nterdependent \textbf{I}nfrastructure CF model ($I^3$), designed to capture CF dynamics both within and across infrastructures. $I^3$ employs a dual GAE with global pooling for intra-infrastructure dynamics and a heterogeneous graph for inter-infrastructure interactions. An initial node enhancement pre-training strategy mitigates GCN-induced over-smoothing. Experiments demonstrate $I^3$ achieves a 31.94\% in terms of AUC, 18.03\% in terms of Precision, 29.17\% in terms of Recall, 22.73\% in terms of F1-score boost in predicting infrastructure failures, and a 28.52\% reduction in terms of RMSE for cascade volume forecasts compared to leading models. It accurately pinpoints phase transitions in interconnected and singular networks, rectifying biases in models tailored for singular networks. Access the code at https://github.com/tsinghua-fib-lab/Icube.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02890v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yinzhou Tang, Jinghua Piao, Huandong Wang, Shaw Rajib, Yong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metric-Based Granular Computing in Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02901v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Networks can be highly complex systems with numerous interconnected components and interactions. Granular computing offers a framework to manage this complexity by decomposing networks into smaller, more manageable components, or granules. In this article, we introduce metric-based granular computing technique to study networks. This technique can be applied to the analysis of networks where granules can represent subsets of nodes or edges and their interactions can be studied at different levels of granularity. We model the network as an information system and investigate its granular structures using metric representation. We establish that the concepts of reducts in rough set theory and resolving sets in networks are equivalent. Through this equivalence, we present a novel approach for computing all the minimal resolving sets of these networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02901v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hibba Arshad, Imran Javaid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generating Networks to Target Assortativity via Archimedean Copula Graphons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03061v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop an approach to generate random graphs to a target level of assortativity by using copula structures in graphons. Unlike existing random graph generators, we do not use rewiring or binning approaches to generate the desired random graph. Instead, we connect Archimedean bivariate copulas to graphons in order to produce flexible models that can generate random graphs to target assortativity. We propose three models that use the copula distribution function, copula density function and their mixed tensor product to produce networks. We express the assortativity coefficient in terms of homomorphism densities. Establishing this relationship forges a connection between the parameter of the copula and the frequency of subgraphs in the generated network. Therefore, our method attains a desired the subgraph distribution as well as the target assortativity. We establish the homomorphism densities and assortativity coefficient for each of the models. Numerical examples demonstrate the ability of the proposed models to produce graphs with different levels of assortativity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03061v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victory Idowu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Multimodal Framework for Topic Propagation Classification in Social Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03112v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rapid proliferation of the Internet and the widespread adoption of social networks have significantly accelerated information dissemination. However, this transformation has introduced complexities in information capture and processing, posing substantial challenges for researchers and practitioners. Predicting the dissemination of topic-related information within social networks has thus become a critical research focus. This paper proposes a predictive model for topic dissemination in social networks by integrating multidimensional features derived from key dissemination characteristics. Specifically, we introduce two novel indicators, user relationship breadth and user authority, into the PageRank algorithm to quantify user influence more effectively. Additionally, we employ a Text-CNN model for sentiment classification, extracting sentiment features from textual content. Temporal embeddings of nodes are encoded using a Bi-LSTM model to capture temporal dynamics. Furthermore, we refine the measurement of user interaction traces with topics, replacing traditional topic view metrics with a more precise communication characteristics measure. Finally, we integrate the extracted multidimensional features using a Transformer model, significantly enhancing predictive performance. Experimental results demonstrate that our proposed model outperforms traditional machine learning and unimodal deep learning models in terms of FI-Score, AUC, and Recall, validating its effectiveness in predicting topic propagation within social networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03112v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchuan Jiang, Chaolong Jia, Yunyi Qin, Wei Cai, Yongsen Qian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topo Goes Political: TDA-Based Controversy Detection in Imbalanced Reddit Political Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03500v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The detection of controversial content in political discussions on the Internet is a critical challenge in maintaining healthy digital discourse. Unlike much of the existing literature that relies on synthetically balanced data, our work preserves the natural distribution of controversial and non-controversial posts. This real-world imbalance highlights a core challenge that needs to be addressed for practical deployment. Our study re-evaluates well-established methods for detecting controversial content. We curate our own dataset focusing on the Indian political context that preserves the natural distribution of controversial content, with only 12.9% of the posts in our dataset being controversial. This disparity reflects the true imbalance in real-world political discussions and highlights a critical limitation in the existing evaluation methods. Benchmarking on datasets that model data imbalance is vital for ensuring real-world applicability. Thus, in this work, (i) we release our dataset, with an emphasis on class imbalance, that focuses on the Indian political context, (ii) we evaluate existing methods from this domain on this dataset and demonstrate their limitations in the imbalanced setting, (iii) we introduce an intuitive metric to measure a model's robustness to class imbalance, (iv) we also incorporate ideas from the domain of Topological Data Analysis, specifically Persistent Homology, to curate features that provide richer representations of the data. Furthermore, we benchmark models trained with topological features against established baselines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03500v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3701716.3717535</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Arvindh Arun, Karuna K Chandra, Akshit Sinha, Balakumar Velayutham, Jashn Arora, Manish Jain, Ponnurangam Kumaraguru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hidden memory and stochastic fluctuations in science</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03011</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03011v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding the statistical laws governing citation dynamics remains a fundamental challenge in network theory and the science of science. Citation networks typically exhibit in-degree distributions well approximated by log-normal distributions, yet they also display power-law behaviour in the high-citation regime, presenting an apparent contradiction that lacks a unified explanation. Here, we identify a previously unrecognised phenomenon: the variance of the logarithm of citation counts per unit time follows a power law with respect to time since publication, scaling as $t^{H}$. This discovery introduces a new challenge while simultaneously offering a crucial clue to resolving this discrepancy. We develop a stochastic model in which latent attention to publications evolves through a memory-driven process incorporating cumulative advantage. This process is characterised by the Hurst parameter $H$, derived from fractional Brownian motion, and volatility. Our framework reconciles this contradiction by demonstrating that anti-persistent fluctuations ($H&lt;\tfrac{1}{2}$) give rise to log-normal citation distributions, whereas persistent dynamics ($H&gt;\tfrac{1}{2}$) favour heavy-tailed power laws. Numerical simulations confirm our model's explanatory and predictive power, interpolating between log-normal and power-law distributions while reproducing the $t^{H}$ law. Empirical analysis of arXiv e-prints further supports our theory, revealing an intrinsically anti-persistent nature with an upper bound of approximately $H=0.13$. By linking memory effects and stochastic fluctuations to broader network dynamics, our findings provide a unifying framework for understanding the evolution of collective attention in science and other attention-driven processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03011v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keisuke Okamura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic block models with many communities and the Kesten--Stigum bound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03047v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the inference of communities in stochastic block models with a growing number of communities. For block models with $n$ vertices and a fixed number of communities $q$, it was predicted in Decelle et al. (2011) that there are computationally efficient algorithms for recovering the communities above the Kesten--Stigum (KS) bound and that efficient recovery is impossible below the KS bound. This conjecture has since stimulated a lot of interest, with the achievability side proven in a line of research that culminated in the work of Abbe and Sandon (2018). Conversely, recent work by Sohn and Wein (2025) provides evidence for the hardness part using the low-degree paradigm.
  In this paper we investigate community recovery in the regime $q=q_n \to \infty$ as $n\to\infty$ where no such predictions exist. We show that efficient inference of communities remains possible above the KS bound. Furthermore, we show that recovery of block models is low-degree hard below the KS bound when the number of communities satisfies $q\ll \sqrt{n}$. Perhaps surprisingly, we find that when $q \gg \sqrt{n}$, there is an efficient algorithm based on non-backtracking walks for recovery even below the KS bound. We identify a new threshold and ask if it is the threshold for efficient recovery in this regime. Finally, we show that detection is easy and identify (up to a constant) the information-theoretic threshold for community recovery as the number of communities $q$ diverges.
  Our low-degree hardness results also naturally have consequences for graphon estimation, improving results of Luo and Gao (2024).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03047v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Byron Chin, Elchanan Mossel, Youngtak Sohn, Alexander S. Wein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Policy Design for Repeated Decision-Making under Social Influence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03657v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a novel model to characterize individual tendencies in repeated decision-making scenarios, with the goal of designing model-based control strategies that promote virtuous choices amidst social and external influences. Our approach builds on the classical Friedkin and Johnsen model of social influence, extending it to include random factors (e.g., inherent variability in individual needs) and controllable external inputs. We explicitly account for the temporal separation between two processes that shape opinion dynamics: individual decision-making and social imitation. While individual decisions occur at regular, frequent intervals, the influence of social imitation unfolds over longer periods. The inclusion of random factors naturally leads to dynamics that do not converge in the classical sense. However, under specific conditions, we prove that opinions exhibit ergodic behavior. Building on this result, we propose a constrained asymptotic optimal control problem designed to foster, on average, social acceptance of a target action within a network. To address the transient dynamics of opinions, we reformulate this problem within a Model Predictive Control (MPC) framework. Simulations highlight the significance of accounting for these transient effects in steering individuals toward virtuous choices while managing policy costs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03657v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chiara Ravazzi, Valentina Breschi, Paolo Frasca, Fabrizio Dabbene, Mara Tanelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The process of polarisation as a loss of dimensionality: measuring changes in polarisation using Singular Value Decomposition of network graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18191v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we present new methods of measuring polarisation in social networks. We use Random Dot Product Graphs to embed social networks in metric spaces. Singular Value Decomposition of this social network then provider an embedded dimensionality which corresponds to the number of uncorrelated dimensions in the network. A decrease in the optimal dimensionality for the embedding of the network graph means that the dimensions in the network are becoming more correlated, and therefore the network is becoming more polarised.
  We demonstrate this method by analysing social networks such as communication interactions among New Zealand Twitter users discussing climate change issues and international social media discussions of the COP conferences. In both cases, the decreasing embedded dimensionality indicates that these networks have become more polarised over time. We also use networks generated by stochastic block models to explore how an increase of the isolation between distinct communities, or the increase of the predominance of one community over the other, in the social networks decrease the embedded dimensionality and are therefore identifiable as polarisation processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18191v3</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sage Anastasi, Giulio Dalla Riva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>More than Memes: A Multimodal Topic Modeling Approach to Conspiracy Theories on Telegram</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08642v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To address the increasing prevalence of (audio-)visual data on social media, and to capture the evolving and dynamic nature of this communication, researchers have begun to explore the potential of unsupervised approaches for analyzing multimodal online content. However, existing research often neglects visual content beyond memes, and in addition lacks methods to compare topic models across modalities. Our study addresses these gaps by applying multimodal topic modeling for analyzing conspiracy theories in German-language Telegram channels. We use BERTopic with CLIP for the analysis of textual and visual data in a corpus of ~40, 000 Telegram messages posted in October 2023 in 571 German-language Telegram channels known for disseminating conspiracy theories. Through this dataset, we provide insights into unimodal and multimodal topic models by analyzing symmetry and intersections of topics across modalities. We demonstrate the variety of textual and visual content shared in the channels discovered through the topic modeling, and propose a conceptual framework for the analysis of textual and visual discursive strategies in the communication of conspiracy theories. We apply the framework in a case study of the topic group Israel Gaza.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08642v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elisabeth Steffen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixing Time Matters: Accelerating Effective Resistance Estimation via Bidirectional Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02513v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the problem of efficiently approximating the \textit{effective resistance} (ER) on undirected graphs, where ER is a widely used node proximity measure with applications in graph spectral sparsification, multi-class graph clustering, network robustness analysis, graph machine learning, and more. Specifically, given any nodes $s$ and $t$ in an undirected graph $G$, we aim to efficiently estimate the ER value $R(s,t)$ between nodes $s$ and $t$, ensuring a small absolute error $\epsilon$. The previous best algorithm for this problem has a worst-case computational complexity of $\tilde{O}\left(\frac{L_{\max}^3}{\epsilon^2 d^2}\right)$, where the value of $L_{\max}$ depends on the mixing time of random walks on $G$, $d = \min\{d(s), d(t)\}$, and $d(s)$, $d(t)$ denote the degrees of nodes $s$ and $t$, respectively. We improve this complexity to $\tilde{O}\left(\min\left\{\frac{L_{\max}^{7/3}}{\epsilon^{2/3}}, \frac{L_{\max}^3}{\epsilon^2d^2}, mL_{\max}\right\}\right)$, achieving a theoretical improvement of $\tilde{O}\left(\max\left\{\frac{L_{\max}^{2/3}}{\epsilon^{4/3} d^2}, 1, \frac{L_{\max}^2}{\epsilon^2 d^2 m}\right\}\right)$ over previous results. Here, $m$ denotes the number of edges. Given that $L_{\max}$ is often very large in real-world networks (e.g., $L_{\max} &gt; 10^4$), our improvement on $L_{\max}$ is significant, especially for real-world networks. We also conduct extensive experiments on real-world and synthetic graph datasets to empirically demonstrate the superiority of our method. The experimental results show that our method achieves a $10\times$ to $1000\times$ speedup in running time while maintaining the same absolute error compared to baseline methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02513v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guanyu Cui, Hanzhi Wang, Zhewei Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From equality to diversity -- bottom-up approach for hierarchy growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1707.00985</link>
      <description>arXiv:1707.00985v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The hierarchical topology is a common property of many complex systems. Here we introduce a simple but generic model of hierarchy growth from the bottom to the top. Therein, two dynamical processes are accounted for: agent's promotions to next hierarchy levels when local speakers are elected and followed by other agents and agent's degradations to the lowest hierarchy. Following the initial stage when all agents are at the bottom level in the course of time the system approaches a stationary state where new hierarchies no longer emerge and the distribution of agents at different levels is exponential. In the stationary state the average hierarchy level and the fraction of agents at the lowest level are independent from the system size however the height of hierarchy, i.e. maximal number of observed hierarchy levels grows logarithmically along the total number of agents. The average number of followers of an agent in the stationary state is much smaller than the number of followers he possessed at the promotion moment. Results from numerical simulations are confirmed by an analytical treatment based on the rate equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1707.00985v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Agnieszka Czaplicka, Janusz A. Ho{\l}yst</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Epidemic-induced local awareness behavior inferred from surveys and genetic sequence data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09983v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Behavior-disease models suggest that pandemics can be contained cost-effectively if individuals take preventive actions when disease prevalence rises among their close contacts. However, assessing local awareness behavior in real-world datasets remains a challenge. Through the analysis of mutation patterns in clinical genetic sequence data, we propose an efficient approach to quantify the impact of local awareness by identifying superspreading events and assigning containment scores to them.
  We validate the proposed containment score as a proxy for local awareness in simulation experiments, and find that it was correlated positively with policy stringency during the COVID-19 pandemic. Finally, we observe a temporary drop in the containment score during the Omicron wave in the United Kingdom, matching a survey experiment we carried out in Hungary during the corresponding period of the pandemic. Our findings bring important insight into the field of awareness modeling through the analysis of large-scale genetic sequence data, one of the most promising data sources in epidemics research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09983v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gergely \'Odor, M\'arton Karsai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Human-Agent Interaction in Synthetic Social Networks: A Framework for Studying Online Polarization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01340v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Online social networks have dramatically altered the landscape of public discourse, creating both opportunities for enhanced civic participation and risks of deepening social divisions. Prevalent approaches to studying online polarization have been limited by a methodological disconnect: mathematical models excel at formal analysis but lack linguistic realism, while language model-based simulations capture natural discourse but often sacrifice analytical precision. This paper introduces an innovative computational framework that synthesizes these approaches by embedding formal opinion dynamics principles within LLM-based artificial agents, enabling both rigorous mathematical analysis and naturalistic social interactions. We validate our framework through comprehensive offline testing and experimental evaluation with 122 human participants engaging in a controlled social network environment. The results demonstrate our ability to systematically investigate polarization mechanisms while preserving ecological validity. Our findings reveal how polarized environments shape user perceptions and behavior: participants exposed to polarized discussions showed markedly increased sensitivity to emotional content and group affiliations, while perceiving reduced uncertainty in the agents' positions. By combining mathematical precision with natural language capabilities, our framework opens new avenues for investigating social media phenomena through controlled experimentation. This methodological advancement allows researchers to bridge the gap between theoretical models and empirical observations, offering unprecedented opportunities to study the causal mechanisms underlying online opinion dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01340v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Donkers, J\"urgen Ziegler</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
