<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI</link>
    <description>cs.SI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 02:37:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hawkes based Representation Learning for Reasoning over Scale-free Community-structured Temporal Knowledge Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01974v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Temporal knowledge graph (TKG) reasoning has become a hot topic due to its great value in many practical tasks. The key to TKG reasoning is modeling the structural information and evolutional patterns of the TKGs. While great efforts have been devoted to TKG reasoning, the structural and evolutional characteristics of real-world networks have not been considered. In the aspect of structure, real-world networks usually exhibit clear community structure and scale-free (long-tailed distribution) properties. In the aspect of evolution, the impact of an event decays with the time elapsing. In this paper, we propose a novel TKG reasoning model called Hawkes process-based Evolutional Representation Learning Network (HERLN), which learns structural information and evolutional patterns of a TKG simultaneously, considering the characteristics of real-world networks: community structure, scale-free and temporal decaying. First, we find communities in the input TKG to make the encoding get more similar intra-community embeddings. Second, we design a Hawkes process-based relational graph convolutional network to cope with the event impact-decaying phenomenon. Third, we design a conditional decoding method to alleviate biases towards frequent entities caused by long-tailed distribution. Experimental results show that HERLN achieves significant improvements over the state-of-the-art models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01974v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuwei Du, Xinyue Liu, Wenxin Liang, Linlin Zong, Xianchao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EvoPath: Evolutionary Meta-path Discovery with Large Language Models for Complex Heterogeneous Information Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02192v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heterogeneous Information Networks (HINs) encapsulate diverse entity and relation types, with meta-paths providing essential meta-level semantics for knowledge reasoning, although their utility is constrained by discovery challenges. While Large Language Models (LLMs) offer new prospects for meta-path discovery due to their extensive knowledge encoding and efficiency, their adaptation faces challenges such as corpora bias, lexical discrepancies, and hallucination. This paper pioneers the mitigation of these challenges by presenting EvoPath, an innovative framework that leverages LLMs to efficiently identify high-quality meta-paths. EvoPath is carefully designed, with each component aimed at addressing issues that could lead to potential knowledge conflicts. With a minimal subset of HIN facts, EvoPath iteratively generates and evolves meta-paths by dynamically replaying meta-paths in the buffer with prioritization based on their scores. Comprehensive experiments on three large, complex HINs with hundreds of relations demonstrate that our framework, EvoPath, enables LLMs to generate high-quality meta-paths through effective prompting, confirming its superior performance in HIN reasoning tasks. Further ablation studies validate the effectiveness of each module within the framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02192v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ipm.2024.103920</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shixuan Liu, Haoxiang Cheng, Yunfei Wang, Yue He, Changjun Fan, Zhong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ensemble-based Deep Multilayer Community Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multilayer graphs, consisting of multiple interconnected layers, are widely used to model diverse relationships in the real world. A community is a cohesive subgraph that offers valuable insights for analyzing (multilayer) graphs. Recently, there has been an emerging trend focused on searching query-driven communities within the multilayer graphs. However, existing methods for multilayer community search are either 1) rule-based, which suffer from structure inflexibility; or 2) learning-based, which rely on labeled data or fail to capture layer-specific characteristics. To address these, we propose EnMCS, an Ensemble-based unsupervised (i.e., label-free) Multilayer Community Search framework. EnMCS contains two key components, i.e., HoloSearch which identifies potential communities in each layer while integrating both layer-shared and layer-specific information, and EMerge which is an Expectation-Maximization (EM)-based method that synthesizes the potential communities from each layer into a consensus community. Specifically, HoloSearch first employs a graph-diffusion-based model that integrates three label-free loss functions to learn layer-specific and layer-shared representations for each node. Communities in each layer are then identified based on nodes that exhibit high similarity in layer-shared representations while demonstrating low similarity in layer-specific representations w.r.t. the query nodes. To account for the varying layer-specific characteristics of each layer when merging communities, EMerge models the error rates of layers and true community as latent variables. It then employs the EM algorithm to simultaneously minimize the error rates of layers and predict the final consensus community through iterative maximum likelihood estimation. Experiments over 10 real-world datasets highlight the superiority of EnMCS in terms of both efficiency and effectiveness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02194v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianwei Wang, Yuehai Wang, Kai Wang, Xuemin Lin, Wenjie Zhang, Ying Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making the Peers' Subjective Well-being Visible Impairs Cooperator-centered Experimental Social Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02288v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Past experiments show that reputation or the knowledge of peers' past cooperation can enhance cooperation in human social networks. On the other hand, the knowledge of peers' wealth undermines cooperativeness, and that of peers' interconnectedness and network structure does not affect it. However, it is unknown if making peers' subjective well-being (SWB) available or visible in social networks may enhance or undermine cooperation. Therefore, we implemented online network experiments (N = 662 in 50 networked groups with 15 rounds of interactions), in which study participants cooperated with or defected against connected peers through Public Goods Game, made and cut social ties with others, and rated their SWB. We manipulated the visibility of connected peers' SWB (25 visible vs. 25 invisible SWB networked groups) while keeping the connected peers' reputation and in-game wealth visible. Results show that making the peers/ SWB visible did not alter overall cooperativeness, wealth, inter-connectedness, or SWB. In contrast, the visible SWB networked groups exhibited a higher number of communities and lower transitivity (the proportion of the cases where a peer of a peer is also a peer) than the invisible SWB networked groups. These phenomena are explained by an altered decision-making pattern in the visible SWB networks: cooperators were less likely to connect with cooperators and more likely to connect with defectors, and consequently, cooperators could not maintain their popularity or stay in the center of the networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02288v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akihiro Nishi, Hiroyasu Ando, Meaghan Woody, Kamal Nayan Reddy Challa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Matching in Correlated Networks with Node Attributes for Improved Community Recovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02851v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study community detection in multiple networks whose nodes and edges are jointly correlated. This setting arises naturally in applications such as social platforms, where a shared set of users may exhibit both correlated friendship patterns and correlated attributes across different platforms. Extending the classical Stochastic Block Model (SBM) and its contextual counterpart (CSBM), we introduce the correlated CSBM, which incorporates structural and attribute correlations across graphs. To build intuition, we first analyze correlated Gaussian Mixture Models, wherein only correlated node attributes are available without edges, and identify the conditions under which an estimator minimizing the distance between attributes achieves exact matching of nodes across the two databases. For correlated CSBMs, we develop a two-step procedure that first applies $k$-core matching to most nodes using edge information, then refines the matching for the remaining unmatched nodes by leveraging their attributes with a distance-based estimator. We identify the conditions under which the algorithm recovers the exact node correspondence, enabling us to merge the correlated edges and average the correlated attributes for enhanced community detection. Crucially, by aligning and combining graphs, we identify regimes in which community detection is impossible in a single graph but becomes feasible when side information from correlated graphs is incorporated. Our results illustrate how the interplay between graph matching and community recovery can boost performance, broadening the scope of multi-graph, attribute-based community detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02851v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joonhyuk Yang, Hye Won Chung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Clustering via Community Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02036v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deep clustering is an essential task in modern artificial intelligence, aiming to partition a set of data samples into a given number of homogeneous groups (i.e., clusters). Even though many Deep Neural Network (DNN) backbones and clustering strategies have been proposed for the task, achieving increasingly improved performance, deep clustering remains very challenging due to the lack of accurately labeled samples. In this paper, we propose a novel approach of deep clustering via community detection. It initializes clustering by detecting many communities, and then gradually expands clusters by community merging. Compared with the existing clustering strategies, community detection factors in the new perspective of cluster network analysis. As a result, it has the inherent benefit of high pseudo-label purity, which is critical to the performance of self-supervision. We have validated the efficacy of the proposed approach on benchmark image datasets. Our extensive experiments have shown that it can effectively improve the SOTA performance. Our ablation study also demonstrates that the new network perspective can effectively improve community pseudo-label purity, resulting in improved clustering performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02036v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianyu Cheng, Qun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Efficient Quadratic Penalty Method for a Class of Graph Clustering Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02187</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02187v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Community-based graph clustering is one of the most popular topics in the analysis of complex social networks. This type of clustering involves grouping vertices that are considered to share more connections, whereas vertices in different groups share fewer connections. A successful clustering result forms densely connected induced subgraphs. This paper studies a specific form of graph clustering problems that can be formulated as semi-assignment problems, where the objective function exhibits block properties. We reformulate these problems as sparse-constrained optimization problems and relax them to continuous optimization models. We apply a quadratic penalty method to the relaxation problem and solve the nonlinear quadratic penalty subproblem with simple box constraints using a projected gradient method based on the active set. Extensive numerical results indicate that our method provides more accurate clustering results for solving graph clustering problems at a faster speed, both for synthetic graphs and real-world network datasets, particularly in large-scale cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02187v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenshun Teng, Qingna Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On LLM-Enhanced Mixed-Type Data Imputation with High-Order Message Passing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02191v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Missing data imputation, which aims to impute the missing values in the raw datasets to achieve the completeness of datasets, is crucial for modern data-driven models like large language models (LLMs) and has attracted increasing interest over the past decades. Despite its importance, existing solutions for missing data imputation either 1) only support numerical and categorical data or 2) show an unsatisfactory performance due to their design prioritizing text data and the lack of key properties for tabular data imputation. In this paper, we propose UnIMP, a Unified IMPutation framework that leverages LLM and high-order message passing to enhance the imputation of mixed-type data including numerical, categorical, and text data. Specifically, we first introduce a cell-oriented hypergraph to model the table. We then propose BiHMP, an efficient Bidirectional High-order Message-Passing network to aggregate global-local information and high-order relationships on the constructed hypergraph while capturing the inter-column heterogeneity and intra-column homogeneity. To effectively and efficiently align the capacity of the LLM with the information aggregated by BiHMP, we introduce Xfusion, which, together with BiHMP, acts as adapters for the LLM. We follow a pre-training and fine-tuning pipeline to train UnIMP, integrating two optimizations: chunking technique, which divides tables into smaller chunks to enhance efficiency; and progressive masking technique, which gradually adapts the model to learn more complex data patterns. Both theoretical proofs and empirical experiments on 10 real world datasets highlight the superiority of UnIMP over existing techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02191v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianwei Wang, Kai Wang, Ying Zhang, Wenjie Zhang, Xiwei Xu, Xuemin Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Keeping Score: A Quantitative Analysis of How the CHI Community Appreciates Its Milestones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02456v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The ACM CHI Conference has a tradition of citing its intellectual heritage. At the same time, we know CHI is highly diverse and evolving. In this highly dynamic context, it is not clear how the CHI community continues to appreciate its milestones (within and outside of CHI). We present an investigation into how the community's citations to milestones have evolved over 43 years of CHI Proceedings (1981-2024). Forgetting curves plotted for each year suggest that milestones are slowly fading from the CHI community's collective memory. However, the picture is more nuanced when we trace citations to the top-cited milestones over time. We identify three distinct types of milestones cited at CHI, a typology of milestone contributions, and define the Milestone Coefficient as a metric to assess the impact of milestone papers on a continuous scale. Further, we provide empirical evidence of a Matthew effect at CHI. We discuss the broader ramifications for the CHI community and the field of HCI.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02456v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Oppenlaender, Simo Hosio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning when to rank: Estimation of partial rankings from sparse, noisy comparisons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02505</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02505v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A common task arising in various domains is that of ranking items based on the outcomes of pairwise comparisons, from ranking players and teams in sports to ranking products or brands in marketing studies and recommendation systems. Statistical inference-based methods such as the Bradley-Terry model, which extract rankings based on an underlying generative model of the comparison outcomes, have emerged as flexible and powerful tools to tackle the task of ranking in empirical data. In situations with limited and/or noisy comparisons, it is often challenging to confidently distinguish the performance of different items based on the evidence available in the data. However, existing inference-based ranking methods overwhelmingly choose to assign each item to a unique rank or score, suggesting a meaningful distinction when there is none. Here, we address this problem by developing a principled Bayesian methodology for learning partial rankings -- rankings with ties -- that distinguishes among the ranks of different items only when there is sufficient evidence available in the data. Our framework is adaptable to any statistical ranking method in which the outcomes of pairwise observations depend on the ranks or scores of the items being compared. We develop a fast agglomerative algorithm to perform Maximum A Posteriori (MAP) inference of partial rankings under our framework and examine the performance of our method on a variety of real and synthetic network datasets, finding that it frequently gives a more parsimonious summary of the data than traditional ranking, particularly when observations are sparse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02505v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Morel-Balbi, Alec Kirkley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Effect of Limited Mobility on the Experienced Segregation of Foreign-born Minorities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00404v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Segregation is a key challenge in promoting more diverse and inclusive cities. Research based on large-scale mobility data indicates that segregation between majority and minority groups persists in daily activities beyond residential areas, like visiting shops and restaurants. Aspects including lifestyle differences, homophily, and mobility constraints have been proposed as drivers of this phenomenon, but their contributions remain poorly quantified. Here, we elucidate how different mechanisms influence segregation outside home, looking at the distinctive segregation experienced by native and foreign-born individuals. Our study is based on the movement of ~320,000 individual smartphone devices collected in Sweden, where immigration creates profound divides. We find that while day-to-day activities lead to mixing for native-born individuals, foreign-born individuals remain segregated in their out-of-home activities. Using counterfactual simulations, we show that this heterogeneous effect of mobility on experienced segregation results mainly from two mechanisms: homophily and limited travel, i.e. foreign-born individuals (i) tend to visit destinations visited by similar individuals, and (ii) have limited mobility ranges. We show that homophily, as represented by destination preference, plays a minor role, while limited mobility, associated with reduced transport access, limits opportunities for foreign-born minorities to diversify their encounters. Our findings suggest that enhancing transport accessibility in foreign-born concentrated areas could reduce social segregation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00404v4</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Liao, Jorge Gil, Sonia Yeh, Rafael H. M. Pereira, Laura Alessandretti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PureRank: A Parameter-Free Recursive Importance Measure for Network Nodes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00417v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: PageRank, widely used for network analysis in various fields, is a form of Katz centrality based on the recursive definition of importance (RDI). However, PageRank has a free parameter known as the damping factor, whose recommended value is 0.85, although its validity has been guaranteed theoretically or rationally. To solve this problem, we propose PureRank, a new parameter-free RDI-based importance measure. The term ``pure'' in PureRank denotes the purity of its parameter-free nature, which ensures the uniqueness of importance scores and eliminates subjective and empirical adjustments. PureRank also offers computational advantages over PageRank, such as improved parallelizability and scalability, due to the use of strongly connected component decomposition in its definition. Furthermore, we introduce the concept of splitting for networks with both positively and negatively weighted links and extend PureRank to such general networks, providing a more versatile tool for network analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00417v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroyuki Masuyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\nu$-LPA: Fast GPU-based Label Propagation Algorithm (LPA) for Community Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11468v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Community detection is the problem of identifying natural divisions in networks. Efficient parallel algorithms for identifying such divisions are critical in a number of applications. This report presents an optimized implementation of the Label Propagation Algorithm (LPA) for community detection, featuring an asynchronous LPA with a Pick-Less (PL) method every 4 iterations to handle community swaps, ideal for SIMT hardware like GPUs. It also introduces a novel per-vertex hashtable with hybrid quadratic-double probing for collision resolution. On an NVIDIA A100 GPU, our implementation, $\nu$-LPA, outperforms FLPA (sequential), NetworKit LPA (multicore), Gunrock LPA (GPU), and cuGraph Louvain (GPU) by 364x, 62x, 2.6x, and 37x, respectively, while running FLPA and NetworKit LPA on a server with dual 16-core Intel Xeon Gold 6226R processors - processing 3.0B edges/s on a 2.2B edge graph - and achieves 4.7% higher modularity than FLPA, but 6.1% and 9.6% lower than NetworKit LPA and cuGraph Louvain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11468v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhajit Sahu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
