<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI</link>
    <description>cs.SI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 04:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The most influential philosophers in Wikipedia: a multicultural analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06034v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the influence and interconnectivity of philosophical thinkers within the Wikipedia knowledge network. Using a dataset of 237 articles dedicated to philosophers across nine different language editions (Arabic, Chinese, English, French, German, Japanese, Portuguese, Russian, and Spanish), we apply the PageRank and CheiRank algorithms to analyze their relative ranking and influence in each linguistic context. Furthermore, we compare our results with entries from the Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy and the Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy, providing insight into the differences between general knowledge networks like Wikipedia and specialized philosophical databases. A key focus of our analysis is the sub-network of 21 presocratic philosophers, grouped into four traditional schools: Italic (Pythagorean + Eleatic), Ionian, Abderian (Atomist), and Sophist. Using the reduced Google matrix method, we uncover both direct and hidden links between these early thinkers, offering new perspectives on their intellectual relationships and influence within the Western philosophical tradition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06034v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillaume Rollin, Jos\'e Lages</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QuHE: Optimizing Utility-Cost in Quantum Key Distribution and Homomorphic Encryption Enabled Secure Edge Computing Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ensuring secure and efficient data processing in mobile edge computing (MEC) systems is a critical challenge. While quantum key distribution (QKD) offers unconditionally secure key exchange and homomorphic encryption (HE) enables privacy-preserving data processing, existing research fails to address the comprehensive trade-offs among QKD utility, HE security, and system costs. This paper proposes a novel framework integrating QKD, transciphering, and HE for secure and efficient MEC. QKD distributes symmetric keys, transciphering bridges symmetric encryption, and HE processes encrypted data at the server. We formulate an optimization problem balancing QKD utility, HE security, processing and wireless transmission costs. However, the formulated optimization is non-convex and NPhard. To solve it efficiently, we propose the Quantum-enhanced Homomorphic Encryption resource allocation (QuHE) algorithm. Theoretical analysis proves the proposed QuHE algorithm's convergence and optimality, and simulations demonstrate its effectiveness across multiple performance metrics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06086v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liangxin Qian, Yang Li, Jun Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical Nodes Identification in Complex Networks: A Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06164v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Complex networks have become essential tools for understanding diverse phenomena in social systems, traffic systems, biomolecular systems, and financial systems. Identifying critical nodes is a central theme in contemporary research, serving as a vital bridge between theoretical foundations and practical applications. Nevertheless, the intrinsic complexity and structural heterogeneity characterizing real-world networks, with particular emphasis on dynamic and higher-order networks, present substantial obstacles to the development of universal frameworks for critical node identification. This paper provides a comprehensive review of critical node identification techniques, categorizing them into seven main classes: centrality, critical nodes deletion problem, influence maximization, network control, artificial intelligence, higher-order and dynamic methods. Our review bridges the gaps in existing surveys by systematically classifying methods based on their methodological foundations and practical implications, and by highlighting their strengths, limitations, and applicability across different network types. Our work enhances the understanding of critical node research by identifying key challenges, such as algorithmic universality, real-time evaluation in dynamic networks, analysis of higher-order structures, and computational efficiency in large-scale networks. The structured synthesis consolidates current progress and highlights open questions, particularly in modeling temporal dynamics, advancing efficient algorithms, integrating machine learning approaches, and developing scalable and interpretable metrics for complex systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06164v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duxin Chen, Jiawen Chen, Xiaoyu Zhang, Qinghan Jia, Xiaolu Liu, Ye Sun, Linyuan Lv, Wenwu Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLMs are Introvert</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05638v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The exponential growth of social media and generative AI has transformed information dissemination, fostering connectivity but also accelerating the spread of misinformation. Understanding information propagation dynamics and developing effective control strategies is essential to mitigate harmful content. Traditional models, such as SIR, provide basic insights but inadequately capture the complexities of online interactions. Advanced methods, including attention mechanisms and graph neural networks, enhance accuracy but typically overlook user psychology and behavioral dynamics. Large language models (LLMs), with their human-like reasoning, offer new potential for simulating psychological aspects of information spread. We introduce an LLM-based simulation environment capturing agents' evolving attitudes, emotions, and responses. Initial experiments, however, revealed significant gaps between LLM-generated behaviors and authentic human dynamics, especially in stance detection and psychological realism. A detailed evaluation through Social Information Processing Theory identified major discrepancies in goal-setting and feedback evaluation, stemming from the lack of emotional processing in standard LLM training. To address these issues, we propose the Social Information Processing-based Chain of Thought (SIP-CoT) mechanism enhanced by emotion-guided memory. This method improves the interpretation of social cues, personalization of goals, and evaluation of feedback. Experimental results confirm that SIP-CoT-enhanced LLM agents more effectively process social information, demonstrating behaviors, attitudes, and emotions closer to real human interactions. In summary, this research highlights critical limitations in current LLM-based propagation simulations and demonstrates how integrating SIP-CoT and emotional memory significantly enhances the social intelligence and realism of LLM agents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05638v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Litian Zhang, Xiaoming Zhang, Bingyu Yan, Ziyi Zhou, Bo Zhang, Zhenyu Guan, Xi Zhang, Chaozhuo Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identity isn't everything -- how far do demographics take us towards self-identified party ID?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06193</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06193v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: How well do demographics explain party identification? Demographics are related to party identification in political polls, news articles, and academic publications. Yet, there is a diversity of party identification even within demographic groups which have historically been attached to one party. And some groups lack a clear connection to either party. It may be that demographics on their own fail to account for the fact that people generally belong to a variety of groups. They must select the groups which are most important to them when shaping a political identity, and may choose to construct an identity relatively unattached to any specific demographic group to which they belong. This prompts the question, do we need to consider measures of identity strength when using demographics to explain party identification? We utilize a predictive framework to address these questions and find that demographics are highly predictive for some groups (e.g., Black Democrats), while others benefit from the inclusion of identity strength (e.g., Hispanic Republicans).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06193v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sabina Tomkins, David Rothschild, Alex Liu, Alexander Thompson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Nexus of AR/VR, AI, UI/UX, and Robotics Technologies in Enhancing Learning and Social Interaction for Children with Autism Spectrum Disorders: A Systematic Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18162v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The emergence of large language models (LLMs), augmented reality (AR), and user interface/user experience (UI/UX) design in therapies for children, especially with disorders like autism spectrum disorder (ASD), is studied in detail in this review study. 150 publications were collected by a thorough literature search throughout PubMed, ACM, IEEE Xplore, Elsevier, and Google Scholar; 60 of them were chosen based on their methodological rigor and relevance to the focus area. Three of the primary areas are studied and covered in this review: how AR can improve social and learning results, how LLMs can support communication, and how UI/UX design affects how effective these technologies can be. Results show that while LLMs can provide individualized learning and communication support, AR has shown promise in enhancing social skills, motivation, and attention. For children with ASD, accessible and engaging interventions rely heavily on effective UI/UX design, but there is still a significant lack of robotics-based education and therapeutic programs specifically tailored for autistic children. To optimize the benefits of these technologies in ASD therapies and immersive education, the study emphasizes the need for additional research to address difficulties related to customization, accessibility, and integration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18162v3</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Biplov Paneru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seeing Sarcasm Through Different Eyes: Analyzing Multimodal Sarcasm Perception in Large Vision-Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12149v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: With the advent of large vision-language models (LVLMs) demonstrating increasingly human-like abilities, a pivotal question emerges: do different LVLMs interpret multimodal sarcasm differently, and can a single model grasp sarcasm from multiple perspectives like humans? To explore this, we introduce an analytical framework using systematically designed prompts on existing multimodal sarcasm datasets. Evaluating 12 state-of-the-art LVLMs over 2,409 samples, we examine interpretive variations within and across models, focusing on confidence levels, alignment with dataset labels, and recognition of ambiguous "neutral" cases. Our findings reveal notable discrepancies -- across LVLMs and within the same model under varied prompts. While classification-oriented prompts yield higher internal consistency, models diverge markedly when tasked with interpretive reasoning. These results challenge binary labeling paradigms by highlighting sarcasm's subjectivity. We advocate moving beyond rigid annotation schemes toward multi-perspective, uncertainty-aware modeling, offering deeper insights into multimodal sarcasm comprehension. Our code and data are available at: https://github.com/CoderChen01/LVLMSarcasmAnalysis</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12149v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junjie Chen, Xuyang Liu, Subin Huang, Linfeng Zhang, Hang Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
