<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI</link>
    <description>cs.SI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Link Prediction and Navigability of Multiplex Energy Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In modern energy networks, where operational efficiency and resilience are critical, this study introduces an in-depth analysis from a multiplex network perspective - defined as a network where multiple types of connections exist between the same set of nodes. Utilizing Belgium's electricity and gas networks, we construct a five-layer multiplex network to simulate random node shutdown scenarios. We tailored the Jaccard and Adamic-Adar link prediction algorithms by integrating the concept of exclusive neighbors, thereby enhancing prediction accuracy with such multi-layered information. Emphasizing navigability, i.e., the network's ability to maintain resilience and efficiency under random failures, we analyze the impact of different random walk strategies and strategic link additions at various stages - individual layers, two-layer combinations, and three-layer combinations - on the network's navigability. Directed networks show modest improvements with new links, partly due to trapping effects, where a random walker can become circumscribed within certain network loops, limiting reachability across the network. In contrast, the undirected networks demonstrate notable increases in navigability with new link additions. Spectral gap analysis in directed networks indicates that new link additions can aid and impede navigability, depending on their configuration. This study deepens our understanding of multiplex energy network navigability and highlights the importance of strategic link additions influenced by random walk strategies in these networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14641v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Kazim, Harun Pirim, Chau Le, Trung Le, Om Prakash Yadav</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of COVID-19 Misinformation: An Analysis of Conspiracy Theories, Fake Remedies, and False Reports</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14765v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper makes four scientific contributions to the area of misinformation detection and analysis on digital platforms, with a specific focus on investigating how conspiracy theories, fake remedies, and false reports emerge, propagate, and shape public perceptions in the context of COVID-19. A dataset of 5,614 posts on the internet that contained misinformation about COVID-19 was used for this study. These posts were published in 2020 on 427 online sources (such as social media platforms, news channels, and online blogs) from 193 countries and in 49 languages. First, this paper presents a structured, three-tier analytical framework that investigates how multiple motives - including fear, politics, and profit - can lead to a misleading claim. Second, it emphasizes the importance of narrative structures, systematically identifying and quantifying the thematic elements that drive conspiracy theories, fake remedies, and false reports. Third, it presents a comprehensive analysis of different sources of misinformation, highlighting the varied roles played by individuals, state-based organizations, media outlets, and other sources. Finally, it discusses multiple potential implications of these findings for public policy and health communication, illustrating how insights gained from motive, narrative, and source analyses can guide more targeted interventions in the context of misinformation detection on digital platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14765v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nirmalya Thakur, Mingchen Shao, Victoria Knieling, Vanessa Su, Andrew Bian, Hongseok Jeong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VIKI: Systematic Cross-Platform Profile Inference of Online Users</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14772v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: What can we learn about online users by comparing their profiles across different platforms? We use the term profile to represent displayed personality traits, interests, and behavioral patterns (e.g., offensiveness). We also use the term {\it displayed personas} to refer to the personas that users manifest on a platform. Though individuals have a single real persona, it is not difficult to imagine that people can behave differently in different ``contexts'' as it happens in real life (e.g., behavior in office, bar, football game). The vast majority of previous studies have focused on profiling users on a single platform. Here, we propose VIKI, a systematic methodology for extracting and integrating the displayed personas of users across different social platforms. First, we extract multiple types of information, including displayed personality traits, interests, and offensiveness. Second, we evaluate, combine, and introduce methods to summarize and visualize cross-platform profiles. Finally, we evaluate VIKI on a dataset that spans three platforms -- GitHub, LinkedIn, and X. Our experiments show that displayed personas change significantly across platforms, with over 78% of users exhibiting a significant change. For instance, we find that neuroticism exhibits the largest absolute change. We also identify significant correlations between offensive behavior and displayed personality traits. Overall, we consider VIKI as an essential building block for systematic and nuanced profiling of users across platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14772v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Treves, Emiliano De Cristofaro, Yue Dong, Michalis Faloutsos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Coupled Friedkin-Johnsen Model of Popularity Dynamics in Social Media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15170v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Popularity dynamics in social media depend on a complex interplay of social influence between users and popularity-based recommendations that are provided by the platforms. In this work, we introduce a discrete-time dynamical system to model the evolution of popularity on social media. Our model generalizes the well-known Friedkin-Johnsen model to a set of influencers vying for popularity. We study the asymptotic behavior of this model and illustrate it with numerical examples. Our results highlight the interplay of social influence, past popularity, and content quality in determining the popularity of influencers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15170v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gaya Cocca, Paolo Frasca, Chiara Ravazzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network Analytics for Anti-Money Laundering -- A Systematic Literature Review and Experimental Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19383v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Money laundering presents a pervasive challenge, burdening society by financing illegal activities. The use of network information is increasingly being explored to more effectively combat money laundering, given it involves connected parties. This led to a surge in research on network analytics (NA) for anti-money laundering (AML). The literature on NA for AML is, however, fragmented and a comprehensive overview of existing work is missing. This results in limited understanding of the methods to apply and their comparative detection power. Therefore, this paper presents an extensive and unique literature review, based on 97 papers from Web of Science and Scopus, resulting in a taxonomy following a recently proposed fraud analytics framework. We conclude that most research relies on expert-based rules and manual features, while deep learning methods have been gaining traction. This paper also presents a comprehensive framework to evaluate and compare the performance of prominent NA methods in a standardized setup. We apply it on two publicly available data sets, comparing manual feature engineering, random walk-based, and deep learning methods. We conclude that (1) network analytics increases the predictive power, but caution is needed when applying GNNs based on the class imbalance and network topology, and that (2) care should be taken with open-source data as this can give overly optimistic results. The open-source implementation facilitates researchers and practitioners to extend upon the results and experiment on proprietary data, promoting a standardized approach for the analysis and evaluation of network analytics for AML.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19383v3</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Deprez, Toon Vanderschueren, Bart Baesens, Tim Verdonck, Wouter Verbeke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating shocking events in the Ethereum stablecoin ecosystem through temporal multilayer graph structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10614v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the dynamic landscape of the Web, we are witnessing the emergence of the Web3 paradigm, which dictates that platforms should rely on blockchain technology and cryptocurrencies to sustain themselves and their profitability. Cryptocurrencies are characterised by high market volatility and susceptibility to substantial crashes, issues that require temporal analysis methodologies able to tackle the high temporal resolution, heterogeneity and scale of blockchain data. While existing research attempts to analyse crash events, fundamental questions persist regarding the optimal time scale for analysis, differentiation between long-term and short-term trends, and the identification and characterisation of shock events within these decentralised systems. This paper addresses these issues by examining cryptocurrencies traded on the Ethereum blockchain, with a spotlight on the crash of the stablecoin TerraUSD and the currency LUNA designed to stabilise it. Utilising complex network analysis and a multi-layer temporal graph allows the study of the correlations between the layers representing the currencies and system evolution across diverse time scales. The investigation sheds light on the strong interconnections among stablecoins pre-crash and the significant post-crash transformations. We identify anomalous signals before, during, and after the collapse, emphasising their impact on graph structure metrics and user movement across layers. This paper pioneers temporal, cross-chain graph analysis to explore a cryptocurrency collapse. It emphasises the importance of temporal analysis for studies on web-derived data and how graph-based analysis can enhance traditional econometric results. Overall, this research carries implications beyond its field, for example for regulatory agencies aiming to safeguard users from shocks and monitor investment risks for citizens and clients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10614v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ACM Transactions on Web 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cheick Tidiane Ba, Richard G. Clegg, Ben A. Steer, Matteo Zignani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Guide to Misinformation Detection Data and Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05060v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Misinformation is a complex societal issue, and mitigating solutions are difficult to create due to data deficiencies. To address this, we have curated the largest collection of (mis)information datasets in the literature, totaling 75. From these, we evaluated the quality of 36 datasets that consist of statements or claims, as well as the 9 datasets that consist of data in purely paragraph form. We assess these datasets to identify those with solid foundations for empirical work and those with flaws that could result in misleading and non-generalizable results, such as spurious correlations, or examples that are ambiguous or otherwise impossible to assess for veracity. We find the latter issue is particularly severe and affects most datasets in the literature. We further provide state-of-the-art baselines on all these datasets, but show that regardless of label quality, categorical labels may no longer give an accurate evaluation of detection model performance. Finally, we we propose and highlight Evaluation Quality Assessment (EQA) as a tool to guide the field toward systemic solutions rather than inadvertently propagating issues in evaluation. Overall, this guide aims to provide a roadmap for higher quality data and better grounded evaluations, ultimately improving research in misinformation detection. All datasets and other artifacts are available at misinfo-datasets.complexdatalab.com.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05060v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Camille Thibault, Jacob-Junqi Tian, Gabrielle Peloquin-Skulski, Taylor Lynn Curtis, James Zhou, Florence Laflamme, Yuxiang Guan, Reihaneh Rabbany, Jean-Fran\c{c}ois Godbout, Kellin Pelrine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scam Detection for Ethereum Smart Contracts: Leveraging Graph Representation Learning for Secure Blockchain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12370v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As more and more attacks have been detected on Ethereum smart contracts, it has seriously affected finance and credibility. Current anti-fraud detection techniques, including code parsing or manual feature extraction, still have some shortcomings, although some generalization or adaptability can be obtained. In the face of this situation, this paper proposes to use graphical representation learning technology to find transaction patterns and distinguish malicious transaction contracts, that is, to represent Ethereum transaction data as graphs, and then use advanced ML technology to obtain reliable and accurate results. Taking into account the sample imbalance, we treated with SMOTE-ENN and tested several models, in which MLP performed better than GCN, but the exact effect depends on its field trials. Our research opens up more possibilities for trust and security in the Ethereum ecosystem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12370v5</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihong Jin, Ze Yang, Xinhe Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
