<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI</link>
    <description>cs.SI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:35:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Individual Fairness in Community Detection: Quantitative Measure and Comparative Evaluation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16326v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Community detection is a fundamental task in complex network analysis. Fairness-aware community detection seeks to prevent biased node partitions, typically framed in terms of individual fairness, which requires similar nodes to be treated similarly, and group fairness, which aims to avoid disadvantaging specific groups of nodes. While existing literature on fair community detection has primarily focused on group fairness, we introduce a novel measure to quantify individual fairness in community detection methods. The proposed measure captures unfairness as the vectorial distance between a node's true and predicted community representations, computed using the community co-occurrence matrix. We provide a comprehensive empirical investigation of a broad set of community detection algorithms from the literature on both synthetic networks, with varying levels of community explicitness, and real-world networks. We particularly investigate the fairness-performance trade-off using standard quality metrics and compare individual fairness outcomes with existing group fairness measures. The results show that individual unfairness can occur even when group fairness or clustering accuracy is high, underscoring that individual and group fairness are not interchangeable. Moreover, fairness depends critically on the detectability of community structure. However, we find that Significance and Surprise for denser graphs, and Combo, Leiden, and SBMDL for sparser graphs result in a better trade-off between individual fairness and community quality. Overall, our findings, together with the fact that community detection is an important step in many network analysis downstream tasks, highlight the necessity of developing fairness-aware community detection methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16326v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrizio Corriera, Frank W. Takes, Akrati Saxena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing Approximate Pareto Frontiers for Submodular Utility and Cost Tradeoffs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15964</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15964v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In many data-mining applications, including recommender systems, influence maximization, and team formation, the goal is to pick a subset of elements (e.g., items, nodes in a network, experts to perform a task) to maximize a monotone submodular utility function while simultaneously minimizing a cost function. Classical formulations model this tradeoff via cardinality or knapsack constraints, or by combining utility and cost into a single weighted objective. However, such approaches require committing to a specific tradeoff in advance and return only a single solution, offering limited insight into the space of viable utility-cost tradeoffs. In this paper, we depart from the single-solution paradigm and examine the problem of computing representative sets of high-quality solutions that expose different tradeoffs between submodular utility and cost. For this, we introduce $(\alpha_1,\alpha_2)$-approximate Pareto frontiers that provably approximate the achievable tradeoffs between submodular utility and cost. Specifically, we formalize the Pareto-$\langle f,c \rangle$ problem and develop efficient algorithms for multiple instantiations arising from different combinations of submodular utility $f$ and cost functions $c$. Our results offer a principled and practical framework for understanding and exploiting utility-cost tradeoffs in submodular optimization. Experiments on datasets from diverse application domains demonstrate that our algorithms efficiently compute approximate Pareto frontiers in practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15964v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karan Vombatkere, Evimaria Terzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Trust and Liquidity Under Payment System Stress: A Multi-Agent Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16186v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Operational disruptions in retail payments can induce behavioral responses that outlast technical recovery and may amplify liquidity stress. We propose a multi-agent model linking card payment outages to trust dynamics, channel avoidance, and threshold-gated withdrawals. Customers and merchants interact through repeated payment attempts, while customers additionally influence one another on a Watts-Strogatz small-world network. Customers update bounded memory variables capturing accumulated negative experience (scar) and perceived systemic risk (rumor), with merchants contributing persistent broadcast signals that may lag operational recovery. We prove that, under mild conditions on memory persistence and threshold gating, aggregate withdrawal pressure can peak strictly after the outage nadir, including during the recovery phase. Simulations reproduce behavioral hysteresis and confirm delayed peaks of outflows. We further study payment substitution via instant transfer: substitution consistently reduces peak avoidance, yet its effect on cumulative outflows is non-monotonic under realistic merchant broadcast persistence. Robustness experiments across random seeds show stable qualitative behavior. The model highlights why "status green" is not equivalent to risk resolution and motivates incident response strategies that address perception, merchant messaging, and post-recovery communication in addition to technical remediation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16186v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masoud Amouzgar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Human Behavior in a Strategic Network Game with Complex Group Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03795v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Human networks greatly impact important societal outcomes, including wealth and health inequality, poverty, and bullying. As such, understanding human networks is critical to learning how to promote favorable societal outcomes. As a step toward better understanding human networks, we compare and contrast several methods for learning models of human behavior in a strategic network game called the Junior High Game (JHG) [39]. These modeling methods differ with respect to the assumptions they use to parameterize human behavior (behavior matching vs. community-aware behavior) and the moments they model (mean vs. distribution). Results show that the highest-performing method, called hCAB, models the distribution of human behavior rather than the mean and assumes humans use community-aware behavior rather than behavior matching. When applied to small societies, the hCAB model closely mirrors the population dynamics of human groups (with notable differences). Additionally, in a user study, human participants had difficulty distinguishing hCAB agents from other humans, thus illustrating that the hCAB model also produces plausible (individual) behavior in this strategic network game.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03795v3</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.65109/NQKD4743</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Skaggs, Jacob W. Crandall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overcoming Non-Submodularity: Towards Constant Approximation for Network Immunization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19205v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given a network with an ongoing epidemic, the network immunization problem seeks to identify a fixed number of nodes to immunize in order to maximize the number of infections prevented. A fundamental computational challenge in network immunization is that the objective function is generally neither submodular nor supermodular. Consequently, no efficient algorithm is known to consistently achieve a constant-factor approximation. Traditionally, this problem is partially addressed using proxy objectives that offer better approximation properties, but these indirect optimizations often introduce losses in effectiveness due to gaps between the proxy and natural objectives.
  In this paper, we overcome these fundamental barriers by leveraging the underlying stochastic structure of the diffusion process. Similar to the traditional influence objective, the immunization objective is an expectation expressed as a sum over deterministic instances. However, unlike the former, some of these terms are not submodular. Our key step is to prove that this sum has a bounded deviation from submodularity, enabling the classic greedy algorithm to achieve a constant-factor approximation for any sparse cascading network. We demonstrate that this approximation holds across various immunization settings and spread models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19205v5</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ajitesh Srivastava, Shang-Hua Teng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VIRENA: Virtual Arena for Research, Education, and Democratic Innovation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12207v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Digital platforms shape how people communicate, deliberate, and form opinions. Studying these dynamics has become increasingly difficult due to restricted data access, ethical constraints on real-world experiments, and limitations of existing research tools. VIRENA (Virtual Arena) is a platform that enables controlled experimentation in realistic social media environments. Multiple participants interact simultaneously in realistic replicas of feed-based platforms (Instagram, Facebook, Reddit) and messaging apps (WhatsApp, Messenger). Large language model-powered AI agents participate alongside humans with configurable personas and realistic behavior. Researchers can manipulate content moderation approaches, pre-schedule stimulus content, and run experiments across conditions through a visual interface requiring no programming skills. VIRENA makes possible research designs that were previously impractical: studying human--AI interaction in realistic social contexts, experimentally comparing moderation interventions, and observing group deliberation as it unfolds. Built on open-source technologies that ensure data remain under institutional control and comply with data protection requirements, VIRENA is currently in use at the University of Zurich and available for pilot collaborations. Designed for researchers, educators, and public organizations alike, VIRENA's no-code interface makes controlled social media simulation accessible across disciplines and sectors. This paper documents its design, architecture, and capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12207v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emma Hoes, K. Jonathan Klueser, Fabrizio Gilardi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
