<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SI updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI</link>
    <description>cs.SI updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SI" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 05:45:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Grok in the Wild: Characterizing the Roles and Uses of Large Language Models on Social Media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11286v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: xAI's large language model, Grok, is called by millions of people each week on the social media platform X. Prior work characterizing how large language models are used has focused on private, one-on-one interactions. Grok's deployment on X represents a major departure from this setting, with interactions occurring in a public social space. In this paper, we systematically sample three months of interaction data to investigate how, when, and to what effect Grok is used on X. At the platform level, we find that Grok responds to 62% of requests, that the majority (51%) are in English, and that engagement is low, with half of Grok's responses receiving 20 or fewer views after 48 hours. We also inductively build a taxonomy of 10 roles that LLMs play in mediating social interactions and use these roles to analyze 41,735 interactions with Grok on X. We find that Grok most often serves as an information provider but, in contrast to LLM use in private one-on-one settings, also takes on roles related to dispute management, such as truth arbiter, advocate, and adversary. Finally, we characterize the population of X users who prompted Grok and find that their self-expressed interests are closely related to the roles the model assumes in the corresponding interactions. Our findings provide an initial quantitative description of human-AI interactions on X, and a broader understanding of the diverse roles that large language models might play in our online social spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11286v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katelyn Xiaoying Mei, Robert Wolfe, Nicholas Weber, Martin Saveski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing Network Outbreaks under Group Surveillance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11419v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A key public health problem during an outbreak is to reconstruct the disease cascade from a partial set of confirmed infections. This has been studied extensively under the Maximum Likelihood Estimation (MLE) formulation, which reduces the problem to finding some type of Steiner subgraph on a network. Group surveillance like wastewater or aerosol monitoring is a form of mass/pooled testing where samples from multiple individuals are pooled together and tested once for all. While a single negative test clears multiple individuals, a positive test does not reveal the infected individuals in the test pool. We introduce the POOLCASCADEMLE problem in the setting of a network propagation process, where the goal is to find a MLE cascade subgraph which is consistent with the pooled test outcomes. Previous work on reconstruction assumes that the test results are of individuals, i.e., pools of size one, and requires a consistent cascade to connect the positive testing nodes. In POOLCASCADEMLE, a consistent cascade must choose at least one node in each positive pool, adding another combinatorial layer. We show that, under the Independent Cascade (IC) model, POOLCASCADEMLE is NP-hard, and present an approximation algorithm based on a reduction to the Group Steiner Tree problem. We also consider a one-hop version of this problem, in which the disease can spread for one time step after being seeded. We show that even this restricted version is NP-hard, and develop a method using linear programming relaxation and rounding. We evaluate the performance of our methods on real and synthetic contact networks, in terms of missing infection recovery and prevalence estimation. We find that our approach outperforms meaningful baselines which correspond to pools of size one and use state-of-the-art methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11419v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ritwick Mishra, Abhijin Adiga, Anil Vullikanti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing edge weights in the inverse eigenvector centrality problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.11772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.11772v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we study the inverse eigenvector centrality problem on directed graphs: given a prescribed node centrality profile, we seek edge weights that realize it. Since this inverse problem generally admits infinitely many solutions, we explicitly characterize the feasible set of admissible weights and introduce six optimization problems defined over this set, each corresponding to a different weight-selection strategy. These formulations provide representative solutions of the inverse problem and enable a systematic comparison of how different strategies influence the structure of the resulting weighted networks. We illustrate our framework using several real-world social network datasets, showing that different strategies produce different weighted graph structures while preserving the prescribed centrality. The results highlight the flexibility of the proposed approach and its potential applications in network reconstruction, and network design or network manipulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.11772v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mauro Passacantando, Fabio Raciti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making the complete OpenAIRE citation graph easily accessible through compact data representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12206v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The OpenAIRE graph contains a large citation graph dataset, with over 200 million publications and over 2 billion citations. The current graph is available as a dump with metadata which uncompressed totals ~TB. This makes it hard to process on conventional computers. To make this network more available for the community we provide a processed OpenAIRE graph which is downscaled to 32GB, while preserving the full graph structure. Apart from this we offer the processed data in very simple format, which allows further straightforward manipulation. We also provide a python pipeline, which can be used to process the next releases of the OpenAIRE graph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12206v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joakim Skarding, Pavel Sanda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>VIRENA: Virtual Arena for Research, Education, and Democratic Innovation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12207</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12207v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Digital platforms shape how people communicate, deliberate, and form opinions. Studying these dynamics has become increasingly difficult due to restricted data access, ethical constraints on real-world experiments, and limitations of existing research tools. VIRENA (Virtual Arena) is a platform that enables controlled experimentation in realistic social media environments. Multiple participants interact simultaneously in realistic replicas of feed-based platforms (Instagram, Facebook, Reddit) and messaging apps (WhatsApp, Messenger). Large language model-powered AI agents participate alongside humans with configurable personas and realistic behavior. Researchers can manipulate content moderation approaches, pre-schedule stimulus content, and run experiments across conditions through a visual interface requiring no programming skills. VIRENA makes possible research designs that were previously impractical: studying human--AI interaction in realistic social contexts, experimentally comparing moderation interventions, and observing group deliberation as it unfolds. Built on open-source technologies that ensure data remain under institutional control and comply with data protection requirements, VIRENA is currently in use at the University of Zurich and available for pilot collaborations. Designed for researchers, educators, and public organizations alike, VIRENA's no-code interface makes controlled social media simulation accessible across disciplines and sectors. This paper documents its design, architecture, and capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12207v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emma Hoes, K. Jonathan Klueser, Fabrizio Gilardi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Community Concealment from Unsupervised Graph Learning-Based Clustering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.12250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.12250v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Graph neural networks (GNNs) are designed to use attributed graphs to learn representations. Such representations are beneficial in the unsupervised learning of clusters and community detection. Nonetheless, such inference may reveal sensitive groups, clustered systems, or collective behaviors, raising concerns regarding group-level privacy. Community attribution in social and critical infrastructure networks, for example, can expose coordinated asset groups, operational hierarchies, and system dependencies that could be used for profiling or intelligence gathering. We study a defensive setting in which a data publisher (defender) seeks to conceal a community of interest while making limited, utility-aware changes in the network. Our analysis indicates that community concealment is strongly influenced by two quantifiable factors: connectivity at the community boundary and feature similarity between the protected community and adjacent communities. Informed by these findings, we present a perturbation strategy that rewires a set of selected edges and modifies node features to reduce the distinctiveness leveraged by GNN message passing. The proposed method outperforms DICE in our experiments on synthetic benchmarks and real network graphs under identical perturbation budgets. Overall, it achieves median relative concealment improvements of approximately 20-45% across the evaluated settings. These findings demonstrate a mitigation strategy against GNN-based community learning and highlight group-level privacy risks intrinsic to graph learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.12250v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dalyapraz Manatova, Pablo Moriano, L. Jean Camp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How segmented is my network?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.10125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.10125v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Network segmentation is a popular security practice for limiting lateral movement, yet practitioners lack a metric to measure how segmented a network actually is. We introduce the first statistically principled metric for network segmentedness based on global edge density, enabling practitioners to quantify what has previously been assessed only qualitatively. Then, we derive a normalized estimator for segmentedness and evaluate its uncertainty using confidence intervals. For a 95\% confidence interval with a margin-of-error of $\pm 0.1$, we show that a minimum of $M=97$ sampled node pairs is sufficient. This result is independent of the total number of nodes in the network, provided that node pairs are sampled uniformly at random. We evaluate the estimator through Monte Carlo simulations on Erd\H{o}s--R\'enyi, stochastic block models, and real-world enterprise network datasets, demonstrating accurate estimation and well-behaved coverage. Finally, we discuss applications of the estimator, such as baseline tracking, zero trust assessment, and merger integration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.10125v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rohit Dube</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
