<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 04:00:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 09 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Delayed parabolic regularity for curve shortening flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04049v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given two curves bounding a region of area $A$ that evolve under curve shortening flow, we propose the principle that the regularity of one should be controllable in terms of the regularity of the other, starting from time $A/\pi$. We prove several results of this form and demonstrate that no estimate can hold before that time. As an example application, we construct solutions to graphical curve shortening flow starting with initial data that is merely an $L^1$ function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04049v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arjun Sobnack, Peter M. Topping</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One-dimensional inelastic Boltzmann equation: Stability and uniqueness of self-similar $L^{1}$-profiles for moderately hard potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04069v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the stability of $L^{1}$ self-similar profiles under the hard-to-Maxwell potential limit
  for the one-dimensional inelastic Boltzmann equation with moderately hard potentials which, in
  turn, leads to the uniqueness of such profiles for hard potentials collision kernels of the form $|\cdot|^{\gamma}$
  with $\gamma &gt;0$ sufficiently small (explicitly quantified). Our result provides the first
  uniqueness statement for self-similar profiles of inelastic
  Boltzmann models allowing for strong inelasticity besides the
  explicitly solvable case of Maxwell interactions (corresponding to
  $\gamma=0$). Our approach relies on a perturbation argument from the
  corresponding Maxwell model and a careful study of the
  associated linearized operator recently derived in the companion paper \cite{maxwel}. The results can be seen as a
  first step towards a complete proof, in the one-dimensional setting, of
  a conjecture in \cite{ernst} regarding the determination of the
  long-time behaviour of solutions to inelastic Boltzmann equation, at least, in a regime of moderately hard potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04069v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Alonso, V. Bagland, J. A. Ca\~nizo, B. Lods, S. Throm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Piecewise constant profiles minimizing total variation energies of Kobayashi-Warren-Carter type with fidelity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04228v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a total variation type energy which measures the jump discontinuities different from usual total variation energy. Such a type of energy is obtained as a singular limit of the Kobayashi-Warren-Carter energy with minimization with respect to the order parameter. We consider the Rudin-Osher-Fatemi type energy by replacing relaxation term by this type of total variation energy. We show that all minimizers are piecewise constant if the data is continuous in one-dimensional setting. Moreover, the number of jumps is bounded by an explicit constant involving a constant related to the fidelity. This is quite different from conventional Rudin-Osher-Fatemi energy where a minimizer must have no jump if the data has no jumps. The existence of a minimizer is guaranteed in multi-dimensional setting when the data is bounded.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04228v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshikazu Giga, Ayato Kubo, Hirotoshi Kuroda, Jun Okamoto, Koya Sakakibara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global large strong solutions to the compressible Navier-Stokes equations with density-dependent viscosities, case I: isentropic flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04305v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the Cauchy problem for the three-dimensional barotropic compressible Navier-Stokes equations with density-dependent viscosities. By considering the system as an elliptic-dominated structure and defining suitable energy functionals, after the elaborate index analysis, we establish the global existence of strong solutions as long as the initial data is large enough. This is a big contrast to the classical results where the initial data is a small perturbation of some resting states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04305v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangdi Huang, Jiaxu Li, Rong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vorticity blowup in compressible Euler equations in $\mathbb{R}^d, d \geq 3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04319v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove finite-time vorticity blowup in the compressible Euler equations in $\mathbb{R}^d$ for any $d \geq 3$, starting from smooth, localized, and non-vacuous initial data. This is achieved by lifting the vorticity blowup result from [CCSV24] in $\mathbb{R}^2$ to $\mathbb{R}^d$ and utilizing the axisymmetry in $\mathbb{R}^d$. At the time of the first singularity, both vorticity blowup and implosion occur on a sphere $S^{d-2}$. Additionally, the solution exhibits a non-radial implosion, accompanied by a stable swirl velocity that is sufficiently strong to initially dominate the non-radial components and to generate the vorticity blowup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04319v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiajie Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On $N$-Euclidean Logarithmic Moser-Trudinger-Onofri inequality and some geometrical variants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04335v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we consider the $N$-dimensional Euclidean Onofri inequality proved by del Pino and Dolbeault for smooth compactly supported functions in $\mathbb{R}^N$, $N \geq 2$. We extend the inequality to a suitable weighted Sobolev space, although no clear connection with standard Sobolev spaces on $\mathbb{S}^N$ through stereographic projection is present, except for the planar case. Moreover, in any dimension $N \geq 2$, we show that the Euclidean Onofri inequality is equivalent to the logarithmic Moser-Trudinger inequality with sharp constant proved by Carleson and Chang for balls in $\mathbb{R}^N$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04335v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Natalino Borgia, Silvia Cingolani, Gabriele Mancini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extensions of divergence-free fields in $\mathrm{L}^{1}$-based function spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04513v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish the first extension results for divergence-free (or solenoidal) elements of $\mathrm{L}^{1}$-based function spaces. Here, the key point is to preserve the solenoidality constraint while simultaneously keeping the underlying $\mathrm{L}^{1}$-boundedness. While previous results as in Kato et al. [Extension and representation of divergence-free vector fields on bounded domains, Math. Res. Lett., 2000] for $\mathrm{L}^{p}$-based function spaces, $1&lt;p&lt;\infty$, rely on PDE approaches, basic principles from harmonic analysis rule out such strategies in the $\mathrm{L}^{1}$-context. By means of a novel method adapted to the divergence-free constraint via differential forms, we establish the existence of such extension operators in the $\mathrm{L}^{1}$-based situation. This applies both to the case of convex domains, where a global extensions can be achieved, as well as to the Lipschitz case, where a local extension can be achieved. Being applicable to $1&lt;p&lt;\infty$ too, our method provides a unifying approach to the cases $p\in\{1,\infty\}$ and $1&lt;p&lt;\infty$. Specifically, covering the exponents $p\in\{1,\infty\}$, this answers a borderline case left open by Kato et al. [Extension and representation of divergence-free vector fields on bounded domains, Math. Res. Lett., 2000] in the affirmative. By use of explicit examples, the assumptions on the underlying domains are shown to be almost optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04513v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Franz Gmeineder, Stefan Schiffer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local and global existence for the stochastic Prandtl equation driven by multiplicative noises in two and three dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04546v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we are concerned with the local and global existence for the stochastic Prandtl equation in two and three dimensions, which governs the velocity field inside the boundary layer that appears in the inviscid limit of the stochastic Navier-Stokes equation with non-slip boundary condition. New problem arises when establishing the well-posedness in the stochastic regime: one can never derive a pathwise control of the energy functional which is used to describe the analytic radius of the solution in the deterministic setting. To this end, we establish higher-order estimates in the conormal Sobolev spaces in order to get rid of the dependence of the analytic radius on the unknown. Three approximate schemes are constructed for solving the stochastic Prandtl equation, and a local well-posedness is obtained in a tangentially analytic and normally Sobolev-type space. Furthermore, we study the stochastic Prandtl equation driven by a tangential random diffusion, and find that the noise regularizes the equation in the sense that in both two and three dimensions, there exists a global Gevrey-2 solution with high probability and the radius growing linearly in time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04546v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ya-Guang Wang, Meng Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compact embedding from variable-order Sobolev space to $L^{q(x)}(\Omega)$ and its application to Choquard equation with variable order and variable critical exponent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04602v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove the compact embedding from the variable-order Sobolev space $W^{s(x,y),p(x,y)}_0 (\Omega)$ to the Nakano space $L^{q(x)}(\Omega)$ with a critical exponent $q(x)$ satisfying some conditions. It is noteworthy that the embedding can be compact even when $q(x)$ reaches the critical Sobolev exponent $p_s^*(x)$. As an application, we obtain a nontrivial solution of the Choquard equation \begin{equation*} \displaystyle (-\Delta)_{p(\cdot,\cdot)}^{s(\cdot,\cdot)}u+|u|^{p(x,x)-2}u=\left(\int_{\Omega}\frac{|u(y)|^{r(y)}}{|x-y|^{\frac{\alpha(x)+\alpha(y)}{2}}}dy\right) |u(x)|^{r(x)-2}u(x)\quad\text{in $\Omega$} \end{equation*} with variable upper critical exponent in the sense of Hardy-Littlewood-Sobolev inequality under an appropriate boundary condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04602v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaki Sakuma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative Convergence of Quadratically Regularized Linear Programs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04088v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Linear programs with quadratic regularization are attracting renewed interest due to their applications in optimal transport: unlike entropic regularization, the squared-norm penalty gives rise to sparse approximations of optimal transport couplings. It is well known that the solution of a quadratically regularized linear program over any polytope converges stationarily to the minimal-norm solution of the linear program when the regularization parameter tends to zero. However, that result is merely qualitative. Our main result quantifies the convergence by specifying the exact threshold for the regularization parameter, after which the regularized solution also solves the linear program. Moreover, we bound the suboptimality of the regularized solution before the threshold. These results are complemented by a convergence rate for the regime of large regularization. We apply our general results to the setting of optimal transport, where we shed light on how the threshold and suboptimality depend on the number of data points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04088v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Gonz\'alez-Sanz, Marcel Nutz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A semigroup approach to the reconstruction theorem and the multilevel Schauder estimate for singular modelled distributions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04322v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend the semigroup approach used in [19, 17] to provide shorter proofs of the reconstruction theorem and the multilevel Schauder estimate for singular modelled distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04322v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masato Hoshino, Ryoji Takano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An existence and uniqueness theory to stochastic partial differential equations involving pseudo-differential operators driven by space-time white noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04529v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we aim to develop a new weak formulation that ensures well-posedness for a broad range of stochastic partial differential equations with pseudo-differential operators whose symbols depend only on time and spatial frequencies. The main focus of this paper is to relax the conditions on the symbols of pseudo-differential operators and data while still ensuring that the stochastic partial differential equations remain well-posed in a weak sense. Specifically, we allow symbols to be random and remove all regularity and ellipticity conditions on them. As a result, our main operators include many interesting rough operators that cannot generate any regularity gain or integrability improvement from the equations. In addition, our data do not need to be regular or possess finite stochastic moments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04529v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jae-Hwan Choi, Ildoo Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double b-fibrations and desingularization of the X-ray transform on manifolds with strictly convex boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.14904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.14904v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the mapping properties of the X-ray transform and its adjoint on spaces of conormal functions on Riemannian manifolds with strictly convex boundary. After desingularizing the double fibration, and expressing the X-ray transform and its adjoint using b-fibrations operations, we employ tools related to Melrose's Pushforward Theorem to describe the mapping properties of these operators on various classes of polyhomogeneous functions, with special focus to computing how leading order coefficients are transformed. The appendix explains that a na\"ive use of the Pushforward Theorem leads to a suboptimal result with non-sharp index sets. Our improved results are obtained by closely inspecting Mellin functions which arise in the process, showing that certain coefficients vanish. This recovers some sharp results known by other methods. A number of consequences for the mapping properties of the X-ray transform and its normal operator(s) follow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.14904v5</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5802/jep.266</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal de l'Ecole Polytechnique - Mathematiques, Vol. 11 (2024), pp. 809-947</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rafe Mazzeo, Fran\c{c}ois Monard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On existence of minimizers for weighted $L^p$-Hardy inequalities on $C^{1,\gamma}$-domains with compact boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.03527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.03527v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $p \in (1,\infty)$, $\alpha\in \mathbb{R}$, and $\Omega\subsetneq \mathbb{R}^N$ be a $C^{1,\gamma}$-domain with a compact boundary $\partial \Omega$, where $\gamma\in (0,1]$. Denote by $\delta_{\Omega}(x)$ the distance of a point $x\in \Omega$ to $\partial \Omega$. Let $\widetilde{W}^{1,p;\alpha}_0(\Omega)$ be the closure of $C_c^{\infty}(\Omega)$ in $\widetilde{W}^{1,p;\alpha}(\Omega)$, where
  $$\widetilde{W}^{1,p;\alpha}(\Omega):= \left\{\varphi \in {W}^{1,p}_{\mathrm{loc}} (\Omega) \mid \left( \| \, |\nabla \varphi \, |\|_{L^p(\Omega;\delta_{\Omega}^{-\alpha})}^p + \|\varphi\|_{L^p(\Omega;\delta_{\Omega}^{-(\alpha+p)})}^p\right)&lt;\infty \!\right\}.$$
  We study the following two variational constants: the weighted Hardy constant \begin{align*}
  H_{\alpha,p}(\Omega): =\!\inf \left\{\int_{\Omega} |\nabla \varphi|^p \delta_{\Omega}^{-\alpha} \mathrm{d}x \biggm| \int_{\Omega} |\varphi|^p \delta_{\Omega}^{-(\alpha+p)} \mathrm{d}x\!=\!1, \varphi \in \widetilde{W}^{1,p;\alpha}_0(\Omega) \right\} , \end{align*}
  and the weighted Hardy constant at infinity \begin{align*} \lambda_{\alpha,p}^{\infty}(\Omega) :=\sup_{K\Subset \Omega}\,
  \inf_{W^{1,p}_{c}(\Omega\setminus K)} \left\{\int_{\Omega\setminus K} |\nabla \varphi|^p \delta_{\Omega}^{-\alpha} \mathrm{d}x \biggm| \int_{\Omega\setminus K} |\varphi|^p \delta_{\Omega}^{-(\alpha+p)} \mathrm{d}x=1 \right\}. \end{align*} We show that $H_{\alpha,p}(\Omega)$ is attained if and only if the spectral gap $\Gamma_{\alpha,p}(\Omega):= \lambda_{\alpha,p}^{\infty}(\Omega)-H_{\alpha,p}(\Omega)$ is strictly positive. Moreover, we obtain tight decay estimates for the corresponding minimizers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.03527v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ujjal Das, Yehuda Pinchover, Baptiste Devyver</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global existence and optimal time-decay rates of the compressible Navier-Stokes-Euler system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.17420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.17420v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the Cauchy problem of the multi-dimensional compressible Navier-Stokes-Euler system for two-phase flow motion, which consists of the isentropic compressible Navier-Stokes equations and the isothermal compressible Euler equations coupled with each other through a relaxation drag force. We first establish the local existence and uniqueness of the strong solution for general initial data in a critical homogeneous Besov space, and then prove the global existence of the solution if the initial data is a small perturbation of the equilibrium state. Moreover, under the additional condition that the low-frequency part of the initial perturbation also belongs to another Besov space with lower regularity, we obtain the optimal time-decay rates of the global solution toward the equilibrium state. These results imply that the relaxation drag force and the viscosity dissipation affect regularity properties and long time behaviors of solutions for the compressible Navier-Stokes-Euler system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.17420v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hai-Liang Li, Ling-Yun Shou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy decay of some multi-term nonlocal-in-time Moore--Gibson--Thompson equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07750</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.07750v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper aims to explore the long-term behavior of some nonlocal high-order-in-time wave equations. These equations, which have come to be known as Moore--Gibson--Thompson equations, arise in the context of acoustic wave propagation when taking into account thermal relaxation mechanisms in complex media such as human tissue. While the long-term behavior of linear local-in-time acoustic equations is well understood, their nonlocal counterparts still retain many mysteries. We establish here a set of assumptions that ensures exponential decay of the energy of the system. These assumptions are then shown to be verified by a large class of rapidly decaying memory kernels. Under weaker assumptions on the kernel we show that one may still obtain that the energy vanishes but without a rate of convergence. Furthermore, we refine previous results on the local well-posedness of the studied equation and establish a necessary initial-data compatibility condition for the solvability of the problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.07750v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mostafa Meliani, Belkacem Said-Houari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Propagating terrace in a two-tubes model of gravitational fingering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05981v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a semi-discrete model for the two-dimensional incompressible porous medium (IPM) equation describing gravitational fingering phenomenon. The model consists of a system of advection-reaction-diffusion equations on concentration, velocity and pressure, describing motion of miscible liquids under the Darcy's law in two vertical tubes (real lines) and interflow between them. Our analysis reveals the structure of gravitational fingers in this simple setting - the mixing zone consists of space-time regions of constant intermediate concentrations and the profile of propagation is characterized by two consecutive traveling waves which we call a terrace. We prove the existence of such a propagating terrace for the parameters corresponding to small distances between the tubes. This solution shows the possible mechanism of slowing down the fingers' growth due to convection in the transversal direction. The main tool in the proof is a reduction to pressure-free transverse flow equilibrium (TFE) model using geometrical singular perturbation theory and the persistence of stable and unstable manifolds under small perturbations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05981v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yulia Petrova, Sergey Tikhomirov, Yalchin Efendiev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear nonlocal potential theory at the gradient level</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04809v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The aim of this work is to establish numerous interrelated gradient estimates in the nonlinear nonlocal setting. First of all, we prove that weak solutions to a class of homogeneous nonlinear nonlocal equations of possibly arbitrarily low order have H\"{o}lder continuous gradients. Using these estimates in the homogeneous case, we then prove sharp higher differentiability as well as pointwise gradient potential estimates for nonlinear nonlocal equations of order larger than one in the presence of general measure data. Our pointwise estimates imply that the first-order regularity properties of such nonlinear nonlocal equations coincide with the sharp ones of the fractional Laplacian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04809v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lars Diening, Kyeongbae Kim, Ho-Sik Lee, Simon Nowak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-order asymptotic profiles of solutions to the Cauchy problem for the convection-diffusion equation with variable diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00896v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the asymptotic behavior of solutions to the convection-diffusion equation: \[ \partial_t u - \mathrm{div}\left(a(x)\nabla u\right) = d\cdot\nabla \left(\left\lvert u\right\rvert ^{q-1}u\right),\ \ x\in\mathbb{R}^n, \ t&gt;0 \] with an integrable initial data $u_{0}(x)$, where $n\ge1$, $q&gt;1+\frac{1}{n}$ and $d\in \mathbb{R}^{n}$. Moreover, we take $a(x)=1+b(x)&gt;0$, where $b(x)$ is smooth and decays fast enough at spatial infinity. It is known that the asymptotic profile of the solution to this problem can be given by the heat kernel. Moreover, some higher-order asymptotic expansions of the solution have already been studied. In particular, the structures of the second asymptotic profiles strongly depend on the nonlinear exponent $q$. More precisely, these profiles have different decay orders in each of the following three cases: $1+\frac{1}{n}&lt;q&lt;1+\frac{2}{n}$; $q=1+\frac{2}{n}$; $q&gt;1+\frac{2}{n}$. In this paper, we focus on the critical case $q=1+\frac{2}{n}$. By analyzing the corresponding integral equation in details, we have succeeded to give the more higher-order asymptotic expansion of the solution, which generalizes the previous works.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00896v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ikki Fukuda, Shinya Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrating the probe and singular sources methods: III. Mixed obstacle case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21612v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The main purpose of this paper is to develop further the integrated theory of the probe and singular sources methods (IPS) which may work for a group of inverse obstacle problems. Here as a representative and typical member of the group, an inverse obstacle problem governed by the Helmholtz equation with a fixed wave number in a bounded domain is considered. It is assumed that the solutions of the Helmholtz equation outside the set of unknown obstacles satisfy the homogeneous Dirichlet or Neumann boundary conditions on each surface of obstacles. This is the case when two extreme types of obstacles are embedded in a medium. By considering this case, not only a concise technique for IPS is introduced but also a general correspondence principle from IPS to the probe method is suggested. Besides, as a corollary it is shown that the probe method together with the singular sources method reformulated in terms of the probe method has the Side B under a smallness conditions on the wave number $k$, which is the blowing up property of a sequence computed from the associated Dirichlet-to-Neumann map.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21612v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaru Ikehata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The well-posedness and scattering theory of nonlinear Schr\"odinger equations on lattice graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01174v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a novel first-order derivative for functions on a lattice graph, which extends the discrete Laplacian and generalizes the theory of discrete PDEs on the lattices. First, we establish the well-posedness of generalized quasilinear Schr\"odinger equations and give a new proof of the global well-posedness of semilinear Schr\"odinger equations. Then we provide explicit expressions of higher order derivatives of the solution map and prove the analytic dependence between solution and initial data. At the end, we show the existence of wave operator and give a sufficient condition for the asymptotic completeness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01174v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiajun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gray and black solitons of nonlocal Gross-Pitaevskii equations: existence, monotonicity and nonlocal-to-local limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03870v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article investigates the qualitative aspects of dark solitons of one-dimensional Gross-Pitaevskii equations with general nonlocal interactions, which correspond to traveling waves with subsonic speeds. Under general conditions on the potential interaction term, we provide uniform bounds, demonstrate the existence of symmetric solitons, and identify conditions under which monotonicity is lost. Additionally, we present new properties of black solitons. Moreover, we establish the nonlocal-to-local convergence, i.e. the convergence of the soliton of the nonlocal model toward the explicit dark solitons of the local Gross-Pitaevskii equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03870v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'e de Laire, Salvador L\'opez-Mart\'inez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drift Control of High-Dimensional RBM: A Computational Method Based on Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.11651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.11651v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by applications in queueing theory, we consider a stochastic control problem whose state space is the $d$-dimensional positive orthant. The controlled process $Z$ evolves as a reflected Brownian motion whose covariance matrix is exogenously specified, as are its directions of reflection from the orthant's boundary surfaces. A system manager chooses a drift vector $\theta(t)$ at each time $t$ based on the history of $Z$, and the cost rate at time $t$ depends on both $Z(t)$ and $\theta(t)$. In our initial problem formulation, the objective is to minimize expected discounted cost over an infinite planning horizon, after which we treat the corresponding ergodic control problem. Extending earlier work by Han et al. (Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 2018, 8505-8510), we develop and illustrate a simulation-based computational method that relies heavily on deep neural network technology. For test problems studied thus far, our method is accurate to within a fraction of one percent, and is computationally feasible in dimensions up to at least $d=30$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.11651v4</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baris Ata, J. Michael Harrison, Nian Si</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bernstein theorems for nonlinear geometric PDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11903v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this expository article we revisit the Bernstein problem for several geometric PDEs including the minimal surface, Monge-Amp\`{e}re, and special Lagrangian equations. We also discuss the minimal surface system where appropriate. The article is based on a lecture series given by the author for the inaugural European Doctorate School of Differential Geometry, held in Granada in June 2024.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11903v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Connor Mooney</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
