<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 04:00:33 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An Expanding Self-Similar Vortex Configuration for the 2D Euler Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18220v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper addresses the long-time dynamics of solutions to the 2D incompressible Euler equations. We construct solutions with continuous vorticity $\omega_{\varepsilon}(x,t)$ concentrated around points $\xi_{j}(t)$ that converge to a sum of Dirac delta masses as $\varepsilon\to0$. These solutions are associated with the Kirchhoff-Routh point-vortex system, and the points $\xi_{j}(t)$ follow an expanding self similar trajectory of spirals, with the support of the vorticities contained in balls of radius $3\varepsilon$ around each $\xi_{j}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18220v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan D\'avila, Manuel del Pino, Monica Musso, Shrish Parmeshwar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic extensions of constrained PDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18286</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18286v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Systems of PDEs comprised of a combination of constraints and evolution equations are ubiquitous in physics. For both theoretical and practical reasons, such as numerical integration, it is desirable to have a systematic understanding of the well-posedness of the Cauchy problem for these systems. Presently we review the use of hyperbolic reductions, in which the evolution equations are singled out for consideration. We then examine in greater detail the extensions, in which constraints are evolved as auxiliary variables alongside the original variables. Assuming a particular structure of the original system, we give sufficient conditions for strong-hyperbolicity of an extension. This theory is then applied to the examples of electromagnetism and a toy for magnetohydrodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18286v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Abalos, Oscar Reula, David Hilditch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniformly Elliptic Equations on Domains with Capacity Density Conditions: Existence of H\"{o}lder Continuous Solutions and Homogenization Results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18327v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This is a progress report on study of uniformly elliptic Poisson-type equations on domains with capacity density conditions (CDC domains). We give a brief summary of known facts of CDC domains, including Hardy's inequality, and review a previous work of existence of globally H\"{o}lder continuous solutions. Additionally, we apply the result to homogenization problems of $\epsilon$-periodic coefficients and present a convergence rate estimate of $L^{\infty}$ norms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18327v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takanobu Hara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sobolev interpolation inequalities with optimal Hardy-Rellich inequalities and critical exponents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18335v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a new family of the critical higher order Sobolev interpolation inequalities for radial functions as well as for non-radial functions. These Sobolev interpolation inequalities are sharp in the sense that they use the optimal quadratic forms of the sharp Hardy-Rellich inequalities and cover the Sobolev critical exponents. Our results extend those studied by Dietze and Nam in [15] for the first order derivative case to higher order setting. The well-known P\'{o}lya-Szeg\"{o} symmetrization principle and the nonlinear ground state representation play an important role in the work of [15]. To overcome the absence of the P\'{o}lya-Szeg\"{o} principle and the nonlinear ground state representation in the higher order case, our proofs rely on the Fourier analysis and a higher order verion of the Talenti comparison principle. We also study a new version of the critical Hardy-Sobolev interpolation inequality involving the critical quadratic form of the Hardy inequality and Lorentz norms. Our critical Hardy-Sobolev interpolation inequality complements the result of Dietze and Nam in [15].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18335v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nguyen Anh Dao, Anh Xuan Do, Nguyen Lam, Guozhen Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On topological solutions to a generalized Chern-Simons equation on lattice graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18407v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study a generalized self-dual Chern-Simons equation on the lattice graph $\mathbb{Z}^n$ for $n \geq 2$ as given by
  \[
  \Delta u = \lambda e^u (e^u - 1)^{2p+1} + 4\pi \sum_{j=1}^M n_j \delta_{p_j},
  \]
  where $\Delta$ denotes the Laplacian operator, $\lambda$ is a positive constant, $p$ is a non-negative integer, $n_1, \ldots, n_M$ are positive integers, and $p_1, \ldots, p_M$ are distinct points with $\delta_{p_j}$ representing the Dirac delta function at $p_j$. We establish the existence of a topological solution that is maximal among all possible solutions. Our findings extend those of of Hua et al. [arXiv:2310.13905], Chao and Hou [J. Math. Anal. Appl. $\bf{519}$(1), 126787(2023)], and Hou and Qiao [J. Math. Phys. $\bf{65}$(8), 081503(2024)].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18407v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Songbo Hou, Xiaoqing Kong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parabolic-scalings on large-time behavior of the incompressible Navier--Stokes flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18452v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Through the asymptotic expansion, large-time behavior of incompressible Navier--Stokes flow in $n$-dimensional whole space is drawn. Especially, from their parabolic-scalings, large-time behaviors of any terms on the expansion are clarified. The parabolic-scalings also guarantee uniqueness of the expansion. In the preceding works, the expansion up to $n$-th order was derived yet. They also predicted that the flow has some logarithmic evolutions in higher order decay. In this paper, asymtptotic expansion with $2n$-th order is presented. Furthermore, the logarithmic evolutions in flow are discovered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18452v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masakazu Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Kato's Square Root Property for the Generalized Stokes Operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18787</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18787v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish the Kato square root property for the generalized Stokes operator on $\mathbb{R}^d$ with bounded measurable coefficients. More precisely, we identify the domain of the square root of $Au := - \operatorname{div}(\mu \nabla u) + \nabla \phi$, $\operatorname{div}(u) = 0$, with the space of divergence-free $\mathrm{H}^1$-vector fields and further prove the estimate $\|A^{1/2} u \|_{\mathrm{L}^2} \simeq \| \nabla u \|_{\mathrm{L}^2}$. As an application we show that $A^{1/2}$ depends holomorphically on the coefficients $\mu$. Besides the boundedness and measurablility as well as an ellipticity condition on $\mu$, there are no requirements on the coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18787v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Haardt, Patrick Tolksdorf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional $p$-Laplacians via Neumann problems in unbounded metric measure spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18883v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove well-posedness, Harnack inequality and sharp regularity of solutions to a fractional $p$-Laplace non-homogeneous equation $(-\Delta_p)^su =f$, with $0&lt;s&lt;1$, $1&lt;p&lt;\infty$, for data $f$ satisfying a weighted $L^{p'}$ condition in a doubling metric measure space $(Z,d_Z,\nu)$ that is possibly unbounded. Our approach is inspired by the work of Caffarelli and Silvestre \cite{CS} (see also Mol{\v{c}}anov and Ostrovski{\u{i}} \cite{MO}), and extends the techniques developed in
  \cite{CKKSS}, where the bounded case is studied. Unlike in \cite{EbGKSS}, we do not assume that $Z$ supports a Poincar\'e inequality. The proof is based on the well-posedness of the Neumann problem on a Gromov hyperbolic space $(X,d_X, \mu)$ that arises as an hyperbolic filling of $Z$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18883v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Capogna, Ryan Gibara, Riikka Korte, Nageswari Shanmugalingam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A geometric characterization of steady laminar flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18946v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the steady states of the Euler equations on the periodic channel or annulus. We show that if these flows are laminar (layered by closed non-contractible streamlines which foliate the domain), then they must be either parallel or circular flows. We also show that a large subset of these shear flows are isolated from non-shear stationary states. For Poiseuille flow, $(v(y),0)=(y^2,0)$, our result shows that all stationary solutions in a sufficiently small $C^2$ neighborhood are shear flows. We then show that if $v(y)=y^n$ with $n \geq 1$, then in any $C^{n-}$ neighborhood, there exist smooth non-shear steady states, traveling waves, and quasiperiodic solutions of any number of non-commensurate frequencies. This proves the rigidity near Poiseuille is sharp. Finally, we prove that on general compact doubly connected domains, laminar steady Euler flows with constant velocity on the boundary must also be either parallel or circular, and the domain a periodic channel or an annulus. This shows that laminar free boundary Euler solutions must have Euclidean symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18946v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Theodore D. Drivas, Marc Nualart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice Approximations to NLS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18949v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove that solutions of the discrete NLS lattice model for $L^2$ initial data with double frequency components converge to solutions of a coupled system of cubic NLS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18949v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhimeng Ouyang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Zero Inertia Limit for the Q-Tensor Model of Liquid Crystals: Analysis and Numerics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18328v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The goal of this work is to rigorously study the zero inertia limit for the Q-tensor model of liquid crystals. Though present in the original derivation of the Ericksen-Leslie equations for nematic liquid crystals, the inertia term of the model is often neglected in analysis and applications. We show wellposedness of the model including inertia and then show using the relative entropy method that solutions of the model with inertia converge to solutions of the model without inertia at a rate ${\sigma}$ in $L^\infty(0,T;H^1(\dom))$, where $\sigma$ is the inertial constant. Furthermore, we present an energy stable finite element scheme that is stable and convergent for all $\sigma$ and study the zero inertia limit numerically. We also present error estimates for the fully discrete scheme with respect to the discretization parameters in time and space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18328v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Hirsch, Franziska Weber, Yukun Yue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuum limit of resonances for discrete Schr\"{o}dinger operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18480v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider complex resonances for discrete and continuous Schr\"odinger operators, and we show that the resonances of discrete models converge to resonances of continuous models in the continuum limit. The potential is supposed to be a sum of an exterior dilation analytic function and an exponentially decaying function, which may have local singularities. The proof employs a generalization of the norm resolvent convergence of discrete Schr\"odinger operators by Nakamura and Tadano (2021), combined with the complex distortion method in the Fourier space. Our results confirm that the complex resonances can be approximately computed using discrete Schr\"odinger operators. We also give a recipe for the construction of approximate discrete operators for Schr\"odinger operators with singular potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18480v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kentaro Kameoka, Shu Nakamura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Torsional Rigidity on Metric Graphs with Delta-Vertex Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18545v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the torsion function or landscape function and its integral, the torsional rigidity, of Laplacians on metric graphs subject to $\delta$-vertex conditions. A variational characterization of torsional rigidity and Hadamard-type formulas are obtained, enabling the derivation of surgical principles. We use these principles to prove upper and lower bounds on the torsional rigidity and identify graphs maximizing and minimizing torsional rigidity among classes of graphs. We also investigate the question of positivity of the torsion function and reduce it to positivity of the spectrum of a particular discrete, weighted Laplacian. Additionally, we explore potential manifestations of Kohler-Jobin-type inequalities in the context of $\delta$-vertex conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18545v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sedef \"Ozcan, Matthias T\"aufer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heat kernel estimates for nonlocal kinetic operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18614v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we employ probabilistic techniques to derive sharp, explicit two-sided estimates for the heat kernel of the nonlocal kinetic operator $$ \Delta^{\alpha/2}_v + v \cdot \nabla_x, \quad \alpha \in (0, 2),\ (x,v)\in {\mathbb R}^{d}\times{\mathbb R}^d,$$ where $ \Delta^{\alpha/2}_v $ represents the fractional Laplacian acting on the velocity variable $v$. Additionally, we establish logarithmic gradient estimates with respect to both the spatial variable $x$ and the velocity variable $v$. In fact, the estimates are developed for more general non-symmetric stable-like operators, demonstrating explicit dependence on the lower and upper bounds of the kernel functions. These results, in particular, provide a solution to a fundamental problem in the study of \emph{nonlocal} kinetic operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18614v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haojie Hou, Xicheng Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the mean-field limit of diffusive games through the master equation: extreme value analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18869v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider an $N$-player game where the players control the drifts of their diffusive states which have no interaction in the noise terms. The aim of each player is to minimize the expected value of her cost, which is a function of the player's state and the empirical measure of the states of all the players. Our aim is to determine the $N \to \infty$ asymptotic behavior of the upper order statistics of the player's states under Nash equilibrium (the Nash states). For this purpose, we consider also a system of interacting diffusions which is constructed by using the Master PDE of the game and approximates the system of the Nash states, and we improve an $L^2$ estimate for the distance between the drifts of the two systems which has been used for establishing Central Limit Theorems and Large Deviations Principles for the Nash states in the past. By differentiating the Master PDE, we obtain that estimate also in $L^{\infty}$, which allows us to control the Radon-Nikodym derivative of a Girsanov transformation that connects the two systems. The latter allows us to reduce the problem to the case of $N$ uncontrolled diffusions with standard mean-field interaction in the drifts, which has been treated in a previous work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18869v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erhan Bayraktar, Nikolaos Kolliopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well-Posedness and regularity properties of 2d $\beta$-plane stochastic Navier-Stokes equations in a periodic channel</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.03209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.03209v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the 2d $\beta$-plane stochastic Navier-Stokes equations in a periodic channel. We prove the well-posedness and existence of the stationary measure, as well as certain regularity estimates concerning the support of the stationary measure. The mentioned estimates are crucial for the rigorous study of the cascade phenomena in this equation [8]. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first mathematically rigorous treatment of these equations involving both the stochastic noise and the Coriolis force.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.03209v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuri Cacchio', Amirali Hannani, Gigliola Staffilani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Propagation of chaos and hydrodynamic description for topological models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.00998</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.00998v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we study the deterministic Cucker-Smale model with topological interaction. Focusing on the solutions of the corresponding Liouville equation, we show that propagation of chaos holds. Moreover, considering monokinetic solutions, we also obtain a rigorous derivation of the hydrodynamic description given by a pressureless Euler-type system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.00998v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dario Benedetto, Thierry Paul, Stefano Rossi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Navier-Stokes equations on manifolds with boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.01221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.01221v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the motion of an incompressible viscous fluid on a compact Riemannian manifold $\sM$ with boundary. The motion on $\sM$ is modeled by the incompressible Navier-Stokes equations, and the fluid is subject to pure or partial slip boundary conditions of Navier type on $\partial\sM$. We establish existence and uniqueness of strong as well as weak (variational) solutions for initial data in critical spaces. Moreover, we show that the set of equilibria consists of Killing vector fields on $\sM$ that satisfy corresponding boundary conditions, and we prove that all equilibria are (locally) stable. In case $\sM$ is two-dimensional we show that solutions with divergence free initial condition in $L_2(\sM; T\sM)$ exist globally and converge to an equilibrium exponentially fast.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.01221v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuanzhen Shao, Gieri Simonett, Mathias Wilke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniqueness, regularity and characteristic flow for a non strictly convex singular variational problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.01849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.01849v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work addresses the question of uniqueness and regularity of the minimizers of a convex but not strictly convex integral functional with linear growth in a two-dimensional setting. The integrand -- whose precise form derives directly from the theory of perfect plasticity -- behaves quadratically close to the origin and grows linearly once a specific threshold is reached. Thus, in contrast with the only existing literature on uniqueness for functionals with linear growth, that is that which pertains to the generalized least gradient, the integrand is not a norm. We make use of hyperbolic {conservation} laws hidden in the structure of the problem to tackle uniqueness. Our argument strongly relies on the regularity of a vector field -- the Cauchy stress in the terminology of perfect plasticity -- which allows us to define characteristic lines, and then to employ the method of characteristics. Using the detailed structure of the characteristic landscape evidenced in our preliminary study \cite{BF}, we show that this vector field is actually continuous, save for possibly two points. The different behaviors of the energy density at zero and at infinity imply an inequality constraint on the Cauchy stress. Under a {barrier type} convexity assumption on the set where the inequality constraint is saturated, we show that uniqueness holds for pure Dirichlet boundary data devoid of any regularity properties, a stronger result than that of uniqueness for a given trace on the whole boundary since our minimizers can fail to attain the boundary data. We also show a partial regularity result for the minimizer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.01849v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Francois Babadjian, Gilles Francfort</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence theorems for the steady-state Navier-Stokes equations with nonhomogeneous slip boundary conditions in two-dimensional multiply-connected bounded domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00164v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the nonhomogeneous boundary value problem for the steady-state Navier-Stokes equations under the slip boundary conditions in two-dimensional multiply-connected bounded domains. Employing the approach of Korobkov-Pileckas-Russo (Ann. Math. 181(2), 769-807, 2015), we prove that this problem has a solution if the friction coefficient is sufficiently large compared with the kinematic viscosity constant and the curvature of the boundary. No additional assumption (other than the necessary requirement of zero total flux through the boundary) is imposed on the boundary data. We also show that such an assumption on the friction coefficient is redundant for the existence of a solution in the case when the fluxes across each connected component of the boundary are sufficiently small, or the domain and the given data satisfy certain symmetry conditions. The crucial ingredient of our proof is the fact that the total head pressure corresponding to the solution to the steady Euler equations takes a constant value on each connected component of the boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00164v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni P. Galdi, Tatsuki Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $L^p$ estimate for the gain term of the Boltzmann collision operator and its application</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05517v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the Hardy-Littlewood-Sobolev type $L^p$ estimates for the gain term of the Boltzmann collision operator including Maxwellian molecule, hard potential and hard sphere models. Combining with the results of Alonso et al. [2] for the soft potential and Maxwellian molecule models, we provide an unified form of $L^p$ estimates for all cutoff models which are sharp in the sense of scaling. The most striking feature of our new estimates for the hard potential and hard sphere models is that they do not increase the moment, the same as Maxwellian molecule and soft potential models. Based on these novelties, we prove the global existence and scattering of the non-negative unique mild solution for the Cauchy problem of the Boltzmann equation when the positive initial data is small in the weighted $L^3_{x,v}$ space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05517v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ling-Bing He, Jin-Cheng Jiang, Hung-Wen Kuo, Meng-Hao Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stress solution of static linear elasticity with mixed boundary conditions via adjoint linear operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04320v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit stress problems in linear elasticity to provide a perspective from the geometrical and functionalanalytic points of view. For the static stress problem of linear elasticity with mixed boundary conditions we write the associated pair of unbounded adjoint operators. The stress solution is found as an intersection of affine translations of the fundamental subspaces of the adjoint operators. In particular, we treat the equilibrium equation in the operator form, involving spaces of traces on a part of the boundary, known as Lions-Magenes spaces. Our analysis of the pair of adjoint operators for the problem with mixed boundary conditions relies on the properties of the analogous pair of operators for the problem with the displacement boundary conditions, which we also include in the paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04320v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jmaa.2024.128986</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Gudoshnikov, Michal K\v{r}\'i\v{z}ek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extremizers for the Strichartz Inequality for a Fourth-Order Schr\"odinger Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.06695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.06695v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the Strichartz inequality for a fourth-order Schr\"odinger equation on $\mathbb{R}^{2+1}$. We show that extremizers exist using a linear profile decomposition which follows from the endpoint version decomposition and the stationary phase method. Based on the existence of extremizers, we investigate the associated Euler-Lagrange equation to show that the extremizers have exponential decay and consequently must be analytic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.06695v3</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boning Di, Ryan Frier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational convergence of the Scharfetter-Gummel scheme to the aggregation-diffusion equation and vanishing diffusion limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.02226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.02226v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we explore the convergence of the semi-discrete Scharfetter-Gummel scheme for the aggregation-diffusion equation using a variational approach. Our investigation involves obtaining a novel gradient structure for the finite volume space discretization that works consistently for any non-negative diffusion constant. This allows us to study the discrete-to-continuum and zero-diffusion limits simultaneously. The zero-diffusion limit for the Scharfetter-Gummel scheme corresponds to the upwind finite volume scheme for the aggregation equation. In both cases, we establish a convergence result in terms of gradient structures, recovering the Otto gradient flow structure for the aggregation-diffusion equation based on the 2-Wasserstein distance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.02226v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anastasiia Hraivoronska, Andr\'e Schlichting, Oliver Tse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence of weak mean curvature flow with prescribed contact angle via elliptic regularization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12283v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the present paper, we study the existence of Brakke-type weak mean curvature flow satisfying the contact angle condition for general angle $ \theta \in ( 0 , \pi ) $ via Ilmanen's regularization. The main ingredients of the result are the establishment of a compactness theorem for varifolds with the contact angle and the extension of Ilmanen's regularization to the capillarity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12283v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kiichi Tashiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
