<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 04:00:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Solutions for fourth order anisotropic nonlinear Schr\"odinger equations in $\R^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12988v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider solutions to the following fourth order anisotropic nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation in $\R \times \R^2$, $$ \left\{ \begin{aligned} &amp;\textnormal{i}\partial_t\psi+\partial_{xx} \psi-\partial_{yyyy} \psi +|\psi|^{p-2} \psi=0, \\ &amp;\psi(0)=\psi_0 \in H^{1,2}(\R^2), \end{aligned} \right. $$ where $p&gt;2$. First we prove the local/global well-posedness and blowup of solutions to the Cauchy problem for the anisotropic nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation. Then we establish the existence, axial symmetry, exponential decay and orbital stability/instability of standing waves to the anisotropic nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation. The pictures are considerably different from the ones for the isotropic nonlinear Schr\"odinger equations. The results are easily extendable to the higher dimensional case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12988v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Georgiev, Tianxiang Gou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Denjoy-Carleman solvability of Vekua-type periodic operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13110v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper explores the solvability and global hypoellipticity of Vekua-type differential operators on the n-dimensional torus, within the framework of Denjoy-Carleman ultradifferentiability. We provide the necessary and sufficient conditions for achieving these global properties in the case of constant-coefficient operators, along with applications to classical operators. Additionally, we investigate a class of variable coefficients and establish conditions for its solvability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13110v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Kirilov, Wagner Augusto Almeida de Moraes, Pedro Meyer Tokoro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normalized solutions to Schr\"{o}dinger systems with potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13204v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the normalized solutions of the Schr\"{o}dinger system with trapping potentials \begin{equation}\label{eq:diricichlet} \begin{cases} -\Delta u_1+V_1(x)u_1-\lambda_1 u_1=\mu_1 u_1^3+\beta u_1u_2^{2}+\kappa u_2~\hbox{in}~ \mathbb{R}^3,\\ -\Delta u_2+V_2(x)u_2-\lambda_2 u_2=\mu_2 u_2^3+\beta u_1^2u_2+\kappa u_1~\hbox{in}~ \mathbb{R}^3,
  u_1\in H^1(\mathbb{R}^3), u_2\in H^1(\mathbb{R}^3),\nonumber \end{cases} \end{equation} under the constraint \begin{equation} \int_{\mathbb{R}^3} u_1^2=a_1^2,~\int_{\mathbb{R}^3} u_2^2=a_2^2\nonumber, \end{equation} where $\mu_1,\mu_2,a_1,a_2,\beta&gt;0$, $\kappa\in\mathbb{R}$, $V_1(x)$ and $V_2(x)$ are trapping potentials, and $\lambda_1,\lambda_2$ are lagrangian multipliers, this is a typical $L^2$-supercritical case in $\mathbb{R}^3$. We obtain the existence of solutions to this system by minimax theory on the manifold for $\kappa=0$ and $\kappa\neq 0$ respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13204v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoyang Yun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well-posedness of the Euler equations in a stably stratified ocean in isopycnal coordinates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13263v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article is concerned with the well-posedness of the incompressible Euler equations describing a stably stratified ocean, reformulated in isopycnal coordinates. Our motivation for using this reformulation is twofold: first, its quasi-2D structure renders some parts of the analysis easier. Second, it closes a gap between the analysis performed in the paper by Bianchini and Duch{\^e}ne in 2022 in isopycnal coordinates, with shear velocity but with a regularizing term, and the analysis performed in the paper by Desjardins, Lannes, Saut in 2020 in Eulerian coordinates, without any regularizing term but without shear velocity. Our main result is an energy estimate in Sobolev spaces on the system in isopycnal coordinates, with shear velocity, without any regularizing term. With additional assumptions, it is uniform in the shallow-water parameter. The main difficulty consists in transposing to the isopycnal reformulation the symmetric structure of the system which is more straightforward in Eulerian coordinates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13263v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Th\'eo Fradin (IMB)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The extremal problem for weighted combined energy and $\rho-$Nitsche type inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13285v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $A_1$ and $A_2$ be two circular annuli and let $\rho$ be a radial metric defined in the annuli $A_2$. We study the existence and uniqueness of the extremal problem for weighted combined energy between $A_1$ and $A_2$, and obtain that the extremal mapping is a certain radial mapping. In fact, this extremal mapping generalizes the $\rho-$harmonic mapping and satisfies equation (2.7) obtained by mean of variation for weighted combined energy. Meanwhile, we get a $\rho-$Nitsche type inequality. This extends the results of Kalaj (J. Differential Equations, 268(2020)) and YTF (Arch. Math., 122(2024)), where they considered the case $\rho=1$ and $\rho=\frac{1}{|h|^{2}}$, respectively.
  Moreover, in the course of proving the extremal problem for weighted combined energy we also investigate the extremal problem for the weighted combined distortion (see Theorem 4.1). This extends the result obtained by Kalaj (J. London Math. Soc., 93(2016)).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13285v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ting Peng, Chaochuan Wang, Xiaogao Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotics of two-dimensional hydroelastic waves: The zero mass, zero bending limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13288v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider two-dimensional hydroelastic waves, in which a free fluid surface separates two fluids of infinite vertical extent. Elastic effects are accounted for at the interface, with a parameter measuring the elastic bending force and another parameter measuring the mass of the elastic sheet. In prior work, the authors have demonstrated well-posedness of this initial value problem in Sobolev spaces. We now take the limit as these two parameters vanish. Since the size of the time interval of existence given by this prior theory vanishes as the mass and bending parameters go to zero, we now establish estimates which are uniform with respect to these parameters. We may then make an additional estimate which demonstrates that the solutions form a Cauchy sequence as the parameters go to zero, so that the limit may be taken. This demonstrates that the vortex sheet with surface tension is the zero mass, zero bending limit of hydroelastic waves in two spatial dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13288v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunlian Liu, David M. Ambrose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Schatten exponent in orthonormal Strichartz estimate for the Dunkl operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13456v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In \cite{PRA} and \cite{SSM} the orthonormal Strichartz estimates for the Schr\"odinger equation associated with the Dunkl Laplacian and the Dunkl-Hermite operator are obtained. In this article, we prove a necessary condition on the Schatten exponent for the above orthonormal Strichartz estimates, which turns out to be optimal for the Schr\"odinger equations associated with Laplacian and Hermite operator as a special case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13456v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sunit Ghosh, Jitendriya Swain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A variational perspective on the dissipative Hamiltonian structure of the Vlasov-Fokker-Planck equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13682</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13682v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Vlasov-Fokker-Planck equation describes the evolution of the probability density of the position and velocity of particles under the influence of external confinement, interaction, friction, and stochastic force. It is well-known that this equation can be formally seen as a dissipative Hamiltonian system in the Wasserstein space of probability measures. In order to better understand this geometric formalism, we introduce a time-discrete variational scheme, solutions of which converge to the solution of the Vlasov-Fokker-Planck equation as time-step vanishes. The implicit scheme is based on the symplectic Euler scheme, and updates the probability density at each iteration first in the velocity variable then in the position variable.
  The algorithm leverages the geometric structure of the Wasserstein space, and has several desirable properties. Energy functionals involved in each variational problem are geodesically-convex, which implies the unique solvability of the problem. Furthermore, the correct dissipation of the Hamiltonian is observed at the discrete level up to higher order errors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13682v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sangmin Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification results, rigidity theorems and semilinear PDEs on Riemannian manifolds: a P-function approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13699v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider solutions to some semilinear elliptic equations on complete noncompact Riemannian manifolds and study their classification as well as the effect of their presence on the underlying manifold. When the Ricci curvature is non-negative, we prove both the classification of positive solutions to the critical equation and the rigidity for the ambient manifold. The same results are obtained when we consider solutions to the Liouville equation on Riemannian surfaces. The results are obtained via a suitable P-function whose constancy implies the classification of both the solutions and the underlying manifold. The analysis carried out on the P-function also makes it possible to classify non-negative solutions for subcritical equations on manifolds enjoying a Sobolev inequality and satisfying an integrability condition on the negative part of the Ricci curvature. Some of our results are new even in the Euclidean case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13699v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulio Ciraolo, Alberto Farina, Camilla Chiara Polvara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A rigorous approach to pattern formation for isotropic isoperimetric problems with competing nonlocal interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13773v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a rigorous approach to the study of the symmetry breaking and pattern formation phenomenon for isotropic functionals with local/nonlocal interactions in competition.
  We consider a general class of nonlocal variational problems in dimension $d\geq 2$, in which an isotropic surface term favouring pure phases competes with an isotropic nonlocal term with power law kernel favouring alternation between different phases.
  Close to the critical regime in which the two terms are of the same order, we give a rigorous proof of the conjectured structure of global minimizers, in the shape of domains with flat boundary (e.g., stripes or lamellae).
  The natural framework in which our approach is set and developed is the one of calculus of variations and geometric measure theory.
  Among others, we detect a nonlocal curvature-type quantity which is controlled by the energy functional and whose finiteness implies flatness for sufficiently regular boundaries.
  The power of decay of the considered kernels at infinity is $p\geq d+3$ and it is related to pattern formation in synthetic antiferromagnets. The decay $p=d+3$ is optimal to get the flatness of regular boundaries of finite energy in the critical regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13773v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara Daneri, Eris Runa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fully Nonlinear Elliptic Equations With Periodic Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13927v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study solutions $u$ of fully nonlinear elliptic equations of the form $F(D^2u)=f$ in $\mathbb{R}^n$, where $f$ is periodic. We establish the existence and Liouville type results for entire quadratic polynomial growth solutions, that is, the solution is a quadratic polynomial plus a periodic function. As a consequence, we consider applications to $k$-Hessian equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13927v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongsheng Li, Lichun Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A general Liouville-type theorem for the 3D steady-state Magnetic-B\'enard system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a Liouville-type theorem for the elliptic and incompressible Magnetic-B\'enard system defined over the entire three-dimensional space. Specifically, we demonstrate the uniqueness of trivial solutions under the condition that they belong to certain local Morrey spaces. Our results generalize in two key directions: firstly, the Magnetic-B\'enard system encompasses other significant coupled systems for which the Liouville problem has not been previously studied, including the Boussinesq system, the MHD-Boussinesq system, and the B\'enard system. Secondly, by employing local Morrey spaces, our theorem applies to Lebesgue spaces, Lorentz spaces, Morrey spaces, and certain weighted-Lebesgue spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13952v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oscar Jarrin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability analysis for a kinetic bacterial chemotaxis model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13994v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform stability analysis of a kinetic bacterial chemotaxis model of bacterial self-organization, assuming that bacteria respond sharply to chemical signals. The resulting discontinuous tumbling kernel represents the key challenge for the stability analysis as it rules out a direct linearization of the nonlinear terms. To address this challenge we fruitfully separate the evolution of the shape of the cellular profile from its global motion. We provide a full nonlinear stability theorem in a perturbative setting when chemical degradation can be neglected. With chemical degradation we prove stability of the linearized operator. In both cases we obtain exponential relaxation to equilibrium with an explicit rate using hypocoercivity techniques. To apply a hypocoercivity approach in this setting, we develop two novel and specific approaches: i) the use of the $H^1$ norm instead of the $L^2$ norm, and ii) the treatment of nonlinear terms. This work represents an important step forward in bacterial chemotaxis modeling from a kinetic perspective as most results are currently only available for the macroscopic descriptions, which are usually parabolic in nature. Significant difficulty arises due to the lack of regularization of the kinetic transport operator as compared to the parabolic operator in the macroscopic scaling limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13994v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Calvez, Gianluca Favre, Franca Hoffmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global counterexamples to uniqueness for a Calder\'on problem with $C^k$ conductivities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14063v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $\Omega \subset R^n$, $n \geq 3$, be a fixed smooth bounded domain, and let $\gamma$ be a smooth conductivity in $\overline{\Omega}$. Consider a non-zero frequency $\lambda_0$ which does not belong to the Dirichlet spectrum of $L_\gamma = -{\rm div} (\gamma \nabla \cdot)$. Then, for all $k \geq 1$, there exists an infinite number of pairs of non-isometric $C^k$ conductivities $(\gamma_1, \gamma_2)$ on $\overline{\Omega}$, which are close to $\gamma$ such that the associated DN maps at frequency $\lambda_0$ satisfy \begin{equation*}
  \Lambda_{\gamma_1,\lambda_0} = \Lambda_{\gamma_2,\lambda_0}. \end{equation*}</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14063v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daud\'e Thierry, Helffer Bernard, Kamran Niky, Nicoleau Fran\c{c}ois</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bridging bulk and surface: An interacting particle system towards the field-road diffusion model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We recover the so-called field-road diffusion model as the hydrodynamic limit of an interacting particle system. The former consists of two parabolic PDEs posed on two sets of different dimensions (a "field" and a "road" in a population dynamics context), and coupled through exchange terms between the field's boundary and the road. The latter stands as a Symmetric Simple Exclusion Process (SSEP): particles evolve on two microscopic lattices following a Markov jump process, with the constraint that each site cannot host more than one particle at the same time. The system is in contact with reservoirs that allow to create or remove particles at the boundary sites. The dynamics of these reservoirs are slowed down compared to the diffusive dynamics, to reach the reactions and the boundary conditions awaited at the macroscopic scale. This issue of bridging two spaces of different dimensions is, as far as we know, new in the hydrodynamic limit context, and raises perspectives towards future related works.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14093v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthieu Alfaro (LMRS), Mustapha Mourragui (LMRS), Samuel Tr\'eton (LMRS)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of nondegenerate ODE type blowup for the Fujita type heat equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14218v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The asymptotic bahavior of blowup solutions to the Fujita type heat equation $u_t=\Delta u+|u|^{p-1}u$ is studied. This equation admits the ODE type blowup given by $u(x,t)=(p-1)^\frac{1}{p-1}(T-t)^{-\frac{1}{p-1}}$. It is known that nondegenerate ODE type blowup is stable if $p\in(1,\frac{n+2}{n-2})$ due to Fermanian Kammerer-Merle-Zaag (2000). This paper extends their result to more general case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14218v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junichi Harada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pointwise convergence for the heat quation on tori $\mathbb T^n$ and waveguide manifold $\mathbb T^n \times \mathbb R^m$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14271v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We completely characterize the weighted Lebesgue spaces on the torus $\mathbb T^n$ and waveguide manifold $\mathbb T^n \times \mathbb R^m$ for which the solutions of the heat equation converge pointwise (as time tends to zero) to the initial data. In the process, we also characterize the weighted Lebesgue spaces for the boundedness of maximal operators on torus and waveguide manifold, which may be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14271v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Divyang G. Bhimani, Rupak K. Dalai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniqueness and modified Newton method for cracks from the far field patterns with a fixed incident direction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14279v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the inverse cracks scattering problems from the far field patterns with a fixed incident direction. We firstly show that the sound-soft cracks can be uniquely determined by the multi-frequency far field patterns with a fixed incident direction. The proof is based on a low frequency asymptotic analysis of the scattered field. One important feature of the uniqueness result is that the background can even be an unknown inhomogeneous medium. A modified Newton method is then proposed for the numerical reconstruction of the shapes and locations of the cracks. Compared to the classical Newton method, the modified Newton method relaxes the dependence of a good initial guess and can be applied for multiple cracks. Numerical examples in two dimensions are presented to demonstrate the feasibility and effectiveness of the modified Newton method. In particular, the quality of the reconstructions can be greatly improved if we use the measurements properly with two frequencies or two incident directions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14279v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jialei Li, Xiaodong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularity properties and dispersive blow-up for the fifth order Korteweg-de Vries equation on the line</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14342</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14342v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we prove that the initial value problem (IVP) for the fifth order Korteweg-de Vries equation \begin{align*} \left. \begin{array}{rlr} u_t+\partial_x^5 u+u\partial_x u&amp;\hspace{-2mm}=0,&amp;\quad x\in\mathbb R,\; t&gt;0,\\ u(x,0)&amp;\hspace{-2mm}=u_0(x),&amp; \end{array} \right\} \end{align*} has a unique local solution in time in the Bourgain spaces $X^{s,b}$ for appropriate values of $s$ and $b$. Besides we prove a regularity property concerning the nonlinear part of that solution. Finally, using the previous property we establish a dispersive blow-up result for global in time solutions of this IVP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14342v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eddye Bustamante, Jos\'e Jim\'enez Urrea, Jorge Mej\'ia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the homogenization of a Signorini-type problem in a domain with inclusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14344v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we investigate the effect of a Signorini-type interface condition on the asymptotic behaviour, as $\varepsilon$ tends to zero, of problems posed in $\varepsilon$-periodic domains with inclusions. The Signorini-type condition is expressed in terms of two complementary equalities involving the jump of the solution on the interface and its conormal derivative via a parameter $\gamma$. Our problem models the heat exchange in a medium hosting an $\varepsilon$-periodic array of thermal conductors in presence of impurities distributed on some regions of the interface. Different limit problems are obtained according to different values of $\gamma$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14344v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara Monsurr\`o, Carmen Perugia, Federica Raimondi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\Gamma$-convergence and stochastic homogenization of second order singular perturbations model for phase transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14356v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the effective behavior of random, heterogeneous, anisotropic, second order phase transitions energies that arise in the study of pattern formations in physical-chemical systems. Specifically, we study the asymptotic behavior, as $\epsilon$ goes to zero, of random heterogeneous anisotropic functionals in which the second order perturbation competes not only with a double well potential but also with a possibly negative contribution given by the first order term. We prove that, under suitable growth conditions and under a stationarity assumption, the functionals $\Gamma$-converge almost surely to a surface energy whose density is independent of the space variable. Furthermore, we show that the limit surface density can be described via a suitable cell formula and is deterministic when ergodicity is assumed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14356v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Flavio Donnarumma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blow-up for a double nonlocal heat equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14428v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the blow-up question for the diffusion equation involving a nonlocal derivative in time defined by convolution with a nonnegative and nonincreasing kernel, and a nonlocal operator in space driven by a nonnegative radial L\'evy kernel. We show that the existence of solutions that blow up in finite time or exist globally depends only on the behaviour of the spatial kernel at infinity. A main difficulty of the work stems from estimating the fundamental pair defining the solution through a Duhamel formula, due to the generality of the setting, which includes singular or not, at the origin, spatial kernels, that can be either positive or compactly supported.
  As a byproduct we obtain that the Fujita exponent for the fractional type operators similar to the Caputo fractional derivative and the fractional Laplacian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14428v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ra\'ul Ferreira, Arturo de Pablo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp Estimates for the Optimal Matching Problem on the 2-Torus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14471v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove sharp estimates for the average cost of the optimal matching problem on the flat 2-torus, using quantitative linearization and the method of trajectories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14471v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ariel Lerman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formulation of Chimera Gradient Flows for Chemotaxis Systems with Indirect Signal Production and Degenerate Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14536v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A parabolic system of three unknown functions, not expressible as gradient flows, is treated as three coupled gradient flows. For each unknown function, the minimizing movement scheme is used to construct a time-discrete approximate solution. Unlike standard minimizing movement scheme for gradient flows, the relative compactness of the time-discrete approximate solution with respect to the time step is not inherently guaranteed. However, the existence of a Lyapunov functional ensures this relative compactness, leading to the existence of time-global solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14536v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshifumi Mimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multilinear paraproducts on Sobolev spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13174v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Paraproducts are a special subclass of the multilinear Calder\'on-Zygmund operators, and their Lebesgue space estimates in the full multilinear range are characterized by the $\mathrm{BMO}$ norm of the symbol. In this note, we characterize the Sobolev space boundedness properties of multilinear paraproducts in terms of a suitable family of Triebel-Lizorkin type norms of the symbol. Coupled with a suitable wavelet representation theorem, this characterization leads to a new family of Sobolev space $T(1)$-type theorems for multilinear Calder\'on-Zygmund operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13174v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Di Plinio, A. Walton Green, Brett D. Wick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence of traveling wave solutions in continuous OV models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13293v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In traffic flow, self-organized wave propagation, which characterizes congestion, has been reproduced in macroscopic and microscopic models. Hydrodynamic models, a subset of macroscopic models, can be derived from microscopic-level car-following models, and the relationship between these models has been investigated. However, most validations have relied on numerical methods and formal analyses; therefore, analytical approaches are necessary to rigorously ensure their validity. This study aims to investigate the relationship between macroscopic and microscopic models based on the properties of the solutions corresponding to congestion with sparse and dense waves. Specifically, we demonstrate the existence of traveling wave solutions in macroscopic models and investigate their properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13293v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kota Ikeda, Toru Kan, Toshiyuki Ogawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of extremal domains for the first eigenvalue of the Laplacian operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13628v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we compute the second variation of the first Dirichlet eigenvalue on extremal domains and establish criteria for stability. We classify the stable extremal domains in the 2-sphere and in higher-dimensional spheres when the boundary is minimal. We also prove topological bounds for stable domains with nonnegative total Gaussian curvature in a general compact Riemannian surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13628v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcos P. Cavalcante, Ivaldo Nunes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetic Monte Carlo methods for three-dimensional diffusive capture problems in exterior domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13644v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cellular scale decision making is modulated by the dynamics of signalling molecules and their diffusive trajectories from a source to small absorbing sites on the cellular surface. Diffusive capture problems are computationally challenging due to the complex geometry and the applied boundary conditions together with intrinsically long transients that occur before a particle is captured. This paper reports on a particle-based Kinetic Monte Carlo (KMC) method that provides rapid accurate simulation of arrival statistics for (i) a half-space bounded by a surface with a finite collection of absorbing traps and (ii) the domain exterior to a convex cell again with absorbing traps. We validate our method by replicating classical results and in addition, newly developed boundary homogenization theories and matched asymptotic expansions on capture rates. In the case of non-spherical domains, we describe a new shielding effect in which geometry can play a role in sharpening cellular estimates on the directionality of diffusive sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13644v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alan E. Lindsay, Andrew J. Bernoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A nonlocal approximation of the area in codimension two</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13696v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For $s\in (0,1)$ we introduce a notion of fractional $s$-mass on $(n-2)$-dimensional closed, orientable surfaces in $\R^n$. Moreover, we prove its $\Gamma$-convergence, with respect to the flat topology, and pointwise convergence to the $(n-2)$-dimensional area.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13696v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michele Caselli, Mattia Freguglia, Nicola Picenni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong existence and uniqueness of a calibrated local stochastic volatility model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14074v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a two-dimensional McKean-Vlasov stochastic differential equation, whose volatility coefficient depends on the conditional distribution of the second component with respect to the first component. We prove the strong existence and uniqueness of the solution, establishing the well-posedness of a two-factor local stochastic volatility (LSV) model calibrated to the market prices of European call options. In the spirit of [Jourdain and Zhou, 2020, Existence of a calibrated regime switching local volatility model.], we assume that the factor driving the volatility of the log-price takes finitely many values. Additionally, the propagation of chaos of the particle system is established, giving theoretical justification for the algorithm [Julien Guyon and Henry-Labord\`ere, 2012, Being particular about calibration.].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14074v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Scander Mustapha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sobolev Wavefront Set of the Causal Propagator in Finite Regularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.04362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.04362v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a globally hyperbolic spacetime $M=\mathbb{R}\times \Sigma$ of dimension four and regularity $C^\tau$, we estimate the Sobolev wavefront set of the causal propagator $K_G$ of the Klein-Gordon operator. In the smooth case, the propagator satisfies $WF'(K_G)=C$, where $C\subset T^*(M\times M)$ consists of those points $(\tilde{x},\tilde{\xi},\tilde{y},\tilde{\eta})$ such that $\tilde{\xi},\tilde{\eta}$ are cotangent to a null geodesic $\gamma$ at $\tilde{x}$ resp. $\tilde{y}$ and parallel transports of each other along $\gamma$.
  We show that for $\tau&gt;2$, $WF'^{-2+\tau-{\epsilon}}(K_G)\subset C$ for every ${\epsilon}&gt;0$. Furthermore, in regularity $C^{\tau+2}$ with $\tau&gt;2$, $C\subset WF'^{-\frac{1}{2}}(K_G)\subset WF'^{\tau-\epsilon}(K_G)\subset C$ holds for $0&lt;\epsilon&lt;\tau+\frac{1}{2}$.
  In the ultrastatic case with $\Sigma$ compact, we show $WF'^{-\frac{3}{2}+\tau-\epsilon}(K_G)\subset C$ for $\epsilon &gt;0$ and $\tau&gt;2$ and $WF'^{-\frac{3}{2}+\tau-\epsilon}(K_G)= C$ for $\tau&gt;3$ and $\epsilon&lt;\tau-3$. Moreover, we show that the global regularity of the propagator $K_G$ is $H^{-\frac{1}{2}-\epsilon}_{loc}(M\times M)$ as in the smooth case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.04362v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yafet Sanchez Sanchez, Elmar Schrohe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remark on a special class of Finsler $p$-Laplacian equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.03439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.03439v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the anisotropic elliptic equation $-\Delta_p^H u = g(u)$. Recently, Esposito, Riey, Sciunzi, and Vuono introduced an anisotropic Kelvin transform in their work \cite{ERSV2022} under the $(H_M)$ condition, where $H(\xi)=\sqrt{\langle M\xi,\xi\rangle}$ with a positive definite symmetric matrix $M$. Here, we emphasize that under the $(H_M)$ assumption, the Finsler $p$-Laplacian and the classical $p$-Laplacian operator are equivalent following a linear transformation. This equivalence offers us a more direct route to derive the pivotal findings presented in \cite{ERSV2022}. While this equivalence is crucial and noteworthy, to our knowledge, it has not been explicitly stated in the current literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.03439v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3934/dcdss.2024099</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Li, Dong Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localization for general Helmholtz</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.03309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.03309v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In \cite{gmw2022}, Guan, Murugan and Wei established the equivalence of the classical Helmholtz equation with a ``fractional Helmholtz" equation in which the Laplacian operator is replaced by the nonlocal fractional Laplacian operator. More general equivalence results are obtained for symbols which are complete Bernstein and satisfy additional regularity conditions. In this work we introduce a novel and general set-up for this Helmholtz equivalence problem. We show that under very mild and easy-to-check conditions on the Fourier multiplier, the general Helmholtz equation can be effectively reduced to a localization statement on the support of the symbol.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.03309v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jde.2024.02.013</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Differential Equations 393 (2024) 139--154</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xinyu Cheng, Dong Li, Wen Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Lipschitz metric for $\alpha$-dissipative solutions to the Hunter-Saxton equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.07150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.07150v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore the Lipschitz stability of solutions to the Hunter-Saxton equation with respect to the initial data. In particular, we study the stability of $ \alpha $-dissipative solutions constructed using a generalised method of characteristics approach, where $\alpha$ is a function determining the energy loss at each position in space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.07150v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katrin Grunert, Matthew Tandy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classifying solutions of ${\rm SU}(n+1)$ Toda system around a singular source</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.13068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.13068v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Consider a positive integer $n$ and $\gamma_1&gt;-1,\cdots,\gamma_n&gt;-1$. Let $D=\{z\in {\Bbb C}:|z|&lt;1\}$, and let $(a_{ij})_{n\times n}$ denote the Cartan matrix of $\frak{su}(n+1)$. Utilizing the ordinary differential equation of $(n+1)$th order around a singular source of ${\rm SU}(n+1)$ Toda system, as discovered by Lin-Wei-Ye ({\it Invent Math}, {\bf 190}(1):169-207, 2012), we precisely characterize a solution $(u_1,\cdots, u_n)$ to the ${\rm SU}(n+1)$ Toda system \begin{equation*}
  \begin{cases} \frac{\partial^2 u_i}{\partial z\partial \bar z}+\sum_{j=1}^n a_{ij} e^{u_j}&amp;=\pi \gamma _i\delta _0\,\,{\rm on}\,\, D\\
  \frac{\sqrt{-1}}{2}\,\int_{D\backslash \{0\}} e^{u_{i} }{\rm d}z\wedge {\rm d}\bar z &amp;&lt; \infty
  \end{cases} \quad \text{for all}\quad i=1,\cdots, n \end{equation*} using $(n+1)$ holomorphic functions that satisfy the normalized condition. Additionally, we demonstrate that for each $1\leq i\leq n$, $0$ represents the cone singularity with angle $2\pi(1+\gamma_i)$ for the metric $e^{u_i}|{\rm d}z|^2$ on $D\backslash\{0\}$, which can be locally characterized by $(n-1)$ non-vanishing holomorphic functions at $0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.13068v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1090/proc/16785</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. Amer. Math. Soc. 152 (2024), 2585-2600</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jingyu Mu, Yiqian Shi, Tianyang Sun, Bin Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solutions to semilinear wave equations of very low regularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.13772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.13772v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper finds solutions to semilinear wave equations with strongly anomalous propagation of singularities. For very low Sobolev regularity we obtain solutions whose singular support propagates along any ray inside or outside the light cone. In one dimension these solutions exist for any Sobolev exponent $s&lt;\frac{1}{2}$ in space, while classical results show that the singular support of solutions with higher regularity is contained in the light cone. The spatial Fourier transform of these anomalous solutions is supported in a half-line. We obtain wellposedness results in such function spaces when the problem is ill-posed for Sobolev data without the support condition and, in some cases, obtain wellposedness below $L^2(\mathbb{R})$. The results are based on new multiplier theorems for Sobolev spaces satisfying the support condition. Extensions to higher space dimensions are given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.13772v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heiko Gimperlein, Michael Oberguggenberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calder\'on-Zygmund type estimate for the parabolic double-phase system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.10615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.10615v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper provides a local and global Calder\'on-Zygmund type estimate of a weak solution to the parabolic double-phase system. The proof of local estimate is based on comparison estimates and the scaling invariant property of the parabolic double-phase system in the intrinsic cylinders of the stopping time argument setting. For the proof of the global estimate, we have applied the reflection and approximation techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.10615v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wontae Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stationarity and Fredholm Theory in Subextremal Kerr-de Sitter Spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.09213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.09213v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In a recent paper, we proved that solutions to linear wave equations in a subextremal Kerr-de Sitter spacetime have asymptotic expansions in quasinormal modes up to a decay order given by the normally hyperbolic trapping, extending the results of Vasy (2013). One central ingredient in the argument was a new definition of quasinormal modes, where a non-standard choice of stationary Killing vector field had to be used in order for the Fredholm theory to be applicable. In this paper, we show that there is in fact a variety of allowed choices of stationary Killing vector fields. In particular, the horizon Killing vector fields work for the analysis, in which case one of the corresponding ergoregions is completely removed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.09213v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3842/SIGMA.2024.052</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SIGMA 20 (2024), 052, 11 pages</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Oliver Petersen, Andr\'as Vasy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Liouville comparison theory for blowup of Euler-Arnold equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.09748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.09748v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article we introduce a new blowup criterion for (generalized) Euler-Arnold equations on $\mathbb R^n$. Our method is based on treating the equation in Lagrangian coordinates, where it is an ODE on the diffeomorphism group, and comparison with the Liouville equation; in contrast to the usual comparison approach at a single point, we apply comparison in an infinite dimensional function space. We thereby show that the Jacobian of the Lagrangian flow map of the solution reaches zero in finite time, which corresponds to $C^1$-blowup of the velocity field solution. We demonstrate the applicability of our result by proving blowup of smooth solutions to some higher-order versions of the EPDiff equation in all dimensions $n\geq 3$. Previous results on blowup of higher dimensional EPDiff equations were only for versions where the geometric description corresponds to a Sobolev metric of order zero or one. In these situations the behavior does not depend on the dimension and thus already solutions to the one-dimensional version were exhibiting blowup. In the present paper blowup is proved even in situations where the one-dimensional equation has global solutions, such as the EPDiff equation corresponding to a Sobolev metric of order two.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.09748v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Bauer, Stephen C. Preston, Justin Valletta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new approach to weighted Sobolev spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12635v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present in this paper a new way to define weighted Sobolev spaces when the weight functions are arbitrary small. This new approach can replace the old one consisting in modifying the domain by removing the set of points where at least one of the weight functions is very small. The basic idea is to replace the distributional derivative with a new notion of weak derivative. In this way, non-locally integrable functions can considered in these spaces. Indeed, assumptions under which a degenerate elliptic partial differential equation has a unique non-locally integrable solution are given. Tools like a Poincar\'e Inequality and a trace operator are developed, and density results of smooth function are established.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12635v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Djamel eddine Kebiche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Navier-Stokes/Cahn-Hilliard equations with generalized Navier boundary condition and relaxation boundary condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17520v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the incompressible Navier-Stokes/Cahn-Hilliard system with generalized Navier boundary condition and relaxation boundary condition in a channel, which is the phase field model for the moving contact line problem in fluid mechanics. We establish the existence and uniqueness of local-in-time strong solution to this initial boundary value problem in 2D. To our knowledge, this is the first result to give the local-in-time well-posedness of Navier-Stokes/Cahn-Hilliard system with generalized Navier boundary condition and relaxation boundary condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17520v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shijin Ding, Yinghua Li, Zhilin Lin, Yuanxiang Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hardy inequalities and uncertainty principles in the presence of a black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06562v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we establish Hardy and Heisenberg uncertainty-type inequalities for the exterior of a Schwarzschild black hole. The weights that appear in both inequalities are tailored to fit the geometry, and can both be compared to the related Riemannian distance from the event horizon to yield inequalities for that distance. Moreover, in both cases the classic Euclidean inequalities with a point singularity can be recovered in the limit where one stands "far enough" from the black hole, as expected from the asymptotic flatness of the metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06562v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miltiadis Paschalis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic solutions to Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman Dirichlet problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17236v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a nonlinear Dirichlet problem on a bounded domain whose Hamiltonian is given by a Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman operator with merely continuous and bounded coefficients. The objective of this paper is to study the existence of viscosity solutions from a stochastic point of view. Using a relaxed control framework, we define a candidate for a viscosity solution, we prove that this stochastic solution satisfies viscosity sub- and supersolution properties and we establish a strong Markov selection principle, which shows that the stochastic solution can be realized through a strong Markov family. Building on the selection principle, we investigate regularity properties of the stochastic solution. For certain elliptic cases, we connect the strong Markov selection to a Feller selection, which entails the continuity of the stochastic solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17236v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Criens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak and Perron's Solutions to Linear Kinetic Fokker-Planck Equations of Divergence Form in Bounded Domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04070v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate weak solutions and Perron-Wiener-Brelot solutions to the linear kinetic Fokker-Planck equation in bounded domains. We establish the existence of weak solutions by applying the Lions-Lax-Milgram theorem and the vanishing viscosity method in product domains. Additionally, we demonstrate the regularity of weak solutions and establish a strong maximum principle. Furthermore, we construct a Perron solution and provide examples of barriers in arbitrary bounded domains. Our findings are based on recent advancements in the theory of kinetic Fokker-Planck equations with rough coefficients, particularly focusing on the characterization of a weaker notion of trace and the convolution-translation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04070v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benny Avelin, Mingyi Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Sobolev theory for Kolmogorov-Fokker-Planck operators with coefficients measurable in time and $VMO$ in space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09358</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09358v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider Kolmogorov-Fokker-Planck operators of the form $$ \mathcal{L}u=\sum_{i,j=1}^{q}a_{ij}(x,t)u_{x_{i}x_{j}}+\sum_{k,j=1}^{N} b_{jk}x_{k}u_{x_{j}}-\partial_{t}u, $$ with $\left( x,t\right) \in\mathbb{R}^{N+1},N\geq q\geq1$. We assume that $a_{ij}\in L^{\infty}\left( \mathbb{R}^{N+1}\right) $, the matrix $\left\{ a_{ij}\right\} $ is symmetric and uniformly positive on $\mathbb{R}^{q}$, and the drift \[ Y=\sum_{k,j=1}^{N}b_{jk}x_{k}\partial_{x_{j}}-\partial_{t} \] has a structure which makes the model operator with constant $a_{ij}$ hypoelliptic, translation invariant w.r.t. a suitable Lie group operation, and $2$-homogeneus w.r.t. a suitable family of dilations. We also assume that the coefficients $a_{ij}$ are $VMO$ w.r.t. the space variable, and only bounded measurable in $t$. We prove, for every $p\in\left( 1,\infty\right) $, global Sobolev estimates of the kind: \begin{align*} \Vert u\Vert _{W_{X}^{2,p}(S_{T})} \equiv &amp; \sum_{i,j=1}^{q}\Vert u_{x_{i}x_{j}}\Vert_{L^{p}(S_{T})}
  +\Vert Yu\Vert _{L^{p}(S_{T})} +\sum_{i=1}^{q}\Vert u_{x_{i}}\Vert _{L^{p}(S_{T})} +\Vert u\Vert _{L^{p}(S_{T})} \\ &amp; \leq c\big\{ \Vert \mathcal{L}u\Vert _{L^{p}(S_{T})}+\Vert u\Vert_{L^{p}(S_{T})}\big\}
  \end{align*} with $S_{T}=\mathbb{R}^{N}\times\left( -\infty,T\right) $ for any $T\in(-\infty,+\infty]$. Also, the well-posedness in $W_{X}^{2,p}(\Omega_{T})$, with $\Omega_{T}=\mathbb{R}^{N}\times(0,T) $ and $T\in\mathbb{R}$, of the Cauchy problem% $$ \begin{cases} \mathcal{L}u=f &amp; \text{in $\Omega_{T}$} \\ u(\cdot,0) =g &amp; \text{in $\mathbb{R}^{N}$} \end{cases} $$ is proved, for $f\in L^{p}(\Omega_{T}), g\in W_{X}^{2,p}(\mathbb{R}^{N})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09358v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Biagi, Marco Bramanti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Propagation of Waves from Finite Sources Arranged in Line Segments within an Infinite Triangular Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18806v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper examines the propagation of time harmonic waves through a two-dimensional triangular lattice with sources located on line segments. Specifically, we investigate the discrete Helmholtz equation with a wavenumber $k \in \left( 0,2\sqrt{2} \right)$, where input data is prescribed on finite rows or columns of lattice sites. We focus on two main questions: the efficacy of the numerical methods employed in evaluating the Green's function, and the necessity of the cone condition. Consistent with a continuum theory, we employ the notion of radiating solution and establish a unique solvability result and Green's representation formula using difference potentials. Finally, we propose a numerical computation method and demonstrate its efficiency through examples related to the propagation problems in the left-handed 2D inductor-capacitor metamaterial.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18806v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Kapanadze, Zurab Vashakidze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Applications of p-Adic Divergence and Gradient Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06439v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: $p$-Adic divergence and gradient operators are constructed giving rise to $p$-adic vertex Laplacian operators used by Z\'u\~niga in order to study Turing patterns on graphs, as well as their edge Laplacian counterparts. It is shown that the Euler characteristic of a finite graph can be expressed via traces of certain heat kernels associated with these new operators. This result is applied to the extraction of topological information from Mumford curves via heat kernels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06439v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Erik Bradley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steady Contiguous Vortex-Patch Dipole Solutions of the 2D Incompressible Euler Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09849v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We rigorously construct the first steady traveling wave solutions of the 2D incompressible Euler equation that take the form of a contiguous vortex-patch dipole, which can be viewed as the vortex-patch counterpart of the well-known Lamb-Chaplygin dipole. Our construction is based on a novel fixed-point approach that determines the patch boundary as the fixed point of a certain nonlinear map. Smoothness and other properties of the patch boundary are also obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09849v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>De Huang, Jiajun Tong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Note on a vector-host epidemic model with spatial structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11407v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magal, Webb and Wu [Nonlinearity 31, 5589-5614 (2018)] studied the outbreak of Zika in Rio De Janerio model, and provided complete dynamic properties. In this note we will use a very simple approach to provide a complete proof.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11407v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingxin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral geometry on manifolds with fibred boundary metrics I: Low energy resolvent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2009.10125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2009.10125v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the low energy resolvent of the Hodge Laplacian on a manifold equipped with a fibred boundary metric. We determine the precise asymptotic behavior of the resolvent as a fibred boundary (aka $\phi$-) pseudodifferential operator when the resolvent parameter tends to zero. This generalizes previous work by Guillarmou and Sher who considered asymptotically conic metrics, which correspond to the special case when the fibres are points. The new feature in the case of non-trivial fibres is that the resolvent has different asymptotic behavior on the subspace of forms that are fibrewise harmonic and on its orthogonal complement. To deal with this, we introduce an appropriate 'split' pseudodifferential calculus, building on and extending work by Grieser and Hunsicker. Our work sets the basis for the discussion of spectral invariants on $\phi$-manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2009.10125v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal de l'Ecole polytechnique - Mathematiques 9 (2022), p. 959-1019</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Grieser, Mohammad Talebi, Boris Vertman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the non-existence of trapped surfaces under low-regularity bounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.09855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.09855v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The emergence of trapped surfaces in solutions to the Einstein field equations is intimately tied to the well-posedness properties of the corresponding Cauchy problem in the low regularity regime. In this paper, we study the question of existence of trapped surfaces already at the level of the initial hypersurface when the scale invariant size of the Cauchy data is assumed to be bounded. Our main theorem states that no trapped surfaces can exist initially when the Cauchy data are close to the data induced on a spacelike hypersurface of Minkowski spacetime (not necessarily a flat hyperplane) in the Besov $B^{3/2}_{2,1}$ norm. We also discuss the question of extending the above result to the case when merely smallness in $H^{3/2}$ is assumed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.09855v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Luk, Georgios Moschidis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial time guarantees for sampling based posterior inference in high-dimensional generalised linear models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.13296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.13296v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The problem of computing posterior functionals in general high-dimensional statistical models with possibly non-log-concave likelihood functions is considered. Based on the proof strategy of [49], but using only local likelihood conditions and without relying on M-estimation theory, nonasymptotic statistical and computational guarantees are provided for a gradient based MCMC algorithm. Given a suitable initialiser, these guarantees scale polynomially in key algorithmic quantities. The abstract results are applied to several concrete statistical models, including density estimation, nonparametric regression with generalised linear models and a canonical statistical non-linear inverse problem from PDEs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.13296v2</guid>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Randolf Altmeyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak uniqueness by noise for singular stochastic PDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.01642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.01642v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove weak uniqueness of mild solutions for general classes of SPDEs on a Hilbert space. The main novelty is that the drift is only defined on a Sobolev-type subspace and no H\"older-continuity assumptions are required. This framework turns out to be effective to achieve novel uniqueness results for several specific examples. Such wide range of applications is obtained by exploiting either coloured or rougher-than-cylindrical noises.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.01642v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Bertacco, Carlo Orrieri, Luca Scarpa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational Wave Displacement and Velocity Memory Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.02594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.02594v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article, we compare in detail the linear and nonlinear approach to the Gravitational Waves Displacement and Velocity Memory (GWDM and GWVM) effects. We consider astrophysical situations that give rise to gravitational waves with GWVM effect, i.e. with a residual velocity (the so-called "velocity-coded memory") and discuss the possibility of future detection of the GWVM effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.02594v5</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/ad4dfe</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Class. Quantum Grav. 41 135012 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lydia Bieri, Alexander Polnarev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical-Quantum correspondence in Lindblad evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09345v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that for the Lindblad evolution defined using (at most) quadratically growing classical Hamiltonians and (at most) linearly growing classical jump functions (quantized into jump operators assumed to satisfy certain ellipticity conditions and modeling interaction with a larger system), the evolution of a quantum observable remains close to the classical Fokker--Planck evolution in the Hilbert--Schmidt norm for times vastly exceeding the Ehrenfest time (the limit of such agreement with no jump operators). The time scale is the same as in the recent papers by Hern\'andez--Ranard--Riedel but the statement and methods are different. The appendix presents numerical experiments illustrating the classical/quantum correspondence in Lindblad evolution and comparing it to the mathematical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09345v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey Galkowski, Zhen Huang, Maciej Zworski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Volume forms on balanced manifolds and the Calabi-Yau equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00995v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce the space of mixed-volume forms endowed with an $L^2$ metric on a balanced manifold. A geodesic equation can be derived in this space that has an interesting structure and extends the equation of Donaldson \cite{Donaldson10} and Chen-He \cite{CH11} in the space of volume forms on a Riemannian manifold. This nonlinear PDE is studied in detail and the existence of weak solution is shown for the Dirichlet problem, under a positivity assumption. Later we study the Calabi-Yau equation for balanced metrics and introduce a geometric criteria for prescribing volume forms that is closely related to the positivity assumption above. We call this assumption the sub-Astheno-K\"ahler condition. By deriving $C^0$ a priori estimates, we show that the existence of solutions can be established on all sub-Astheno-K\"ahler manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00995v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathew George</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
