<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 01:36:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Global well-posedness of the free boundary problem for incompressible viscous resistive MHD in critical Besov spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15279v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper aims to establish the global well-posedness of the free boundary problem for the incompressible viscous resistive magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) equations. Under the framework of Lagrangian coordinates, a unique global solution exists in the half-space provided that the norm of the initial data in the critical homogeneous Besov space $\dot{B}_{p, 1}^{-1+N/p}(\mathbb{R}_{+}^N)$ is sufficiently small, where $p \in [N, 2N-1)$. Building upon prior work such as (Danchin and Mucha, J. Funct. Anal. 256 (2009) 881--927) and (Ogawa and Shimizu, J. Differ. Equations 274 (2021) 613--651) in the half-space setting, we establish maximal $L^{1}$-regularity for both the Stokes equations without surface stress and the linearized equations of the magnetic field with zero boundary condition. The existence and uniqueness of solutions to the nonlinear problems are proven using the Banach contraction mapping principle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15279v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Zhang, Jie Fu, Chengchun Hao, Siqi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singularity formation for the higher dimensional Skyrme model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15345v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper demonstrates that singularities form in the classical $(5+1)$-dimensional, co-rotational Skyrme model. It was recently proven by Chen, Sch\"orkhuber, and the author that the strong field limit of the $(5+1)$-dimensional, co-rotational Skyrme model admits an explicit self-similar solution which is asymptotically stable within backwards light cones. Seeded by the limiting model, we construct an open set of initial data whose evolution within a backwards light cone, according to the full model, suffers a gradient blowup in finite time. Moreover, the singularity develops at the self-similar rate and possesses an asymptotic profile given by the self-similar profile of the strong field model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15345v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael McNulty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic stability of solitary waves for the 1D focusing cubic Schr\"odinger equation under even perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15427v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish the full asymptotic stability of solitary waves for the focusing cubic Schr\"odinger equation on the line under small even perturbations in weighted Sobolev norms. The strategy of our proof combines a space-time resonances approach based on the distorted Fourier transform to capture modified scattering effects with modulation techniques to take into account the symmetries of the problem, namely the invariance under scaling and phase shifts. A major challenge is the slow local decay of the radiation term caused by the threshold resonances of the non-selfadjoint linearized matrix Schr\"odinger operator around the solitary waves. Our analysis hinges on two remarkable null structures that we uncover in the quadratic nonlinearities of the evolution equation for the radiation term as well as of the modulation equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15427v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongming Li, Jonas Luhrmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlocal Differential Operators with Integrable, Nonsymmetric Kernels: Part I--Operator Theoretic Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15448v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent decades have provided a host of examples and applications motivating the study of nonlocal differential operators. We discuss a class of such operators acting on bounded domains, focusing on those with integrable kernels having compact support. Notably, we make no explicit symmetry assumptions on the kernel and discuss some implications of this decision. We establish a nonlocal-to-local convergence result, showing that these operators coincide with the classical derivative as the nonlocality vanishes. We also provide a new integration by parts result, a characterization of the compactness of these nonlocal operators, an implication for the nonlocal Poincar\'e inequality, and a variety of examples. This work establishes several key results needed to analyze nonlocal variational problems, given in Part II. We hope that this paper can serve as a relatively gentle introduction to the field of nonlocal modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15448v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikil Foss, Michael Pieper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction between initial behavior of temperature and the mean curvature of the interface in two-phase heat conductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15539v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the Cauchy problem for the heat diffusion equation in the whole Euclidean space consisting of two media locally with different constant conductivities, where initially one medium has temperature 0 and the other has temperature 1. Under the assumption that a part of the interface between two media with different constant conductivities is of class $C^2$ in a neighborhood of a point $x$ on it, we extract the mean curvature of the interface at $x$ from the initial behavior of temperature at $x$. This result is purely local in space. As a corollary, when the whole Euclidean space consists of two media globally with different constant conductivities, it is shown that if a connected component $\Gamma$ of the interface is of class $C^2$ and is stationary isothermic, then the mean curvature of $\Gamma$ must be constant. Moreover, we apply this result to some overdetermined problems for two-phase heat conductors and obtain some symmetry theorems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15539v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shigeru Sakaguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularity for a class of degenerate fully nonlinear nonlocal elliptic equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15559v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a wide class of fully nonlinear integro-differential equations that degenerate when the gradient of the solution vanishes. By using compactness and perturbation arguments, we give a complete characterization of the regularity of viscosity solutions according to different diffusion orders. More precisely, when the order of the fractional diffusion is sufficiently close to 2, we obtain H\"{o}lder continuity for the gradient of any viscosity solutions and further derive an improved gradient regularity estimate at the origin. For the order of the fractional diffusion in the interval $(1, 2)$, we prove that there is at least one solution of class $C^{1, \alpha}_{\rm loc}$. Additionally, if the order of the fractional diffusion is in the interval $(0,1]$, the local H\"{o}lder continuity of solutions is inferred.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15559v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuzhou Fang, Vicentiu D. Radulescu, Chao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On $p$-Laplace equations with a critical Hardy-Sobolev exponent and a Hardy potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15574v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For $N\ge2$ and $1&lt;p&lt;N$, we classify all positive $\mathcal{D}^{1,p}(\mathbb{R}^N)$-solutions to $p$-Laplace equations with a critical Hardy-Sobolev exponent and a Hardy potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15574v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phuong Le</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decay Rates for Viscous Surface Waves of Isotropic Micropolar Fluids With or Without Surface Tension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15586v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider a layer of viscous incompressible isotropic micropolar fluid in a uniform gravitational field of finite depth, lying above a flat rigid bottom and below the atmosphere in a three-dimensional horizontally periodic setting. The fluid dynamics are governed by gravity-driven incompressible micropolar equations. We investigate the global well-posedness for both the cases with and without surface tension. On one hand, in the case with surface tension (i.e. {\sigma} &gt; 0), we show that the global solution decays to the equilibrium exponentially. On the other hand, in the case without surface tension (i.e. {\sigma} = 0), the solution decays to the equilibrium at an almost exponential rate. Comparing the two different cases for {\sigma} &gt; 0 and {\sigma} = 0 reveals that the surface tension can enhance the decay rate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15586v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchong Wei, Zheng-an Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exponential stability of a free boundary problem with spherical symmetry for a gas bubble immersed in a bounded incompressible liquid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15587v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper is mainly concerned with the free boundary problem for an approximate model (for example, arising from the study of sonoluminescence) of a gas bubble of finite mass enclosed within a bounded incompressible viscous liquid, accounting for surface tensions at both the gas-liquid interface and the external free surface of the entire gas-liquid region. It is found that any regular spherically symmetric steady-state solution is characterized by a positive root of a ninth-degree polynomial for which the existence and uniqueness are proved and a one-to-one correspondence between equilibria and pairs of gas mass and liquid volume is established. We prove that these equilibria exhibit nonlinear and exponential asymptotic stability under small perturbations that conserve gas mass and liquid volume, and an equilibrium solution acts as a local minimizer of the energy functional, even under relatively large perturbations, with the proportionality constant determined by the adiabatic constant. Moreover, we construct a global center manifold to apply the center manifold theory. Our results apply to gases and liquids of all sizes. Furthermore, we derive the optimal exponential decay rate for small liquid volumes by analyzing the spectrum bounds of the associated linear operator and show that decreasing the gas mass or increasing the temperature can accelerate the convergence rate, a behavior not seen in unbounded liquid scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15587v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengchun Hao, Tao Luo, Siqi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of a class of exact solutions of the incompressible Euler equation in a disk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15598v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a sharp orbital stability result for a class of exact steady solutions, expressed in terms of Bessel functions of the first kind, of the two-dimensional incompressible Euler equation in a disk. A special case of these solutions is the truncated Lamb dipole, whose stream function corresponds to the second eigenfunction of the Dirichlet Laplacian. The proof is achieved by establishing a suitable variational characterization for these solutions via conserved quantities of the Euler equation and employing a compactness argument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15598v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guodong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-regulated biological transportation structures with general entropy dissipation: 2D case and leaf-shaped domain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15680v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, the study of biological transportation networks has attracted significant interest, focusing on their self-regulating, demand-driven nature. This paper examines a mathematical model for these networks, featuring nonlinear elliptic equations for pressure and an auxiliary variable, and a reaction-diffusion parabolic equation for the conductivity tensor, introduced in \cite{portaro2022emergence}. The model, based on an energy functional with diffusive and metabolic terms, allows for various entropy generating functions, facilitating its application to different biological scenarios. We proved a local well-posedness result for the problem in H\"older spaces employing Schauder and semigroup theory. Then, after a suitable parameter reduction through scaling, we computed the numerical solution for the proposed system using a recently developed ghost nodal finite element method \cite{astuto2024nodal}. An interesting aspect emerges when the solution is very articulated and the branches occupy a wide region of the domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15680v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clarissa Astuto, Peter Markowich, Simone Portaro, Giovanni Russo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feedback boundary stabilization for the Hirota-Satsuma system with time-delay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15705v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paper investigates the boundary stabilization problem of the Hirota-Satsuma system. It designs an appropriate boundary feedback law that consists of a linear combination of a damping mechanism and a delay term. The study shows that, with time delay feedback and a smallness restriction on the size of the initial data the energy the Hirota-Satsuma system decays exponentially by employing the Lyapunov method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15705v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Hugo Gonzalez Martinez, Juan Ricardo Mu\~noz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local well-posedness of a system coupling compressible atmospheric dynamics and a micro-physics model of moisture in air</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15749v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish here the local-in-time well-posedness of strong solutions with large initial data to a system coupling compressible atmospheric dynamics with a refined moisture model introduced in Hittmeir and Klein (Theor. Comput. Fluid Dyn. 32:137--164, 2018). This micro-physics moisture model is a refinement of the one communicated by Klein and Majda (Theor. Comput. Fluid Dyn. 20:525--551, 2006), which serves as a foundation of multi-scale asymptotic expansions for moist deep convection in the atmosphere. Specifically, we show, in this paper, that the system of compressible Navier--Stokes equations coupled with the moisture dynamics is well-posed. In particular, the micro-physics of moisture model incorporates the phase changes of water in moist air.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15749v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sabine Doppler, Rupert Klein, Xin Liu, Edriss Titi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global well-posedness and large time behavior of solutions to the compressible Oldroyd-B model without stress diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15812v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the Cauchy problem ($\mathbb{R}^d, d=2,3$) and the initial boundary values problem ($\mathbb{T}^d, d=2,3$)associated to the compressible Oldroyd-B model which is first derived by Barrett, Lu and S\"{u}li [Existence of large-data finite-energy global weak solutions to a compressible Oldroyd-B model, Commun. Math. Sci., 15 (2017), 1265--1323] through micro-macro-analysis of the compressible Navier-Stokes-Fokker-Planck system.Due to lack of stress diffusion, the problems considered here are very difficult. Exploiting tools from harmonic analysis,notably the Littlewood Paley theory,we first establish the global well-posedness and time-decay rates for solutions of the model with small initial data in Besov spaces with critical regularity.Then, through deeply exploring and fully utilizing the structure of the perturbation system,we obtain the global well-posedness and exponential decay rates for solutions of the model with small initial data in the Soboles spaces $H^3(\mathbb{T}^d)$.Our obtained results improve considerably the recent results by Lu, Pokorn\'{y} [Anal. Theory Appl., 36 (2020), 348--372],Wang, Wen [Math. Models Methods Appl. Sci., 30 (2020), 139--179],and Liu, Lu, Wen [SIAM J. Math. Anal., 53 (2021), 6216--6242].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15812v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yajuan Zhao, Yongsheng Li, Tao Liang, Xiaoping Zhai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modified scattering for long-range Hartree equations of infinite rank near vacuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15860v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish the asymptotic behavior and decay of solutions near vacuum to the Hartree equation with the Coulomb interaction potential in three dimensions. Our approach is direct, which consists of independently deriving the sharp dispersive decay estimates for the density function and establishing the boundedness of energy norms. The global in time well-posedness is done without introducing the phase correction, while the phase modification is explicit in terms of the density function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15860v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Toan T. Nguyen, Chanjin You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase mixing estimates for the nonlinear Hartree equation of infinite rank</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15972v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove the phase mixing estimates for the density and its derivatives associated with the nonlinear Hartree equation around certain translation-invariant equilibria. Their decay rates are exactly the same as those of free Hartree dynamics. Our method is based on pointwise decay estimates of the Green function associated with the linearized operator in Fourier space and a nonlinear iterative scheme. Another proof of short-range scattering, established in [arXiv:1310.0604, arXiv:1607.07958, arXiv:2308.15929], is also provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15972v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chanjin You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimizing movements solutions for a monotone model of droplet motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15984v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the uniqueness and regularity of minimizing movements solutions of a droplet model in the case of piecewise monotone forcing. We show that such solutions evolve uniquely on each interval of monotonicity, but branching non-uniqueness may occur where jumps and monotonicity changes coincide. This classification of minimizing movements solutions allows us to reduce the quasi-static evolution to a finite sequence of elliptic problems and establish $L^\infty_tC^{1,1/2-}_x$-regularity of solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15984v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carson Collins, William M Feldman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>L^2-instability of the Taub-Bolt metric under the Ricci flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15269v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we prove that there exists a compact perturbation of the Ricci flat Taub-Bolt metric that evolves under the Ricci flow into a finite time singularity modelled on the shrinking solition FIK [5]. Moreover, this perturbation can be made arbitrarily L^2-small with respect to the Taub-Bolt metric. The method of proof closely follows the strategy adopted in [14], where the author constructs, via a Wa\.zewski box argument, Ricci flows on compact manifolds which encounter finite singularities modelled on a given asymptotically conical shrinking soliton.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15269v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Hughes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Divergence-free neural operators for stress field modeling in polycrystalline materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15408v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The purpose of the current work is the development and comparison of Fourier neural operators (FNOs) for surrogate modeling of the quasi-static mechanical response of polycrystalline materials. Three types of such FNOs are considered here: a physics-guided FNO (PgFNO), a physics-informed FNO (PiFNO), and a physics-encoded FNO (PeFNO). These are trained and compared with the help of stress field data from a reference model for heterogeneous elastic materials with a periodic grain microstructure. Whereas PgFNO training is based solely on these data, that of the PiFNO and PeFNO is in addition constrained by the requirement that stress fields satisfy mechanical equilibrium, i.e., be divergence-free. The difference between the PiFNO and PeFNO lies in how this constraint is taken into account; in the PiFNO, it is included in the loss function, whereas in the PeFNO, it is "encoded" in the operator architecture. In the current work, this encoding is based on a stress potential and Fourier transforms. As a result, only the training of the PiFNO is constrained by mechanical equilibrium; in contrast, mechanical equilibrium constrains both the training and output of the PeFNO. Due in particular to this, stress fields calculated by the trained PeFNO are significantly more accurate than those calculated by the trained PiFNO in the example cases considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15408v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad S. Khorrami, Pawan Goyal, Jaber R. Mianroodi, Bob Svendsen, Peter Benner, Dierk Raabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Option Pricing with Stochastic Volatility, Equity Premium, and Interest Rates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15416v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a new model for options pricing. The Black-Scholes-Merton (BSM) model plays an important role in financial options pricing. However, the BSM model assumes that the risk-free interest rate, volatility, and equity premium are constant, which is unrealistic in the real market. To address this, our paper considers the time-varying characteristics of those parameters. Our model integrates elements of the BSM model, the Heston (1993) model for stochastic variance, the Vasicek model (1977) for stochastic interest rates, and the Campbell and Viceira model (1999, 2001) for stochastic equity premium. We derive a linear second-order parabolic PDE and extend our model to encompass fixed-strike Asian options, yielding a new PDE. In the absence of closed-form solutions for any options from our new model, we utilize finite difference methods to approximate prices for European call and up-and-out barrier options, and outline the numerical implementation for fixed-strike Asian call options.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15416v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicole Hao, Echo Li, Diep Luong-Le</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomaly Flow: Shi-Type Estimates and Long-time Existence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15514v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the long-time existence of the anomaly flow on a compact complex $3$-fold with general slope parameter $\alpha'$. In particular, we obtain integral Shi-type estimates for the flow by adapting a integration-by-parts type argument instead of the usual maximum principle techniques. Following this, we prescribe a sufficient smallness condition on $\alpha'$ in order to extend the flow on $[0,\tau)$ to $[0,\tau + \epsilon)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15514v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caleb Suan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-component multi-scale hydrodynamic plasma flow models in mechanical and thermal disequilibria</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15531v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The present work is motivated by the mixing mechanism in inertial confinement fusion (ICF), which remarkably degrades the ignition performance. The mixing is a direct result of velocity disequilibrium and affected by temperature disequilibrium.To deal with these disequilibria, we propose a fully-disequilibrium hydrodynamic model (termed as Baer-Nunziato-Zeldovich model or BNZ model) with 9 equations, 4 temperatures (two for ions, and two for electrons), 4 pressures (two for ions, and two for electrons) and 2 ion velocities for two-component dense plasma flows. The model can be used for describing both grain and atomic mixing by choosing corresponding relaxation mechanism. The derivation starts from a multi-component conservative entropy-dissipative Bhatnagar-Gross-Krook (BGK) model to obtain a 14-equation model. It is then reduced to more practical 9-equation BNZ model and further to simpler 8-equation model, 6-equation model (the Kapila-Zeldovich model or the KZ model), and the 5-equation model. The reductions are performed on the basis of various relaxation time evaluations, the plasma neutrality and the smallness of the electron mass. The models are thermodynamics-compatible, and capable of dealing with mechanical and thermal disequilibria at both atomic and grain scales. Moreover, the corresponding hydrodynamic subsystems are shown to be hyperbolic and solved with the Godunov finite volume method. The BNZ model and solution methods are verified and validated by some benchmark problems and 1D-2D comparisons. We then consider the velocity, pressure and temperature disequilibria during the passage of an ablation shock in ICF.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15531v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iterated graph systems and the combinatorial Loewner property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15692v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce iterated graph systems which yield fractal spaces through a projective sequence of self-similar graphs. Our construction yields new examples of self-similar fractals, such as the pentagonal Sierpi\'nski carpet and a pillow-space, and it yields a new framework to study potential theory on many standard examples in the literature, including generalized Sierpi\'nski carpets. We demonstrate that a fractal arising from an iterated graph system satisfying mild geometric conditions and having enough reflection symmetries, satisfies the combinatorial Loewner property (CLP) of Bourdon and Kleiner. For certain exponents, one can also obtain the conductive homogeneity condition of Kigami. This shows, in a precise sense, that self-similarity and sufficient symmetry yields CLP.
  Furthermore, we show that our examples satisfy important asymptotic behaviors of discrete moduli. In particular, we establish the so-called super-multiplicative inequality for our examples - which when $p=2$ plays a crucial role in the study of Dirichlet forms and random walks on fractals. This implies the super-multiplicativity bound also for many fractals for which it was not known before, such as the Menger sponge. A particular feature here is using replacement flows and the notion of a flow basis. This yields a simpler way to establish many known estimates, and allows us to prove several new ones. Further, super-multiplicativity shows that one can effectively estimate the conformal dimensions numerically for many self-similar fractals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15692v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riku Anttila, Sylvester Eriksson-Bique</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds for Eigenvalue Sums of Schr\"odinger Operators with Complex Radial Potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15783v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider eigenvalue sums of Schr\"odinger operators $-\Delta+V$ on $L^2(\R^d)$ with complex radial potentials $V\in L^q(\R^d)$, $q&lt;d$. We prove quantitative bounds on the distribution of the eigenvlaues in terms of the $L^q$ norm of $V$. A consequence of our bounds is that, if the eigenvlaues $(z_j)$ accumulates to a point in $(0,\infty)$, then $(\im z_j)$ is summable. The key technical tools are resolvent estimates in Schatten spaces. We show that these resolvent estimates follow from spectral measure estimates by an epsilon removal argument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15783v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Claude Cuenin, Solomon Keedle-Isack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>About the first eigenvector of the simple random walk killed upon exiting a large bounded domain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15858v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article, we study a discrete version of a Dirichlet problem in an open bounded set $D\subset \mathbb{R}^d$, in dimension $d\geq 2$. More precisely, we consider the simple random walk on $\mathbb{Z}^d$, $d\geq 2$, killed upon exiting the large (bounded) domain $D_N :=(ND)\cap \mathbb{Z}^d$. We denote by $P_N$ the corresponding transition matrix and we study the properties of its ($L^2$-normalized) principal eigenvector $\phi_N$ -- one of our motivation is that the random walk ``conditioned to stay in $D_N$'' is a random walk among conductances $c_N(x,y) = \phi_N(x)\phi_N(y)$. With probabilistic arguments and under mild assumptions on the domain, we show that $\phi_N$ varies regularly, with a uniform control inside $D_N$. We derive several corollaries, among which a uniform convergence of $\phi_N$ to the first eigenfunction of the corresponding continuous Dirichlet problem. Our results may not be new, but our proofs use (simple) probabilistic ideas that could be helpful in other contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15858v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quentin Berger, Nicolas Bouchot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bifurcation of homogenization and nonhomogenization of the curvature G-equation with shear flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.16304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.16304v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The level-set curvature G-equation, a well-known model in turbulent combustion, has the following form
  $G_t + \left(1-d\, \mathrm{dvi}\left({\frac{DG}{|DG|}}\right)\right)_+|DG|+V(X)\cdot DG=0.$
  Here the cutoff correction $()_+$ is imposed to avoid non-physical negative local burning velocity. The existence of the effective burning velocity has been established for a large class of physically relevant incompressible flows $V$ in two dimensions [13] via game theory dynamics. In this paper, we show that the effective burning velocity associated with shear flows in dimensions three or higher ceases to exist when the flow intensity surpasses a bifurcation point. The characterization of the bifurcation point in three dimensions is closely related to the regularity theory of two-dimensional minimal surface type equations due to [29]. As a consequence, a bifurcation also exists for the validity of full homogenization of the curvature G-equation associated with shear flows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.16304v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroyoshi Mitake, Connor Mooney, Hung V. Tran, Jack Xin, Yifeng Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-similar finite-time blowups with smooth profiles of the generalized Constantin-Lax-Majda model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.05895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.05895v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that the $a$-parameterized family of the generalized Constantin-Lax-Majda model, also known as the Okamoto-Sakajo-Wunsch model, admits exact self-similar finite-time blowup solutions with interiorly smooth profiles for all $a\leq 1$. Depending on the value of $a$, these self-similar profiles are either smooth on the whole real line or compactly supported and smooth in the interior of their closed supports. The existence of these profiles is proved in a consistent way by considering the fixed-point problem of an $a$-dependent nonlinear map, based on which detailed characterizations of their regularity, monotonicity, and far-field decay rates are established. Our work unifies existing results for some discrete values of $a$ and also explains previous numerical observations for a wide range of $a$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.05895v5</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00205-024-01971-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>De Huang, Xiang Qin, Xiuyuan Wang, Dongyi Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence, uniqueness, and regularity of solutions to nonlinear and non-smooth parabolic obstacle problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01498v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish the existence, uniqueness, and $W^{1,2,p}$-regularity of solutions to fully-nonlinear, parabolic obstacle problems when the obstacle is the pointwise supremum of functions in $W^{1,2,p}$ and the nonlinear operator is required only to be measurable in the state and time variables. In particular, the results hold for all convex obstacles. Applied to stopping problems, they provide general conditions under which a decision maker never stops at a convex kink of the stopping payoff. The proof relies on new $W^{1,2,p}$-estimates for obstacle problems when the obstacle is the maximum of finitely many functions in $W^{1,2,p}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01498v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Durandard Th\'eo, Strulovici Bruno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal gradient estimates for the insulated conductivity problem with general convex inclusions case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17201v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the insulated conductivity problem which involves two adjacent convex insulators embedded in a bounded domain. It is known that the gradient of solutions may blow up as the distance between the two inclusions tends to zero. However, the sharpness of the blow up rate for general convex insulator case in dimension $n\geq3$ has remained open. The novelty of this paper is that we answer this problem affirmatively by establishing a pointwise upper bound of the gradient for general convex insulators, along with a corresponding lower bound that achieves optimal blow up rates. These rates are associated with the first nonzero eigenvalue of an elliptic operator determined by the geometry of insulators. Our results improve and make complete the previous result for ball insulators case studied in \cite{DLY}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17201v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haigang Li, Yan Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restriction estimates for hyperbolic paraboloids in higher dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08549v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove restriction estimates for hyperbolic paraboloids in dimensions $n&gt;=5$ by the polynomial partitioning method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08549v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuoran Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A shape optimization problem for nematic and cholesteric liquid crystal drops</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05651v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We generalize the shape optimization problem for the existence of stable equilibrium configurations of nematic and cholesteric liquid crystal drops surrounded by an isotropic solution to include a broader family of admissible domains with inner boundaries, allowing discontinuities in the director field across them. Within this setting, we prove the existence of optimal configurations under a volume constraint and show that the minimization problem is a natural generalization of that posed for regular domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05651v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Giacomini, Silvia Paparini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Caffarelli's work on elliptic free boundary problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07007v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The aim of the note is to illustrate some of the ideas introduced by Luis Caffarelli in his groundbreaking works on the regularity theory for elliptic free boundary problems, in a way which can be understood by non-experts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07007v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Camillo De Lellis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inequalities between Neumann and Dirichlet Laplacian eigenvalues on planar domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.12922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.12922v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We generalize a classical inequality between the eigenvalues of the Laplacians with Neumann and Dirichlet boundary conditions on bounded, planar domains: in 1955, Payne proved that below the $k$-th eigenvalue of the Dirichlet Laplacian there exist at least $k + 2$ eigenvalues of the Neumann Laplacian, provided the domain is convex. It has, however, been conjectured that this should hold for any domain. Here we show that the statement indeed remains true for all simply connected planar Lipschitz domains. The proof relies on a novel variational principle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.12922v2</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Rohleder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feller generators with singular drifts in the critical range</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12332v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider diffusion operator $-\Delta + b \cdot \nabla$ in $\mathbb R^d$, $d \geq 3$, with drift $b$ in a large class of locally unbounded vector fields that can have critical-order singularities. Covering the entire range of admissible magnitudes of singularities of $b$ (but excluding the borderline value), we construct a strongly continuous Feller semigroup on the space of continuous functions vanishing at infinity, thus completing a number of results on well-posedness of SDEs with singular drifts. The previous results on Feller semigroups employed strong elliptic gradient bounds and hence required the magnitude of the singularities to be less than a small dimension-dependent constant. Our approach is different and uses De Giorgi's method ran in $L^p$ for $p$ sufficiently large, hence the gain in the assumptions on singular drift.
  For the critical borderline value of the magnitude of singularities of $b$, we construct a strongly continuous semigroup in a ``critical'' Orlicz space on $\mathbb R^d$ whose local topology is stronger than the local topology of $L^p$ for any $2 \leq p&lt;\infty$ but is slightly weaker than that of $L^\infty$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12332v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Kinzebulatov, Yu. A. Semenov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
