<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 04:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Uniqueness for the Schr\"odinger equation with an inverse square potential and application to controllability and inverse problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21466v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove a sharp uniqueness result for the singular Schr\"odinger equation with an inverse square potential. This will be done without assuming geometrical restrictions on the observation region. The proof relies on a recent technique transforming the Schr\"odinger equation into an elliptic equation. We show that this technique is still applicable for singular equations. In our case, substantial difficulties arise when dealing with singular potentials of cylindrical type. Using the uniqueness result, we show the approximate controllability of the equation using a distributed control. The uniqueness result is also applied to prove the uniqueness for an inverse source problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21466v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. E. Chorfi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of backward inverse problems for degenerate mean-field game systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21541v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate inverse backward-in-time problems for a class of second-order degenerate Mean-Field Game (MFG) systems. More precisely, given the final datum $(u(\cdot, T),m(\cdot, T))$ of a solution to the one-dimensional mean-field game system with a degenerate diffusion coefficient, we aim to determine the intermediate states $(u(\cdot,t_{0}),m(\cdot,t_{0}))$ for any $t_{0} \in [0, T)$, i.e., the value function and the mean distribution at intermediate times, respectively. We prove conditional stability estimates under suitable assumptions on the diffusion coefficient and the initial state $(u(\cdot,0),m(\cdot,0))$. The proofs are based on Carleman's estimates with a simple weight function. We first prove a Carleman estimate for the Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman (HJB) equation. A second Carleman estimate will be derived for the Fokker-Planck (FP) equation. Then, by combining the two estimates, we obtain a Carleman estimate for the mean-field game system, leading to the stability of the backward problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21541v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. E. Chorfi, A. Habbal, M. Jahid, L. Maniar, A. Ratnani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universality in the Small-Dispersion Limit of the Benjamin-Ono Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21581v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine the solution of the Benjamin-Ono Cauchy problem for rational initial data in three types of double-scaling limits in which the dispersion tends to zero while simultaneously the independent variables either approach a point on one of the two branches of the caustic curve of the inviscid Burgers equation, or approach the critical point where the branches meet. The results reveal universal limiting profiles in each case that are independent of details of the initial data. We compare the results obtained with corresponding results for the Korteweg-de Vries equation found by Claeys-Grava in three papers. Our method is to analyze contour integrals appearing in an explicit representation of the solution of the Cauchy problem, in various limits involving coalescing saddle points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21581v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elliot Blackstone, Peter D. Miller, Matthew D. Mitchell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stationary self-similar profiles for the two-dimensional inviscid Boussinesq equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21765v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider ($-\alpha$)-homogeneous solutions (stationary self-similar solutions of degree $-\alpha$) to the two-dimensional inviscid Boussinesq equations in a half-plane. We show their non-existence and existence with both regular and singular profile functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21765v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ken Abe, Daniel Ginsberg, In-Jee Jeong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ideal Magnetohydrodynamics Around Couette Flow: Long Time Stability and Vorticity-Current Instability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21835v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article considers the ideal 2D magnetohydrodynamic equations on an infinite periodic channel close to a combination of an affine shear flow, called Couette flow, and a constant magnetic field. This setting combines important physical effects of mixing and coupling of velocity and magnetic field. We establish the existence and stability of the velocity and magnetic field for Gevrey-class perturbations of size $\varepsilon$, valid up to times $t \sim \varepsilon^{-1}$. Additionally, the vorticity and current grow as $O(t)$ and there is no inviscid damping of the velocity and magnetic field. This has parallels to the above threshold case for the $3D$ Navier-Stokes \cite{bedrossian2022dynamics} where growth in `streaks' leads to time scales of $t\sim \varepsilon^{-1}$. In particular, for the ideal MHD equations, our article suggests that for a wide range of initial data, the scenario ``dynamo effect $\Rightarrow $ vorticity and current growth $\Rightarrow $ vorticity and current breakdown'' leads to instability and possible turbulences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21835v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Knobel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp spectral gap for degenerated Witten Laplacian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21899v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the Witten Laplacian associated to a non-Morse potential. We prove Eyring-Kramers formulas for the bottom of the spectrum of this operator in the semiclassical regime and quantify the spectral gap between these eigenvalues and the rest of the spectrum. The main ingredient is the construction of sharp degenerated Gaussian quasimodes through an adaptation of the WKB method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21899v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lo\"is Delande</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gelfand-Type problems in Random Walk Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21927v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper deals with Gelfand-type problems
  \begin{equation}\label{Gelfand10} \qquad\qquad\left\{\begin{array}{ll} - \Delta_m u = \lambda f(u), \quad&amp;\hbox{in} \ \Omega, \ \lambda &gt;0, \\[10pt] u =0, \quad&amp;\hbox{on} \ \partial_m\Omega, \end{array} \right.
  \end{equation}
  in the framework of Random Walk Spaces, which includes as particular cases: Gelfand-type problems posed on locally finite weighted connected graphs and Gelfand-type problems driven by convolution integrable kernels. Under the same assumption on the nonlinearity $f$ as in the local case, we show there exists an extremal parameter $\lambda^* \in (0, \infty)$ such that, for $0 \leq \lambda &lt; \lambda^*$, problem \eqref{Gelfand10} admits a minimal bounded solution $u_\lambda$ and there are not solution for $\lambda &gt; \lambda^*$. Moreover, assuming $f$ is convex, we show that Problem \eqref{Gelfand10} admits a minimal bounded solution for $\lambda = \lambda^*$. We also show that $u_\lambda$ are stable, and, for $f$ strictly convex, we show that they are the unique stable solutions. We give simple examples that illustrate the many situations that can occur when solving Gelfand-type problems on weighted graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21927v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. M. Mazon, A. Molino, J. Toledo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On bifurcation from infinity: a compactification approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22146v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a scalar parabolic partial differential equation on the interval with nonlinear boundary conditions that are asymptotically linear. As the parameter crosses critical values (e.g. the Steklov eigenvalues), it is known that there are large equilibria that arise through a bifurcation from infinity (i.e., such equilibria converge, after rescaling, to the Steklov eigenfunctions). We provide a compactification approach to the study of such unbounded bifurcation curves of equilibria, their stability, and heteroclinic orbits. In particular, we construct an induced semiflow at infinity such that the Steklov eigenfunctions are equilibria. Moreover, we prove the existence of infinite-time blow-up solutions that converge, after rescaling, to certain eigenfunctions that are equilibria of the induced semiflow at infinity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22146v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e M. Arrieta, Juliana Fernandes, Phillipo Lappicy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Major symmetry of the induced tangent stiffness tensor for the Zaremba-Jaumann rate and Kirchhoff stress in hyperelasticity: two different approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22163v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We recall in this note that the induced tangent stiffness tensor $\mathbb{H}^{\text{ZJ}}_{\tau}(\tau)$ appearing in a hypoelastic formulation based on the Zaremba-Jaumann corotational derivative and the rate constitutive equation for the Kirchhoff stress tensor $\tau$ is minor and major symmetric if the Kirchhoff stress $\tau$ is derived from an elastic potential $\mathrm{W}(F)$. This result is vaguely known in the literature. Here, we expose two different notational approaches which highlight the full symmetry of the tangent stiffness tensor $\mathbb{H}^{\text{ZJ}}_{\tau}(\tau)$. The first approach is based on the direct use of the definition of each symmetry (minor and major), i.e., via contractions of the tensor with the deformation rate tensor $D$. The second approach aims at finding an absolute expression of the tensor $\mathbb{H}^{\text{ZJ}}_{\tau}(\tau)$, by means of special tensor products and their symmetrisations. In some past works, the major symmetry of $\mathbb{H}^{\text{ZJ}}_{\tau}(\tau)$ has been missed because not all necessary symmetrisations were applied. The approach is exemplified for the isotropic Hencky energy. Corresponding stability checks of software packages are shortly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22163v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salvatore Federico, Sebastian Holthausen, Nina J. Husemann, Patrizio Neff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modulational Stability of Wave Trains in the Camassa-Holm Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22219v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the nonlinear wave modulation of arbitrary amplitude periodic traveling wave solutions of the Camassa-Holm (CH) equation. Slow modulations of wave trains is often described through Whitham's theory of modulations, which at leading order models the slow evolution of the fundamental wave characteristics (such as the wave's frequency, mass and momentum) through a disperionless system of quasi-linear partial differential equations. The modulational stability or instability of such a slowly modulated wave is considered to be determined by the hyperbolicity or ellipticity of this Whitham modulation system of equations. In work by Abenda \&amp; Grava, the Whitham modulation system for the CH equation was derived through averaged Lagrangian methods and was further shown to always be hyperbolic (although strict hyperbolicity may fail). In this work, we provide an independent derivation of the Whitham modulation system for the CH equation through nonlinear WKB / multiple scales expansions. We further provide a rigorous connection between the Whitham modulation equations for the CH equation and the spectral stability of the underlying periodic wave train to localized (i.e. integrable on the line) perturbations. In particular, we prove that the strict hyperbolicity of the Whitham system implies spectral stability in a neighborhood of the origin in the spectral plane, i.e. spectral modulational stability. As an illustration of our theory, we examine the Whitham modulation system for wave trains with asymptotically small oscillations about their total mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22219v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathew A. Johnson, Jeffrey Oregero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New results for the Cahn-Hilliard equation with non-degenerate mobility: well-posedness and longtime behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22234v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the Cahn-Hilliard equation with non-degenerate concentration-dependent mobility and logarithmic potential in two dimensions. We show that any weak solution is unique, exhibits propagation of uniform-in-time regularity, and stabilizes towards an equilibrium state of the Ginzburg-Landau free energy for large times. These results improve the state of the art dating back to a work by Barrett and Blowey. Our analysis relies on the combination of enhanced energy estimates, elliptic regularity theory and tools in critical Sobolev spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22234v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Monica Conti, Pietro Galimberti, Stefania Gatti, Andrea Giorgini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Stability of Schwarzschild-Anti-de Sitter spacetimes III: Quasimodes and sharp decay of gravitational perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.21994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.21994v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this last part of the series we prove that the slow (inverse logarithmic) decay in time of solutions to the linearised Einstein equations on Schwarzschild-Anti-de Sitter backgrounds obtained in~\cite{Gra.Hol24,Gra.Hol24a} is in fact optimal by constructing quasimode solutions for the Teukolsky system. The main difficulties compared with the case of the scalar wave equation treated in earlier works arise from the first order terms in the Teukolsky equation, the coupling of the Teukolsky quantities at the conformal boundary and ensuring that the relevant quasimode solutions satisfy the Teukolsky-Starobinsky relations. The proof invokes a quasimode construction for the corresponding Regge-Wheeler system (which can be fully decoupled at the expense of a higher order boundary condition) and a reverse Chandrasekhar transformation which generates solutions of the Teukolsky system from solutions of the Regge-Wheeler system. Finally, we provide a general discussion of the well-posedness theory for the higher order boundary conditions that typically appear in the process of decoupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.21994v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olivier Graf, Gustav Holzegel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On uniqueness in structured model learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22009v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper addresses the problem of uniqueness in learning physical laws for systems of partial differential equations (PDEs). Contrary to most existing approaches, it considers a framework of structured model learning, where existing, approximately correct physical models are augmented with components that are learned from data. The main result of the paper is a uniqueness result that covers a large class of PDEs and a suitable class of neural networks used for approximating the unknown model components. The uniqueness result shows that, in the idealized setting of full, noiseless measurements, a unique identification of the unknown model components is possible as regularization-minimizing solution of the PDE system. Furthermore, the paper provides a convergence result showing that model components learned on the basis of incomplete, noisy measurements approximate the ground truth model component in the limit. These results are possible under specific properties of the approximating neural networks and due to a dedicated choice of regularization. With this, a practical contribution of this analytic paper is to provide a class of model learning frameworks different to standard settings where uniqueness can be expected in the limit of full measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22009v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Holler, Erion Morina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On weighted Ces\`{a}ro function spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22301v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The main objective of this paper is to provide a comprehensive demonstration of recent results regarding the structures of the weighted Ces\`aro and Copson function spaces. These spaces' definitions involve local and global weighted Lebesgue norms; in other words, the norms of these spaces are generated by positive sublinear operators and by weighted Lebesgue norms. The weighted Lebesgue spaces are the special cases of these spaces with a specific set of parameters.
  Our primary method of investigating these spaces will be the so-called discretization technique. Our technique will be the development of the approach initiated by K.G. Grosse-Erdmann, which allows us to obtain the characterization in previously unavailable situations, thereby addressing decades-old open problems.
  We investigate the relation (embeddings) between weighted Ces\`aro and Copson function spaces. The characterization of these embeddings can be used to tackle the problems of characterizing pointwise multipliers between weighted Ces\`aro and Copson function spaces, the characterizations of the associate spaces of Ces\`aro (Copson) function spaces, as well as the relations between local Morrey-type spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22301v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amiran Gogatishvili, Tu\u{g}\c{c}e \"Unver</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of a cross-diffusion system and approximation by repulsive random walks: a duality approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.07146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.07146v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider conservative cross-diffusion systems for two species where individual motion rates depend linearly on the local density of the other species. We develop duality estimates and obtain stability and approximation results. We first control the time evolution of the gap between two bounded solutions by means of its initial value. As a by product, we obtain a uniqueness result for bounded solutions valid for any space dimension, under a non-perturbative smallness assumption. Using a discrete counterpart of our duality estimates, we prove the convergence of random walks with local repulsion in one dimensional discrete space to cross-diffusion systems. More precisely, we prove quantitative estimates for the gap between the stochastic process and the cross-diffusion system. We give first rough but general estimates; then we use the duality approach to obtain fine estimates under less general conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.07146v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vincent Bansaye (CMAP), Ayman Moussa (LJLL), Felipe Mu\~noz-Hern\'andez (CMAP, DIM)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A thin film model for meniscus evolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.04181</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.04181v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we discuss a particular model arising from sinking of a rigid solid into a thin film of fluid, i.e. a fluid contained between two solid surfaces and part of the fluid surface is in contact with the air. The fluid is governed by Navier-Stokes equation, while the contact point, i.e. where the gas, liquid and solid meet, is assumed to be given by a constant, non-zero contact angle. We consider a scaling limit of the fluid thickness (lubrication approximation) and the contact angle between the fluid-solid and the fluid-gas interfaces is close to $\pi$. This resulting model is a free boundary problem for the equation $h_t + (h^3h_{xxx})_x = 0$, for which we have $h&gt;0$ at the contact point (different from the usual thin film equation with $h=0$ at the contact point). We show that this fourth order quasilinear (non-degenerate) parabolic equation, together with the so-called partial wetting condition at the contact point, is well-posed. Also the contact point in our thin film equation can actually move, contrary to the classical thin film equation for a droplet arising from no-slip condition. Furthermore, we show the global stability of steady state solutions in a periodic setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.04181v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amrita Ghosh, Juan J. L. Vel\'azquez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence, uniqueness and $L^2_t (H_x ^2) \cap L^\infty_t (H^1_x) \cap H^1_t (L^2_x) $ regularity of the gradient flow of the Ambrosio-Tortorelli functional</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.13645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.13645v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the gradient flow of the Ambrosio-Tortorelli functional at fixed $\epsilon&gt;0$, proving existence, uniqueness and $L^2 _t (H_x ^2) \cap L^\infty _t (H^1 _x) \cap H^1 _t (L^2 _x) $ regularity in dimension 2. In particular we improve a previous result where such regularity was known only up to a finite number of space time points, which diverged as $\epsilon \to 0$. By employing a different technique for the crucial $L^2 _t (H^2 _x)$ estimates we can see how in fact the desired regularity holds everywhere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.13645v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/cocv/2024060</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ESAIM:Control, Optimisation and Calculus of Variations 30 (2024) 70</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Cortopassi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximation and perturbations of stable solutions to a stationary mean field game system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16377v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work introduces a new general approach for the numerical analysis of stable equilibria to second order  mean field games systems in cases where the uniqueness of solutions may fail. For the sake of simplicity, we focus on a simple stationary case. We propose an abstract framework to study these solutions by reformulating the mean field game system as an abstract equation in a Banach space. In this context, stable equilibria turn out to be regular solutions to this equation, meaning that the linearized system is well-posed. We provide three applications of this property: we study the sensitivity analysis of stable solutions, establish error estimates for their finite element approximations, and prove the local converge of Newton's method in infinite dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16377v4</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jules Berry (IRMAR, INSA Rennes, UR), Olivier Ley (IRMAR), Francisco J Silva (XLIM)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp spectral gap of adaptive Langevin dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00552v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a degenerated Fokker-Planck type differential operator associated to an adaptive Langevin dynamic. We prove Eyring-Kramers formulas for the bottom of the spectrum of this operator in the low temperature regime. The main ingredients are resolvent estimates obtained via hypocoercive techniques and the construction of sharp Gaussian quasimodes through an adaptation of the WKB method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00552v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lo\"is Delande</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some Comparison Results for First-Order Hamilton-Jacobi Equations and Second-Order Fully Nonlinear Parabolic Equations with Ventcell Boundary Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01899v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we consider fully nonlinear, possibly degenerate, parabolic equations associated with Ventcell boundary conditions in bounded or unbounded, smooth domains. We first analyze the exact form of such boundary conditions in general domains in order that the notion of viscosity solutions make sense. Then we prove general comparison results under natural assumptions on the nonlinearities, assuming only that the equation is either coercive (first-order case) or strictly elliptic (second-order case) in the normal direction in a neighborhood of the boundary. Our method is inspired by the ``twin blow-up method'' of Forcadel-Imbert-Monneau and ideas of Lions-Souganidis which we extend to the framework of Ventcell boundary conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01899v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guy Barles (IDP), Emmanuel Chasseigne (IDP)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary layer expansions of the steady MHD equations in a bounded domain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09726v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the validity of boundary layer expansions for the MHD system in a rectangle. We describe the solution up to any order when the tangential magnetic field is much smaller or much larger than the tangential velocity field, thereby extending a previous work of S.J. Ding, Z.L. Lin and F. Xie.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09726v4</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongfen Bian, Zhenjie Si</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local well-posedness in the critical regularity setting for hyperbolic systems with partial diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04791v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is dedicated to the local existence theory of the Cauchy problem for a general class of symmetrizable hyperbolic partially diffusive systems (also called hyperbolic-parabolic systems) in the whole space $\mathbb{R}^d$ with $d\ge 1$. We address the question of well-posedness for large data having critical Besov regularity in the spirit of previous works by the second author on the compressible Navier-Stokes equations. Compared to the pioneering of Kawashima (S. Kawashima. Systems of a hyperbolic parabolic type with applications to the equations of magnetohydrodynamics. PhD thesis, Kyoto University, 1983) and to the more recent work by Serre (D. Serre. Local existence for viscous system of conservation laws: $H^s$-data with $s &gt; 1+d/2$. In Nonlinear partial differential equations and hyperbolic wave phenomena, volume 526 of Contemp. Math., pages 339-358. Amer. Math. Soc., Providence, RI, 2010), we take advantage of the partial parabolicity of the system to consider data in functional spaces that need not be embedded in the set of Lipschitz functions. This is in sharp contrast with the classical well-posedness theory of (multi-dimensional) hyperbolic systems where it is mandatory. A leitmotiv of our analysis is to require less regularity for the components experiencing a direct diffusion, than for the hyperbolic components. We then use an energy method that is performed on the system after spectral localization and a suitable G\r{a}rding inequality. As an example, we consider the Navier-Stokes-Fourier equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04791v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Paul Adogbo, Raph\"ael Danchin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polynomial mixing for the white-forced Navier-Stokes system in the whole space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15727v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the mixing properties of the white-forced Navier-Stokes system in the whole space $\mathbb{R}^2$. Assuming that the noise is sufficiently non-degenerate, we prove the uniqueness of stationary measure and polynomial mixing in the dual-Lipschitz metric. The proof combines the coupling method with a Foia\c{s}-Prodi type estimate, weighted growth estimates for trajectories, and an estimate for the Leray projector involving Muckenhoupt $A_2$-class weights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15727v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vahagn Nersesyan, Meng Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimates on the Laplace Operator in Heat Flows of Harmonic Maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.20419</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.20419v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we investigate estimates about the Laplace operator in heat flows of harmonic maps, focusing outside the singularities through spherical coordinates. These estimates can be used in the general Ericksen--Leslie system to obtain higher-order estimates. We consider the problem subject to the $\mathbb{T}^2$ and $\mathbb{T}^3$ boundary conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.20419v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingtong Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean-field limit of non-exchangeable systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.15406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.15406v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper deals with the derivation of the mean-field limit for multi-agent systems on a large class of sparse graphs. More specifically, the case of non-exchangeable multi-agent systems consisting of non-identical agents is addressed. The analysis does not only involve PDEs and stochastic analysis but also graph theory through a new concept of limits of sparse graphs (extended graphons) that reflect the structure of the connectivities in the network and has critical effects on the collective dynamics. In this article some of the main restrictive hypothesis in the previous literature on the connectivities between the agents (dense graphs) and the cooperation between them (symmetric interactions) are removed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.15406v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications on Pure and Applied Mathematics, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pierre-Emmanuel Jabin, David Poyato, Juan Soler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-local Boundary Value Problems, stochastic resetting and Brownian motions on graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.14135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.14135v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider dynamic boundary conditions involving non-local operators. Our analysis includes a detailed description of such operators together with their relations with random times and random (additive) functionals. We provide some new characterizations for the boundary behaviour of the Brownian motion based on the interplay between non-local operators and boundary value problems. Our main focus is on Feller-Wentzell diffusions. We first consider the instructive case of the real line, then we extend our results on star graphs with trapping points or repulsive vertices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.14135v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Bonaccorsi, Fausto Colantoni, Mirko D'Ovidio, Gianni Pagnini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deformation of a planar ferromagnetic elastic ribbon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.03447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.03447v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: While extensive studies have been conducted on purely elastic ribbons, in this paper we explore the influence of magnetisation on the deformation of planar ferromagnetic elastic ribbons. We begin the investigation by deriving the leading-order magnetic energy associated with a curved planar ferromagnetic elastic ribbon. The sum of the magnetic and the elastic energy is the total energy of the ribbon. We derive the equilibrium equations by taking the first variation of the total energy. We then systematically determine and analyse solutions to these equilibrium equations under various canonical boundary conditions. We also analyse the stability of the equilibrium solutions. Comparing our findings with the well-studied Euler's Elastica provides insights into the magnetic effects on the deformation behaviour of elastic ribbons. Our analysis contributes to a deeper understanding of the interplay between magnetisation and the mechanical response of planar ferromagnetic structures, and offers valuable insights for both theoretical and practical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.03447v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G R Krishna Chand Avatar, Vivekanand Dabade</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning equilibria in Cournot mean field games of controls</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01812v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider Cournot mean field games of controls, a model originally developed for the production of an exhaustible resource by a continuum of producers. We prove uniqueness of the solution under general assumptions on the price function. Then, we prove convergence of a learning algorithm which gives existence of a solution to the mean field games system. The learning algorithm is implemented with a suitable finite difference discretization to get a numerical method to the solution. We supplement our theoretical analysis with several numerical examples and illustrate the impacts of model parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01812v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Camilli, Mathieu Lauri\`ere, Qing Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
