<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 05:00:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse problems for time-fractional Schr\"odinger equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08701v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study some inverse problems for time-fractional Schr\"odinger equations involving the Caputo derivative of fractional order $\alpha \in (0,1)$. We prove refined uniqueness results from sets of positive Lebesgue measure for various problems by weakening the regularity of initial data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08701v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. E. Chorfi, F. Et-tahri, L. Maniar, M. Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microlocal analysis of the non-relativistic limit of the Klein--Gordon equation: Asymptotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08724</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08724v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This is the less technical half of a two-part work in which we introduce a robust microlocal framework for analyzing the non-relativistic limit of relativistic wave equations with time-dependent coefficients, focusing on the Klein--Gordon equation. Two asymptotic regimes in phase space are relevant to the non-relativistic limit: one corresponding to what physicists call ``natural'' units, in which the PDE is approximable by the free Klein--Gordon equation, and a low-frequency regime in which the equation is approximable by the usual Schr\"odinger equation. As shown in the companion paper, combining the analyses in the two regimes gives global estimates which are uniform as the speed of light goes to infinity. In this paper, we derive asymptotics from those estimates. Our framework differs from those in previous works in that ours is based on spacetime phase-space analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08724v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Hassell, Qiuye Jia, Ethan Sussman, Andras Vasy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ginzburg-Landau minimizers with high topological degrees in an annulus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08744v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by recent experiments on fermionic rings, we study the asymptotic behaviour of minimizers of the Ginzburg-Landau (GL) energy in an annulus with a Dirichlet data which depends on the GL parameter on the outer boundary. We show that there is a critical degree of order $|\ln \varepsilon|$ under which the ground state displays a giant vortex and above which minimizers exhibit a combination of a giant vortex and vortices which tend to the outer boundary as the GL parameter tends to zero. Our analysis relies on the construction of suitable upper and lower bounds, on the extension to a slightly bigger annulus and on the minimization of the mean-field energy appearing in the lower bound. In order to be able to derive the minimum of this energy we use the symmetry of the domain and criticality with respect to inner variations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08744v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amandine Aftalion, R\'emy Rodiac</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the existence of non-negative weak solutions for $1D$ fourth order equations of gradient flow type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08776v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider a family of one-dimensional fourth order evolution equations arising as gradient flows of the Korteweg energy, i.e. the $L^2$-norm of the first derivative of some power of the density. This family of equations generalizes the Quantum-Drift-Diffusion equation and the Thin-Film equation. We prove the global-in-time existence of {\em non-negative} weak solutions without requiring any upper bound on the exponent of the power of the density in the energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08776v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefanos Georgiadis, Stefano Spirito</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Doubling variables and uniqueness of probability solutions to degenerate stationary Kolmogorov equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08781v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We obtain sufficient conditions for the uniqueness of a probability solution to the stationary Kolmogorov equation with a degenerate diffusion matrix. We employ the method of doubling variables known in stochastic analysis directly to the Kolmogorov equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08781v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. I. Bogachev, S. V. Shaposhnikov, D. V. Shatilovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a partial data inverse problem for the semi-linear wave equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08794v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that a partial Dirichlet-to-Neumann map, where the measurement set is arbitrarily small, uniquely determines the time-dependent nonlinearity of order three or higher in a semi-linear wave equation up to natural obstructions on a Lorentzian manifold with boundary. In particular, we do not impose any geometric or size restrictions on the measurement set. The proof relies on the technique of higher order linearization combined with the construction of Gaussian beams with reflections on the boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08794v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boya Liu, Weinan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An existence theory for solitary waves on a ferrofluid jet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08799v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss axisymmetric solitary waves on the surface of an otherwise cylindrical ferrofluid jet surrounding a stationary metal rod. The ferrofluid, which is governed by a general (nonlinear) magnetisation law, is subject to an azimuthal magnetic field generated by an electric current flowing along the rod. We treat the governing equations using a modification of the Zakharov-Craig-Sulem formulation for water waves, reducing the problem to a single nonlocal equation for the free-surface elevation variable $\eta$. The nonlocality in the equation takes the form of a Dirichlet-Neumann operator whose analyticity (in standard function spaces) is demonstrated by studying its defining boundary-value problem in newly introduced Sobolev spaces for radial functions.\ Using rudimentary fixed-point arguments and Fourier analysis we rigorously reduce the equation for $\eta$ to a perturbation of a Korteweg-de Vries equation (for strong surface tension) or a nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger equation (for weak surface tension), both of which have nondegenerate explicit solitary-wave solutions. The existence theory is completed using an appropriate version of the implicit-function theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08799v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark D. Groves, Dag Nilsson, Leon Sch\"utz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singularly Weighted X-ray Tensor Tomography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08871v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: If $d$ is a boundary defining function for the Euclidean unit disk and $I$ denotes the geodesic X-ray transform, for $\gamma\in (-1,1)$, we study the singularly-weighted X-ray transforms $I_m d^\gamma$ acting on symmetric $m$-tensors. For any $m$, we provide a sharp range decomposition and characterization in terms of a distinguished Hilbert basis of the data space, that comes from earlier studies of the Singular Value Decomposition for the case $m=0$. Since for $m\ge 1$, the transform considered has an infinite-dimensional kernel, we fully characterize this kernel, and propose a representative for an $m$-tensor to be reconstructed modulo kernel, along with efficient procedures to do so. This representative is based on a new generalization of the potential/conformal/transverse-tracefree decomposition of tensor fields in the context of singularly weighted $L^2$-topologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08871v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Kay, Fran\c{c}ois Monard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well-posedness for a diffuse interface model of non-Newtonian two-phase flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08876v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The evolution of two partially miscible, nonhomogeneous, incompressible viscous fluids of non-Newtonian type, can be governed by the Navier-Stokes-Cahn-Hilliard system. In the present work, we prove the global existence of weak solutions for the case of initial density containing zero and the concentration depending viscosity with free energy potential equal to the Landau potential in a bounded domain of three dimensions. Furthermore, we show that a strong solutions exist locally in time in the case of three dimensions periodic domain ${\mathbb T}^3.$ The proof relies on a suitable semi-Galerkin scheme and the monotonicity method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08876v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fang Li, Duan Xingyu, Guo Zhenhua</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular solutions and bifurcation diagram of semilinear elliptic equations with general nonlinearity in two dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate semilinear elliptic equations with general exponential-type nonlinearities in two dimensions. For such nonlinearities, we establish two main results. The first is the construction of a singular solution. Recently, Fujishima, Ioku, Ruf, and Terraneo [10] proved the existence of singular solutions under certain assumptions for nonlinearities. We succeed in relaxing these conditions by providing the precise asymptotic form of a singular solution. Our second result concerns the bifurcation diagram of regular solutions. While the bifurcation structure has been extensively studied in three or higher dimensions, comparatively little was known in two dimensions until recently. In [18], the second author proved that the bifurcation curve possesses infinitely many turning points for supercritical analytic nonlinearities. In the present work, we refine this analysis by showing the bifurcation curve oscillates infinitely many times around some point, without assuming analyticity of the nonlinearities. The novelty of our approach lies in the introduction of a generalized Emden-type transformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08961v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroaki Kikuchi, Kenta Kumagai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Propagation of chaos for the Landau equation via microcanonical binary collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a fully constructive, conservative, and collision-level realization of Kac's program for the spatially homogeneous Landau equation across the full interaction range, including the Coulomb case. Our model is the microcanonical binary-collision (MBC) process: a reversible pure-jump $N$-particle Markov process that is Landau-native, realizing the grazing-collision mechanism via small conservative rotations of relative velocities. The analysis hinges on two critical structural pillars: a Fisher-information dissipation mechanism that extends the Guill\'en--Silvestre paradigm (Acta Math. 234:315-375, 2025) to a genuinely conservative particle system, yielding robust control of singular configurations, and a quantitative self-averaging principle that enforces a coherent deterministic emergence of the Landau flow from the microscopic dynamics. We prove propagation of chaos in the joint mean-field and grazing-collision limit ($N\to\infty, h\to 0$), identifying any limit point with the unique global solution to the Landau equation. Furthermore, we rigorously derive the Landau master equation as the grazing-collision limit of the MBC process. To the best of our knowledge, this provides the first fully conservative, Landau-native binary-collision model rigorously shown to produce the Landau equation over the entire interaction range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09035v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A few techniques to achieve invisibility in waveguides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09172v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this lecture is to consider a concrete problem, namely the identification of situations of invisibility in waveguides, to present techniques and tools that may be useful in various fields of applied mathematics. To be more specific, we will be interested in the propagation of acoustic waves in guides which are unbounded in one direction. In general, the diffraction of an incident field in such a structure in presence of an obstacle generates a reflection and a transmission characterized by some scattering coefficients. Our goal will be to play with the geometry, the frequency and/or the index material to control these scattering coefficients. We will explain how to:
  - develop a continuation method based on the use of shape derivatives to construct invisible defects;
  - exploit complex resonances located closed to the real axis to hid obstacles;
  - construct a non self-adjoint operator whose eigenvalues coincide with frequencies such that there are incident fields whose energy is completely transmitted.
  Our approaches will mainly rely on techniques of asymptotic analysis as well as spectral theory for self-adjoint and non self-adjoint operators. Most of the results will be illustrated by numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09172v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Chesnel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Dirichlet problem for the degenerate $k$-Hessian equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09205v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the existence of a global $C^{1,1}$ solution to the Dirichlet problem for the $k$-Hessian equation with a nonnegative right-hand side $f$, focusing on the required conditions for $f$. A well-known counterexample demonstrates the sharpness of the condition $f^{1/(k-1)}\in C^{1,1}(\overline{\Omega_{0}})$ with $f\geq0$ in a domain $\Omega_{0}\Supset\Omega$. We establish the existence for all $2\leq k\leq n-1$ under the condition $f^{1/(k-1)}\in C^{1,1}(\overline{\Omega_{0}})$ with $f\geq0$ in $\Omega_{0}$, and under an a priori assumption that $\Delta u\geq1$. Surprisingly, higher smoothness of $f$ permits a better exponent to be achieved. The condition $f^{3/(2k-2)}\in C^{2,1}(\overline{\Omega_{0}})$ with $f\geq0$ in $\Omega_{0}$ is also sharp, as demonstrated by the same counterexample. For the Monge-Amp\`ere equation (the case $k=n$), we establish the existence under the optimal condition $f^{3/(2n-2)}\in C^{2,1}(\overline{\Omega_{0}})$ with $f\geq0$ in $\Omega_{0}$. For any $5\leq k\leq n-1$, we prove the existence under the condition $f^{3/(2k-2)}\in C^{2,1}(\overline{\Omega_{0}})$ with $f\geq0$ in $\Omega_{0}$, and under the a priori assumption $\Delta u\geq1$. Moreover, we obtain the existence for all $2\leq k\leq n-1$ under the condition $f^{3/(2k)}\in C^{2,1}(\overline{\Omega_{0}})$ with $f\geq0$ in $\Omega_{0}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09205v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yasheng Lyu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Fractional Anisotropic Musielak-Sobolev Spaces with Applications to Nonlocal Eigenvalue Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09256v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce and study a new class of fractional modular function spaces, called \emph{Fractional Anisotropic Musielak--Sobolev Spaces}, which generalize both the fractional Anisotropic Orlicz--Sobolev spaces and the Anisotropic fractional Sobolev spaces with variable exponent. These spaces are designed to handle anisotropic and heterogeneous behaviors that naturally arise in nonlocal and nonlinear models. We develop their fundamental properties and embedding results, establishing a solid variational framework. As an application, we investigate a class of nonlocal anisotropic eigenvalue problems involving variable growth and direction-dependent fractional integro-differential operators. We prove the existence of eigenvalues by means of critical point theory and modular analysis. Our results extend and unify several existing models in the theory of nonlocal partial differential equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09256v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Srati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Dirac equations on noncompact quantum graphs with potentials: Multiplicity and Concentration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09285v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the existence and multiplicity of solutions to the following class of nonlinear Dirac equations (NLDE) on noncompact quantum graphs:
  \[
  -i\,\varepsilon c\,\sigma_1\,\partial_x u + m c^2 \sigma_3 u + V(x)\,u = f(|u|)\,u, \quad x\in \mathcal{G}, \tag{P}
  \]
  where \(V:\mathcal{G}\to\mathbb{R}\) and \(f:\mathbb{R}\to\mathbb{R}\) are continuous, \(\varepsilon&gt;0\) is a semiclassical parameter, \(m&gt;0\) denotes the mass, and \(c&gt;0\) the speed of light. Here \(\sigma_1,\sigma_3\) are Pauli matrices, and \(\mathcal{G}\) is a noncompact quantum graph. We prove that when \(\varepsilon\) is sufficiently small, the number of solutions to \((P)\) is at least the number of global minima of \(V\).
  Moreover, these solutions exhibit semiclassical concentration: as \(\varepsilon\to0\), their concentration points approach the set of global minima of \(V\).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09285v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guangze Gu, Ziwei Li, Michael Ruzhansky, Zhipeng Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Singular Limit in Hibler's Sea Ice Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09327v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish the existence of energy-driven solutions to the momentum balance equation in Hibler's sea ice model. As a main novelty and different from previous results, we deal with the singular limit and therefore cover the true unregularized Hibler stress. To this end, we introduce an energy-based notion of solution that is able to capture plasticity effects of sea ice. This requires certain relaxations of the Hibler energies and, by the different function space set-up, comes with novel challenges. In particular, we establish a bulk approximation result of the boundary terms in the evolutionary relaxed Hibler energies. This is achieved by developing a novel reduction scheme for nonlinear trace expressions which should be of independent interest. Finally, based on our main results, we classify our findings within a broader concept of solutions that is applicable to the non-constant mass case too.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09327v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert Denk, Franz Gmeineder, Matthias Hieber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular, finite-time $L^2$ attractors for odd, smooth solutions of Burgers equation on the torus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09528v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we show that the positive multiples of a particular function $F$ -- which is singular with a jump discontinuity at the origin -- are finite-time global attractors in $L^2$ for generic odd, smooth solutions of the one dimensional inviscid Burgers equation. Furthermore, the identity that leads to this result provides to an alternative proof of finite-time blowup for the fractal Burgers equation in the supercritical range $0&lt;\alpha&lt;\frac{1}{2}$. This proof is based on lower bounds on a Lyapunov functional given by the inner product of the solution with the global attractor $F$. We will also show that this property holds for a broader class of odd functions that are strictly increasing on $(0,\pi)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09528v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evan Miller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instantaneous Type~I blow-up and non-uniqueness of smooth solutions of the Navier--Stokes equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09556v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For any smooth, divergence-free initial data, we construct a solution of the Navier--Stokes equations that exhibits Type~I blow-up of the $L^\infty$ norm at time $T_*&gt;0$, while remaining smooth in space and time on $\mathbb T^d\times([0,T]\setminus\{T_*\})$. An instantaneous injection of energy from infinite wavenumber initiates a bifurcation from the classical solution, producing an infinite family of spatially smooth solutions with the same data and thereby violating uniqueness of the Cauchy problem. A key ingredient is the first known construction of a complete inverse energy cascade realized by a classical Navier--Stokes flow, which transfers energy from infinitely high to low frequencies. The result holds in all dimensions $d\geq2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09556v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey Cheskidov, Mimi Dai, Stan Palasek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comments on the paper `Modelling and nonclassical symmetry analysis of a complex porous media flow in a dilating channel'</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08656v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Comments are devoted to the recently published paper 'Modelling and nonclassical symmetry analysis of a complex porous media flow in a dilating channel' (Physica D. 481 (2025) 134834), in which a model describing an unsteady two-dimensional viscous incompressible fluid flow through a porous medium is studied. The main theoretical results of that study consists of finding Lie and nonclassical symmetries of a fourth-order PDE, which was derived by simplification of the given model. Here it is shown that the main theoretical results derived therein are incomplete and misleading.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08656v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman Cherniha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundedness for the wave equation on $C^1$ stationary axisymmetric perturbations of Kerr</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08751v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: On the full range of sub-extremal Kerr exterior spacetimes we give a new proof of energy boundedness for high-frequency projections of solutions to the wave equation onto trapped frequencies. A key feature of the new estimate is that it circumvents the use of an integrated local energy decay (ILED) statement. As an illustration of the robustness of the estimate, we use it to establish energy boundedness for solutions to the wave equation on stationary and axisymmetric metrics which are merely $C^1$ close to a sub-extremal Kerr spacetime. We show explicitly that such perturbed metrics may possess stably trapped null geodesics, and thus one does not expect ILED statements to hold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08751v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yakov Shlapentokh-Rothman, Mihai Tohaneanu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence and uniqueness of solutions to SDEs with state-dependent variable exponent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08882v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a time-inhomogeneous, nonlinear stochastic differential equation whose drift and diffusion terms involve state-dependent variable exponents. This novel structure introduces flexibility, allowing the system to adapt dynamically to its current state and better capture real-world phenomena compared to classical models such as GBM and CEV. While this flexibility enhances modeling accuracy, it also creates analytical challenges. Using a fixed-point approach, we establish existence and uniqueness under suitable conditions. The model generalizes GBM and CEV while exhibiting distinct behavior for small states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08882v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mustafa Avci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rademacher's Theorem for Calderon-Zygmund-type Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09159v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Rademacher's Theorem is a classical result stating that a Lipschitz function on $\mathbb{R}^d$ possesses a total differential almost everywhere. This implies that if $f$ is a function defined on $\mathbb{R}^d$ belonging to the Calder\'on--Zygmund space $T^\infty_1(x)$ for every $x \in \mathbb{R}^d$, then $f \in t^\infty_1(x)$ for almost every $x \in \mathbb{R}^d$.
  The main purpose of this paper is to extend this property to a broader functional framework. More precisely, we replace the Lipschitz condition by the assumption that $f$ belongs to a general weighted Calder\'on--Zygmund space $T^p_{\phi}(x)$ for $x \in E$, where $E$ is a measurable subset of $\mathbb{R}^d$ and $\phi$ is a weight with fractional indices. We then show that, under suitable assumptions, the function belongs to $t^p_{\phi}(x)$ for almost every $x \in E$.
  The result can be obtained either by imposing additional hypotheses or by working within a suitably adapted $t^p_{\phi}$ space. Whenever relevant, we also provide counterexamples illustrating the sharpness and the limitations of the statement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09159v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Lamby</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The exterior Steklov problem for Euclidean domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09490v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the Steklov eigenvalue problem in an exterior Euclidean domain. First, we present several formulations of this problem and establish the equivalences between them. Next, we examine various properties of the exterior Steklov eigenvalues and eigenfunctions. One of our main findings is an Escobar-type lower bound for the first exterior Steklov eigenvalue on convex domains in dimensions three and higher. This bound is expressed in terms of the principal curvatures of the boundary and is sharp, with equality attained for a ball. Moreover, it implies the existence of a sequence of convex domains with fixed volume and the first exterior Steklov eigenvalues tending to infinity. This contrasts with the interior case, as well as with the two-dimensional exterior case, for which we show that an analogue of the Weinstock isoperimetric inequality holds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09490v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Bundrock, Alexandre Girouard, Denis S. Grebenkov, Michael Levitin, Iosif Polterovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Formation of Apparent Horizons due to Boundary Effect in Vacuum Einstein Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09508v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that an apparent horizon can form as a result of Einsteinian evolution in pure vacuum spacetime starting from regular initial data free of apparent horizons due to pure boundary effects. We adapt a Cauchy-double-null framework and use the boundary generalized mean curvature condition for the existence of an interior apparent horizon imposed by the author S-T Yau in \cite{yau}. In particular, we prove that the condition of \cite{yau} can be met dynamically starting from a configuration that does not verify the same through a focusing mechanism. This is the first part of a two-part sequence, and in the sequel, we will focus on explicitly constructing the Cauchy data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09508v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Puskar Mondal, Shing-Tung Yau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Level sets of solutions to the stationary Hamilton-Jacobi equation are John regular</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17635v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $u$ be the unique nonnegative viscosity solution of the Hamilton-Jacobi equation $H(x,\nabla u)=0$ in the external domain ${\mathbb R}^{ n} \setminus K$ with $u=0$ on $K$. Under general conditions on $H$, we prove that all sublevels of $u$ are John domains. Moreover, if $K$ itself is a John domain, we provide a uniform lower bound on the John constant of all sublevels. We exhibit counterexamples showing that John regularity is sharp in this setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17635v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elisa Davoli, Ulisse Stefanelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A priori bounds for 2-d generalised Parabolic Anderson Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.05544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.05544v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show a priori bounds for solutions to $(\partial_t - \Delta) u = \sigma (u) \xi$ in finite volume in the framework of Hairer's Regularity Structures [Invent Math 198:269--504, 2014]. We assume $\sigma \in C_b^2 (\mathbb{R})$ and that $\xi$ is of negative H\"older regularity of order $- 1 - \kappa$ where $\kappa &lt; \bar{\kappa}$ for an explicit $\bar{\kappa}&lt; 1/3$, and that it can be lifted to a model in the sense of Regularity Structures. Our main results guarantee non-explosion of the solution in finite time and a growth which is at most polynomial in $t &gt; 0$. Our estimates imply global well-posedness for the 2-d generalised parabolic Anderson model on the torus, as well as for the parabolic quantisation of the Sine-Gordon Euclidean Quantum Field Theory (EQFT) on the torus in the regime $\beta^2 \in (4 \pi, (1 + \bar{\kappa}) 4 \pi)$. We also consider the parabolic quantisation of a massive Sine-Gordon EQFT and derive estimates that imply the existence of the measure for the same range of $\beta$. Finally, our estimates apply to It\^o SPDEs in the sense of Da Prato-Zabczyk [Stochastic Equations in Infinite Dimensions, Enc. Math. App., Cambridge Univ. Press, 1992] and imply existence of a stochastic flow beyond the trace-class regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.05544v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ajay Chandra, Guilherme de Lima Feltes, Hendrik Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trend to equilibrium and hypoelliptic regularity for the relativistic Fokker-Planck equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15139v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the relativistic, spatially inhomogeneous Fokker-Planck equation with an external confining potential. We prove the exponential time decay of solutions towards the global equilibrium in weighted $L^2$ and Sobolov spaces. Our result holds for a wide class of external potentials and the estimates on the rate of convergence are explicit and constructive. Moreover, we prove that the associated semigroup of the equation has hypoelliptic regularizing properties and we obtain explicit rates on this regularization. The technique is based on the construction of suitable Lyapunov functionals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15139v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Arnold, Gayrat Toshpulatov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the principle of linearized stability for quasilinear evolution equations in time-weighted spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13940v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quasilinear (and semilinear) parabolic problems of the form $v'=A(v)v+f(v)$ with strict inclusion $\mathrm{dom}(f)\subsetneq \mathrm{dom}(A)$ of the domains of the function $v\mapsto f(v)$ and the quasilinear part $v\mapsto A(v)$ are considered in the framework of time-weighted function spaces. This allows one to establish the principle of linearized stability in intermediate spaces lying between $\mathrm{dom}(f)$ and $\mathrm{dom}(A)$ and yields a greater flexibility with respect to the phase space for the evolution. In applications to differential equations such intermediate spaces may correspond to critical spaces exhibiting a scaling invariance. Several examples are provided to demonstrate the applicability of the results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13940v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bogdan-Vasile Matioc, Lina Sophie Schmitz, Christoph Walker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contractivity of Wasserstein distance and exponential decay for the Landau equation with Maxwellian molecules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13802v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Following the breakthrough work of Guillen and Silvestre \cite{GS24}, that shows that the Fisher information is monotonically decreasing for solutions to the homogeneous Landau equation, we study, for the same equation, the monotonicity properties of other physically relevant functionals. In the case of Maxwellian molecules, we show that the relative $L^2$ norm with respect to the equilibrium decays exponentially fast in time and is monotonically decreasing after some time. Moreover, still for the Maxwellian case, we provide a novel and short quantitative proof of time monotonicity of the entropic Wasserstein metric. For soft potentials, we show that the Wasserstein metric is contractive, conditional to $L^1(0,T,L^p(\mathbb{R}^3))$ bound for the solution. This result provides an alternative proof of the Fournier and Fournier-Guerin uniqueness theorem in \cite{fournier2009well_posedness_soft_potentials} \cite{fournier2010uniqueness_Coulomb}</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13802v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. -U. Caja-Lopez, M. G. Delgadino, M. -P. Gualdani, M. Taskovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ill-posedness and inviscid limit of basic equations of fluid dynamics in Besov spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02247v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the Cauchy problem to the basic equations of fluid dynamics on the torus. Our aim of this paper is two fold. Firstly, we construct a new initial data and present a simple proof of the ill-posedness of $B^s_{p,\infty}$ solution of the Euler equations and the surface quasi-geostrophic equation, which covers the result obtained by Cheskidov and Shvydkoy in \cite[Proc. Amer. Math. Soc. 138 (2010)]{CS} and Misio{\l}ek and Yoneda in \cite{MY}. Secondly, we prove the failure of the $B^s_{p,\infty}$-convergence in the inviscid limit for both the Navier-Stokes equations and the surface quasi-geostrophic equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02247v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinlu Li, Xing Wu, Yanghai Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Stability of multi-solitons for $1$d Supercritical NLS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03637v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Consider the one-dimensional $L^2$ supercritical nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation \begin{equation} i\partial_{t}\psi+\partial^{2}_{x}\psi+\vert \psi\vert^{2k}\psi=0 \text{, $k&gt;2$}. \end{equation} It is well known that solitary waves for this equation are unstable. In the pioneering work of Krieger and Schlag \cite{KriegerSchlag}, the asymptotic stability of a solitary wave was established on a codimension-one center-stable manifold. In the present paper, using linear estimates developed for one-dimensional matrix charge transfer models in our previous work, \cite{dispanalysis1}, we prove asymptotic stability of multi-solitons on a finite-codimension manifold for $k&gt;\frac{11}{4}.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03637v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gong Chen, Abdon Moutinho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entropy-energy solutions for Thermo-Visco-Elastic systems with Mr\'oz-type inelastic behavior</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04152</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04152v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we study a thermodynamically consistent thermo-visco-elastic model describing the balance of internal energy in a heat-conducting inelastic body. In the considered problem, the temperature dependence appears in both the elastic and inelastic constitutive relations. For such a system, we introduce the concept of a weak entropy-energy solution, which satisfies the entropy equality instead of the internal energy equation. Although the model does not possess any mathematically favorable structural properties, such as Kelvin-Voigt type effects or simplifications eliminating temperature from the constitutive relations, we prove the global-in-time existence of weak entropy-energy solutions for large initial data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04152v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomasz Cie\'slak, Sebastian Owczarek, Karolina Wielgos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic representation of solutions for the parabolic Cauchy problem with variable exponent coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00773v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we prove existence and uniqueness of a bounded viscosity solution for the Cauchy problem of degenerate parabolic equations with variable exponent coefficients. We construct the solution directly using the stochastic representation, then verify it satisfies the Cauchy problem. The corresponding SDE, on the other hand, allows the drift and diffusion coefficients to respond nonlinearly to the current state through the state-dependent variable exponents, and thus, extends the expressive power of classical SDEs to better capture complex dynamics. To validate our theoretical framework, we conduct comprehensive numerical experiments comparing finite difference solutions (Crank-Nicolson on logarithmic grids) with Monte Carlo simulations of the SDE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00773v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mustafa Avci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Factorization method for the biharmonic scattering problem for an absorbing penetrable scatterer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05711v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work extends the factorization method to the inverse scattering problem of reconstructing the shape and location of an absorbing penetrable scatterer embedded in a thin infinite elastic (Kirchhoff--Love) plate. With the assumption that the plate thickness is small compared to the wavelength of the incident wave, the propagation of flexural perturbations is modeled by the two--dimensional biharmonic wave equation in the frequency domain. Within this setting, we provide a rigorous justification of the factorization method and demonstrate that it yields a binary criterion for distinguishing whether a sampling point lies inside or outside the scatterer, using only the spectral data of the far--field operator. In addition, we numerically analyze the Born approximation for weak scatterers in this biharmonic scattering context and compute the relative error against exact far--field data for sample weak scatterers, thereby quantifying its validity as a limited but useful approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05711v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Ceja Ayala, Isaac Harris, General Ozochiawaeze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on the a.e. second-order differentiability of rank-one convex functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08397v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the Euclidean setting, the well-known Alexandrov theorem states that convex functions are twice differentiable almost everywhere. In this note, we extend this theorem to rank-one convex functions. Our approach is novel in that it draws more from viscosity techniques developed in the context of fully nonlinear elliptic equations. As a byproduct, the original Alexandrov theorem can essentially be reduced to the a.e. differentiability of one-dimensional monotone functions, as presented in the appendix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08397v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Hirsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse Source Problem for a Nonlinear Parabolic Equation via Paralinearization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08460v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This thesis investigates an inverse source problem for a semilinear parabolic equation that includes both a quadratic reaction and a convection-type nonlinearity depending on the unknown function and its gradient. Based on partial boundary observations of the time derivative and its spatial gradient on a nonempty portion of the boundary, together with interior data at a fixed time, the goal is to recover an unknown spatial source term. On a short time interval, the nonlinear part is treated by Bony paralinearization technique, which transforms the original nonlinear problem into a linear parabolic equation with small, bounded coefficients and a negligible remainder term. By differentiating the equation with respect to time, a linearized model for the time derivative of the solution is obtained, which is suitable for the application of Carleman estimates. Using these tools, the work establishes conditional stability of Holder-logarithmic type for the recovery of the source term under the same observation geometry as in the corresponding linear case. The analysis combines techniques from Littlewood-Paley theory, Besov space estimates, and Carleman inequalities, showing that the stability structure of the linear inverse source problem extends naturally to the nonlinear setting under smallness and short-time assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08460v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hu Xirui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient flow structure, well-posedness and asymptotic behavior of Fokker-Planck equation on locally finite graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03531v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the gradient flow structure, well-posedness, and asymptotic behavior of the Fokker-Planck equation defined on locally uniformly finite graphs, which is highly non-trivial compared with the finite case. We first construct a 2-Wasserstein-type metric and gradient flow equation in the probability density space associated with the underlying graphs. Then, we prove the global existence of solution to the Fokker-Planck equation using a novel approach that differs significantly from the methods applied in the finite case. We also demonstrate that the solution converges to the Gibbs distribution in the $\ell^{r}(V,\bm{\pi})$ norm with $r\in [2,\infty]$, by using the indicator set partitioning method. To the best of our knowledge, this work seems the first result on the study of Wasserstein-type metrics and the Fokker-Planck equation in probability density spaces defined on infinite graphs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03531v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A proof of Onsager's conjecture for the stochastic 3D Euler equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06915v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the stochastic 3D Euler equations on a periodic domain $\mathbb{T}^3$, driven by a $GG^*$-Wiener process $B$ of trace class:
  \begin{align*}
  \mathrm{d} u+\mathrm{div}(u\otimes u)\,\mathrm{d} t+\nabla p\,\mathrm{d}t=\mathrm{d}B, \quad \mathrm{div} u=0.
  \end{align*} First, for any $\vartheta&lt;1/3$, we construct infinitely many global-in-time probabilistically strong and analytically weak solutions $u\in C([0,\infty),C^{\vartheta}(\mathbb{T}^3,\mathbb{R}^3))$. These solutions dissipate the energy pathwisely up to a stopping time $\mathfrak{t}$, which can be chosen arbitrarily large with high probability, i.e. it holds almost surely
  \begin{align*}
  \|u(t\wedge\mathfrak{t})\|_{L^2}^2&lt; \|u(s\wedge\mathfrak{t})\|_{L^2}^2 +2 \int_{s\wedge\mathfrak{t}}^{t\wedge\mathfrak{t}} \big\langle u(r), \mathrm{d} B(r) \big\rangle +\mathrm{Tr}\big(GG^*\big) (t\wedge\mathfrak{t}-s\wedge\mathfrak{t}),
  \end{align*}
  for any $0\leq s &lt; t&lt;\infty$. We also provide a brief proof of energy conservation for $\vartheta&gt;1/3$ based on \cite{CET94}, thereby confirming the Onsager theorem for the stochastic 3D Euler equations. Second, let $0&lt;\bar{\vartheta}&lt;\bar{\beta}&lt;1/3$, we construct infinitely many global-in-time probabilistically strong and analytically weak solutions in $C([0,\infty),C^{\bar{\vartheta}}(\mathbb{T}^3,\mathbb{R}^3))$ for arbitrary divergence-free initial data in $C^{\bar{\beta}}(\mathbb{T}^3,\mathbb{R}^3)$. Our construction relies on the convex integration method developed in the deterministic setting by \cite{Ise18}, adapting it to the stochastic context by introducing a novel energy inequality into the convex integration scheme and combining stochastic analysis arguments with a Wong--Zakai type estimate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06915v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huaxiang L\"u, Lin L\"u, Rongchan Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Riemann wave superpositions obtained from the Euler system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09576v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The paper contains an analysis of the conditions for the existence of elastic versus non-elastic wave superpositions governed by the Euler system in (1+1)-dimensions. A review of recently obtained results is presented including the introduction of the notion of quasi-rectifiability of vector fields and its application to both elastic and non-elastic wave superpositions. It is shown that the smallest real Lie algebra containing vector fields associated with the waves admitted by the Euler system is isomorphic to an infinite-dimensional Lie algebra which is the semi-direct sum of an Abelian ideal and the three-dimensional real Lie algebra K+ or K-. The maximal module corresponding to the Euler system can be transformed by an angle preserving transformation to a real algebra isomorphic to the Lie algebras K+, K-. The algebras K+ and K- are quasirectifiable and describe the behavior of wave superpositions. Based on these facts, we are able to find a parametrization of the region of non-elastic wave superpositions which allows for the construction of the reduced form of the Euler system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09576v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>{\L}ukasz Chomienia, Alfred Michel Grundland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fast integral methods for the Neumann Green's function: applications to capture and signaling problems in two dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08458v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a high order numerical method for the solution of the Neumann Green's function in two dimensions. For a general closed planar curve, our computational method resolves both the interior and exterior Green's functions with the source placed either in the bulk or on the surface -- yielding four distinct functions. Our method exactly represents the singular nature of the Green's function by decomposing the singular and regular components. In the case of the interior function, we exactly prescribe an integral constraint which is necessary to obtain a unique solution given the arbitrary constant solution associated with Neumann boundary conditions. Our implementation is based on a fast integral method for the regular part of the Green's function which allows for a rapid and high order discretization for general domains. We demonstrate the accuracy of our method for simple geometries such as disks and ellipses where closed form solutions are available. To exhibit the usefulness of these new routines, we demonstrate several applications to open problems in the capture of Brownian particles, specifically, how the small traps or boundary windows should be configured to maximize the capture rate of Brownian particles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08458v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Nov 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanchita Chakraborty, Jeremy Hoskins, Alan E. Lindsay</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
