<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 05:00:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Regularity for minimizers of degenerate, non-autonomous, orthotropic integral functionals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04281</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04281v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the higher differentiability of integer order of locally bounded minimizers of integral functionals of the form \begin{equation*}
  \mathcal{F}(u,\Omega):= \,\sum_{i=1}^{n} \dfrac{1}{p_i}\displaystyle \int_\Omega \, a_i(x) \lvert u_{x_i} \rvert^{p_i} dx- \int_\Omega \omega(x)u(x) dx, \end{equation*} where the exponents $ p_i \geq 2 $ and the coefficients $ a_i(x) $ satisfy a suitable Sobolev regularity. The main novelty consists in dealing with non-autonomous, anisotropic functionals, which depend also on the solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04281v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio Giuseppe Grimaldi, Stefania Russo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusive limit of the Boltzmann equation around Rayleigh profile in the half space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04403v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper concerns the diffusive limit of the time evolutionary Boltzmann equation in the half space $\mathbb{T}^2\times\mathbb{R}^+$ for a small Knudsen number $\varepsilon&gt;0$. For boundary conditions in the normal direction, it involves diffuse reflection moving with a tangent velocity proportional to $\varepsilon$ on the wall, whereas the far field is described by a global Maxwellian with zero bulk velocity. The incompressible Navier-Stokes equations, as the corresponding formal fluid dynamic limit, admit a specific time-dependent shearing solution known as the Rayleigh profile, which accounts for the effect of the tangentially moving boundary on the flow at rest in the far field. Using the Hilbert expansion method, for well-prepared initial data we construct the Boltzmann solution around the Rayleigh profile without initial singularity over any finite time interval.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04403v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongxu Chen, Renjun Duan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on lifespan estimates for higher-order parabolic equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04428v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the lifespan of solutions to the higher-order semilinear parabolic equation $$u_t+(-\Delta)^m u=|u|^p, \quad x \in \mathbb{R}^n, t&gt;0 $$ with initial data. We focus on the precise asymptotic behavior of the lifespan of nontrivial solutions. By combining the test function method and semigroup estimates, we derive both upper and lower bounds for the lifespan of solutions $$T_{\varepsilon} \simeq \left\{\begin{array}{l}\varepsilon^{-\left(\frac{1}{p-1}-\frac{n}{2m}\right)^{-1}}, \,\, 1&lt;p&lt;p_{\text {Fuj}}, \\ \exp\left(\varepsilon^{-(p-1)}\right), \,\, p=p_{\text {Fuj}},\end{array}\right.$$ where $p_{Fuj}=1+\frac{2m}{n}$ is the critical exponent of Fujita. These estimates refine and extend the earlier results of Caristi-Mitidieri [J. Math. Anal. Appl., 279:2 (2003), 710-722] and Sun [Electron. J. Differential Equations, 17 (2010)], who obtained only upper bounds under slowly decaying initial data assumptions. In our setting, the above condition on the initial data is replaced by the assumption $L^1\cap L^\infty$, which sharpens the results of the aforementioned works.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04428v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nurdaulet N. Tobakhanov, Berikbol T. Torebek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irreversibility condition and stability of equilibria in the inverse-deformation approach to fracture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04479v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive the irreversibility condition in fracture for the inverse-deformation approach using the second law of thermodynamics. We consider the problem of brittle failure in an elastic bar previously solved in (Rosakis et al 2021). Despite the presence of a non-zero interfacial/surface energy, the third derivative of the inverse-deformation map is discontinuous at the crack faces. This is due to the presence of the inequality constraint ensuring the inverse strain is nonnegative and the orientation of matter is preserved. A change in the material location of a crack results in negative entropy production, violating the second law. Consequently, such changes are disallowed giving the irreversibility condition. The inequality constraint and the irreversibility condition limit the space of admissible variations. We prove necessary and sufficient conditions for local stability that incorporate these restrictions. Their numerical implementation shows that all broken equilibria found in (Rosakis et al 2021) are locally stable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04479v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnav Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parabolic problems whose Fujita critical exponent is not given by scaling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04506v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the (fractional) heat equation with a nonlocal nonlinearity involving a Riesz potential: \begin{equation*} u_{t}+(-\Delta)^{\frac{\beta}{2}} u= I_\alpha(|u|^{p}),\qquad x\in \mathbb{R}^n,\,\,\,t&gt;0, \end{equation*} where $\alpha\in(0,n)$, $\beta\in(0,2]$, $n\geq1$, $p&gt;1.$ We introduce the Fujita-type critical exponent $p_{\mathrm{Fuj}}(n,\beta,\alpha)=1+(\beta+\alpha)/(n-\alpha)$, which characterizes the global behavior of solutions: global existence for small initial data when $p&gt;p_{\mathrm{Fuj}}(n,\beta,\alpha),$ and finite-time blow-up when $p\leq p_{\mathrm{Fuj}}(n,\beta,\alpha)$.
  It is remarkable that the critical Fujita exponent is not determined by the usual scaling argument that yields $p_{sc}=1+(\beta+\alpha)/n$, but instead arises in an unconventional manner, similar to the results of Cazenave et al. [Nonlinear Analysis, 68 (2008), 862-874] for the heat equation with a nonlocal nonlinearity of the form $\int_0^t(t-s)^{-\gamma}|u(s)|^{p-1}u(s)ds,\,0\leq \gamma&lt;1.$
  The result on global existence for $p&gt;p_{\mathrm{Fuj}}(n,2,\alpha),$ provides a positive answer to the hypothesis proposed by Mitidieri and Pohozaev in [Proc. Steklov Inst. Math., 248 (2005) 164-185]. We further establish global nonexistence results for the above heat equation, where the Riesz potential term $I_\alpha(|u|^{p})$ is replaced by a more general convolution operator $(\mathcal{K}\ast |u|^p),\,\mathcal{K}\in L^1_{loc}$, thereby extending the Mitidieri-Pohozaev's results established in the aforementioned work.
  Proofs of the blow-up results are obtained using a nonlinear capacity method specifically adapted to the structure of the problem, while global existence is established via a fixed-point argument combined with the Hardy-Littlewood-Sobolev inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04506v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmad Z. Fino, Berikbol T. Torebek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp stability on the second Robin eigenvalue with negative boundary parameters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove a quantitative refinement of the isoperimetric type inequality for the second Robin eigenvalue with negative boundary parameters established by Freitas and Laugesen [Amer.J.Math.143 (2021), no.3, 969-994].Such new stability estimate is proved when the boundary parameter is not too far from 0.By constructing a suitable family of nearly spherical domains, we prove that the exponent for the Fraenkel asymmetry in this quantitative type inequality is sharp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04584v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhijie Chen, Zhen Song, Wenming Zou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical concave-convex problems in Carnot group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04640v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a model Dirichlet problem with concave-convex and critical nonlinearity settled in Carnot groups. Our aim is to prove the existence of two positve solutions in the spirit of a famous result by Ambrosetti, Brezis and Cerami. To this aim we use a variational Perron method combined with proper estimates of a family of functions which are minimizers of the relevant Sobolev inequality. Due to the lack of boundary regularity, we also have to be careful while proving that the first solution found is a local minimizer in the proper topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04640v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mattia Galeotti, Eugenio Vecchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinity of solutions to initial-boundary value problems for linear constant-coefficient evolution PDEs on semi-infinite intervals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04670v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this short communication, we announce an algorithmic procedure for constructing non-uniqueness counter-examples of classical solutions to initial-boundary-value problems for a wide class of linear evolution partial differential equations, of any order and with constant coefficients, formulated in a quarter-plane. Our approach relies on analysis of regularity and asymptotic properties, near the boundary of the spatio-temporal domain, of closed-form integral-representation formulae derived via complex-analytic techniques and rigorous implementation of the modern PDE technique known as Fokas unified transform method. In order to elucidate the novel idea and demonstrate the proposed technique in a self-contained fashion, we explicitly present its application to two concrete examples, namely the heat equation and the linear KdV equation with Dirichlet data. New uniqueness theorems for these two models are also presented herein.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04670v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Chatziafratis, Spyridon Kamvissis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a fuzzy Landau Equation: Part III. The grazing collision limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04713v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the grazing limit from the non-cutoff fuzzy Boltzmann equations to the fuzzy Landau equation, where particles interact through delocalised collisions. We show the grazing limit through variational formulations that correspond to the GENERIC (General Equations for Non-Equilibrium Reversible-Irreversible Coupling) structure of the respective equations. We show that the variational formulation associated with a non-quadratic dual dissipation pair for the fuzzy Boltzmann equations converges to a variational formulation of the fuzzy Landau equation corresponding to a quadratic dissipation pair.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04713v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manh Hong Duong, Boris Golubkov, Zihui He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal cost for the null controllability of the Stokes system with controls having $n-1$ components and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04721v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate the optimal cost of null controllability for the $n$-dimensional Stokes system when the control acts on $n-1$ scalar components. We establish a novel spectral estimate for low frequencies of the Stokes operator, involving solely $n-1$ components, and use it to show that the cost of controllability with controls having $n-1$ components remains of the same order in time as in the case of controls with $n$ components, namely $O(e^{C/T})$, i.e. the cost of null controllability is not affected by the absence of one component of the control. We also give several applications of our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04721v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felipe W. Chaves-Silva, Diego A. Souza, Marcos G. Ferreira-Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Navier-Stokes equations, associated with the Dolbeault complex</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04777v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the Cauchy problem in the band $\mathbb{C}^{n}\times[0, T], n&gt;1,T&gt;0$, for a system of nonlinear differential equations structurally similar to the classical Navier-Stokes equations for an incompressible fluid. The main difference of this system is that it is generated not by the standard gradient operators $\nabla$, divergence div and rotor rot, but by the multidimensional Cauchy-Riemann operator $\overline{\partial}$ in $\mathbb{C}^{n}$, its formally adjoint operator $\overline{\partial}^{*}$ and the compatibility complex for $\overline{\partial}$, which is usually called the Dolbeault complex. The similarity of the structure makes it possible to prove for this problem the theorem of the existence of weak solutions and the open mapping theorem on the scale of specially constructed Bochner-Sobolev spaces. In addition, a criterion for the existence of a ``strong'' solution in these spaces is obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04777v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10958-025-08014-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Shlapunov, A.A., Polkovnikov, A.N. GENERALIZED NAVIER-STOKES EQUATIONS ASSOCIATED WITH THE DOLBEAULT COMPLEX. J Math Sci 293, 430-439 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shlapunov Alexander, Polkovnikov Alexander</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homogenized limits of Stokes flow and advective transport in thin perforated domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04782</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04782v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We deal with the rigorous homogenization and dimension reduction of flow and transport problems posed in thin $\varepsilon$-periodic perforated layers with thickness of order $\varepsilon^{\alpha}$ with $\alpha \in (0,1)$ and therefore the thickness of the layer is large compared its porosity. The aim is the derivation of effective models for $\varepsilon\to 0 $, when the thickness of the layer tends to zero. For the flow problem we consider incompressible Stokes equations with a pressure boundary condition on the top/bottom of the layer, and the transport problem is given by reaction-diffusion-advection problem with advective flow governed from the fluid velocity from the Stokes model and different scalings for the diffusion coefficient modelling low and fast diffusion in the horizontal direction. In the limit, a Darcy-type law is obtained for the Stokes flow with Darcy-velocity depending only on the derivative of the Darcy-pressure in the vertical direction. The effective equation for the transport problem is again of diffusion-advection-type including homogenized coefficients, and with advective flow given by the Darcy-velocity and only taking place in the vertical direction. In the case of slow diffusion in the vertical direction, effective diffusion only takes place in the vertical direction, where in the case of high diffusion in horizontal direction, we obtain effective diffusion in all space directions. To pass to the limit we use the method of two-scale convergence adapted to our microscopic geometry, which is based on uniform a priori estimates. Critical parts in the derivation of the macro-models are the control of the fluid pressure, for which we construct a Bogovskii-operator for thin perforated domains, as well as the strong two-scale convergence for the microscopic solution of the transport equation, necessary to pass to the limit in the advective term.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04782v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Markus Gahn, Vlad Revnic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The initial-to-final-state inverse problem with unbounded potentials and Strichartz estimates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04796v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The initial-to-final-state inverse problem consists in determining a quantum Hamiltonian assuming the knowledge of the state of the system at some fixed time, for every initial state. We formulated this problem to establish a theoretical framework that would explain the viability of data-driven prediction in quantum mechanics. In a previous work, we analysed this inverse problem for Hamiltonians of the form $-\Delta + V$ with an electric potential $V = V({\rm t}, {\rm x})$, and we showed that uniqueness holds whenever the potentials are bounded and decay super-exponentially at infinity. In this paper, we extend this result for unbounded potentials. One of the key steps consists in proving a family of suitable Strichartz estimates -- including the corresponding endpoint of Keel and Tao.
  In the context of the inverse Calder\'on problem this family of inequalities corresponds to the Carleman inequality proved by Kenig, Ruiz and Sogge. Haberman showed that this inequality can be also retrieved as an embedding of a suitable Bourgain space. The corresponding Bourgain space in our context do not capture the mixed-norm Lebesgue spaces of Strichartz inequalities. In this paper, we give a counterexample that justifies this fact, and shows the limitations of Bourgain spaces to address the initial-to-final-state inverse problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04796v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pedro Caro, Alberto Ruiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-periodic solutions to an energy balance model coupled with an active fluid under arbitrary large forces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04800v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article concerns time-periodic solutions to a two-dimensional Sellers-type energy balance model coupled to the three-dimensional primitive equations via a dynamic boundary condition. It is shown that the underlying equations admit at least one strong time-periodic solution, provided the forcing term is time-periodic. The forcing term does not need to satisfy a smallness condition and is allowed to be arbitrarily large.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04800v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gianmarco Del Sarto, Matthias Hieber, Filippo Palma, Tarek Z\"ochling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Theory of Krein-Feller Type Operators and Applications in Stochastic Fractional Elliptic and Parabolic Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04826v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has been shown that the space $C^{\infty}_{W,V}(\mathbb{T})$, introduced in Simas and Sousa (Potential Analysis, 2025), is the natural regularity space for solutions of the eigenvalue problem $\Delta_{W,V} u = \lambda u$ on the torus $\mathbb{T}$, where $\Delta_{W,V} = \frac{d^{+}}{dV}\frac{d^{-}}{dW}$ is the Krein Feller operator in the case where $W$ and $V$ are strictly increasing and right continuous (respectively left continuous), possibly with dense sets of discontinuities. In this work we provide conditions ensuring that every function in $C^{\infty}_{W,V}(\mathbb{T})$, which may be highly discontinuous, admits a series expansion that generalizes the classical Taylor expansion. A central feature of our approach is that all proofs are nonstandard, since classical analytical and spectral arguments cannot be adapted to this singular setting. Using these methods we characterize the eigenvectors of $\Delta_{W,V}$ in terms of generalized trigonometric functions and obtain an asymptotic lower bound for the associated eigenvalues. We also derive a sharp upper bound for the convergence exponent of these eigenvalues, and as a consequence we prove that $C^{\infty}_{W,V}(\mathbb{T})$ is a nuclear space. Further consequences include results on the asymptotic behavior of eigenvalues of compact operators and improvements in traceability. As a final application we establish existence results for generalized fractional stochastic and deterministic differential equations, as well as for parabolic stochastic partial differential equations acting on nuclear spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04826v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kelvin J. R. Almeida-Sousa, Alexandre B. Simas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On hyperbolic approximations for a class of dispersive and diffusive-dispersive equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04882v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce novel approximate systems for dispersive and diffusive-dispersive equations with nonlinear fluxes. For purely dispersive equations, we construct a first-order, strictly hyperbolic approximation. Local well-posedness of smooth solutions is achieved by constructing a unique symmetrizer that applies to arbitrary smooth fluxes. Under stronger conditions on the fluxes, we provide a strictly convex entropy for the hyperbolic system that corresponds to the energy of the underlying dispersive equation. To approximate diffusive-dispersive equations, we rely on a viscoelastic damped system that is compatible with the found entropy for the hyperbolic approximation of the dispersive evolution. For the resulting hyperbolic-parabolic approximation, we provide a global well-posedness result. Using the relative entropy framework \cite{dafermos2005hyperbolic}, we prove that the solutions of the approximate systems converge to solutions of the original equations. The structure of the new approximate systems allows to apply standard numerical simulation methods from the field of hyperbolic balance laws. We confirm the convergence of our approximations even beyond the validity range of our theoretical findings on set of test cases covering different target equations. We show the applicability of the approach for strong nonlinear effects leading to oscillating or shock-layer-forming behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04882v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rahul Barthwal, Firas Dhaouadi, Christian Rohde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative rigidity of the Wasserstein contraction under convolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04928v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to investigate the contraction properties of $p$-Wasserstein distances with respect to convolution in Euclidean spaces both qualitatively and quantitatively. We connect this question to the question of uniform convexity of the Kantorovich functional on which there was substantial recent progress (mostly for $p=2$ and partially for $p&gt;1$). Motivated by this connection we extend these uniform convexity results to the case $p=1$, which is of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04928v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Fathi, Michael Goldman, Daniel Tsodyks</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence and a priori bounds for fully nonlinear PDEs with a harmonic map-like structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study a new class of fully nonlinear uniformly elliptic equations with a so-called harmonic map-like structure, whose model case is given by \begin{equation*} \mathcal{M}^{\pm}_{\lambda,\Lambda}(D^2u) \pm b(x) |Du| \pm \beta(u)\langle M(x) Du,Du \rangle \pm c(x) u = f(x)\; \textrm{ in } \Omega, \end{equation*} where $\Omega\subset \mathbb{R}^n$ is a bounded $C^{1,1}$ domain, $\mathcal{M}^{\pm}$ are the Pucci extremal operators, $\beta(s) = s^k$ for some $k \in \mathbb{N} $ odd, $b \in L^{q}_{+}(\Omega)$, $c,f \in L^p(\Omega)$, and $n \leq p \leq q$, $q&gt;n$.
  We obtain existence results under a smallness regime on the coefficients, along with some classical results such as the Aleksandrov--Bakelman--Pucci estimate and the comparison principle, as well as a priori bounds for the respective Dirichlet problem in the noncoercive case. We also establish multiplicity results and qualitative behavior, which seem to be new in the case of the Laplacian operator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04961v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabrielle Nornberg, Ricardo Ziegele</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractured Poroelastic Media in the Limit of Vanishing Aperture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04978v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a poroelastic medium with a thin heterogeneity, also referred to as a fracture. Fluid flow and mechanical deformation inside both bulk and fracture are governed by the quasi-static Biot equations. The fracture's material parameters, such as hydraulic conductivity and elasticity, are assumed to scale with powers of the width-to-length ratio $\varepsilon$ of the fracture. Based on a priori estimates, we rigorously derive limit models as $\varepsilon \rightarrow 0$ and identify different limit regimes. We obtain five regimes for the hydraulic conductivity and two for the elasticity. While many cases yield discrete fracture models, others result in two-scale limit problems dominated by normal flow or deformation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04978v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian H\"orl, Kundan Kumar, Christian Rohde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geophysical intensity problems: the axisymmetric case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05010v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Considering the earth or any other celestial body the main sources of the gravitational as well as of the magnetic field lie inside the body. Above the surface both fields are in good approximation harmonic vector fields determined by their values at the body's surface or any other surface enclosing the body. The intensity problem seeks to determine harmonic vector fields vanishing at infinity and with prescribed intensity of the field at the surface. This problem constitutes a nonlinear boundary value problem, whose general solvability is not yet established. In this paper {\em axisymmetric} harmonic fields ${\bf H}$ outside the unit sphere $S^2$ are studied and, given an axisymmetric H\"older continuous intensity function $I\neq 0$ on $S^2$, the existence of infinitely many solutions of the intensity problem is proved. These solutions can more precisely be characterized as follows: fix a number $\de \in \nat\setminus \{1 \}$ and a meridional plane $M$ through the symmetry axis $S\!A$, and in $M$ a unit circle $S^1$ (symmetric with respect to $S\!A$) and, furthermore, $2\, N$, $N \in \nat_0$, points $z_n \in M$ (symmetric with respect to $S\!A$, avoiding $S\!A$, and outside $S^1$), then the existence of an (up to a sign) unique harmonic field ${\bf H}$ is established that vanishes at (the axisymmetric circles piercing $M$ at) $z_n$ and nowhere else, that has intensity $I$ at $S^2$ and (exact) decay order $\de$ at infinity. The proof is based on the solution of a nonlinear elliptic equation with discontinuous coefficients, which are, moreover, singular at the symmetry axis. Its combination with fixed boundary conditions was the basis of a recent treatment of the ``geomagnetic direction problem'' \cite{KR22}. Here we have instead natural boundary conditions, which provide less information, and which require, therefore, in part new solution techniques and sharper estimates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05010v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ralf Kaiser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Nehari manifold method for nonvariational problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05055</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05055v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to extend the Nehari manifold method from the variational setting to the nonvariational framework of fixed point equations. This is achieved by constructing a radial energy functional that generalizes the standard one from the variational case. Furthermore, the solutions obtained through our method are localized in conical annular sets, which leads to the existence of multiple solutions. The abstract results are illustrated by two representative applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05055v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Radu Precup, Andrei Stan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean curvature flow near a peanut solution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05077v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It was shown by Angenent, Altschuler and Giga, and by Angenent and Velazquez that there exist closed mean curvature flow solutions that extinct to a point in finite time, without ever becoming convex prior to their extinction. These solutions develop a degenerate neckpinch singularity, meaning that the tangent flow at a singularity is a round cylinder, but at the same time for each of these solutions there exists a sequence of points in space and time, so that the pointed blow up limit around this sequence is the Bowl soliton. These solutions are called peanut solutions and they were first conjectured to exist by Richard Hamilton, while the existence of those solutions was shown by Angenent, Altschuler and Giga. In this paper we show that this type of solutions are highly unstable, in the sense that in every small neighborhood of any such peanut solution we can find a perturbation so that the mean curvature flow starting at that perturbation develops spherical singularity, and at the same time we can find a perturbation so that the mean curvature flow starting at that perturbation develops a nondegenerate neckpinch singularity. We also show that appropriately rescaled subsequence of any sequence of solutions whose initial data converge to the peanut solution, and all of which develop spherical singularities, converges to the Ancient oval solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05077v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sigurd Angenent, Panagiota Daskalopoulos, Natasa Sesum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase mixing and the Vlasov equation in cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04214v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the Vlasov equation on slowly expanding isotropic homogeneous tori, described by the Friedmann--Lema\^itre--Robertson--Walker cosmological spacetimes. For expansion rate $t^q$, with $0&lt; q&lt;\frac{1}{2}$ (excluding certain exceptional values), we show that the spatial density decays at the rate $t^{-6q}$ and that, when the spatial average is removed, the density decays at an enhanced rate due to a phase mixing effect. This enhancement is polynomial for Sobolev initial data and super-polynomial, but sub-exponential, for real analytic initial data. We further show that, when the expansion rate is the borderline $t^{\frac{1}{2}}$ -- the rate which describes a radiation filled universe -- a degenerate phase mixing effect results in a logarithmic enhancement for Sobolev initial data and a super-logarithmic enhancement (in fact, a gain of $\exp(-\mu(\log t)^{\epsilon})$ for some $\mu,\epsilon&gt;0$) for analytic initial data. The proof is based on a collection of commuting vector fields, and certain combinatorial properties of an associated collection of differential operators. The vector fields are not explicit, but are shown to have good properties when $t$ is large with respect to the momentum support of the solution. A physical space dyadic localisation is employed to treat non-compactly supported (in particular, non-trivial real analytic) but suitably decaying solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04214v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Taylor, Renato Velozo Ruiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixing at the Batchelor Scale for White-In-Time Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04297v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the mixing properties of solutions to the advection-diffusion equation of a white-in-time velocity field on the 2-dimensional torus with four forced modes. As the diffusivity parameter goes to zero, we show that the almost-sure exponential dissipation rate stays bounded from below. Together with the corresponding upper bound established by Gess and Yaroslavtsev, this constitutes an example of a velocity field for which the Batchelor scale conjecture can be verified. In addition, we characterize the exponential mixing rate without diffusion of this system. Our results are not restricted to two dimensions, and we construct a three-dimensional white-in-time velocity field with the same properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04297v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robin Chemnitz, Dennis Chemnitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homogenizationof non-divergence form operators in i.i.d. random environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04410v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study random walks in a balanced, i.i.d. random environment in $\mathbb Z^d$ for $d\geq 3$. We establish improved convergence rates for the homogenization of the Dirichlet problem associated with the corresponding non-divergence form difference operators, surpassing the $O(R^{-1})$ rate, which is expected to be optimal for environments with a finite range of dependence. In particular, the improved rates are $O(R^{-3/2})$ when $d=3$, and $O(R^{-2}\log R)$ when $d\geq 4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04410v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoqin Guo, Timo Sprekeler, Hung V. Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Dirichlet heat trace for domains with curved corners</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04422v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the short-time asymptotics of the Dirichlet heat trace on planar curvilinear polygons. For such domains we show that the coefficient of $t^{1/2}$ in the expansion splits into a boundary integral of $\kappa^2$ and a sum of local corner contributions, one for each vertex. Each curved corner contribution depends only on the interior angle $\alpha$ and on the limiting curvatures $\kappa_{\pm}$ on the adjacent sides. Using a conformal model and a parametrix construction on the sector heat space, we express this contribution in the form $c_{1/2}(\alpha)\,r_0(\alpha,\kappa_+, \kappa_-)$, where $c_{1/2}(\alpha)$ is given by a Hadamard finite part of an explicit trace over the exact sector. For right-angled corners we compute $c_{1/2}(\pi/2)=1/(16\sqrt{\pi})$ and obtain a closed formula for the $t^{1/2}$ coefficient. As an application we extend a previous result in the literature by showing that any admissible curvilinear polygon that is Dirichlet isospectral to a polygon must itself be a polygon with straight sides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04422v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi Zhuo Looi, David Sher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical matrix approximability of inverse of convection dominated finite element matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04824v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Several researchers have developed a rich toolbox of matrix compression techniques that exploit structure and redundancy in large matrices. Classical methods such as the block low-rank format and the Fast Multipole Method make it possible to manipulate very large systems by representing them in a reduced form. Among the most sophisticated tools in this area are hierarchical matrices (H-matrices), which exploit local properties of the underlying kernel or operator to approximate matrix blocks by low-rank factors, organized in a recursive hierarchy. H-matrices offer a flexible and scalable framework, yielding nearly linear complexity in both storage and computation. Hierarchical matrix techniques, originally developed for boundary integral equations, have recently been applied to matrices stemming from the discretization of advection-dominated problems. However, their effectiveness is limited by the loss of coercivity induced by convection phenomena, where traditional methods fail. Initial work by Le Borne addressed this by modifying the admissibility criterion for structured grids with constant convection, but challenges remain for more general grids and advection fields. In this work, we propose a novel partitioning strategy based on "convection tubes", clusters aligned with the convection vector field. This method does not require a structured grid or constant convection, overcoming the limitations of previous approaches. We present both theoretical analyses and numerical experiments, that demonstrate the efficiency and robustness of our method for convection-dominated PDEs on unstructured grids. The approach builds on a P\'eclet-robust Caccioppoli inequality, crucial for handling convection-dominated problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04824v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arthur Saunier, Leo Agelas, Ani Anciaux Sedrakian, Ibtihel Ben Gharbia, Xavier Claeys</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cumulant expansions of operator groups of quantum many-particle systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05036v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The article presents a method of cluster expansions for groups of operators associated with the von Neumann equations for states and the Heisenberg equations for observables, aiming to construct generating operators for nonperturbative solutions to the Cauchy problem for hierarchies of evolution equations of many-particle quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05036v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. I. Gerasimenko, I. V. Gapyak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-phase averaged system justification for ideal gases without conductivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16720v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article concerns the mathematical justification of an averaged system of partial differential equations governing the evolution of a two-phase mixture of compressible ideal fluids, with viscosity and without conductivity, in space dimension 1 with periodic boundary conditions. The derivation is done by some homogenization procedure. The originality and the difficulty of the paper consists in the fact that both the density and temperature are allowed to oscillate (because of the absence of heat conduction), so that the limiting model is a six-equations, two-pressures, two-temperatures model. The key point is to show the strong convergence of the stress tensor in $\(L^2((0,T)\times (0, 1))\)$. The main difficulties are to obtain uniform estimates in spite of the presence of oscillating coefficients in the energy equation. It requires to look at solutions with low regularity for the density and the temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16720v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D Bresch (LAMA), C Burtea (UFR Math\'ematiques UPCit\'e), P Gonin--Joubert (MMCS, ICJ), F Lagouti\`ere (MMCS, ICJ)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wasserstein Gradient Flows of MMD Functionals with Distance Kernel and Cauchy Problems on Quantile Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.07498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.07498v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give a comprehensive description of Wasserstein gradient flows of maximum mean discrepancy (MMD) functionals $\mathcal F_\nu := \text{MMD}_K^2(\cdot, \nu)$ towards given target measures $\nu$ on the real line, where we focus on the negative distance kernel $K(x,y) := -|x-y|$. In one dimension, the Wasserstein-2 space can be isometrically embedded into the cone $\mathcal C(0,1) \subset L_2(0,1)$ of quantile functions leading to a characterization of Wasserstein gradient flows via the solution of an associated Cauchy problem on $L_2(0,1)$. Based on the construction of an appropriate counterpart of $\mathcal F_\nu$ on $L_2(0,1)$ and its subdifferential, we provide a solution of the Cauchy problem. For discrete target measures $\nu$, this results in a piecewise linear solution formula. We prove invariance and smoothing properties of the flow on subsets of $\mathcal C(0,1)$. For certain $\mathcal F_\nu$-flows this implies that initial point measures instantly become absolutely continuous, and stay so over time. Finally, we illustrate the behavior of the flow by various numerical examples using an implicit Euler scheme, which is easily computable by a bisection algorithm. For continuous targets $\nu$, also the explicit Euler scheme can be employed, although with limited convergence guarantees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.07498v4</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard Duong, Viktor Stein, Robert Beinert, Johannes Hertrich, Gabriele Steidl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equivalence of Sobolev norms for Kolmogorov operators with scaling-critical drift</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00191v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the ordinary or fractional Laplacian plus a homogeneous, scaling-critical drift term. This operator is non-symmetric but homogeneous, and generates scales of $L^p$-Sobolev spaces which we compare with the ordinary homogeneous Sobolev spaces. Unlike in previous studies concerning Hardy operators, i.e., ordinary or fractional Laplacians plus scaling-critical scalar perturbations, handling the drift term requires an additional, possibly technical, restriction on the range of comparable Sobolev spaces, which is related to the unavailability of gradient bounds for the associated semigroup.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00191v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>The Anh Bui, Xuan Thinh Duong, Konstantin Merz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixed norm estimates for dilated averages over planar curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05140v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the mixed norm estimates for the operator $ T $associated with a dilated plane curve $(ut, u\gamma(t))$, defined by \[ Tf(x, u) := \int_{0}^{1} f(x_1 - ut, x_2 - u\gamma(t)) \, dt, \] where $ x := (x_1, x_2) $ and $\gamma $ is a general plane curve satisfying appropriate smoothness and curvature conditions. More precisely, we establish the $ L_x^p(\mathbb{R}^2) \rightarrow L_x^q L_u^r(\mathbb{R}^2 \times [1, 2]) $ (space-time) estimates for $ T $, whenever $(\frac{1}{p},\frac{1}{q})$ satisfy \[ \max\left\{0, \frac{1}{2p} - \frac{1}{2r}, \frac{3}{p} - \frac{r+2}{r}\right\} &lt; \frac{1}{q} \leq \frac{1}{p} &lt; \frac{r+1}{2r} \] and $$1 + (1 + \omega)\left(\frac{1}{q} - \frac{1}{p}\right) &gt; 0,$$ where $ r \in [1, \infty] $ and $ \omega := \limsup_{t \rightarrow 0^+} \frac{\ln|\gamma(t)|}{\ln t} $. These results are sharp, except for certain borderline cases. Additionally, we examine the $ L_x^p(\mathbb{R}^2) \rightarrow L_u^r L_x^q(\mathbb{R}^2 \times [1, 2]) $ (time-space) estimates for $T $, which are especially almost sharp when $p=2$ or $p\in [1, \frac{3}{2}]\cup [4, \infty]$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05140v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junfeng Li, Zengjian Lou, Haixia Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative blow-up suppression for the Patlak-Keller-Segel(-Navier-Stokes) system via Couette flow on $\mathbb{R}^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12915v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is well known that solutions to the Patlak--Keller--Segel system on $\mathbb{R}^2$ blow up in finite time if the initial mass exceeds $8\pi$. In this paper, we investigate the mixing effect induced by a Couette flow $(Ay, 0)$ with a quantitatively determined amplitude $A$, which suppresses bacterial aggregation. For the Patlak--Keller--Segel system advected by such a flow on $\mathbb{R}^2$, we prove that the solutions remain global in time even for large initial mass, provided the amplitude $A$ is sufficiently large. Specifically, global well-posedness holds if $A$ satisfies a lower bound of the form $C_* \left(\| \langle D_x\rangle^{m} \langle {D_x}^{-1}\rangle^\epsilon n_{\mathrm{in}} \|_{L^2}^2+1\right)^{9/2}$. A notable feature of our result is the explicit estimate of the sufficient constant, given by $C_* = 2,058,614$. Furthermore, for the coupled Patlak--Keller--Segel--Navier--Stokes system near the Couette flow, we establish an analogous global existence result, provided the amplitude is sufficiently large in form of $C_*\|(n_{\rm in}, |D_x|^{1/3} n_{\rm in},\omega_{\rm in})\|_{Y_{m,\epsilon}}^9$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12915v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yubo Chen, Wendong Wang, Guoxu Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the multiplicity of weak solutions for a class of coupled quasilinear elliptic systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22665v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the existence and regularity of weak solutions to the following quasilinear elliptic system: \[
  -\mathrm{div}(A_k(x, u_k) |\nabla u_k|^{p_k - 2} \nabla u_k) + \dfrac{1}{p_k} D_s A_k(x, u_k) |\nabla u_k|^{p_k} = g_k(x, u) \quad \text{in } \Omega,\quad
  u_k = 0 \quad \text{on } \partial\Omega, \]
  where $k=1,\dots,d$, $ \Omega \subset \mathbb{R}^N $ is a bounded domain with $ N \geq 2 $, $ \boldsymbol{p} = (p_1, \dots, p_d) $, $ p_k &gt; 1 $. Using tools from nonsmooth critical point theory, we prove the existence of infinitely many weak solutions in $ W_0^{1,\boldsymbol{p}}(\Omega) \cap L^\infty(\Omega; \mathbb{R}^d) $, where $W_0^{1,\boldsymbol p}(\Omega)=W_0^{1,p_1}(\Omega)\times\dots\times W_0^{1,p_d}(\Omega)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22665v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Annamaria Canino, Simone Mauro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absolute continuity of Wasserstein barycenters on manifolds with a lower Ricci curvature bound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.13832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.13832v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given a complete Riemannian manifold $M$ with a lower Ricci curvature bound, we consider barycenters in the Wasserstein space $\mathcal{W}_2(M)$ of probability measures on $M$. We refer to them as Wasserstein barycenters, which by definition are probability measures on $M$. The goal of this article is to present a novel approach to proving their absolute continuity. We introduce a new class of displacement functionals exploiting the Hessian equality for Wasserstein barycenters. To provide suitable instances of such functionals, we revisit Souslin space theory, Dunford-Pettis theorem and the de la Vall\'ee Poussin criterion for uniform integrability. Our method shows that if a probability measure $\mathbb{P}$ on $\mathcal{W}_2(M)$ gives mass to absolutely continuous measures on $M$, then its unique barycenter is also absolutely continuous. This generalizes the previous results on compact manifolds by Kim and Pass arXiv:1412.7726 [math.AP] .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.13832v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00526-025-03183-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Ma, J. Absolute continuity of Wasserstein barycenters on manifolds with a lower Ricci curvature bound. Calc. Var. 65, 9 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jianyu Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restrictions of Maass forms on $\mathrm{SL}(2,\mathbb{C})$ to hyperbolic surfaces and geodesic tubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17164v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $\psi$ be an $L^2$-normalized Hecke-Maass form with a large spectral parameter $\lambda&gt;0$ on a compact arithmetic congruence hyperbolic 3-manifold $X=\Gamma\backslash\mathrm{SL}(2,\mathbb{C})/\mathrm{SU}(2)$, and let $Y$ be a totally geodesic surface in $X$ with bounded diameter. The local $L^2$-bound for the restriction of $\psi$ to $Y$ is $\|\psi|_Y\|_{L^2(Y)}\ll \lambda^{1/4}$ by Burq, G\'erard, and Tzvetkov. We apply the method of arithmetic amplification developed by Iwaniec and Sarnak to obtain a power saving over the local bound. The new feature in the proof is that we establish two different estimates for the integrals of $\psi|_Y$ against geodesic beams over $Y$ via two amplification arguments. Combining these estimates, we can improve the local bound for generalized Fourier coefficients of $\psi|_Y$ against eigenfunctions on $Y$ with spectral parameters near $\lambda$. We also apply the amplification method to obtain a power saving over the trivial bound $O(1)$ for $L^2$-norms of $\psi$ restricted to $\lambda^{-1/2}$-neighborhoods of unit-length geodesic segments. Consequently, by applying a result of Blair and Sogge, we obtain power savings over the local $L^p$-bounds of $\psi$ by Sogge for $2&lt;p&lt;4$ from our improved bound for the Kakeya-Nikodym norm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17164v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaqi Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of fermion-mediated interactions in Bose-Fermi mixtures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18678v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work is inspired by recent experimental observations in ultracold atomic Bose-Fermi mixtures [DeSalvo et al., Nature 568 (2019)]. These experiments reveal the emergence of an attractive fermion-mediated interaction between bosons, as well as a stability-instability transition. We give the first mathematical demonstration of this transition by studying the low-energy spectrum of a many-body interspecies Hamiltonian. More precisely, we show the convergence of its eigenvalues towards those of an effective Bose Hamiltonian, which includes fermion-mediated effects. Applying this result to a model with short-range potentials, we derive a stability-instability transition in the bosonic subsystem, driven by the Bose-Fermi coupling strength $g$. For small $|g|$, the bosons form a stable Bose-Einstein condensate with the energy per particle uniformly bounded from below. For large $|g|$, the energy per particle is no longer uniformly bounded from below, signaling the collapse of the condensate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18678v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Esteban C\'ardenas, Joseph K. Miller, David Mitrouskas, Nata\v{s}a Pavlovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An analytic approach to the stress energy tensor in quantum field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00487v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss a framework for quantum fields in curved spacetimes that possess a stress energy tensor as a connection one form on a suitable moduli space of metrics. In generic spacetimes the existence of such a tensor is thought to be a replacement for the existence of symmetries that the Minkowski theory relies on. It is shown that the local time-slice property and the implementability of local isometries is a consequence of the existence of a stress energy tensor that is a local field. We prove that the Klein-Gordon field, in an irreducible Fock representation in which the ground state is Hadamard, is an example. In this example we show that the scattering matrix for compactly supported metric perturbations exists in the Fock space and is smooth on a dense set with respect to the perturbation parameter. This generalises results by Dimock and Wald.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00487v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Strohmaier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean Field Games of Controls with Boundary Conditions &amp; Invariance Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21642v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In a mean field game of controls, a large population of identical players seek to minimize a cost that depends on the joint distribution of the states of the players and their controls. We first consider the classes of mean field games of controls in which the value function and the distribution of player states satisfy either Dirichlet or Neumann boundary conditions. We prove that such systems are well-posed either with sufficient smallness conditions or in the case of monotone couplings. Next, we consider mean field games of controls under invariance constraints imposed on the state space. We prove the existence and uniqueness of weak solutions to our mean field game system, and then we prove higher regularity of solutions under some additional assumptions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21642v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Jameson Graber, Kyle Rosengartner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The exterior Steklov problem for Euclidean domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09490v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the Steklov eigenvalue problem in an exterior Euclidean domain. First, we present several formulations of this problem and establish the equivalences between them. Next, we examine various properties of the exterior Steklov eigenvalues and eigenfunctions. One of our main findings is an Escobar-type lower bound for the first exterior Steklov eigenvalue on convex domains in dimensions three and higher. This bound is expressed in terms of the principal curvatures of the boundary and is sharp, with equality attained for a ball. Moreover, it implies the existence of a sequence of convex domains with fixed volume and the first exterior Steklov eigenvalues tending to infinity. This contrasts with the interior case, as well as with the two-dimensional exterior case, for which we show that an analogue of the Weinstock isoperimetric inequality holds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09490v2</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lukas Bundrock, Alexandre Girouard, Denis S. Grebenkov, Michael Levitin, Iosif Polterovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
