<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 05:00:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Weighted weak-type (1, 1) inequalities for pseudo-differential operators with symbol in $S^{n}_{0,\delta}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10738v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $T_a$ be a pseudo-differential operator defined by exotic symbol $a$ in H\"{o}rmander class $S^m_{0,\delta}$ with $m \in \mathbb{R} $ and $0 \leq \delta \leq 1 $. It is well-known that the weak type (1,1) behavior of $T_a $ is not fully understood when the index $m $ is equal to the possibly optimal value $-\frac{n}{2} - \frac{n}{2} \delta $ for $0 \leq \delta &lt; 1 $, and that $T_a $ is not of weak type (1,1) when $m = -n $ and $\delta = 1 $.
  In this note, we prove that $T_a $ is of weighted weak type (1,1) if $a \in S^{-n}_{0, \delta}$ with $0 \leq \delta &lt; 1 $. Additionally, we show that the dual operator $T_a^* $ is of weighted weak type (1,1) if $a \in L^\infty S^{-n}_0 $. We also identify $m = -n $ as a critical index for these weak type estimates. As applications, we derive weighted weak type (1,1) estimates for certain classes of Fourier integral operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10738v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guangqing Wang, Suixin He, Lihua Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An extension problem of higher order operators and operators of logarithmic type via renormalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10747v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a method of obtaining a higher order extension problem, \'a la Caffarelli-Silvestre, utilizing ideas from renormalization. Moreover, we give an alternative perspective of the recently developed extension problem for the logarithmic laplacian developed by Chen, Hauer and Weth (2023) [arXiv:2312.15689] through the lens of renormalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10747v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-term behavior for wave equation with nonlinear damping and super-cubic nonlinearity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10774v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the semilinear wave equation involving the nonlinear damping term $g(u_t) $ and nonlinearity $f(u)$. The well-posedness of the weak solution satisfying some additional regularity is achieved under the wider ranges of the exponents $g$ and $f$. Moreover, the existence of global attractor and exponential attractor are proved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10774v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3934/dcdsb.2025027</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Discrete and Continuous Dynamical Systems - B, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cuncai Liu, Fengjuan Meng, Chang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized principal eigenvalue of time-periodic cooperative nonlocal dispersal systems and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10936</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10936v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is well known that, in the study of the dynamical properties of nonlinear reaction-diffusion systems, the sign of the principal eigenvalue of the linearized system plays an important role. However, for the nonlocal dispersal systems, due to the lack of compactness, the essential spectrum appear, and the principal eigenvalue may not exist. In this paper, by constructing monotonic upper and lower control systems, we obtain the generalized principal eigenvalue of the cooperative irreducible system and demonstrate that this generalized principal eigenvalue plays the same role as the usual principal eigenvalue.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10936v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingxin Wang, Lei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability for the Sobolev inequality in cones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11087v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a quantitative Sobolev inequality in cones of Bianchi-Egnell type, which implies a stability property. Our result holds for any cone as long as the minimizers of the Sobolev quotient are nondegenerate, which is the case of most cones. When the minimizers are the classical bubbles we have more precise results. Finally, we show that local estimates are not enough to get the optimal constant for the quantitative Sobolev inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11087v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Filomena Pacella, Giulio Ciraolo, Camilla Chiara Polvara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solutions for a critical elliptic system with periodic boundary condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11373v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the following nonlinear critical Schr\"odinger system: \begin{eqnarray*}\begin{cases} -\Delta u=K_1(y)u^{2^*-1}+\frac{1}{2} u^{\frac{2^*}{2}-1}v^\frac{2^*}{2}, \,\,\,\,\,y\in\Omega,\,\,\,\,\,u&gt;0,\cr -\Delta v=K_2(y)v^{2^*-1}+\frac{1}{2} v^{\frac{2^*}{2}-1}u^\frac{2^*}{2}, \,\,\,\,\,y\in\Omega,\,\,\,\,\,v&gt;0,\cr u(y'+Le_j,y'')=u(y), \,\,\,\,\,\frac{\partial u(y'+Le_j,y'')}{\partial y_j}=\frac{\partial u(y)}{\partial y_j}, \,\,\,\,\,if\,\, y'=-\frac{L}{2}e_j,\,\,\,j=1, \ldots, k,\cr v(y'+Le_j,y'')=v(y), \,\,\,\,\,\frac{\partial v(y'+Le_j,y'')}{\partial y_j}=\frac{\partial v(y)}{\partial y_j}, \,\,\,\,\,if\,\, y'=-\frac{L}{2}e_j,\,\,\,j=1, \ldots, k,\cr u,v \to 0 \,\,as \,\,|y''|\to \infty, \end{cases} \end{eqnarray*} where $K_1(y),\,K_2(y)$ satisfy some periodic conditions and $\Omega$ is a strip. Under some conditions which are weaker than Li, Wei and Xu(J. Reine Angew. Math. 743: 163-211, 2018), we prove that there exists a single bubbling solution for the above system. Moreover, as the appearance of the coupling terms, we construct different forms of solutions, which makes it more interesting. Since there are periodic boundary conditions, this expansion for the difference between the standard bubbles and the approximate bubble can not be obtained by using the comparison theorem as one usually does for Dirichlet boundary condition. To overcome this difficulty, we will use the Green's function of $-\Delta$ in $\Omega$ with periodic boundary conditions which helps us find the approximate bubble. Due to the lack of the Sobolev inequality, we will introduce a suitable weighted space to carry out the reduction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11373v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qingfang Wang, Wenju Wu, Mingxue Zhai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform-in-time asymptotic limits of generalized Kuramoto models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11392v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study two uniform-in-time asymptotic limits for generalized Kuramoto (GK) models. For these GK type models, we first derive the uniform stability estimates with respect to initial data, natural frequency and communication network under a suitable framework, and then as direct applications of this uniform stability estimate, we establish two asymptotic limits which are valid in the whole time interval, namely uniform-in-time continuum and mean-filed limit to the continuum and kinetic GK models, respectively. In the mean-field limit setting (the number of particles tends to infinity), we show global-in-time existence of measure-valued solutions to the corresponding kinetic equation. On the other hand, in a continuum limit setting (the lattice size tends to zero), we show that the lattice GKM solutions converge to a classical solution to the continuum GK model in supremum norm. Two asymptotic limits improve earlier results for the generalized GK type models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11392v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hangjun Cho, Seung-Yeal Ha, Myeongju Kang, Chan Ho Min</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplicity result for a mass supercritical NLS with a partial confinement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11472v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider an NLS equation in $\mathbb{R}^3$ with partial confinement and mass supercritical nonlinearity. In Bellazzini, Boussaid, Jeanjean and Visciglia (Comm. Math. Phys. 353, 2017, 229-251) for such a problem, a solution with a prescribed $L^2$ norm was obtained, as a local minima, and the existence of a second solution, at a mountain pass energy level, was proposed as an open problem. We give here a positive, non-perturbative, answer to this problem. Our solution is obtained as a limit of a sequence of solutions of corresponding problems on bounded domains of $\mathbb{R}^3$. The symmetry of solutions on bounded domains is used centrally in the convergence process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11472v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Jeanjean, Linjie Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-uniqueness of Regular Solutions for Incompressible Static Euler Equations with Given Boundary Conditions and Turbulent Global Solutions of Incompressible Navier-Stokes Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11485v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The incompressible Navier-Stokes equations and static Euler equations are considered. We find that there exist infinite non-trivial regular solutions of incompressible static Euler equations with given boundary conditions. Moreover there exist random solutions of incompressible static Euler equations. Provided Reynolds number is large enough and time variable $t$ goes to infinity, these random solutions of static Euler equations are the path limits of corresponding Navier-Stokes flows. But the double limits of these Navier-Stokes flows do not exist. These phenomena reveal randomness and turbulence of incompressible fluids. Therefore these solutions are called turbulent solutions. Here some typing models without Prandtl layer are given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11485v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongqian Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A non-trivial conservation law with a trivial characteristic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11502v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the conservation law of the overdetermined system $u_t - 4u_x^3 - u_{xxx} = 0$, $u_y = 0$, associated with the characteristic $(u_{xy}, 0)$, is non-trivial despite the characteristic vanishing on the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11502v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kostya Druzhkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transport equations for Osgood velocity fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11531v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the transport equation with a velocity field satisfying the Osgood condition. The weak formulation is not meaningful in the usual Lebesgue sense, meaning that the usual DiPerna--Lions treatment of the problem is not applicable {(in particular, the divergence of the velocity might be unbounded)}. Instead, we use Riemann--Stieltjes integration to interpret the weak formulation, leading to a well-posedness theory in regimes not covered by existing works. The most general results are for the one-dimensional problem, with generalisations to multiple dimensions in the particular case of log-Lipschitz velocities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11531v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulrik Skre Fjordholm, Ola Isaac H{\o}g{\aa}sen M{\ae}hlen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinitely many saturated travelling waves for epidemic models with distributed-contacts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11589v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider an epidemic model with distributed-contacts. When the contact kernel concentrates, one formally reaches a very degenerate Fisher-KPP equation with a diffusion term that is not in divergence form. We make an exhaustive study of its travelling waves. For every admissible speed, there exists not only a non-saturated (smooth) wave but also infinitely many saturated (sharp) ones. Furthermore their tails may differ from what is usually expected. These results are thus in sharp contrast with their counterparts on related models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11589v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthieu Alfaro, Maxime Herda, Andrea Natale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Moutard transformation singularity for the Davey--Stewartson II equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11590v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We indicate explicitly how to obtain the Moutard transformation singularity for the Davey--Stewartson II equation with two indeterminancy points. We also justify an arbitrary order ``mass drop" phenomenon via this singularity formation scheme.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11590v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi C. Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Solvability for the Compressible Hookean Viscoelastic Fluids with a Free Boundary in Some Classes of Large Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11683v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently Jiang-Jiang established a global (in time) existence result for unique strong solutions of the two-dimensional (2D) free-boundary problem of an incompressible Hookean viscoelastic fluid, the rest state of which is defined in a slab, in some classes of large data [28]. In particular, Jiang-Jiang's mathematical result shows that, if the initial free boundary is flat, the way the elastic deformation under the large elasticity coefficient $\kappa$ acts on the free boundary prevents the natural tendency of the fluid to form singularities, even when the initial velocity is properly large. However it is not clear whether their result can be extended to the corresponding 3D case. In this paper, we further find a similar result in the 3D stratified (immiscible) compressible Hookean viscoelastic fluids in an infinite slab with two restrictive conditions: that the elasticity coefficients of two fluids are equal, and that the initial density functions satisfy the asymptotic stability condition in Lagrangian coordinates. These two restrictive conditions in the compressible case contribute us to avoid the essential obstacles that would be faced in the extension of Jiang-Jiang's result from two dimensions to our 3D case. In addition, we can further obtain a new result regarding the vanishing phenomena of the nonlinear interactions of solutions with the fixed initial velocity and the initial zero perturbation deformation. Such a new result roughly presents that the solutions of the problem considered by us can be approximated by the ones of a linear problem for sufficiently large $\kappa$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11683v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fei Jiang, Youyi Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximate radial symmetry for $p$-Laplace equations via the moving planes method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11759v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate quasi-symmetry for small perturbations of the Gidas-Ni-Nirenberg problem involving the $p$-Laplacian and for small perturbations the critical $p$-Laplace equation for $p&gt;2$.
  To achieve these results, we provide a quantitative review of the work by Damascelli &amp; Sciunzi (Calc. Var. Partial Differential Equations 25 (2006), no. 2, 139-159) concerning the weak Harnack comparison inequality and the local boundedness comparison inequality. Moreover, we prove a comparison principle for small domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11759v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michele Gatti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Lamm-Rivi\`ere system II: energy identity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11802v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish an angular energy quantization for the following fourth order inhomogeneous Lamm-Rivi\`ere system $$ \Delta^2u=\Delta(V\cdot\nabla u)+\text{div}(w\nabla u)+W\cdot\nabla u+f $$ in dimension four, with an inhomogeneous term $f\in L\log L$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11802v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chang-Yu Guo, Wen-Juan Qi, Zhao-Min Sun, Changyou Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak solutions and sharp interface limit of the anisotropic Cahn-Hilliard equation with disparate mobility and inhomogeneous potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11849v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the existence of weak solutions and the corresponding sharp interface limit of an anisotropic Cahn-Hilliard equation with disparate mobility, i.e., the mobility is degenerate in one of the two pure phases, making the diffusion in that phase vanish. The double-well potential is polynomial and is weighted by a spatially inhomogeneous coefficient. In the limit when the parameter of the interface width tends to zero, and under an energy convergence assumption, we prove that the weak solutions converge to BV solutions of a weighted anisotropic Hele-Shaw flow. We also add some numerical simulations to analyze the effects of anisotropy on the Cahn-Hilliard equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11849v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles Elbar, Andrea Poiatti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An initial-boundary problem for a mixed fractional wave equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11871v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We aim to prove a unique solvability of an initial-boundary value problem (IBVP) for a time-fractional wave equation in a rectangular domain. We exploited the spectral expansion method as a main tool and used the solution to Cauchy problems for fractional-order differential equations. Moreover, certain properties of the Mittag-Leffler-type functions of single and two variables have been applied to prove the uniform convergence of the solution to the considered problem, represented in the form of infinite series.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11871v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erkinjon Karimov, Nasser Al-Salti, Muna Al-Ghabsi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trace operators for Riemann--Liouville fractional equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11884</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11884v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We begin with a brief overview of the most commonly used fractional derivatives, namely the Caputo and Riemann-Liouville derivatives. We then focus on the study of the fractional time wave equation with the Riemann-Liouville derivative, addressing key questions such as well-posedness, regularity, and a trace result in appropriate interpolation spaces. Additionally, we explore the duality relationship with the Caputo fractional time derivative. The analysis is based on expanding the solution in terms of Mittag-Leffler functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11884v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paola Loreti, Daniela Sforza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stationary wave solutions to two dimensional viscous shallow water equations: theory of small and large solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11899v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a system of forced viscous shallow water equations with nontrivial bathymetry in two spatial dimensions. We develop a well-posedness theory for small but arbitrary forcing data, as well as for a fixed data profile but large amplitude. In the latter case, solutions may actually fail to exist for large amplitude, but in this case we prove that one of three physically meaningful breakdown scenarios occurs. Through the use of implicit function theorem techniques and a priori estimates, we construct both spatially periodic and solitary (non-periodic but spatially localized) solutions. The solitary case is substantially more complicated, requiring a delicate analysis in weighted Sobolev spaces. To the best of our knowledge, these results constitute the first general construction of stationary wave solutions, large or otherwise, to the viscous shallow water equations and the first general analysis of large solitary wave solutions to any viscous free boundary fluid model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11899v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noah Stevenson, Ian Tice</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Removable set for H\"older continuous solutions of $\mathscr{A}$-harmonic functions on Finsler manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish that a closed set $\mathcal{S}$ is removable for $\alpha$-H\"older continuous $\mathscr{A}$-harmonic functions in a reversible Finsler manifold $(\Omega, F, \mathtt{V})$ of dimension $n \geq 2$, provided that (under certain conditions on $(\Omega, F, \mathtt{V})$ and the variable exponent $p$ ) for each compact subset $K$ of $\mathcal{S}$, the $\mathrm{n}_1-p_K^{+}+\alpha\left(p_K^{+}-1\right)$-Hausdorff measure of $K$ is zero. Here, $p_K^{+}=\sup _K p$ and $\mathrm{n}_1$ is chosen so that $\mathtt{V}(B(x, r)) \leq \mathtt{K} r^{\mathrm{n}_1}$ for every ball.
  The estimates used to remove the singularities will focus on a family $\left\{u_{\ell}\right\}_{\ell \in \mathcal{J}} \subset W_{\mathrm{loc}}^{1, p(x)}(\Omega ; \mathtt{V})$ that converges to $u$ in a certain sense. As a second main result of this article, we will also obtain an estimate (when $\lim _{d\left(x, 0_{\Omega}\right) \rightarrow \infty} p=1$ ) for $$ \mu_{\ell}(B(x, r)):=\sup \left\{\int_{B(x, r)} \mathscr{A} \left(\cdot, \nabla u_{\ell}\right) \bullet \mathcal{D} \zeta \mathrm{dV} \mid 0 \leq \zeta \leq 1 \text { and } \zeta \in C_0^{\infty}(B(x, r))\right\}, $$ which is related to the measure $\mu=\operatorname{div}( \mathscr{A} (\cdot, \nabla u))$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11922v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Pablo Alcon Apaza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasiconvexity and self-improving size estimates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11980v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that M\"uller's $L\log L$ bound $$F(Du)\geq 0,\,Du\in L^p_{\mathrm{loc}}(\mathbb{R}^n)\implies F(Du)\in L\log L_{\mathrm{loc}}(\mathbb{R}^n)$$ for $F =\det$ and $p=n$ holds for quasiconcave $F$ which are homogeneous of degree $p&gt;1$. This contrasts similar Hardy space bounds which hold only for null Lagrangians.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11980v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bogdan Rai\c{t}\u{a}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Formulation and Capacity Estimates for Non-Self-Adjoint Fokker-Planck Operators in Divergence Form</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12036v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a variational formulation for a general class of possibly degenerate, non-self-adjoint Fokker-Planck operators in divergence form, motivated by the work of Albritton et al. (2024), and prove that it is suitable for defining the variational capacity. Using this framework, we establish rough estimates for the equilibrium potential in the elliptic case, providing a novel approach compared to previous methods. Finally, we derive the Eyring-Kramers formula for non-self-adjoint elliptic Fokker-Planck operators in divergence form, extending the results of Landim et al. (2019) and Lee &amp; Seo (2022).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12036v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingyi Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Examples of $p$-harmonic maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12059v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct explicit examples of $p$-harmonic maps $u:\mathbb{R}^n \to \mathbb{R}^N$. These are more irregular than the previously known examples and thus provide new upper bounds for the regularity of $p$-harmonic maps, including the case of $\infty$-harmonic maps. To optimize our approach, we utilize solutions of the Hurwitz problem from algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12059v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Balci, Linus Behn, Lars Diening, Johannes Storn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularized $n$-Conformal heat flow and global smoothness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10679v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce the regularized conformal heat flow of $n$-harmonic maps, or simply regularized $n$-conformal heat flow from $n$-dimensional Riemannian manifold. This is a system of evolution equations combined with regularized $n$-harmonic map flow and a metric evolution equation in conformal direction. For $n=2$, the conformal heat flow does not develop finite time singularity unlike usual harmonic map flow \cite{P23} (Park, 2024). In this paper, we show the analogous result, that regularized $n$-conformal heat flow does not develop finite time singularity unlike the (regularized) $n$-harmonic map flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10679v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Woongbae Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incidence bounds related to circular Furstenberg sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10686v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove bounds on approximate incidences between families of circles and families of points in the plane. As a consequence, we prove a lower bound for the dimension of circular $(u,v)$-Furstenberg sets, which is new for large $u$ and $v$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10686v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Green, Terence L. J. Harris, Yumeng Ou, Kevin Ren, Sarah Tammen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating convergence of a natural convection solver by continuous data assimilation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10850v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Picard iteration for the Boussinesq model of natural convection can be an attractive solver because it stably decouples the fluid equations from the temperature equation (for contrast, the Newton iteration does not stably decouple). However, the convergence of Picard for this system is only linear and slows as the Rayleigh number increases, eventually failing for even moderately sized Rayleigh numbers. We consider this solver in the setting where sparse solution data is available, e.g. from data measurements or solution observables, and enhance Picard by incorporating the data into the iteration using a continuous data assimilation (CDA) approach. We prove that our approach scales the linear convergence rate by $H^{1/2}$, where $H$ is the characteristic spacing of the measurement locations. This implies that when Picard is converging, CDA will accelerate convergence, and when Picard is not converging, CDA (with enough data) will enable convergence. In the case of noisy data, we prove that the linear convergence rate of the nonlinear residual is similarly scaled by $H^{1/2}$ but the accuracy is limited by the accuracy of the data. Several numerical tests illustrate the effectiveness of the proposed method, including when the data is noisy. These tests show that CDA style nudging adapted to an iteration (instead of a time stepping scheme) enables convergence at much higher $Ra$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10850v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elizabeth Hawkins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A large data semi-global existence and convergence theorem for vacuum Einstein's equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11289v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: I prove a convergence theorem in the context of $3+1$ dimensional vacuum Einstein's equations including a positive cosmological constant on spacetimes $\widetilde{M}$ of topological type $M\times \mathbb{R}$, where $M$ is a closed connected oriented Riemannian $3-$manifold of negative Yamabe type. The theorem concerns the global existence of the solutions of the vacuum Einstein$-\Lambda$ equations for arbitrary large initial data and convergence of the spatial geometry to a constant negative scalar curvature metric in a constant mean extrinsic curvature (CMC) transported spatial gauge. This theorem could be interpreted as a weak cosmic censorship result in the cosmological framework under \textit{generic} initial data. An important corollary of the theorem is the failure of cosmological principle as a derived consequence of Einstein's equations including a positive cosmological constant as well as the failure of geometrization of spatial slice in the sense of Thurston. A similar theorem is stated for positive Yamabe slices under a technical assumption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11289v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Puskar Mondal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on optimization of the second positive Neumann eigenvalue for parallelograms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11542v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It has recently been conjectured by Bogosel, Henrot, and Michetti that the second positive eigenvalue of the Neumann Laplacian is maximized, among all planar convex domains of fixed perimeter, by the rectangle with one edge length equal to twice the other. In this note we prove that this conjecture is true within the class of parallelogram domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11542v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Lotoreichik, Jonathan Rohleder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Iterative Procedure for Non-Linear Fractional Integro-Differential Equations via Daftardar--Jafari Polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11676</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11676v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce a novel approach called the Iterative Aboodh Transform Method (IATM) which utilizes Daftardar--Jafari polynomials for solving non-linear problems. Such method is employed to derive solutions for non-linear fractional partial integro-differential equations (FPIDEs). The key novelty of the suggested method is that it can be used for handling solutions of non-linear FPIDEs in a very simple and effective way. {More precisely, we show that Daftardar--Jafari polynomials have simple calculations as compared to Adomian polynomials with higher accuracy}. The results obtained within the Daftardar--Jafari polynomials are demonstrated with graphs and tables, and the IATM's absolute error confirms the higher accuracy of the suggested method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11676v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qasim Khan, Anthony Suen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixing for dynamical systems driven by stationary noises</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11699v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The paper deals with the problem of long-time asymptotic behaviour of solutions for classes of ODEs and PDEs, perturbed by stationary noises. The latter are not assumed to be $\delta$-correlated in time, so that the evolution in question is not necessarily Markovian. We first prove an abstract result which imply the mixing for random dynamical systems satisfying appropriate dissipativity and controllability conditions. It is applicable to a large class of evolution equations, and we illustrate it on the examples of a chain of anharmonic oscillators coupled to heat reservoirs, the 2d Navier-Stokes system, and a complex Ginzburg-Landau equation. Our results also apply to the general theory of random processes on the 1d lattice and allow one to get for them results related to Dobrushin's theorems on reconstructing processes via their conditional distributions. The proof is based on an iterative construction with quadratic convergence. It uses the method of Kantorovich functional, introduced in [KPS02, Kuk02, Kuk06] in the context of randomly forced PDEs, and some ideas suggested in [Shi15, KNS20] to prove mixing with the help of controllability properties of an associated system</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11699v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergei Kuksin, Armen Shirikyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A family of triharmonic maps to spheres in all dimensions greater than two</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11898v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a construction method for triharmonic maps to spheres. In particular, we show that for any $m\in\mathbb{N}$ with $m\geq 3$ there exists a triharmonic map from $\mathbb{R}^m\setminus\{0\}$ into a round sphere. In addition, we provide a construction method for proper $r$-harmonic maps between spheres based on a suitable deformation of eigenmaps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11898v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Volker Branding, Anna Siffert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximating a spatially-heterogeneously mass-emitting object by multiple point sources in a diffusion model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11908v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Various biological cells secrete diffusing chemical compounds into their environment for communication purposes. Secretion usually takes place over the cell membrane in a spatially heterogeneous manner. Mathematical models of these processes will be part of more elaborate models, e.g. of the movement of immune cells that react to cytokines in their environment. Here, we compare two approaches to modelling of the secretion-diffusion process of signalling compounds. The first is the so-called spatial exclusion model, in which the intracellular space is excluded from consideration and the computational space is the extracellular environment. The second consists of point source models, where the secreting cell is replaced by one or more non-spatial point sources or sinks, using -- mathematically -- Dirac delta distributions. We propose a multi-Dirac approach and provide explicit expressions for the intensities of the Dirac distributions. We show that two to three well-positioned Dirac points suffice to approximate well a temporally constant but spatially heterogeneous flux distribution of compound over the cell membrane, for a wide range of variation in flux density and diffusivity. The multi-Dirac approach is compared to a single-Dirac approach that was studied in previous work. Moreover, an explicit Green's function approach is introduced that has significant benefits in circumventing numerical instability that may occur when the Dirac sources have high intensities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11908v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiyao Peng, Sander C. Hille</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vlasov Equations on Directed Hypergraph Measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.03806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.03806v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we propose a framework to investigate the mean field limit (MFL) of interacting particle systems on directed hypergraphs. We provide a non-trivial measure-theoretic viewpoint and make extensions of directed hypergraphs as directed hypergraph measures (DHGMs), which are measure-valued functions on a compact metric space. These DHGMs can be regarded as hypergraph limits which include limits of a sequence of hypergraphs that are sparse, dense, or of intermediate densities. Our main results show that the Vlasov equation on DHGMs are well-posed and its solution can be approximated by empirical distributions of large networks of higher-order interactions. The results are applied to a Kuramoto network in physics, an epidemic network, and an ecological network, all of which include higher-order interactions. To prove the main results on the approximation and well-posedness of the Vlasov equation on DHGMs, we robustly generalize the method of [Kuehn, Xu. Vlasov equations on digraph measures, JDE, 339 (2022), 261--349] to higher-dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.03806v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Kuehn, Chuang Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two dimensional NLS ground states with attractive Coulomb potential and point interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.13629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.13629v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the existence and the properties of ground states at fixed mass for a focusing nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation in dimension two with a point interaction, an attractive Coulomb potential and a nonlinearity of power type. We prove that for any negative value of the Coulomb charge, for any positive value of the mass and for any L$^2$-subcritical power nonlinearity, such ground states exist and exhibit a logarithmic singularity where the interaction is placed. Moreover, up to multiplication by a phase factor, they are positive, radially symmetric and decreasing. An analogous result is obtained also for minimizers of the action restricted to the Nehari manifold, getting the existence also in the L$^2$-critical and supercritical cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.13629v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jde.2024.08.076</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Differential Equations 414 (2025) 1-33</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Boni, Matteo Gallone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well-posedness for Ohkitani model and long-time existence for surface quasi-geostrophic equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.02107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.02107v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the Cauchy problem for the logarithmically singular surface quasi-geostrophic (SQG) equation, introduced by Ohkitani, $$\partial_t \theta - \nabla^\perp \log(10+(-\Delta)^{\frac12})\theta \cdot \nabla \theta = 0 ,$$ and establish local existence and uniqueness of smooth solutions in the scale of Sobolev spaces with exponent decreasing with time. Such a decrease of the Sobolev exponent is necessary, as we have shown in the companion paper that the problem is strongly ill-posed in any fixed Sobolev spaces. The time dependence of the Sobolev exponent can be removed when there is a dissipation term strictly stronger than log. These results improve wellposedness statements by Chae, Constantin, C\'{o}rdoba, Gancedo, and Wu in \cite{CCCGW}.
  This well-posedness result can be applied to describe the long-time dynamics of the $\delta$-SQG equations, defined by $$\partial_t \theta + \nabla^\perp (10+(-\Delta)^{\frac12})^{-\delta}\theta \cdot \nabla \theta = 0,$$ for all sufficiently small $\delta&gt;0$ depending on the size of the initial data. For the same range of $\delta$, we establish global well-posedness of smooth solutions to the logarithmically dissipative counterpart: $$\partial_t \theta + \nabla^\perp (10+(-\Delta)^{\frac12})^{-\delta}\theta \cdot \nabla \theta + \log(10+(-\Delta)^{\frac12})\theta = 0.$$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.02107v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongho Chae, In-Jee Jeong, Jungkyoung Na, Sung-Jin Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The blow-up rate for a loglog non-scaling invariant semilinear wave equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.12220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.12220v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider blow-up solutions of a semilinear wave equation with a loglog perturbation of the power nonlinearity in the subconformal case, and show that the blow-up rate is given by the solution of the associated ODE which has the same blow-up time. In fact, our result shows an upper bound and a lower bound of the blow-up rate, both proportional to the blow-up solution of the associated ODE. The main difficulty comes from the fact that the PDE is not scaling invariant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.12220v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tristan Roy, Hatem Zaag</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exotic traveling waves for a quasilinear Schr\"odinger equation with nonzero background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.08918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.08918v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a defocusing quasilinear Schr\"odinger equation with nonzero conditions at infinity in dimension one. This quasilinear model corresponds to a weakly nonlocal approximation of the nonlocal Gross--Pitaevskii equation, and can also be derived by considering the effects of surface tension in superfluids. When the quasilinear term is neglected, the resulting equation is the classical Gross-Pitaevskii equation, which possesses a well-known stable branch of subsonic traveling waves solution, given by dark solitons.
  Our goal is to investigate how the quasilinear term affects the traveling-waves solutions. We provide a complete classification of finite energy traveling waves of the equation, in terms of the two parameters: the speed and the strength of the quasilinear term. This classification leads to the existence of dark and antidark solitons, as well as more exotic localized solutions like dark cuspons, compactons, and composite waves, even for supersonic speeds. Depending on the parameters, these types of solutions can coexist, showing that finite energy solutions are not unique. Furthermore, we prove that some of these dark solitons can be obtained as minimizers of the energy, at fixed momentum, and that they are orbitally stable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.08918v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andr\'e de Laire, Erwan Le Quiniou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Studies on a system of nonlinear Schr\"odinger equations with potential and quadratic interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.06225v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we study the existence of various classes of standing waves for a nonlinear Schr\"odinger system with quadratic interaction, along with a harmonic or partially harmonic potential. We establish the existence of ground-state normalized solutions for this system, which serve as local minimizers of the associated functionals. To address the difficulties raised by the potential term, we employ profile decomposition and concentration-compactness principles. The absence of global energy minimizers in critical and supercritical cases leads us to focus on local energy minimizers. Positive results arise in scenarios of partial confinement, attributed to the spectral properties of the associated linear operators. Furthermore, we demonstrate the existence of a second normalized solution using Mountain-pass geometry, effectively navigating the difficulties posed by the nonlinear terms. We also explore the asymptotic behavior of local minimizers, revealing connections with unique eigenvectors of the linear operators. Additionally, we identify global and blow-up solutions over time under specific conditions, contributing new insights into the dynamics of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.06225v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vicente Alvarez, Amin Esfahani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable solution and extremal solution for fractional $p$-Laplacian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.16624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.16624v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To our knowledge, this paper is the first attempt to consider the existence issue for fractional $p$-Laplacian equation: $(-\Delta)_p^s u= \lambda f(u),\; u&gt; 0 ~\text{in}~\Omega;\; u=0\;\text{in}~ \mathbb{R}^N\setminus\Omega$, where $p&gt;1$, $s\in (0,1)$, $\lambda&gt;0$ and $\Omega$ is a bounded domain with $C^{1, 1}$ boundary. We first propose a notion of stable solution, then we prove that when $f$ is of class $C^1$, nondecreasing and satisfying $f(0)&gt;0$ and $\underset{t\to \infty}{\lim}\frac{f(t)}{t^{p-1}}=\infty$, there exists an extremal parameter $\lambda^*\in (0, \infty)$ such that a bounded minimal solution $u_\lambda \in W_0^{s,p}(\Omega)$ exists if $\lambda\in (0, \lambda^*)$, and no bounded solution exists if $\lambda&gt;\lambda^*$. Moreover, no $W_0^{s,p}(\Omega)$ solution exists for $\lambda &gt; \lambda^*$ if in addition $f(t)^{\frac{1}{p-1}}$ is convex.
  To handle our problems, we show a Kato-type inequality for fractional $p$-Laplacian. We show also $L^r$ estimates for the equation $(-\Delta)_p^su=g$ with $g\in W_0^{s, p}(\Omega)^*\cap L^q(\Omega)$ for $q \geq 1$, especially for $q \le \frac{N}{sp}$. We believe that these general results have their own interests. Finally, using the stability of minimal solutions $u_\lambda$, under the polynomial growth or convexity assumption on $f$, we show that the extremal function $u_* =\lim_{\lambda\to\lambda^*}u_\lambda \in W_0^{s,p}(\Omega)$ in all dimensions, and $u^*\in L^{\infty}(\Omega)$ in some low dimensional cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.16624v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3934/dcds.2025005</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Weimin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform-in-time estimates on corrections to mean field for interacting Brownian particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19306</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19306v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a system of classical Brownian particles interacting via a smooth long-range potential in the mean-field regime, and we analyze the propagation of chaos in form of sharp, uniform-in-time estimates on many-particle correlation functions. Our results cover both the kinetic Langevin setting and the corresponding overdamped Brownian dynamics. The approach is mainly based on so-called Lions expansions, which we combine with new diagrammatic tools to capture many-particle cancellations, as well as with fine ergodic estimates on the linearized mean-field equation, and with discrete stochastic calculus with respect to initial data. In the process, we derive some new ergodic estimates for the linearized Vlasov-Fokker-Planck kinetic equation that are of independent interest. Our analysis also leads to a uniform-in-time quantitative central limit theorem and to uniform-in-time concentration estimates for the empirical measure associated with the particle dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19306v4</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Armand Bernou, Mitia Duerinckx</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stationary solution to Stochastically Forced Euler-Poisson Equations in Bounded Domain: Part 1. 3-D Insulating Boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00017v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is concerned with $3$-D stochastic Euler-Poisson equations with insulating boundary conditions forced by the Wiener process. We first establish the global existence and uniqueness of the solution to the system, then we prove that the solution converges to its steady-state time-asymptotically. To obtain the converging rate, we need to develop weighted energy estimates, which are not required for the deterministic counterpart of the problem. Moreover, we observe that the invariant measure is just the Dirac measure generated by the steady-state, in which the time-exponential convergence rate to the steady-state plays an essential role.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00017v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yachun Li, Ming Mei, Lizhen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$C^2$ estimates for $k$-Hessian equations and a rigidity theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10781v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive a concavity inequality for $k$-Hessian operators under the semi-convexity condition. As an application, we establish interior estimates for semi-convex solutions of the $k$-Hessian equations with vanishing Dirichlet boundary and obtain a Liouville-type result. Additionally, we provide new and simple proofs of Guan-Ren-Wang's results on global curvature estimates for $k$-curvature equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10781v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruijia Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shape Derivatives of the Eigenvalues of the De Rham Complex for Lipschitz Deformations and Variable Coefficients: Part I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19960v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study eigenvalue problems for the de Rham complex on varying three dimensional domains. Our analysis includes the Helmholtz equation as well as the Maxwell system with mixed boundary conditions and non-constant coefficients. We provide Hadamard-type formulas for the shape derivatives under weak regularity assumptions on the domain and its perturbations. Our proofs are based on abstract results adapted to varying Hilbert complexes. As a bypass product of our analysis we give a proof of the celebrated Helmann-Feynman theorem both for simple and multiple eigenvalues of suitable families of self-adjoint operators in Hilbert space depending on possibly infinite dimensional parameters. This series of papers consists of Parts I and II.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19960v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pier Domenico Lamberti, Dirk Pauly, Michele Zaccaron</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Similar Solutions to the steady Navier-Stokes Equations in a two-dimensional sector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07283v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is concerned with self-similar solutions of the steady Navier-Stokes system in a two-dimensional sector with the no-slip boundary condition. We give necessary and sufficient conditions in terms of the angle of the sector and the flux to guarantee the existence of self-similar solutions of a given type. We also investigate the uniqueness and non-uniqueness of flows with a given type, which not only give rigorous justifications for some statements in \cite{Rosenhead40} but also show that some numerical computations in \cite{Rosenhead40} may not be precise. The non-uniqueness result is a new phenomenon for these flows. As a consequence of the classification of self-similar solutions in the half-space, we characterize the leading order term of the steady Navier-Stokes system in an aperture domain when the flux is small. The main approach is to study the ODE system governing self-similar solutions, where the detailed properties of both complete and incomplete elliptic functions have been investigated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07283v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeaheang Bang, Changfeng Gui, Hao Liu, Yun Wang, Chunjing Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unconditional well-posendness for the fourth order nonlinear Schrodinger type equations on the torus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11455v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the unconditional well-posedness for the fourth order nonlinear Schrodinger type equations in H^s(\mathbb{T}) when s \geq 1, which includes the non-integrable case. This regularity threshold is optimal because the nonlinear terms cannot be defined in the space-time distribution framework for s&lt;1. The main idea is to employ the normal form reduction and a kind of cancellation property to deal with derivative losses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11455v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takamori Kato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the well-posedness of (nonlinear) rough continuity equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04982v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by applications to fluid dynamics, we study rough differential equations (RDEs) and rough partial differential equations (RPDEs) with non-Lipschitz drifts. We prove well-posedness and existence of a flow for RDEs with Osgood drifts, as well as well-posedness of weak $L^p$-valued solutions to linear rough continuity and transport equations on $\mathbb{R}^d$ under DiPerna--Lions regularity conditions; a combination of the two then yields flow representation formula for linear RPDEs. We apply these results to obtain existence, uniqueness and continuous dependence for $L^1\cap L^\infty$-valued solutions to a general class of nonlinear continuity equations. In particular, our framework covers the $2$D Euler equations in vorticity form with rough transport noise, providing a rough analogue of Yudovich's theorem. As a consequence, we construct an associated continuous random dynamical system, when the driving noise is a fractional Brownian motion with Hurst parameter $H \in (1/3,1)$. We further prove weak existence of solutions for initial vorticities in $L^1\cap L^p$, for any $p\in [1,\infty)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04982v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucio Galeati, James-Michael Leahy, Torstein Nilssen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disc stackings and their Morse index</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.07138v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct free boundary minimal disc stackings, with any number of strata, in the three-dimensional Euclidean unit ball, and prove uniform, linear lower and upper bounds on the Morse index of all such surfaces. Among other things, our work implies for any positive integer $k$ the existence of $k$-tuples of distinct, pairwise non-congruent, embedded free boundary minimal surfaces all having the same topological type. In addition, since we prove that the equivariant Morse index of any such free boundary minimal stacking, with respect to its maximal symmetry group, is bounded from below by (the integer part of) half the number of layers, it follows that any possible realization of such surfaces via an equivariant min-max method would need to employ sweepouts with an arbitrarily large number of parameters. This also shows that it is only for $N=2$ and $N=3$ layers that free boundary minimal disc stackings can be obtained by means of one-dimensional mountain pass schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.07138v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Carlotto, Mario B. Schulz, David Wiygul</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularization of Stationary Second-order Mean Field Game Partial Differential Inclusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10810v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Mean field Game (MFG) Partial Differential Inclusions (PDI) are generalizations of the system of Partial Differential Equations (PDE) of Lasry and Lions to situations where players in the game may have possibly nonunique optimal controls, and the resulting Hamiltonian is not required to be differentiable. We study second-order MFG PDI with convex, Lipschitz continuous, but possibly nondifferentiable Hamiltonians, and their approximation by systems of classical MFG PDE with regularized Hamiltonians. Under very broad conditions on the problem data, we show that, up to subsequences, the solutions of the regularized problems converge to solutions of the MFG PDI. In particular, we show the convergence of the value functions in the $H^1$-norm and of the densities in $L^q$-norms. Under stronger hypotheses on the problem data, we also show rates of convergence between the solutions of the original and regularized problems, without requiring any higher regularity of the solutions. We give concrete examples that demonstrate the sharpness of several aspects of the analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10810v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yohance A. P. Osborne, Iain Smears</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A normalized Ricci flow on surfaces with boundary towards the complete hyperbolic metric</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00660v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $(\overline{M},g_0)$ be a $2$-D compact surface with boundary $\partial M$ and its interior $M$. We show that for a large class of initial and boundary data, the initial-boundary value problem of the normalized Ricci flow $(1.10)-(1.12)$, with prescribed geodesic curvature $\psi$ on $\partial M$, has a unique solution for all $t&gt;0$, and it converges to the complete hyperbolic metric locally uniformly in $M$. Here the natural condition that $\psi&gt;0$ causes the main difficulty in the a priori estimates in the corresponding initial-boundary problem $(1.15)-(1.17)$ of the parabolic equations, for which an auxiliary Cauchy-Dirichlet problem is introduced. We also provide examples of the boundary data $\psi$ which fits well with the natural asymptotic behavior of the geodesic curvature, but the solution to $(1.10)-(1.12)$ fails to converge to the complete hyperbolic metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00660v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
