<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 04:00:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A subsequentially fast dynamo on $\mathbb{T}^3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.23936</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.23936v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We construct a smooth velocity field $u$ on $\mathbb{R}_+ \times \mathbb{T}^3$ that exhibits kinematic dynamo action, causing exponential growth in solutions to the magnetohydrodynamic induction equation, with a rate that is uniform in diffusivity, for suitable sequences of diffusivity $\kappa_j \to 0.$ We call this a subsequentially fast dynamo, giving dynamo behavior intermediate between a truly slow dynamo and a truly fast dynamo.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.23936v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keefer Rowan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence of new self-similar solutions of the fast diffusion equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24131v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $n\ge 3$, $0&lt;m&lt;\frac{n-2}{n}$, $\eta&gt;0$, $\eta_0&gt;0$, $\rho_1&gt;0$, $-\frac{\rho_1}{2}&lt;\beta&lt;\frac{m\rho_1}{n-2-nm}$ and $\alpha=\frac{2\beta+\rho_1}{1-m}$. We will prove the existence of radially symmetric solution of the equation $\Delta(f^m/m)+\alpha f+\beta x\cdot\nabla f=0$, $f&gt;0$, in $\mathbb{R}^n$, which satisfies $f(0)=\eta_0$, $f_r(0)=0$. When $\beta&lt;\frac{m\rho_1}{n-2-nm}$ holds instead, we will also prove the existence of radially symmetric solution of the equation $\Delta(f^m/m)+\alpha f+\beta x\cdot\nabla f=0$, $f&gt;0$, in $\mathbb{R}^n\setminus\{0\}$, which satisfies $\lim_{x\to\infty}|x|^{\frac{n-2}{m}}f(x)=\eta$. As a consequence if $f_1$, $f_2$, are the solutions of the above two problems with $\rho_1=1$, then the function $V_i(x,t)=(T-t)^{\alpha}f_i(T-t)^{\beta} x)$, $i=1,2$, are backward similar solutions of the fast diffusion equation $u_t=\Delta (u^m/m)$ in $\mathbb{R}^n\times (-\infty,T)$ and $(\mathbb{R}^n\setminus\{0\})\times (-\infty,T)$ respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24131v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kin Ming Hui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the time-decay with the diffusion wave phenomenon of the solution to the compressible Navier-Stokes-Korteweg system in critical spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24206v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the initial value problem of the compressible Navier-Stokes-Korteweg equations in the whole space $\mathbb{R}^d$ ($d \ge 2$). The purposes of this paper are to obtain the global-in-time solution around the constant equilibrium states $(\rho_*,0)$ and investigate the $L^p$-$L^1$ type time-decay estimates in a scaling critical framework, where $\rho_*&gt;0$ is a constant. In addition, we study the diffusion wave property came from the wave equation with strong damping for the solution with the initial data belonging to the critical Besov space. The key idea of the proof is the derivation of the time-decay for the Fourier-Besov norm with higher derivatives by using $L^1$-maximal regularity for the perturbed equations around $(\rho_*,0)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24206v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takayuki Kobayashi, Ryosuke Nakasato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear PDEs with modulated dispersion IV: normal form approach and unconditional uniqueness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24270v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the modulated Korteweg-de~Vries equation (KdV) on the circle with a time non-homogeneous modulation acting on the linear dispersion term. By adapting the normal form approach to the modulated setting, we prove sharp unconditional uniqueness of solutions to the modulated KdV in $L^2(\mathbb T)$ if a modulation is sufficiently irregular. For example, this result implies that if the modulation is given by a sample path of a fractional Brownian motion with Hurst index $0 &lt; H &lt; \frac 25$, the modulated KdV on the circle is unconditionally well-posed in $L^2(\mathbb T)$. Our normal form approach provides the construction of solutions to the modulated KdV (and the associated nonlinear Young integral) {\it without} assuming any positive regularity in time. As an interesting byproduct of our normal form approach, we extend the construction of the nonlinear Young integral to a much larger class of functions, and obtain an improved Euler approximation scheme as compared to the classical sewing lemma approach. We also establish analogous sharp unconditional uniqueness results for the modulated Benjamin-Ono equation and the modulated derivative nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation (NLS) with a quadratic nonlinearity. In the appendix, we prove sharp unconditional uniqueness of the cubic modulated NLS on the circle in $H^{\frac 16}(\mathbb T)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24270v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Massimiliano Gubinelli, Guopeng Li, Jiawei Li, Tadahiro Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting Bourgain's probabilistic construction of solutions to the 2-$d$ cubic NLS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24271v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a seminal paper (1996), Bourgain proved invariance of the Gibbs measure for the defocusing cubic nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation on the two-dimensional torus by constructing local-in-time solutions in a probabilistic manner. In this note, we revisit and streamline his argument, using the random tensor estimate developed by Deng, Nahmod, and Yue (2022).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24271v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tadahiro Oh, Yuzhao Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Factorization method for near-field inverse scattering problems in elastodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24288v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Consider a time-harmonic elastic point source incident on a bounded obstacle which is embedded in an open space filled with a homogeneous and isotropic elastic medium. This paper is concerned with the inverse problem of recovering the location and shape of the obstacle from near-field data generated by infinitely many incident point source waves at a fixed energy. The incident point sources and the receivers for recording scattered signals are both located on a spherical closed surface, on which an outgoing-to-incoming operator is defined for facilitating the factorization of the near-field operator. Numerical examples in 2D are presented to show the validity and accuracy of the inversion algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24288v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chun Liu, Guanghui Hu, Tao Yin, Bo Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adams-Trudinger-Moser inequalities of Adimurthi-Druet type regulated by the vanishing phenomenon and its extremals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24297v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $W^{m,\frac{n}{m}}(\mathbb{R}^n)$ with $1\le m &lt; n$ be the standard higher order derivative Sobolev space in the critical exponential growth threshold. We investigate a new Adams-Adimurthi-Druet type inequality on the whole space $\mathbb{R}^n$ which is strongly influenced by the vanishing phenomenon. Specifically, we prove
  \begin{equation}\nonumber
  \sup_{\underset{\|\nabla^{m} u\|_{\frac{n}{m}}^{^{\frac{n}{m}}}+\|u\|_{\frac{n}{m}}^{\frac{n}{m}} \leq 1}{u\in W^{m,\frac{n}{m}}(\mathbb{R}^n)}} \int_{\mathbb{R}^n}\Phi\left(\beta \left(\frac{1+\alpha\|u\|_{\frac{n}{m}}^{\frac{n}{m}}}{1-\gamma\alpha\|u\|_{\frac{n}{m}}^{\frac{n}{m}}}\right)^{\frac{m}{n-m}}|u|^{\frac{n}{n-m}}\right) \mathrm{d}x&lt;+\infty.
  \end{equation}
  where $0\le \alpha&lt;1$, $0&lt;\gamma&lt;\frac{1}{\alpha}-1$ for $\alpha&gt;0$, $\nabla^{m} u$ is the $m$-th order gradient for $u$, $0\le\beta\le \beta_0$, with $\beta_0$ being the Adams critical constant, and $\Phi(t) = \operatorname{e}^{t}-\sum_{j=0}^{j_{m,n}-2}\frac{t^{j}}{j!}$ with $j_{m,n}=\min\{j\in\mathbb{N}\;:\: j\ge n/m\}$. In addition, we prove that the constant $\beta_0$ is sharp.
  In the subcritical case $\beta&lt;\beta_0$, the existence and non-existence of extremal function are investigated for $n=2m$ and attainability is proven for $n=4$ and $m=2$ in the critical case $\beta=\beta_0$. Our method to analyze the extremal problem is based on blow-up analysis, a truncation argument recently introduced by DelaTorre-Mancini \cite{DelaTorre} and some ideas by Chen-Lu-Zhu \cite{luluzhu20}, who studied the critical Adams inequality in $\mathbb{R}^4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24297v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abiel Costa Macedo, Jos\'e Francisco de Oliveira, F\'abio Sodr\'e Rocha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relaxed uniqueness conditions for the parabolic Schrodinger equation on Riemannian manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24368v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study uniqueness for solutions to the Cauchy problem associated with the parabolic Schr\"odinger equation on complete noncompact Riemannian manifolds, under suitable integral conditions on the solution. We show that, under suitable assumptions on the potential V, the required integrability condition can be significantly relaxed compared to the case without potential. This improvement is achieved by exploiting the decay of positive solutions to the associated stationary Schrodinger equation. To the best of our knowledge, identifying how the behavior of the potential influences the uniqueness integral condition, through the decay properties of solutions to the corresponding stationary equation, constitutes a novel contribution to the theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24368v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Punzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-bubble solutions for the Brezis-Nirenberg problem in four dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24387v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paper addresses the existence of multi-bubble solutions for the well-known Brezis-Nirenberg problem. Although there is extensive literature on the subject, the existence of solutions that blow up at multiple points in a 4D bounded domain remains an open problem. The goal of the present paper is to resolve this longstanding issue. In particular, we exhibit examples of domains where a large number of multi-bubble solutions exist. Our result can also be seen as the counterpart of the asymptotic analysis carried out by Konig and Laurin in Ann. Inst. H. Poincar\`e C Anal. Non Lin\`eaire, 2024.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24387v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angela Pistoia, Giuseppe Mario Rago, Giusi Vaira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$C^{1,\alpha}$ regularity of the solution for the obstacle problem for the linearized Monge-Amp\`ere operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24410v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the regularity of the solution for the obstacle problem associated with the linearized Monge-Amp\`ere operator: \begin{align*}
  \begin{cases}
  &amp;u\geq\varphi \text{\quad in } \Omega
  &amp;L_{ w}u=\tr( W D^{2}u)\leq 0 \text{\quad in } \Omega
  &amp;L_{ w}u= 0 \text{\quad in } \{u&gt;\varphi\}
  &amp;u=0 \text{\quad on } \partial\Omega,
  \end{cases} \end{align*} where $ W=(\det D^{2} w) D^{2} w^{-1}$ is the matrix of cofactor of $D^{2} w$, $w$ satisfies $\lambda \leq \det D^{2} w \leq \Lambda$ and $ w=0$ on $\partial \Omega$, $\varphi$ is the obstacle with at least $C^{2}(\bar{\Omega})$ smoothness, $\Omega$ is an open bounded convex domain. We show the existence and uniqueness of a viscosity solution by using Perron's method and the comparison principle. Our primary result is to prove that the solution exhibits local $C^{1,\gamma}$ regularity for any $\gamma \in (0,1)$, provided that it is a strong solution in $W^{2,n}_{\text{loc}}(\Omega)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24410v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meng Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Front propagation on a general metric graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24418v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a bistable reaction-diffusion equation on a metric graph that is a generalization of the so-called star graphs. More precisely, our graph $\Omega$ consists of a bounded finite metric graph $D$ of arbitrary configuration and a finite number of branches $\Omega_1,\ldots,\Omega_N\,(N\geq 2)$ of infinite length emanating from some of the vertices of $D$. Each $\Omega_i\,(i=1,\ldots,N)$ is called an ``outer path''. Our goal is to investigate the behavior of the front coming from infinity along a given outer path $\Omega_i$ and to discuss whether or not the front propagates into other outer paths $\Omega_j\,(j\ne i)$. Unlike the case of star graphs, where $D$ is a single vertex, the dynamics of solutions can be far more complex and may depend sensitively on the configuration of the center graph $D$. We first focus on general principles that hold regardless of the structure of the center graph $D$. Among other things, we introduce the notion ``limit profile'', which allows us to define ``propagation'' and ``blocking'' without ambiguity, then we prove transient properties, that is, propagation $\Omega_i\to \Omega_j$ and $\Omega_j\to \Omega_k$ imply propagation $\Omega_i\to \Omega_k$. Next we consider perturbations of the graph $D$ while fixing the outer paths $\Omega_1,\ldots,\Omega_N$ and prove that if, for a given choice of $i,j$, propagation $\Omega_i\to \Omega_j$ occurs for a graph $D$, then the same holds for any graph $D'$ that is sufficiently close to $D$ (robustness under perturbation). We also consider several specific classes of graphs, such as those with a ``reservoir'' type subgraph, and study their intriguing properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24418v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroshi Matano, Shuichi Jimbo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An inverse problem for the Standard Model of particle physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24454v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We pose and solve an inverse problem for the classical field equations that arise in the Standard Model of particle physics. Our main result describes natural conditions on the representations, so that it is possible to recover all the fields from measurements in a small set within a causal domain in Minkowski space. These conditions are satisfied for the representations arising in the Standard Model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24454v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xi Chen, Matti Lassas, Lauri Oksanen, Gabriel P. Paternain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravity driven traveling bore wave solutions to the free boundary incompressible Navier-Stokes equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24562v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give the first mathematical construction of two-dimensional traveling bore wave solutions to the free boundary incompressible Navier-Stokes equations for a single finite depth layer of constant density fluid. Our construction is based on a rigorous justification of the formal shallow water limit, which postulates that in a certain scaling regime the full free boundary traveling Navier-Stokes system of PDEs reduces to a governing system of ODEs. We find heteroclinic orbits solving these ODEs and, through a delicate fixed point argument employing the Stokes problem in thin domains and a nonautonomous orbital perturbation theory, use these ODE solutions as the germs from which we build bore PDE solutions for sufficiently shallow layers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24562v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noah Stevenson, Ian Tice</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the rate of convergence for Landau type Schr\"odinger Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24568v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the pointwise convergence of Landau type Schr\"odinger operators within the fractional Sobolev space $W^{s,p}(\mathbb R)$. Our results extend those established by Bailey (Rev. Mat. Iberoam., 29 (2): 531-546, 2013) and Yuan, Zhao and Zheng (Nonlinear Anal., 208: Paper No. 112312, 28, 2021). Furthermore, we also analyze the convergence rate of Landau type Schr\"odinger operators along curves and derive a sharp result for the case of convergence along vertical lines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24568v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yucheng Pan, Wenchang Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well-posedness for a two-phase Stefan problem with radiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24602v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we consider a free boundary problem for the melting of ice where we assume that the heat is transported by conduction in both the liquid and the solid part of the material and also by radiation in the solid. Specifically, we study a one-dimensional two-phase Stefan-like problem which contains a non-local integral operator in the equation describing the temperature distribution of the solid. We will prove the local well-posedness of this free boundary problem combining the Banach fixed-point theorem and classical parabolic theory. Moreover, constructing suitable stationary sub- and supersolutions we will develop a global well-posedness theory for a large class of initial data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24602v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena Dematt\`e, Juan J. L. Vel\'azquez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent structures in long range FPUT lattices, Part I: Solitary Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24828</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24828v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider long range variants of Fermi-Pasta-Ulam-Tsingou lattice and in particular allow for particles to interact over arbitrarily long distances. We develop sufficient conditions which allow for the construction of solitary wave solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24828v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Douglas Wright, Udoh Akpan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak solutions of Navier-Stokes Equation with purely discontinuous L\'evy Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24043v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we prove the existence of weak martingale solutions to the stochastic Navier-Stokes Equations driven by pure jump L\'evy processes. Our proof consists of two parts. In the first one, mostly classical, we recall a priori estimates, from the paper by the third named author, for solutions to suitable constructed Galerkin approximations and we use the Jakubowski-Skorokhod Theorem to find a sequence of processes on a new probability space convergent point-wise to a limit process. In the second one, we show that the limit process is a weak martingale solution to the SNSEs by using an approach of Kallianpur and Xiong. The core of this method consists of a proof that a certain natural process on the new probability space is a purely discontinuous martingale and then to use a suitable representation theorem. In this way we propose a method of proving solutions to stochastic PDEs which is different from the method used recently by the first and fourth named author in their joint paper with E.\ Hausenblas, see \cite{Brz+Haus+Raza_2018_reaction_diffusion}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24043v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zdzis{\l}aw Brze\'zniak, Tomasz Kosmala, El\.zbieta Motyl, Paul Razafimandimby</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary bilinear control of semilinear parabolic PDEs: quadratic convergence of the SQP method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24237v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze a bilinear control problem governed by a semilinear parabolic equation. The control variable is the Robin coefficient on the boundary. First-order necessary and second-order sufficient optimality conditions are derived. A sequential quadratic programming algorithm is then proposed to compute local solutions. Starting the iterations from an initial point in an $L^2$-neighborhood of the local solution we prove stability and quadratic convergence of the algorithm in $L^p$ ($p &lt; \infty$) and $L^\infty$ assuming that the local solution satisfies a no-gap second-order sufficient optimality condition and a strict complementarity condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24237v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduardo Casas, Mariano Mateos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The quantitative semi-classical limit of a large Fermi system at zero temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24706v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article we consider a large system of fermions in a combined mean-field and semiclassical limit, in three dimensions. We investigate the convergence of the Wigner function of the ground state, towards the classical Thomas-Fermi theory. The main novelty of the present article is quantifying the convergence rate with respect to the semi-classical parameter. One of the main ingredients is a recent result on the validity of semi-classical commutator estimates satisfied by the Hartree theory. Singular potentials, up to the Coulomb interaction, are included.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24706v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Esteban C\'ardenas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the deep-water and shallow-water limits of the intermediate long wave equation from a statistical viewpoint</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.03243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.03243v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: (Due to the limit on the number of characters for an abstract set by arXiv, the full abstract can not be displayed here. See the abstract in the paper.) We study convergence problems for the intermediate long wave equation (ILW), with the depth parameter $\delta &gt; 0$, in the deep-water limit ($\delta \to \infty$) and the shallow-water limit ($\delta \to 0$) from a statistical point of view. In particular, we establish convergence of invariant Gibbs dynamics for ILW in both the deep-water and shallow-water limits. For this purpose, we first construct the Gibbs measures for ILW, $0 &lt; \delta &lt; \infty$. As they are supported on distributions, a renormalization is required. With the Wick renormalization, we carry out the construction of the Gibbs measures for ILW. We then prove that the Gibbs measures for ILW converge in total variation to that for the Benjamin-Ono equation (BO) in the deep-water limit. In the shallow-water regime, after applying a scaling transformation, we prove that, as $\delta \to 0$, the Gibbs measures for the scaled ILW converge weakly to that for the Korteweg-de Vries equation (KdV). We point out that this second result is of particular interest since the Gibbs measures for the scaled ILW and KdV are mutually singular (whereas the Gibbs measures for ILW and BO are equivalent).
  We also discuss convergence of the associated dynamical problem.
  Lastly, we point out that our results also apply to the generalized ILW equation in the defocusing case, converging to the generalized BO in the deep-water limit and to the generalized KdV in the shallow-water limit. In the non-defocusing case, however, our results can not be extended to a nonlinearity with a higher power due to the non-normalizability of the corresponding Gibbs measures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.03243v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1112/tlm3.70005</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Trans. London Math. Soc. 12 (2025), no. 1, Paper No. e70005</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Guopeng Li, Tadahiro Oh, Guangqu Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Infinite Double Bubble Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.08063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.08063v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The classical double bubble theorem characterizes the minimizing partitions of $\mathbb{R}^n$ into three chambers, two of which have prescribed finite volume. In this paper we prove a variant of the double bubble theorem in which two of the chambers have infinite volume. Such a configuration is an example of a (1,2)-cluster, or a partition of $\mathbb{R}^n$ into three chambers, two of which have infinite volume and only one of which has finite volume. A $(1,2)$-cluster is locally minimizing with respect to a family of weights $\{c_{jk}\}$ if for any $B_r(0)$, it minimizes the interfacial energy $\sum_{j&lt;k} c_{jk} \mathscr{H}^n(\partial \mathscr{X}(j) \cap \partial\mathscr{X}(k) \cap B_r(0))$ among all variations with compact support in $B_r(0)$ which preserve the volume of $\mathscr{X}(1)$. For $(1,2)$ clusters, the analogue of the weighted double bubble is the weighted lens cluster, and we show that it is locally minimizing. Furthermore, under a symmetry assumption on $\{c_{jk}\}$ that includes the case of equal weights, the weighted lens cluster is the unique local minimizer in $\mathbb{R}^n$ for $n\leq 7$, with the same uniqueness holding in $\mathbb{R}^n$ for $n\geq 8$ under a natural growth assumption. We also obtain a closure theorem for locally minimizing $(N,2)$-clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.08063v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lia Bronsard, Michael Novack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the second-order regularity of solutions to widely singular or degenerate elliptic equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13116v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider local weak solutions to PDEs of the type \[ -\,\mathrm{div}\left((\vert Du\vert-\lambda)_{+}^{p-1}\frac{Du}{\vert Du\vert}\right)=f\,\,\,\,\,\,\,\text{in}\,\,\Omega, \] where $1&lt;p&lt;\infty$, $\Omega$ is an open subset of $\mathbb{R}^{n}$ for $n\geq2$, $\lambda$ is a positive constant and $(\,\cdot\,)_{+}$ stands for the positive part. Equations of this form are widely degenerate for $p\ge 2$ and widely singular for $1&lt;p&lt;2$. We establish higher differentiability results for a suitable nonlinear function of the gradient $Du$ of the local weak solutions, assuming that $f$ belongs to the local Besov space $B^{(p-2)/p}_{p',1,loc}(\Omega)$ when $p&gt;2$, and that $f\in L_{loc}^{{\frac{np}{n(p-1)+2-p}}}(\Omega)$ if $1&lt;p\leq2$. The conditions on the datum $f$ are essentially sharp. As a consequence, we obtain the local higher integrability of $Du$ under the same minimal assumptions on $f$. For $\lambda=0$, our results give back those contained in [12,28].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13116v5</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pasquale Ambrosio, Antonio Giuseppe Grimaldi, Antonia Passarelli di Napoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global existence of weak solutions to incompressible anisotropic Cahn-Hilliard-Navier-Stokes system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05757v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the anisotropic, incompressible Cahn-Hilliard-Navier-Stokes system with variable density in a bounded smooth domain $\Omega \subset \mathbb{R}^d$. This work extends previous studies on the isotropic case by incorporating anisotropic surface energy, represented by $\mathfrak{F}= \int_{\Omega} \frac{\epsilon}{2}\, \Gamma^2(\nabla \phi) $. The thermodynamic consistency of this system, as well as its modeling background and physical motivation, has been established in [3,5,7]. Using a Galerkin approximation scheme, we prove the existence of global weak solutions in both two and three dimensions $(d=2,3)$. A crucial element in extending the existence of approximate solutions from local to global lies in the application of Bihari's inequality and a fixed-point argument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05757v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Azeddine Zaidni, Saad Benjelloun, Radouan Boukharfane</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compressible Navier-Stokes system with slip boundary from Boltzmann equations with reflection boundary: derivations and justifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08715v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This is the first in a series of papers connecting the boundary conditions for the compressible Navier-Stokes system from the Boltzmann equations with the Maxwell reflection boundary. The slip boundary conditions are formally derived from the Boltzmann equation with both specular and almost specular reflection boundary conditions. That is, the accommodation coefficient $\alpha_\eps=O(\eps^\beta)$ with $\beta&gt;0$ or $\alpha_\eps =0$. Here, the small number $\eps&gt;0$ denotes the Knudsen number. The systematic formal analysis is based on the Chapman-Enskog expansion and the analysis of the Knudsen layer. In particular, for the first time, we employ the appropriate ansatz for the general $\beta&gt;0$. This completes the program started in \cite{aoki2017slip}. In the second part, the compressible Navier-Stokes-Fourier approximation for the Boltzmann equation with specular reflection in general bounded domains is rigorously justified. The uniform regularity for the compressible Navier-Stokes system with the derived boundary conditions is investigated. For the remainder equation, the $L^2\mbox{-}L^6\mbox{-}L^\infty$ framework is employed to obtain uniform estimates in $\eps$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08715v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ning Jiang, Yulong Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local well-posedness for a system of modified KdV equations in modulation spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12423v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we consider the initial value problem (IVP) for a system of modified Korteweg-de Vries (mKdV) equations
  \begin{equation*}
  \begin{cases} \partial_t v + \partial_x^3 v+ \partial_x (v w^2) = 0, \hspace{0.98 cm} v(x,0)=\psi(x),\\ \partial_t w + \alpha \partial_x^3 w+\partial_x (v^2 w) = 0,\hspace{0.5 cm} w(x,0)=\phi(x). \end{cases} \end{equation*} The main interest is in addressing the well-posedness issues of the IVP when the initial data are considered in the modulation space $M_s^{2,p}(\mathbb{R})$, $p\geq 2$. In the case when $0&lt;\alpha\ne 1$, we derive new trilinear estimates in these spaces and prove that the IVP is locally well-posed for data in $M_s^{2,p}(\mathbb{R})$ whenever $s&gt; \frac14-\frac{1}{p}$ and $p\geq 2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12423v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xavier Carvajal, Fidel Cuba, Mahendra Panthee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Gauss formulas for Laplacians on submanifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.11928</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.11928v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: There are several types of Laplacians of a vector field on a Riemannian manifold. These include the Bochner and the Hodge Laplacian. The Gauss formula for the Levi-Civita connection relates the extrinsic connection to the intrinsic connection. We extend the Gauss formula for the connection to formulas for the different types of Laplacians of a vector field on a submanifold of any codimension $k\geq 1$. In the process, we derive a Gauss formula for the Ricci operator, formulas for the divergence of the second fundamental form, and a formula for the Laplacian of a $1$-form on a surface of revolution in terms of the Lie derivatives. The formulas have applications to the study of the formulation of the incompressible Navier-Stokes equations on a Riemannian manifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.11928v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chi Hin Chan, Magdalena Czubak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical threshold for weakly interacting log-correlated focusing Gibbs measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09790v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study log-correlated Gibbs measures on the $d$-dimensional torus with weakly interacting focusing quartic potentials whose coupling constants tend to $0$ as we remove regularization. In particular, we exhibit a phase transition for this model by identifying a critical threshold, separating the weakly and strongly coupling regimes; in the weakly coupling regime, we show that the frequency-truncated measures converge to the base Gaussian measure (possibly with a renormalized $L^2$-cutoff), whereas, in the strongly coupling regime, we prove non-convergence of the frequency-truncated measures, even up to a subsequence. Our result answers an open question posed by Brydges and Slade (1996).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09790v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Damiano Greco, Tadahiro Oh, Liying Tao, Leonardo Tolomeo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
