<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 04:00:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Fredholm properties of singular elliptic operators arising in the study of point defects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01534</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01534v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Motivated by the dynamics of defects in planar pattern-forming systems, we study Fredholm properties of elliptic operators with singular coefficients in weighted Sobolev spaces. In particular, we consider a family of doubly weighted spaces that encode algebraic decay/growth of functions at infinity, and near the origin. Our results give conditions on the weights under which the operators are either injective, surjective, or isomorphisms. We also give a precise description of the kernel and range of these operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01534v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriela Jaramillo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundedness of pseudo-differential operators on the torus revisited. II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01573v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we continue our program of revisiting the new aspects about the boundedness properties of pseudo-differential operators on the torus. Here we prove $H^p$-$L^p$ and $H^p$-estimates for H\"ormander classes of pseudo-differential operators on the torus $\mathbb{T}^n$ for $p\leq 1$. The results are presented in the context of the global symbolic analysis developed by Ruzhansky and Turunen on $\mathbb{T}^n \times \mathbb{Z}^n$ by using the discrete Fourier analysis, which extends the $(\rho, \delta)$-H\"ormander classes on $\mathbb{T}^n$ defined by local coordinate systems. These results extend those proved by \'Alvarez and Hounie for the Euclidean case, considering even the case $\rho\leq\delta$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01573v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duv\'an Cardona, Manuel Alejandro Mart\'inez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exceptional point enhanced small particle detection in systems of subwavelength resonators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01646v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper considers the effects of small highly contrasted particles on the subwavelength resonances of a system of high-contrast resonators, with an application to sensing. The key technique is a multiple scattering expansion of the capacitance matrix associated with the perturbed system. At leading order, the perturbation of the scattering resonances is characterized by the associated term of the truncated multiple scattering expansion. When an exceptional point is present in the resonance structure, the perturbation critically affects the subwavelength resonances, which improves the sensitivity of a sensing task in the presence of noise. Numerical experiments demonstrate the use of the proposed reconstruction techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01646v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinghao Cao, J\"org Nick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Steady three-dimensional rotational flows: existence via Kato's approach to locally coercive problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01748v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stationary flows of an inviscid and incompressible fluid of constant density in the region $D=(0, L)\times \mathbb R^2$, periodic in the second and third variables, are considered. The flux and the Bernoulli function are prescribed at each point of the boundary $\partial D$. The previous existence proof relying on the Nash-Moser iteration scheme is replaced by an adaptation of Kato's approach to locally coercive problems, allowing a more precise statement: the regularity required in Sobolev spaces is the one needed to ensure a basic local coercivity property, and there is a loss of control of only two derivatives in the obtained solutions. The underlying variational structure gives an additional property: the obtained solutions are local minimizers of an integral functional. The strategy of proof is first developed for a simpler nonlinear partial differential equation in two variables which satisfies a weaker form of ellipticity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01748v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boris Buffoni, Eric S\'er\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shape Gradient Based Non-Parametric Mumford-Shah Segmentation Without Level Sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01791v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A non parametric, level set free method is proposed for detecting image boundaries using the shape gradient of the Mumford Shah energy for segmentation. Minimizing the variance in pixel intensities inside and outside a boundary set of points is the primary pursuit. The boundary set as a polygon of points rather than a parametric form or a level set, evolves under the guidance of a shape gradient of the Mumford Shah piece wise constant segments model. Iteratively updating through the gradient descent method. The proposed method has been tested on various images, demonstrating its effectiveness in capturing intricate and narrow boundaries texture images.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01791v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shafeequdheen P, Jyotiranjan Nayak, Vijayakrishna Rowthu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global hypoellipticity for involutive systems on non-compact manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01889v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the global hypoellipticity of the operator $\mathbb{L} = \mathrm{d}_t + \sum_{k=1}^m \omega_k \wedge \partial_{x_k}$, defined on differential forms over product manifolds of the form $M \times \mathbb{T}^m$, where $M$ is a non-compact manifold homeomorphic to the interior of a compact manifold with boundary, equipped with a scattering metric, and $\omega_1,\dots,\omega_m$ are smooth closed 1-forms on $M$. Extending previous results obtained in the compact setting, we characterize global hypoellipticity of $\mathbb{L}$ in terms of arithmetic properties of the forms $\omega_k$. The analysis relies on microlocal techniques adapted to the scattering setting and a version of the Hodge Theorem for scattering manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01889v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sandro Coriasco, Alexandre Kirilov, Wagner Augusto Almeida de Moraes, Pedro Meyer Tokoro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New characterization of Hardy-Fofana spaces and temperature equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01908v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to give a characterization of Hardy-Fofana spaces via Riesz trasforms. This characterization allow us to describ the distributions belonging to these spaces as a bounded solutions of Cauchy-Riemann's general temperature equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01908v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martial Agbly Dakoury, Justin Feuto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstruction of a vector field and a symmetric $2$-tensor field from the moment ray transforms in $\mathbb{R}^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02028v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a technique for recovering a vector field and a symmetric $2$-tensor field, both real-valued and compactly supported in some strictly convex bounded domain with smooth boundary in the Euclidean plane, from the sum of their attenuated moment ray transforms. In addition, we provide a stability estimate for recovering both the vector field and the symmetric $2$-tensor field from the aforementioned ray transform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02028v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rahul Bhardwaj, Karishman B. Solanki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bound states of nonlinear Dirac equation on noncompact quantum graphs with localized nonlinearities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02036v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the nonlinear Dirac equation (NLDE) on noncompact quantum graphs featuring localized nonlinearities, specifically under Kirchhoff-type vertex conditions. Our primary focus is on the existence and multiplicity of bound states, which emerge as critical points of the NLDE Lagrangian functional. The associated action functional is strongly indefinite, and notably, the Palais-Smale condition fails to hold. To address these challenges, we employ recently developed critical point theorems to derive our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02036v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhipeng Yang, Ling Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Standing waves with prescribed mass for biharmonic NLS with positive dispersion and Sobolev critical exponent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02042v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate standing waves with prescribed mass for a class of biharmonic Schrodinger equations with positive Laplacian dispersion in the Sobolev critical regime. By establishing novel energy inequalities and developing a direct minimization approach, we prove the existence of two normalized solutions for the corresponding stationary problem. The first one is a ground state with negative level, and the second one is a higher-energy solution with positive level. It is worth noting that we do not work in the space of radial functions, and do not use Palais-Smale sequences so as to avoid applying the relatively complex mini-max approach based on a strong topological argument. Finally, we explore the relationship between the ground states and the least action solutions, some asymptotic properties and dynamical behavior of solutions, such as the orbital stability and the global existence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02042v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juntao Sun, Shuai Yao, He Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiple solutions for elliptic equations driven by higher order fractional Laplacian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02065v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider an elliptic partial differential equation driven by higher order fractional Laplacian $(-\Delta)^{s}$, $s \in (1,2)$ with homogeneous Dirichlet boundary condition
  \begin{equation*}
  \left\{%
  \begin{array}{ll}
  (-\Delta)^{s} u=f(x,u) &amp; \text{ in }\Omega,
  u=0 &amp; \text{ in } \mathbb{R}^n \setminus \Omega.
  \end{array}%
  \right.
  \end{equation*}
  The above equation has a variational nature, and we investigate the existence and multiplicity results for its weak solutions under various conditions on the nonlinear term $f$: superlinear growth, concave-convex and symmetric conditions and their combinations.
  The existence of two different non-trivial weak solutions is established by Mountain Pass Theorem and Ekeland's variational principle, respectively.
  Furthermore, due to Fountain Theorem and its dual form, both infinitely many weak solutions with positive energy and infinitely many weak solutions with negative energy are obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02065v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fuwei Cheng, Xifeng Su, Jiwen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oscillatory approximations and maximum entropy principle for the Euler system of gas dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02070v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the measure-valued solutions of the Euler system of gas dynamics generated by oscillatory sequences of consistent approximations violate the principle of maximal entropy production formulated by Dafermos. Numerical results illustrate that solutions obtained by standard numerical methods may be oscillatory and thus do not comply with the Dafermos criterion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02070v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eduard Feireisl, M\'aria Luk\'a\v{c}ov\'a-Medvid'ov\'a, Changsheng Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ground states to a quasilinear Schr\"{o}dinger equation with Berestycki-Lions type nonlinearities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02141v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the following quasilinear {S}chr\"{o}dinger equation: $$\left\{ \begin{array}{l} - {\Delta u} - \frac{\kappa }{2}\Delta \left( {u}^{2}\right) u = h\left( u\right) \text{ in }{\mathbb{R}}^{N}, \\ u \in {H}^{1}\left( {\mathbb{R}}^{N}\right), \end{array}\right. $$ where $N \geq 3,\kappa &gt; 0$ is a parameter, and $h$ satisfies Berestycki-Lions condition. By using a critical point theory on a topological manifold, we obtain the existence of a ground state for $N \geq 3$, a nonradial ground state for $N \geq 4$, and infinitely many nonradial solutions for $N = 4$ or $N \geq 6$. Our results generalize several classical works into quasilinear equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02141v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xianyong Yang, Yue Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary value problem of magnetically insulated diode: existence of solutions and complex bifurcation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02155v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The paper focuses on the stationary self-consistent problem of magnetic insulation for a vacuum diode with space-charge limitation, described by a singularly perturbed Vlasov-Maxwell system of dimension 1.5. The case of insulated diode when the electrons are deflected back towards the cathode at the point $x^{*}$ is considered. First, the initial VM system is reduced to the nonlinear singular limit system of ODEs for the potentials of electric and magnetic fields. The second step deals with the limit system's reduction to the new nonlinear singular ODE equation for effective potential $\Theta(x)$. The existence of non-negative solutions is proved for the last equation on the interval $[0, x^{*})$ where $\Theta(x)&gt;0$. The most interesting and unexplored case is when $\Theta(x)&lt;0$ on the interval $(x^{*}, 1]$ and corresponds to the case of an insulated diode. For the first time, a numerical analysis of complex bifurcation of solutions in insulated diode is considered for $\Theta(x)&lt;0$ depending on parameters and boundary conditions. Bifurcation diagrams of the dependence of solution $\Theta(x)$ on a free point (free boundary) $x^{*}$ were constructed. Insulated diode spacing is found.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02155v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis Sidorov, Alexander Sinitsyn, David Leguizamon, Liguo Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Landau damping in mixed hyperbolic-kinetic systems and thick sprays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02295v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article is devoted to the study of a model of thick sprays which combines the Vlasov equation for the particles and the barotropic compressible Euler equations to describe the fluid, coupled through the gradient of the pressure of the fluid. We prove that sound waves interact with particles of nearby velocities, which results in a damping or an amplification of these sound waves, depending on the sign of the derivative of the distribution function at the sound speed. This mechanism is very similar to the classical Landau damping which occurs in the Vlasov-Poisson system. If the sound waves are amplified then the thick spray model is linearly ill-posed in Sobolev spaces, even locally in time.
  We also show that such Landau damping type phenomena naturally arise when we couple an hyperbolic system of conservation laws with the Vlasov equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02295v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Bian, B. Despr\'es, V. Fournet, E. Grenier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inverse problem to determine simultaneously several scalar parameters and a time-dependent source term in a superdiffusion equation involving a multiterm fractional Laplacian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02348v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inverse problem to recover simultaneously a scalar coefficient, order of a time-fractional derivative, parameters of multiterm fractional Laplacian and a time-dependent source term occurring in a superdiffusion equation from measurements over the time is considered. Uniqueness of a solution is proved. The proof uses asymptotics of poles of the Laplace transform of a measured function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02348v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hany Gerges, Jaan Janno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SOPTX: A High-Performance Multi-Backend Framework for Topology Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02438v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, topology optimization (TO) has gained widespread attention as a powerful structural design method. However, its application remains challenging due to the deep expertise and extensive development effort required. Traditional TO methods, tightly coupled with computational mechanics like finite element method (FEM), result in intrusive algorithms demanding a comprehensive system understanding. This paper presents SOPTX, a TO package based on FEALPy, which implements a modular architecture that decouples analysis from optimization, supports multiple computational backends (NumPy, PyTorch, JAX), and achieves a non-intrusive design paradigm. Core innovations include: (1) cross-platform design that supports multiple computational backends, enabling efficient algorithm execution on central processing units (CPUs) and flexible acceleration using graphics processing units (GPUs), while leveraging automatic differentiation (AD) technology for efficient sensitivity computation of objective and constraint functions; (2) fast matrix assembly techniques that overcome the performance bottlenecks of traditional numerical integration methods, significantly accelerating finite element computations and enhancing overall efficiency; (3) a modular framework supporting TO problems for arbitrary dimensions and meshes, allowing flexible configuration and extensibility of optimization workflows through a rich library of composable components. Using the density-based method for the classic compliance minimization problem with volume constraints as an example, numerical experiments demonstrate SOPTX's high efficiency in computational speed and memory usage, while showcasing its strong potential for research and engineering applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02438v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang He, Huayi Wei, Tian Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimates of variational eigenvalues on metric measure spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02617v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the article, we study variational eigenvalues on doubling metric measure spaces. We prove existence of minimizers of variational Neumann $(p,q)$-eigenvalues on metric measure spaces and on this base we obtain estimates of Neumann eigenvalues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02617v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prashanta Garain, Alexander Ukhlov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimates for the first and second Steklov-Dirichlet eigenvalues</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02757v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we deal with the Steklov-Dirichlet eigenvalue problem for the Laplacian in annular domains. More precisely, we consider $\Omega_r = \Omega_0 \setminus \overline{B}_r$, where $\Omega_0 \subset \mathbb{R}^n$, $n \geq 2$, is an open, bounded set with a Lipschitz boundary, and $B_r$ is the ball centered at the origin with radius $r &gt; 0$, such that $\overline{B}_r \subset \Omega_0$. In the first part of the paper, we focus on the first Steklov-Dirichlet eigenvalue $\sigma_1(\Omega_r)$ and prove that the sequence of corresponding normalized eigenfunctions converges to a particular constant as $r \to 0^+$. This will allow us to prove an isoperimetric inequality for $ \sigma_1(\Omega_r)$ when $r$ is small enough, under a measure constraint. The second part is focused on the second Steklov-Dirichlet eigenvalue $\sigma_2(\Omega_r)$. We prove that it converges to the first non-trivial Steklov eigenvalue $\overline{\sigma}_1(\Omega_0)$ of the non-perforated domain $\Omega_0$. This result, together with the Brock and Weinstock inequalities, respectively, allows us to prove two isoperimetric inequalities for small holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02757v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rossano Sannipoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp stability of the Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle: Second-Order and Curl-Free Field Cases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02758v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using techniques from harmonic analysis, we derive several sharp stability estimates for the second order Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle. We also present the explicit lower and upper bounds for the sharp stability constants and compute their exact limits when the dimension $N\rightarrow\infty$. Our proofs rely on spherical harmonics decomposition and Fourier analysis, differing significantly from existing approaches in the literature. Our results substantially improve the stability constants of the second order Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle recently obtained in [26]. As direct consequences of our main results, we also establish the sharp stability, with exact asymptotic behavior of the stability constants, of the Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle with curl-free vector fields and a sharp version of the second order Poincar\'{e} type inequality with Gaussian measure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02758v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anh Xuan Do, Nguyen Lam, Guozhen Lu, Lingxiao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A non-asymptotic approach to stochastic differential games with many players under semi-monotonicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01526v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider stochastic differential games with a large number of players, with the aim of quantifying the gap between closed-loop, open-loop and distributed equilibria. We show that, under two different semi-monotonicity conditions, the equilibrium trajectories are close when the interactions between the players are weak. Our approach is non-asymptotic in nature, in the sense that it does not make use of any a priori identification of a limiting model, like in mean field game (MFG) theory. The main technical step is to derive bounds on solutions to systems of PDE/FBSDE characterizing the equilibria that are independent of the number of players. When specialized to the mean field setting, our estimates yield quantitative convergence results for both open-loop and closed-loop equilibria without any use of the master equation. In fact, our main bounds hold for games in which interactions are much sparser than those of MFGs, and so we can also obtain some "universality" results for MFGs, in which we show that games governed by dense enough networks converge to the usual MFG limit. Finally, we use our estimates to study a joint vanishing viscosity and large population limit in the setting of displacement monotone games without idiosyncratic noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01526v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Cirant, Joe Jackson, Davide Francesco Redaelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Martingale Solutions of Stochastic Constrained Modified Swift-Hohenberg Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01720v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we aim to prove the existence of global Martingale solution to Stochastic Constrained Modified Swift-Hohenberg Equation driven by stratonovich multiplicative noise. This equation belongs to class of amplitude equations which describe the appearance of pattern formation in nature. This structure allows us to work in a Hilbert space framework and to apply a stochastic Galerkin method. The existence proof is based on energy-type estimates, the tightness criterion of Brzezniak and collaborators, and Jakubowski's generalization of the Skorokhod theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01720v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saeed Ahmed, Javed Hussain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On $L$-special domains with algebraic boundaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01765v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The concept of $L$-special domain appeared in the early 2000s. This analytical characteristic of domains in the complex plane is related to the problem on uniform approximation of functions on Carath\'eodory compacts in $\mathbb{R}^2$ by polynomial solutions of homogeneous second-order elliptic partial differential equations $Lu=0$ with constant complex coefficients. In this paper, new properties and examples of $L$-special domains with algebraic boundaries are obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01765v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Borovikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the quantum dynamics of long-ranged Bose-Hubbard Hamiltonians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01786v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the quantum dynamics generated by Bose-Hubbard Hamiltonians with long-ranged (power law) terms. We prove two ballistic propagation bounds for suitable initial states: (i) A bound on all moments of the local particle number for all power law exponents $\alpha&gt;d+1$ in $d$ dimensions, the sharp condition. (ii) The first thermodynamically stable Lieb-Robinson bound (LRB) for these Hamiltonians. To handle the long-ranged and unbounded terms, we further develop the multiscale ASTLO (adiabatic space time localization observables) method introduced in our recent work [arXiv:2310.14896].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01786v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marius Lemm, Carla Rubiliani, Jingxuan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An atomic decomposition for functions of bounded variation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02053</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02053v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we give a decomposition of the gradient measure $Du$ of an arbitrary function of bounded variation $u$ into a sum of atoms $\mu=D\chi_{F}$, where $F$ is a set of finite perimeter. The atoms further satisfy the support, cancellation, normalization, and size conditions: For each $\mu$, there exists a cube $Q$ such that $\operatorname*{supp}\mu\subset Q$, $\mu(Q)=0$, $|\mu|(Q)\leq 1$, and, denoting by $p_t$ the heat kernel in $\mathbb{R}^d$, \[ \sup_{x \in \mathbb{R}^d, t&gt;0} |t^{1/2} p_t \ast \mu (x)| \leq \frac{1}{l(Q)^{d-1}}. \] Our proof relies on a sampling of the coarea formula and a new boxing identity. We present several consequences of this result, including Sobolev inequalities, dimension estimates, and trace inequalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02053v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Spector, Cody B. Stockdale, Dmitriy Stolyarov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffeomorphic Reconstruction Of A 2D Simple Non Parametric Manifold From Level Set Data Via Shape Gradients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02061v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A variational approach to the reconstruction of a shape (2D simple manifolds) as triangulated surface from given level set using shape gradients is presented. It involves an energy functional that depends on the local shape characteristics of the surface. Minimization of the energy through an iterative procedure using the gradient descent method yields a triangulated surface mesh which matches the boundary of the object of interest and this model ensures the smoothness of the boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02061v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shafeequdheen P, Jyotiranjan Nayak, Vijayakrishna Rowthu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix-Weighted Besov-Triebel-Lizorkin Spaces of Optimal Scale: Real-Variable Characterizations, Invariance on Integrable Index, and Sobolev-Type Embedding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02136v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article, using growth functions we introduce generalized matrix-weighted Besov-Triebel-Lizorkin-type spaces with matrix $\mathcal{A}_{\infty}$ weights. We first characterize these spaces, respectively, in terms of the $\varphi$-transform, the Peetre-type maximal function, and the Littlewood-Paley functions. Furthermore, after establishing the boundedness of almost diagonal operators on the corresponding sequence spaces, we obtain the molecular and the wavelet characterizations of these spaces. As applications, we find the sufficient and necessary conditions for the invariance of those Triebel-Lizorkin-type spaces on the integrable index and also for the Sobolev-type embedding of all these spaces. The main novelty exists in that these results are of wide generality, the growth condition of growth functions is not only sufficient but also necessary for the boundedness of almost diagonal operators and hence this new framework of Besov-Triebel-Lizorkin-type is optimal, some results either are new or improve the known ones even for known matrix-weighted Besov-Triebel-Lizorkin spaces, and, furthermore, even in the scalar-valued setting, all the results are also new.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02136v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Bu, Dachun Yang, Wen Yuan, Mingdong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Four-dimensional shrinkers with nonnegative Ricci curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02315v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate classifications of $4$-dimensional simply connected complete noncompact nonflat shrinkers satisfying $Ric+\mathrm{Hess}\,f=\tfrac 12g$ with nonnegative Ricci curvature. One one hand, we show that if the sectional curvature $K\le 1/4$ or the sum of smallest two eigenvalues of Ricci curvature has a suitable lower bound, then the shrinker is isometric to $\mathbb{R}\times\mathbb{S}^3$. We also show that if the scalar curvature $R\le 3$ and the shrinker is asymptotic to $\mathbb{R}\times\mathbb{S}^3$, then the Euler characteristic $\chi(M)\geq 0$ and equality holds if and only if the shrinker is isometric to $\mathbb{R}\times\mathbb{S}^3$. On the other hand, we prove that if $K\le 1/2$ (or the bi-Ricci curvature is nonnegative) and $R\le\tfrac{3}{2}-\delta$ for some $\delta\in (0,\tfrac{1}{2}]$, then the shrinker is isometric to $\mathbb{R}^2\times\mathbb{S}^2$. The proof of these classifications mainly depends on the asymptotic analysis by the evolution of eigenvalues of Ricci curvature, the Gauss-Bonnet-Chern formula with boundary and the integration by parts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02315v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guoqiang Wu, Jia-yong Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of Schr\"odinger operators on domains with scaled resonant potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02480v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider Schr\"odinger operators on a bounded, smooth domain of dimension $d \ge 2$ with Dirichlet boundary conditions and a properly scaled potential, which depends only on the distance to the boundary of the domain. Our aim is to analyse the convergence of these operators as the scaling parameter tends to zero. If the scaled potential is resonant, the limit in strong resolvent sense is a Robin Laplacian with boundary coefficient expressed in terms of the mean curvature of the boundary. A counterexample shows that norm resolvent convergence cannot hold in general in this setting. If the scaled potential is non-negative (hence non-resonant), the limit in strong resolvent sense is the Dirichlet Laplacian. We conjecture that we can drop the non-negativity assumption in the non-resonant case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02480v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Lotoreichik, Olaf Post</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of multi-solitons for the Benjamin-Ono equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.14205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.14205v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is concerned with the dynamical stability of the $m$-solitons of the Benjamin-Ono (BO) equation. This extends the work of Neves and Lopes [41], which was restricted to $m=2$ the double solitons case. By constructing a suitable Lyapunov functional, it is found that the multi-solitons are non-isolated constrained minimizers satisfying a suitable variational nonlocal elliptic equation. The stability issue is reduced to the spectral analysis of higher order nonlocal operators consist of the Hilbert transform. Such operators are isoinertial and the negative eigenvalues of which are fully classified. Our approach in the spectral analysis consists of an invariance for the multi-solitons and new operator identities motivated by the bi-Hamiltonian structure of the BO equation. Since the BO equation is more likely a two dimensional integrable system, its recursion operator is not explicit which makes our analysis more involved. The key ingredient in the spectral analysis is to employ the completeness in $L^2$ of the squared eigenfunctions of the eigenvalue problem for the BO equation. It is demonstrated here that orbital stability of soliton in $H^{\frac{1}{2}}$ implies that all $m$-solitons are dynamically stable in $H^{\frac{m}{2}}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.14205v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Lan, Zhong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary controllability for a fourth order degenerate parabolic equation with a singular potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08745v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove the null controllability of a one-dimensional fourth-order degenerate parabolic equation with a singular potential. Here, we analyze cases where boundary control conditions are applied at the left endpoint. We utilize a spectral decomposition involving Bessel functions and their zeros in a convenient weighted Sobolev space for a degenerate parabolic operator with specific boundary conditions. We establish the well-posedness of the system using semigroup operator theory. Subsequently, we employ the moment method by Fattorini and Russell to obtain an upper estimate of the cost of controllability. Additionally, we derive a lower estimate of the cost of controllability using a representation theorem for analytic functions of exponential type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08745v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leandro Galo-Mendoza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local well-posedness for a novel nonlocal model for cell-cell adhesion via receptor binding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15222v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Local well-posedness is established for a highly nonlocal nonlinear diffusion-adhesion system for bounded initial values with small support. Macroscopic systems of this kind were previously obtained by the authors through upscaling in [32] and can account for the effect of microscopic receptor binding dynamics in cell-cell adhesion. The system analysed here couples an integro-PDE featuring degenerate diffusion of the porous media type and nonlocal adhesion with a novel nonlinear integral equation. The approach is based on decoupling the system and using Banach's fixed point theorem to solve each of the two equations individually and subsequently the entire system. The main challenge of the implementation lies in selecting a suitable framework. One of the key results is the local well-posedness for the integral equation with a Radon measure as a parameter. The analysis of this equation utilizes the Kantorovich-Rubinstein norm, marking the first application of this norm in handling a nonlinear integral equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15222v5</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mabel Lizzy Rajendran, Anna Zhigun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph structure of the nodal set and bounds on the number of critical points of eigenfunctions on Riemannian manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11800v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we illustrate and draw connections between the geometry of zero sets of eigenfunctions, graph theory and the vanishing order of eigenfunctions. We identify the nodal set of an eigenfunction of the Laplacian (with smooth potential) on a compact, two-dmensional Riemannian manifolds, that is on Riemannian surfaces, as an embedded metric graph and then use tools from elementary graph theory in order to estimate the number of critical points in the nodal set of the $k$-th eigenfunction and the sum of vanishing orders at critical points in terms of $k$ and the Euler-Poincar\'e characteristic of the surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11800v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Hofmann, Matthias T\"aufer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compressible Navier--Stokes--Coriolis system in critical Besov spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02191v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the three-dimensional compressible Navier--Stokes system with the Coriolis force and prove the long-time existence of a unique strong solution. More precisely, we show that for any $0&lt;T&lt;\infty$ and arbitrary large initial data in the scaling critical Besov spaces, the solution uniquely exists on $[0,T]$ provided that the speed of rotation is high and the Mach numbers are low enough. To the best of our knowledge, this paper is the first contribution to the well-posedness of the \textit{compressible} Navier--Stokes system with the Coriolis force in the whole space $\mathbb R^3$. The key ingredient of our analysis is to establish the dispersive linear estimates despite a quite complicated structure of the linearized equation due to the anisotropy of the Coriolis force.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02191v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikihiro Fujii, Keiichi Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wasserstein Gradient Flows of MMD Functionals with Distance Kernels under Sobolev Regularization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09848v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider Wasserstein gradient flows of maximum mean discrepancy (MMD) functionals $\text{MMD}_K^2(\cdot, \nu)$ for positive and negative distance kernels $K(x,y) := \pm |x-y|$ and given target measures $\nu$ on $\mathbb{R}$. Since in one dimension the Wasserstein space can be isometrically embedded into the cone $\mathcal C(0,1) \subset L_2(0,1)$ of quantile functions, Wasserstein gradient flows can be characterized by the solution of an associated Cauchy problem on $L_2(0,1)$. While for the negative kernel, the MMD functional is geodesically convex, this is not the case for the positive kernel, which needs to be handled to ensure the existence of the flow. We propose to add a regularizing Sobolev term $|\cdot|^2_{H^1(0,1)}$ corresponding to the Laplacian with Neumann boundary conditions to the Cauchy problem of quantile functions. Indeed, this ensures the existence of a generalized minimizing movement for the positive kernel. Furthermore, for the negative kernel, we demonstrate by numerical examples how the Laplacian rectifies a "dissipation-of-mass" defect of the MMD gradient flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09848v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Richard Duong, Nicolaj Rux, Viktor Stein, Gabriele Steidl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite time blow-up in a 1D model of the incompressible porous media equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16376v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive a PDE that models the behavior of a boundary layer solution to the incompressible porous media (IPM) equation posed on the 2D periodic half-plane. This 1D IPM model is a transport equation with a non-local velocity similar to the well-known C\'{o}rdoba-C\'{o}rdoba-Fontelos (CCF) equation. We discuss how this modification of the CCF equation can be regarded as a reasonable model for solutions to the IPM equation. Working in the class of bounded smooth periodic data, we then show local well-posedness for the 1D IPM model as well as finite time blow-up for a class of initial data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16376v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6544/adcdb8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2025 Nonlinearity 38 055018</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Kiselev, Naji A. Sarsam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence and multiplicity of $L^2$-Normalized solutions for the periodic Schr\"{o}dinger system of Hamiltonian type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15656v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the following nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger system of Hamiltonian type \begin{equation*} \left\{\begin{array}{l} -\Delta u+V(x)u=\partial_v H(x,u,v)+\omega v, \ x \in \mathbb{R}^N, \\ -\Delta v+V(x)v=\partial_u H(x,u,v)+\omega u,\ x \in \mathbb{R}^N, \\ \displaystyle\int_{\mathbb{R}^N}|z|^2dx=a^2, \end{array}\right. \end{equation*} where the potential function $V(x)$ is periodic, $z:=(u,v):\mathbb{R}^N\rightarrow \mathbb{R}\times\mathbb{R}$, $\omega\in \mathbb{R}$ appears as a Lagrange multiplier, $a&gt;0$ is a prescribed constant. The existence and multiplicity of $L^2$-normalized solutions for the above Schr\"{o}dinger system are obtained, and the combination of the Lyapunov-Schmidt reduction, a perturbation argument and the multiplicity theorem of Ljusternik-Schnirelmann is involved in the proof. In addition, a bifurcation result is also given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15656v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruowen Qiu, Yuanyang Yu, Fukun Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonexistence of Solutions to classes of parabolic inequalities in the Riemannian setting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00203</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00203v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish conditions for nonexistence of global solutions for a class of quasilinear parabolic problems with a potential on complete, non-compact Riemannian manifolds, including the Porous Medium Equation and the p-Laplacian with a potential term. Our results reveal the interplay between the manifold's geometry, the power nonlinearity, and the potential's behavior at infinity. Using a test function argument, we identify explicit parameter ranges where nonexistence holds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00203v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dorothea-Enrica von Criegern, Gabriele Grillo, Dario Monticelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniqueness Domains for ${\bf L}^\infty$ Solutions of $2 \times 2$ Hyperbolic Conservation Laws</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00420v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For a genuinely nonlinear $2\times 2$ hyperbolic system of conservation laws, assuming that the initial data have small ${\bf L}^\infty$ norm but possibly unbounded total variation, the existence of global solutions was proved in a classical paper by Glimm and Lax (1970). In general, the total variation of these solutions decays like $t^{-1}$. Motivated by the theory of fractional domains for linear analytic semigroups, we consider here solutions with faster decay rate: $\mathrm{Tot. Var. }\bigl\{u(t,\cdot)\bigr\}\leq C t^{\alpha-1}$. For these solutions, a uniqueness theorem is proved. Indeed, as the initial data range over a domain of functions with $\|\bar u\|_{{\bf L}^\infty} \leq\varepsilon_1$ small enough, solutions with fast decay yield a H\"older continuous semigroup. The H\"older exponent can be taken arbitrarily close to $1$ by further shrinking the value of $\varepsilon_1&gt;0$. An auxiliary result identifies a class of initial data whose solutions have rapidly decaying total variation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00420v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Bressan, Elio Marconi, Ganesh Vaidya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniqueness in the near isotropic Lp dual Minkowski problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01066v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For n&gt;1 and -1&lt;p&lt;1, we prove that if q is close to n and the qth Lp dual curvature is Holder close to be the constant one function, then this "near isotropic" qth Lp dual Minkowski problem on the (n-1)-dimensional sphere has a unique solution. Along the way, we establish a C0 estimate for -1&lt;p&lt;1 that is optimal in the sense that if p&lt;-1 and q=n, then it is known that the analogous C0 estimate does not hold. We also prove the uniqueness of the solution of the near isotropic even qth Lp dual Minkowski problem on the (n-1)-dimensional sphere if -1&lt;p&lt;q&lt;min{n,n+p} and q&gt;0.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01066v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karoly J. Boroczky, Shibing Chen, Weiru Liu, Christos Saroglou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heat kernel estimates for Dirichlet forms degenerate at the boundary</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.08606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.08606v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The goal of this paper is to establish sharp two-sided estimates on the heat kernels of two types of purely discontinuous symmetric Markov processes in the upper half-space of $\mathbb R^d$ with jump kernels degenerate at the boundary. The jump kernels are of the form $J(x,y)=\mathcal B(x,y)|x-y|^{-\alpha-d}$, $\alpha\in (0,2)$, where the function $\mathcal B$ depends on four parameters and may vanish at the boundary. Our results are the first sharp two-sided estimates for the heat kernels of non-local operators with jump kernels degenerate at the boundary. The first type of processes are conservative Markov processes on $\overline{\mathbb R}^d_+$ with jump kernel $J(x,y)$. Depending on the regions where the parameters belong, the heat kernels estimates have three different forms, two of them are qualitatively different from all previously known heat kernel estimates. The second type of processes are the processes above killed either by a critical potential or upon hitting the boundary of the half-space. We establish that their heat kernel estimates have the approximate factorization property with survival probabilities decaying as a power of the distance to the boundary, where the power depends on the constant in the critical potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.08606v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soobin Cho, Panki Kim, Renming Song, Zoran Vondra\v{c}ek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\Phi^4_3$ measures on compact Riemannian $3$-manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.10185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.10185v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We construct the $\Phi^4_3$ measure on an arbitrary 3-dimensional compact Riemannian manifold without boundary as an invariant probability measure of a singular stochastic partial differential equation. Proving the nontriviality and the covariance under Riemannian isometries of that measure gives for the first time a non-perturbative, non-topological interacting Euclidean quantum field theory on curved spaces in dimension 3. This answers a longstanding open problem of constructive quantum field theory on curved 3 dimensional backgrounds. To control analytically several Feynman diagrams appearing in the construction of a number of random fields, we introduce a novel approach of renormalization using microlocal and harmonic analysis. This allows to obtain a renormalized equation which involves some universal constants independent of the manifold. We also define a new vectorial Cole-Hopf transform which allows to deal with the vectorial $\Phi^4_3$ model where $\Phi$ is now a bundle valued random field. In a companion paper, we develop in a self-contained way all the tools from paradifferential and microlocal analysis that we use to build in our manifold setting a number of analytic and probabilistic objects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.10185v5</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Bailleul, N. V. Dang, L. Ferdinand, T. D. T\^o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical Exploration of Nonlinear Dispersion Effects via a Strongly Coupled Two-scale System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.09607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.09607v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The effective, fast transport of matter through porous media is often characterized by complex dispersion effects. To describe in mathematical terms such situations, instead of a simple macroscopic equation (as in the classical Darcy's law), one may need to consider two-scale boundary-value problems with full coupling between the scales where the macroscopic transport depends non-linearly on local (i.e. microscopic) drift interactions, which are again influenced by local concentrations. Such two-scale problems are computationally very expensive as numerous elliptic partial differential equations (cell problems) have to constantly be recomputed. In this work, we investigate such an effective two-scale model involving a suitable nonlinear dispersion term and explore numerically the behavior of its weak solutions. We introduce two distinct numerical schemes dealing with the same non-linear scale-coupling: (i) a Picard-type iteration and (ii) a time discretization decoupling. In addition, we propose a precomputing strategy where the calculations of cell problems are pushed into an offline phase. Our approach works for both schemes and significantly reduces computation times. We prove that the proposed precomputing strategy converges to the exact solution. Finally, we test our schemes via several numerical experiments that illustrate dispersion effects introduced by specific choices of microstructure and model ingredients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.09607v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Surendra Nepal, Vishnu Raveendran, Michael Eden, Rainey Lyons, Adrian Muntean</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compact pseudodifferential and Fourier integral operators via localization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.15096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.15096v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a general framework of localized operators, i.e., operators whose matrix coefficients with respect to the Gabor frame are concentrated on the diagonal. We show that localized operators are bounded between modulation spaces, and we deduce their compactness from an easily verifiable weak compactness condition. We apply this abstract formalism to unify and extend existing theorems for pseudodifferential and Fourier integral operators, and to obtain new results for three-parameter pseudodifferential operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.15096v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cody B. Stockdale, Cody Waters</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local controllability of a free-boundary problem for 1D degenerate parabolic equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11929v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper deals with the local controllability of a free-boundary problem for the 1D boundary-degenerate parabolic equation with distributed controls, locally supported in space. We prove that, if the final time T is fixed and the initial state is sufficiently small, there exist controls that drive the state exactly to rest at time t = T. The proof is based on Schauder's fixed point theorem, combined with appropriate estimates for solutions to degenerate parabolic equations and for the control function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11929v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lingyang Liu, Hang Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotics for resolutions and smoothings of Calabi-Yau conifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16702v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that the Calabi-Yau metrics with isolated conical singularities of Hein-Sun admit polyhomogeneous expansions near their singularities. Moreover, we show that, under certain generic assumptions, natural families of smooth Calabi-Yau metrics on crepant resolutions and on polarized smoothings of conical Calabi-Yau manifolds degenerating to the initial conical Calabi-Yau metric admit polyhomogeneous expansions where the singularities are forming. The construction proceeds by performing weighted Melrose-type blow-ups and then gluing conical and scaled asymptotically conical Calabi-Yau metrics on the fibers, close to the blow-up's front face without compromising polyhomogeneity. This yields a polyhomogeneous family of K\"ahler metrics that are approximately Calabi-Yau. Solving formally a complex Monge-Amp\`ere equation, we obtain a polyhomogeneous family of K\"ahler metrics with Ricci potential converging rapidly to zero as the family is degenerating. We can then conclude that the corresponding family of degenerating Calabi-Yau metrics is polyhomogeneous by using a fixed point argument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16702v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdou Oussama Benabida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$p$-Poincar\'e inequalities and cutoff Sobolev inequalities on metric measure spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09503v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For $p\in(1,+\infty)$, we introduce the cutoff Sobolev inequality on general metric measure spaces, and prove that there exists a metric measure space endowed with a $p$-energy that satisfies the chain condition, the volume regular condition with respect to a doubling scaling function $\Phi$, and that both the Poincar\'e inequality and the the cutoff Sobolev inequality with respect to a doubling scaling function $\Psi$ hold if and only if $$\frac{1}{C}\left(\frac{R}{r}\right)^p\le\frac{\Psi(R)}{\Psi(r)}\le C\left(\frac{R}{r}\right)^{p-1}\frac{\Phi(R)}{\Phi(r)}\text{ for any }r\le R.$$ In particular, given any pair of doubling functions $\Phi$ and $\Psi$ satisfying the above inequality, we construct a metric measure space endowed with a $p$-energy on which all the above conditions are satisfied. As a direct corollary, we prove that there exists a metric measure space which is $d_h$-Ahlfors regular and has $p$-walk dimension $\beta_p$ if and only if $$p\le\beta_p\le d_h+(p-1).$$ Our proof builds on the Laakso-type space theory, which was recently developed by Murugan (arXiv:2410.15611).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09503v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meng Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
