<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2025 03:26:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Heat Kernel Estimates for Schr\"odinger Operators in the Domain Above a Bounded Lipschitz Function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05641v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give matching upper and lower bounds for the Dirichlet heat kernel of a Schr\"odinger operator $\Delta+W$ in the domain above the graph of a bounded Lipschitz function, in the case when $W$ decays away from the boundary faster than quadratically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05641v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anthony Graves-McCleary</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Neumann problem for a class of Hessian quotient type equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05695v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the Neumann problem for a class of Hessian quotient equations involving a gradient term on the right-hand side in Euclidean space. More precisely, we derive the interior gradient estimates for the $(\Lambda, k)$-convex solution of Hessian quotient equation $\frac{\sigma_k(\Lambda(D^2 u))}{\sigma_l(\Lambda(D^2 u))}=\psi(x,u,D u)$ with $0\leq l&lt;k\leq C^{p-1}_{n-1}$ under the assumption of the growth condition. As an application, we obtain the global a priori estimates and the existence theorem for the Neumann problem of this Hessian quotient type equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05695v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiabao Gong, Zixuan Liu, Qiang Tu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some Sobolev-type inequalities for twisted differential forms on real and complex manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05697v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove certain $L^p$ Sobolev-type inequalities for twisted differential forms on real (and complex) manifolds for the Laplace operator $\Delta$, the differential operators $d$ and $d^*$, and the operator $\bar\partial$. A key tool to get such inequalities are integral representations for twisted differential forms. The proofs of the main results involves certain uniform estimate for the Green forms and their differentials and codifferentials, which are also established in the present work. As applications of the uniform estimates, using Hodge theory, we can get an $L^{q,p}$-estimate for the operator $d$ or $\bar\partial$. Furthermore, we get an improved $L^2$-estimate of H\"ormander on a strictly pseudoconvex open subset of a K\"ahler manifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05697v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fusheng Deng, Gang Huang, Xiangsen Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homogenization of Inhomogeneous Incompressible Navier-Stokes Equations in Domains with Very Tiny Holes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05734v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the homogenization problems of $3D$ inhomogeneous incompressible Navier-Stokes system perforated with very tiny holes whose diameters are much smaller than their mutual distances. The key is to establish the equations in the homogeneous domain without holes for the zero extensions of the weak solutions. This allows us to derive time derivative estimates and show the strong convergence of the density and the momentum by Aubin-Lions type argument. For the case of small holes, we finally show the limit equations remain unchanged in the homogenization limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05734v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yong Lu, Jiaojiao Pan, Peikang Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparison Between Effective and Individual Fitness in a Heterogeneous Population</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05751v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Is there an advantage of displaying heterogeneity in a population where the individuals grow and divide by fission? This is a wide-ranging question, for which a universal answer cannot be easily provided. This article thus aims at providing a quantitative answer in the specific context of growth rate heterogeneity by comparing the fitness of homogeneous versus heterogeneous populations. We focus on a size-structured population, where an individual's growth rate is chosen at its birth through heredity and/or random mutations. We use the long-term behaviour to define the Malthus parameter of such a population, and compare it to the ones of averaged homogeneous populations. We obtain analytical formulae in two paradigmatic cases: first, constant rates for growth and division, second, linear growth rates and uniform fragmentation. Surprisingly, these two cases happen to display similar analytical formulae linking effective and individual fitness. They allow us to investigate quantitatively the crossed influence of heredity and heterogeneity, and revisit previous results stating that heterogeneity is beneficial in the case of strong heredity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05751v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marie Doumic (MERGE), Ana\"is Rat (MAMBA, LMBA, I2M), Magali Tournus (I2M, AMU, ECM, CNRS)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positive solutions for fractional-order boundary value problems with or without dependence of integer-order ones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05810v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the existence, non-existence, uniqueness, and multiplicity of positive solutions to the following problem: \begin{align}\label{P}
  \left\{
  \begin{array}{l}
  D_{0+}^\alpha u + h(t)f(u) = 0, \quad 0&lt;t&lt;1, \\[1ex]
  u(0)=u(1)=0,
  \end{array}
  \right. \end{align} where $D_{0+}^\alpha$ is the Riemann-Liouville fractional derivative of order $\alpha\in(1,2]$. Firstly, by considering the first eigenvalue $\lambda_1(\alpha)$ of the corresponding eigenvalue problem, we establish the existence of positive solutions for both sublinear and superlinear cases involving $\lambda_1(\alpha)$, thereby extending existing results in the literature. In addition, we address the issue of non-existence, which reinforces the sharpness of both hypotheses. Secondly, we demonstrate the uniqueness of positive solutions. For the sublinear case, we impose certain monotonicity conditions on $f$. For the superlinear case, we assume that $h$ satisfies a specific condition to ensure the uniqueness of positive solutions when $\alpha =2.$ Near $\alpha =2,$ we prove uniqueness by leveraging the non-degeneracy of the unique solution, which represents a novel approach to studying fractional-order differential equations. Finally, we apply this methodology to establish the multiple existence of at least three positive solutions for H\'{e}non-type problems, which is also a new contribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05810v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Inbo Sim, Satoshi Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Born approximation for the fixed energy Calder\'on problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05889v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Born approximation of a potential in the context of the Calder\'on inverse problem is an object that can be formally defined in terms of spectral data of the Dirichlet-to-Neumann map of the corresponding Schr\"odinger operator. In this article, we prove, in the case of radial potentials in the Euclidean ball and any fixed energy, that this Born approximation is well-defined as a compactly supported radial distribution, and that the Calder\'on problem can be reformulated as recovering a potential from its Born approximation. In addition, we show that the Born approximation depends locally on the potential and captures exactly its singularities, and that the functional that maps the Born approximation to the potential is H\"older continuous. We also prove that the Born approximation converges to the potential in the high-energy limit. Moreover, we give an explicit formula for the Fourier transform of the Born approximation at any fixed energy, and illustrate how it can be used as the basis of an accurate procedure to approximate a potential from its Dirichlet-to-Neumann map.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05889v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabricio Maci\`a, Crist\'obal J. Mero\~no, Daniel S\'anchez-Mendoza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional Sobolev spaces related to an ultraparabolic operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05898v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a functional framework of fractional Sobolev spaces for a class of ultra-parabolic Kolmogorov type operators satisfying the weak H\"ormander condition. We characterize these spaces as real interpolation of natural order intrinic Sobolev spaces recently introduced in [27], and prove continuous embeddings into $L^p$ and intrinsic H\"older spaces from [24]. These embeddings naturally extend the standard Euclidean ones, coherently with the homogeneous structure of the associated Kolmogorov group. Our approach to interpolation is based on approximation of intrinsically regular functions, the latter heavily relying on integral estimates of the intrinsic Taylor remainder. The embeddings exploit the aforementioned interpolation property and the corresponding embeddings of natural order intrinsic spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05898v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonello Pesce, Sascha Portaro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normalized Solutions for nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger-Poisson equations involving nearly mass-critical exponents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05983v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the Schr\"{o}dinger-Poisson-Slater equation \begin{equation*}\left\{\begin{array}{lll}
  -\Delta u + \lambda u + \big(|x|^{-1} \ast |u|^{2}\big)u = V(x) u^{ p_{\varepsilon}-1 }, \, \text{ in } \mathbb{R}^{3},\\[2mm]
  \int_{\mathbb{R}^3}u^2 \,dx= a,\,\, u &gt; 0,\,\, u \in H^{1}(\mathbb{R}^{3}),
  \end{array}
  \right. \end{equation*} where $\lambda$ is a Lagrange multiplier, $V(x)$ is a real-valued potential, $a\in \mathbb{R}_{+}$ is a constant, $ p_{\varepsilon} = \frac{10}{3} \pm \varepsilon$ and $\varepsilon&gt;0$ is a small parameter. In this paper, we prove that it is the positive critical value of the potential $V$ that affects the existence of single-peak solutions for this problem. Furthermore, we prove the local uniqueness of the solutions we construct.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05983v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qidong Guo, Rui He, Qiaoqiao Hua, Qingfang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear partial differential equations in neuroscience: from modelling to mathematical theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06015v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many systems of partial differential equations have been proposed as simplified representations of complex collective behaviours in large networks of neurons. In this survey, we briefly discuss their derivations and then review the mathematical methods developed to handle the unique features of these models, which are often nonlinear and non-local. The first part focuses on parabolic Fokker-Planck equations: the Nonlinear Noisy Leaky Integrate and Fire neuron model, stochastic neural fields in PDE form with applications to grid cells, and rate-based models for decision-making. The second part concerns hyperbolic transport equations, namely the model of the Time Elapsed since the last discharge and the jump-based Leaky Integrate and Fire model. The last part covers some kinetic mesoscopic models, with particular attention to the kinetic Voltage-Conductance model and FitzHugh-Nagumo kinetic Fokker-Planck systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06015v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e A Carrillo (ICJ), Pierre Roux (ICJ)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Efficient Approach to Fractional Analysis for Non-Linear Coupled Thermo-Elastic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06127v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nonlinear thermoelastic systems play a crucial role in understanding thermal conductivity, stresses, elasticity, and temperature interactions. This research focuses on finding solutions to these systems in their fractional forms, which is a significant aspect of the study. We consider various proposed models related to fractional thermoelasticity and derive results through sophisticated methodologies. Numerical simulations are conducted for both fractional and integer order thermoelastic coupled systems, with results presented in tables and graphs. The graphs indicate a close correspondence between the approximate and exact solutions. The solutions obtained demonstrate convergence for both fractional and integer order problems, ensuring accurate modeling. Furthermore, the tables confirm that greater accuracy can be achieved by increasing the number of terms in the series of solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06127v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qasim Khan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform local well-posedness and liviscid limit for the KdV-Burgers equation on $\mathbb{T}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06147v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article investigates the uniform well-posedness and inviscid limit problem for the Korteweg-de Vries-Burgers equation on a torus, we consider the KdV-Burgers equation $$\partial_t u(t,x)+\partial_x^3u(t,x)-\varepsilon\partial_x^2u(t,x)=\dfrac{1}{2}\partial_x(u(t,x))^2, \quad u(0)=\phi, $$ where $\varepsilon\in(0, 1]$ represents the diffusion coefficient, and $u(t,x):\mathbb{R}^{+}\times\mathbb{T}\rightarrow \mathbb{R}$ is a real-valued function, we show that it is uniformly local well-posed in $H^s$ with $s\geq 0$ for all $\varepsilon\in[0,1]$. Moreover, we prove that there exists some $T&gt;0$ such that for any $s\geq 0$, its solution converges in $C([0,T];H^s)$ to that of the KdV equation if $\varepsilon$ tends to $0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06147v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xintong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Serrin's type Problems in convex cones in Riemannian manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05551v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we discuss several results concerning Serrin's problem in convex cones in Riemannian manifolds. First, we present a rigidity result for an overdetermined problem in a class of warped products with Ricci curvature bounded below. As a consequence, we obtain a rigidity result for Einstein warped products. Next, we derive a soap bubble result and a Heintze-Karcher inequality that characterize the intersection of geodesic balls with cones in these spaces. Finally, we analyze the analogous ovedetermined problem for the drift Laplacian, where the ambient space is a cone in the Euclidean space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05551v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Murilo Ara\'ujo, Allan Freitas, M\'arcio Santos, Joyce Sindeaux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Atiyah-Bott formula for the Lefschetz number of a singular foliation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05812v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a formula for the Lefschetz number of a geometric endomorphism in the style of the Atiyah-Bott theorem. The underlying data consist, first, of a compact manifold and a nowhere vanishing smooth real vector field $\mathcal{T}$ that preserves some Riemannian metric, and second, a sequence of first order operators on sections of Hermitian vector bundles with connection whose curvature is annihilated by $\mathcal{T}$ and for which parallel transport along integral curves of $\mathcal{T}$ is unitary. Assuming that the operators of the sequence commute with the various covariant derivatives $\mathcal{L}_{\mathcal{T}}=\nabla_{\mathcal{T}}$ and that their restriction to the spaces of sections annihilated by $\mathcal{L}_{\mathcal{T}}$ form a complex, an ellipticity condition gives finite-dimensionality of the resulting equivariant cohomology spaces. The Atiyah-Bott framework, adapted to give a geometric endomorphism only for the complex of $\mathcal{L}_{\mathcal{T}}$-parallel sections, together with the finiteness of cohomology allows for the definition of a Lefschetz number. Replacing the condition that the fixed points of the equivariant map $f$ associated with the endomorphism be simple by a condition on wave front sets, which is the underlying condition of Atiyah and Bott, yields that the set of closures of orbits by $\mathcal{T}$ left invariant by $f$ is finite, and then a formula similar to theirs, now relating the Lefschetz number with traces along these orbits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05812v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luiz Hartmann, Gerardo A. Mendoza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence, uniqueness and asymptotic stability of invariant measures for the stochastic Allen-Cahn-Navier-Stokes system with singular potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06174v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the long-time behaviour of a stochastic Allen-Cahn-Navier-Stokes system modelling the dynamics of binary mixtures of immiscible fluids. The model features two stochastic forcings, one on the velocity in the Navier-Stokes equation and one on the phase variable in the Allen-Cahn equation, and includes the thermodynamically-relevant Flory-Huggins logarithhmic potential. We first show existence of ergodic invariant measures and characterise their support by exploiting ad-hoc regularity estimates and suitable Feller-type and Markov properties. Secondly, we prove that if the noise acting in the Navier-Stokes equation is non-degenerate along a sufficiently large number of low modes, and the Allen-Cahn equation is highly dissipative, then the stochastic flow admits a unique invariant measure and is asymptotically stable with respect to a suitable Wasserstein metric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06174v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Di Primio, Luca Scarpa, Margherita Zanella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Derivation of the viscoelastic stress in Stokes flows induced by non-spherical Brownian rigid particles through homogenization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.09317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.09317v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a microscopic model of $n$ identical axis-symmetric rigid Brownian particles suspended in a Stokes flow. We rigorously derive in the homogenization limit of many small particles a classical formula for the viscoelastic stress that appears in so-called Doi models which couple a Fokker-Planck equation to the Stokes equations. We consider both Deborah numbers of order $1$ and very small Deborah numbers. Our microscopic model contains several simplifications, most importantly, we neglect the time evolution of the particle centers as well as hydrodynamic interaction for the evolution of the particle orientations. The microscopic fluid velocity is modeled by the Stokes equations with given torques at the particles in terms of Stratonovitch noise. We give a meaning to this PDE in terms of an infinite dimensional Stratonovitch integral. This requires the analysis of the shape derivatives of the Stokes equations in perforated domains, which we accomplish by the method of reflections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.09317v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.2140/paa.2023.5.409</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Pure Appl. Analysis 5 (2023) 409-460</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Richard M. H\"ofer, Marta Leocata, Amina Mecherbet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quadratic growth solutions of fully nonlinear elliptic equations with periodic data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13927v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study quadratic growth solutions $u$ of fully nonlinear elliptic equations of the form $F(D^2u)=f$ in $\mathbb{R}^n$, where $f$ is periodic and $F$ may be not uniformly elliptic. The existence of solutions and Liouville type results in the whole space and exterior domains are established, which generalize the classical results when $f$ is constant. As applications, the corresponding results are given to $k$-Hessian equations, which include the celebrated results for Monge-Amp\`{e}re equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13927v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongsheng Li, Lichun Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gradient regularity for a class of doubly nonlinear parabolic partial differential equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05631v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the local gradient regularity of non-negative weak solutions to doubly nonlinear parabolic partial differential equations of the type \begin{align*}
  \partial_t u^q - \mbox{div}\, A(x,t,Du)=0
  \qquad\mbox{in $\Omega_T$}, \end{align*} with $q&gt;0$, $\Omega_T=\Omega\times(0,T)\subset\mathbb{R}^{n+1}$ a space-time cylinder, and $A=A(x,t,\xi)$ a vector field satisfying standard $p$-growth conditions. Our main result establishes the local H\"older continuity of the spatial gradient of non-negative weak solutions in the super-critical fast diffusion regime $$0&lt;p-1&lt;q&lt;\frac{n(p-1)}{(n-p)_+}.$$ This result is achieved by utilizing a time-insensitive Harnack inequality and Schauder estimates that are developed for equations of parabolic $p$-Laplacian type. Additionally, we establish a local $L^{\infty}$-bound for the spatial gradient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05631v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Strunk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigidity of the subelliptic heat kernel on $\operatorname{SU}(2)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12183v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study heat kernel rigidity for the Lie group $\operatorname{SU}\left( 2 \right)$ kernel equipped with a sub-Riemannian structure. We prove that a metric measure space equipped with a heat kernel of a special form is bundle-isometric to the Hopf fibration $\operatorname{U}\left( 1 \right)\to \operatorname{SU}\left( 2 \right)\to \mathbb{CP}^1$, which coincides with the sub-Riemannian sphere $\operatorname{SU}\left( 2 \right)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12183v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Gordina, Jing Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shubin calculi for actions of graded Lie groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14347v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we develop a calculus of Shubin type pseudodifferential operators on certain non-compact spaces, using a groupoid approach similar to the one of van Erp and Yuncken. More concretely, we consider actions of graded Lie groups on graded vector spaces and study pseudodifferential operators that generalize fundamental vector fields and multiplication by polynomials. Our two main examples of elliptic operators in this calculus are Rockland operators with a potential and the generalizations of the harmonic oscillator to the Heisenberg group due to Rottensteiner-Ruzhansky.
  Deforming the action of the graded group, we define a tangent groupoid which connects pseudodifferential operators to their principal (co)symbols. We show that our operators form a calculus that is asymptotically complete. Elliptic elements in the calculus have parametrices, are hypoelliptic, and can be characterized in terms of a Rockland condition. Moreover, we study the mapping properties as well as the spectra of our operators on Sobolev spaces and compare our calculus to the Shubin calculus on $\mathbb R^n$ and its anisotropic generalizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14347v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.bulsci.2024.103572</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Eske Ewert, Philipp Schmitt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Space-Time Wave Localisation in Systems of Subwavelength Resonators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10100v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we study the dynamics of metamaterials composed of high-contrast subwavelength resonators and show the existence of localised modes in such a setting. A crucial assumption in this paper is time-modulated material parameters. We prove a so-called capacitance matrix approximation of the wave equation in the form of an ordinary differential equation. These formulas set the ground for the derivation of a first-principles characterisation of localised modes in terms of the generalised capacitance matrix. Furthermore, we provide numerical results supporting our analytical results showing for the first time the phenomenon of space-time localised waves in a perturbed time-modulated metamaterial. Such spatio-temporal localisation is only possible in the presence of subwavelength resonances in the unperturbed structure. We introduce the time-dependent degree of localisation to quantitatively determine the localised modes and provide a variety of numerical experiments to illustrate our formulations and results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10100v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Habib Ammari, Erik Orvehed Hiltunen, Liora Rueff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the justification of Koiter's model for generalised membrane shells of the fist kind confined in a half-space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16837v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we justify Koiter's model for linearly elastic generalised membrane shells of the first kind subjected to remaining confined in a prescribed half-space. After showing that the confinement condition considered in this paper is in general stronger, under the validity of the Kirchhoff-Love assumptions, than the classical Signorini condition, we formulate the corresponding obstacle problem for a three-dimensional linearly elastic generalised membrane shell of the first kind, and we conduct a rigorous asymptotic analysis as the thickness approaches to zero on the unique solution for one such model. We show that the solution to the three-dimensional obstacle problem converges to the unique solution of a two-dimensional model consisting of a set of variational inequalities that are posed over the abstract completion of a non-empty, closed and convex set. We recall that the two-dimensional limit model obtained departing from Koiter's model is characterised by the same variational inequalities as the two-dimensional model obtained departing from the variational formulation of a three-dimensional linearly elastic generalised membrane shell subjected to remaining confined in a prescribed half-space, with the remarkable difference that the sets where solutions for these two-dimensional limit models are sought do not coincide, in general. In order to complete the justification of Koiter's model for linearly elastic generalised membrane shells of the first kind subjected to remaining confined in a half-space, we give sufficient conditions ensuring that the sets where solutions for these two-dimensional limit models are sought coincide.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16837v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Piersanti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On $p$-fractional weakly-coupled system with critical nonlinearities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04994v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper deals with the following nonlocal system of equations: \begin{align}\tag{$\mathcal S$}\label{MAT1} (-\Delta_p)^s u = \frac{\alpha}{p_s^*}|u|^{\alpha-2}u|v|^{\beta}+f(x) \text{ in } \mathbb{R}^{d}, \, (-\Delta_p)^s v = \frac{\beta}{p_s^*}|v|^{\beta-2}v|u|^{\alpha}+g(x) \text{ in } \mathbb{R}^{d},\, u,v &gt;0 \mbox{ in } \mathbb{R}^{d}, \end{align} where $s\in(0,1)$, $p\in(1,\infty)$, $d&gt;sp$, $\alpha,\beta&gt;1$, $\alpha+\beta=dp/(d-sp)$, and $f,\, g$ are nonnegative functionals in the dual space of $\mathcal{D}^{s,p}(\mathbb{R}^{d})$. When $f=g=0$, we prove a uniqueness result for the ground state solution of \eqref{MAT1}. On the other hand, when $f \not \equiv 0, g \not \equiv 0$, the primary objective is to present a global compactness result that offers a complete characterization of the Palais-Smale sequences of the energy functional associated with \eqref{MAT1}. Using this characterization, within a certain range of $s$, we establish the existence of a solution with negative energy for \eqref{MAT1} when $\ker(f)=\ker(g)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04994v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nirjan Biswas, Souptik Chakraborty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral multipliers for maximally subelliptic operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.07086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.07086v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Consider a non-negative, self-adjoint, maximally subelliptic operator on a compact manifold. We show that the spectral multiplier is a singular integral operator under an appropriate Mihlin-H\"ormander type condition. We establish the equivalence between non-isotropic Besov and Triebel-Lizorkin spaces adapted to the operator and those adapted to a Carnot-Carath\'eodory geometry on the manifold. We also give a Mihlin-H\"ormander type condition for the boundedness of the spectral multiplier on non-isotropic $L^p$ Sobolev spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.07086v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lingxiao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniform doubling for abelian products with $\operatorname{SU}(2)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17102v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that the uniform doubling property holds for every Lie group which can be written as a quotient group of $\operatorname{SU}(2) \times \mathbb{R}^n$ for some $n$. In particular, this class includes the four-dimensional unitary group $\operatorname{U}(2)$. As this class contain non-compact as well as compact Lie groups, we discuss a number of analytic and spectral consequences for the corresponding heat kernels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17102v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathaniel Eldredge, Maria Gordina, Laurent Saloff-Coste</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>La formule de Cauchy dans les alg\`ebres</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19307v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We Study versions of Cauchy formula in more general algebras than the complex case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19307v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Bonneau, Emmanuel Mazzilli</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
