<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 May 2025 01:55:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Second domain variation for a product of domain functionals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20307v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The second domain variation of the $p$-capacity and the $q$ - torsional rigidity for compact sets in $R^d, d\geq3$ with $1&lt;p&lt;d$ is computed. Conditions on $p$ and $q&gt;1$ are given such that the ball is a local minimzer or maximizer of the product.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20307v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alfred Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global and nonglobal solutions for a mixed local-nonlocal heat equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20401v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we establish optimal conditions concerning the global and nonglobal existence of solutions of a semilinear parabolic equations governed by a mixed local-nonlocal operator. Furthermore, our findings recover the Fujita exponent recently derived by Biagi, Punzo and Vecchi, as well as by Del Pezzo and Ferreira.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20401v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brandon Carhuas, Ricardo Castillo, Ricardo Freire, Alex Lira, Miguel Loayza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A two-player zero-sum probabilistic game that approximates the mean curvature flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20559v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we introduce a new two-player zero-sum game whose value function approximates the level set formulation for the geometric evolution by mean curvature of a hypersurface. In our approach the game is played with symmetric rules for the two players and probability theory is involved (the game is not deterministic).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20559v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Irene Gonzalvez, Alfredo Miranda, Julio D. Rossi, Jorge Ruiz-Cases</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp Spectral-Cluster Restriction Bounds for Orthonormal Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20657v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For a smooth $k$-dimensional submanifold $\Sigma$ of a $d$-dimensional compact Riemannian manifold $M$, we extend the $L^p(\Sigma)$ restriction bounds of Burq-G\'erard-Tzvetkov -- originally proved for individual Laplace--Beltrami eigenfunction -- to arbitrary systems of $L^2(M)$-orthonormal functions. Our bounds are essentially optimal for every triple $(k,d,p)$ with $p\ge2$, except possibly when $ d\ge3,\quad k=d-1,\quad 2\le p\le4. $ This work is inspired by a work of Frank and Sabin, who established analogous $L^p(M)$ bounds for $L^2(M)$-orthonormal systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20657v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changbiao Jian, Xing Wang, Yakun Xi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic inverse problem for complex Jacobi matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20689v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the inverse dynamic problem for a dynamical system with discrete time associated with a semi-infinite complex Jacobi matrix. We propose two approaches of recovering coefficients from dynamic response operator and answer a question on the characterization of dynamic inverse data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20689v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. S. Mikhaylov, V. S. Mikhaylov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$L^2$-normalized solutions of a class of $(2,q)$-Laplacian Schr\"odinger equations with inhomogeneous nonlinearity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20758v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study systematically the $L^2$-normalized solutions of a class of $(2,q)$-Laplacian Schr\"odinger equations with inhomogeneous nonlinearity. Our results contain the existence, non-existence, multiplicity and some asymptotic behaviors of the $L^2$ normalized solutions, covering the mass-subcritical, mass-critical and mass-supercritical cases. Some of the existence results are given sharply. The proofs are mainly based on the constrained variational methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20758v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying Huang, Tingjian Luo, Youde Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dislocations in a multi-layered elastic solid with applications to fault and interface identifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20763v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates an elastic dislocation problem within a bounded and multi-layered solid governed by the Lam\'e system. We address the simultaneous reconstruction of the faults, the jumps in displacement and traction fields across the faults, and the interfaces of layers using a single passive boundary measurement. This inverse problem is particularly challenging due to the discontinuities in both the displacement and traction fields across the faults and the inherent difficulty of establishing uniqueness results with limited measurement data. Under the assumptions that the Lam\'e parameters are piecewise constants within each layer, satisfying strong convexity conditions, and that the faults exhibit corner singularities, we establish local uniqueness identifiability results for both the interfaces and the faults, as well as the jumps across the faults. Furthermore, we derive global uniqueness results for reconstructing the interfaces, the faults, and the corresponding displacement and traction jumps in generic scenarios under a priori geometric information, where the faults are geometrically general and may be either open or closed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20763v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huaian Diao, Hongyu Liu, Qingle Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-Minnaert Resonances in 2D Elastic Wave Scattering with Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20768v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In our earlier work [13], we introduced a novel quasi-Minnaert resonance for three-dimensional elastic wave scattering in the sub-wavelength regime. Therein, we provided a rigorous analysis of the boundary localization and surface resonance phenomena for both the total and scattered waves, achieved through carefully selected incident waves and tailored physical parameters of the elastic medium. In the present study, we focus on quasi-Minnaert resonances in the context of two-dimensional elastic wave scattering. Unlike the 3D case [13], the 2D setting introduces fundamental theoretical challenges stemming from (i) the intrinsic coupling between shear and compressional waves, and (ii) the complex spectral properties of the associated layer potential operators. By combining layer potential techniques with refined asymptotic analysis and strategically designed incident waves, we rigorously establish quasi-Minnaert resonances in both the internal and scattered fields. In addition, the associated stress concentration effects are quantitatively characterized. Notably, the boundary-localized nature of the scattered field reveals potential applications in near-cloaking (via wave manipulation around boundaries). Our results contribute to a more comprehensive framework for studying resonance behaviors in high-contrast elastic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20768v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huaian Diao, Kaixin Lu, Ruixiang Tang, Weisheng Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calder\'{o}n-Zygmund estimates for double phase problems with matrix weights</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20856v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a degenerate/singular double phase problem with the matrix weight to announce that the Calder\'{o}n-Zygmund theory for the classical problem is still available provided the matrix weight has a sufficient smallness in $\log$-BMO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20856v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sun-Sig Byun, Yumi Cho, Seungjin Ryu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some optimal control and shape optimisation problems for bulk-surface cooperative systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20865v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The goal of this paper is to address some optimal control and shape optimisation problems arising from bulk-surface cooperative systems. The basic model under consideration is the following: letting $\Omega$ be a fixed domain, we assume that a population (with density $u$) lives inside $\Omega$ and can access some resources $f$, while a second population (with density $v$) lives on the boundary $\partial \Omega$ and can access other resources $g$. These two populations are coupled in a cooperative manner by a constant exchange rate at the boundary, leading to a non-standard PDE system that has already been studied in previous works by Bogosel, Giletti and Tellini, for its connection with road-field models. Building on the considerations of the aforementioned previous works, we have two main objectives here: first, investigate the question of optimal resources distribution inside the domain $\Omega$ and on the surface $\partial \Omega$, i.e. how to spread resources in order to guarantee an optimal survival of the two species. We establish rigid Talenti inequalities and comparison results when $\Omega$ is a ball, extending in particular the results of J. J. Langford on symmetrisation for Neumann and Robin problems. Second, when the resources distribution $f$ and $g$ are constant, we provide a partial analysis of the natural shape optimisation problem: which shape $\Omega$ maximises the survival rate of the two species? Namely, we show that in certain regimes there can be no optimal shape and, by computing second-order shape derivatives, we investigate the local optimality of the ball.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20865v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Gentile, Idriss Mazari-Fouquer, Rapha\"el Prunier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local well-posedness for the derivative nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation with nonvanishing boundary conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20883v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the derivative nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation on the real line, with a background function $\psi(t,x)\in L^\infty(\mathbb{R}^2)$ that satisfies suitable conditions. Such a function may, for example, be a non-decaying solution of the equation, such as a dark soliton. By developing the energy method with correction terms, we prove that the Cauchy problem for perturbations around such an $L^\infty$ function is unconditionally locally well-posed in $ H^s(\mathbb{R}) $ for $ s&gt;3/4 $. As a byproduct, we also establish local well-posedness in the Zhidkov space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20883v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luc Molinet, Tomoyuki Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the construction of de Branges spaces for dynamical systems associated with finite Jacobi matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20905v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider dynamical systems with boundary control associated with finite Jacobi matrices. Using the method previously developed by the authors, we associate with these systems special Hilbert spaces of analytic functions (de Branges spaces)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20905v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.17586/2220-8054-2022-13-1-24-29</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>A. S. Mikhaylov, V. S. Mikhaylov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An anisotropic Alt-Caffarelli problem of higher order</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20923v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a higher order version of the Alt-Caffarelli problem in two dimensions, where the Dirichlet energy is replaced by an anisotropic bending energy. This extends a previous study of the isotropic case in [41]. It turns out that smooth anisotropies do not affect the optimal $C^{2,1}$-regularity of minimizers. The proof requires an anisotropic version of an estimate by Frehse for the fundamental solution of the bilaplacian. This generalization paves the way for further studies of various free boundary problems of higher order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20923v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marius M\"uller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-time singularity via multi-layer degenerate pendula for the 2D Boussinesq equation with uniform $C^{1,\sqrt{\frac{4}{3}}-1-\epsilon}\cap L^2$ force</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20988v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish the existence of compactly supported solutions of the inviscid incompressible 2D Boussinesq equation with $C^{1,\sqrt{\frac{4}{3}}-1-\varepsilon}\cap L^{2}$ force that develop a singularity in finite time. Importantly, the force preserves this regularity at the blow-up time. Moreover, the forces in the vorticity and density equations have compact support. The mechanism behind the blow-up is an accumulated hysteresis effect on the vorticity caused by an infinite chain of "degenerate" pendula and flickering density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20988v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego C\'ordoba, Andr\'es La\'in-Sanclemente, Luis Mart\'inez-Zoroa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric results for hyperbolic operators with spectral transition of the Hamilton map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21078v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we study a class of non-effectively hyperbolic operators vanishing of order 2 on a manifold, on a sub-region of which the spectral structure of the Hamilton map changes type. Suitable normal symplectic coordinates are found together with an analysis of the Hamilton system associated to the principal symbol and a factorization result, preparing the operator for a microlocal energy estimate, is finally proven.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21078v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Bernardi, Tatsuo Nishitani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weak-strong uniqueness for the Landau equation by a relative entropy method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21120v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive a weak-strong uniqueness and stability principle for the Landau equation in the soft potentials case (including Coulomb interactions). The distance between two solutions is measured by their relative entropy, which to our knowledge was never used before in stability estimates. The logarithm of the strong solution is required to have polynomial growth while the weak solution can be any H-solution with sufficiently many moments at initial time. Since we require a substantial amount of regularity on the strong solution, we also provide an example of sufficient conditions on the initial data that ensure this regularity in the Coulomb (and very soft potentials) case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21120v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\^ome Tabary</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\Gamma$-convergence of the $p$-Dirichlet energy for manifold-valued maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21257v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove a ${\Gamma}$-convergence result for the $p$-Dirichlet energy functional defined on maps from a smooth bounded domain $\Omega \subseteq \mathbb{R}^{n+k}$ to $\mathscr{N}$, a $(k-2)$-connected and smooth closed Riemannian manifold with Abelian fundamental group, where $n$ and $k$ are integers, $n \geq 0$, $k \geq 2$. We focus on the regime $p \to~k^-$ under Dirichlet boundary conditions. The result provides a description of the asymptotic behavior of the $\textit{topological singular sets}$ for families of $\mathscr{N}$-valued Sobolev maps which satisfy suitable energy bounds. Such topological singular sets are $n$-dimensional flat chains with coefficients in $\pi_{k-1}(\mathscr{N})$ endowed with a suitable norm. As a consequence of our main result, it follows that the topological singular sets of energy minimizing $p$-harmonic maps converge to a $n$-dimensional flat chain $S$ with coefficients in $\pi_{k-1}(\mathscr{N})$ which has finite mass and solves the Plateau problem within the homology class associated to the boundary datum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21257v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giacomo Canevari, Van Phu Cuong Le, Ramon Oliver-Bonafoux, Giandomenico Orlandi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local and nonlocal homogenization of wave propagation in time-varying media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21390v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Temporal metamaterials are artificially manufactured materials with time-dependent material properties that exhibit interesting phenomena when waves propagate through them. The propagation of electromagnetic waves in such time-varying dielectric media is governed by Maxwell's equations, which lead to wave equations with temporal highly oscillatory coefficients for the electric and magnetic fields. In this study, we analyze the effective behavior of electromagnetic fields in time-varying metamaterials using a formal two-scale asymptotic expansion. We provide a mathematical derivation of the effective equations for the leading-order homogenized solution, as well as for the first- and second-order corrections of the effective solution. While the effective solution and the first-order correction are governed by local material laws, we reveal a nonlocal constitutive relation for the second-order corrections. Special attention is also paid to temporal interface conditions through initial values of the homogenized equations. The results provide a mathematically justified framework for the effective description of wave-type equations of time-varying media, applicable to models in optics, elasticity, and acoustics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21390v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian D\"oding, Barbara Verf\"urth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simplicity and boundary behavior of spike sequences for a superlinear problem in plasma physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21402v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that spike sequences related to a nonlinear problem of Grad-Shafranov type are always simple and always converge toward interior points of the domain. This sharpens the blow-up analysis carried out by Bartolucci-Jevnikar-Wu [Calc. Var. 2025] and provides a converse to the existence result for spike sequences obtained by Wei [Proc. Edinb. Math. Soc. 2001].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21402v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Cosentino, Francesco Malizia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Hyperbolic Approximation of the Nonlinear Schr\"odinger Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a first-order hyperbolic approximation of
  the nonlinear Schr\"odinger (NLS) equation. We show that the system
  is strictly hyperbolic and possesses a modified Hamiltonian structure, along with
  at least three conserved quantities that approximate those of NLS.
  We provide families of explicit standing-wave solutions to the hyperbolic system,
  which are shown to converge uniformly to ground-state solutions
  of NLS in the relaxation limit.
  The system is formally equivalent to NLS in the relaxation limit, and we
  develop asymptotic preserving discretizations that tend to a consistent discretization
  of NLS in that limit, while also conserving mass.
  Examples for both the focusing and defocusing regimes demonstrate that the
  numerical discretization provides an accurate approximation of the NLS
  solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21424v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhijit Biswas, Laila S. Busaleh, David I. Ketcheson, Carlos Mu\~noz-Moncayo, Manvendra Rajvanshi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Modulation of Wave Trains in the Ostrovsky Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21466v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the nonlinear wave modulation of arbitrary amplitude periodic traveling wave solutions of the Ostrovsky equation, which arises as a model for the unidirectional propagation of small-amplitude, weakly nonlinear surface and internal gravity waves in a rotating fluid of finite depth. While the modulation of such waves with asymptotically small amplitudes of oscillation (the so-called Stokes waves) has been studied in several works, our goal is to understand the modulational dynamics of general amplitude wave trains. To this end, we first use Whitham's theory of modulations to derive a dispersionless system of quasilinear partial differential equations that is expected to model the slow evolution of the fundamental characteristics of a given wave train. In practice, the modulational stability or instability of a given wave train is considered to be determined by the hyperbolicity or ellipticity, respectively, of the resulting system of Whitham modulation equations. Using rigorous spectral perturbation theory we then study the spectral (linearized) stability problem for a given wave train solution of the Ostrovsky equation, directly connecting the hyperbolicity or ellipticity of the associated Whitham system to the rigorous spectral stability problem for the underlying wave. Specifically, we prove that strict hyperbolicity of the Whitham system implies spectral stability near the origin in the spectral plane, i.e. so-called spectral modulational stability, while ellipticity implies spectral instability of the underlying wave train.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21466v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathew A. Johnson, Jeffrey Oregero, Wesley R. Perkins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Martingale Solutions of Fractional Stochastic Reaction-Diffusion Equations Driven by Superlinear Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.12180v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove the existence of martingale solutions of a class of stochastic equations with pseudo-monotone drift of polynomial growth of arbitrary order and a continuous diffusion term with superlinear growth. Both the nonlinear drift and diffusion terms are not required to be locally Lipschitz continuous. We then apply the abstract result to establish the existence of martingale solutions of the fractional stochastic reaction-diffusion equation with polynomial drift driven by a superlinear noise. The pseudo-monotonicity techniques and the Skorokhod-Jakubowski representation theorem in a topological space are used to pass to the limit of a sequence of approximate solutions defined by the Galerkin method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12180v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bixiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A minimax method for the spectral fractional Laplacian and related evolution problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20560v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a numerical method for the approximation of the inverse of the fractional Laplacian $(-\Delta)^{s}$, based on its spectral definition, using rational functions to approximate the fractional power $A^{-s}$ of a matrix $A$, for $0&lt;s&lt;1$. The proposed numerical method is fast and accurate, benefiting from the fact that the matrix $A$ arises from a finite element approximation of the Laplacian $-\Delta$, which makes it applicable to a wide range of domains with potentially irregular shapes. We make use of state-of-the-art software to compute the best rational approximation of a fractional power. We analyze the convergence rate of our method and validate our findings through a series of numerical experiments with a range of exponents $s \in (0,1)$. Additionally, we apply the proposed numerical method to different evolution problems that involve the fractional Laplacian through an interaction potential: the fractional porous medium equation and the fractional Keller-Segel equation. We then investigate the accuracy of the resulting numerical method, focusing in particular on the accurate reproduction of qualitative properties of the associated analytical solutions to these partial differential equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20560v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e A. Carrillo, Stefano Fronzoni, Yuji Nakatsukasa, Endre S\"uli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controllability of partial differential equations on graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20690v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the boundary control problems for the wave, heat, and Schr\"odinger equations on a finite graph. We suppose that the graph is a tree (i.e., it does not contain cycles), and on each edge an equation is defined. The control is acting through the Dirichlet condition applied to all or all but one boundary vertices. The exact controllability in $L_2$-classes of controls is proved and sharp estimates of the time of controllability are obtained for the wave equation. The null controllability for the heat equation and exact controllability for the Schr\"odinger equation in arbitrary time interval are obtained.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20690v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4064/am35-4-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>S. A. Avdonin, V. S. Mikhaylov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar perturbations to naked singularities of perfect fluid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20766</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20766v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the instability of naked singularities arising in the Einstein equations coupled with isothermal perfect fluid. We show that the spherically symmetric self-similar naked singularities of this system, are unstable to trapped surface formation, under $C^{1,\alpha}$ perturbations of an external massless scalar field. We viewed this as a toy model in studying the instability of these naked singularities under gravitational perturbations in the original Einstein--Euler system which is non-spherically symmetric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20766v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junbin Li, Xi-Ping Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Null-Lagrangians and calibrations for general nonlocal functionals and an application to the viscosity theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11636v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article we build a null-Lagrangian and a calibration for general nonlocal elliptic functionals in the presence of a field of extremals. Thus, our construction assumes the existence of a family of solutions to the Euler-Lagrange equation whose graphs produce a foliation. Then, as a consequence of the calibration, we show the minimality of each leaf in the foliation. Our model case is the energy functional for the fractional Laplacian, for which such a null-Lagrangian was recently discovered by us.
  As a first application of our calibration, we show that monotone solutions to translation invariant nonlocal equations are minimizers. Our second application is somehow surprising, since here ``minimality'' is assumed instead of being concluded. We will see that the foliation framework is broad enough to provide a proof which establishes that minimizers of nonlocal elliptic functionals are viscosity solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11636v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xavier Cabre, I\~nigo U. Erneta, Juan-Carlos Felipe-Navarro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geodesic X-ray transform and streaking artifacts on simple surfaces or on spaces of constant curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.06899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.06899v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The X-ray transform on the plane or on the three-dimensional Euclidean space can be considered as the measurements of CT scanners for normal human tissue. If the human body contains metal regions such as dental implants, stents in blood vessels, metal bones, etc., the beam hardening effect for the energy level of the X-ray causes streaking artifacts in its CT image. More precisely, if there are two strictly convex metal regions contained in the cross-section of normal human tissue, then streaking artifacts occur along the common tangent lines of the two regions. In this paper we study the geodesic X-ray transform and streaking artifacts on nontrapping simple compact Riemannian manifolds with strictly convex boundaries. We show that the streaking artifacts result from the propagation of conormal singularities on the boundary of metal regions along the common tangent geodesics under the strong and seemingly strange assumption that the manifolds are two dimensional or spaces of constant curvature. This condition ensures that every Jacobi field takes the form of the product of a scalar function and parallel transport along the geodesic. Our results clarify the geometric meaning of the theory, which was imperceptible in the known results on the Euclidean space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.06899v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroyuki Chihara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cahn-Hilliard equations with singular potential, reaction term and pure phase initial datum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12113v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider local and nonlocal Cahn-Hilliard equations with constant mobility and singular potentials including, e.g., the Flory-Huggins potential, subject to no-flux (or periodic) boundary conditions. The main goal is to show that the presence of a suitable class of reaction terms allows to establish the existence of a weak solution to the corresponding initial and boundary value problem even though the initial condition is a pure state. In other words, the separation process takes place even in presence of a pure phase, provided that it is triggered by a convenient reaction term. This fact was already observed by the authors in a previous contribution devoted to a specific biological model. In this context, we generalize the previously-mentioned concept by examining the essential assumptions required for the reaction term to apply the new strategy. Also, we explore the scenario involving the nonlocal Cahn-Hilliard equation and provide illustrative examples that contextualize within our abstract framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12113v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maurizio Grasselli, Luca Scarpa, Andrea Signori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global well-posedness of the defocusing, cubic nonlinear wave equation outside of the ball with radial data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05614v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the defocusing, cubic nonlinear wave equation with zero Dirichlet boundary value in the exterior $\Omega = \mathbb{R}^3\backslash \bar{ B}(0,1)$. We make use of the distorted Fourier transform in \cite{LiSZ:NLS, Taylor:PDE:II} to establish the dispersive estimate and the global-in-time (endpoint) Strichartz estimate of the linear wave equation outside of the ball with radial data. As an application, we combine the Fourier truncation method as those in \cite{Bourgain98:FTM, GallPlan03:NLW, KenigPV00:NLW} with the energy method to show global well-posedness of radial solution to the defoucusing, cubic nonlinear wave equation outside of a ball in the Sobolev space $\left(\dot H^{s}_{D}(\Omega) \cap L^4(\Omega) \right)\times \dot H^{s-1}_{D}(\Omega)$ with $s&gt;3/4$. To the best of the author's knowledge, it is first result about low regularity of semilinear wave equation with zero Dirichlet boundary value on the exterior domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05614v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guixiang Xu, Pengxuan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$L^p$ estimates for the Laplacian via blow-up</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05882v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note we provide a new proof of the $W^{2,p}$ Calder\'on-Zygmund regularity estimates for the Laplacian, i.e., $\Delta u=f$ and its parabolic counterpart $\partial_t u-\Delta u=f$. Our proof is an adaptation of a contradiction and compactness argument that so far had been only used to prove estimates in H\"older spaces. This new approach is simpler than previous ones, and avoids the use of any interpolation theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05882v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Lewenstein-Sanpera, Xavier Ros-Oton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong instability of standing waves for $L^2$-supercritical Schr\"odinger-Poisson system with a doping profile</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03991v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper is devoted to the study of the nonlinear Schr\"odinger-Poisson system with a doping profile. We are interested in the strong instability of standing waves associated with ground state solutions in the $L^2$-supercritical case. The presence of a doping profile causes several difficulties, especially in examining geometric shapes of fibering maps along an $L^2$-invariant scaling curve. Furthermore, the classical approach by Berestycki-Cazenave for the strong instability cannot be applied to our problem due to a remainder term caused by the doping profile. To overcome these difficulties, we establish a new energy inequality associated with the $L^2$-invariant scaling and adopt the strong instability result developed by Fukaya-Ohta(2018). When the doping profile is a characteristic function supported on a bounded smooth domain, some geometric quantities related to the domain, such as the mean curvature, are responsible for the strong instability of standing waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03991v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathieu Colin, Tatsuya Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global well-posedness of the defocusing nonlinear wave equation outside of a ball with radial data for $3&lt;p&lt;5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05188v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We continue the study of the Dirichlet boundary value problem of nonlinear wave equation with radial data in the exterior $\Omega = \mathbb{R}^3\backslash \bar{B}(0,1)$. We combine the distorted Fourier truncation method in \cite{Bourgain98:FTM}, the global-in-time (endpoint) Strichartz estimates in \cite{XuYang:NLW} with the energy method in \cite{GallPlan03:NLW} to prove the global well-posedness of the radial solution to the defocusing, energy-subcriticial nonlinear wave equation outside of a ball in $\left(\dot H^{s}_{D}(\Omega) \cap L^{p+1}(\Omega) \right)\times \dot H^{s-1}_{D}(\Omega)$ with $1-\frac{(p+3)(1-s_c)}{4(2p-3)}&lt;s&lt;1$, $s_c=\frac{3}{2}-\frac{2}{p-1} $, which extends the result for the cubic nonlinearity in \cite{XuYang:NLW} to the case $3&lt;p&lt;5$. Except from the argument in \cite{XuYang:NLW}, another new ingredient is that we need make use of the radial Sobolev inequality to deal with the super-conformal nonlinearity in addition to the Sobolev inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05188v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guixiang Xu, Pengxuan Yang, Zhuohui You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limiting absorption principle of Helmholtz equation with sign changing coefficients under periodic structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07229</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07229v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Negative refractive index materials have attracted significant research attention due to their unique electromagnetic response characteristics. In this paper, we employ the complementing boundary condition to establish rigorous a priori estimates for the Helmholtz equation, from which the limiting absorption principle is analytically derived. Within this mathematical framework, we conclusively establish the well-posedness of the electromagnetic transmission problem at the interface between conventional materials and negative refractive index materials in two-dimensional periodic structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07229v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenjing Zhang, Yu Chen, Yixian Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Propagation of coherent states in the logarithmic Schrodinger equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16809v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the logarithmic Schr{\"o}dinger equation in a semiclassical scaling, in the presence of a smooth, at most quadratic, external potential. For initial data under the form of a single coherent state, we identify the notion of criticality as far as the nonlinear coupling constant is concerned, in the semiclassical limit. In the critical case, we prove a general error estimate, and improve it in the case of initial Gaussian profiles. In this critical case, when the initial datum is the sum of two Gaussian coherent states with different centers in phase space, we prove a nonlinear superposition principle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16809v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R\'emi Carles (IRMAR), Fangyuan Dong (Department of Applied Mathematics)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of a nonisothermal and conserved phase field system with inertial term</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13600v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper deals with a conserved phase field system that couples the energy balance equation with a Cahn--Hilliard type system including temperature and the inertial term for the order parameter. In the case without inertial term, the system under study was introduced by Caginalp. The inertial term is motivated by the occurrence of rapid phase transformation processes in nonequilibrium dynamics. A double-well potential is well chosen and the related nonlinearity governing the evolution is assumed to satisfy a suitable growth condition. The viscous variant of the Cahn--Hilliard system is also considered along with the inertial term. The existence of a global solution is proved via the analysis of some approximate problems with Yosida regularizations, and the use of the Cauchy--Lipschitz--Picard theorem in an abstract setting. Moreover, we study the convergence of the system, with or without the viscous term, as the inertial coefficient tends to zero.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13600v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierluigi Colli, Shunsuke Kurima</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on helicity conservation for compressible Euler equations in a bounded domain with vacuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20080v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the helicity conservation of weak solutions for the compressible Euler equations in a bounded domain with general pressure law and vacuum. We deduce a sufficient condition for a weak solution conserving the helicity based on the interior Besov-VMO type regularity, the continuous conditions for velocity and vorticity near the boundary, and some regularities for density near vacuum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20080v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yulin Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Policy Iteration for Exploratory Hamilton--Jacobi--Bellman Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.00612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.00612v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the policy iteration algorithm (PIA) for entropy-regularized stochastic control problems on an infinite time horizon with a large discount rate, focusing on two main scenarios. First, we analyze PIA with bounded coefficients where the controls applied to the diffusion term satisfy a smallness condition. We demonstrate the convergence of PIA based on a uniform $\mathcal{C}^{2,\alpha}$ estimate for the value sequence generated by PIA, and provide a quantitative convergence analysis for this scenario. Second, we investigate PIA with unbounded coefficients but no control over the diffusion term. In this scenario, we first provide the well-posedness of the exploratory Hamilton--Jacobi--Bellman equation with linear growth coefficients and polynomial growth reward function. By such a well-posedess result we achieve PIA's convergence by establishing a quantitative locally uniform $\mathcal{C}^{1,\alpha}$ estimates for the generated value sequence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.00612v4</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hung Vinh Tran, Zhenhua Wang, Yuming Paul Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sobolev and H\"older estimates for the $\overline \partial$ equation on pseudoconvex domains of finite type in $\mathbb C^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07655v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove a homotopy formula which yields almost sharp estimates in all (positive-indexed) Sobolev and H\"older-Zygmund spaces for the $\overline \partial$ equation on pseudoconvex domains of finite type in $\mathbb C^2$, extending the earlier results of Fefferman-Kohn (1988), Range (1990), and Chang-Nagel-Stein (1992). The main novelty of our proof is the construction of holomorphic support functions that admit precise estimates when the parameter variable lies in a thin shell outside the domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07655v3</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziming Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing Optimal Transport Plans via Min-Max Gradient Flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16890v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We pose the Kantorovich optimal transport problem as a min-max problem with a Nash equilibrium that can be obtained dynamically via a two-player game, providing a framework for approximating optimal couplings. We prove convergence of the timescale-separated gradient descent dynamics to the optimal transport plan, and implement the gradient descent algorithm with a particle method, where the marginal constraints are enforced weakly using the KL divergence, automatically selecting a dynamical adaptation of the regularizer. The numerical results highlight the different advantages of using the standard Kullback-Leibler (KL) divergence versus the reverse KL divergence with this approach, opening the door for new methodologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16890v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lauren Conger, Franca Hoffmann, Ricardo Baptista, Eric Mazumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weyl laws for exponentially small singular values of the $\overline{\partial}$ operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07292v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the number of exponentially small singular values of the semiclassical $\overline{\partial}$ operator on exponentially weighted $L^2$ spaces on the two-dimensional torus. Accurate upper and lower bounds on the number of such singular values are established with the help of auxiliary notions of upper and lower bound weights. Assuming that the Laplacian of the exponential weight changes sign along a curve, we construct optimal such weights by solving a free boundary problem, which yields a Weyl asymptotics for the counting function of the singular values in an interval of the form $[0,\mathrm{e}^{-\tau/h}]$, for $\tau&gt;0$ smaller than the oscillation of the weight. We also provide a precise description of the leading term in the Weyl asymptotics, in the regime of small $\tau &gt; 0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07292v2</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Hitrik, Johannes Sj\"ostrand, Martin Vogel</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
