<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 05:00:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Weak--strong uniqueness for bi-fluid compressible system with algebraic closure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15970v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a real two-fluid system of compressible viscous fluids with a common velocity field and algebraic closure for the pressure law. The constitutive relation involves densities of both fluids through an implicit function. The existence of global-in-time finite energy weak solutions to this system is known since the work of Novotn\'{y} and Pokorn\'{y} [Arch. Rational Mech. Anal., 2020]. On the other hand, existence of local-in-time strong solutions is due to Piasecki and Zatorska [J. Math Fluid Mech.,, 2022]. In this paper, we establish the weak--strong uniqueness principle using the relative entropy method. In sharp contrast to the two-phase model of Baer-Nunziato type, the volume fraction of phase $+$ obeys a transport equation with an additional nonlinear term. This gives rise to troublesome terms in the relative entropy inequality. We are able to close the estimate by making an elaborate use of the structure of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15970v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Li, M\'aria Luk\'a\v{c}ov\'a-Medvid'ov\'a, Milan Pokorn\'y, Ewelina Zatorska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The lingering phenomenon and pattern formation in a nonlocal population model with cognitive map</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16022v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rates at which individuals memorize and forget environmental information strongly influence their movement paths and long-term space use. To understand how these cognitive time scales shape population-level patterns, we propose and analyze a nonlocal population model with a cognitive map. The population density moves by a Fokker--Planck type diffusion driven by a cognitive map that stores a habitat quality information nonlocally. The map is updated through local presence with learning and forgetting rates, and we consider both truncated and normalized perception kernels.
  We first study the movement-only system without growth. We show that finite perceptual range generates spatial heterogeneity in the cognitive map even in nearly homogeneous habitats, and we prove a lingering phenomenon on unimodal landscapes: for the fixed high learning rate, the peak density near the best location is maximized at an intermediate forgetting rate.
  We then couple cognitive diffusion to logistic growth. We establish local well-posedness and persistence by proving instability of the extinction equilibrium and the existence of a positive steady state, with uniqueness under an explicit condition on the motility function. Numerical simulations show that lingering persists under logistic growth and reveal a trade-off between the lingering and total population size, since near the strongest-lingering regime the total mass can fall below the total resource, in contrast to classical random diffusive--logistic models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16022v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyung-Han Choi, Thomas Hillen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative Landis-type result for Dirac operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16049v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study quantitative unique continuation at infinity for Dirac equations with bounded matrix-valued potentials. For the massless Dirac operator $\mathcal{D}_n$ in $\mathbb{R}^n$, we establish a Landis-type estimate showing that the vanishing order of any nontrivial bounded solution of $( \mathcal{D}_n + \mathbb{V} ) \varphi = 0$ satisfies a lower bound of order $\exp(-\kappa R^{2} (\log R)^{2})$ as $|x|=R\to \infty$; the quadratic growth in the exponent is sharp, in view of previous known results. Our proof follows a Bourgain--Kenig type approach based on a Carleman inequality for Dirac operators which relies on a local H\"older regularity result, which we also prove. In two dimension, we obtain improved quantitative estimates under symmetry assumptions on the potential $\mathbb{V}$ and for real-valued solutions. Finally, we also derive qualitative Landis-type results for Dirac equations with decaying potentials, including critical decay rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16049v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ujjal Das, Luca Fanelli, Luz Roncal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An intrinsic expansion approach to the Galerkin approximations for the Navier-Stokes equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16064v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the Galerkin approximation of the three-dimensional Navier-Stokes equations. In particular, we examine the convergence of these solutions in a sequence of finite dimensional spaces as the dimension goes to infinity. For any sequence of steady state or, respectively, time dependent Galerkin solutions that converges to a solution of the Navier-Stokes equations, we obtain a subsequence with an intrinsic asymptotic expansion in appropriate nested function spaces. Consequently, an induced asymptotic expansion is obtained in a more standard spatial Sobolev or, respectively, spatiotemporal Sobolev-Lebesgue space. In the case of steady states, we establish certain relations among leading terms of this expansion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16064v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luan Hoang, Michael S. Jolly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation with combined nonlinearities in 1D</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16122v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the one-dimensional nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation $$ iu_t + u_{xx} + \mathcal{N}(u)u=0, \quad x,t \in \mathbb R, $$ with the nonlinearity term that is expressed as a sum of powers, possibly infinite: $$ \mathcal{N}(u) = \sum d_k |u|^{\alpha_k}, \quad \alpha_k &gt; 0. $$
  We first investigate the local well-posedness of this equation for any positive powers of $\alpha_k$ in a certain weighted class of initial data, subset of $H^1 (\mathbb R)$. For that we use an approach of Cazenave-Naumkin [19], thus, avoiding any Strichartz estimates. Then, using the pseudo-conformal transformation, we extend the local result to the global one for the initial data with a quadratic phase. Furthermore, we investigate the asymptotic behavior of such global solutions and prove scattering for data with the quadratic phase $e^{ib|x|^2}$ with sufficiently large positive $b$, in $H^1(\mathbb R)$. One of the advantages of considering an infinite sum in the nonlinearity term is being able to consider exponential nonlinearities, such as $e^{\gamma |u|^{k}} u$, as well as sine or cosine nonlinearities, and obtain well-posedness in those cases, the first such result for most of those nonlinearities.
  To conclude, we show numerical simulations for various examples of combined nonlinearities, including the double nonlinearity and an exponential one, then investigate the behavior of solutions with positive or negative initial $b$ in a quadratic phase data. Furthermore, we also show that a ground state in the NLS equation with combined nonlinearities no longer provides a sharp threshold for global behavior such as scattering vs. finite time blow-up, instead the equation has a much richer dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16122v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oscar Ria\~no, Alex D Rodriguez, Svetlana Roudenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global dynamic stability of contact lines in fluids: 2-D droplet problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16164v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the dynamics of an incompressible viscous Navier-Stokes fluid evolving above a one-dimensional flat surface. The fluid is subject to a uniform gravitational field and capillary forces acting along the free boundary. The interface between the fluid and the surrounding air is a free surface whose motion is driven by gravity, surface tension, and the fluid velocity field. The triple-phase intersections where the fluid, the air above the vessel, and the solid vessel wall meet are referred to as contact points, and the angles formed there are called contact angles. The model under consideration incorporates boundary conditions that allow for full motion of the contact points and dynamic contact angles. Under these conditions, \cite{Yang} established the existence of equilibrium configurations for the model. These equilibria consist of a quiescent fluid occupying a domain whose upper boundary can be represented as the graph of a function in polar coordinates, minimizing a gravity-capillary energy functional subject to a fixed mass constraint. The equilibrium contact angles may take any value in $(0,\pi)$ depending on the choice of capillary parameters. In the present work, we develop a framework of a priori estimates for this model. We prove that, for initial data sufficiently close to equilibrium, the system admits global solutions that converge exponentially fast to a (horizontally) shifted equilibrium state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16164v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoding Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concentration Phenomena for $(p,N)$-Laplace Equation Under Discontinuous Nonlinearities and Penalization Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16254v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the existence and concentration of solutions to a $(p,N)$-Laplace equation in $\mathbb{R}^N$ involving a discontinuous nonlinearity and critical exponential growth. To establish the existence of solutions, we employ a penalization technique in the sense of Del Pino and Felmer adapted to a locally Lipschitz functional. Furthermore, by combining variational methods with Moser-type iteration techniques, we obtain the concentration behavior of the solutions. Our results contribute to the study of nonlinear elliptic problems with irregular nonlinearities and critical growth phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16254v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Ankit, Giovany M. Figueiredo, Abhishek Sarkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence and nonexistence of normalized solutions for nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger equation involving combined nonlinearities in bounded domain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16263v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the existence, multiplicity and nonexistence of solutions for the following equation \begin{equation*} \begin{cases} \begin{aligned} &amp;-\Delta u+\omega u=\mu u^{p-1}+u^{q-1},~ u&gt;0 \quad &amp;&amp;\text { in } \Omega, \\ &amp;u=0 &amp;&amp;\text { on } \partial\Omega, \\ \end{aligned} \end{cases} \end{equation*} with prescribed $L^2$-norm $\|u\|_2^2=\rho$, where $N\ge 1$, $\rho&gt;0$, $\mu\in \mathbb{R}$, $1&lt;p\le q$, and $\Omega\subset\mathbb{R}^N$ is a bounded smooth domain. The parameter $\omega\in\mathbb{R}$ arises as a Lagrange multiplier. Firstly, when $2&lt;p\le q\le \frac{2N}{(N-2)^+}$ and $\rho$ is small, we establish the existence of a local minimizer of energy. Furthermore, when $\mu\ge 0$ and $\Omega$ is a star-shaped domain, using the monotonicity trick and the Pohozaev identity, we show that there exists a second solution which is of mountain pass type. Secondly, when $\mu\ge 0$, $N\ge 3$, $1&lt;p\le 2$, $q\ge \max\left\{\frac{2N}{N-2}, 3\right\}$ and $\Omega$ is a convex domain, using the moving-plane method, we prove the nonexistence of normalized solutions for large $\rho$. Finally, when $\mu=0$, $N\ge 3$, $q=\frac{2N}{N-2}$ and $\Omega$ is a ball, we give a dichotomy result of normalized solutions for the Br\'{e}zis-Nirenberg problem by continuation arguments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16263v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen-Feng Jin, Weimin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical thresholds for semilinear damped wave equations with Riesz potential power nonlinearity and initial data in pseudo-measure spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16293v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, our primary objective is to establish the time decay properties of solutions $u(t, x)$ with initial data $u_0, u_1 \in \mathcal{Y}^q$ (pseudo-measure spaces) to the linear damped wave equation in the spaces $L^2\left(\mathbb{R}^n\right)$ and $\dot{H}^s\left(\mathbb{R}^n\right)$ (for $s \leq 0$ or $s \geq 0$). Our subsequent aim is to investigate the semilinear damped wave equation with a Riesz potential-type power nonlinearity $\mathcal{I}_\gamma\left(|u|^p\right)$, where $\gamma \in [0, n)$, and initial data belonging to pseudo-measure spaces $\mathcal{Y}^q$. In addition, we derive a new critical exponent $p=p_{\mathrm{crit}}(n, q, \gamma):=1+\frac{2+\gamma}{n-q}$ for some $q \in\left(0, \frac{n}{2}\right)$ and in low spatial dimensions, within the framework of pseudo-measure spaces $\mathcal{Y}^q$. Specifically, we prove the global (in time) existence of small-data Sobolev solutions with low regularity when $p \geq p_{\mathrm{crit}}(n, q, \gamma)$, and the finite-time blow-up of weak solutions, even for small initial data, whenever $1&lt; p&lt;p_{\mathrm{crit}}(n, q, \gamma)$. Moreover, in order to characterize the blow-up time more precisely, we establish sharp upper and lower bound estimates for the lifespan of solutions in the subcritical regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16293v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tang Trung Loc, Duong Dinh Van, Phan Duc An</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large-Time Asymptotics for Heat and Fractional Heat Equations on the Lattice and General Finite Subgraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16339v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study large-time asymptotics for heat and fractional heat equations in two discrete settings: the full lattice \(\mathbb Z^d\) and finite connected subgraphs with Dirichlet boundary condition. These results provide a unified discrete theory of long-time asymptotics for local and nonlocal diffusions.
  For \(d\ge1\) and \(s\in(0,1]\), we consider on \(\mathbb Z^d\) the Cauchy problem \[ \partial_t u+(-\Delta)^s u=0,\qquad u(0)=u_0\in \ell^1(\mathbb Z^d), \] and derive a precise first-order asymptotic expansion toward the lattice fractional heat kernel \(G_t^{(s)}\). The main technical input is a pair of sharp translation-increment bounds for \(G_t^{(s)}\): a pointwise estimate and an \(\ell^1\)-estimate. As consequences, under finite first moment we obtain the optimal decay rate \(t^{-1/(2s)}\) in \(\ell^p\)-asymptotics (\(1\le p\le\infty\)), and we prove sharpness by explicit shifted-kernel examples. Without moment assumptions, we still establish convergence in the full \(\ell^1\)-class, and we show that no universal quantitative rate can hold in general.
  We also analyze fractional Dirichlet diffusion on finite connected subgraphs (restricted fractional setting, including \(s=1\) as the local case). In this finite-dimensional framework, solutions admit spectral decomposition and exhibit exponential large-time behavior governed by the principal eigenvalue and the spectral gap. In addition, we study positivity improving properties of the associated semigroups for both the lattice and Dirichlet evolutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16339v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rui Chen, Bo Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heat Equation driven by mixed local-nonlocal operators with non-regular space-dependent coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16348v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the Cauchy problem for a heat equation governed by a mixed local--nonlocal diffusion operator with spatially irregular coefficients. We first establish classical well-posedness in an energy framework for bounded, measurable coefficients that satisfy uniform positivity, and we derive an a priori estimate ensuring uniqueness and continuous dependence on the initial data. We then extend the notion of solution to distributional coefficients and initial data by a Friedrichs-type regularisation procedure. Within this very weak framework, we establish the existence and uniqueness of solution nets and prove consistency with the classical weak solution whenever the coefficients are regular.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16348v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arshyn Altybay, Michael Ruzhansky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Gevrey Hypoellipticity of Involutive Systems on Non-Compact Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16366v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the global Gevrey hypoellipticity of a class of first-order differential operators associated with tube-type involutive structures on $M\times\mathbb{T}^m$, where $M$ is a non-compact manifold diffeomorphic to the interior of a compact manifold with boundary and $\mathbb{T}^m$ is the $m$-dimensional torus. For $s&gt;1$, we work in Gevrey classes of Roumieu and Beurling type. A key step is the construction, on $M$, of a scattering metric whose coefficients are Gevrey of order $s$ in every analytic chart; this allows us to use Hodge theory and obtain Gevrey regularity for the harmonic forms. Under a natural condition on the defining closed $1$-forms, we obtain a sharp criterion for global Gevrey hypoellipticity in terms of rationality and (Roumieu/Beurling) exponential Liouville behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16366v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sandro Coriasco, Alexandre Kirilov, Wagner Augusto Almeida de Moraes, Pedro Meyer Tokoro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A remark on staircase laminates in restricted sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16407v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We slightly extend the convex integration via staircase laminate toolbox recently developed by Kleiner, M\"uller, Sz\'{e}kelyhidi, and Xie. As an example we revisit the proof by Astala-Faraco-Sz\'{e}kelyhidi on optimal Meyers' regularity theory via this framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16407v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Buchowiec, Pholphum Kamthorntaksina, Katarzyna Mazowiecka, Armin Schikorra, Akshara Vincent</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiscale Hyperbolic-Parabolic Models for Nonlinear Reactive Transport in Heterogeneously Fractured Porous Media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16439v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study nonlinear reactive transport in a layered porous medium separated by an $\varepsilon$-thin, highly heterogeneous fracture whose aperture and obstacle pattern vary periodically. Species transport in the bulk is governed by parabolic reaction--diffusion equations, coupled to a convection-diffusion-reaction problem in the fracture with nonlinear wall and obstacle reactions and Peclet number of order $O(\varepsilon^{-1})$. Via multiscale analysis as $\varepsilon \to 0$, when the fracture collapses to a flat interface, we derive a new type of homogenized model consisting of bulk diffusion--reaction equations coupled through nonlinear interface conditions and a first-order semilinear hyperbolic system on the interface. We prove well-posedness and regularity of the limit system, construct a multiscale approximation with boundary-layer correctors, and derive quantitative error estimates in suitable energy norms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16439v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taras Mel'nyk, Sorin Pop, Christian Rohde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the uniqueness and structural stability of Couette-Poiseuille flow in a channel for arbitrary values of the flux</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16460v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish uniqueness and structural stability of a class of parallel flows in a 2D straight, infinite channel, under perturbations with either globally or locally bounded Dirichlet integrals. The significant feature of our result is that it does not require any restriction on the size of the flux characterizing the flow. Precisely, by extending and refining an approach initially introduced by J.B. McLeod, we demonstrate the continuous invertibility of the linearized operator at a generic Couette-Poiseuille solution that does not exhibit flow reversal. We then deduce local uniqueness of these solutions as well as their nonlinear structural stability under small external forces. Moreover, we prove the uniqueness of certain class of Couette-Poiseuille solutions ``in the large," within the set of solutions possessing natural symmetry. Finally, we bring an example showing that, in general, if the flow reversal assumption is violated, the linearized operator is no longer invertible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16460v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni P. Galdi, Filippo Gazzola, Mikhail V. Korobkov, Xiao Ren, Gianmarco Sperone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularity and Pathwise bounds for probabilistic solutions of PDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16478v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we build a procedure that allows to establish regularity and controls in time for probabilistic solutions to PDEs. Probabilistic approaches to global wellposedness problems usually provide ensemble bounds on the solutions. These bounds are the main tools to ensure convergence procedures yielding the existence and uniqueness of global solutions. A question of interest consists in transforming such ensemble bounds into individual controls on the flow ; this, among other uses, gives valuable information on the long-time behavior of the solutions. Toward such question of bounds transformation, Bourgain initiated a successful procedure that exploited the local wellposedness of the PDE, with an estimate of the time of size-doubling. In this note, we construct an estimation procedure which relies on a different local requirement. It turns out that this substitute is flexible enough to be possible to fulfill with the help of the ensemble bound itself. For applications of the procedure, we are able to provide new pathwise controls on solutions to NLS equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16478v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mouhamadou Sy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fully sign-changing Nehari constraint vs sign-changing solutions of a competitive Schr\"{o}dinger system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16506v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a competitive nonlinear Schr\"odinger system in $\mathbb{R}^N$ whose nonlinear potential is localized in small regions that shrink to isolated points. Within a variational framework based on a fully sign-changing Nehari constraint and Krasnosel'skii genus, we construct, for all $\varepsilon&gt;0$, a sequence of sign-changing solutions with increasing and unbounded energies, and after suitable translations they converge to a sequence of sign-changing solutions of the associated limiting system as $\varepsilon\to 0$ in $H^1$-norm. Moreover, these sign-changing solutions concentrate around the prescribed attraction points both in $H^1$-norm and $L^q$-norm for $q\in [1,\infty]$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16506v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuejiao Fu, Fukun Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Schr\"odinger equations with a critical, inverse-square potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16524v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the existence of solutions of the following nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation $$ -\Delta u+V(x)u-\frac{(N-2)^2}{4|x|^2}u=f(x,u) $$ where $V:\mathbb{R}^N\to\mathbb{R}$ and $f:\mathbb{R}^N\times \mathbb{R}\to \mathbb{R}$ are periodic with respect to $x\in\mathbb{R}^N.$ We assume that $V$ has positive essential infimum, $f$ satisfies weak growth conditions and $N\geq 3$. The approach to the problem uses variational methods with nonstandard functional setting. We obtain the existence of the ground state solution using the new profile decomposition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16524v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bartosz Bieganowski, Adam Konysz, Simone Secchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well-posedness and stability of the self-similar profile for a thin-film equation with gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16549v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the thin-film equation with linear mobility and a stabilizing second-order porous-medium type term modeling gravity. The model admits self-similar solutions, and our goal is to analyze their stability. We reformulate the problem in mass-Lagrangian coordinates and exploit the underlying gradient-flow structure of the equation with respect to a weighted $L^2$ inner product, where the weight is given by the self-similar source-type profile. This framework allows us to establish a coercivity result for the Hessian (the linearization around the self-similar solution) in a suitably weighted inner product. As a consequence, we prove the convergence of perturbations toward the self-similar profile at an algebraic rate of order $t^{-\frac 1 5}$, in arbitrary scales of weighted Sobolev norms. The analysis relies on maximal-regularity estimates for the linearized evolution, combined with appropriate estimates for the nonlinear terms.
  Notably, beyond perturbative regimes and in contrast to previous results for the thin-film equation (convergence to the Smyth-Hill profile) or the porous-medium equation (convergence to the Barenblatt-Pattle solution), our analysis does not rely on an explicit (algebraic) representation of the self-similar profile. Instead, it is based solely on a systematic use of the ordinary differential equation satisfied by the self-similar solution, together with a careful analysis of its boundary asymptotics. As a result, we expect that the approach developed here can serve as a flexible toolbox for the study of more general classes of equations and for the stability analysis of special solutions in future work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16549v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel V. Gnann, Slim Ibrahim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry properties for positive solutions of mixed boundary value problems in a sub-spherical sector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16630v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the symmetry properties of positive solutions $u$ to a semilinear elliptic equation under mixed Dirichlet-Neumann boundary conditions in symmetric domains. First, we establish a maximum principle tailored to mixed-boundary problems in domains of either small volume or narrow width, thereby enabling the application of the moving plane method. Secondly, in contrast to the purely Dirichlet case, a key challenge is to establish the non-vanishing of the tangential derivative of $u$ along the Neumann boundary. To address this, we employ local analysis techniques of angular derivatives, as introduced by Hartman and Wintner [Amer. J. Math., 1953]. Thirdly, we identify the signs of directional derivatives of $u$ along sections of the moving line. Using a planar sub-spherical sector as an example, we illustrate how these new innovative techniques and the moving plane method can be combined to derive symmetry and monotonicity results, particularly when the amplitude is less than or equal to $2\pi/3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16630v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruofei Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical paraproducts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16644v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We outline an extension of paraproduct decompositions for compositions of the form $A(f)$ where $A \in C^{d}(\mathbb{R}), f \in \Lambda_{\alpha}([0,1]^d)$ developed in [arXiv:2503.12629] and [arXiv:2508.13322] to settings where $(A \in C^1(\mathbb{R}),f \in \Lambda_{\alpha}(X))$ and $ (A \in C^2(\mathbb{R}),f \in \Lambda_{\alpha}(X \times Y))$. To do so, we construct partition trees on $X$ and $X \times Y$ such that analysis with respect to scale is sensible. We obtain results resembling those of [arXiv:2503.12629] and [arXiv:2508.13322], but with the finite sets $X$ and $X \times Y $ as support. In particular we construct the paraproduct $\Pi_{A',A''}^{L,S}: f \to \tilde{A}_{L,S}(f) + \Delta_{L,S}(A,f)$ such that $\Delta_{L,S}(A,f) \in \Lambda_{2\alpha}(X \times Y)$ and $\lVert \Delta_{L,S}(A,f) \rVert_{\Lambda_{2\alpha}(X \times Y)} \leq C_A \lVert f \rVert_{\Lambda_{\alpha}(X \times Y)}$. Analogous results are obtained when the support is just one finite set, $X$. This extension is motivated by situations where one wishes to separate the singular and smooth components of such compositions in graph signal processing environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16644v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oluwadamilola Fasina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Calabi--Yau Conjectures for Minimal Hypersurfaces in Higher Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16048v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the Calabi--Yau conjectures for complete minimal hypersurfaces $\Sigma^{n}\subset \mathbb{R}^{n+1}$ in dimensions $n\ge 3$. These conjectures ask whether a complete minimal hypersurface must be unbounded, and more strongly, whether it must be proper. For the unboundedness question, we prove a chord--arc estimate for an embedded minimal disk with bounded curvature, showing that intrinsic distance is controlled by a polynomial of the extrinsic distance. On the other hand, using gluing techniques, we construct a complete, improperly embedded minimal hypersurface in $\mathbb{R}^{n+1}$ for every $n\ge 3$. This example shows that the properness conjecture suggested by the deep work of Colding Minicozzi [CM08] in the case $n=2$ fails in higher dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16048v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shrey Aryan, Alexander McWeeney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Lorentzian Equivariant Index Theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16547</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16547v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a formula for the equivariant index of a twisted Dirac operator on a compact globally hyperbolic spacetime with timelike boundary on which a group acts isometrically, subject to APS boundary conditions. The formula is the same as in the Riemannian case: the equivariant index for a group element is an integral over the fixed point set of that element plus some boundary terms. The proof uses a surprisingly simple technique for reducing from the equivariant to the non-equivariant regime in order to show an equivariant version of the Lorentzian "index $=$ spectral flow" formula.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16547v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Onirban Islam, Lennart Ronge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Optimization Techniques for Multi-State Optimal Design Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16592v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper addresses optimal design problems governed by multi-state stationary diffusion equations, aiming at the simultaneous optimization of the domain shape and the distribution of two isotropic materials in prescribed proportions. Existence of generalized solutions is established via a hybrid approach combining homogenization-based relaxation in the interior with suitable restrictions on admissible domains.
  Based on this framework, we propose a numerical method that integrates homogenization and shape optimization. The domain boundary is evolved using a level set method driven by the shape derivative, while the interior material distribution is updated via an optimality criteria algorithm. The approach is demonstrated on a representative example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16592v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marko Erceg, Petar Kun\v{s}tek, Marko Vrdoljak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-mode dominance and deterministic parameter bias bounds for equatorial Kerr-de Sitter ringdown</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16691v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study scalar waves on subextremal Kerr-de Sitter spacetimes in a compact slow-rotation regime and at a fixed overtone index. Working initially at a fixed cosmological constant $\Lambda&gt;0$ and uniformly for $(M,a)$ in a compact slow-rotation set, using the meromorphic/Fredholm framework for quasinormal modes and a semiclassical equatorial labeling proved in a companion paper, we establish a quantitative two-mode dominance theorem in an equatorial high-frequency package: after exact azimuthal reduction, microlocal equatorial localization, and analytic pole selection by entire localization weights constructed from equatorial pseudopoles, the $k=\pm\ell$ sector signals are each governed by a single quasinormal exponential, up to an explicitly controlled tail and an $\mathcal O(\ell^{-\infty})$ contribution from all other poles. We then develop a fully deterministic frequency-extraction stability estimate based on time-shift invariance, and combine it with the two-mode dominance result and the companion paper's inverse stability theorem to obtain an explicit parameter bias bound for ringdown-based recovery of $(M,a)$. Finally, using the companion paper's three-parameter inverse theorem and a damping observable based on the scaled imaginary part of one equatorial mode, we propagate the same deterministic error chain to a local bias bound for recovery of $(M,a,\Lambda)$ on compact parameter sets with $|a|$ bounded away from $0$. As a further consequence, we obtain a localized pseudospectral stability statement for the equatorial resolvent package, quantifying how large microlocalized resolvent norms enforce proximity to the labeled equatorial poles. The resulting estimates clarify the conditioning mechanisms (start time, window length, shift step, and detector nondegeneracy) and provide a rigorous PDE-to-data interface for high-frequency black-hole spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16691v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruiliang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wrinkling of an elastic sheet floating on a liquid sphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.15504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.15504v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A thin circular elastic sheet floating on a drop-like liquid substrate is deformed due to incompatibility between the curved substrate and the planar sheet. We adopt a variational viewpoint by minimizing the non-convex membrane energy together with a higher-order convex bending energy. Focusing on thin sheets, we expand the minimum of the energy in terms of a small thickness ratio $h$, and identify the first two terms of this expansion. The leading-order term arises from the minimization of a family of one-dimensional relaxed problems, while for the next-order term we establish lower and upper bounds. This generalizes the previous work [P. Bella and R.V. Kohn. Wrikling of a thin circular sheet bonded to a spherical substrate, Philos. Trans. Roy. Soc. A, 375(2017). arXiv:1611.01781] to the physically relevant case of a liquid substrate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.15504v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Bella, Carlos Rom\'an</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A continuation criterion for the Landau equation with very soft and Coulomb potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.15690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.15690v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the spatially inhomogeneous Landau equation in the case of very soft and Coulomb potentials, $\gamma \in [-3,-2]$. We show that solutions can be continued as long as the following three quantities remain finite, uniformly in $t$ and $x$: (1) the mass density, (2) the velocity moment of order $s$ for any small $s&gt;0$, and (3) the $L^p_v$ norm for any $p&gt;3/(5+\gamma)$. In particular, we do not require a bound on the energy density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.15690v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stanley Snelson, Caleb Solomon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Geometric properties of free boundaries in degenerate quenching problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.11536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.11536v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study minimizers of non-differentiable functionals modeled on the degenerate quenching problem. Our main result establishes the finiteness of the $(n-1)-$dimensional Hausdorff measure of the free boundary. The proof is based on optimal gradient decay estimates obtained from an intrinsic Harnack-type inequality, along with a detailed analysis in a flatness regime, where minimizers enjoy improved regularity. Our arguments provide an alternative proof of classical results of Phillips and, although developed in the degenerate setting, also offer insights relevant to the singular case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.11536v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dami\~ao J. Ara\'ujo, Rafayel Teymurazyan, Jos\'e Miguel Urbano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rigorous derivation of damped-driven wave turbulence theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10711v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide a rigorous justification of various kinetic regimes exhibited by the nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger equation with an additive stochastic forcing and a viscous dissipation. The importance of such damped-driven models stems from their wide empirical use in studying turbulence for nonlinear wave systems. The force injects energy into the system at large scales, which is then transferred across scales, thanks to the nonlinear wave interactions, until it is eventually dissipated at smaller scales. The presence of such scale-separated forcing and dissipation allows for the constant flux of energy in the intermediate scales, known as the inertial range, which is the focus of the vast amount of numerical and physical literature on wave turbulence.
  Roughly speaking, our results provide a rigorous kinetic framework for this turbulent behavior by proving that the stochastic dynamics can be effectively described by a deterministic damped-driven kinetic equation, which carries the full picture of the turbulent energy dynamic across scales (like cascade spectra or other flux solutions). The analysis extends previous works in the unperturbed setting arXiv:1912.09518-arXiv:2301.07063 to the above empirically motivated damped driven setting. Here, in addition to the size $L$ of the system, and the strength $\lambda$ of the nonlinearity, an extra thermodynamic parameter has to be included in the kinetic limit ($L\to \infty, \lambda\to 0$), namely the strength $\nu$ of the forcing and dissipation. Various regimes emerge depending on the relative sizes of $L$, $\lambda$ and $\nu$, which give rise to different kinetic equations. Two major novelties of this work is the extension of the Feynman diagram analysis to additive stochastic objects, and the sharp asymptotic development of the leading terms in that expansion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10711v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ricardo Grande, Zaher Hani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global well-posedness and relaxation for solutions of the Fokker-Planck-Alignment equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20294v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we prove global existence of weak solutions, their regularization, and relaxation for large data for a broad class of Fokker-Planck-Alignment models which appear in collective dynamics. The main feature of these results, as opposed to previously known ones, is the lack of regularity or no-vacuum requirements on the initial data. With a particular application to the classical kinetic Cucker-Smale model, we demonstrate that any bounded data with finite higher moment, $f_0 \in L^1(1+ |v|^q) \cap L^\infty$, $q \geq n+4$, gives rise to a global instantly smooth solution, satisfying entropy equality and relaxing exponentially fast.
  The results are achieved through the use of a new thickness-based renormalization procedure, which circumvents the problem of degenerate diffusion in non-perturbative regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20294v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Shvydkoy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homogenization for the nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation with sprinkled nonlinearity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00589v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We first prove homogenization for the nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation with sprinkled nonlinearity introduced in [19]. We then investigate how solutions fluctuate about the homogenized solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00589v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Harrop-Griffiths, Maria Ntekoume</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H\"older continuous dissipative solutions of ideal MHD with nonzero helicity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23749v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove the existence of weak solutions to the 3D ideal MHD equations, of class $C^\alpha$ with $\alpha=1/200$, for which the total energy and the cross helicity (i.e., the so-called Els\"asser energies) are not conserved. The solutions do not possess any symmetry properties and the magnetic helicity, which is necessarily conserved for H\"older continuous solutions, is nonzero. The construction, which works both on the torus $\mathbb{T}^3$ and on $\mathbb{R}^3$ with compact spatial support, is based on a novel convex integration scheme in which the magnetic helicity is preserved at each step. This is the first construction of continuous weak solutions at a regularity level where one conservation law (here, the magnetic helicity) is necessarily preserved while another (here, the total energy or cross helicity) is not, and where the preservation of the former is nontrivial in the sense that it does not follow from symmetry considerations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23749v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Enciso, Javier Pe\~nafiel-Tom\'as, Daniel Peralta-Salas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>D-tensor paraproducts and its caricatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13322v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We generalize the $2$-tensor paraproduct decomposition result of [arXiv:2503.12629] to $d$-tensors. In particular, we show that for $A \in C^{d}(\mathbb{R}), f \in \Lambda_{\alpha}([0,1]^d)$, $A(f)$ can be approximated by $\tilde{A}_{(N_i)_{i=0}^d}(f) = (\sum_{\beta=1}^d A^{\beta}(P^{j_1,j_2, \ldots, j_d}(f)) \tilde{\mathbf{v}}^{\beta}(f) ) $ with the residual $\Delta_{(N_i)_{i=1}^d}(A,f) = \tilde{A}_{(N_i)_{i=1}^d}(f) - A(f) \in \Lambda_{2\alpha}([0,1]^d)$. Our theoretical findings are supported by a computational example for d=3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13322v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oluwadamilola Fasina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a class of thin obstacle-type problems for the bi-Laplacian operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.11372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.11372v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the regularity of solutions and structural properties of the free boundary for a class of fourth-order elliptic problems with Neumann-type boundary conditions. The singular and degenerate elliptic operators studied naturally emerge from the extension procedure for higher-order fractional powers of the Laplacian, while the choice of non-linearity considered encompasses two-phase boundary obstacle problems as a special case. After establishing local regularity properties of solutions, Almgren- and Monneau-type monotonicity formulas are derived and utilized to carry out a blow-up analysis and prove a stratification result for the free boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.11372v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donatella Danielli, Giovanni Gravina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rothe's method in direct and time-dependent inverse source problems for a semilinear pseudo-parabolic equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20642v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the inverse problem of determining an unknown time-dependent source term in a semilinear pseudo-parabolic equation with variable coefficients and a Dirichlet boundary condition. The unknown source term is recovered from additional measurement data expressed as a weighted spatial average of the solution. By employing Rothe's time-discretisation method, we prove the existence and uniqueness of a weak solution under a smallness condition on the problem data. We also provide a numerical scheme based on a perturbation approach, which reduces the solution of the resulting discrete problem to solving two standard variational problems and evaluating a scalar coefficient, and we demonstrate its accuracy and stability through numerical experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20642v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karel Van Bockstal, Khonatbek Khompysh, Arshyn Altybay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upper bounds for Courant-sharp Neumann and Robin eigenvalues</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1810.09950</link>
      <description>arXiv:1810.09950v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the eigenvalues of the Laplacian on an open, bounded, connected set in $\mathbb{R}^n$ with $C^2$ boundary, with a Neumann boundary condition or a Robin boundary condition. We obtain upper bounds for those eigenvalues that have a corresponding eigenfunction which achieves equality in Courant's Nodal Domain theorem. In the case where the set is also assumed to be convex, we obtain explicit upper bounds in terms of some of the geometric quantities of the set.
  Corrigendum. A previous version of this work was accepted and published by the "Bulletin de la Soci\'et\'e Math\'ematique de France" (see [2] in the bibliography of Appendix B). It contained a gap: the classical (Euclidean) Faber-Krahn inequality was applied in a setting where it might not hold. This version reproduces the previous one with the addition of a corrigendum in Appendix B that addresses the issue. All the results in Sections 2--8 and most of those in Section 9 are thus preserved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1810.09950v3</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katie Gittins, Corentin L\'ena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$L_p$ estimates in the Androulidakis-Mohsen-Yuncken calculus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13701v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that order zero operators in the pseudodifferential calculus associated to a filtration defined by Androulidakis, Mohsen and Yuncken are bounded on $L_p$ spaces for $1&lt;p&lt;\infty.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13701v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edward McDonald</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The trace-free Einstein tensor is not variational for the metric as field variable</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02490v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is well-known that the trace-free Einstein tensor of a pseudo-Riemannian metric cannot arise by variation of a local diffeomorphism-invariant action functional with the (inverse) metric as field variable. We show that this statement remains true even for general local actions, without the assumption of diffeomorphism invariance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02490v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6382/ae4709</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Arian L. von Blanckenburg, Domenico Giulini, Philip K. Schwartz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Formation of Black Holes due to Boundary Effect in Vacuum Gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.09508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.09508v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that a marginally outer trapped surface (MOTS) can form as a result of Einsteinian evolution in pure vacuum spacetime starting from regular initial data free of MOTSs due to pure boundary effects. We adapt a Cauchy-double-null framework and use the boundary generalized mean curvature condition for the existence of an interior MOTS imposed by the author S-T Yau in \cite{yau}. In particular, we prove that the condition of \cite{yau} can be met dynamically starting from a configuration that does not verify the same through a focusing mechanism. In fact, a very mild incoming radiation can cause a large enough generalized boundary mean curvature of an isotropically large domain so that a MOTS exists in the interior. This is fundamentally different from black hole formation by standard ``gravitational collapse" and can be interpreted as the dynamical realization of a long-suspected idea in GR: MOTS can form because of ``global geometry", not just quasi-local concentration of gravity/matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.09508v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Puskar Mondal, Shing-Tung Yau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Green's function on the Tate curve</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24935v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by the question of defining a $p$-adic string worldsheet action in genus one, we define a Laplacian operator on the Tate curve, and study its Green's function. We show that the Green's function exists. We provide an explicit formula for the Green's function, which turns out to be a non-Archimedean counterpart of the Archimedean Green's function on a flat torus. In particular, it turns out that this Green's function recovers the N\'eron local height function for the Tate curve in the $p\to\infty$ limit, when the $j$-invariant has odd valuation. So this non-Archimedean height function now acquires a physics meaning in terms of the large $p$ limit of a non-Archimedean conformal field theory two point function on the Tate curve, as well as a direct analytic interpretation as a Green's function, on the same footing as in the Archimedean place.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24935v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>An Huang, Rebecca Rohrlich, Yaojia Sun, Eric Whyman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary Delocalization and Spectral Packets for Dirichlet Eigenfunctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.11605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.11605v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We establish a boundary delocalization principle for high-frequency Dirichlet eigenfunctions on smooth strictly convex domains. The main result is an exclusion of persistent boundary concentration at the level of individual eigenmodes relative to short spectral packets of sublinear length. Quantitatively, we compare boundary energies of single eigenfunctions to packet sums over frequency windows of size $N_k = o(k)$, without asserting any asymptotic gain in magnitude. The main mode-to-packet estimate relies only on the Rellich identity. For the multi-mode bias exclusion we additionally use the boundary local Weyl law to obtain a packet zero-mean cancellation estimate at the scale $N_k/k^{1-2/d} \to \infty$. This mode-to-packet comparison is independent of eigenvalue monotonicity and is stable under eigenvalue crossings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.11605v4</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Alexa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variable Elliptic Structures on the Plane: Transport Dynamics, Rigidity, and Function Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.19274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.19274v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a theory of variable elliptic structures on planar domains, in which the imaginary unit $i(x,y)$ is a moving generator of a rank-two real algebra bundle defined by a smoothly varying quadratic relation. Differentiating this relation produces an intrinsic obstruction $G = i_x + i\, i_y$ that governs all deviations from the constant-coefficient theory: the failure of the Leibniz rule, the inhomogeneity of the generalized Cauchy-Riemann system, and the forcing of a universal complex inviscid Burgers equation for the spectral parameter. The vanishing of $G$ -- rigidity -- selects the conservative regime of this transport law and simultaneously restores a coherent function theory: Cauchy-Pompeiu representation, covariant holomorphicity with gauge structure, power series, a similarity principle, and a factorization of the variable Laplacian. A rigidity-flatness theorem shows that the only structure that is both rigid and Riemannian-flat is the constant one. Translated into Beltrami coordinates, the rigidity condition becomes $\mu_{\bar{z}} = \mu\, \mu_z$: the structure map satisfies its own Beltrami equation, a self-dilatation property in the Poincar\'e disk. The central result is the Fundamental Independence Theorem: the Beltrami modulus $\|\mu\|_{C^0}$ (zeroth order) and the transport obstruction $\|R(\mu)\|_{C^{0,\alpha}}$ (first order) are independently prescribable. The classical Beltrami literature, which measures difficulty by $\|\mu\|_{C^0}$ alone, projects a two-dimensional difficulty space onto one axis. A one-parameter family of rigid structures -- the $\delta$-family -- realizes every point of the Beltrami disk with $R \equiv 0$, providing explicit examples with condition number $O(\delta^{-2})$ that are trivially solvable by transport at cost independent of $\delta$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.19274v4</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Alay\'on-Solarz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the discrete spectrum of non-selfadjoint operators with applications to Schr\"odinger operators with complex potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.02359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.02359v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For relatively form-compact perturbations of non-negative selfadjoint operators, we obtain an upper bound on the number of discrete eigenvalues in half-planes separated from the positive real axis. The bound is given in terms of a partial trace of the real part of the Birman--Schwinger operator, or an appropriate rotation thereof. While eigenvalue counting estimates of this type are classical in the selfadjoint setting, no analogous connection between the number of discrete eigenvalues and the Birman--Schwinger operator has previously been established in the non-selfadjoint theory. The proof proceeds via techniques in antisymmetric tensor product spaces that serve as a non-selfadjoint replacement for the classical arguments. As an application to Schr\"odinger operators, we generalise the Cwikel--Lieb--Rozenblum inequality to complex potentials and derive new Lieb--Thirring type inequalities. We also analyse the sharpness of the obtained bounds and discuss their optimality within the considered framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.02359v2</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sabine B\"ogli, Sukrid Petpradittha</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
