<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 02:35:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Hyperbolicity of Second-Order PDEs via Matrix Pencils</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13223v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a definition of strong hyperbolicity for second order partial differential equations using second order pencils. We show that this definition is equivalent to the standard one, derived by reducing the equations to first order form, but with the benefit of simplifying the calculations necessary to check hyperbolicity. In addition, we observe an interesting property, namely that when a system is strongly hyperbolic, its second order pencil can be factorized as a product of two diagonalizable first order pencils. Finally, we present an application to a vector potential for of Maxwell's equations, with a general extension and gauge fixing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13223v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Abalos, David Hilditch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Topological Analysis of Variable Growth Kirchhoff-Type Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13225v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a nonlocal differential equation of Kirchhoff type with a convolution coefficient involving variable growth. The novelty of our work lies in allowing a variable exponent in the nonlocal term. By relating the variable growth problem to a corresponding constant growth problem, we establish the existence of at least one positive solution subject to boundary conditions. Our approach relies on topological fixed point theory. The results treat convex, concave, and mixed growth regimes, providing a unified framework for one-dimensional Kirchhoff-type problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13225v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/prm.2025.10073</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proc. R. Soc. Edinb. A Math., First View (2025), 1-30</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Christopher S. Goodrich, Gabriel Nakhl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Corrections to: "The Willmore flow of Hopf-tori in the 3-sphere"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13228</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13228v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This erratum addresses a logical mistake in the author's article [Jakob, R. The Willmore flow of Hopf-tori in the $3$-sphere. Journal of Evolution Equations 23, No. 72 (2023)] which resulted in two wrong assertions in parts (II) and (III) of Theorem 1 in the author's cited paper and in an inaccuracy in the formulation of the second part of Proposition 6 in that paper. We will not only point out these mistakes and their corrections, but we will additionally give a concrete counterexample to Statement (III) in Theorem 1 of the author's cited article which will automatically imply the optimality of the corrected version of that statement, as it is formulated in this erratum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13228v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruben Jakob</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Supercritical Mass and Condensation in Fokker--Planck Equations for Consensus Formation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13276v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by recently developed Fokker--Planck models for Bose--Einstein statistics, we study a consensus formation model with condensation effects driven by a polynomial diffusion coefficient vanishing at the domain boundaries. For the underlying kinetic model, given by a nonlinear Fokker--Planck equation with superlinear drift, it was shown that if the initial mass exceeds a critical threshold, the solution may exhibit finite-time concentration in certain parameter regimes. Here, we show that this supercritical mass phenomenon persists for a broader class of diffusion functions and provide estimates of the critical mass required to induce finite-time loss of regularity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13276v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Monica Caloi, Mattia Zanella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normalized solutions of quasilinear Schr\"odinger-Poisson system with critical nonlinear term in bounded domain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13295v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work examines a quasilinear Schr\"odinger-Poisson system involving a critical nonlinearity, expressed as \[ -\Delta u + \phi u + \lambda u = |u|^{q-2} u + |u|^4 u, \quad x \in \Omega_r, \] \[ -\Delta \phi - \varepsilon^4 \Delta_4 \phi = u^2, \qquad\qquad\qquad\quad\ x \in \Omega_r, \] \[ \enspace u = \phi = 0, \qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad\qquad\enspace\ \ \,x \in \partial \Omega_r \] subject to the normalized condition \[ \int_{\Omega_r} |u|^2\, \mathrm d x = b^2. \] Here $\varepsilon &gt; 0$, $q \in (2, 8/3)$, $\Omega_r \subset \mathbb R^3$ is a bounded domain. By means of a truncation method combined with genus theory, we establish the existence of multiple families of normalized solutions. Due to the presence of a critical exponent in the nonlinear term, the associated energy functional fails to satisfy the usual compactness properties. To address this issue, we invoke the concentration-compactness principle. Furthermore, we derive the asymptotic result that the aforementioned system reduces to the classical Schr\"odinger-Poisson system (with $\varepsilon = 0$). Our findings extend several recent results concerning problems of this type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13295v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li Chen, Li Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Cauchy problem for the generalized KdV equation in the Sobolev space $H^{s}(\mathbf{R})$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13364v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we are concerned with the Cauchy problem for the generalized KdV equation with random data and rough data. Firstly, when $s\in\mathbf{R}$, by using the initial value randomization technique introduced by Shen et al. (arXiv:2111.11935) and the construction of appropriate auxiliary spaces, we establish the almost sure local well-posedness of the generalized KdV equation in $H^{s}(\mathbf{R})$, which improves Theorem 1.3 of Hwang and Kwak (Proc. Amer. Math. Soc. 146(2018), 267-280.) and Theorem 1.5 of Yan et al.(arXiv:2011.07128.). Secondly, by using the well-posedness results proved in Theorem 1.1, for $f\in H^{s}(\mathbf{R}),\, s\in\mathbf{R}$, we obtain \begin{eqnarray*} &amp;&amp;\mathbb{P}\left(\left\{\omega:\lim_{t\rightarrow0}\|u(t,x)-U(t)f^{\omega}(x)\|_{L_{x}^{\infty}}=0\right\}\right)=1, \end{eqnarray*} which improves Theorem 1.6 of Yan et al.(arXiv:2011.07128.). Thirdly, by using the dyadic decomposition and constructing appropriate function spaces, we establish nonlinear smoothing for the generalized KdV equation with rough data. Furthermore, by using this estimate, when data $f\in H^{s}(\mathbf{R})\cap\hat{L}^{\infty}(\mathbf{R}),\, s&gt;\frac{1}{2}-\frac{2}{k+1},\, k\geq4$, we obtain \begin{eqnarray*} &amp;&amp;\lim_{|x|\rightarrow \infty}u(t,x)=0,\quad t\in[0, T]. \end{eqnarray*} In particular, for $f(x)\in H^{s}(\mathbf{R}),\,s&gt;\frac{1}{2}-\frac{2}{k+1},\,k\geq4$, we prove \begin{eqnarray*} &amp;&amp;\lim_{|x|\rightarrow \infty}(u(t,x)-U(t)f(x))=0. \end{eqnarray*} Finally, by using Theorem 1.1, when $f\in H^{s}(\mathbf{R}),\, s\in\mathbf{R}$, we obtain \begin{eqnarray*} &amp;&amp;\mathbb{P}\left(\left\{\omega: \forall t\in I_{\omega}, \lim_{|x|\rightarrow \infty}\left(u(t,x)-U(t)f^{\omega}(x)\right)=0\right\}\right)=1. \end{eqnarray*}</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13364v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangqian Yan, Yongsheng Li, Juan Huang, Jianhua Huang, Wei Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong maximum principle for fully nonlinear nonlocal problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13425v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study solvability and qualitative properties of nonnegative solutions for a sublinear nonlocal problem with fully nonlinear structure in the form $$
  \mathcal{M}^{\pm}[u]+a(x)u^{q}(x)=0 \; \text{ in }\Omega,\qquad u\geq 0 \; \text{ in }\Omega. $$ Here $\Omega \subset \mathbb{R}^n$ is a bounded $C^{1,1}$ convex domain, $\mathcal{M}^{ \pm}$ stands for nonlocal Pucci extremal operators defined in a class $\mathcal{L}_*$ of homogeneous kernels, $q\in(0,1)$, and $a$ is a possibly sign-changing weight.
  We introduce a new nonlocal hypothesis on the negative part of the solution outside the domain, which together with the negative part of the potential, influences the formation of dead cores and cannot be removed. Our approach relies on uniform bounds from below of the maximum of nontrivial solutions through Liouville theorems, and on a Hopf lemma for viscosity solutions driven by fully nonlinear operators, which we also prove.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13425v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Pablo Cabeza, Gabrielle Nornberg, Disson dos Prazeres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radial Sobolev embeddings on spherically symmetric Riemannian manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13501v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study Sobolev spaces of radial functions on spherically symmetric Riemannian manifolds. Using geodesic polar coordinates, we give a sharp one-dimensional reduction: a radial function belongs to the Sobolev space on the manifold if and only if its radial representation lies in an associated weighted Sobolev space on an interval, with weights determined explicitly by the metric. This characterization allows us to prove optimal Sobolev-type embeddings for radial functions into weighted Lebesgue spaces on both bounded and unbounded spherically symmetric manifolds. As further consequences, we establish new radial lemmas and decay estimates that capture the precise behaviour of radial Sobolev functions near the origin and at infinity. Our results unify and extend the classical radial embeddings in Euclidean and hyperbolic spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13501v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jo\~ao Marcos do \'O, Guozhen Lu, Raon\'i Ponciano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularity and stability of two coupled Euler-Bernoulli equations with a localized singular structural damping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13525</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13525v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper is concerned with the study of regularity and stability properties of two Euler-Bernoulli beam equations with localized singular damping. Under suitable regularity assumptions on the damping coefficient, we establish Gevrey regularity for the semigroup generated by the associated operator. Furthermore, for a broader class of damping mechanisms, including less regular damping, we derive uniform stability result. These findings provide a detailed description of the long-term behavior of the corresponding dynamical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13525v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Ammari, F. Hassine, L. Tebou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Painlev\'{e} XXXIV asymptotics for the defocusing nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation with a finite-genus algebro-geometric background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13589v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the Cauchy problem for the defocusing nonlinear Schr$\ddot{\text{o}}$dinger equation with a finite genus algebro-geometric background. Long-time asymptotics of the solution are derived in four space-time regions. It comes out that the leading-order term in the expansion is, up to a constant, given by the background solution with a shift of the parameter. The subleading term, however, decays at different rates for different regions. We particularly highlight that in the two transition regions, they are of order $\mathcal{O}(t^{-1/3})$ and the coefficients involve an integral of the Painlev\'e XXXIV transcendent. We establish our results by applying a nonlinear steepest descent analysis to the associated Riemann-Hilbert problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13589v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00208-026-03322-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Mathematische Annalen, Volume 394, article number 44, (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Engui Fan, Gaozhan Li, Yiling Yang, Lun Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Formula for Time-to-Frequency Wave Boundary Data Conversion by the Boundary Control Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given the wave equation on a compact Riemannian manifold with boundary, we derive an explicit reconstruction procedure to represent the frequency-domain Neumann-to-Dirichlet map in terms of the time-domain Neumann-to-Dirichlet map at any non-eigenfrequency. If the wave equation is exactly controllable, we derive an explicit formula to compute the former from the latter. The derivation is based on the boundary control method and requires only knowledge on the boundary of the manifold. The formula is stable when the level of regularization is fixed. The numerical feasibility is validated using one-dimensional examples in both Euclidean and non-Euclidean geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13612v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shinbrot Type Criteria for Energy Conservation of the Compressible Navier-Stokes Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13696v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that weak solutions to the compressible Navier-Stokes equations satisfy the energy equality under a Shinbrot-type regularity criterion. Our method applies to the fluids with both constant and degenerate viscosity and relies on a novel weak-type commutator estimate. These criterion are strictly weaker than those required in prior works [Arch. Ration. Mech. Anal., 225 (2017)] and [SIAM J. Math. Anal. 52 (2020)].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13696v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruxuan Chen, Qi Zhang, Zhikang Zhang, Xiongbo Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability in the anisotropic Calder\'{o}n problem for Painlev\'e-Liouville Riemannian manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13703v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the question of stability of the global and partial anisotropic Calder\'on inverse problems for the class of Painlev\'e-Liouville Riemannian manifolds, that is compact $n$-dimensional manifolds with boundary $(M,g)$, where $M=[0,1]\times K\,$, $K$ is any smooth closed connected orientable manifold of dimension $n-1$ endowed with a Riemannian metric $g_K$, and $g=\alpha^4 g_{0}$ is any conformal deformation of the product metric $g_{0}=dx^2+g_{K}$ on $M$ which is compatible with the Painlev\'e block-separability of the Laplace-Beltrami operator $\Delta_{g_0}$. Given a pair of Painlev\'e-Liouville Riemannian manifolds $(M,g)$ and $(M,\tilde{g})$ satisfying some technical hypothesis, denoting the corresponding Dirichlet-to-Neumann maps by $\Lambda_{g}$ and $\Lambda_{\tilde{g}}$, and assuming that $\lVert \Lambda_{g}-\Lambda_{\tilde{g}}\rVert_{\mathcal{B}(H^{1/2}(\partial M), H^{-1/2}(\partial M))}\ = \epsilon $, we show a logarithmic stability result for the global anisotropic Calder\'on problem which says that there exists constants $C$ and $0&lt;\theta&lt;1$ such that $\| \alpha - \tilde{\alpha} \|_{C^{0,r}(M)} \leq C \left( \ln \frac{1}{\epsilon} \right)^{-\theta}$ for some $0&lt;r&lt;1$. Similar results are obtained for the partial anisotropic Calder\'on problem, corresponding to the case where the data are measured on only one connected component of the boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13703v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thierry Daud\'e, Niky Kamran, Fran\c{c}ois Nicoleau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolvent approaches to elliptic regularity in stationary Fokker-Planck equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13727v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the local regularity of solutions to stationary Fokker-Planck equations on an open set $U \subset \mathbb{R}^d$ with $d \geq 2$. A central objective is to relax the classical assumptions on the coefficients by focusing on the case where the drift vector field $\mathbf{G}$ is only assumed to be locally square-integrable, i.e. $\mathbf{G} \in L^2_{loc}(U, \mathbb{R}^d)$, the diffusion matrix $A = (a_{ij})_{1 \leq i,j \leq d}$ is assumed to be locally uniformly strictly elliptic and bounded, with coefficients satisfying $\frac{a_{ij}+a_{ji}}{2} \in VMO_{loc}(U)$ for all $1 \leq i,j \leq d$ and ${\rm div}A \in L^2_{loc}(U, \mathbb{R}^d)$. Our main result shows that any locally bounded function $h \in L^\infty_{loc}(U)$ satisfying the stationary Fokker-Planck equation $L^*(h\, dx) = 0$ must in fact belong to the local Sobolev space $H^{1,2}_{loc}(U)$. The proof is based on the construction of a sub-Markovian resolvent associated with the principal elliptic operator $L^A := \operatorname{trace}(A \nabla^2)$, combined with delicate energy-type inequalities. In particular, we show that the density $h$ can be realized as the weak $H^{1,2}$-limit of images of resolvent operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13727v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haesung Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entire solutions to a strongly competitive nonlinear Schr\"odinger system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13753v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We build infinitely-many non-radial positive solutions to the Schr\"odinger system \begin{equation*} \left\{\begin{aligned} &amp;-\Delta u_1+u_1=u_1^{{\mathfrak p} }-\Lambda u_1^{a_1} u_2^{a_2}\ \hbox{in}\ \mathbb R^N\\ &amp;-\Delta u_2+u_2=u_2^{{\mathfrak p} }-\Lambda u_1^{b_1}u_2^{b_2} \ \hbox{in}\ \mathbb R^N\\ \end{aligned}\right. \end{equation*} with sub-critical $\mathfrak p$-growth as $\Lambda \to +\infty$. The profile of each component is the sum of several copies of the positive solution to $-\Delta U+U=U^{{\mathfrak p} }$ in $\mathbb R^N$, centered at suitable {\em peaks} whose mutual distances diverge as $\Lambda$ increases. More precisely, given two concentric regular polygons with $k$ sides and very large radii, the peaks of the first component are arranged along the edges of the {\em outer} polygon, alternated with those of the second component, and along the $k$ rays joining the vertices of the two polygons. To the best of our knowledge, this provides the first example of non-radial positive solutions for strongly competitive Schr\"odinger systems in the whole space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13753v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierpaolo Esposito, Pablo Salgado, Angela Pistoia, Giusi Vaira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contraction of viscous-dispersive shocks: Zero viscosity-capillarity limits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13788v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the contraction property of any large solution perturbed from a viscous-dispersive shock wave of the Navier--Stokes--Korteweg (NSK) system. The contraction holds up to a dynamical shift, since the contraction is measured by the relative entropy that is locally $L^2$. We use the contraction property to show the global existence of large solution perturbed from a viscous-dispersive shock wave. To prove the contraction property, we first employ the effective velocity to transform the NSK system into the system of two degenerate parabolic equations, then apply the method of $a$-contraction with shifts. The contraction property does not depend on the strengths of viscosity and capillarity. Based on this uniformity, we show the existence of zero viscosity-capillarity limits of solutions to the NSK system, on which Riemann shocks are unique and stable up to shifts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13788v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Namhyun Eun, Moon-Jin Kang, Jeongho Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Liouville-type theorems for Lane--Emden inequalities involving nonlocal operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13822v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish a Liouville-type theorem for nonnegative weak supersolutions to $\mathcal{L}_K u = u^q$ in $\mathbb{R}^n$, where $\mathcal{L}_K$ is a translation-invariant integro-differential operator of order $2s$ with $s \in (0,1)$. The kernel $K$ is assumed to be even and satisfy uniform ellipticity bounds. We prove that the only nonnegative supersolution is the trivial one $u \equiv 0$ in the range $1 &lt; q \le \frac{n}{n-2s}$ for $n &gt; 2s$ (and for all $q &gt; 1$ when $n \le 2s$). Our proof is elementary and relies on a test function method combined with a dyadic decomposition of the nonlocal tail. Notably, our argument does not rely on the maximum principle or the fundamental solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13822v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Kim, T. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact non-stationary solutions of the Euler equations in two and three dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop, via Arnold's geometric framework, a mechanism for constructing explicit, smooth, global-in-time, and typically non-stationary solutions of the incompressible Euler equations. The approach introduces a notion of generalized Coriolis force, whose spectrum underlies the construction of these solutions. In the setting of ideal hydrodynamics, the construction recovers classical exact solutions such as Kelvin and Rossby-Haurwitz waves, while also producing new explicit examples on curved surfaces and three-dimensional manifolds including the round three-sphere. We further obtain a complete classification in two dimensions and a partial classification in three dimensions of the Riemannian manifolds that admit such solutions. The method is also formulated in the general Euler-Arnold setting and yields a simple criterion for non-stationarity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13929v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Heslin, Stephen C. Preston</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global regularity for axisymmetric, swirl-free solutions of the Euler equation in four dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13963v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove global regularity for all smooth, axisymmetric, swirl-free solutions of the Euler equation in four dimensions. Previous works establishing global regularity for certain axisymmetric, swirl-free solutions of the Euler equation in four dimensions required the additional assumption that $\frac{\omega^0}{r^2}\in L^\infty$, which can fail even for Schwartz class solutions. The key advance is a new bound on the vortex stretching term that only requires $\frac{\omega^0}{r^2}\in L^{2,1}(\mathbb{R}^4)$, which is generically true for any axisymmetric, swirl-free initial data $u^0\in H^s\left(\mathbb{R}^4\right), s&gt;4$, with reasonable decay at infinity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13963v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evan Miller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constrained variational problems on perturbed lattice graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13978v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we solve some constrained variational problems on perturbed lattice graphs $G$. The first problem addresses the existence of ground state normalized solutions to Schr\"odinger equations
  \begin{equation*} \left\{
  \begin{aligned}
  &amp;-\Delta_{G} u+\lambda u=\vert u\vert^{p-2}u,x\in G
  &amp;\Vert u\Vert_{l^2(G)}^2=a.
  \end{aligned}
  \right. \end{equation*} We prove that if the graph is obtained by deleting finite edges in lattice graphs while maintaining connectivity, then there exists a threshold $\alpha_G\in[0,\infty)$ such that there do not exist ground state normalized solution if $0&lt;a&lt;\alpha_G$, and there exists a ground state normalized solution if $a&gt;\alpha_G.$ If the graph is obtained by adding finite edges $E^{'}$ to lattice graphs, we prove that there exist $E^{'}$ and $a_1$ such that for all $a&gt;a_1,$ there do not exist ground state normalized solutions.
  The second problem concerns the existence of an extremal function for the Sobolev inequality. If the graph $G$ is obtained by deleting finite edges in lattice graphs while maintaining connectivity, for the Sobolev super-critical regime, we prove that there exists an extremal function. for the Sobolev critical regime, we prove that there exists $G$ such that extremal can be attained. If the graph is obtained by adding finite edges $E^{'}$ to lattice graphs, we prove that there exists $E^{'}$ such that there does not exist an extremal function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13978v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiqi Guan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Theory of Fractional Cooperative Systems and Threshold Dynamics in Epidemic Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13986v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spectral analysis has long been recognized as a fundamental tool for studying the existence, uniqueness, and qualitative behavior of solutions to semilinear elliptic and parabolic equations, as well as their long-time dynamics. In modern mathematics, fractional Laplacians are widely used to model nonlocal or long-range diffusion processes arising in biology, including anomalous movement, long-distance dispersal, and Levy-flight migration of organisms, cells, and epidemics.
  In this paper, we employ the spectral fractional Laplacian introduced by Caffarelli and Stinga (2016) to develop the eigentheory for a cooperative system describing an infectious epidemic process and to analyze its long-term behavior. Using Fredholm theory and related analytical techniques, building in part on ideas of Lam and Lou (2016), we establish a sharp criterion ensuring the existence and simplicity of the principal eigenvalue, together with variational characterizations and consequences for the validity of maximum principles. We further derive the asymptotic behavior of the principal eigenvalue with respect to diffusion coefficients, fractional orders, and domain scaling, complementing recent developments by Zhao and Ruan (2023) and Feng, Li, Ruan, and Xin (2024).
  As an application of this spectral framework, we prove the existence, uniqueness, and threshold-type long-time dynamics of solutions to an endemic reaction-diffusion system with fractional diffusion, providing a perspective that differs from earlier approaches such as Hsu and Yang (2013). Our results contribute to the growing interaction between spectral theory and nonlocal analysis, in line with recent advances in the area.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13986v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cong-Bang Trang, Hoang-Hung Vo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability and instability of a one-dimensional MHD model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13995v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a one-dimensional magnetohydrodynamics model introduced by Dai \textit{et al.}~(2023), in a parameter regime where, in the absence of a magnetic field, the system reduces to the De Gregorio model for the Euler equations. We analyze stability and instability near the first excited state on the torus, thus generalizing the recent results obtained by Guo and Jiu~(2025) for the De Gregorio model. Specifically, we establish global well-posedness of the linearized system, local well-posedness for the nonlinear system, and demonstrate both linear and nonlinear instability for a broad class of initial data in the weighted Sobolev space introduced by Lai \textit{et al.}~(2020). We identify the principal linearized operator, which is structurally equivalent to that of the De Gregorio model, as the primary mechanism of instability. Moreover, we prove global well-posedness and stability of both linear and nonlinear systems for initial data in a particular subspace of the aforementioned weighted Sobolev space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13995v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicola De Nitti, Jie Guo, Quansen Jiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long time smooth solutions of 2-D quadratic quasilinear wave equations in exterior domains with Neumann boundary conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14019v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For the 3-D quadratic quasilinear wave equations in exterior domains with Dirichlet or Neumann boundary conditions, the global existence or the maximal existence time of small data smooth solutions have been established in the past. However, so far it is still open for the corresponding 2-D Neumann boundary value problem. In this paper, we investigate the long time existence of small data solutions to 2-D quadratic quasilinear wave equations with homogeneous Neumann boundary values. Our main ingredients include: establishing some new pointwise spacetime decay estimates for the 2-D initial boundary value problem of the divergence form wave equations, and introducing a series of good unknowns to derive the required energy estimates. The obtained results can be directly applied to the initial boundary value problem of 2-D isentropic and irrotational compressible Euler equations for both the polytropic gases and the Chaplygin gases in exterior domains with impermeable conditions, the 2-D relativistic membrane equations and 2-D membrane equations with homogeneous Neumann boundary values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14019v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fei Hou, Huicheng Yin, Meng Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interior Hessian estimates for Hessian quotient equations in dimension three</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14064v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish the interior Hessian estimates for $2$-convex solutions to $\frac{\sigma_2}{\sigma_1} (D^2 u) = \psi (x,u)$ in dimension three. In higher dimensions ($n \geq 4$), we prove the interior Hessian estimates for semi-convex solutions. We provide a new method to prove the doubling inequality for smooth solutions in dimensions three and four. In higher dimensions ($n\geq 5$) the doubling inequality is proved under an additional dynamic semi-convexity condition which is the same to that in \cite{SY2025}. The method also applies to the equation $\sigma_2 (D^2 u) = \psi (x, u, \nabla u)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14064v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heming Jiao, Zhenan Sui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence for the Discrete Nonlinear Fragmentation Equation with Degenerate Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14070v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A mathematical model for the discrete nonlinear fragmentation (collision-induced breakage) equation with diffusion is studied. The existence of global weak solutions is established in arbitrary spatial dimensions without assuming a strictly positive lower bound on the diffusion coefficients, extending previous results that were restricted to one-dimensional domains and relied on uniformly positive diffusion. The analysis is carried out under boundedness assumptions on the collision and breakage kernels. The proof is based on the construction of a suitable regularized system, combined with weak $L^2$ a priori estimates and compactness arguments in $L^1$, which allow the passage to the limit in the nonlinear fragmentation operator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14070v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saumyajit Das, Ram Gopal Jaiswal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Liouville theorems for conformal $Q$-curvature equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the non-existence of positive solutions for the following conformal $Q$-curvature equation \begin{equation*} (-\Delta)^\sigma u = K(x) u^{\frac{n+2\sigma}{n-2\sigma}} \quad \text{in } \mathbb{R}^n, \end{equation*} where $ \sigma \in (0, n/2)$ is a real number. When $\sigma=1$, this equation reduces to the well-known scalar curvature equation arising from the prescribed scalar curvature problem. For general $\sigma \in (0, n/2)$, it appears in the study of prescribing $Q$-curvature. We establish Liouville theorems under various assumptions on the $Q$-curvature $K(x)$ by developing a unified approach applicable to all $\sigma \in (0, n/2)$. Our method successfully addresses the challenges posed by the absence of ODE tools in the fractional regime and the lack of a classification of Delaunay-type singular solutions for the general fractional Yamabe equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14072v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meiqing Xu, Hui Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oblique wave interactions in 2D steady supersonic flows of Bethe-Zel'dovich-Thompson fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14144v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies steady supersonic flow in a 2D semi-infinite divergent duct. We assume that the flow satisfies the slip boundary condition on the walls of the duct, and the state of the flow is given at the inlet of the divergent duct. When the fluid is a polytropic ideal gas, the problem can be reduced to some interactions of rarefaction simple waves, and the existence of a global classical solution inside the divergent duct can be established using the method of characteristics. In this paper we assume that the fluid is a nonconvex Bethe-Zel'dovich-Thompson (BZT) fluid. This type of fluid may significantly differ from polytropic ideal gases. For instance, physically admissible rarefaction shocks can occur. Depending on the oncoming flow state and the flare angles of the divergent duct, thirteen distinct types of oblique wave interactions may occur, including oblique composite waves consisting of shocks and centered simple waves. This paper systematically studies these oblique wave interactions and constructs global, piecewise smooth, supersonic solutions within the divergent duct using characteristic decomposition and hodograph transformation methods. We also obtain the detailed structures of these solutions in addition to their existence. The results and methods of this paper are also applicable to some 2D Riemann problems for gases with nonconvex equations of state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14144v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Geng Lai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logarithmic Sobolev, Poincar\'e and Beckner Inequalities on Hyperbolic Spaces and Riemannian Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14202v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate several functional and geometric inequalities on the hyperbolic space $\mathbb{H}^N$, with a primary emphasis on logarithmic Sobolev inequalities, Poincar\'e inequalities, and Beckner-type inequalities, all studied within the framework of the AB program. The main analytical tool employed throughout this paper is symmetrization. More precisely, our approach relies on an improved version of the P\'olya-Szeg\"o inequality on the hyperbolic space, obtained through a careful comparison of the gradient norms of rearranged functions in the hyperbolic and Euclidean settings. For Beckner-type inequalities, we adopt a semigroup approach based on sharp estimates for the heat semigroup, leading to refined interpolation inequalities between Poincar\'e and logarithmic Sobolev inequalities. Finally, we extend our results beyond hyperbolic space to a class of Riemannian model manifolds $\mathbb{M}^N$ satisfying the centered isoperimetric inequality. This shows that the inequalities and methods developed in this work are robust and rely mainly on geometric and isoperimetric properties, rather than on the specific structure of hyperbolic space itself.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14202v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anh Xuan Do, Debdip Ganguly, Nguyen Lam, Guozhen Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlocal logistics and nonlinear productions in an attraction-repulsion chemotaxis model: analysis of the global well-posedness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14227v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates a {{three-component}} chemotaxis system involving both attraction and repulsion effects, as well as a nonlocal logistic-type source term. Mathematically, if $u=u(x,t)$, $v = v(x,t)$ and $w = w(x,t)$ denote the cell distribution, and the attractive and the repulsive chemical signals, the model is then described by
  \begin{equation*}
  \begin{cases}
  u_t = \Delta u - \chi \nabla \cdot (u \nabla v) + \xi \nabla \cdot (u \nabla w) + a u^\alpha - b u^\alpha \int_\Omega u^\beta, &amp; x \in \Omega, \ t &gt; 0,
  \tau v_t = \Delta v - v + f(u), &amp; x \in \Omega, \ t &gt; 0,
  \tau w_t = \Delta w - w + g(u), &amp; x \in \Omega, \ t &gt; 0.
  \end{cases}
  \end{equation*}
  Here, $\Omega \subset \mathbb{R}^n$ ($n \geq 1$) is a bounded smooth domain, $\tau\in\{0,1\}$, $a,b,\alpha,\beta,\chi,\xi&gt;0$, the production functions $f(u)$ and $g(u)$ are assumed to satisfy algebraic growth conditions of order $\ell$ and $\rho$, generalizing prototypes of the form $u^\ell$ and $u^\rho$, $\ell,\rho&gt;0$. The work is devoted to proving the global existence and boundedness of classical solutions under a suitable balance between the signal production exponents $\ell, \rho$ and the nonlocal damping exponents $\alpha, \beta$, for regular enough initial data and zero-flux boundary restrictions. In this regard, two main theorems are established for the cases where the chemical signals satisfy either elliptic ($\tau=0$) or parabolic ($\tau=1$) partial differential equations, highlighting how sufficiently strong nonlocal damping prevents the formation of singularities in time.
  We extend the results obtained in [Chiyo et al., Appl. Math. Optim. 89:9 (2024)], where the fully parabolic ($\tau=1$) and only attraction version is studied. In our context, we establish well-posedness of the system and the long-time behavior of solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14227v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael D\'iaz Fuentes, Mar\'ia Victoria Redondo Neble, Giuseppe Viglialoro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partial regularity of the gradient for subsolutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14305v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that the gradient of any bounded subharmonic function is upper semi-continuous, provided that its super-level sets can be touched from the exterior by uniform $C^{1,\text{Dini}}$ domains at every point. This idea extends to a class of general operators, as well as to the boundary behaviour of the gradient of solutions of the Dirichlet problem in a domain whose boundary satisfy this geometric condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14305v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aram Hakobyan, Michael Poghosyan, Henrik Shahgholian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observability and Semiclassical Control for Schr\"odinger Equations on Non-compact Hyperbolic Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14316v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the observability of the Schr\"odinger equation on $X$, a non-compact covering space of a compact hyperbolic surface $M$. Using a generalized Bloch theory, functions on $X$ are identified as sections of flat Hilbert bundles over $M$. We develop a semiclassical analysis framework for such bundles and generalize the result of semiclassical control estimates in [Dyatlov and Jin, Acta Math., 220 (2018), pp. 297-339] to all flat Hilbert bundles over $M$, with uniform constants with respect to the choice of bundle. Furthermore, when the Riemannian cover $X \to M$ is a normal cover with a virtually Abelian deck transformation group $\Gamma$, we combine the uniform semiclassical control estimates on flat Hilbert bundles with the generalized Bloch theory to derive observability from any $\Gamma$-periodic open subsets of $X$. We also discuss applications of the uniform semiclassical control estimates in spectral geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14316v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Fu, Yulin Gong, Yunlei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence and nonexistence of solutions for fractional elliptic equations arising from closed MEMS model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14346v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The objective of our paper is to investigate fractional elliptic equations of the form $(-\Delta)^s u=\frac{\lambda }{(a-u)^2}$ within a bounded domain $\Omega$, subject to zero Dirichlet boundary conditions. Here, $s\in(0,1)$, $\lambda&gt;0$, and the function $a$ vanishes at the boundary while satisfying additional conditions. This problem originates from Micro-Electromechanical Systems (MEMS) devices, particularly when the elastic membrane makes contact with the ground plate at the boundary. We establish both existence and nonexistence results, illustrating how the boundary decay of the membrane influences the solutions and pull-in voltage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14346v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huyuan Chen, Jialei Jiang, Jun Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The small Deborah number limit for the compressible fluid-particle flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14412v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the hydrodynamic limit for the fluid-particle flows governed by the Vlasov-Fokker-Planck equation coupled with the compressible Navier-Stokes equation as the Deborah number tends to zero. The limit is valid globally in time provided that the initial perturbation is small in a neighborhood of a steady state. The proof is based on a formal derivation via the Hilbert expansion around the limiting system, the rigorous justification of which is completed by the refined energy estimates involving the macro-micro decomposition. Compared with the existing results obtained by the relative entropy argument([A. Mellet and A. F. Vasseur, Comm. Math. Phys., 281 (2008), pp. 573--596]), the present work provides a stronger pointwise convergence of the hydrodynamic limits with an explicit rate for the fluid-particle coupled model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14412v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhendong Fang, Kunlun Qi, Huanyao Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Neumann problems with Aharonov-Bohm potentials: boundary asymptotics of eigenvalues and splitting phenomena</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14522v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a planar magnetic Schr\"odinger operator with an Aharonov-Bohm vector potential, under Neumann boundary conditions. Through a gauge transformation, the corresponding eigenvalue problem can be formulated in terms of the Laplacian on a fractured domain, where the fracture lies along the segment connecting the pole to its projection on the boundary. As the pole approaches the boundary, we prove that the eigenvalues converge to those of the Neumann Laplacian and the variation exhibits a logarithmic vanishing rate. In the case of multiple eigenvalues, when the pole approaches a fixed point of the boundary, we observe a splitting phenomenon, with the largest branch separating from the others.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14522v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Veronica Felli, Prasun Roychowdhury, Giovanni Siclari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the first eigenvalue of a nonlinear Schr\"odinger type equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14545v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider an eigenvalue problem for the generalized nonlinear Schr\"{o}dinger type operator with the Robin boundary condition as given below. \begin{equation*} \label{ab-Robin p-Laplace evp with potential term_intro} \left\{ \begin{split} -\Delta_p u+V(x)|u|^{p-2}u&amp;=\lambda |u|^{p-2}u\quad &amp;&amp;\mathrm{in} ~\Omega,\\ |\nabla u|^{p-2}\frac{\partial u}{\partial\eta}+\beta|u|^{p-2}u&amp;=0\quad &amp;&amp;\mathrm{on}~\partial\Omega, \end{split} \right. \end{equation*} where $\Delta_p u := \operatorname{div}(|\nabla u|^{p-2}\nabla u)$ is the $p$-Laplace operator, $\Omega $ is a bounded domain in $\mathbb{R}^n$ with smooth boundary, $V \in C^1(\mathbb{R}^n),$ $ \eta $ denotes the outward unit normal, and $ \beta $ is a positive real constant. We study the properties of its first eigenvalue with respect to the potential $V$, the boundary parameter $\beta$ as well as the domain. First, we establish some properties of the smallest eigenvalue $\lambda_1(V)$ with respect to the potential. We then prove the differentiability of $\lambda_1(V)$ with respect to the Robin boundary parameter $\beta$ and give an explicit formula for this derivative, which is then used to investigate some monotonicity properties of $\lambda_1(V).$ We also obtain a shape derivative formula for the smallest eigenvalue. Using these derivatives, we also study domain monotonicity properties of the first eigenvalue.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14545v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ardra A</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feedback Stabilization and Tracking for Heat Equations Using Thermo-Plasmonic Nanoparticles as Actuators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14581</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14581v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a feedback strategy to track prescribed heat profiles using plasmonic nanoparticles as actuators. Starting from a thermo--plasmonic Maxwell--heat model, we use a time-domain discrete effective description in which the generated heat is approximated by a superposition of heat kernels centered at particle locations with amplitudes governed by a coupled Volterra system. We recast this dynamics as a heat equation on a bounded domain with finitely many point actuators and design a tracking feedback based on pointwise evaluations of $\mathcal A^{-1}y$, where $\mathcal A=I-A_0$ and $A_0$ is the Neumann diffusion operator. Working in the natural $V'$ setting with $V=D(\mathcal A)$, we prove exponential stabilization of the tracking error via distribution-actuator theory. For non-equilibrium reference profiles, we add a constant feedforward term and a low-mode fixed-point pre-compensation on $X_N$, ensuring exact steady matching on $X_N$ and an explicit bound on the residual tail mismatch.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14581v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpan Mukherjee, S\'ergio S. Rodrigues, Mourad Sini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kernel estimates and weak (1,1)-boundedness of pseudo-differential operators on compact Lie groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14638v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a compact Lie group $G$ and its unitary dual $\widehat{G}$, we establish the weak (1,1) continuity for pseudo-differential operators in the global H\"ormander classes of order $-n(1-\rho)/2$ on $G\times \widehat{G}$. Our approach consists of proving suitable estimates for the kernel of such operators. Furthermore, we use these kernel estimates to give an alternative proof for the $H^1(G)$-$L^1(G)$-continuity of these classes now allowing the full range $0\leq\delta\leq\rho\leq1, \;\rho\neq0,\;\delta\neq1$. The conditions for the operators are formulated using the H\"ormander classes $S^m_{\rho,\delta}(G):=S^m_{\rho,\delta}(G\times \widehat{G})$ of symbols in the non-commutative phase space $G\times \widehat{G}$, which are extensions of the well-known $(\rho,\delta)$-classes in the Euclidean space. Our results are formulated in the complete range $0\leq \delta\leq \rho\leq 1,$ $\rho\neq0,\;$$\delta\neq 1$.
  As an application of this boundedness result we provide end-point a-priori $L^1$-estimates for the sub-Laplacian $\mathcal{L}_{sub}=X^2+Y^2,$ and for the heat type operator $T=Z-X^2-Y^2$ on $SU(2)\cong \mathbb{S}^3$ that cannot be obtained by application of the standard pseudo-differential calculus due to H\"ormander. More precisely, we prove that if one considers the subelliptic problem,
  \begin{equation}\label{IVP:abstract} \begin{cases}Tu=f ,&amp; \text{ } \\u,f\in \mathscr{D}'(SU(2)):=(C^\infty(SU(2)))', &amp; \text{ } \end{cases} \end{equation} then, for $f\in W^{1,-\frac{1}{4}}(SU(2)),$ one has that $u\in L^{1,\infty}(SU(2)).$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14638v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duv\'an Cardona, Rafik Yeghoyan, Michael Ruzhansky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Morrey estimates for the gradient in non-linear variational transmission problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14658v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a class of variational transmission problems driven by nonlinear energies with discontinuous coefficients across a prescribed interface. The model setting consists of integral functionals of the form \[ \mathcal{F}(u;E)=\int_{\Omega}\sigma_E(x)\,F(\nabla u)\,dx, \] where the coefficient $\sigma_E$ takes two constant values on complementary regions separated by a $C^1$ hypersurface, and the integrand $F$ satisfies standard $p$-growth and monotonicity conditions with $p&gt;2$.
  In this nonlinear variational framework, we establish local Morrey-space regularity for the gradient of local minimizers, proving that $\nabla u\in L^{2,\lambda}_{\mathrm{loc}}(\Omega)$ for every $0\leq\lambda&lt;n$, provided $2&lt;p&lt;\frac{2n}{n-2}$. The proof is based on quantitative decay estimates for the energy near the interface, first obtained in a flat configuration and then extended to the general case by a suitable approximation argument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14658v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Esposito, Lorenzo Lamberti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the kinetic equation arising from the large-scale limit of the Cucker-Smale model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14685v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a large-scale scaling viewpoint for deriving mesoscopic dynamics from interacting particle systems and apply it to the Cucker--Smale flocking model. In contrast with the classical mean-field regime leading to the Vlasov-type Cucker--Smale equation with spatially nonlocal (convolution) alignment force, our scaling yields a kinetic equation whose alignment field becomes local in space and nonlocal only in velocity. For the spatially homogeneous case, we obtain an explicit solution and derive quantitative flocking rates. For the spatially inhomogeneous equation we establish a local well-posedness in $W^{1,\infty}$ and in $C_b^{1,\alpha}$, highlighting the additional difficulties caused by the absence of a convolution structure. Moreover, for sufficiently small interaction strength we present a global well-posedness and a forward-in-time $L^1$ asymptotic completeness property. Finally, we investigate mono-kinetic solutions and exhibit finite-time blow-up scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14685v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruicheng Cheng, Seung-Yeal Ha, Jaemoon Lee, Zhenfu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matching conditions for scattering solutions of scalar wave equations on extremal Reissner-Nordstr\"{o}m spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14712v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study scattering solutions $\phi$ of the linear wave equation on extremal Reissner-Nordstr\"{o}m spacetimes, satisfying the following properties: i) $\phi$ attains a prescribed radiation field $\psi_{\mathcal{I}}$ through future null infinity, which decays at an inverse polynomial rate; ii) $\phi$ is regular in the exterior region up to and including the future event horizon, i.e. $\phi\in C^N$, where $N\gg1$ is independent of the decay rate of $\psi_{\mathcal{I}}$. We prove that such solutions exist for arbitrary $N$, and that they are not unique. The proof consists of: 1) finding an approximate solution $\phi_{\mathrm{app}}$ with fast decaying error; 2) the use of backwards energy estimates in order to correct $\phi_{\mathrm{app}}$ to an exact solution. Extremality is used only in the second step. The methods of the linear case described above are then used to show the same results for semilinear equations where the nonlinearity satisfies the null condition, as well as to geometries describing the hyperbolic orbit of multiple extremal Reissner-Nordstr\"{o}m black holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14712v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yannis Angelopoulos, Istvan Kadar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the H\"{o}lder continuity of signed solutions to doubly nonlinear parabolic equations in the mixed degenerate/singular cases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14800v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the H\"{o}lder continuity of sign-changing solutions to the equation of the type $$\frac{\partial}{\partial t}\big(|u|^{q-1} u\big)- div\Big(|D u|^{p-2}\,D u\Big)=0,$$ where numbers $p$, $q$ satisfy the conditions $$0&lt;q&lt;p-1\quad \text{and}\quad p&lt;2,$$ or $$q&gt;p-1\quad\text{and}\quad p&gt;2.$$ Our proof uses new versions of the integral Harnack type inequalities for sign-changing solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14800v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor I. Skrypnik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence of large-data solutions to a thermo-piezoelectric system and forward operator analysis for associated inverse problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14848v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider an inverse problem governed by the initial-boundary value problem for the thermoviscoelastic Kelvin-Voigt system \begin{align*}\left\{ \begin{array}{l} \rho(z,t) u_{tt}- \left(\Gamma(\Theta) u_{zt} +p(z,t) u_z -\beta\Theta\right)_z=0\\ b(z,t) \Theta_t-\left(k(z,t)\Theta_z\right)_z - \Gamma(\Theta) u_{zt}^2+\beta \Theta u_{zt}=0, \end{array} \right.
  \end{align*} in an open bounded interval $\Omega\subset\mathbb{R}$, for the evolution of the displacement variable $u$, and the temperature $\Theta\geq 0$. Assuming the material coefficients $\rho$, $\Gamma$, $p$, $b$, $\beta$ and $k$ are strictly positive and bounded, a global-in-time existence result is established for weak solutions. The present manuscript demonstrates that this can be achieved under energy- and entropy-minimal assumptions, in the sense that global weak solutions are shown to exist for any initial data $$u_0\in W^{1,2}(\Omega),\quad u_{0t}\in L^2(\Omega)\quad\text{and}\quad 0\le\Theta_0\in L^2(\Omega).$$ The qualitative analysis of the evolution problem then allows to model and analyze the structural properties of the corresponding forward operator that naturally arises in inverse parameter identification settings. Therein, two modeling approaches of the observation operator as approximations of the electrical surface charge are presented and results on their well-definedness and boundedness are established. With the results on well-definedness and boundedness of the model operator, established in this paper as well, results on well-definedness, boundedness and continuous Fr\'{e}chet differentiability of the forward operator are presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14848v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Torben J. Fricke, Raphael Kuess, Felix Meyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Liouville's theorem for the Hessian quotient equation $\sigma_2/\sigma_1$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14946v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove Liouville's theorem for semi-convex entire solutions to Hessian quotient equation $\sigma_2/\sigma_1=1$ in $\mathbb{R}^n$. The proof is based on the observation that after rewriting the quotient operator as the $\sigma_2$ operator, acting on a new function, one can refer to the recent result of Shankar and Yuan on Liouville's theorem for $\sigma_2$ equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14946v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siyuan Lu, Marcin Sroka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transitions and linear stability for the mean-field Kuramoto-Daido model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14954v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the mean-field noisy Kuramoto-Daido model, which is a McKean-Vlasov equation on the circle with bimodal interaction $W(\theta)=\cos\theta+m\cos2\theta$ for $m\ge 0$ and interaction strength $K$, generalizing the celebrated noisy Kuramoto model corresponding to $m=0$.
  Our first contribution is to characterize the phase transition threshold $K_{c}$ by comparing it to the linear stability threshold $K_\# = \min (1, m^{-1})$ of the uniform distribution. When $m \leq 1/2,$ $K_{c}=1$, coinciding with that of the Kuramoto model. On the other hand, for $m \geq 2$, we show $K_c= m^{-1}$. We also classify the regimes in which the phase transition is continuous or discontinuous.
  Our second contribution is to analyze the linear stability of a global minimizer $q$ (the ``ordered phase'') of the mean-field free energy in the supercritical regime $K&gt;1$. This stationary solution of the Kuramoto-Daido equation is unique up to translation invariance and distinct from the uniform distribution (the ``disordered phase''). Our approach extends the Dirichlet form method of Bertini et al. from the unimodal to bimodal setting. In particular, for $m \leq 1.590 \times 10^{-4}$ and $K&gt;1$, we show an explicit lower bound on the spectral gap of the linearized McKean-Vlasov operator at $q$. To our knowledge, this is the first rigorous stability analysis for this class of models with bimodal interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14954v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyunghoo Mun, Matthew Rosenzweig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invariant Gibbs dynamics for the hyperbolic sinh-Gordon model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14996v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the hyperbolic defocusing sinh-Gordon model with parameter $\beta^2&gt;0$ and its associated Gibbs dynamics on the two-dimensional torus. We establish global well-posedness of the model for a certain range of parameters $\beta^2&gt;0$ with the corresponding Gibbs measure initial data and prove invariance of the Gibbs measure under the flow, thereby resolving a question posed by Oh, Robert, and Wang (2019). Our physical space approach hinges on developing a novel $L^\infty$-based well-posedness theory for wave equations with exponential-type nonlinearities, going beyond the classical $L^2$-based framework. This refinement allows us to fully leverage structural properties of Gaussian multiplicative chaos. As a by-product of our method, we also obtain an improved well-posedness theory for the hyperbolic Liouville model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14996v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Justin Forlano, Younes Zine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fine properties of functions in complex Sobolev spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.13968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.13968v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study comprehensively local properties of functions in complex Sobolev spaces on a bounded open subset of $\mathbb{C}^n$. The main tool is the corresponding functional capacity for the space which is inspired by the global one due to Vigny (2007). An inequality between this capacity and the Bedford-Taylor capacity for plurisubharmonic functions is proved, which is sharp as far as the exponents are concerned. Moreover, it is shown that the functional capacity is a Choquet capacity. The Alexander-Taylor type inequality for the capacity is also proved. This allows us to strengthen the results in the works of Dinh, Marinescu and Vu (2023), Vigny and Vu (2024). Lastly, the Moser-Trudinger type inequality in this space is characterized by the volume-capacity inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.13968v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ngoc Cuong Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Higher Order Discretization for the Stochastic Navier--Stokes equations with additive Noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14268v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a new higher-order time discretization scheme for the stochastic Navier--Stokes equations with additive noise, where its velocity and pressure approximates converge at strong rate $1.5$ in probability. The construction rests on its reformulation as a random PDE for the transform $y = u- \Phi W$, and different higher order numerical quadrature rules for the diffusion and the drift part. The theoretical findings are supported by numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14268v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Banas, D. Breit, A. Chaudhary, A. Prohl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix-Weighted Poincar\'e-Type Inequalities with Applications to Logarithmic Haj{\l}asz--Besov Spaces on Spaces of Homogeneous Type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14361v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let ${\mathcal {X}}$ be a space of homogeneous type. In this article, based on the reducing operators of matrix $A_p$-weights, the authors introduce the vector-valued Haj\l asz gradient sequences and establish some related matrix-weighted Poincar\'{e}-type inequalities on ${\mathcal {X}}$. As an application, the authors introduce the matrix-weighted logarithmic Besov spaces on ${\mathcal {X}}$ and establish their pointwise characterization via Haj{\l}asz gradient sequences. The novelty of this article lies in that, by means of both the $A_p$ dimension and its properties of matrix $A_p$-weights and the wavelet reproducing formula with exponential decay of P. Auscher and T. Hyt\"onen, all the main results get rid of the dependence on the reverse doubling conditions of both weights and ${\mathcal {X}}$ under consideration and these results are also completely new even for unweighted logarithmic Besov spaces on ${\mathcal {X}}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14361v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziwei Li, Dachun Yang, Wen Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gel'fand's inverse problem under Ricci curvature bounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14527v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The classical Gel'fand's inverse problem asks whether a Riemannian manifold is uniquely determined by the knowledge of the heat kernel on any open subset of the manifold. We study this inverse problem in the non-smooth setting in the framework of ${\rm RCD}(K,N)$ spaces, namely, metric-measure spaces with synthetic Riemannian Ricci curvature bounded below by $K$ and dimension bounded above by $N$. We establish the unique solvability of Gel'fand's inverse problem for the class of compact ${\rm RCD}(K,N)$ spaces whose regular set admits $C^1$-Riemannian structure. As an application, we obtain the stability of Gel'fand's inverse problem in the class of closed Riemannian manifolds with bounded Ricci curvature, diameter and volume bounded from below. We note that the results are new even for Einstein orbifolds and (weighted) Riemannian manifolds with non-smooth boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14527v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shouhei Honda, Jinpeng Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Propagation of regularity along unstable manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14558v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\varphi_t : M \to M$ be a flow on a smooth closed connected manifold $M$ that preserves and expands a foliation $F$. We establish a theorem of propagation of regularity along the leaves of $F$ for sections of vector bundles satisfying a transport equation involving the generator of a cocycle over $\varphi_t$. As a consequence, we prove a regularity result for Pollicott-Ruelle resonant states: if such state is smooth in restriction to a piece of an unstable leaf, then it is in fact smooth over the entire manifold. We also announce further applications related to joint integrability of extreme bundles of partially hyperbolic diffeomorphisms. The proofs rely on a leafwise semiclassical pseudodifferential calculus adapted to a foliated space, which may be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14558v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thibault Lefeuvre, Rafael Potrie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic behavior at infinity of Weingarten surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14651v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We derive the asymptotic expansion at infinity for embedded ends of uniformly elliptic Weingarten surfaces with finite total curvature in $\mathbb{R}^3$, and we establish a maximum principle at infinity. Furthermore, we solve the Dirichlet problem for the uniformly elliptic Weingarten equation in dimension two on strictly convex bounded domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14651v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aires E. M. Barbieri, Jos\'e A. G\'alvez, Yuanyuan Lian, Kai Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Bergman space functions from intervals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.14801</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.14801v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We characterize functions of a Bergman space on a square by their values and derivatives on the diagonals. This problem is connected with the reachable space of the one-dimensional heat equation on a finite interval with boundary $L^2$-controls.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.14801v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Hartmann, Marcu-Antone Orsoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generic non-uniqueness of minimizing harmonic maps from a ball to a sphere</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12662v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note, we study non-uniqueness for minimizing harmonic maps from $B^3$ to $\mathbb{S}^2$. We show that every boundary map can be modified to a boundary map that admits multiple minimizers of the Dirichlet energy by a small $W^{1,p}$-change for $p&lt;2$. This strengthens a remark by the second-named author and Strzelecki. The main novel ingredient is a homotopy construction, which is the answer to an easier variant of a challenging question regarding the existence of a norm control for homotopies between $ W^{1,p} $ maps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12662v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5802/crmath.648</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>C. R. Math. Acad. Sci. Paris 362 (2024), 1357-1364</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Detaille, Katarzyna Mazowiecka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upper bounds of nodal sets for Gevrey regular parabolic equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09879v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the size of the nodal set of the solution of the second order parabolic-type equation with Gevrey regular coefficients. We provide an upper bound as a function of time. The dependence agrees with a sharp upper bound when the coefficients are analytic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09879v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guher Camliyurt, Igor Kukavica, Linfeng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Normalized solutions of one-dimensional defocusing NLS equations with nonlinear point interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21700v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate normalized solutions for doubly nonlinear Schr\"odinger equations on the real line with a defocusing standard nonlinearity and a focusing nonlinear point interaction of $\delta$-type at the origin. We provide a complete characterization of existence and uniqueness for normalized solutions and for energy ground states for every value of the nonlinearity powers. We show that the interplay between a defocusing standard and a focusing point nonlinearity gives rise to new phenomena with respect to those observed with single nonlinearities, standard combined nonlinearities, and combined focusing standard and pointwise nonlinearities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21700v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Barbera, Filippo Boni, Simone Dovetta, Lorenzo Tentarelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mean oscillation conditions for nonlinear equation and regularity results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02159v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider general nonlinear elliptic equations of the form \[ \operatorname{div}\, A(x,Du) = 0 \quad \text{in } \Omega, \] where $A:\Omega \times \mathbb R^n \to \mathbb R^n$ satisfies a quasi-isotropic $(p,q)$-growth condition, which is equivalent to the point-wise uniform ellipticity of $A$. We establish sharp and comprehensive mean oscillation conditions on $A(x,\xi)$ with respect to the $x$ variable to obtain $C^1$- and $W^{1,s}$-regularity results. The results provide new conditions even in the standard $p$-growth case with coefficient $\operatorname{div}(a(x)|Du|^{p-2}Du)=0$. Also included are variable exponent growth with and without perturbation as well as borderline double-phase growth and double-phase growth with a coefficient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02159v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter H\"ast\"o, Mikyoung Lee, Jihoon Ok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinitely many solutions for nonlinear superposition operators of mixed fractional order involving critical exponent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.11832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.11832v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper addresses a class of elliptic problems involving the superposition of nonlinear fractional operators with the critical Sobolev exponent in the sublinear regimes. We establish the existence of infinitely many nontrivial weak solutions using a variational framework combining a truncation argument with the notion of genus. A central part of our analysis is the verification of the Palais--Smale (PS) condition for the associated energy functional for every $q \in (1, p_{s_\sharp}^*)$, despite the challenges posed by the lack of compactness due to the critical exponent. The results obtained in the paper are new even in the classical case $p = 2$, highlighting the broader applicability of the methods developed here.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.11832v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Souvik Bhowmick, Sekhar Ghosh, Vishvesh Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isogeometric fluid-structure interaction using a mixed continuous/discontinuous Galerkin scheme</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.13363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.13363v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A mixed continuous / discontinuous Galerkin scheme is introduced for the simulation of fluid-structure interaction problems in an isogeometric analysis framework. The properties of Non-Uniform Rational B-Spline basis functions are leveraged to enable an exact transfer of the structural displacement to the fluid domain, while using different discretizations and refinements on the two sides of the coupling interface. The proposed approach is applied to the simulation of a compressible flow around an elastic wing membrane and to a classical fluid-structure benchmark involving the flow around a cylinder equipped with a hyper-elastic bar. For both cases, the results obtained are compared to those found in the literature to assess the accuracy of the proposed method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.13363v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Computer Methods in Applied Mechanics and Engineering, 2026, 453, pp.118795</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>R\'egis Duvigneau (ACUMES)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional higher differentiability of solutions to strongly nonlinear Stokes systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.22675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.22675v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work concerns stationary Stokes type systems governed by a general class of non-necessarily power-type nonlinearities. Fractional regularity properties of the symmetric gradient of local solutions are established, depending on a balance between the nonlinearity of the differential operator and the degree of integrability of the datum on right-hand side. The non-polynomial character of the differential operators calls for the use of Orlicz and Orlicz-Sobolev spaces as an appropriate functional framework for both the solutions and the datum. The regularity result amounts to the membership of a nonlinear expression of the symmetric gradient in Besov spaces. Fractional regularity of the pressure term is also exhibited and is formulated in terms of Orlicz-Besov spaces. Fractional Sobolev regularity of the symmetric gradient and of the pressure follow as a consequence.} Parallel results for the symmetric gradient of local solutions to the associated plain elliptic system are also offered. A new version of a Poincar\'e-Sobolev inequality in Orlicz spaces, in modular form, on domains with finite measure plays a role in the proofs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.22675v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Cianchi, Flavia Giannetti, Antonia Passarelli di Napoli, Christoph Scheven</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solutions of the singular Yamabe problem near singular boundaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.23331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.23331v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the asymptotic behaviors of solutions to the singular Yamabe problem with negative constant scalar curvature near singular boundaries and derive optimal estimates, where the background metrics are not assumed to be conformally flat. Specifically, we demonstrate that for a wide class of Lipschitz domains with asymptotic conical structure, the local positive solutions are well approximated by the positive solutions in the tangent cones at singular boundary points. This extends the results of [10, 12, 26].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.23331v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiming Shen, Zhehui Wang, Jiongduo Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundedness of Fourier Integral Operators with complex phases on Fourier Lebesgue spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.24854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.24854v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we develop boundedness estimates for Fourier integral operators on Fourier Lebesgue spaces when the associated canonical relation is parametrised by a complex phase function. Our result constitutes the complex analogue of those obtained for real canonical relations by Rodino, Nicola, and Cordero. We prove that, under the spatial factorization condition of rank $\varkappa$, the corresponding Fourier integral operator is bounded on the Fourier Lebesgue space $\mathcal{F}L^p,$ provided that the order $m$ of the operator satisfies that $ m \leq -\varkappa\left|\frac{1}{p}-\frac{1}{2}\right|, 1 \leq p \leq \infty. $ This condition on the order $m$ is sharp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.24854v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duv\'an Cardona, William Obeng-Denteh, Frederick Opoku</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-linear parabolic PDEs with rough coefficients and critical data: existence, uniqueness and regularity of weak solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.05080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.05080v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article investigates the well-posedness of weak solutions to non-linear parabolic PDEs driven by rough coefficients with rough initial data in critical homogeneous Besov spaces. Well-posedness is understood in the sense of existence and uniqueness of maximal weak solutions in suitable weighted $Z$-spaces in the absence of smallness conditions. We showcase our theory with an application to rough reaction--diffusion equations. Subsequent articles will treat further classes of equations, including equations of Burgers-type and quasi-linear problems, using the same approach. Our toolkit includes a novel theory of hypercontractive singular integral operators (SIOs) on weighted $Z$-spaces and a self-improving property for super-linear reverse H\"older inequalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.05080v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pascal Auscher, Sebastian Bechtel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A free boundary problem in accretive growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.08755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.08755v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove an existence result for a free boundary problem inspired by the modelization of accretive growth. The growth process is formulated through a level-set approach, leading to a boundary-value problem for a Hamilton-Jacobi equation within a prescribed constraining set. Existence, variational representability, and regularity of solutions to the growth subproblem are investigated. The full system arises from coupling the growth dynamics with an elliptic equation for the activation field. Existence of solutions to the fully coupled free boundary problems is obtained via an iterative procedure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.08755v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulisse Stefanelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A stochastic perturbation approach to nonlinear bifurcating problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16803v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Incorporating probabilistic terms in mathematical models is crucial for capturing and quantifying uncertainties in real-world systems, especially when the solution is not unique or exhibits sudden qualitative changes as parameters vary. However, stochastic models typically require large computational resources to produce meaningful statistics. In this work, we leverage the Polynomial Chaos (PC) expansion to propose a systematic approach for bifurcation detection in parametric systems of equations. We show that the method, exploiting a perturbed version of the deterministic model, avoids repeated costly simulations across multiple parameter values and requires no prior information for initializing numerical solvers, while still providing accurate characterization of the bifurcation branches. We argue that the PC solutions of the perturbed model not only provide access to statistical information about the deterministic branches, but also approximate these branches in a meaningful sense. Finally, we validate our claims by means of numerical tests on the pitchfork bifurcation, examining both its normal form and a classical realization in fluid-dynamics PDEs, namely the Coanda effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16803v4</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isabella Carla Gonnella, Moaad Khamlich, Federico Pichi, Gianluigi Rozza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence and asymptotic autonomous robustness of random attractors for three-dimensional stochastic globally modified Navier-Stokes equations on unbounded domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07460v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article, we discuss the existence and asymptotically autonomous robustness (AAR) (almost surely) of random attractors for 3D stochastic globally modified Navier-Stokes equations (SGMNSE) on Poincar\'e domains (which may be bounded or unbounded). Our aim is to investigate the existence and AAR of random attractors for 3D SGMNSE when the time-dependent forcing converges to a time-independent function under the perturbation of linear multiplicative noise as well as additive noise. The main approach is to provide a way to justify that, on some uniformly tempered universe, the usual pullback asymptotic compactness of the solution operators is uniform across an infinite time-interval $(-\infty,\tau]$. The backward uniform ``tail-smallness'' and ``flattening-property'' of the solutions over $(-\infty,\tau]$ have been demonstrated to achieve this goal. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first attempt to establish the existence as well as AAR of random attractors for 3D SGMNSE on unbounded domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07460v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bui Kim My, Ho Thi Hang, Kush Kinra, Manil T. Mohan, Pham Tri Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On uniqueness in structured model learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22009v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper addresses the problem of uniqueness in learning physical laws for systems of partial differential equations (PDEs). Contrary to most existing approaches, it considers a framework of structured model learning, where existing, approximately correct physical models are augmented with components that are learned from data. The main results of the paper are a uniqueness and a convergence result that cover a large class of PDEs and a suitable class of neural networks used for approximating the unknown model components. The uniqueness result shows that, in the limit of full, noiseless measurements, a unique identification of the unknown model components as functions is possible as classical regularization-minimizing solutions of the PDE system. This result is complemented by a convergence result showing that model components learned as parameterized neural networks from incomplete, noisy measurements approximate the regularization-minimizing solutions of the PDE system in the limit. These results are possible under specific properties of the approximating neural networks and due to a dedicated choice of regularization. With this, a practical contribution of this analytic paper is to provide a class of model learning frameworks different to standard settings where uniqueness can be expected in the limit of full measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22009v4</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Holler, Erion Morina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotics of the quantization problem on metric measure spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18779v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The problem of quantization of measures looks for best approximations of probability measures on a metric space by discrete measures supported on $N$ points, where the error of approximation is measured with respect to the Wasserstein distance. Zador's theorem states that, for measures on $\mathbb{R}^d$ or $d$-dimensional Riemannian manifolds satisfying appropriate integrability conditions, the quantization error decays to zero as $N \to \infty$ at the rate $N^{-1/d}$.
  In this paper, we provide a general treatment of the asymptotics of quantization on metric measure spaces $(X, \nu)$. We show that a weaker version of Zador's theorem involving the Hausdorff densities of $\nu$ holds also in this general setting. We also prove Zador's theorem in full for appropriate $m$-rectifiable measures on Euclidean space, answering a conjecture by Graf and Luschgy in the affirmative. For both results, the higher integrability conditions of Zador's theorem are replaced with a general notion of $(p,s)$-quantizability, which follows from Pierce-type (non-asymptotic) upper bounds on the quantization error, and we also prove multiple such bounds at the level of metric measure spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18779v2</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00208-026-03376-x</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Math. Ann. 394, 48 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ata Deniz Aydin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiharmonic algorithms for contrast-enhanced ultrasound</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13335v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Harmonic generation plays a crucial role in contrast-enhanced ultrasound, both for imaging and therapeutic applications. However, accurately capturing these nonlinear effects is computationally very demanding when using traditional time-domain approaches. To address this issue, in this work, we develop algorithms based on a time discretization that uses a multiharmonic Ansatz applied to a model that couples the Westervelt equation for acoustic pressure with a volume-based approximation of the Rayleigh--Plesset equation for the dynamics of microbubble contrast agents. We first rigorously establish the existence of time-periodic solutions for this Westervelt-ODE system. We then derive a multiharmonic representation of the system under time-periodic excitation and develop iterative algorithms that rely on the successive computation of higher harmonics under the assumption of real-valued or complex solution fields. In the real-valued setting, we characterize the approximation error in terms of the number of harmonics and a contribution owing to the fixed-point iteration. Finally, we investigate these algorithms numerically and illustrate how the number of harmonics and presence of microbubbles influence the propagation of acoustic waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13335v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vanja Nikoli\'c, Teresa Rauscher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A mixed finite element method for a class of fourth-order stochastic evolution equations with multiplicative noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04866v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a fully discrete, semi-implicit mixed finite element method for approximating solutions to a class of fourth-order stochastic partial differential equations (SPDEs) with non-globally Lipschitz and non-monotone nonlinearities, perturbed by spatially smooth multiplicative Gaussian noise. The proposed scheme is applicable to a range of physically relevant nonlinear models, including the stochastic Landau--Lifshitz--Baryakhtar (sLLBar) equation, the stochastic convective Cahn--Hilliard equation with mass source, and the stochastic regularised Landau--Lifshitz--Bloch (sLLB) equation, among others. To overcome the difficulties posed by the interplay between the nonlinearities and the stochastic forcing, we adopt a `truncate-then-discretise' strategy: the nonlinear term is first truncated before discretising the resulting modified problem. We show that the strong solution to the truncated system converges in probability to that of the original problem. A fully discrete numerical scheme is then proposed for the truncated problem. Assuming initial data in $\mathbb{H}^2$, we utilise parabolic smoothing estimates and the temporal H\"older continuity of the solution to establish both convergence in probability and strong convergence (with quantitative rates) for the two fields used in the mixed formulation. Numerical simulations are provided to support the theoretical results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04866v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/m2an/2026018</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ESAIM: Mathematical Modelling and Numerical Analysis (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Beniamin Goldys, Agus L. Soenjaya, Thanh Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heterotopic energy for Sobolev mappings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16204v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the notion of heterotopic energy defined as the limit of Sobolev energies of Sobolev mappings in a given homotopy class approximating almost everywhere a given Sobolev mapping. We show that the heterotopic energy is finite if and only if the mappings in the corresponding homotopy classes are homotopic on a codimension one skeleton of a triangulation of the domain. When this is the case, the heterotopic energy of a mapping is the sum of its Sobolev energy and its disparity energy, defined as the minimum energy of a bubble to pass between these homotopy classes. At the more technical level, we rely on a framework that works when the target and domain manifolds are not simply connected and there is no canonical isomorphism between homotopy groups with different basepoints.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16204v2</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antoine Detaille, Jean Van Schaftingen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of memory on clustering in spontaneous particle aggregation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15335v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The effect of short-term and long-term memory on spontaneous aggregation of organisms is investigated using a stochastic agent-based model. Each individual modulates the amplitude of its random motion according to the perceived local density of neighbors. Memory is introduced via a chain of $K$~internal variables that allow agents to retain information about previously encountered densities. The parameter $K$ controls the effective length of memory. A formal mean-field limit yields a macroscopic Fokker--Planck equation, which provides a continuum description of the system in the large-population limit. Steady states of this equation are characterized to interpret the emergence and morphology of clusters. Systematic stochastic simulations in one- and two-dimensional spatial domains reveal that short- or moderate-term memory promotes coarsening, resulting in a smaller number of larger clusters, whereas long-term memory inhibits aggregation and increases the proportion of isolated individuals. Statistical analysis demonstrates that extended memory reduces the agents' responsiveness to environmental stimuli, explaining the transition from aggregation to dispersion as $K$ increases. These findings identify memory as a key factor controlling the collective organization of self-driven agents and provide a bridge between individual-level dynamics and emergent spatial patterns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15335v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Radek Erban, Jan Haskovec</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regularity of Einstein 5-manifolds via 4-dimensional gap theorems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.21317v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We refine the regularity of noncollapsed limits of 5-dimensional manifolds with bounded Ricci curvature. In particular, for noncollapsed limits of Einstein 5-manifolds, we prove that
  (1) tangent cones are unique of the form $\mathbb{R}\times\mathbb{R}^4/\Gamma$ on the top stratum, hence outside a countable set of points; this follows from a new isolation result for cones of the form $\mathbb{R}\times\mathbb{R}^4/\Gamma$ among all tangent cones,
  (2) the singular set is entirely contained in a countable union of Lipschitz curves and points,
  (3) away from a nowhere dense subset, these Lipschitz curves consist of smooth geodesics,
  (4) the interior of any geodesic is removable: limits of Einstein manifolds are real-analytic orbifolds with singularities along geodesic and bounded curvature away from their extreme points, and
  (5) if an asymptotically Ricci-flat 5-manifold with Euclidean volume growth has one tangent cone at infinity that splits off a line, then it is the unique tangent cone at infinity.
  These results prompt the question of the orbifold regularity of noncollapsed limits of Einstein manifolds off a codimension 5 set in arbitrary dimension.
  The proofs rely on a new result of independent interest: all spherical and hyperbolic 4-orbifolds are isolated among Einstein 4-orbifolds in the Gromov-Hausdorff sense. This yields various gap theorems for Einstein 4-orbifolds, which do not extend to higher dimensions. The proofs of these gap theorems require a careful analysis of singular metrics and families of metrics that degenerate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.21317v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiqi Huang, Tristan Ozuch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Numerical Treatment of an Abstract Nonlinear System of Coupled Hyperbolic Equations Associated with the Timoshenko Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.02068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.02068v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The present work addresses the Cauchy problem for an abstract nonlinear system of coupled hyperbolic equations associated with the Timoshenko model in a real Hilbert space. Our purpose is to develop and delve into a temporal discretization scheme for approximating a solution to this problem. To this end, we propose a symmetric three-layer semi-discrete time-stepping scheme in which the nonlinear term is evaluated at the temporal midpoint. As a result, at each time step, this approach reduces the original nonlinear problem to a linear one and enables parallel computation of its solution. Convergence is proved, and second-order accuracy with respect to the time-step size is established on a local temporal interval. The proposed scheme is then applied to a spatially one-dimensional nonlinear dynamic Timoshenko beam system, and the results obtained for the abstract nonlinear system are extended to this setting. A Legendre-Galerkin spectral approximation is employed for the spatial discretization. By taking differences of Legendre polynomials within the Galerkin framework, the resulting linear system is sparse and can be efficiently decoupled. The convergence of the method is also investigated. Finally, several numerical experiments on carefully chosen benchmark problems are conducted to validate the proposed approach and to confirm the theoretical findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.02068v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jemal Rogava, Zurab Vashakidze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sharp estimates for the Robin Laplacian under a perimeter constraint in hyperbolic space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.07510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.07510v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish a lower bound, in terms of the isoperimetric deficit, for the first eigenvalue of the Robin Laplacian with negative boundary parameter on horospherically convex bounded domains in the hyperbolic space. This implies that the geodesic ball maximizes this eigenvalue among all such domains, thereby providing a partial resolution to an open problem posed by Celentano, Krej\v{c}i\v{r}\'{i}k and Lotoreichik in \cite{CKL26}. Furthermore, we derive upper bounds for the first eigenvalue of the Robin Laplacian with positive boundary parameter on horospherically convex bounded domains in the hyperbolic space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.07510v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daguang Chen, Shan Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
