<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.AP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP</link>
    <description>math.AP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.AP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 05:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Nodal Deficiency of Neumann Eigenfunctions on a Symmetric Dumbbell Domain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17140v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the nodal deficiency of pairs of Neumann eigenfunctions defined over symmetric dumbbell domains. As the width of the connecting neck shrinks, these eigenfunctions converge to Neumann eigenfunctions defined over the ends of the dumbbell, together with a one-dimensional Sturm-Liouville solution in the neck. In this limit, the corresponding eigenvalues become degenerate, with multiplicity two. The nodal deficiency, defined as the difference between the eigenvalue index and the nodal domain count, is known by the Courant nodal domain theorem to be nonnegative. We show that, for small neck widths, the nodal deficiencies of the dumbbell eigenfunctions are no smaller than the nodal deficiencies of the limiting eigenfunctions in the ends, and we provide conditions under which equality is achieved. As a consequence, we establish a criterion for identifying eigenfunctions of zero nodal deficiency for the dumbbell domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17140v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Beck, Andrew Lyons</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calder\'on's inverse problem via Vekua theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17313v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we will prove a uniqueness result for Calder\'on's inverse problem via some integral representation formulas for solutions of the Vekua equation in the framework of Clifford analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17313v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Briceyda B. Delgado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Spectral Fractional Hirota Bilinear Operator: Analysis and Application to a Time-Fractional KdV Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17347v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We develop a fractional version of Hirota's bilinear calculus that is built directly from the spectral (Fourier-multiplier) fractional derivative on $\mathbb{R}$. For $0&lt;\alpha\le 1$ we define \[ D_{\xi}^{\alpha}f\cdot g := (D_{\xi}^{\alpha}f)\,g - f\,(D_{\xi}^{\alpha}g), \] equivalently through the two-variable extension $D_{\xi_1}^{\alpha}-D_{\xi_2}^{\alpha}$. In Fourier variables this is a bilinear multiplier with symbol $(ik_1)^{\alpha}-(ik_2)^{\alpha}$. For $0&lt;\alpha&lt;1$ we prove a Marchaud-type singular integral representation, and we use it to establish basic algebraic identities (bilinearity, skew-symmetry and $D_{\xi}^{\alpha}f\cdot f=0$), a Sobolev estimate $H^{s}\times H^{s}\to H^{s-\alpha}$ for $s&gt;\tfrac12$, and convergence to the classical Hirota derivative as $\alpha\to 1^-$. As an application we derive a Hirota bilinear form for a spectral time-fractional KdV equation and construct explicit one- and two-soliton $\tau$-functions. The fractional order changes the dispersion relation to $\omega^{\alpha}=-k^{3}$, while the two-soliton interaction coefficient agrees with the classical KdV value.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17347v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Ray</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well-posedness and numerical approximation of nonlinear conservation laws with hysteresis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17403v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article studies the Cauchy problem for the scalar conservation law \[ \partial_t u + \partial_t w + \partial_x f(u) = 0, \] where $w(x,t) = [\mathcal{F}(u)(x,t)]$ is the output of a specific hysteresis operator, namely the Play hysteresis operator, and $f$ is a $\mathbf{C}^2$ convex flux function. The hysteresis operator models a rate-independent memory effect, introducing a specific non-local feature into the partial differential equation. We define a suitable notion of entropy weak solution and analyse in detail the Riemann problem. Furthermore, a Godunov-type finite volume numerical scheme is developed to compute approximate solutions. The convergence of the scheme for $\mathrm{BV}$ initial data provides the existence of an entropy weak solution. Finally, a stability estimate is established, implying the uniqueness and overall well-posedness of the entropy weak solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17403v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paola Goatin, Stefan Moreti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explicit inversion of spherical Radon transforms in odd dimensions with partial radial data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17411v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive an explicit inversion algorithm for the spherical Radon transform in odd dimensions with partial radial data. We prove that the reconstruction of the unknown function can be reduced to solving ordinary differential equations, thereby providing a more explicit approach in odd dimensions than solving Volterra integral equation of the first kind established in prior works. We also provide analytical solutions in some special cases. Finally, we present numerical simulations validating our theoretical results. Our work answers a question posed by Rubin in ``Inversion formulae for the spherical mean in odd dimensions and the Euler-Poisson-Darboux equation,'' Inverse Problems 24 (2008), no. 2, 025021, 10 pp.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17411v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pradipta Chatterjee, Venkateswaran P. Krishnan, Abhilash Tushir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolvent, spectrum and resonances for the acoustic operator with piecewise constant coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17522v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the acoustic operator $A_{v,\rho }:=v^{2}\rho\nabla\!\cdot\rho^{-1}\nabla$ with transmission conditions at the boundary of $\Omega=\Omega_{1}\cup\dots\cup\Omega_{n}$, where the $\Omega_{\ell}$'s are connected disjoint open bounded Lipschitz domains, the positive functions $v$ and $\rho$ are constant on each connected component of $\Omega$ and $v=\rho=1$ on ${\mathbb R}^{3}\backslash\overline\Omega$. Through a formula for the resolvents difference $(-A_{v,\rho }+z)^{-1}-(-\Delta+z)^{-1}$, we provide a Limiting Absorption Principle, determine the spectrum, which turns out to be purely absolutely continuous, and, in the case the connected components of $\Omega$ are of class ${\mathcal C}^{1,\alpha}$, characterize the resonance set. The second part of the paper is devoted to the case where $\Omega=\Omega(\varepsilon)$ is connected with a small size $\varepsilon$ and the $\varepsilon$-analytic functions $v=v(\varepsilon)$ and/or $\rho=\rho(\varepsilon)$ converge to $0_{+}$ inside $\Omega(\varepsilon)$ as $\varepsilon\downarrow 0$; there, we provide the analytic $\varepsilon$-expansions of the resonances of $A_{v,\rho }$ according to different choices of the rate of convergence towards zero of the material parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17522v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Mantile, Andrea Posilicano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterisation of homogenisation for nonlocal diffusion by local topologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17579v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider fractional variants of divergence form problems with highly oscillatory local coefficients. We characterise the convergence of these coefficients by means of classical $H$-convergence covering the local behaviour of the fractional divergence form problem and weak-$\ast$ convergence on the complement caused by the nonlocality of the differential operators. The results are further described in the light of nonlocal $H$-convergence as introduced in [Waurick, Calc Var PDEs, 57, 2018] and certain Schur topologies. Applications to symmetric coefficients and a homogenisation problem for a fractional heat type equation are provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17579v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Buchinger, Kre\v{s}imir Burazin, Ivana Crnjac, Marko Erceg, Maja Joli\'c, Marcus Waurick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long time behavior of Fokker-Planck equations for bosons and fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17594v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper is concerned with space inhomogeneous quantum Fokker-Planck equations posed on a classical kinetic phase space. The nonlinear factor $f(1\pm f)$ appears both in the transport term and in the collison part of the Fokker-Planck operator, accounting for the inclusion principle of bosons and the exclusion principle of fermions. Assuming that global solutions exist, we prove exponential decay of the solutions to the global equilibrium in a weighted $L^2$-space without a close-to-equilibrium assumption. Our analysis is in the spirit of an $L^2$-hypocoercivity method. Our main Lyapunov functional is constructed from a logarithmic relative entropy and the (nonlinear) projection of the solution to the manifold of local-in-$x$ equilibria.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17594v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anton Arnold, Marlies Pirner, Gayrat Toshpulatov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniqueness and stability in bottom detection through surface measurements of water waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17639</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17639v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates the geometric inverse problem of recovering the bottom shape from surface measurements of water waves. Using the general water-waves system on a bounded subdomain of the fluid domain, we address this inverse problem, focusing on the identifiability and the stability issues. We establish uniqueness and derive logarithmic stability estimates in the determination of the bathymetry on any fixed smooth, bounded, open domain
  ${\mathcal O}\subset {\mathbb R} ^d$, $d=1,2$, from the knowledge of the free surface, its first time derivative, the velocity potential at a given instant $t_0$ within $\mathcal O $, and the knowledge of the bottom along $\partial \mathcal O$. No further assumptions are required for uniqueness. For stability, we impose only a \textit{local fatness} condition on the region between the bottom profiles, allowing us to adapt the size estimates method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17639v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noureddine Lamsahel, Lionel Rosier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global well-posedness of 3D two-fluid type model with vacuum: smallness on scaling invariant quantity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17709v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper focuses on Cauchy problem for the three-dimensional two-fluid type model, in which the presence of vacuum is permitted. Under some assumptions that the initial data satisfy appropriate regularity conditions and a compatibility constraint, and that the newly introduced scaling-invariant initial quantities $\bar P^{\frac{ 3}{\gamma}} \left(\|\sqrt{\rho_0}u_0\|_{L^2}^2+\|P_0\|_{L^1}\right) \left(\|\nabla u_0\|_{L^2}^2+\|P_0\|_{L^2}^2\right)$ and $\bar P^{\frac{6}{\gamma}+1} \left(\|\sqrt{\rho_0}u_0\|_{L^2}^2+\|P_0\|_{L^1}\right)^3 \left(\|\nabla u_0\|_{L^2}^2+\|P_0\|_{L^2}^2\right)$ are sufficiently small, the global well-posedness of strong solutions to the two-fluid type model is derived.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17709v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huanyao Wen, Chanxin Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The existence of solutions of Schr\"odinger equations with essence resonance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17776v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The current paper investigates a class of asymptotically linear Schrodinger equations. The Palais-Smale condition fails to hold in this case. Especially under the hypothesis (V2), the lack of compactness occurs at the interaction between nonlinear term and continuum spectrum. For this reason, we introduce a bootstrap iteration approach for elliptic equation on RN. The iteration is self-contained and can be regarded as a generalization of Agmon-Douglis-Nirenberg theorem. The proof characterizes iteration steps independent of the choice of the parameter, which are indeed manipulated by intrinsic natures of potentials and nonlinear terms, and furthermore presents precise estimates for asymptotically linear functions or continuous nonlinear terms restricted on a bounded domain in RN. Additionally, a comparison theorem for the spectrum of Schrodinger operator is also established in this paper. With above preparations, we can get a nontrivial solution without mountain pass geometry, and more importantly make an explicit description of nondegeneracy of solutions with monotonicity hypothesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17776v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic stability of smooth solitons and multi-solitons for the Camassa--Holm equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17793v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish the asymptotic stability of smooth solitons and multi-solitons for the Camassa-Holm (CH) equation in the energy space $H^1(\R)$. We show that solutions initially close to a soliton converge, up to translation, weakly in $H^1(\R)$ as time tends to infinity to a (possibly different) soliton. The analysis is based on a Liouville-type rigidity theorem characterizing solutions that remain localized near a soliton trajectory.
  A central feature of the proof is a complete spectral resolution of the linearized CH operator around a soliton. This linear theory is obtained via the bi-Hamiltonian and integrable structure of the CH equation, through the recursion operator and the completeness of the associated squared eigenfunctions. It provides a substitute for the classical spectral framework used in KdV and gKdV equations, which is unavailable in the nonlocal and variable-coefficient setting of CH.
  The spectral resolution yields sharp decay estimates for the linearized flow in exponentially weighted spaces, which in turn lead to the nonlinear rigidity result and the asymptotic stability of a single soliton. Combined with known orbital stability results, this approach extends to well-ordered trains of solitons and to the explicit multi-soliton solutions generated by the inverse scattering method. As an additional application, we revisit the linearized problems associated with other integrable dispersive equations, including the KdV and mKdV equations, from the perspective of squared-eigenfunction expansions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17793v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robin Ming Chen, Yang Lan, Yue Liu, Zhong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The effect of boundary geometry in nonlocal critical problems with Hardy-Littlewood-Sobolev exponent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17872v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we consider a mixed Dirichlet-Neumann boundary value problem. lem involving Choquard nonlinearity with upper critical exponent in the sense of Hardy- Littlewood Sobolev inequality. We investigate the effect of the geometry of the boundary part where the Neumann condition is prescribed on the existence problem of ground state solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17872v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hichem Chtioui, Tuhina Mukherjee, Lovelesh Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectrum properties of mixed operators under the mixed boundary conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17878v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we describe the spectrum properties of mixed operators, precisely the superposition of the classical Laplace operator and the fractional Laplace operator in the presence of mixed boundary conditions, that is
  \begin{equation} \label{1}
  \left\{\begin{split} \mathcal{L}u\: &amp;= \lambda u,~~\text{in} ~\Omega,
  u&amp;=0~~~~~\text{in} ~~{U^c},
  \mathcal{N}_s(u)&amp;=0 ~~~~~\text{in} ~~{\mathcal{N}},
  \frac{\partial u}{\partial \nu}&amp;=0 ~~~~~\text{in}~~ \partial \Omega \cap \overline{\mathcal{N}},
  \end{split} \right.\tag{$P_\lambda$} \end{equation} where $U= (\Omega \cup {\mathcal{N}} \cup (\partial\Omega\cap\overline{\mathcal{N}}))$, $\Omega \subseteq \mathbb{R}^n$ is a non empty bounded open set with sufficiently smooth boundary $\partial\Omega$, say of class $C^1$, and $\mathcal{D}$, $\mathcal{N}$ are open subsets of $\mathbb{R}^n\setminus{\bar{\Omega }}$ such that $\overline{{\mathcal{D}} \cup {\mathcal{N}}}= \mathbb{R}^n\setminus{\Omega}$, $\mathcal{D} \cap {\mathcal{N}}= \emptyset $ and $\Omega\cup \mathcal{N}$ is a bounded set with sufficiently smooth boundary, $\lambda &gt;0$ is a real parameter and
  $\mathcal{L}= -\Delta+(-\Delta)^{s},~ \text{for}~s \in (0, 1).$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17878v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lovelesh Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cloaking laminate design based on GPT-vanishing structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17932v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a near-cloaking design which is a lamination of a finite number of layers of isotropic materials. The proposed design is an approximation of a cloaking material obtained by pushing forward a multi-coated structure for which the coating cancels the generalized polarization tensors (GPTs) up to several leading orders. The enhanced cloaking effect achieved by the GPT-vanishing structure permits a coarser microscale requirement and reduces the contrast in the constituent isotropic materials, thereby improving constructibility of cloaking laminates compared with designs based on a non-coated structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17932v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eleanor Gemida, Mikyoung Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time decay estimates for localized perturbations around a helical state for the Landau-Lifshitz-Gilbert equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17941v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the dynamics of the Landau--Lifshitz--Gilbert equation with the Dzyaloshinskii--Moriya interaction. The equation admits a family of exact stationary solutions, referred to as helical states, which are periodic in one spatial variable and constant in the others. We investigate the dynamical stability of a helical state with respect to perturbations belonging to suitable Lebesgue and Sobolev spaces. Under a smallness assumption on the initial perturbation, we prove global existence and time decay estimates for solutions, demonstrating that the above helical state is stable. The analysis of the relevant linear operator is carried out via the Bloch--Fourier-wave decomposition, where the eigenvalue problem for the reduced operator is characterized by certain Mathieu equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17941v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ikkei Shimizu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Well-Posedness and Numerical Approximation of a Coupled Darcy-Convection-Diffusion System with Exponential Nonlinearity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17968v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates density driven flow in porous media, focusing on the roles of viscosity contrast, density contrast, and linear adsorption. In this setup, the fluid on top is heavier and more viscous than the fluid below. Under the effect of gravity, this system becomes unstable, and finger-like structures appear. The phenomenon is described mathematically by coupling Darcy's law with a convection-diffusion reaction equation. The nonlinearity in this model arises mainly from the concentration dependence of viscosity and the convective transport term. The existence of a unique pair of weak solutions is shown in both two and three dimensions using the Galerkin approximation method and truncation technique. Moreover, an application of the maximum principle shows non-negativity of the concentration. Additionally, we analyze the long-time behavior of the solution and prove that the concentration converges exponentially to zero in the $L^p$-norm for all $1 \le p \le \infty$ as $t \to \infty.$ To complement the theoretical analysis, we perform numerical simulations based on a pressure formulation. By tracking total kinetic energy and mixing measures over time, we discuss the instability and the mixing efficiency, respectively. The present study reveals that although increasing the density contrast amplifies the total kinetic energy, the marginal impact diminishes with successive increments of density contrast. Similarly, while adsorption acts to suppress mixing, its efficiency in doing so tends to saturate with further increases. These non-linear sensitivities are predicted by our theoretical estimates and confirmed by the numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17968v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahil Kundu, Amiya K. Pani, Manoranjan Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Existence and Finite-Time Blow-Up for a Coupled Darcy-Forchheimer-Brinkman System with Quadratic Reaction Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17984v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a nonlinear system coupling the Darcy-Forchheimer-Brinkman equations with a convection-diffusion-reaction equation, arising in reactive transport through porous media. The model features a nonlinear viscosity coupling, Forchheimer inertial drag, convective transport, and a quadratic reaction term. We establish the existence of local-in-time weak solutions for general initial data. Under the physically relevant condition on initial data $0 \leq c_0 \leq 1$, a maximum principle for the concentration is proved, yielding global existence and uniqueness of weak solutions in two and three space dimensions. For higher regular initial data, we obtain the existence, uniqueness, and continuous dependence of strong solutions. In this regime, the concentration decays exponentially to zero in $L^p$-norm for all $1 \leq p \leq \infty$ with a uniform decay rate. In contrast, if $c_0 &gt; 1$, we demonstrate the occurrence of finite-time blow-up of solutions and derive an explicit upper bound for the blow-up time. Finally, numerical simulations based on the finite element method are presented to illustrate both the decay behavior and finite-time blow-up predicted by the theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17984v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sahil Kundu, Manmohan Vashisth, Manoranjan Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolvent Approach to Atangana--Baleanu Evolution Equations: Laplace Symbols, Mild Solutions, and Regularity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17992v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fractional evolution equations with memory terms are widely used to model anomalous diffusion, viscoelastic response, and hereditary dynamics in physics, biology, and engineering. Among the recently introduced operators, the Atangana--Baleanu (AB) derivatives have attracted considerable attention due to their non-singular Mittag--Leffler kernels. However, their analytic treatment remains limited, as the AB kernel does not fall within the classical Volterra or Bernstein-function frameworks.
  This paper develops a unified resolvent approach for AB-type evolution equations in Banach spaces. Using a Laplace-domain formulation inspired by Hille--Phillips theory, we introduce a fractional resolvent associated with the AB kernel and establish optimal bounds on sectorial contours. Under the natural condition $\beta&lt;1+\alpha$, we construct an AB--Mittag--Leffler resolvent family and obtain a complete representation of mild solutions to the AB Cauchy problem. Sharp stability and regularity estimates of Mittag--Leffler type are derived, including fractional-domain bounds.
  Numerical illustrations confirm the predicted decay, and connections with non-autonomous operators, maximal $L^p$-regularity, and weighted AB kernels are outlined. The results place AB-type equations within a functional-analytic framework comparable to the classical theory for Caputo and Volterra models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17992v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohamed Wakrim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A unified view of nonlinear, nonlocal operators and qualitative properties of associated elliptic and parabolic problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18028v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We put together a general framework to deal with elliptic and parabolic equations associated with (nonlinear) nonlocal (fractional order) operators. Many well-known nonlocal operators enter into our framework, and in addition one may introduce many other, new nonlocal operators that have not yet been considered in the literature. We use the abstract theory of (nonlinear) semigroups generated by subgradients of proper, lower semicontinuous and convex functionals on Hilbert spaces to build a rigorous and applicable framework that works for many classical elliptic operators but also nonlocal or sometimes fractional operators. After recalling the notion of a nonlinear semigroup generated by subgradients and $j$-subgradients of the associated energy functions, we introduce a general class of (nonlinear) nonlocal elliptic type operators and define rigorously subgradients and $j$-subgradients of such functionals that generate (nonlinear) submarkovian semigroups and hence, the abstract Cauchy problem associated with these subgradients and/or $j$-subgradients is wellposed. The existence and the qualitative properties of solutions to these Cauchy problems and the corresponding semigroups are investigated. More precisely, we show some comparison and maximum principles, submarkovian, domination, ultracontractivity properties, and some H\"older type estimates for these semigroups of operators. These results are usually useful in several branches of pure and applied partial differential equations. We finish the paper by giving several examples of nonlocal operators in Euclidean spaces, graphs, metric random walk spaces, fractional Brownian motions, and L\'evy flights, that fit in our general framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18028v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ralph Chill, Mahamadi Warma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heat flow of harmonic maps into CAT($0$)-spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18046v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a new approach to prove the global existence and uniqueness of suitable weak solutions of the heat flow of harmonic mappings into CAT(0) metric spaces. Our method allows also to prove Lipschitz continuity in spatial variables for such solutions into a wide class of CAT$(0)$ spaces, answering a long-standing open problem in the field. Our approach is based on an elliptic regularization of the gradient flow of the Dirichlet energy and even in the case of smooth Riemannian targets provides a novel viewpoint, together with a new Dynamical Variational Principle and a new proof of the celebrated Eells-Sampson theorem. The spatial Lipschitz regularity for such weak solutions is achieved by fully exploiting the variational structure of the problem at the regularized level and introducing a parabolic frequency function of Almgren-Poon type. Our contribution is the first instance of the use of monotonicity methods for parabolic deformations of maps into singular targets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18046v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fang-Hua Lin, Antonio Segatti, Yannick Sire, Changyou Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On fractional semilinear wave equations in non-cylindrical domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18355v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate a class of semilinear wave equations in non-cylindrical time-dependent domains, subject to exterior homogeneous Dirichlet conditions. Under mild regularity and monotonicity assumptions on the evolving spatial domains, we establish existence of weak solutions by two different methods: a constructive time-discretization scheme and a penalty approach. The analysis applies to nonlocal fractional Laplacians and potentials with Lipschitz continuous gradient, and to vector-valued maps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18355v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bonafini Mauro, Le Van Phu Cuong, Molinarolo Riccardo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of the free boundary Willmore problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18388</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18388v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the Willmore problem with free boundary by means of a new {\L}ojasiewicz-Simon gradient inequality for functionals on infinite dimensional manifolds. In contrast to previous works, we do not rely on a gradient-like representation of the Fr\'echet derivative, but merely on an inequality. For the free boundary Willmore flow, we prove that solutions starting sufficiently close to a local minimizer exist for all times and converge. In the static setting, we prove quantitative stability of free boundary Willmore immersions and a local rigidity result in a neighborhood of free boundary minimal surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18388v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Dall'Acqua, Fabian Rupp, Reiner Sch\"atzle, Manuel Schlierf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A brush problem. Homogenization involving thin domains and PDEs in graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18430v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work analyses the homogenization of a linear elliptic equation with Neumann boundary conditions in a comb/brush domain, composed of a fixed base and a family of thin teeth. The teeth are defined as rescalings of order less than or equal to $\varepsilon$ of a model tooth of arbitrary shape. Periodicity in their distribution is not assumed; instead, the existence of an asymptotic limit density $\theta$, which may vanish in certain regions, is assumed. The convergence analysis is performed using an adaptation of the unfolding operator method to a non-periodic framework. Finally, it is shown that, under certain conditions on the geometry of the teeth, the resulting limit problem can be interpreted as a differential equation on a graph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18430v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e M. Arrieta, Joaqu\'in Dom\'inguez-de-Tena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unstable Interface Dynamics for Gravity Stokes Flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18460</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18460v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate some unstable behavior of the interface given by two incompressible fluids of different densities evolving by the regular Stokes law with gravity force. In the unstable scenario, where the denser fluid lies above the lighter fluid, we prove infinite-in-time growth of the length or the curvature of the interface. We support these analytical results with numerical simulations that confirm the predicted growth phenomena. In the stable configuration, where the denser fluid lies below the lighter fluid, we show that certain initial configurations evolve into the unstable regime in finite time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18460v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francisco Gancedo, Rafael Granero-Belinch\'on, Zhongtian Hu, Elena Salguero, Yao Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On decay of solutions to the anisotropic Boussinesq equations near the hydrostatic balance in half space $\mathbb{R}_+^3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18481v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The system of the Boussinesq equations is one of the most important models for geophysical fluids. This paper focuses on the initial-boundary problem of the 3D incompressible anisotropic Boussinesq system with horizontal dissipation. The goal here is to assess the stability property and large-time behavior of perturbations near the hydrostatic balance. By utilizing the structure of the system, the energy methods and the means of bootstrapping argument, we prove the global stability property in the Sobolev space $H^3(\mathbb{R}^3_+)$. After taking a Fourier transform in $x_h = (x_1, x_2)$ and Fourier cosine and sine transforms in $x_3$ for the system, we obtain the decay rates for the global solution itself as well as its derivatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18481v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wangrong Yang, Aibin Zang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semilinear Diffusion Equations on Infinite Graphs: The Dissipative and Lipschitz Cases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18549v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a class of semilinear diffusion equations on infinite, connected, weighted graphs, focusing on two types of nonlinearities: monotone decreasing and Lipschitz continuous. Under minimal structural assumptions on the graph, we establish existence, uniqueness, and regularity of mild solutions for initial data in $\ell^p$ spaces, with $1\leq p&lt;\infty$. Our approach relies on time discretization via an implicit Euler scheme and an exhaustion technique using Dirichlet subgraphs. As a by-product, we obtain existence and uniqueness results for a related time-independent equation. Finite-time extinction and positivity for solutions under a specific forcing term are also proved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18549v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elvise Berchio, Davide Bianchi, Alberto G. Setti, Maria Vallarino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Liquid crystals and topological vorticity: smoothness of mild solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18726v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce several new models whose common feature is to take into account effects from topological vorticity. The macroscopic unknown is driven by a dissipative anomalous diffusion (of SQG-type) and is coupled with the orientation of the crystal, moving by the gradient flow of the energy of maps. The main idea of such models is to have a better insight on the vorticity formulation of the Liquid Crystal Flow and to tackle some regularity issues in the associated conserved geometric motions. One of the advantage of the present PDEs is to capture features of the Navier-Stokes equations (or Euler) through a {\sl scalar} unknown, keeping the advection-diffusion structure of the orientation field. We obtain regularity for mild solutions under natural assumptions for the initial data, which are actually near-optimal. Along the way, we also draw some links with natural models of (anti-)ferromagnets previously investigated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18726v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fanghua Lin, Yannick Sire, Yantao Wu, Yifu Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recovering Riemannian Geometry from Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17166v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an intrinsic reconstruction of Riemannian geometry from a symmetric, strongly local diffusion semigroup. Starting from a diffusion operator and its associated first- and second-order diffusion calculus, we recover the full weighted Riemannian structure of the underlying manifold. In particular, we show that the carre du champ determines a unique smooth Riemannian metric, that the iterated carre du champ encodes curvature, and that the symmetry of the diffusion fixes the Levi-Civita connection and reference measure. As a consequence, the diffusion semigroup determines the global Riemannian manifold uniquely up to isometry. The results provide an information-theoretic perspective on differential geometry in which geometric structure emerges from the intrinsic behavior of diffusion, without assuming any prior metric or coordinate description.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17166v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amandip Sangha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From microscopic social force models to macroscopic continuum models for pedestrian flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17304v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The pedestrian flow is one of the most complex systems, involving large populations of interacting agents. Models at microscopic and macroscopic scales offer different advantages for studying related problems. In general, microscopic models can describe interaction forces at the individual level. Macroscopic models, on the other hand, provide analytical insights into global interactions and long-term overall dynamics, along with efficient numerical simulations and predictions. However, the relationship between models at different scales has rarely been explored. In this study, based on the original microscopic social force model with a reactive optimal route choice strategy, we first derive kinetic equations at the mesoscopic level. By varying the interaction force in different scenarios, we then derive several continuum models at the macroscopic level. Finally, numerical examples are given to evaluate the behaviors of the social force model and our continuum models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17304v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liangze Yang, Hui Yu, Jie Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fully Turbulent Wakes at Low Reynolds Numbers: the Case of the Thin Flat Plate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17341v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the wake flow past a thin two-dimensional flat plate normal to the uniform stream and demonstrate that this flow is turbulent already at a relatively low Reynolds number of $Re = 400$. This is achieved by performing a careful comparison of the results of a DNS of this flow with experimental measurements of wake flows in the same geometric configuration at the Reynolds numbers of $Re=12500, 19700$. This comparison reveals that the distribution of several key quantities, including the mean velocity, Reynolds stresses and different effects contributing to the transport of the turbulent kinetic energy, are, up to measurement uncertainty, the same in these flows. Moreover, the wake flow at $Re = 400$ also features energy spectra characteristic of turbulent flows with intermittency detected in the distributions of the fluctuating strain and rotation rates. In contrast, these features are absent from the results of the DNS of the wake flow at $Re = 150$ where the distribution of the key quantities is also fundamentally different. These results show that the path to transition to turbulence in the wake past a thin flat plate is different from that in the wakes of canonical (i.e., circular or square) cylinders. We also identify possible physical mechanisms that may be responsible for these differences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17341v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isaac T. Rosin, Melanie S. Chapman, Bartosz Protas, Robert J. Martinuzzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harmonic Approximation and Resolvent Estimates for Non-Self-Adjoint Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17643v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove a semiclassical resolvent estimate for a broad class of non-self-adjoint, non-elliptic pseudodifferential operators in the low-lying spectral regime. The proof relies on improved ellipticity properties for the symbol of the operator, which we obtain by imposing a dynamical condition on the average of the real part of the symbol along the Hamiltonian flow generated by its imaginary part. An application of the resolvent estimate to a family of semiclassical Schr\"{o}dinger operators with complex potentials allows us to localize the spectral problem to an $O(h)$-sized neighborhood of the origin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17643v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stepan Malkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on continuous data assimilation for stochastic convective Brinkman-Forchheimer equations in 2D and 3D</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17650v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Continuous data assimilation (CDA) methods, such as the nudging algorithm introduced by Azouani, Olson, and Titi (AOT), have proven to be highly effective in deterministic settings for asymptotically synchronizing approximate solutions with observed dynamics. In this note, we introduce and analyze an algorithm for CDA for the two- and three-dimensional stochastic convective Brinkman-Forchheimer equations (CBFEs) driven by either additive or multiplicative Gaussian noise. The model is believed to provide an accurate description when the flow velocity exceeds the regime of validity of Darcy's law and the porosity remains moderately large. We derive sufficient conditions on the nudging parameter and the spatial resolution of observations that ensure convergence of the assimilated solution to the true stochastic flow. We demonstrate convergence in the mean-square sense, and additionally establish pathwise convergence in the presence of additive noise. The CBFEs, also known as Navier-Stokes equations with damping, exhibit enhanced stability properties due to the presence of nonlinear damping term. In particular, we show that nonlinear damping not only enables the implementation of CDA in three dimensions but also yields improved convergence results in two dimensions when compared to the classical Navier-Stokes equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17650v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kush Kinra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Logarithmic Sobolev inequality in manifolds with nonnegative curvature via the ABP method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17748v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we employ the ABP method developed by Brendle to establish the optimal $L^p$-logarithmic-Sobolev inequality on manifolds with nonnegative Ricci curvature, as well as a sharp $L^2$-logarithmic-Sobolev inequality for submanifolds in manifolds with nonnegative sectional curvature. The sharp constants in both inequalities depend on the asymptotic volume ratio of the ambient manifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17748v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lingen Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eigenvalue optimization in higher dimensions and $p$-harmonic maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17896v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove existence results for optimization problems for the $k$th Laplace eigenvalue on closed Riemannian manifolds of dimension $m \geq 3$, depending on the choice of normalization. One such normalization leads to eigenvalue optimization within a conformal class, for which existence of maximizers was previously known only in dimension two. We also prove that all absolutely continuous maximizers of the normalized eigenvalue functionals are always induced by $p$-harmonic maps into spheres, where $p \in [2,m]$. For $p$ sufficiently close to $m$, the maximizers are smooth, whereas for $p&lt;m$ no bubbling occurs. A key tool in our analysis is the application of techniques from the theory of topological tensor products, which appear to be well suited for studying eigenvalue-related optimization problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17896v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis Vinokurov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbation Theory and the Quantum Rabi-model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.17924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.17924v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the first part of the paper we study a perturbative model of the Rabi system of Quantum Optics. We therefore are able to describe, through Rellich's theory, an analytic expansion of finite families, but of any fixed length, of eigenvalues. In particular, we prove that for finite families of eigenvalues the Braak conjecture holds. In the second part we study the asymptotics of the Weyl spectral counting function of a class of systems that generalize the Quantum Rabi Model to an $N$-level atom ($N\geq3$) with $N-1$ cavity modes of the electromagnetic field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.17924v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcello Malagutti, Alberto Parmeggiani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The global attractor of the Toner-Tu-Swift-Hohenberg equations of active turbulence and its properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18233v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Toner-Tu-Swift-Hohenberg (TTSH) equations are one of the basic equations that are used to model turbulent behaviour in active matter, specifically the swarming of bacteria in suspension. They combine features of the incompressible Navier-Stokes, the Toner-Tu and Swift-Hohenberg equations, together with the important properties that they are linearly driven, and that the Laplacian diffusion is taken to be negative in combination with hyper-dissipation. We prove that the TTSH equations possess a finite-dimensional compact global attractor on the periodic domain $\mathbb{T}^d$ ($d=2,3$) and we establish explicit estimates for its Lyapunov dimension which agree with the heuristic prediction based on the Swift-Hohenberg length scale. The predominance of this length scale (as a vortex length scale) has been observed in both numerical and experimental studies of bacterial turbulence, so our methods and results provide a rigorous theoretical foundation for this phenomenon. We also carry out pseudospectral direct numerical simulations of these PDEs in dimension $d=2$ through which we obtain Lyapunov spectra for representative parameter values. We show that our numerical results are consistent with the analytically derived rigorous bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18233v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel W. Boutros, Kolluru Venkata Kiran, John D. Gibbon, Rahul Pandit</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Validity of the stochastic Ginzburg-Landau approximation in higher space dimensions -A Wiener algebra approach-</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18406v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider an anisotropic $d$-dimensional Swift-Hohenberg model $ \mathcal{O}(\varepsilon^2) $-close to the first instability, where $ 0 &lt; \varepsilon \ll 1 $ is a small perturbation parameter. This model for pattern formation is perturbed with additive noise in time and space. By a multiple scaling ansatz we derive a stochastic $ d $-dimensional Ginzburg-Landau equation for the approximate description of the bifurcating solutions. We prove the validity of the approximation by this amplitude equation on its natural time scale in case of $ d $-dimensional periodic domains of length $ \mathcal{O}(1/\varepsilon) $ for the Swift-Hohenberg model under suitable conditions on the additive noise. In detail, we prove the validity of this approximation for noise whose set of Fourier coefficients with respect to $ x $ is in $ \ell^1 $ for fixed $ t \geq 0 $. Moreover, we improve existing approximation results in the sense that the stable part of the noise can be larger.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18406v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Logioti, Guido Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A stabilized finite element method for a flow problem arising from 4D flow magnetic resonance imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18454v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work we propose, {analyze}, and validate a stabilized finite element method for a flow problem arising from the assessment of {4D Flow Magnetic Resonance Imaging quality}. Starting from the Navier-Stokes equation and splitting its velocity as the MRI-observed one (considered a datum) plus an ``observation error'', a modified Navier-Stokes problem is derived. This procedure allows us to estimate the quality of the measured velocity fields, while also providing an alternative approach to pressure reconstruction, thereby avoiding invasive procedures. Since equal-order approximations have become a popular choice for problems linked to pressure recovery from MRI images, we design a stabilized finite element method allowing equal-order interpolations for velocity and pressure. In the linearized version of the resulting model, we prove stability and (optimal order) error estimates and test the method with a variety of numerical experiments testing both the linearized case and the more realistic nonlinear one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18454v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Barrenechea, Cristian C\'arcamo, Abner Poza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Justification of a Relaxation Approximation for the Navier-Stokes-Cahn-Hilliard System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18463v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Navier-Stokes-Cahn-Hilliard (NSCH) system governs the diffuse-interface dynamics of two incompressible and immiscible fluids. We consider a relaxation approximation of the NSCH system that is composed by a system of first-order hyperbolic balance laws and second-order elliptic operators. We prove first that the solutions of an initial boundary value problem for the approximation recover the limiting NSCH system for vanishing relaxation parameters. To cope with the singular limit we exploit the fact that the approximate solutions dissipate an almost quadratic energy, and employ the relative entropy-framework. In the second part of the work we provide numerical evidence for the analytical results, even in flow regimes not covered by the assumptions needed for the theoretical results. Using a novel marker-and-cell conservative finite-difference approach for both the approximation and the limit system, we are able to compute physically relevant interfacial flow problems including Ostwald ripening and high-velocity flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18463v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Giesselmann, Jens Keim, Fabio Leotta, Christian Rohde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chemotaxis-inspired PDE models of airborne infectious disease transmission: epidemiologically-motivated mathematical and numerical analyses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18703</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18703v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Partial differential equation (PDE) models for infectious diseases, while less common than their ordinary differential equation (ODE) counterparts, have found successful applications for many years. Such models are typically of reaction-diffusion type, and model spatial propagation as a diffusive process. However, given the complex nature of human mobility, such models are limited in their ability to describe airborne infectious diseases in human populations. Recent work has advocated for the inclusion of an additional chemotaxis-type term as an alternative; spatial propagation of infection fronts is assumed additionally to flow from low-to-high concentrations of susceptible populations. The present work extends the study of such models by providing an epidemiologically interpretable analysis, directly connecting model behavior to information readily available to policymakers. In particular, we derive a spatially-aware basic reproduction number, which accounts for spatial heterogeneity in population density. Furthermore, we discuss several important aspects concerning the numerical solution of the model, including the introduction of a stabilization scheme. Finally, we perform a series of simulation studies in the Italian region of Lombardy (severely affected by the COVID-19 outbreak in 2020) and in the US state of Georgia, in which we demonstrate the model's potential to better capture important spatiotemporal dynamics observed in real-world data compared to pure reaction-diffusion models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18703v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Viguerie, Mal\'u Grave, Alvaro L. G. A. Coutinho, Alessandro Veneziani, Thomas J. R. Hughes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Area-minimizing capillary cones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.18794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.18794v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct non-flat minimal capillary cones with bi-orthogonal symmetry groups for any dimension and contact angle. These cones interpolate between rescalings of a singular solution to the one-phase problem and the free-boundary cone obtained by halving a Lawson cone along a hyperplane of symmetry. The existence and uniqueness of such cones is proved by solving a nonlinear free boundary equation parametrized by the contact angle and obtaining monotonicity properties for the solutions. The constructed cones are minimizing in ambient dimension $8$ or higher, for appropriate contact angles, demonstrating that the regularity theory for minimizing capillary hypersurfaces can have singularities in codimension $7$ and completing the capillary regularity theory for contact angles near $\pi/2$. We further develop the connection between capillary hypersurfaces and solutions of the one-phase problem, consequently producing new examples of singular minimizing free boundaries for the Alt-Caffarelli functional.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.18794v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjy Firester, Raphael Tsiamis, Yipeng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low regularity ill-posedness and shock formation for 3D ideal compressible MHD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.10647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2110.10647v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The study of magnetohydrodynamics (MHD) significantly boosts the understanding and development of solar physics, planetary dynamics and controlled nuclear fusion. Dynamical properties of the MHD system involve nonlinear interactions of waves with multiple travelling speeds (the fast and slow magnetosonic waves, the Alfv\'{e}n wave and the entropy wave). One intriguing topic is the shock phenomena accompanied by the magnetic field, which have been affirmed by astronomical observations. However, permitting the residence of all above multi-speed waves, mathematically, whether one can prove shock formation for three dimensional (3D) MHD is still open. The multiple-speed nature of the MHD system makes it fascinating and challenging. In this paper, we report our recent progress in answering the above question. For 3D ideal compressible MHD, we construct planar symmetric examples of shock formation allowing the presence of all characteristic waves with multiple wave speeds. This also answers a question raised by Majda on conservation law in 1984. Building on our construction, we further prove that the Cauchy problem for 3D ideal MHD is $H^2$ ill-posed. And this is caused by the shock formation. In particular, when the magnetic field is absent, we also provide a desired low-regularity ill-posedness result for the 3D compressible Euler equations, and it is sharp with respect to the regularity of the fluid velocity. Our proof for 3D MHD is based on a coalition of a carefully designed algebraic approach and a geometric approach. To trace the nonlinear interactions of various waves, we algebraically decompose the 3D ideal MHD equations into a $7\times 7$ non-strictly hyperbolic system. Via detailed calculations, we reveal its hidden subtle structures. With them we give a complete description of MHD dynamics up to the earliest singular event, when a shock forms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2110.10647v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinliang An, Haoyang Chen, Silu Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Cauchy problems for the 2D compressible Euler equations and ideal MHD system are ill-posed in $H^\frac{7}{4}(\mathbb{R}^2)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.14003</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.14003v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In a fractional Sobolev space $H^s(\mathbb{R}^2)$ with $s\leq\frac74$, we prove the low-regularity ill-posedness for the 2D compressible Euler equations and the 2D ideal compressible MHD system. Our ill-posedness results match the $H^\frac74$ regularity threshold for the 2D compressible Euler system with respect to the fluid velocity and density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.14003v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinliang An, Haoyang Chen, Silu Yin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new space of generalised vector-valued functions of bounded variation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.11538v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In [Dal Maso and Toader, NoDEA 2022], the authors introduced the space $GBV_\star(A)$ to minimise a class of functionals whose study is motivated by fracture mechanics. In this paper, we extend the definition of $GBV_\star(A)$ to the vectorial case, introducing the space $GBV_\star(A;\mathbb{R}^k)$. We study the main properties of $GBV_\star(A;\mathbb{R}^k)$ and prove a lower semicontinuity result useful for minimisation purposes. With the Direct Method in mind, we adapt the arguments of [Dal Maso and Toader, NoDEA 2022] to show that minimising sequences in $GBV_\star(A;\mathbb{R}^k)$ can be modified to obtain a minimising sequence converging $\mathcal{L}^d$-a.e in $A$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.11538v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00030-025-01063-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>NoDEA Nonlinear Differential Equations Appl. 32, 59 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Davide Donati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H\"older regularity of harmonic functions on metric measure spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20789v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a H\"older regularity condition for harmonic functions on metric measure spaces and prove that, under a slow volume regular condition and an upper heat kernel estimate, the H\"older regularity condition, the weak Bakry-\'Emery non-negative curvature condition, H\"older continuity of the heat kernel (with or without exponential terms), and the near-diagonal lower bound for the heat kernel are equivalent. As applications, first, we establish the validity of the so-called generalized reverse H\"older inequality on the Sierpi\'nski carpet cable system, resolving an open problem left by Devyver, Russ, Yang (Int. Math. Res. Not. IMRN (2023), no. 18, 15537-15583). Second, we prove that two-sided heat kernel estimates alone imply gradient estimates for the heat kernel on strongly recurrent fractal-like cable systems, improving the main results of the aforementioned paper. Third, we obtain H\"older (Lipschitz) estimates for the heat kernel on strongly recurrent metric measure spaces, extending the classical Li-Yau gradient estimate for the heat kernel on Riemannian manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20789v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.aim.2026.110797</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advances in Mathematics, March 2026, Article 110797, Volume 488</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jin Gao, Meng Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Blow-up dynamics for radial self-dual Chern-Simons-Schr\"odinger equation with prescribed asymptotic profile</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13274v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct finite energy blow-up solutions for the radial self-dual Chern-Simons-Schr\"odinger equation with a continuum of blow-up rates. Our result stands in stark contrast to the rigidity of blow-up of $H^{3}$ solutions proved by the first author for equivariant index $m \geq 1$, where the soliton-radiation interaction is too weak to admit the present blow-up scenarios. It is optimal (up to an endpoint) in terms of the range of blow-up rates and the regularity of the asymptotic profiles in view of the authors' previous proof of $H^{1}$ soliton resolution for the self-dual Chern-Simons-Schr\"odinger equation in any equivariance class.
  Our approach is a backward construction combined with modulation analysis, starting from prescribed asymptotic profiles and deriving the corresponding blow-up rates from their strong interaction with the soliton. In particular, our work may be seen as an adaptation of the method of Jendrej-Lawrie-Rodriguez (developed for energy critical equivariant wave maps) to the Schr\"odinger case. However, the Schr\"odinger nature of the equation (in particular, the lack of finite speed of propagation) and the optimal range (up to the $H^{1}$-endpoint) of our blow-up construction give rise to new challenges. Notably, the construction of (approximate) radiation from the prescribed asymptotic profile is one of our key novelties and might be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13274v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kihyun Kim, Soonsik Kwon, Sung-Jin Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Existence and Uniqueness for a Porous-Medium-Type Diffusion Model with Time-Dependent Growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19823v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates a nonlinear diffusion equation, characterized by a power-law dispersal mechanism and a time-dependent growth rate in a bounded domain with homogeneous Dirichlet boundary conditions. We establish three main theoretical contributions: first, the existence and uniqueness of separable classical solutions via a transformation into a stationary sublinear elliptic framework; second, a generalized comparison principle with respect to both initial conditions and growth rates; and third, a general existence and uniqueness result for non-separable solutions via a monotone iteration method. The connection between the temporal dynamics and the spatial profile is made explicit, providing analytical expressions for the solution. Furthermore, we demonstrate the model's effectiveness as a successful application in digital image denoising, showing superior robustness compared to the classical Perona--Malik model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19823v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dragos-Patru Covei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Existence and Incompressible Limit of the Cauchy Problem for 2D Compressible Navier-Stokes Equations with Large Bulk Viscosity and Large Initial Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02497v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the Cauchy problem for the barotropic compressible Navier-Stokes equations in $\mathbb{R}^2$ with the constant state as far field, which may be vacuum or non-vacuum. Under the assumption of a sufficiently large bulk viscosity coefficient, we establish the global existence and large time behavior of weak, strong, and classical solutions. It should be mentioned that this result is obtained without any restrictions on the size of the initial data. Moreover, we demonstrate that as the bulk viscosity coefficient tends to infinity, the solutions of the compressible Navier-Stokes equations converge to those of the inhomogeneous incompressible Navier-Stokes equations. The incompressible limit of the weak solutions holds even without requiring the initial velocity to be divergence-free.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02497v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qinghao Lei, Chengfeng Xiong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative analysis for $L^2$-estimates in linear elliptic equations via divergence-free transformation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.04940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.04940v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper establishes an explicit $L^2$-estimate for weak solutions $u$ to linear elliptic equations in divergence form with general coefficients and external source term $f$, stating that the $L^2$-norm of $u$ over $U$ is bounded by a constant multiple of the $L^2$-norm of $f$ over $U$. In contrast to classical approaches based on compactness arguments, the proposed method, which employs a divergence-free transformation method, provides a computable and explicit constant $C&gt;0$. The $L^2$-estimate remains robust even when there is no zero-order term, and the analysis further demonstrates that the constant $C&gt;0$ decreases as the diffusion coefficient or the zero-order term increases. These quantitative results provide a rigorous foundation for applications such as a posteriori error estimates in Physics-Informed Neural Networks (PINNs), where explicit error bounds are essential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.04940v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haesung Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Biharmonic nonlinear vector field equations in $\mathbb{R}^4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14640v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Following the approach of Brezis and Lieb, we prove the existence of a ground state solution for the biharmonic nonlinear vector field equations in the limiting case of space dimension $4$. Our results complete those obtained by Mederski and Siemianowski for dimensions $d\geq 5$. We also extend the biharmonic logarithmic Sobolev inequality to dimension $4$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14640v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ioannis Arkoudis, Panayotis Smyrnelis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The 2D Chern-Simons-Schr{\"o}dinger system reduced to 1D</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21464v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study a mean-field model for a system of 2D abelian anyons, given by the dynamics of a Schr{\"o}dinger matter field coupled to a Chern-Simons gauge field. We derive an effective 1D equation by adding a strongly anisotropic trapping potential (wave-guide) acting on the Schr{\"o}dinger field, and tracing out the tight confinement direction. The effective dynamics in the loose direction of the wave-guide turns out to be governed by the classical 1D quintic NLS equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21464v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Rougerie (UMPA-ENSL), Qiyun Yang (UMPA-ENSL)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functions of bounded Musielak-Orlicz-type deformation and anisotropic Total Generalized Variation for image-denoising problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09237v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the first part of this paper we introduce the space of bounded deformation fields with generalized Orlicz growth. We establish their main properties, provide a modular representation, and characterize a decomposition of the modular into an absolutely continuous part and a singular part weighted via a recession function. A further analysis in the variable exponent case is also provided. The second part of the paper contains a notion of Musielak-Orlicz anisotropic Total Generalized Variation. We establish a duality representation, and show well-posedness of the corresponding image reconstruction problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09237v4</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giacomo Bertazzoni, Elisa Davoli, Samuele Ricc\`o, Elvira Zappale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary pointwise regularity for the divergence form elliptic boundary problem on uniform domain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.17690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.17690v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the boundary pointwise regularity for the divergence form elliptic boundary problem on domains with rough boundaries, specifically uniform domains. In general, it is not straightforward to define weak solutions for non-zero boundary data on such domains. To address this, we introduce a novel definition of weak solutions tailored to the setting of uniform domains. Remarkably, this definition allows for the analysis of the regularity of weak solutions. In particular, by establishing an energy inequality, we prove the boundary pointwise $C^\alpha$ regularity by using compactness methods under the admissible condition. Furthermore, by exploiting the the linear structure of solutions with respective to the harmonic functions, we establish boundary pointwise $C^{1,\alpha}$ and $C^{2,\alpha}$ regularities when the boundary data and the domain boundary are pointwise $C^{1,\alpha}$ and $C^{2,\alpha }$, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.17690v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianyu Guan, Lihe Wang, Chunqin Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Functional a posteriori estimates for the fractional Laplacian problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.12664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.12664v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The paper is concerned with a posteriori estimates for approximations of boundary value problems generated by the spectral fractional Laplace operator. The derivation is based upon the Stinga--Torrea extension, which generalizes the Caffarelli--Silvestre extension and transfers the corresponding nonlocal problem in a bounded domain to a local problem of higher dimensionality. A posteriori estimates are first derived for this local problem. Two-sided error bounds for the original problem follow from them. The estimates are fully computable and contain no conditions and constants depending on a method or mesh used to compute an approximation. They are valid for any energy admissible approximation of the extended problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.12664v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Nazarov, Sergey Repin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Support growth of vorticity for bi-rotational Euler flows in high dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18335v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study incompressible Euler equations in $\mathbb{R}^d$ with $d \ge 4$ under bi-rotational symmetry without swirl, which reduces the Euler equations to a scalar vorticity advection in the first quadrant. We show that patch type initial vorticities exhibit infinite growth of the support diameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18335v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>In-Jee Jeong, Deokwoo Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification results for bounded positive solutions to the critical $p$-Laplace equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23243v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: By providing optimal or nearly optimal integral estimates, we show that every positive, bounded or moderately growing, local weak solution to the critical $p$-Laplace equation in $\mathbb{R}^n$, with $n\geq 3$, and whose infimum over a ball behaves properly must be a bubble.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23243v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulio Ciraolo, Michele Gatti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Singular Integrals and Quantitative Rectifiability in Parabolic Space and the Heisenberg Group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26934v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: David and Semmes proved that if all CZOs (of suitable dimension) are bounded with respect to an Ahlfors regular measure, then the measure is uniformly rectifiable. We extend this theorem to the parabolic space and the first Heisenberg group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26934v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Hoffman, Ben Jaye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Revisiting of the Pressure Elimination for a Fluid-Structure PDE Interaction and Its Implications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.06615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.06615v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we construct a novel technique for eliminating and recovering the pressure for a fluid-structure interaction model. This pressure elimination methodology is valid for general bounded Lipschitz domains. The specific fluid-structure interaction (FSI) that we consider is a well-known model of Stokes flow coupled to a system of linear elasticity, which constitutes a coupled parabolic-hyperbolic system. The coupling between the two distinct PDE dynamics occurs across a boundary interface, with each of the components evolving on its own distinct geometry, with the domains of each being Lipschitz. Our new pressure elimination technique admits of an explicit $C_{0}$-semigroup generator representation $\mathcal{A}: D(\mathcal{A}) \subset \mathbf{H} \to \mathbf{H}$, where $\mathbf{H}$ is the associated finite energy space of fluid-structure initial data. This leads to a novel proof of well-posedness in the explicit semigroup sense of the continuous PDE, now valid in general geometries. Subsequently, we illustrate an immediate consequence of our semigroup well-posedness result; namely a finite element method (FEM) with associated rates of convergence for a static version of the FSI, posed on polygonal domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.06615v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Avalos, Yuhao Mu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Fujita Phenomenon for a Forced Spatio-Temporal Fractional Diffusion Equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.19424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.19424v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the Cauchy problem for a semilinear spatio--temporal fractional diffusion equation with a time-dependent forcing term: \[ \partial_t^\alpha u + (-\Delta)^{\mathsf{s}} u = |u|^p + t^{\sigma}\,\mathbf{w}(x), \quad (t,x) \in (0,\infty) \times \mathbb{R}^N, \] where $\alpha,\mathsf{s}\in (0,1)$, $\sigma &gt; -\alpha$, and $\mathbf{w}$ is a given continuous function. Here $\partial_t^\alpha$ denotes the Caputo fractional derivative. Our main results are threefold. First, we establish local-in-time existence of mild solutions and prove finite-time blow-up in the subcritical regime, under the positivity condition \[ \int\limits_{\mathbb{R}^N} \mathbf{w}(x)\,dx &gt; 0. \] Second, in the supercritical case $-\alpha &lt; \sigma &lt; 0$, we prove the global existence of solutions for sufficiently small initial data and forcing term, and we identify the corresponding critical exponent as \[ p_F=\frac{N\alpha-2\mathsf{s}\sigma}{N\alpha-2\mathsf{s}(\alpha+\sigma)}. \] Finally, within this supercritical range, we obtain a more robust global existence result under weaker assumptions that require only local smallness and controlled growth of the data. To the best of our knowledge, a sharp Fujita-type threshold for fully spatio-temporal fractional diffusion equations with time-growing external forcing has not been previously established.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.19424v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rihab Ben Belgacem, Mohamed Majdoub</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry and uniqueness of the positive solution for the critical Hartree equation on the Heisenberg group</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.20264</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.20264v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We apply the moving plane method in integral forms to classify the positive solutions of the critical Hartree equation on Heisenberg group \begin{equation}\label{0.1}
  -\Delta_{\mathbb{H}}u=\left(\int_{\mathbb{H}^{n}}\frac{|u(\xi)|^{Q^{\ast}_{\mu}}}{|\zeta^{-1}\xi|^{\mu}}\mathrm{d}\xi\right)|u|^{Q^{\ast}_{\mu}-2}u,~~~\zeta,\xi\in\mathbb{H}^{n}, \end{equation} where $\Delta_{\mathbb{H}}$ denotes the Kohn Laplacian, $u(\xi)$ is a real-valued function, $Q=2n+2$ is the homogeneous dimension of $\mathbb{H}^{n}$, $\mu\in (0,Q)$ is a real parameter and $Q^{\ast}_{\mu}=\frac{2Q-\mu}{Q-2}$ is the upper critical exponent associated with the Hardy-Littlewood-Sobolev inequality on the Heisenberg group. By introducing the $\mathbb{H}$-reflection, we prove that the solutions of (\ref{0.1}) are cylindrical, upto Heisenberg translation and suitable scaling of function \begin{equation*}\label{0.2} u_{0}(\zeta)=u_{0}(z,t)=\left((1+|z|^{2})^{2}+t^{2}\right)^{-\frac{Q-2}{4}},~~~\zeta=(z,t)\in \mathbb{H}^{n}. \end{equation*} Furthermore, we show that these positive solutions are also CR inversion-symmetric with respect to the unit CC sphere. Consequently, we establish the uniqueness of positive solutions to equation (\ref{0.1}).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.20264v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuijin Zhang, Jialin Wang, Yu Zheng, Xiang Li, Jijie Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry conditions for spacetime observability of wave equations on the torus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09873v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study observability for the one-dimensional wave equation on the torus from spacetime measurable observation sets. While the Geometric Control Condition (GCC) provides a sufficient criterion in many classical settings, it is no longer sufficient in this framework.
  We construct explicit counterexamples showing the failure of observability despite the validity of GCC. This leads to the introduction of an additional symmetry condition on the observation set, referred to as the Observable Symmetry Condition (OSC).
  We prove that observability holds if and only if both GCC and OSC are satisfied. We also show that unique continuation holds if and only if both OSC and a weak form of GCC are satisfied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09873v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingrui Niu, Ming Wang, Shengquan Xiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wave propagation for 1-dimensional reaction-diffusion equations with nonzero random drift</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.21906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.21906v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the wave propagation for a reaction-diffusion equation on the real line, with a random drift and Fisher-Kolmogorov-Petrovskii-Piscounov (FKPP) type nonlinear reaction. We show that when the average drift is positive, the asymptotic wave fronts propagating to the positive and negative directions are both pushed in the negative direction, leading to the possibility that both wave fronts propagate toward negative infinity. Our proof is based on the Large Deviations Principle for diffusion processes in random environments, as well as an analysis of the Feynman-Kac formula. Such probabilistic arguments also reveal the underlying physical mechanism of the wave fronts formation: the drift acts as an external field that shifts the (quenched) free-energy reference level without altering the intrinsic fluctuation structure of the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.21906v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dihang Guan, Hui He, Wenqing Hu, Jiaojiao Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extinction and persistence criteria in non-local Klausmeier model of vegetation dynamics on flat landscapes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06681</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.06681v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the dynamics of vegetation patterns in water-limited ecosystems using a generalized Klausmeier model that incorporates non-local plant dispersal within a finite habitat. We establish the well-posedness of the system and provide a rigorous analysis of the conditions required for vegetation survival. Our results identify a critical patch size governed by the trade-off between local growth and boundary losses; habitats smaller than this threshold lead to inevitable extinction. Furthermore, we derive a critical maximal biomass density below which the population collapses to a desert state, regardless of the domain size. We determine stability criteria for stationary solutions and describe the emergence of stable, non-trivial biomass distributions. Numerical experiments comparing sub-Gaussian and super-Gaussian kernels confirm that non-local dispersal mechanisms, particularly those with fat tails, enhance ecosystem resilience by allowing vegetation to persist in smaller, fragmented habitats than predicted by classical local diffusion models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06681v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maciej Tadej, Ricardo Martinez-Garcia, Michael Hecht</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characteristics of drift effects arising from nonlinear symmetry of the quasi-geostrophic equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.10185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.10185v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper compares two similar diffusion equations that appear in meteorology. One is the quasi-geostrophic equation, and the other is the convection-diffusion equation. Both are two-dimensional bilinear equations, and the order of differentiation is the same. Naturally, their scales also coincide. However, the direction in which the nonlinear effects act differs: one acts along the isothermal surface, while the other acts along the temperature gradient in a specified direction. The main assertion quantifies this difference through the large-time behavior of their solutions. In particular, the nonlinear distortions in the asymptotic profiles of both equations are compared. In this context, the spatial symmetry of the first approximation plays a crucial role, but the solutions require no symmetry. As an appendix, the mixed problem of those models are studied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.10185v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masakazu Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrating the probe and singular sources methods: IV. IPS function for the Schr\"odinger equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14779v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The integrated theory of the probe and singular sources methods (IPS) is developed for an inverse obstacle problem governed by the stationary Schr\"odinger equation in a bounded domain. The unknown obstacles are penetrable, and their surface is modeled by a part of the support of the potential in the governing equation. The main results concern an analytical detection method for these obstacles from the Dirichlet-to-Neumann map. They consist of three parts: a singular sources method via the probe method using a solution with higher-order singularity for the governing equation of the background medium; the discovery of an IPS function whose two ways of decomposition give us the indicator functions for both the probe and singular sources methods; a completely integrated version of both methods, which means their indicator functions coincide. Furthermore, a result on Side B of IPS is also given, concerning the blowing-up property of a sequence calculated from the Dirichlet-to-Neumann map.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14779v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaru Ikehata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random models for singular SPDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.09596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.09596v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We give a proof of the convergence of the BHZ renormalized model associated with the generalized (KPZ) equation that does not require the full strength of the BPHZ renormalisation. Our approach is based on a convenient form of chaos decomposition. The other key ingredient is a generalisation of the Hairer-Quastel convergence theorem for Feynman diagrams with certain decorations encoding Taylor remainders. With these ideas we are able to construct the model for the generalised KPZ equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.09596v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Bailleul, Y. Bruned</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral comparison of compound cocycles generated by delay equations in Hilbert spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.02537v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study linear cocycles generated by nonautonomous delay equations in a suitable Hilbert space and their extensions, called compound cocycles, to exterior powers. Using a recent version of the frequency theorem, we develop analytical techniques for comparing spectral properties, such as uniform exponential dichotomies, between such cocycles and semigroups generated by stationary equations. These methods are based on properties related to regularity and structure in PDEs associated with delay equations. In particular, the developed machinery leads to effective robust criteria that guarantee the absence of closed invariant contours on global attractors arising in nonlinear problems and are expected to ensure global stability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.02537v5</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Anikushin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Post-Lie algebras of derivations and regularity structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.02484</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.02484v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Given a commutative algebra $\mathcal{A}$, we exhibit a canonical structure of post-Lie algebra on the space $\mathcal{A}\otimes {\rm Der}(\mathcal{A})$ where ${\rm Der}(\mathcal{A})$ is the space of derivations on $\mathcal{A}$, in order to use the machinery given by Oudom-Guin (2008) and Ebrahimi-Fard--Lundervold--Munthe-Kaas (2015), and to define a Hopf algebra structure on the associated enveloping algebra with a natural action on $\mathcal{A}$. We apply these results to the setting of Linares-Otto-Tempelmayr (2023), giving a simpler and more efficient construction of their action and extending the recent work by Bruned-Katsetsiadis (2023). This approach gives an optimal setting to perform explicit computations in the associated structure group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.02484v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.4171/JCA/119</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jean-David Jacques, Lorenzo Zambotti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Architecture independent generalization bounds for overparametrized deep ReLU networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05695v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that overparametrized neural networks are able to generalize with a test error that is independent of the level of overparametrization, and independent of the Vapnik-Chervonenkis (VC) dimension. We prove explicit bounds that only depend on the metric geometry of the test and training sets, on the regularity properties of the activation function, and on the operator norms of the weights and norms of biases. For overparametrized deep ReLU networks with a training sample size bounded by the input space dimension, we explicitly construct zero loss minimizers without use of gradient descent, and prove a uniform generalization bound that is independent of the network architecture. We perform computational experiments of our theoretical results with MNIST, and obtain agreement with the true test error within a 22 % margin on average.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05695v5</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anandatheertha Bapu, Thomas Chen, Chun-Kai Kevin Chien, Patricia Mu\~noz Ewald, Andrew G. Moore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence of Schr\"odinger operators on domains with scaled resonant potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02480v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider Schr\"odinger operators on a bounded, smooth domain of dimension $d \ge 2$ with Dirichlet boundary conditions and a properly scaled potential, which depends only on the distance to the boundary of the domain. Our aim is to analyse the convergence of these operators as the scaling parameter tends to zero. If the scaled potential is resonant, the limit in strong resolvent sense is a Robin Laplacian with boundary coefficient expressed in terms of the mean curvature of the boundary. A counterexample shows that norm resolvent convergence cannot hold in general in this setting. If the scaled potential is non-resonant and satisfies an explicit assumption on the smallness of the negative part, the limit in strong resolvent sense is the Dirichlet Laplacian. We conjecture that we can drop this additional assumption in the non-resonant case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02480v2</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Lotoreichik, Olaf Post</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on isothermic coordinate systems for spacelike surfaces with constant mean curvature in Lorentz-Minkowski space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.07516v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this note, we use isothermic coordinate systems to explore global properties of space-like surfaces with constant mean curvature in the Lorentz-Minkowski three-space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.07516v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Kawakami, Kaito Satake</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bruck conjecture for solutions of first-order partial differential equations in Cm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.02576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.02576v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the Br\"{u}ck conjecture \cite{Bruck-1996} by interpreting it through solutions of first-order partial differential equations in several complex variables. Our results show that the Br\"{u}ck conjecture \cite{Bruck-1996} in $\mathbb{C}^m$ holds under certain additional conditions. In pursuit of this objective, we also establish a Borel-Caratheodory theorem in $\mathbb{C}^m$ and derive several fundamental results on the order and hyper-order of entire functions in higher dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.02576v2</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sujoy Majumder, Nabadwip Sarkar, Debabrata Pramanik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Navier-Stokes Equations with Fractional Dissipation and Associated Doubly Stochastic Yule Cascades</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10806v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We identify a probabilistic structure known as self-similar doubly stochastic Yule (DSY) cascade associated with the deterministic Navier-Stokes equations (NSE) in $\mathbb{R}^d$ with fractional dissipation $(-\Delta)^\gamma$. Interestingly, such a structure is well-defined only in the scaling-supercritical regime $\gamma\in(\frac{1}{2},\frac{d+2}{4})$. We then characterize parametric regions of $(d,\gamma)$ that correspond to the non-explosive, explosive, and hyperexplosive behavior of the DSY cascade. Stochastic solution processes are constructed recursively, and their expectations yield solutions to the fractional NSE whenever these expectations exist. Explosion and geometric properties of the DSY cascade are then exploited to establish non-uniqueness and finite-time blowup results for a scalar partial differential equation associated with the fractional NSE thanks to a majorization principle for stochastic solution processes. In the special case $d=2$, we derive a closed form for the solution process and prove the finite-time loss of integrability of the solution process for sufficiently large initial data. Notably, this lack of integrability does not necessarily imply finite-time blowup of solutions to the fractional NSE. Indeed, for vortex-flow initial data, we show that the solution can be continued beyond the time of integrability breakdown by employing a notion of averaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10806v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Radu Dascaliuc, Tuan N. Pham, Enrique Thomann, Edward C. Waymire</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Analysis of Willmore Surfaces and its Generalizations in Higher Dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01777v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We review recent progress concerning the analysis of Lagrangians on immersions into $\mathbb{R}^d$ depending on the first and second fundamental forms and their covariant derivatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01777v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tian Lan, Dorian Martino, Tristan Rivi\`ere</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-linear equation $\Delta_pv+av^q=0$ on manifolds with integral bounded Ricci curvature and geometric applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01837v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider nonexistence and gradient estimate for solutions to $\Delta_pv +av^{q}=0$ defined on a complete Riemannian manifold with $\chi$-type Sobolev inequality. A Liouville theorem on this equation is established if the lying manifold $(M, g)$ supports a $\chi$-type Sobolev inequality and the $L^{\frac{\chi}{\chi-1}}$ norm of $\mathrm{Ric}_-(x)$ of $(M, g)$ is bounded from upper by some constant depending on $\dim(M)$, Sobolev constant $\mathbb{S}_\chi(M)$ and volume growth order of geodesic ball $B_r\subset M$. This extends and improves some conclusions obtained recently by Ciraolo, Farina and Polvara [17], but our method employed in this paper is different from their "P-function" method. In particular, for such manifold with a $\chi$-type Sobolev inequality, we give the lower estimate of volume growth of geodesic ball. If $\chi\leq n/(n-2)$, we also establish the local logarithm gradient estimate for positive solutions to this equation under the condition $\mathrm{Ric}_-(x)$ is $L^\gamma$-integrable where $\gamma&gt;{\frac{\chi}{\chi-1}}$.
  As topological applications of main results(see Corollary 1.8) we show that for a complete noncompact Riemannian manifold on which the Sobolev inequality (1.8) holds true, $\dim(M)=n\geq 3$ and $\mathrm{Ric}(x)\geq 0$ outside some geodesic ball $B(o,R_0)$, there exists a positive constant $C(n)$ depending only on $n$ such that, if $$\|\mathrm{Ric}_-\|_{L^{\frac{n}{2}}}\leq C(n)\mathbb{S}_{\frac{n}{n-2}}(M),$$ then $(M, g)$ is of a unique end.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01837v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youde Wang, Guodong Wei, Liqin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Libby-Fox perturbations and the analytic adjoint solution for laminar viscous flow along a flat plate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16718v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The properties of the solution to the adjoint two-dimensional boundary layer equations on a flat plate are investigated from the viewpoint of Libby-Fox theory that describes the algebraic perturbations to the Blasius boundary layer. The adjoint solution is obtained from the Green's function of the perturbation equation as a sum over the infinite perturbation modes of the Blasius solution. The analysis of the solution allows us to obtain constraints on the eigenvalues and eigenfunctions. The extension of the analysis to the case with non-zero pressure gradient, corresponding to the Falkner-Skan solution, is also briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16718v2</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Lozano, Jorge Ponsin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
