<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.PF updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.PF</link>
    <description>cs.PF updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.PF" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 04:00:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Automatic Generation of Fast and Accurate Performance Models for Deep Neural Network Accelerators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08595</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08595v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Implementing Deep Neural Networks (DNNs) on resource-constrained edge devices is a challenging task that requires tailored hardware accelerator architectures and a clear understanding of their performance characteristics when executing the intended AI workload. To facilitate this, we present an automated generation approach for fast performance models to accurately estimate the latency of a DNN mapped onto systematically modeled and concisely described accelerator architectures. Using our accelerator architecture description method, we modeled representative DNN accelerators such as Gemmini, UltraTrail, Plasticine-derived, and a parameterizable systolic array. Together with DNN mappings for those modeled architectures, we perform a combined DNN/hardware dependency graph analysis, which enables us, in the best case, to evaluate only 154 loop kernel iterations to estimate the performance for 4.19 billion instructions achieving a significant speedup. We outperform regression and analytical models in terms of mean absolute percentage error (MAPE) compared to simulation results, while being several magnitudes faster than an RTL simulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08595v1</guid>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantin L\"ubeck, Alexander Louis-Ferdinand Jung, Felix Wedlich, Mika Markus M\"uller, Federico Nicol\'as Peccia, Felix Th\"ommes, Jannik Steinmetz, Valentin Biermaier, Adrian Frischknecht, Paul Palomero Bernardo, Oliver Bringmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>E-QUARTIC: Energy Efficient Edge Ensemble of Convolutional Neural Networks for Resource-Optimized Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08369v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ensemble learning is a meta-learning approach that combines the predictions of multiple learners, demonstrating improved accuracy and robustness. Nevertheless, ensembling models like Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs) result in high memory and computing overhead, preventing their deployment in embedded systems. These devices are usually equipped with small batteries that provide power supply and might include energy-harvesting modules that extract energy from the environment. In this work, we propose E-QUARTIC, a novel Energy Efficient Edge Ensembling framework to build ensembles of CNNs targeting Artificial Intelligence (AI)-based embedded systems. Our design outperforms single-instance CNN baselines and state-of-the-art edge AI solutions, improving accuracy and adapting to varying energy conditions while maintaining similar memory requirements. Then, we leverage the multi-CNN structure of the designed ensemble to implement an energy-aware model selection policy in energy-harvesting AI systems. We show that our solution outperforms the state-of-the-art by reducing system failure rate by up to 40% while ensuring higher average output qualities. Ultimately, we show that the proposed design enables concurrent on-device training and high-quality inference execution at the edge, limiting the performance and energy overheads to less than 0.04%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08369v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Le Zhang, Onat Gungor, Flavio Ponzina, Tajana Rosing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confidential Computing on nVIDIA H100 GPU: A Performance Benchmark Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03992v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This report evaluates the performance impact of enabling Trusted Execution Environments (TEE) on nVIDIA H100 GPUs for large language model (LLM) inference tasks. We benchmark the overhead introduced by TEE mode across various LLMs and token lengths, with a particular focus on the bottleneck caused by CPU-GPU data transfers via PCIe. Our results indicate that while there is minimal computational overhead within the GPU, the overall performance penalty is primarily attributable to data transfer. For the majority of typical LLM queries, the overhead remains below 5%, with larger models and longer sequences experiencing nearly zero overhead.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03992v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianwei Zhu, Hang Yin, Peng Deng, Shunfan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
