<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.PF updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.PF</link>
    <description>cs.PF updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.PF" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 04:01:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Generative diffusion model surrogates for mechanistic agent-based biological models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09630v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Mechanistic, multicellular, agent-based models are commonly used to investigate tissue, organ, and organism-scale biology at single-cell resolution. The Cellular-Potts Model (CPM) is a powerful and popular framework for developing and interrogating these models. CPMs become computationally expensive at large space- and time- scales making application and investigation of developed models difficult. Surrogate models may allow for the accelerated evaluation of CPMs of complex biological systems. However, the stochastic nature of these models means each set of parameters may give rise to different model configurations, complicating surrogate model development. In this work, we leverage denoising diffusion probabilistic models to train a generative AI surrogate of a CPM used to investigate in vitro vasculogenesis. We describe the use of an image classifier to learn the characteristics that define unique areas of a 2-dimensional parameter space. We then apply this classifier to aid in surrogate model selection and verification. Our CPM model surrogate generates model configurations 20,000 timesteps ahead of a reference configuration and demonstrates approximately a 22x reduction in computational time as compared to native code execution. Our work represents a step towards the implementation of DDPMs to develop digital twins of stochastic biological systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09630v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/2632-2153/ae11f8</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tien Comlekoglu, J. Quetzalcoatl Toledo-Mar\'in, Douglas W. DeSimone, Shayn M. Peirce, Geoffrey Fox, James A. Glazier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next-Generation Event-Driven Architectures: Performance, Scalability, and Intelligent Orchestration Across Messaging Frameworks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04404v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Modern distributed systems demand low-latency, fault-tolerant event processing that exceeds traditional messaging architecture limits. While frameworks including Apache Kafka, RabbitMQ, Apache Pulsar, NATS JetStream, and serverless event buses have matured significantly, no unified comparative study evaluates them holistically under standardized conditions. This paper presents the first comprehensive benchmarking framework evaluating 12 messaging systems across three representative workloads: e-commerce transactions, IoT telemetry ingestion, and AI inference pipelines. We introduce AIEO (AI-Enhanced Event Orchestration), employing machine learning-driven predictive scaling, reinforcement learning for dynamic resource allocation, and multi-objective optimization. Our evaluation reveals fundamental trade-offs: Apache Kafka achieves peak throughput (1.2M messages/sec, 18ms p95 latency) but requires substantial operational expertise; Apache Pulsar provides balanced performance (950K messages/sec, 22ms p95) with superior multi-tenancy; serverless solutions offer elastic scaling for variable workloads despite higher baseline latency (80-120ms p95). AIEO demonstrates 34\% average latency reduction, 28\% resource utilization improvement, and 42% cost optimization across all platforms. We contribute standardized benchmarking methodologies, open-source intelligent orchestration, and evidence-based decision guidelines. The evaluation encompasses 2,400+ experimental configurations with rigorous statistical analysis, providing comprehensive performance characterization and establishing foundations for next-generation distributed system design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04404v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jahidul Arafat, Fariha Tasmin, Sanjaya Poudel</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
