<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 04:00:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A generalized framework for straintronics in 2D quantum materials using group theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19095v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the era of 2D and quasi-2D quantum materials one needs to model strain at the level of the Hamiltonian as opposed to a semi-classical approach. Corrections to the electronic Hamiltonian due to strain arise from two sources: deformations of the lattice and changes in the hoppings. Here, we provide a general theory that takes into account the symmetry of the lattice and that of the bonds, and allows us to write down the strain corrections from all sources in any 2D lattice in terms of the band structure parameters like the velocity and the inverse mass tensor. We then use Group theory to identify when strain can be described as a scalar- and/or a vector-potential. We discuss the nature of the potentials that arise from in- and out-of-plane hoppings, allowing us to model multi-layer systems. We also show that, in general, one encounters multiple vector-potentials in different sectors of the Hilbert space, but one can derive a simpler effective low energy strained Hamiltonian via Hilbert space projections. We discuss several toy models of 2D systems and present strained bilayer graphene as a practical system that incorporates all of the above features. We identify a strain dependent energy scale in bilayer graphene above which we would no longer need to account for multiple vector-potentials. The generality of this formulation allows for a wider range of materials to be investigated for quantum transport straintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19095v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Zemouri, A. R. Champagne, S. Maiti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic-resonance-induced nonlinear current response in magnetic Weyl semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19124v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we propose a geometric nonlinear current response induced by magnetic resonance in magnetic Weyl semimetals. This phenomenon is in analog to the quantized circular photogalvanic effect previously proposed for Weyl semimetal phases of chiral crystals. However, the nonlinear current response in our case can occur in magnetic Weyl semimetals where time-reversal symmetry, instead of inversion symmetry, is broken. The occurrence of this phenomenon relies on the special coupling between Weyl electrons and magnetic fluctuations induced by magnetic resonance. To further support our analytical solution, we perform numerical studies on a model Hamiltonian describing the Weyl semimetal phase in a topological insulator system with ferromagnetism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19124v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruobing Mei, Chao-Xing Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaging magnetic switching in orthogonally twisted stacks of a van der Waals antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19209v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stacking van der Waals magnets holds promise for creating new hybrid materials with properties that do not exist in bulk materials. Here we investigate orthogonally twisted stacks of the van der Waals antiferromagnet CrSBr, aiming to exploit an extreme misalignment of magnetic anisotropy across the twisted interface.Using nitrogen-vacancy centre microscopy, we construct vector maps of the magnetisation, and track their evolution under an external field, in a range of twisted compensated and uncompensated configurations differing by the number of layers. We show that twisted stacking consistently modifies the local magnetic switching behaviour of constituent flakes, and that these modifications are spatially non-uniform. In the case of compensated component flakes (even number of layers), we demonstrate that the combination of dipolar coupling and stacking-induced strain can reduce the switching field by over an order of magnitude. Conversely, in uncompensated component flakes (odd number of layers), we observe indications of a non-zero interlayer exchange interaction between twisted flakes during magnetization reversal, which can persistently modify magnetic order. This work highlights the importance of spatial imaging in investigating stacking-induced magnetic effects, particularly in the case of twistronics where spatial variation is expected and can be conflated with structural imperfections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19209v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander J Healey, Cheng Tan, Boris Gross, Sam C Scholten, Kaijian Xing, Daniel G Chica, Brett C Johnson, Martino Poggio, Michael E Ziebel, Xavier Roy, Jean-Philippe Tetienne, David A Broadway</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunneling current-controlled spin states in few-layer van der Waals magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19255v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Effective control of magnetic phases in two-dimensional magnets would constitute crucial progress in spintronics, holding great potential for future computing technologies. Here, we report a new approach of leveraging tunneling current as a tool for controlling spin states in CrI3. We reveal that a tunneling current can deterministically switch between spin-parallel and spin-antiparallel states in few-layer CrI3, depending on the polarity and amplitude of the current. We propose a mechanism involving nonequilibrium spin accumulation in the graphene electrodes in contact with the CrI3 layers. We further demonstrate tunneling current-tunable stochastic switching between multiple spin states of the CrI3 tunnel devices, which goes beyond conventional bi-stable stochastic magnetic tunnel junctions and has not been documented in two-dimensional magnets. Our findings not only address the existing knowledge gap concerning the influence of tunneling currents in controlling the magnetism in two-dimensional magnets, but also unlock possibilities for energy-efficient probabilistic and neuromorphic computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19255v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-024-47820-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Communications 15 (2024) 3630</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>ZhuangEn Fu, Piumi I. Samarawickrama, John Ackerman, Yanglin Zhu, Zhiqiang Mao, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Wenyong Wang, Yuri Dahnovsky, Mingzhong Wu, TeYu Chien, Jinke Tang, Allan H. MacDonald, Hua Chen, Jifa Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast selective mid-infrared sublattice manipulation in the ferrimagnet $FeCr_2S_4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19263v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: $FeCr_2S_4$ is a ferrimagnet with two oppositely-ordered spin sublattices (Fe and Cr), connected via superexchange interaction, giving a non-zero net magnetic moment. We show how the magnetic dynamics of the sublattices can be selectively manipulated by resonantly perturbing the Fe sublattice using ultrashort laser pulses. The mid-infrared excitation through intra-atomic Fe $d-d$ transitions triggers a markedly slower magneto-optical Kerr effect dynamics compared to an off-resonant pumping affecting both the two sublattices simultaneously. The analysis and conclusions are supported by probing resonantly and off-resonantly to the Fe sublattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19263v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Soranzio, Matteo Savoini, Fabian Graf, Rafael T. Winkler, Abhishek Nag, Hiroki Ueda, Kenya Ohgushi, Yoshinori Tokura, Steven L. Johnson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum electrometry of non-volatile space charges in diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19309v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The microscopic electric environment surrounding a spin defect in a wide-bandgap semiconductor plays a determining role in the spin coherence and charge stability of a given qubit and has an equally important role in defining the electrical properties of the host material. Here, we use electrometry of quantum defects embedded within a diamond to observe stable, micron-scale space charge distributions formed from trapped photogenerated charges. These space charges grow under optical illumination in the presence of an applied electric field, eventually screening the applied electric field entirely over a spatial extent of tens of microns due to charge carrier drift and capture. Our measurements suggest that these space charge fields originate from widely-dispersed spatial configurations of nitrogen charges. Our results have important consequences for electrometry and photoelectric detection using qubits in wide-bandgap semiconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19309v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. M. Goldblatt, N. Dontschuk, D. J. McCloskey, A. M. Martin, A. A. Wood</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductive coupling and Josephson diode effect in selectively-grown topological insulator based three-terminal junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19311v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The combination of an ordinary s-type superconductor with three-dimensional topological insulators creates a promising platform for fault-tolerant topological quantum computing circuits based on Majorana braiding. The backbone of the braiding mechanism are three-terminal Josephson junctions. It is crucial to understand the transport in these devices for further use in quantum computing applications. We present low-temperature measurements of topological insulator-based three-terminal Josephson junctions fabricated by a combination of selective-area growth of $\mathrm{Bi_{0.8}Sb_{1.2}Te_3}$ and shadow mask evaporation of Nb. This approach allows for the in-situ fabrication of Josephson junctions with an exceptional interface quality, important for the study of the proximity-effect. We map out the transport properties of the device as a function of bias currents and prove the coupling of the junctions by the observation of a multi-terminal geometry induced diode effect. We find good agreement of our findings with a resistively and capacitively shunted junction network model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19311v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gerrit Behner, Abdur Rehman Jalil, Alina Rupp, Hans L\"uth, Detlev Gr\"utzmacher, Thomas Sch\"apers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic Nernst effect of the magnon orbital moment in a honeycomb ferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19337v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Nernst effect of the magnon orbital moment is theoretically investigated in a honeycomb ferromagnet, whose Hamiltonian contains the Heisenberg exchange, the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya, the Kitaev, and the Zeeman interactions. More specifically, we obtain the magnon band structure, the Berry curvature, the magnon orbital moment Berry curvature, and the magnon orbital moment Nernst conductivity (MOMNC) for the Hamiltonian within the linear spin-wave theory in the polarized phase. We found the magnon orbital moment Berry curvature is largely independent of the sign of the Chern number of the band. For an experimental proposal, we estimate MOMNC of $\mathrm{CrI}_{3}$ for the Heisenberg-Kitaev-$\Gamma$-Zeeman model and Heisenberg-Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya-Zeeman model for a perpendicular external magnetic field. We found that certain Kitaev materials provide us with a broad tunability of the MOMNC through a magnetic field. We envision that our findings lead to further investigations of the novel transport properties of the magnon orbital moment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19337v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daehyeon An, Se Kwon Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microsecond-lived quantum states in a carbon-based circuit driven by cavity photons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19477v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Semiconductor quantum dots are an attractive platform for the realisation of quantum processors. To achieve long-range coupling between them, quantum dots have been integrated into microwave cavities. However, it has been shown that their coherence is then reduced compared to their cavity-free implementations. Here, we manipulate the quantum states of a suspended carbon nanotube double quantum dot with ferromagnetic contacts embedded in a microwave cavity. By performing quantum manipulations via the cavity photons, we demonstrate coherence times of the order of $1.3\mu s$, two orders of magnitude larger than those measured so far in any carbon quantum circuit and one order of magnitude larger than silicon-based quantum dots in comparable environment. This holds promise for carbon as a host material for spin qubits in circuit quantum electrodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19477v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Neukelmance, B. Hue, Q. Schaeverbeke, L. Jarjat, A. Th\'ery, J. Craquelin, W. Legrand, T. Cubaynes, G. Abulizi, J. Becdelievre, M. El Abbassi, A. Larrouy, K. F. Ourak, D. Stefani, J. A. Sulpizio, A. Cottet, M. M. Desjardins, T. Kontos, M. R. Delbecq</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approaches to tunnel magnetoresistance effect with antiferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19513v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The tunnel magnetoresistance (TMR) effect is one of the representative phenomena in spintronics. Ferromagnets, which have a net spin polarization, have been utilized for the TMR effect. Recently, by contrast, the TMR effect with antiferromagnets, which do not possess a macroscopic spin polarization, has been proposed, and also been observed in experiments. In this topical review, we discuss recent developments in the TMR effect, particularly focusing on the TMR effect with antiferromagnets. First, we review how the TMR effect can occur in antiferromagnetic tunnel junctions. The Julliere model, which has been conventionally utilized to grasp the TMR effect with ferromagnets, breaks down for the antiferromagnetic TMR effect. Instead, we see that the momentum dependent spin splitting explains the antiferromagnetic TMR effect. After that, we revisit the TMR effect from viewpoint of the local density of states (LDOS). We particularly focus on the LDOS inside the barrier, and show that the product of the LDOS will qualitatively capture the TMR effect not only in the ferromagnetic tunnel junctions but also in the ferrimagnetic and antiferromagnetic tunnel junctions. This method is expected to work usefully for designing magnetic tunnel junctions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19513v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katsuhiro Tanaka, Takuya Nomoto, Ryotaro Arita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherent spectroscopy of a single Mn-doped InGaAs quantum dot</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19537v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Doping a self-assembled InGaAs/GaAs quantum dot (QD) with a single Mn atom, a magnetic acceptor impurity, provides a quantum system with discrete energy levels and original spin-dependent optical selection rules, which thus has large potential in quantum photonics, notably as a source of multi-entangled photons. To investigate this potential further, we perform coherent optical spectroscopy under continuous wave excitation of the 3-level V-like system formed in such a Mn-doped QD when charged by a single hole. In spite of a large inhomogeneous broadening of the optical transitions, we demonstrate Autler-Townes splitting both by resonant Raman scattering and by probe absorption spectroscopy for different saturation powers. Analysing these data with a comprehensive model based on optical Bloch equations, we show evidence for quantum interference within the V-like system and assess the pure dephasing rate between the corresponding spin states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19537v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jovana Filipovic, Ankit Kundu, Neelesh Kumar Vij, Simon F\'echerolle, Aristide Lema\^itre, Shilpi Gupta, Olivier Krebs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proof of bulk-edge correspondence for band topology by Toeplitz algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19539v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We rigorously yet concisely prove the bulk-edge correspondence for general $d$-dimensional ($d$D) topological insulators in complex Altland-Zirnbauer classes, which states that the bulk topological number equals to the edge-mode index. Specifically, an essential formula is discovered that links the quantity expressed by Toeplitz algebra, i.e., hopping terms on the lattice with an edge, to the Fourier series on the bulk Brillouin zone. We then apply it to chiral models and utilize exterior differential calculations, instead of the sophisticated \emph{K}-theory, to show that the winding number of bulk system equals to the Fredholm index of 1D edge Hamiltonian, or to the sum of edge winding numbers for higher odd dimensions. Moreover, this result is inherited to the even-dimensional Chern insulators as each of them can be mapped to an odd-dimensional chiral model. It is revealed that the Chern number of bulk system is identical to the spectral flow of 2D edge Hamiltonian, or to the negative sum of edge Chern numbers for higher even dimensions. Our methods and conclusions are friendly to physicists and could be easily extended to other physical scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19539v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zixian Zhou, Liang-Liang Wan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating Thiele's Equation and Collective Skyrmion Dynamics in Circuit Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19598v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Developed half a century ago, Thiele's equation has played a crucial role in describing the motion of magnetic textures, ranging from simple magnetic domains to exotic magnetic solitons like skyrmions and hopfions. However, it remains a challenge to fully understand the collective dynamics of magnetic texture crystals, due to the complex many-body interactions. On the other hand, electrical circuits have recently been proved to be a powerful platform to realize rich physical phenomena in solids. In this Letter, we first construct a circuit unit to simulate Thiele's equation, which enables us to experimentally observe the "skyrmion Hall effect". By coupling a pair of such circuit units, we find an emerging frequency comb under strong pumpings, a long-sought nonlinear effect in interacting skyrmion systems. By extending our strategy to circuit arrays, we experimentally observe the topological edge state, thus confirming the theoretical prediction of topological solitonic insulators years ago. Our work builds a faithful connection between electric circuits and magnetic solitons, two seemingly unrelated areas, and opens the door for exploring collective magnetization dynamics in circuit networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19598v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huanhuan Yang, Lingling Song, Yunshan Cao, Peng Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Suppressing chaos with mixed superconducting qubit devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18543v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In quantum information processing, a tension between two different tasks occurs: while qubits' states can be preserved by isolating them, quantum gates can be realized only through qubit-qubit interactions. In arrays of qubits, weak coupling leads to states being spatially localized and strong coupling to delocalized states. Here, we study the average energy level spacing and the relative entropy of the distribution of the level spacings (Kullback-Leibler divergence from Poisson and Gaussian Orthogonal Ensemble) to analyze the crossover between localized and delocalized (chaotic) regimes in linear arrays of superconducting qubits. We consider both transmons as well as capacitively shunted flux qubits, which enables us to tune the qubit anharmonicity. Arrays with uniform anharmonicity, comprising only transmons or flux qubits, display remarkably similar dependencies of level statistics on the coupling strength. In systems with alternating anharmonicity, the localized regime is found to be more resilient to the increase in qubit-qubit coupling strength in comparison to arrays with a single qubit type. This result supports designing devices that incorporate different qubit types to achieve higher performances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18543v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Blain, Giampiero Marchegiani, Luigi Amico, Gianluigi Catelani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Circuit Quantisation in Hamiltonian Framework: A Constraint Analysis Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19004</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19004v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work we apply Dirac's Constraint Analysis (DCA) to solve Superconducting Quantum Circuits (SQC). The Lagrangian of a SQC reveals the constraints, that are classified in a Hamiltonian framework, such that redundant variables can be removed to isolate the canonical degrees of freedom for subsequent quantization of the Dirac Brackets. We demonstrate the robustness of DCA unlike certain other set of ideas like null vector and loop charge which are each applicable only to specific types of quantum circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19004v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akshat Pandey, Subir Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>1D Spontaneous Symmetry Breaking in thermal equilibrium via Non-Hermitian Construction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19052</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19052v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spontaneous symmetry breaking generally circumvents one-dimensional systems with local interactions in thermal equilibrium. Here, we analyze a category of one-dimensional Hermitian models via local non-Hermitian constructions. Notably, spontaneous symmetry breaking and long-range order may emerge at finite temperatures in such systems under periodic boundary conditions, in sharp contrast to Hermitian constructions. We demonstrate clear numerical evidence, such as order parameters and specific heat, supporting phase diagrams with robust ordered phases. Non-Hermitian physics plays a vital role in prohibiting domain-wall proliferation and promoting spontaneous symmetry breaking. The fermions exhibit an exotic topological nature in their path-integral windings, which uphold nonzero integers -- commonly a non-Hermitian signature -- in the ordered phases, thus offering a novel and spontaneous origin for both symmetry breaking and non-Hermiticity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19052v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Bao Wang, Zi-Hao Dong, Yi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable topological edge states in black phosphorus-like Bi(110)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19369v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We have investigated the structures and electronic properties of ultra-thin Bi(110) films grown on an s-wave superconductor substrate using low-temperature scanning tunneling microscopy and spectroscopy. Remarkably, our experimental results validate the theoretical predictions that the manipulation of Bi(110) surface atom buckling can control the topological phase transition. Notably, we have observed robust unreconstructed edge states at the edges of both 3-bilayer (BL) and 4-BL Bi(110) films, with the 4-BL film displaying stronger edge state intensity and a smaller degree of atomic buckling. First-principle calculations further substantiate these findings, demonstrating a gradual reduction in buckling as the film thickness increases, with average height differences between two Bi atoms of approximately 0.19 {\AA}, 0.10 {\AA}, 0.05 {\AA}, and 0.00 {\AA} for the 1-BL, 2-BL, 3-BL, and 4-BL Bi(110) films, respectively. When Bi films are larger than 2 layers, the system changes from a trivial to a non-trivial phase. This research sets the stage for the controlled realization of topological superconductors through the superconducting proximity effect, providing a significant platform for investigating Majorana zero modes and fabricating quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19369v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Liu, Shengdan Tao, Guanyong Wang, Hongyuan Chen, Bing Xia, Hao Yang, Xiaoxue Liu, Liang Liu, Yaoyi Li, Shiyong Wang, Hao Zheng, Canhua Liu, Dandan Guan, Yunhao Lu, Jin-feng Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional Rashba semiconductors and inversion-asymmetric topological insulators in monolayers Janus MAA'Z$_x$Z'$_{(4-x)}$ family</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19421v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Rashba effect and nontrivial topology related to spintronics are receiving increasing attention. However, there are no clear, effective and universal rules for finding Rashba semiconductors and nontrivial topological insulators (TIs). Herein, through first-principles calculations, we systematically investigate the geometric stability and electronic structures of the MAA'Z$_x$Z'$_{(4-x)}$ systems obtained through comprehensive Janus structural design based on the MA$_2$Z$_4$ (M=Mg, Ga, Sr; A=Al, Ga; Z=S, Se, Te) family. In the process of doping these materials with different Janus configurations, the bandgap decreases continuously with the enhancement of spin-orbit coupling (SOC) strength, and ideal isolated Rashba splitting occurs at the conduction-band minimum (CBM) of multiple materials. It is found that the generation and strength of Rashba splitting are closely related to orbital contribution and charge transfer. Further doping with heavy elements, the material appears to open the bandgap and invert the bands when considering SOC, exhibiting nontrivial TIs features. In addition, the pz orbitals appearing in the valence band after band inversion cause special Rashba splitting at the VBM of multiple materials. Importantly, the Rashba effect, nontrivial topological states, and hybridized spin textures in the MAA'Z$_x$Z'$_{(4-x)}$ systems can be significantly tuned through biaxial strain. Our work not only comprehensively investigates the MAA'Z$_x$Z'$_{(4-x)}$ systems with multifunctional application prospects, but also identifies the mechanisms and principles of Rashba effect and nontrivial topology in Janus materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19421v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinghui Wei, Qikun Tian, XinTing Xu, Haipeng Wu, Guangzhao Qin, Zhenzhen Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological bosonic Bogoliubov excitations with sublattice symmetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19554v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Here we investigate the internal sublattice symmetry, and thus the enriched topological classification of bosonic Bogoliubov excitations of thermodynamically stable free-boson systems with non-vanishing particle-number-nonconserving terms. Specifically, we show that such systems well described by the bosonic Bogoliubov-de Gennes Hamiltonian can be in general reduced to particle-number-conserving (single-particle) ones. Building upon this observation, the sublattice symmetry is uncovered with respect to an excitation energy, which is usually hidden in the bosonic Bogoliubov-de Gennes Hamiltonian. Thus, we obtain an additional topological class, i.e., class AIII, which enriches the framework for the topological threefold way of free-boson systems. Moreover, a construction is proposed to show a category of systems respecting such a symmetry. For illustration, we resort to a one-dimensional (1D) prototypical model to demonstrate the topological excitation characterized by a winding number or symplectic polarization. By introducing the correlation function, we present an approach to measure the topological invariant. In addition, the edge excitation together with its robustness to symmetry-preserving disorders is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19554v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.109.023307</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 109, 023307 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ling-Xia Guo, Liang-Liang Wan, Liu-Gang Si, Xin-You L\"u, Ying Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Landau-Level Quantization and Band Splitting of FeSe Monolayers Revealed by Scanning Tunneling Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19577v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) superconductors that reside on substrates must be influenced by Rashba spin-orbit coupling (SOC). The intriguing effect of Rashba-type SOCs on iron-based superconductors (IBSs) has remained largely a mystery. In this work, we unveil modified Landau-level spectroscopy and the intricate band splitting of FeSe monolayers through the precision of scanning tunneling spectroscopy, which unequivocally demonstrates the presence of Rashba SOC. The discovery sheds light on a nonparabolic electron band at the X/Y point, displaying a distinctive Landau quantization behavior characterized by $E_n\propto(nB)^{4/3}$. The theoretical model aligns with our experimental insights, positing that the k$^4$-term of the electron band becomes predominant and profoundly reshapes the band structure. Our research underscores the pivotal role of the Rashba SOC effect on 2D superconductors and sets the stage to probe new quantum states in systems with remarkably low carrier concentrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19577v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wantong Huang, Haicheng Lin, Yuguo Yin, Cheng Zheng, Wei Chen, Lichen Ji, Jack Hughes, Fedor Kusmartsev, Anna Kusmartseva, Qi-Kun Xue, Xi Chen, Shuai-Hua Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-impedance resonators for strong coupling to an electron on helium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19592v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The in-plane motion of an electron on helium can couple to superconducting microwave resonators via electrical dipole coupling, offering a robust and rapid readout scheme. In previous efforts, microwave resonator designs for electrons on helium have lacked the coupling strength to reach the strong coupling regime, where coherent quantum effects outlast both electron and resonator decoherence rates. High-impedance superconducting microwave resonators offer a path to strong coupling, but integrating such resonators with electrons on helium remains an outstanding challenge. Here, we introduce a high-impedance resonator design compatible with strong coupling to electrons on helium. We fabricate and measure titanium nitride resonators with median internal quality factors of $3.9\times 10^5$ and average impedance of 2.5 k$\Omega$, promising a seven-fold increase in coupling strength compared with standard 50$\Omega$ resonators. Additionally, we develop a simplified resonator model from the capacitance matrix and sheet inductance that accurately predicts the mode frequencies, significantly simplifying the design process of future resonators for investigating quantum effects with electrons on helium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19592v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Koolstra, E. O. Glen, N. R. Beysengulov, H. Byeon, K. E. Castoria, M. Sammon, B. Dizdar, C. S. Wang, D. I. Schuster, S. A. Lyon, J. Pollanen, D. G. Rees</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design nearly optimal quantum algorithm for linear differential equations via Lindbladians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19628v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Solving linear ordinary differential equations (ODE) is one of the most promising applications for quantum computers to demonstrate exponential advantages. The challenge of designing a quantum ODE algorithm is how to embed non-unitary dynamics into intrinsically unitary quantum circuits. In this work, we propose a new quantum algorithm for ODEs by harnessing open quantum systems. Specifically, we utilize the natural non-unitary dynamics of Lindbladians with the aid of a new technique called the non-diagonal density matrix encoding to encode general linear ODEs into non-diagonal blocks of density matrices. This framework enables us to design a quantum algorithm that has both theoretical simplicity and good performance. Combined with the state-of-the-art quantum Lindbladian simulation algorithms, our algorithm, under a plausible input model, can outperform all existing quantum ODE algorithms and achieve near-optimal dependence on all parameters. We also give applications of our algorithm including the Gibbs state preparations and the partition function estimations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19628v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Xia Shang, Naixu Guo, Dong An, Qi Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pomeranchuk instability of a topological crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19636v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nematic quantum fluids appear in strongly interacting systems and break the rotational symmetry of the crystallographic lattice. In metals, this is connected to a well-known instability of the Fermi liquid-the Pomeranchuk instability. Using scanning tunneling microscopy, we identified this instability in a highly unusual setting: on the surface of an elemental topological metal, arsenic. By directly visualizing the Fermi surface of the surface state via scanning tunneling spectroscopy and photoemission spectroscopy, we find that the Fermi surface gets deformed and becomes elliptical at the energies where the nematic state is present. Known instances of nematic instability typically need van-Hove singularities or multi-orbital physics as drivers. In contrast, the surface states of arsenic are essentially indistinguishable from well-confined isotropic Rashba bands near the Fermi level, rendering our finding the first realization of Pomeranchuk instability of the topological surface state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19636v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Md Shafayat Hossain, Zahir Muhammad, Rajibul Islam, Zi-Jia Cheng, Yu-Xiao Jiang, Maksim Litskevich, Tyler A. Cochran, Xian P. Yang, Byunghoon Kim, Fei Xue, Ilias E. Perakis, Weisheng Zhao, Mehdi Kargarian, Luis Balicas, Titus Neupert, M. Zahid Hasan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scattering makes a difference in circular dichroic angle-resolved photoemission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19652v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent years have witnessed a steady progress towards blending 2D quantum materials into technology, with future applications often rooted in the electronic structure. Since crossings and inversions of electronic bands with different orbital characters determine intrinsic quantum transport properties, knowledge of the orbital character is essential. Here, we benchmark angle-resolved photoelectron emission spectroscopy (ARPES) as a tool to experimentally derive orbital characters. For this purpose we study the valence electronic structure of two technologically relevant quantum materials, graphene and WSe$_2$, and focus on circular dichroism that is believed to provide sensitivity to the orbital angular momentum. We analyze the contributions related to angular atomic photoionization profiles, interatomic interference, and multiple scattering. Regimes in which initial-state properties could be disentangled from the ARPES maps are critically discussed and the potential of using circular-dichroic ARPES as a tool to investigate the spin polarization of initial bands is explored. For the purpose of generalization, results from two additional materials, GdMn$_6$Sn$_6$ and PtTe$_2$ are presented in addition. This research demonstrates rich complexity of the underlying physics of circular-dichroic ARPES, providing new insights that will shape the interpretation of both past and future circular-dichroic ARPES studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19652v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Honey Boban, Mohammed Qahosh, Xiao Hou, Tomasz Sobol, Edyta Beyer, Magdalena Szczepanik, Daniel Baranowski, Simone Mearini, Vitaliy Feyer, Yuriy Mokrousov, Keda Jin, Tobias Wichmann, Jose Martinez-Castro, Markus Ternes, F. Stefan Tautz, Felix L\"upke, Claus M. Schneider, J\"urgen Henk, Lukasz Plucinski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-chiral one-dimensional states propagating inside AB/BA domain walls in bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.14293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.14293v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Boundaries between structural twins of bilayer graphene (so-called AB/BA domain walls) are often discussed in terms of the formation of topologically protected valley-polarised chiral states. Here, we show that, depending on the width of the AB/BA boundary, the latter can also support non-chiral one-dimensional (1D) states that are confined to the domain wall at low energies and take the form of quasi-bound states at higher energies, where the 1D bands cross into the two-dimensional spectral continuum. We present the results of modeling of electronic properties of AB/BA domain walls with and without magnetic field as a function of their width and interlayer bias.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.14293v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.20935/AcadNano7267</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Academia Nano: Science, Materials, Technology, volume 1, no. 1 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. V. Enaldiev, C. Moulsdale, A. K. Geim, V. I. Fal'ko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital magnetization senses the topological phase transition in a spin-orbit coupled $\alpha$-$T_3$ system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.07074v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The $\alpha$-$T_3$ system undergoes a topological phase transition(TPT) between two distinct quantum spin-Hall phases across $\alpha=0.5$ when the spin-orbit interaction of Kane-Mele type is taken into consideration. As a hallmark of such a TPT, we find that the Berry curvature and the orbital magnetic moment change their respective signs across the TPT. We also find the trails of the TPT in another physical observable, namely, the orbital magnetization(OM) that can be, in principle, detected experimentally through the circular dichroism associated with optical absorption. The topological features of the OM are understood in terms of valley and spin physics. The valley-resolved OM(VROM) and the spin-resolved OM(SROM) exhibit interesting characteristics related to the valley and the spin Chern number when the chemical potential is tuned in the forbidden gap(s) of the energy spectrum. In particular, we find that the slope of the VROM versus the chemical potential in the forbidden gap changes its sign abruptly across the TPT, which is also consistent with the corresponding change in the valley Chern number. Moreover, the slope of the SROM demonstrates a sudden jump by one unit of $e/h$ (where $e$ is the electronic charge and $h$ is the Planck's constant) across the TPT, which is also in agreement with the corresponding change in the spin Chern number. It is further seen that a definite spin-valley optical selection rule governs the circular dichroism. The $k$-resolved degree of the optical polarization and the low-frequency differential optical absorbance manifest sign change across the TPT. We discuss experimentally viable signatures of different quantum spin-Hall phases in the optical absorbance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.07074v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.165426</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 165426 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lakpa Tamang, Sonu Verma, Tutul Biswas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital diffusion, polarization and swapping in centrosymmetric metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.04763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.04763v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a general theory of charge, spin, and orbital diffusion based on Keldysh formalism. Our findings indicate that the diffusivity of orbital angular momentum in metals is much lower than that of spin or charge due to the strong orbital intermixing in crystals. Furthermore, our theory introduces the concept of spin-orbit polarization by which a pure orbital (spin) current induces a longitudinal spin (orbital) current, a process as efficient as spin polarization in ferromagnets. Finally, we find that orbital currents undergo momentum swapping, even in the absence of spin-orbit coupling. This theory establishes several key parameters for orbital transport of direct importance to experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.04763v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaobai Ning, A. Pezo, Kyoung-Whan Kim, Weisheng Zhao, Kyung-Jin Lee, Aurelien Manchon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling dephasing of coupled qubits via shared-bath coherence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14685v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The interaction of a quantum system with its environment limits its coherence time. This, in particular, restricts the utility of qubits in quantum information processing applications. In this paper, we show that the decoherence of a coupled qubit system can be minimized, or even eliminated, by exploiting the quantum coherence of the bath itself. We investigate the dephasing in a system of two spatially separated, electronically decoupled qubits, with direct or mediated coupling, interacting with a shared bath. For illustration, we treat F\"orster or cavity-mediated coupling between semiconductor quantum dots interacting with acoustic phonons. Using the rigorous method of Trotter's decomposition with cumulant expansion, we demonstrate a reduction in the dephasing rates at specific distances between the dots. The control of dephasing with distance is a coherent effect of the shared bath and is absent for independent baths. It can be understood in terms of phonon-assisted transitions between the entangled qubit states of the coupled system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14685v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. M. J. Hall, L. S. Sirkina, A. Morreau, W. Langbein, E. A. Muljarov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quarter- and half-filled quantum Hall states and their competing interactions in bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19405v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bilayer graphene has emerged as a key platform for non-Abelian fractional quantum Hall (FQH) states, exhibiting multiple half-filled plateaus with large energy gaps. Here, we report four unexpected quarter-filled states and complete the sequence of half-filled plateaus by observing the previously missing $\nu=-\frac{3}{2}$ and $\nu=\frac{1}{2}$ states. Identifying the half-filled plateaus according to their Levin--Halperin daughter states, we reveal an alternating pattern of non-Abelian topological orders. Whenever a pair of $N=1$ Landau levels cross, anti-Pfaffian and Pfaffian develop in the lower and higher levels, respectively. Surprisingly, quarter states occur in $N=0$ levels and are also accompanied by daughters. The mutual exclusion of half- and quarter-filled states indicates a robust competition between the interactions favoring paired states of either two-flux or four-flux composite fermions. Finally, we observe several FQH states that require strong interactions between composite fermions. The systematic pattern of non-Abelian states across two generations of even denominators strengthens the identification of their topological orders and suggests a universal origin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19405v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ravi Kumar, Andr\'e Haug, Jehyun Kim, Misha Yutushui, Konstantin Khudiakov, Vishal Bhardwaj, Alexey Ilin, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, David F. Mross, Yuval Ronen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Persistent nodal magnon-photon polariton in ferromagnetic heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21597v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Exceptional points with coalescence of eigenvalues and eigenvectors are spectral singularities in the parameter space, achieving which often needs fine-tuning of parameters in quantum systems. We predict a \textit{persistent} realization of nodal magnon-photon polariton, i.e., a polariton of long wavelength without any gap splitting in a thin ferromagnetic insulator film sandwiched by two normal metals, which persistently exists when the ferromagnet is sufficiently thick $\sim 100$~nm due to the joint effect of dissipation and dissipative coupling. We perform the model calculation \textit{beyond the perturbation theory} using a classical approach, develop a quantum scheme able to account for the Ohmic dissipation, and find ultrastrong coupling with coupling strength comparable to the bare magnon frequency. Via revealing a simple conversion relation we extend this formalism to superconductors and predict the gap opened by the ultrastrong coupling strongly depends on the direction of polariton propagation. Our findings may help search for robust non-Hermitian topological phases in magnonic and spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21597v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuolun Qiu, Xi-Han Zhou, Hanchen Wang, Guang Yang, Tao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metastability in individual magnetic vortices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14344v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetic nanoparticles play a crucial role in different fields such as biomedicine or information and quantum technologies. These applications require nanoparticles with a single, well-defined energy minimum, free of metastable states, and characterized by narrow switching field distributions. Here, we demonstrate that high-transition-temperature nanoSQUIDs can be successfully applied to the characterization of individual nanodiscs hosting magnetic vortices. We present measurements performed under varying temperature and external magnetic field, revealing signatures of ubiquitous, multiple metastable configurations. We also demonstrate that metastability can be reduced by introducing an intended asymmetry. NanoSQUID measurements can be applied to optimize the fabrication of on-demand spin-texture states, such as degenerated vortices or particles with fixed circulation and deterministic and narrow switching probabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14344v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Garc\'ia-Pons, J. P\'erez-Bail\'on, A. M\'endiz, V. J\'ulvez, M. Hack, K. Wurster, R. Kleiner, D. Koelle, M. J. Mart\'inez-P\'erez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A 300 mm foundry silicon spin qubit unit cell exceeding 99% fidelity in all operations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15590</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15590v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Fabrication of quantum processors in advanced 300 mm wafer-scale complementary metal-oxide-semiconductor (CMOS) foundries provides a unique scaling pathway towards commercially viable quantum computing with potentially millions of qubits on a single chip. Here, we show precise qubit operation of a silicon two-qubit device made in a 300 mm semiconductor processing line. The key metrics including single- and two-qubit control fidelities exceed 99% and state preparation and measurement fidelity exceeds 99.9%, as evidenced by gate set tomography (GST). We report coherence and lifetimes up to $T_\mathrm{2}^{\mathrm{*}} = 30.4$ $\mu$s, $T_\mathrm{2}^{\mathrm{Hahn}} = 803$ $\mu$s, and $T_1 = 6.3$ s. Crucially, the dominant operational errors originate from residual nuclear spin carrying isotopes, solvable with further isotopic purification, rather than charge noise arising from the dielectric environment. Our results answer the longstanding question whether the favourable properties including high-fidelity operation and long coherence times can be preserved when transitioning from a tailored academic to an industrial semiconductor fabrication technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15590v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Steinacker, Nard Dumoulin Stuyck, Wee Han Lim, Tuomo Tanttu, MengKe Feng, Andreas Nickl, Santiago Serrano, Marco Candido, Jesus D. Cifuentes, Fay E. Hudson, Kok Wai Chan, Stefan Kubicek, Julien Jussot, Yann Canvel, Sofie Beyne, Yosuke Shimura, Roger Loo, Clement Godfrin, Bart Raes, Sylvain Baudot, Danny Wan, Arne Laucht, Chih Hwan Yang, Andre Saraiva, Christopher C. Escott, Kristiaan De Greve, Andrew S. Dzurak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Angular dependence of spin-orbit torque in monolayer $Fe_3GeTe_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.04900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.04900v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In ferromagnetic systems lacking inversion symmetry, an applied electric field can control the ferromagnetic order parameters through the spin-orbit torque. The prototypical example is a bilayer heterostructure composed of a ferromagnet and a heavy metal that acts as a spin current source. In addition to such bilayers, spin-orbit coupling can mediate spin-orbit torques in ferromagnets that lack bulk inversion symmetry. A recently discovered example is the two-dimensional monolayer ferromagnet $Fe_3GeTe_2$. In this work, we use first-principles calculations to study the spin-orbit torque and ensuing magnetic dynamics in this material. By expanding the torque versus magnetization direction as a series of vector spherical harmonics, we find that higher order terms (up to $\ell=4$) are significant and play important roles in the magnetic dynamics. They give rise to deterministic, magnetic field-free electrical switching of perpendicular magnetization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.04900v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.108.144422</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 108, 144422 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fei Xue, Mark D. Stiles, Paul M. Haney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological fingerprints in Liouvillian gaps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13732v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Topology in many-body physics usually emerges as a feature of equilibrium quantum states. We show that topological fingerprints can also appear in the relaxation rates of open quantum systems. To demonstrate this we consider one of the simplest models that has two topologically distinct phases in its ground state: the Kitaev chain model for the $p$-wave superconductor. After introducing dissipation to this model we estimate the Liouvillian gap in both strong and weak dissipative limits. Our results show that a non-zero superconducting pairing opens a Liouvillian gap that remains open in the limit of infinite system size. At strong dissipation this gap is essentially unaffected by the topology of the underlying Hamiltonian ground state. In contrast, when dissipation is weak, the topological phase of the Hamiltonian ground state plays a crucial role in determining the character of the Liouvillian gap. We find, for example, that in the topological phase this gap is completely immune to changes in the chemical potential. On the other hand, in the non-topological phase the Liouvillian gap is suppressed by a large chemical potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13732v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Kavanagh, Joost K. Slingerland, Shane Dooley, Graham Kells</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonon-induced contrast in a matter-wave interferometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04210v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Utilizing the Stern-Gerlach apparatus to create matter-wave superposition states is a long-sought-after goal, not only due to its potential applications in the quantum realm but also because of its fundamental implications for studying the quantum properties of gravity. The main challenge in creating a macroscopic quantum interferometer arises from the loss of coherence, primarily through two channels. One channel involves strong coupling with the environment for macroscopic matter, leading to decoherence. The other channel relates to the precision of wave packet overlap, which can occur due to external and internal fluctuations of various sources. The latter introduces a unique challenge for larger-scale masses by perturbing the centre of mass motion of the macroscopic object. Here, we study a particular challenge, namely, the issue of internal degrees of freedom, specifically phonon fluctuations and contrast reduction. This work will investigate the contrast reduction caused by spin-magnetic field and diamagnetic interactions at the phonon occupation level in the quantum gravity-induced entanglement of masses (QGEM) protocol configuration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04210v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.110.042614</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.A 110 (2024) 4, 042614</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Qian Xiang, Run Zhou, Sougato Bose, Anupam Mazumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counting statistics of ultra-broadband microwave photons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07868</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07868v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report measurements of counting statistics, average and variance, of microwave photons of ill-defined frequency : bichromatic photons, i.e. photons involving two well separated frequencies, and "white" broadband photons. Our setup allows for the analysis of single photonic modes of arbitrary waveform over the 1-10 GHz frequency range. The photon statistics are obtained by on-the-fly numerical calculation from the sampled time-dependent voltage. Using an ac+dc biased tunnel junction as a source of quantum microwave, we report an ultra-wide squeezing spectrum representing a competitive source for entanglement generation (up to 0.9 billion measured entangled bits per second) easily achievable experimentally. We also report the observation of quantum steering by the tunnel junction, and show how the presence of squeezing of a broadband mode implies the existence of entanglement between two modes it encompasses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07868v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Bolduc Beaudoin, Edouard Pinsolle, Bertrand Reulet</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
