<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 04:00:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on "Emergence of Nodal-Knot Transitions by Disorder"</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07223v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a recent paper arXiv:2409.01034, Gong et al. studied the disorder effects in nodal-knot semimetal through Wilson momentum-shell renormalization group (RG) method. They stated that various nodal-knot transitions emerge driven by disorders. However, we notice that there are serious problems in this paper. First, in this paper, the RG analysis is not performed in the momentum space around the Fermi surface but in an incorrect momentum space around the point $k=0$. Accordingly, the RG equations are completely unreliable. Second, the criterion for phase transition employed in this paper is invalid. Accroding to the criterion in this paper, we can find that the various phase transitions stated in this paper even emerge in clean nodal-knot semimetal system! Thus, the conclusions in this paper are unfounded.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07223v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing-Rong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active nonreciprocal cloaking for pseudo-Hermitian magnons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07233v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cloaking has important applications but entails sophisticated control of signal propagation and scattering characteristics. Here, we show that invisibility for magnon signals is achievable in a non-reciprocal and electrically controlled way by engineering the magnonic channels such that they exhibit PT-symmetry. This is accomplished by attaching current-carrying heavy metal contacts to the magnon waveguides and exerting fields from an attached bias layer. Tuning the current density in the metal layer, the magnons in this setup experience electrically controlled, compensated gain and loss due to spin-orbit torque which renders the setup PT-symmetric. The magnon dynamics is then shown to be pseudo-Hermitian with exceptional points (EPs) determined actively by an external electric field. We analyze the magnon scattering from single and periodic PT-symmetric regions and identify the conditions necessary for the formation of unidirectional invisibility which can be steered by specific combinations of bias layers and current amplitudes in the heavy metal as to reach the EP. The unidirectional invisibility at EP is found to be extended for a periodic PT-symmetric region. Intrinsic damping on PT-symmetric unidirectional invisibility is shown to be marginal confirming the experimental feasibility. It is shown how the unidirectional magnons can be utilized to amplify and generate magnonic orbital angular momentum states in coupled magnetic rings demonstrating a new path for manipulating magnon propagation and processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07233v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominik Schulz, Jamal Berakdar, Xi-guang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-particle spectral function of fractional quantum anomalous Hall states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07319v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fractional quantum Hall states are the most prominent example of states with topological order, hosting excitations with fractionalized charge. Recent experiments in twisted $\text{MoTe}_2$ and graphene-based heterostructures provide evidence of fractional quantum anomalous Hall (FQAH) states, which spontaneously break time-reversal symmetry and persist even without an external magnetic field. Understanding the unique properties of these states requires the characterization of their low-energy excitations. To that end, we construct a parton theory for the energy and momentum-resolved single-particle spectral function of FQAH states. We explicitly consider several experimentally observed filling fractions as well as a composite Fermi liquid in the half-filled Chern band. The parton description captures qualitatively our numerical exact diagonalization results. Additionally, we discuss how the finite bandwidth of the Chern band and the non-ideal quantum geometry affect the fractionalized excitations. Our work demonstrates that the energy and momentum-resolved electronic single-particle spectral function provides a valuable tool to characterize fractionalized excitations of FQAH states in moir\'e lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07319v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Pichler, Wilhelm Kadow, Clemens Kuhlenkamp, Michael Knap</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering the origin of spin current in spintronic terahertz emitters and its imprint on their electromagnetic radiation via time-dependent density functional theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07360v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin current flowing between femtosecond laser pulse (fsLP)-driven ferromagnetic metal and adjacent normal metal (NM) hosting strong spin-orbit coupling is invariably invoked to explain THz radiation believed to be emitted solely by NM layer. Despite being such a central concept, the microscopic origin of such interlayer spin current remains vague. Here, we employ recently developed [A. Kefayati {\em et al.}, Phys. Rev. Lett. {\bf 133}, 136704 (2024)] time-dependent density functional theory plus Jefimenko equations approach to extract spin current between Co and NM=Pt or W layer where Co is driven by fsLP responsible for its demagnetization, i.e., shrinking of its magnetization vector, $M^y(t)/M^y(t=0)&lt;1$ [while $M^x(t) \approx M^z (t) \approx 0$]. By comparing time dependence of spin current with those of other relevant quantities, we find that: ({\em i}) spin current is generated by demagnetization dynamics because it {\em follows} closely $dM^y/dt$, thus it is an example of quantum pumping phenomenon that cannot be captured by phenomenological notions (such as ``spin voltage'') or semiclassical theories; ({\em ii}) time dependence of pumped spin current {\em does not follow} closely that of charge current emerging within NM layer via spin-to-charge conversion mechanisms; ({\em iii}) emitted THz radiation is dominated by charge current within Co layer, rather than usually assumed charge current [from ({\em ii})] within NM layer, especially in the case of NM=W where spin-to-charge conversion by the inverse spin Hall effect is suppressed, despite large spin Hall angle of W, due to localization of excited electrons onto the outer unfilled $d$-orbitals of W.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07360v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Kefayati, Yafei Ren, M. Benjamin Jungfleisch, Lars Gundlach, John Q. Xiao, Branislav K. Nikolic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of impurities and disorder on the braiding dynamics of Majorana zero modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07373v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Impurities and random disorder are known to affect topological superconducting phases and their Majorana zero modes (MZMs). In particular, it is a common assumption that disorder negatively influences the braiding dynamics of MZMs. Recently, it was shown, however, that random disorder can also stabilize or even increase topological phases. Here, we investigate quantitatively how a single impurity can lead to braiding errors. We show that the impurity increases, in most scenarios, the dynamical hybridization of the MZMs, reducing the braiding performance. In addition, we show how random disorder, i.e., impurities on all lattice sites but with different strengths, affects braiding. As for the static case, we observe a window of opportunity where random disorder decreases the average energy of a braid, and thus improves braiding outcomes. This window of opportunity is, however, limited due to an increase of diabatic effects in the presence of disorder. Nevertheless and contrary to physical intuition, disorder can in certain situations be beneficial and improve braiding outcomes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07373v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cole Peeters, Themba Hodge, Eric Mascot, Stephan Rachel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Nature of Tellurium Atomic Helices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07464v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A theoreticsal study of single, double and triple hydrogen-terminated chains of tellurium atoms is presented. Surprisingly, H-terminated single chains with 3 Te atoms per unit cell (as in Te crystals) are found to be unstable. They relax to helices with lower energies and smaller twist angles. However, some compact disordered Te chains of mixed chirality are found to have still lower energies. Pairs of H-terminated Te atomic chains are found to form DNA-like double helices with lower energies than compact disordered structures of the two chains. Triplets of H-terminated Te atomic chains are found to form triple helices. The single, double and triple Te helices reported here are beyond the scope of previously studied periodic models with small unit cells.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07464v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Kirczenow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal Nanoquakes: Terahertz Frequency Surface Rayleigh Waves in Diamond Nanocrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07480v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mechanical THz vibrations in nanocrystals have recently been harnessed for quantum sensing and thermal management. The free boundaries of nanocrystals introduce new surface wave solutions, analogous to the seismic waves on Earth, yet the implications of these surface waves on nanocrystals have remained largely unexplored. Here, we use atomistic molecular dynamics simulations and experimental neutron spectroscopy to elucidate these THz-scale features in nanodiamond. Our key insight is that thermally induced Rayleigh surface phonons, which have a low group velocity and an amplitude that decays exponentially away from the surface, are responsible for the previously observed but unexplained linear scaling of the low-energy vibrational density of states in nanocrystals. Large thermal atomic displacements, relative to the nanoparticle radius, induce perpetual surface quakes, even at ambient conditions. Normalised to the radius, the surface displacement ratio in diamond nanocrystals exceeds that of the largest recorded earthquakes by a factor of $10^{5\pm1}$. We explicate how these dramatic Rayleigh waves coexist with other distinctive features including confined lattice phonons, soft surface modes, the acoustic gap, Love waves, and Lamb modes, thereby offering a complete framework for the vibrational dynamics of nanocrystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07480v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caleb Stamper, Matteo Baggioli, Pablo Galaviz, Roger A. Lewis, Kirrily C. Rule, Ablikim Bake, Kyle A. Portwin, Sha Jin, Xue Fan, Dehong Yu, David L. Cortie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formation, Prevalence and Stability of Bouncing-Ball Scars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07709v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum scars correspond to enhanced probability densities along unstable classical periodic orbits. In recent years, research on quantum scars has extended to various systems including the many-body regime. In this work we focus on the formation, prevalence, and stability of linear "bouncing-ball" (BB) scars in two-dimensional (2D) quantum wells. These scars have relevance as effective and controllable channels in quantum transport. We utilize imaginary time propagation to solve the 2D Schr\"odinger equation within an arbitrary external confining potential, specifically the quantum well model with external perturbations. We show how BB scars begin to emerge with a single perturbative peak, such as a repulsive bump or attractive dip that simulates the effect of a charged nanotip in the system. We then identify the optimal size of the perturbative peak to maximize the prevalence of these scars. Finally, we investigate the stability of BB scars against external noise and find that some of them are remarkably robust. This suggests promising opportunities for further applications of BB scars in quantum transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07709v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simo Selinummi, Joonas Keski-Rahkonen, Fartash Chalangari, Esa R\"as\"anen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-color laser control of photocurrent and high harmonics in graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07767v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We comprehensively investigate two-color laser driven photocurrent and high harmonic generation (HHG) in graphene models. By numerically solving the quantum master equation, we unifiedly explore a broad parameter regime including both the weak (perturbative) and intense laser (non-perturbative) cases while considering the dissipation effects. We demonstrate that the HHG spectra can be drastically altered by tuning the spatial symmetry of the laser-field trajectory. This controllability is explained by the dynamical symmetry argument. We also show that both the magnitude and the direction of photocurrent (zero-th order harmonics) can be controlled by varying the frequency, intensity, ellipticity, and phase of the two-color laser. Furthermore, the nature of photocurrent is shown to be classified into shift or injection current types, depending on the phase of two-color laser. Our findings indicate that even in centrosymmetric electron systems, photocurrent and HHG can be quantitatively controlled by adjusting various external parameters if we utilize multiple-color laser with a lower spatial or temporal symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07767v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Minoru Kanega, Masahiro Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural Manipulation of Spin Excitations in a Molecular Junction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07777v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Single metallocene molecules act as sensitive spin detectors when decorating the probe of a scanning tunneling microscope (STM). However, the impact of the atomic-scale electrode details on the molecular spin state has remained elusive to date. Here, a nickelocene (Nc) STM junction is manipulated in an atom-wise manner showing clearly the dependence of the spin excitation spectrum on the anchoring of Nc to Cu(111), a Cu monomer and trimer. Moreover, while the spin state of the same Nc tip is a triplet with tunable spin excitation energies upon contacting the surface, it transitions to a Kondo-screened doublet on a Cu atom. Notably, the non-trivial magnetic exchange interaction of the molecular spin with the electron continuum of the substrate determines the spectral line shape of the spin excitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07777v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian K\"ogler, Nicolas N\'eel, Laurent Limot, J\"org Kr\"oger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flat-band (de)localization emulated with a superconducting qubit array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07878v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Arrays of coupled superconducting qubits are analog quantum simulators able to emulate a wide range of tight-binding models in parameter regimes that are difficult to access or adjust in natural materials. In this work, we use a superconducting qubit array to emulate a tight-binding model on the rhombic lattice, which features flat bands. Enabled by broad adjustability of the dispersion of the energy bands and of on-site disorder, we examine regimes where flat-band localization and Anderson localization compete. We observe disorder-induced localization for dispersive bands and disorder-induced delocalization for flat bands. Remarkably, we find a sudden transition between the two regimes and, in its vicinity, the semblance of quantum critical scaling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07878v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilan T. Rosen, Sarah Muschinske, Cora N. Barrett, David A. Rower, Rabindra Das, David K. Kim, Bethany M. Niedzielski, Meghan Schuldt, Kyle Serniak, Mollie E. Schwartz, Jonilyn L. Yoder, Jeffrey A. Grover, William D. Oliver</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fidelity of the acoustic control of single photon scattering with semiconductor quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07902v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Acoustic modulation of quantum dots (QDs) allows one to control the scattering of photons. Here we theoretically characterize the fidelity of acoustic control of the scattering in the frequency domain. We formulate the theory of low-intensity resonance fluorescence in the presence of white noise and show that a high degree of control is achievable with a two-tone acoustic field for appropriate settings of modulation amplitudes as long as the noise-induced phase diffusion coefficient remains one order of magnitude smaller than the acoustic frequency. In addition, using a quantitative model of optical signal collection, we determine that the acoustic phase must be stable over $\mathbf{10^4}$ to $\mathbf{10^5}$ acoustic periods for efficient control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07902v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafa{\l} A. Bogaczewicz, Pawe{\l} Machnikowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Current density distribution in the quantum Hall effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07943v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The integer quantum Hall effect (QHE) is one of the most fundamental and important phenomena in condensed matter physics. Its most outstanding application is the resistance standard of the SI units, while new applications are likely to emerge in the advent of quantum technologies. Nevertheless, our microscopic understanding of the QHE is not yet complete. For decades, there has been a controversal discussion about the current density distribution for a quantized Hall resistance. This question is essential for applications as it effects the stability of the quantized Hall states as well as the quantum mechanical phase of the charge carriers. It is also important for the understanding of the fractional, spin or anomalous quantum Hall effects. Here, we discuss the current density distribution based on the screening theory of the QHE. The current flow is chiral and consists of the externally applied imposed and a closed loop persistent current, where the latter descreases as the imposed current is increased.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07943v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Serkan Sirt, Stefan Ludwig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing nonlinear spin dynamics in canted easy-plane antiferromagnets using spin-rectification effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08013v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate spin-rectification phenomena in canted antiferromagnets, closely connected to the family of altermagnetic materials. Our results show that excitation efficiency is significantly enhanced by the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction. Antiferromagnetic dynamics can be detected through spin-Hall magnetoresistance and bolometric effects, with an efficiency reaching up to mV/W. The rectified voltage shape is influenced by both the symmetry of the exciting torques, detection mechanisms (continuous spin-pumping and spin-Hall magnetoresistance), and the antiferromagnetic crystalline axis. Under high pumping power, we observe a saturation effect related to Suhl-like spin-wave instabilities and a nonlinear redshift of the antiferromagnetic resonance. These findings open new avenues for studying nonlinear dynamics in antiferromagnetic and altermagnetic spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08013v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. El Kanj, S. Mantion, I. Boventer, P. Bortolotti, V. Cros, A. Anane, O. Gomonay, R. Lebrun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instability in domain wall dynamics in almost compensated ferrimagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08018v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nanoscale self-localized topological spin textures, such as domain walls and skyrmions, are of interest for the fundamental physics of magnets and spintronics applications. Ferrimagnets (FiMs), in the region close to the angular momentum compensation point, are promising materials because of their ultrafast spin dynamics at nonzero magnetization. In this work, we study specific features of the FiM domain wall (DW) dynamics, which are absent in both ferromagnets (FM) and antiferromagnets (AFM). In low-damping FMs and AFMs ($\alpha \ll 1$), the non-stationary forced motion of DWs is characterized by slow ($t_{diss}\propto 1/\alpha$) changes of the DW's velocity and internal structure for all accepted values of the DW energy $E$ and its linear momentum $P$ -- a consequence of the stability of DWs for any value of $P$. In contrast, the dispersion law of FiM DWs has specific points, $P=P_{cr}$ and $E_{cr}=E(P_{cr})$, such that stable DWs are only present for $P&lt;P_{cr}$, i.e., $P_{cr}$ and $E_{cr}$ act as endpoints in the $E(P)$ dependence. We show that when a field-like torque driven DW reaches this endpoint, it falls into a highly-non-equilibrium state with the excitation of fast ($t \ll t_{diss}$) and highly-nonlinear intra-wall magnetization dynamics, covering a wide frequency range up until the frequencies of propagating spin waves. The domain wall finally throws off an "excessive" energy by a short "burst" of the propagating spin waves and returns to the stationary state; the full picture of the forced motion is a periodic repetition of such "explosive" events.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08018v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. V. Ovcharov, B. A. Ivanov, E. G. Galkina, J. \r{A}kerman, R. S. Khymyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photonic Non-Abelian Braid Monopole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08191v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Monopoles and braids are exotic but elusive aspects of fundamental theories of light and matter. In lattice systems, monopoles of band-structure degeneracies are subject to well-established no-go (doubling) theorems that appear to universally apply in closed Hermitian systems and open non-Hermitian systems alike. However, the non-Abelian braid topology of non-Hermitian multi-band systems provides a remarkable loophole to these constraints. Here we make use of this loophole, and experimentally implement, for the first time, a monopole degeneracy in a non-Hermitian three-band system in the form of a single third-order exceptional point. We explicitly demonstrate the intricate braiding topology and the non-Abelian fusion rules underlying the monopole degeneracy. The experiment is carried out using a new design of single-photon interferometry, enabling eigenstate and spectral resolutions for non-Hermitian multi-band systems with widely tunable parameters. Thus, the union of state-of-the-art experiments, fundamental theory, and everyday concepts such as braids paves the way toward the highly exotic non-Abelian topology unique to non-Hermitian settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08191v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kunkun Wang, J. Lukas K. K\"onig, Kang Yang, Lei Xiao, Wei Yi, Emil J. Bergholtz, Peng Xue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gate-tunable Bose-Fermi mixture in a strongly correlated moir\'e bilayer electron system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07308v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum gases consisting of species with distinct quantum statistics, such as Bose-Fermi mixtures, can behave in a fundamentally different way than their unmixed constituents. This makes them an essential platform for studying emergent quantum many-body phenomena such as mediated interactions and unconventional pairing. Here, we realize an equilibrium Bose-Fermi mixture in a bilayer electron system implemented in a WS$_{2}$/WSe$_{2}$ moir\'e heterobilayer with strong Coulomb coupling to a nearby moir\'e-free WSe$_{2}$ monolayer. Absent the fermionic component, the underlying bosonic phase manifests as a dipolar excitonic insulator. By injecting excess charges into it, we show that the bosonic phase forms a stable mixture with added electrons but abruptly collapses upon hole doping. We develop a microscopic model to explain the unusual asymmetric stability with respect to electron and hole doping. By studying the Bose-Fermi mixture via monitoring excitonic resonances from both layers, we demonstrate gate-tunability over a wide range in the boson/fermion density phase space, in excellent agreement with theoretical calculations. Our results further the understanding of phases stabilized in moir\'e bilayer electron systems and demonstrate their potential for exploring the exotic properties of equilibrium Bose-Fermi mixtures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07308v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amine Ben Mhenni, Wilhelm Kadow, Miko{\l}aj J. Metelski, Adrian O. Paulus, Alain Dijkstra, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Seth Ariel Tongay, Matteo Barbone, Jonathan J. Finley, Michael Knap, Nathan P. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-induced antiferromagnetic correlations in a nanopatterned van der Waals ferromagnet: a potential artificial spin ice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07310v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nano-patterned magnetic materials have opened new venues on the investigation of strongly correlated phenomena including artificial spin-ice systems, geometric frustration, magnetic monopoles, for technologically important applications such as reconfigurable ferromagnetism. With the advent of atomically thin two-dimensional (2D) van der Waals (vdW) magnets a pertinent question is whether such compounds could make their way into this realm where interactions can be tailored so that unconventional states of matter could be assessed. Here we show that square islands of CrGeTe3 vdW ferromagnets distributed in a grid manifest antiferromagnetic correlations, essential to enable frustration resulting in an artificial spin-ice. By using a combination of SQUID-on-tip microscopy, focused ion beam lithography, and atomistic spin dynamic simulations, we show that pristine, isolated CGT flakes as small as 150*150*60 nm3 have tunable dipole-dipole interactions, which can be precisely controlled by their lateral spacing. There is a crossover between non-interacting islands and significant inter-island anticorrelation depending how they are spatially distributed allowing the creation of complex magnetic patterns not observable at the isolated flakes. Our findings suggest that the cross-talk between the nano-patterned magnets can be explored in the generation of even more complex spin configurations where exotic interactions may be manipulated in an unprecedent way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07310v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/advs.202409240</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Avia Noah, Nofar Fridman, Yishay Zur, Maya Markman, Yotam Katz King, Maya Klang, Ricardo Rama-Eiroa, Harshvardhan Solanki, Michael L. Reichenberg Ashby, Tamar Levin, Edwin Herrera, Martin E. Huber, Snir Gazit, Elton J. G. Santos, Hermann Suderow, Hadar Steinberg, Oded Millo, Yonathan Anahory</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement-induced transitions for interacting fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07334v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Effect of measurements on interacting fermionic systems with particle-number conservation, whose dynamics is governed by a time-independent Hamiltonian, is studied. We develop Keldysh field-theoretical framework that provides a unified approach to observables characterizing entanglement and charge fluctuations. Within this framework, we derive a replicated Keldysh non-linear sigma model (NLSM), which incorporates boundary conditions specifically designed to produce generating functions for charge cumulants and entanglement entropies directly in the NLSM language. By using the renormalization-group approach for the NLSM, we determine the phase diagram and the scaling of physical observables. Crucially, the interaction-induced terms in the NLSM action reduce its symmetry, which affects the physics of the problem in a dramatic way. First, this leads to the "information-charge separation": charge cumulants get decoupled from entanglement entropies. Second, the interaction stabilizes the volume-law phase for the entanglement. Third, for spatial dimensionality $d=1$, the interaction stabilizes the phase with logarithmic growth of charge cumulants (in the thermodynamic limit). Thus, in the presence of interaction, there are measurement transitions in any $d$, at variance with free fermions, for which a $d=1$ system is always in the area-law phase. Analytical results are supported by numerical simulations using time-dependent variational principles for matrix product states, which, in particular, confirm the separation of information and charge as a hallmark of the delocalized phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07334v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Poboiko, Paul P\"opperl, Igor V. Gornyi, Alexander D. Mirlin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding and predicting adsorption energetics on monolayer transition metal dichalcogenides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07469v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) have recently been shown to demonstrate non-volatile resistive switching (NVRS), offering significant advantages such as high-density integration and low energy consumption due to their atomic-scale thinness. In this study, we focus on the adsorption and desorption of metal adatoms, which can modulate the electrical resistivity by several orders of magnitude. We develop material-based relationships of the adsorption energy with electronic and atomic structure descriptors by examining the effects of various transition-metal adsorbates on the surface of TMDs. Our results reveal that adsorption energies of transition metals exhibit consistent trends across different TMDs (MoS$_2$, MoSe$_2$, WS$_2$, WSe$_2$) and can be explained using simple descriptors of the atomic and electronic structure. We propose several models to describe this adsorption process, providing a deeper understanding of a crucial step in the resistive switching mechanism based on formation and dissolution of point defects. Finally, we connect our computed adsorption energies to the switching energy. These findings will help guide rational materials selection for the development of NVRS devices using 2D TMDs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07469v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brian Lee, Jameela Fatheema, Deji Akinwande, Wennie Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Certifying the quantumness of a single nuclear spin qudit through its uniform precession</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07641v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spin precession is a textbook example of dynamics of a quantum system that exactly mimics its classical counterpart. Here we challenge this view by certifying the quantumness of exotic states of a nuclear spin through its uniform precession. The key to this result is measuring the positivity, instead of the expectation value, of the $x$-projection of the precessing spin, and using a spin &gt; 1/2 qudit, that is not restricted to semi-classical spin coherent states. The experiment is performed on a single spin-7/2 $^{123}$Sb nucleus, implanted in a silicon nanoelectronic device, amenable to high-fidelity preparation, control, and projective single-shot readout. Using Schr\"odinger cat states and other bespoke states of the nucleus, we violate the classical bound by 19 standard deviations, proving that no classical probability distribution can explain the statistic of this spin precession, and highlighting our ability to prepare quantum resource states with high fidelity in a single atomic-scale qudit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07641v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arjen Vaartjes, Martin Nurizzo, Lin Htoo Zaw, Benjamin Wilhelm, Xi Yu, Danielle Holmes, Daniel Schwienbacher, Anders Kringh{\o}j, Mark R. van Blankenstein, Alexander M. Jakob, Fay E. Hudson, Kohei M. Itoh, Riley J. Murray, Robin Blume-Kohout, Namit Anand, Andrew S. Dzurak, David N. Jamieson, Valerio Scarani, Andrea Morello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable second harmonic generation in 2D materials: comparison of different strategies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07661v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nonlinear optical frequency conversion, where optical fields interact with a nonlinear medium to generate new frequencies, is a key phenomenon in modern photonic systems. However, a major challenge with these techniques lies on the difficulty of tuning the nonlinear electrical susceptibilities that drive such effects in a given material. As a result, dynamic control of optical nonlinearities has remained largely confined to research laboratories, limiting its practical use as a spectroscopic tool. In this work, we aim to advance the development of devices with tunable nonlinear responses by exploring two potential mechanisms for electrically manipulating second-order optical nonlinearity in two-dimensional materials. Specifically, we consider two configurations: in the first, the material does not inherently exhibit second-harmonic generation (SHG), but this response is induced by an external field; in the second, an external field induces doping in a material that already exhibits SHG, altering the intensity of the nonlinear signal. These two approaches are investigated and compared with existing experimental results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07661v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone Grillo, Elena Cannuccia, Maurizia Palummo, Olivia Pulci, Claudio Attaccalite</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Hall liquids in high-density QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07665v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: There exist metastable domain walls of the flavor-singlet meson $\eta$ for the ${\rm U}(1)$ axial symmetry in two-flavor color superconductivity (2SC) in QCD at large baryon density. We show that, due to the coupling of $\eta$ to confined ${\rm SU}(2)$ gluons in the 2SC phase, the effective theory on the domain wall is described by the ${\rm SU}(2)_{-1}$ Chern-Simons theory, which is dual to the ${\rm U}(1)_{2}$ Chern-Simons theory. This theory has a spin-1 droplet excitation that does not carry baryon number, which we identify as a vector meson. We also discuss the effective theories and baryonic droplet excitations on the domain walls of the flavor-singlet mesons in the superfluid phases of QCD at large isospin density and two-color QCD at large baryon density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07665v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kentaro Nishimura, Naoki Yamamoto, Ryo Yokokura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum applications of hexagonal boron nitride</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07712v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) has emerged as a compelling platform for both classical and quantum technologies. In particular, the past decade has witnessed a surge of novel ideas and developments, which may be overwhelming for newcomers to the field. This review provides an overview of the fundamental concepts and key applications of hBN, including quantum sensing, quantum key distribution, quantum computing, and quantum memory. Additionally, we highlight critical experimental and theoretical advances that have expanded the capabilities of hBN, in a cohesive and accessible manner. The objective is to equip readers with a comprehensive understanding of the diverse applications of hBN, and provide insights into ongoing research efforts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07712v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Asl{\i} \c{C}akan, Chanaprom Cholsuk, Angus Gale, Mehran Kianinia, Serkan Pa\c{c}al, Serkan Ate\c{s}, Igor Aharonovich, Milos Toth, Tobias Vogl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curved graphene nanoribbons derived from tetrahydropyrene-based polyphenylenes via one-pot K-region oxidation and Scholl cyclization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07726</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07726v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Precise synthesis of graphene nanoribbons (GNRs) is of great interest to chemists and materials scientists because of their unique opto-electronic properties and potential applications in carbon-based nanoelectronics and spintronics. In addition to the tunable edge structure and width, introducing curvature in GNRs is a powerful structural feature for their chemi-physical property modification. Here, we report an efficient solution synthesis of the first pyrene-based GNR (PyGNR) with curved geometry via one-pot K-region oxidation and Scholl cyclization of its corresponding well-soluble tetrahydropyrene-based polyphenylene precursor. The efficient A2B2-type Suzuki polymerization and subsequent Scholl reaction furnishes up to 35 nm long curved GNRs bearing cove- and armchair-edges. The construction of model compound, as a cutout of PyGNR, from a tetrahydropyrene-based oligophenylene precursor proves the concept and efficiency of the one-pot K-region oxidation and Scholl cyclization, which is clearly revealed by single crystal X-ray diffraction analysis. The structure and optical properties of PyGNR are investigated by Raman, FT-IR, solid-state NMR and UV-Vis analysis with the support of DFT calculations. PyGNR shows the absorption maximum at 680 nm, exhibiting a narrow optical bandgap of 1.4 eV, qualifying as a low-bandgap GNR. Moreover, THz spectroscopy on PyGNR estimates its macroscopic charge mobility of 3.6 cm2/Vs, outperforming other curved GNRs reported via conventional Scholl reaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07726v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chem. Sci. 2023 14, 8607-8614</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Obermann, Wenhao Zheng, Jason Melidonie, Steffen B\"ockmann, Silvio Osella, Lenin Andr\'es Guerrero Le\'on, Felix Hennersdorf, David Beljonne, Jan J. Weigand, Mischa Bonn, Michael Ryan Hansen, Hai I. Wang, Ji Ma, Xinliang Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital Hall Effect Accompanying Quantum Hall Effect: Landau Levels Cause Orbital Polarized Edge Currents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07784v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The quantum Hall effect emerges when two-dimensional samples are subjected to strong magnetic fields at low temperatures: Topologically protected edge states cause a quantized Hall conductivity in multiples of $e^2/h$. Here we show that the quantum Hall effect is accompanied by an orbital Hall effect. Our quantum mechanical calculations fit well the semiclassical interpretation in terms of "skipping orbits". The chiral edge states of a quantum Hall system are orbital polarized akin to a hypothetical orbital version of the quantum anomalous Hall effect in magnetic systems. The orbital Hall resistivity scales quadratically with the magnetic field making it the dominant effect at high fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07784v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.146301</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Letters 133, 146301 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>B\"orge G\"obel, Ingrid Mertig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meissner effect in non-Hermitian superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07853v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study theoretically Meissner effect in non-Hermitian systems of BCS type via superfluid stiffness. We show that depending on the values of the mean fields, chemical potential, and temperature, we obtain paramagnetic or diamagnetic Meissner effect. Notably, positive real part of the product of mean fields guarantees diamagnetic Meissner effect in an $s$-wave 3D non-Hermitian superconductor. Once the mean fields are close to being anti-Hermitian, 2D $s$-, $p_x$-, and $d$-wave superconductors exhibit interesting behaviour, including paramagnetic Meissner effect for certain parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07853v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shun Tamura, Helene M\"uller, Viktoriia Kornich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Considerations for Electromagnetic Simulations for a Quantitative Correlation of Optical Spectroscopy and Electron Tomography of Plasmonic Nanoparticles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08093v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The optical cross sections of plasmonic nanoparticles are intricately linked to the morphology of the particle. If this connection can be made accurately enough, it would become possible to determine a particles shape solely from its measured optical cross sections. For that, electromagnetic simulations can be used to bridge the morphology and optical properties assuming that they can be performed in an accurate manner. In this paper, we study key factors that influence the accuracy of electromagnetic simulations. First, we compare several standard electromagnetic simulation methods and discuss in detail the effects of the meshing accuracy, choice of dielectric function and inclusion of a substrate for the boundary element method. To help the boundary element methods complex parametrization, we develop a workflow including reconstruction, meshing and mesh simplification steps to be able to use electron tomography data as input for these simulations. In particular, we analyze how the choice of reconstruction algorithm and the intricacies of image segmentation influence the simulated optical cross sections and correlate it to induced shape errors, which can be minimized in the data processing pipeline. In our case, optimal results could be obtained by using the Total Variation Minimization (TVM) reconstruction method in combination with Otsu thresholding and slight smoothing, which was important to create a reliable and watertight surface mesh using the marching cubes algorithm, especially for more complex shapes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08093v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mees Dieperink, Alexander Skorikov, Nathalie Claes, Sara Bals, Wiebke Albrecht</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable on-chip multiplexing of silicon single and double quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.12131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.12131v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Owing to the maturity of complementary metal oxide semiconductor (CMOS) microelectronics, qubits realized with spins in silicon quantum dots (QDs) are considered among the most promising technologies for building scalable quantum computers. For this goal, ultra-low-power on-chip cryogenic CMOS (cryo-CMOS) electronics for control, read-out, and interfacing of the qubits is an important milestone. We report on-chip interfacing of tunable electron and hole QDs by a 64-channel cryo-CMOS multiplexer with less-than-detectable static power dissipation. We analyze charge noise and measure state-of-the-art addition energies and gate lever arm parameters in the QDs. We correlate low noise in QDs and sharp turn-on characteristics in cryogenic transistors, both fabricated with the same gate stack. Finally, we demonstrate that our hybrid quantum-CMOS technology provides a route to scalable interfacing of a large number of QD devices, enabling, for example, variability analysis and QD qubit geometry optimization, which are prerequisites for building large-scale silicon-based quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.12131v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s42005-024-01806-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications Physics 7, 323 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Heorhii Bohuslavskyi, Alberto Ronzani, Joel H\"atinen, Arto Rantala, Andrey Shchepetov, Panu Koppinen, Janne S. Lehtinen, Mika Prunnila</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of geometry on chemical analysis exemplified for photoelectron spectroscopy of black silicon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.10625</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.10625v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For smooth surfaces, chemical composition can be readily analyzed using various spectroscopic techniques, a prominent example is X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS), where the relative proportions of the elements are mainly determined by the intensity ratio of the element-specific photoelectrons. However, this analysis becomes more complex for nanorough surfaces like black silicon (b-Si) due to the geometry's steep slopes, which mimic local variations in emission angles. In this study, we explicitly quantify this effect through an integral geometric analysis using Minkowski tensors, correlating XPS chemical data with topographical information from Atomic Force Microscopy (AFM). This approach yields reliable estimates of layer thicknesses for nanorough surfaces. For b-Si, we found that the oxide layer is approximately 50% thicker than the native oxide layer on a standard Si wafer. This study underscores the significant impact of nanoscale geometries on chemical property analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.10625v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jens U. Neurohr, Anton Wittig, Hendrik H\"ahl, Friederike Nolle, Thomas Faidt, Samuel Grandthyll, Karin Jacobs, Michael A. Klatt, Frank M\"uller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coexistence of non-trivial van der Waals magnetic orders enable field-free spin-orbit torque switching at room temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.13408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.13408v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The discovery of van der Waals (vdW) magnetic materials exhibiting non-trivial and tunable magnetic interactions can give rise to exotic magnetic states, which are not readily attainable with conventional materials. Such vdW magnets can provide a unique platform for studying new magnetic phenomena and realizing magnetization dynamics for energy-efficient and non-volatile spintronic memory and computing technologies. Here, we discover the coexistence of ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic orders in vdW magnet (Co0.5Fe0.5)5-xGeTe2 (CFGT) CFGT above room temperature, inducing an intrinsic exchange bias and canted perpendicular magnetism. Such non-trivial intrinsic magnetic order enables us to realize energy-efficient, magnetic field-free, and deterministic spin-orbit torque (SOT) switching of CFGT in heterostructure with Pt. The devices show a very large spin Hall conductivity, a low critical current density, and yield a large SOT effective field. These experiments, together with density functional theory and Monte Carlo simulations establish coexisting non-trivial magnetic orders in CFGT that enable field-free SOT magnetization dynamics in spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.13408v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bing Zhao, Lakhan Bainsla, Soheil Ershadrad, Lunjie Zeng, Roselle Ngaloy, Peter Svedlindh, Eva Olsson, Biplab Sanyal, Saroj P. Dash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing the Microscopic Mechanism of Displacive Excitation of Coherent Phonons in a Bulk Rashba Semiconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.08411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.08411v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Changing the macroscopic properties of quantum materials by optically activating collective lattice excitations has recently become a major trend in solid state physics. One of the most commonly employed light-matter interaction routes is the displacive mechanism. However, the fundamental contribution to this process remains elusive, as the effects of free-carrier density modification and raised effective electronic temperature have not been disentangled yet. Here we use time-resolved pump-probe spectroscopy to address this issue in the Rashba semiconductor BiTeI. Exploring the conventional regime of electronic interband transitions for different excitation wavelengths as well as the barely accessed regime of electronic intraband transitions, we answer a long-standing open question regarding the displacive mechanism: the lattice modes are predominantly driven by the rise of the effective electronic temperature. In the intraband regime, which allows to increase the effective carrier temperature while leaving their density unaffected, the phonon coherence time does not display significant fluence-dependent variations. Our results thus reveal a pathway to displacive excitation of coherent phonons, free from additional scattering and dissipation mechanisms typically associated with an increase of the free-carrier density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.08411v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peter Fischer, Julian Baer, Moritz Cimander, Volker Wiechert, Oleg Tereshchenko, Davide Bossini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single and multi-frequency driving protocols in a Rashba nanowire proximitized to an s-wave superconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.11307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.11307v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We perform systematic analyses of single and multi-frequency driving protocols on a Rashba nanowire with superconducting correlations induced by proximity effects. The results for the single-mode drive reveal interesting frequency dependencies of the Majorana modes, in the sense that the parameters corresponding to the trivial and topological limits of the undriven (static) case host Majorana zero modes, respectively at low and high frequencies. Further, emergence of long-range interactions are noted that give rise to multiple gap-closing scenarios, which imply occurrence of multiple Majorana modes. On the other hand, the multi-frequency driving protocol, sub-grouped into commensurate and incommensurate ratios of the frequencies, demonstrates intriguing consequences. The commensurate case yields dynamical control over the stability of the edge modes. Moreover, complex driving protocols harm the Majoranas by pushing them into the bulk. Finally, the incommensurate case yields independent Majorana modes occurring at low-symmetry points in the Brillouin zone. While the single and the commensurate multi-frequency driving protocols admit the usage of symmetric time frames for the computation of the topological invariants, the incommensurate case relies on the framework of many-mode Floquet theory, where the topological properties are ascertained via calculating the Berry phase. We present band structure and phase diagrams to substantiate all our results. The robustness and concurrent existence of these unique Majorana modes, even amidst a very dense energy spectrum along with a lack of global time-periodicity, hold promise for applications in quantum computing and the development of Floquet time crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.11307v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.165403</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 165403 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Koustav Roy, Saurabh Basu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Haldane model on the Sierpi\'nski gasket</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20075v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the topological phases of the Haldane model on the Sierpi\'nski gasket. As a consequence of the fractal geometry, multiple fractal gaps arise. Additionally, a flat band appears, and due to a complex next-nearest neighbour hopping, this band splits and multiple topological flux-induced gaps emerge. Owing to the fractal nature of the model, conventional momentum-space topological invariants cannot be used. Therefore, we characterise the system's topology in terms of a real-space Chern number. In addition, we verify the robustness of the topological states to disorder. Finally, we present phase diagrams for both a fractal gap and a flux-induced gap. Previous work on a similar system claims that fractality "squeezes" the well-known Haldane phase diagram. However, this result arises because a doubled system was considered with two Sierpi\'nski gaskets glued together. We consider only a single copy of the Sierpi\'nski gasket, keeping global self-similarity. In contrast with these previous results, we find intricate and complex patterns in the phase diagram of this single fractal. Our work shows that the fractality of the model greatly influences the phase space of these structures, and can drive topological phases in the multitude of fractal and flux-induced gaps, providing a richer platform than a conventional integer dimensional geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20075v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zebedeus Osseweijer, Lumen Eek, Anouar Moustaj, Mikael Fremling, Cristiane Morais Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear transport theory at the order of quantum metric</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.04995</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.04995v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum metric, a probe to spacetime of the Hilbert space, has been found measurable in the nonlinear electronic transport and attracted tremendous interest. We show that the quantum metric is only a tip of the iceberg, by deriving unknown 11 out of 14 formulas of the quadratic nonlinear conductivity under the same symmetry that the quantum metric emerges. The formulas allow us to determine nonzero nonlinear conductivity elements for the magnetic point groups, calculate the quadratic nonlinear conductivity for arbitrary Hamiltonian, e.g., the even-layered MnBi$_2$Ti$_4$ thin films with and without the $C_{3}$ symmetry, and formulate scaling laws at the order of quantum metric to distinguish different mechanisms in the recent experiments. The theory is a comprehensive description of the quadratic nonlinear transport and will facilitate future experiments and applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.04995v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen-Hao Gong, Z. Z. Du, Hai-Peng Sun, Hai-Zhou Lu, X. C. Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Catalog of Unconventional Magnons in Collinear Magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.12366</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.12366v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Topological magnons have garnered significant interest for their potential in both fundamental research and device applications, owing to their exotic, uncharged, yet topologically protected boundary modes. However, their comprehension has been hindered by the absence of fundamental symmetry descriptions of magnetic materials, which are primarily governed by isotropic Heisenberg interactions in spin Hamiltonians. The ensuing magnon dispersions enable gapless magnon band nodes that go beyond the scenario of representation theory of the magnetic space groups (MSGs), thus referred to as unconventional magnons. Here we developed spin space group (SSG) theory to elucidate collinear magnetic configurations, classifying the 1421 collinear SSGs into four types, constructing their band representations, and providing a comprehensive tabulation of unconventional magnons, such as duodecuple points, octuple nodal lines, and charge-4 octuple points. Based on the MAGNDATA database, we identified 498 collinear magnets with unconventional magnons, among which over 200 magnon band structures were obtained by using first-principles calculations and linear spin wave theory. Additionally, we evaluated the influence of the spin-orbit coupling-induced exchange interaction in these magnets and found that more than 80% are predominantly governed by the Heisenberg interactions, indicating that SSG serves as an ideal framework for describing magnon band nodes in most 3d, 4d and half-filled 4f collinear magnets. Our work offers new pathways for exploring uncharged transports in magnonic systems, holding promise for advancements in next-generation spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.12366v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaobing Chen, Yuntian Liu, Pengfei Liu, Yutong Yu, Jun Ren, Jiayu Li, Ao Zhang, Qihang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting Multipartite Entanglement Patterns using Single Particle Green's Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.05870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.05870v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a protocol for detecting multipartite entanglement in itinerant many-body electronic systems using single particle Green's functions. To achieve this, we first establish a connection between the quantum Fisher information (QFI) and single particle Green's functions by constructing a set of witness operators built out of single electron creation and destruction operators in a doubled system. This set of witness operators is indexed by a momenta $k$. We compute the QFI for these witness operators and show that for thermal ensembles it can be expressed as an auto-convolution of the single particle spectral function. We then apply our framework to a one-dimensional fermionic system to showcase its effectiveness in detecting entanglement in itinerant electron models. We observe that the detected entanglement level is sensitive to the wave vector associated with witness operator. Our protocol will permit detecting entanglement in many-body systems using scanning tunneling microscopy and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy, two spectroscopies that measure the single particle Green's function. It offers the prospect of the experimental detection of entanglement through spectroscopies beyond the established route of measuring the dynamical spin response.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.05870v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajesh K. Malla, Andreas Weichselbaum, Tzu-Chieh Wei, Robert M. Konik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Driving a Josephson Traveling Wave Parametric Amplifier into chaos: effects of a non-sinusoidal current-phase relation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01185v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we develop a comprehensive numerical analysis of the dynamic response of a Josephson Traveling Wave Parametric Amplifier (JTWPA) by varying the driving parameters, with a focus on the pathways leading to chaotic behavior. By tuning the working conditions, we capture the broad spectrum of dynamical regimes accessible to JTWPAs, delineating the settings under which transition to chaos occurs. Furthermore, we extend our investigation to device formed by junctions characterized by a non--sinusoidal current phase relation (CPR) and exploring the impact of its shape on the amplifier's performance. Through the study of gain characteristics, Poincar\'e sections, and Fourier spectra, we provide an in-depth understanding of how non-linearity and CPR nonsinusoidality influence the JTWPAs' operational effectiveness and stability. This investigation offers insights into optimizing the device designs for enhanced performance and robustness against chaotic disruptions, in order to establish a framework for predicting and controlling JTWPA behavior in practical applications. This effort will pave the way for the development of devices with tailored dynamic responses and for advancements in quantum computing and precision measurement technologies, where stability and high fidelity are of paramount importance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01185v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.chaos.2024.115598</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chaos, Solitons Fractals, 189, 115598 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Claudio Guarcello, Carlo Barone, Giovanni Carapella, Veronica Granata, Giovanni Filatrella, Andrea Giachero, Sergio Pagano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Designing metasurface optical interfaces for solid-state qubits using many-body adjoint shape optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.08212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.08212v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a general strategy for the inverse design of metasurfaces composed of elementary shapes. We use it to design a structure that collects and collimates light from nitrogen-vacancy centers in diamond. Such metasurfaces constitute scalable optical interfaces for solid-state qubits, enabling efficient photon coupling into optical fibers and eliminating free-space collection optics. The many-body shape optimization strategy is a practical alternative to topology optimization that explicitly enforces material and fabrication constraints throughout the optimization, while still achieving high performance. The metasurface is easily adaptable to other solid-state qubits, and the optimization method is broadly applicable to fabrication-constrained photonic design problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.08212v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1364/OE.522501</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Opt. Express 32, 38504-38515 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Amelia R. Klein, Nader Engheta, Lee C. Bassett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-component fractional quantum Hall effect in topological flat bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08568v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the many-body ground states of three-component quantum particles in two prototypical topological lattice models under strong intercomponent and intracomponent repulsions. At band filling $\nu=3/4$ for hardcore bosons, we demonstrate the emergence of three-component fractional quantum Hall (FQH) effect characterized by the $\mathbf{K}$ matrix, through exact diagonalization study of four-fold quasidegenerate ground states with a robust spectrum gap and the combined density-matrix renormalization group calculation of fractional drag charge pumping. Further we formulate the topological characterization of FQH states of three-component Bose-Fermi mixtures at various fillings by the $\mathbf{K}$ matrix. At last we discuss the possible generalization of our approach to identify non-Abelian three-component spin-singlet FQH states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08568v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.165126</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, 165126 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tian-Sheng Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting axion dynamics on the surface of magnetic topological insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17230v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Axions, initially proposed to solve the strong CP problem, have recently gained attention in condensed matter physics, particularly in topological insulators. However, detecting axion dynamics has proven challenging, with no experimental confirmations to date. In this study, we identify the surface of magnetic topological insulators as an ideal platform for observing axion dynamics. The vanishing bulk gap at the surface allows for order $O(1)$ variations in the axion field, making the detection of axion-like phenomena more feasible. In contrast, these phenomena are strongly suppressed in the bulk due to the small magnetic exchange gap. We investigate two-photon decay as a signature of axion dynamics and calculate the branching ratio using a perturbative approach. Our findings reveal that the photon flux emitted from the surface is in-plane and orders of magnitude larger than that from the bulk, making it detectable with modern microwave technology. We also discuss potential material platforms for detecting axion two-photon decay and strategies to enhance the signal-to-noise ratio.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17230v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhi-Qiang Gao, Taige Wang, Michael P. Zaletel, Dung-Hai Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of dynamical electron correlations on the tunnelling magnetoresistance of Fe/MgO/Fe(001) junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06679v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We employ dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT) combined with density functional theory (DFT) and the non-equilibrium Green's function technique to investigate the steady-state transport properties of an Fe/MgO/Fe magnetic tunnel junction (MTJ), focusing on the impact of dynamical electron correlations on the Fe $3d$ orbitals. By applying the rigid shift approximation, we extend the calculations from zero- to finite-bias in a simple and computationally efficient manner, obtaining the bias-dependent electronic structure and current-versus-voltage characteristic curve in both the parallel and antiparallel configurations. In particular, we find that dynamical electron correlation manifests as a reduction in the spin splitting of the Fe $3d_{z^2}$ state compared to DFT predictions and introduces a finite relaxation time. The impact of these effects on the transport properties, however, varies significantly between magnetic configurations. In the parallel configuration, the characteristic curves obtained with DFT and DMFT are similar, as the transport is mostly due to the coherent transmission of spin-up electrons through the MgO barrier. Conversely, in the antiparallel configuration, correlation effects become more significant, with DMFT predicting a sharp current increase due to bias-driven inelastic electron-electron scattering. As a consequence, DMFT gives a lower bias threshold for the suppression of the tunneling magnetoresistance ratio compared to DFT, matching experimental data more closely.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06679v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Declan Nell, Stefano Sanvito, Ivan Rungger, Andrea Droghetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
