<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 04:01:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Superconducting Cavity-Based Sensing of Band Gaps in 2D Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05867v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The superconducting coplanar waveguide (SCPW) cavity plays an essential role in various areas like superconducting qubits, parametric amplifiers, radiation detectors, and studying magnon-photon and photon-phonon coupling. Despite its wide-ranging applications, the use of SCPW cavities to study various van der Waals 2D materials is relatively unexplored. The resonant modes of the SCPW cavity exquisitely sense the dielectric environment. In this work, we measure the charge compressibility of bilayer graphene coupled to a half-wavelength SCPW cavity. Our approach provides a means to detect subtle changes in the capacitance of the bilayer graphene heterostructure, which depends on the compressibility of bilayer graphene, manifesting as shifts in the resonant frequency of the cavity. This method holds promise for exploring a wide class of van der Waals 2D materials, including transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) and their moir\'e where DC transport measurement is challenging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05867v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.nanolett.3c04990</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Krishnendu Maji, Joydip Sarkar, Supriya Mandal, Sriram H., Mahesh Hingankar, Ayshi Mukherjee, Soumyajit Samal, Anirban Bhattacharjee, Meghan P. Patankar, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Mandar M. Deshmukh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancement of interlayer exciton emission in a TMDC heterostructure via a multi-resonant chirped microresonator up to room temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06008v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report on multi-resonance chirped distributed Bragg reflector (DBR) microcavities. These systems are employed to investigate the light-mater interaction with both intra- and inter-layer excitons of transition metal dichalcogenide (TMDC) bilayer heterostructures. The chirped DBRs consisting of SiO2 and Si3N4 layers with gradually changing thickness exhibit a broad stopband with a width exceeding 600 nm. Importantly, and in contrast to conventional single-resonance microcavities, our structures provide multiple resonances across a broad spectral range, which can be matched to spectrally distinct resonances of the embedded TMDC heterostructures. We study cavity-coupled emission of both intra- and inter-layer excitons from an integrated WSe2/MoSe2 heterostructure in a chirped microcavity system. We observe an enhanced interlayer exciton emission with a Purcell factor of 6.67 +- 1.02 at 4 K. Additionally, we take advantage of cavity-enhanced emission of the interlayer exciton to investigate its temperature-dependent luminescence lifetime, which yields a value of 60 ps at room temperature. Our approach provides an intriguing platform for future studies of energetically distant and confined excitons in different semiconducting materials, which paves the way for various applications such as microlasers and single-photon sources by enabling precise control and manipulation of excitonic interactions utilizing multimode resonance light-matter interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06008v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chirag C. Palekar, Barbara Rosa, Niels Heermeier, Ching-Wen Shih, Imad Limame, Aris Koulas-Simos, Arash Rahimi-Iman, Stephan Reitzenstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic magnetism in KTaO$_3$ heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06022v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: There has been intense recent interest in the two-dimensional electron gases (2DEGs) that form at the surfaces and interfaces of KTaO$_3$ (KTO), with the discovery of superconductivity at temperatures significantly higher than those of similar 2DEGs based on SrTiO$_3$ (STO). Like STO heterostructures, these KTO 2DEGs are formed by depositing an overlayer on top of appropriately prepared KTO surfaces. Some of these overlayers are magnetic, and the resulting 2DEGs show signatures of this magnetism, including hysteresis in the magnetoresistance (MR). Here we show that KTO 2DEGs fabricated by depositing AlO$_x$ on top of KTO also show hysteretic MR, indicative of long range magnetic order, even though the samples nominally contain no intrinsic magnetic elements. The hysteresis appears in both the transverse and longitudinal resistance in magnetic fields both perpendicular to and in the plane of the 2DEG. The hysteretic MR has different characteristic fields and shapes for surfaces of different crystal orientations, and vanishes above a few Kelvin. Density functional theory (DFT) calculations indicate that the magnetism likely arises from Ta$^{4+}$ local moments created in the presence of oxygen vacancies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06022v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0189956</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Appl. Phys. Lett. 26 February 2024; 124 (9): 093102</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Patrick W. Krantz, Alexander Tyner, Pallab Goswami, Venkat Chandrasekhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implementation and characterization of the dice lattice in the electron quantum simulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06040v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Materials featuring touching points, localized states, and flat bands are of great interest in condensed matter and artificial systems due to their implications in topology, quantum geometry, superconductivity, and interactions. In this theoretical study, we propose the experimental realization of the dice lattice with adjustable parameters by arranging carbon monoxide molecules on a two-dimensional electron system at a (111) copper surface. First, we develop a theoretical framework to obtain the spectral properties within a nearly free electron approximation and then compare them with tight-binding calculations. Our investigation reveals that the high mobility of Shockley state electrons enables an accurate theoretical description of the artificial lattice using a next-nearest-neighbor tight-binding model, resulting in the emergence of a touching point, a quasi-flat band, and localized lattice site behavior in the local density of states. Additionally, we present theoretical results for a long-wavelength low-energy model that accounts for next-nearest-neighbor hopping terms. Furthermore, we theoretically examine the model's behavior under an external magnetic field by employing Peierl's substitution, a commonly used technique in theoretical physics to incorporate magnetic fields into lattice models. Our theoretical findings suggest that, owing to the exceptional electron mobility, the highly degenerate eigenenergy associated with the Aharonov-Bohm caging mechanism may not manifest in the proposed experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06040v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Camillo Tassi, Dario Bercioux</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Drag on Cylinders Moving in Superfluid 3He-B as the Dimension Spans the Coherence Length</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06226v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vibrating probes when immersed in a fluid can provide powerful tools for characterising the surrounding medium. In superfluid 3He-B, a condensate of Cooper pairs, the dissipation arising from the scattering of quasiparticle excitations from a mechanical oscillator provides the basis of extremely sensitive thermometry and bolometry at sub-millikelvin temperatures. The unique properties of the Andreev reflection process in this condensate also assist by providing a significantly enhanced dissipation. While existing models for such damping on an oscillating cylinder have been verified experimentally, they are valid only for flows with scales much greater than the coherence length of 3He, which is of the order of a hundred nanometres. With our increasing proficiency in fabricating nanosized oscillators which can be readily used in this superfluid there is a pressing need for the development of new models that account for the modification of the flow around these smaller oscillators. Here we report preliminary results on measurements of the damping in superfluid 3He-B of a range of cylindrical nano-sized oscillators with radii comparable to the coherence length, and outline a model for calculating the associated drag.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06226v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Autti, R. P. Haley, A. Jennings, G. R. Pickett, E. V. Surovtsev, V. Tsepelin, D. E. Zmeev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin Waves and Spin Currents in Magnon-Phonon Composite Resonator Induced by Acoustic Waves of Various Polarizations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06274v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we present the results of a systematic experimental study of linear and parametric spin wave resonant excitation accompanied by spin currents (spin pumping) in a multifrequency composite bulk acoustic wave resonator with a ZnO-YIG-GGG-YIG/Pt structure. The features of magnetic dynamics excitation in YIG films due to magnetoelastic coupling with acoustic thickness modes of various polarizations are studied. Acoustic spin waves and spin pumping are detected by simultaneous frequency-field mapping of the inverse spin Hall effect voltage and the resonant frequencies of thickness extensional modes. In the parametric range of frequencies and fields, acoustic spin pumping induced by both shear and longitudinal polarization modes was observed. Linear acoustic spin waves are excited only by shear thickness extensional modes because longitudinal acoustic waves do not couple with the magnetic subsystem in linear regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06274v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. G. Alekseev, N. I. Polzikova, V. A. Luzanov, S. A. Nikitov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>f(R,T) Analogue Gravity in (2+1) D graphene sheet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06283v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We examine the analogue gravity model within the context of f(R,T) gravity applied to graphene. The derivation of the Lagrangian density in two dimensions (2D) is undertaken, accounting for the altered gravitational effects as characterized by the function f(R,T). The Lagrangian encompasses the quasiparticle field $\psi(x)$, its adjoint $\overline{\psi}$, the effective metric tensor $g^{\mu\nu}$, and the gauge field $A_{\nu}$. The equations of motion are established through variational principles applied to the Lagrangian, resulting in modified Dirac equations. We discuss the interpretation of the additional terms in the equations of motion and their significance in capturing the modified gravitational dynamics in the graphene system. Our findings contribute to the understanding of analogue gravity models and their applications in condensed matter systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06283v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcelo Lapola, Luiz Antonio Barreiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of quantum cellular automata electron transition in triple quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06333v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum cellular automata (QCA) effect is a transition in which multiple electron move coordinately by Coulomb interactions and observed in multiple quantum dots. This effect will be useful for realizing and improving quantum cellular automata and information transfer using multiple electron transfer. In this paper, we investigate the real-time dynamics of the QCA charge transitions in a triple quantum dot by using fast charge-state readout realized by rf reflectometry. We observe real-time charge transitions and analyze the tunneling rate comparing with the first-order tunneling processes. We also measure the gate voltage dependence of the QCA transition and show that it can be controlled by the voltage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06333v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takumi Aizawa, Motoya Shinozaki, Yoshihiro Fujiwara, Takeshi Kumasaka, Wataru Izumida, Arne Ludwig, Andreas D. Wieck, Tomohiro Otsuka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic characteristics of terahertz hot-electron graphene FET bolometers: effect of electron cooling in channel and at side contacts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06373v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze the operation of the hot-electron FET bolometers with the graphene channels (GCs) and the gate barrier layers (BLs). Such bolometers use the thermionic emission of the hot electrons heated by incident modulated THz radiation. The hot electron transfer from the GC into the metal gate. As the THz detectors, these bolometers can operate at room temperature. We show that the response and ultimate modulation frequency of the GC-FET bolometers are determined by the efficiency of the hot-electron energy transfer to the lattice and the GC side contacts due to the 2DEG lateral thermal conductance. The dependences of these mechanisms on the band structure and geometrical parameters open the way for the GC-FET bolometers optimization, in particular, for the enhancement of the maximum modulation frequency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06373v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Ryzhii, C. Tang, T. Otsuji, M. Ryzhii, V. Mitin, M. S. Shur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dyakonov-Shur instability of electronic fluid: Spectral effect of weak magnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06386v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study numerically and analytically how the Dyakonov-Shur instability for a two-dimensional (2D) inviscid electronic fluid in a long channel can be affected by an external, out-of-plane static magnetic field. By linear stability analysis for a model based on the shallow-water equations, we describe the discrete spectrum of frequencies in the complex plane. When the fluid system is near the subsonic-to-supersonic transition point, a magnetically controlled gap between the stability and instability spectra of the complex eigen-frequencies is evident by our computations. This suggests that the passage from stability to instability (and vice versa) is no longer continuous in the effective Mach parameter of the boundary conditions. We connect this complex-valued gap to a multivalued function characterizing the exact electronic steady state. In a regime of weak magnetic fields, we derive a scaling law for the eigen-frequencies by perturbation theory. We discuss implications of our results in efforts to generate terahertz electromagnetic radiation by 2D electronic transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06386v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Maier, Dennis Corraliza, Dionisios Margetis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Formation of artificial Fermi surfaces with a triangular superlattice on a conventional two dimensional electron gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06426v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In nearly free electron theory the imposition of a periodic electrostatic potential on free electrons creates the bandstructure of a material, determined by the crystal lattice spacing and geometry. Imposing an artificially designed potential to the electrons confined in a GaAs quantum well makes it possible to engineer synthetic two-dimensional band structures, with electronic properties different from those in the host semiconductor. Here we report the fabrication and study of a tuneable triangular artificial lattice on a GaAs/AlGaAs heterostructure where it is possible to transform from the original GaAs bandstructure and Fermi surface to a new bandstructure with multiple artificial Fermi surfaces simply by altering a gate bias. For weak electrostatic potential modulation magnetotransport measurements reveal quantum oscillations from the GaAs two-dimensional Fermi surface, and classical oscillations due to these electrons scattering from the artificial lattice. Increasing the strength of the modulation reveals new quantum oscillations due to the formation of multiple artificial Fermi surfaces, and ultimately to new classical oscillations of the electrons from the artificial Fermi surface scattering from the superlattice modulation. These results show that low disorder gate-tuneable lateral superlattices can be used to form artificial two dimensional crystals with designer electronic properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06426v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.nanolett.2c04358</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Daisy Q. Wang, Zeb Krix, Oleg P. Sushkov, Ian Farrer, David A. Ritchie, Alexander R. Hamilton, Oleh Klochan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What is a proper definition of spin current? -- Lessons from the Kane-Mele Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06472v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin current, a key concept in spintronics that carries spin angular momentum, has a non-unique definition due to the non-conservation of spins in solids. While two primary definitions exist -- conventional spin current and conserved spin current -- their validity has not been quantitatively examined. Here, we examine the validity of these definitions of spin current by comparing their spin Hall conductivities to the spin accumulation on edges of materials calculated in a real-time evolution simulation. Employing the Kane-Mele model with the Rashba term, which explicitly violates spin conservation, we reveal that the spin Hall conductivities calculated under both definitions fail to reproduce the simulated results of spin accumulation when the Rashba term is large. Our results suggest that the standard definitions of spin current and the associated spin Hall conductivity do not give an accurate quantitative estimate of spin accumulation. This conclusion indicates that real-time simulations are necessary to accurately estimate spin accumulation on edges/surfaces of materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06472v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomohiro Tamaya, Takeo Kato, Takahiro Misawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological transport of a classical droplet in a lattice of time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06500v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Thouless charge pumps are quantum mechanical devices whose operation relies on topology. They provide the means for transporting quantum matter in space lattices with a single quantum precision. Contrasting space crystals that spontaneously break a continuous spatial translation symmetry and form crystals in space,time crystals have emerged as novel states of matter that organize into time lattices and spontaneously break a discrete time translation symmetry. The utility of Thouless pumps that enable topologically protected quantised transport of electrons and neutral atoms in spatial superlattices leads to the question if corresponding devices exist for time crystals? Here we show that topological pumps can be realized for time solids by transporting droplets of a liquid forward and backward in time lattices and we measure the topological index that characterises such pumping processes. By exploiting a synthetic time dimension classical time crystals can circumvent the quantum tunneling that underpins Thouless charge pumps. Our results establish topological pumping through time instead of space and pave the way for applications of time crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06500v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tapio Simula, Niels Kj{\ae}rgaard, Tilman Pfau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Entanglement in a Diluted Magnetic Semiconductor Quantum Dot</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06522v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigated the entanglement in a diluted magnetic semiconductor quantum dot, crucial for quantum technologies. Despite their potential, these systems exhibit low extraction rates. We explore self-assembled InGaAs quantum dots, focusing on entanglement between them based on spin states. Our analysis involves defining wavefunctions, employing density matrix operators, and measuring entanglement entropy. Numerical assessments reveal few promising pairs among various quantum dot combinations that exhibit significant entanglement. Additionally, this work discusses theoretical developments and statistical evaluations of entanglement in diluted magnetic semiconductor quantum dots, providing insights into their potential for quantum applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06522v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manish Kumar Mehta, Joseph Thomas Andrews, Pratima Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological properties of a class of generalized Su-Schrieffer-Heeger networks: chains and meshes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06556v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyze the topological properties of a family of generalized Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) chains and mesh geometries. In both the geometries the usual staggering in the distribution of the two overlap integrals is delayed (in space) by the inclusion of a third (additional) hopping term. A tight-binding Hamiltonian is used to unravel the topological phases, characterized by a topological invariant. While in the linear chains, the topological invariant (the Zak phase) always appears to be quantized, in the quasi-one dimensional strip geometries and the generalized SSH mesh patterns the quantization of the Zak phase is sensitive to the strength of the additional interaction (the `extra' hopping integral). We study its influence thoroughly and explore the edge states and their robustness against disorder in the cross-linked generalized SSH mesh geometries. The systems considered here can be taken to model (though crudely) two-dimensional polymers where the cross-linking brings in non-trivial modification of the energy bands and transport properties. In addition to the topological features studied, we provide a prescription to unravel any flat, non-dispersive energy bands in the mesh geometries, along with the structure and distribution of the compact localized eigenstates. Our results are analytically exact.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06556v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sougata Biswas, Arunava Chakrabarti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermoelectric transport of the coexistence topological semimetal in the quantum limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We explore the thermoelectric transport properties of a coexistence topological semimetal, characterized by the presence of both a pair of Weyl points and a nodal ring in the quantum limit. This system gives rise to complex Landau bands when subjected to a magnetic field aligned with the direction connecting two Weyl points. In the longitudinal configuration, where the magnetic field is parallel to the electric field or the temperature gradient, the thermoelectric conductivity indicates a plateau independent of the magnetic field and the Fermi energy at $\delta$-form short-range scattering. This platform structure should also exist in pure two-node Weyl semimetals. However, the thermoelectric conductivity and the Seebeck coefficient are significantly influenced by the parameters of long-ranged Gaussian or screened Coulomb scattering potentials for both fixed carrier density and Fermi energy scenarios. In the transverse configuration, both Gaussian and screened Coulomb scatterings yield substantial positive magnetoresistance and thermoelectric conductance. Since the Hall conductivity is larger than the longitudinal one, the Seebeck coefficient, exhibiting a quadratic increase with the magnetic field, is close to the dissipationless limit irrespective of scatterings, while the Nernst response is notably dependent on the scattering mechanism. Additionally, the model parameter, distinct from the two-node Weyl model, influences the thermoelectric transport properties. The magnetic field response of the thermoelectric coefficients to different scattering potentials can be used as a basis for distinguishing scattering mechanisms in materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06603v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. W. Guo, C. M. Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hot Carrier Nanowire Transistors at the Ballistic Limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06630v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate experimentally non-equilibrium transport in unipolar quasi-1D hot electron devices reaching ballistic limit. The devices are realized with heterostructure engineering in nanowires to obtain dopant- and dislocation-free 1D-epitaxy and flexible bandgap engineering. We show experimentally the control of hot electron injection with a graded conduction band profile and subsequent filtering of hot and relaxed electrons with rectangular energy barriers. The number of electron passing the barrier depends exponentially on the transport length with a mean free path of 200 - 260 nm and reaches ballistic transport regime for the shortest devices with 70 % of the electrons flying freely through the base electrode and the barrier reflections limiting the transport to the collector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06630v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Kumar, A. Nowzari, A. R. Persson, S. Jeppesen, A. Wacker, G. Bastard, R. Wallenberg, F. Capasso, V. F. Maisi, L. Samuelson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Two-Field-Scan Harmonic Hall Voltage Analysis For Fast, Accurate Quantification Of Spin-Orbit Torques In Magnetic Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06740v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The efficiencies of the spin-orbit torques (SOTs) play a key role in the determination of the power consumption, integration density, and endurance of SOT-driven devices. Accurate and time-efficient determination of the SOT efficiencies is of great importance not only for evaluating the practical potential of SOT devices but also for developing new mechanisms for enhancing the SOT efficiencies. Here, we develop a "two-field-scan" harmonic Hall voltage (HHV) analysis that collects the second HHV as a function of a swept in-plane magnetic field at 45{\deg} and 0{\deg} relative to the excitation current. We demonstrate that this two-field-scan analysis is as accurate as the well-established but time-consuming angle-scan HHV analysis even in the presence of considerable thermoelectric effects but takes more than a factor of 7 less measurement time. We also show that the 3-parameter fit of the HHV data from a single field scan at 0{\deg}, which is commonly employed in the literature, is not reliable because the employment of too many free parameters in the fitting of the very slowly varying HHV signal allows unrealistic pseudo-solution and thus erroneous conclusion about the SOT efficiencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06740v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Lin, Lijun Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital relaxation length from first-principles scattering calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06827v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The orbital Hall effect generates a current of orbital angular momentum perpendicular to a charge current. Experiments suggest that this orbital current decays on a long length scale that is of the order of the spin flip diffusion length or longer. We examine this suggestion using first-principles quantum mechanical scattering calculations to study the decay of orbital currents injected from an orbitally-polarized lead into thermally disordered bulk systems of selected transition metals. We find that the decay occurs over only a few atomic layers. On this length scale the orbital current may be converted into a spin current if the spin Hall angle is sufficiently large, as for Pt. In Cu, Cr and V with small spin Hall angles, the conversion into a spin current is negligible in the bulk and significant conversion only occurs at interfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06827v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Rang, Paul J. Kelly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anderson-Higgs amplitude mode in Josephson junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06878v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Anderson-Higgs mode in a superconductor corresponds to a collective and coherent oscillation of the order parameter amplitude. We propose to detect this mode in a tunnel Josephson junction between two singlet s-wave diffusive superconductors. We find a strong enhancement of the tunneling current when the junction is pumped at the equilibrium gap frequency, corresponding to the activation of the Anderson-Higgs mode. By solving the Keldysh-Usadel equations, we obtain current peaks at specific bias voltages that can serve as signatures of the Anderson-Higgs mode.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06878v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre Vallet, J\'er\^ome Cayssol</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heat transport in the quantum Rabi model: Universality and ultrastrong coupling effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heat transport in the quantum Rabi model at weak interaction with the heat baths is controlled by the qubit-oscillator coupling. Universality of the linear conductance versus the temperature is found for $T\lesssim T_K$, with $T_K$ a coupling-dependent Kondo-like temperature. At low temperature, coherent heat transfer via virtual processes yields a $\sim T^3$ behavior with destructive interference in the presence of quasi-degeneracies in the spectrum. As the temperature increases, incoherent emission and absorption dominate and a maximum is reached at $T\sim T_K/2$. In the presence of a bias on the qubit, the conductance makes a transition from a resonant to a broad, zero-bias peak regime. Parallels and differences are found compared to the spin-boson model in [K. Saito and T. Kato, Phys. Rev. Lett. \textbf{111}, 214301 (2013)], where the qubit-bath coupling instead of the internal qubit-oscillator coupling rules thermal transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06909v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Magazz\`u, E. Paladino, M. Grifoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of spin torques and spin pumping phenomena on magnon-plasmon polaritons in antiferromagnetic insulator-semiconductor heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06934v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the impact of spin torque and spin pumping on the surface magnon polariton dispersion in a antiferromagnetic insulator-semiconductor heterostructure. In the bilayer system, the surface magnon polaritons conventionally couple to the plasma-oscillations in the semiconductor via electromagnetic fields. Additionally, magnons in the antiferromagnetic insulator layer may interact with the semiconductor layer via spin torques and their reciprocal phenomena of spin pumping. Due to the spin-to-charge conversion from the spin Hall and inverse spin Hall effects in the semiconductor layer with a strong spin-orbit coupling, this can couple the magnons to the plasmons in the semiconductor layer. Our research reveals that modifications in the mode frequency and the hybridization gap induced by these phenomena depend on the thickness of the antiferromagnetic layer. In thick layers, the spin-pumping contribution to the frequency shift and damping is inversely proportional to the wavelength, while in thin layers it is inversely proportional to the thickness. Furthermore, hybridization of the surface magnon polariton and dispersive magnons in the antiferromagnet is shown to depend on both the thickness and wavelength of the modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06934v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vemund Falch, Jeroen Danon, Alireza Qaiumzadeh, Arne Brataas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-rectification near-field radiative thermal diode using Weyl semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05769v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Thermal diodes, which allow heat transfer in a preferential direction while being blocked in a reverse direction, have numerous applications in thermal management, information processing, energy harvesting, etc. Typical materials of thermal diodes in previous works include phase-change and magneto-optical materials. However, such thermal diodes highly depend on specific working temperatures or external magnetic fields. In this work, we propose a near-field radiative thermal diode (NFRTD) based on two Weyl semimetals (WSMs) nanoparticles (NPs) mediated by WSMs planar substrate, which works without external magnetic field and with flexible temperatures. Numerical results show that the maximum rectification ratio of NFRTD can be up to 2673 when the emitter is 200 K and receiver is 180 K, which exceeds the maximum value reported in previous works by more than 10 times. The underlying physical mechanism is the strong coupling of the localized plasmon modes in the NPs and nonreciprocal surface plasmon polaritons in the substrate. In addition, we calculate the distribution of the Green function and reflection coefficient to investigate nonreciprocal energy transfer in NFRTD. Finally, we discuss the effects of momentum-separation on the rectification performance of the NFRTD. This work demonstrates the great potential of WSMs in thermal rectification and paves a novel path in designing high-performance NFRTD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05769v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Hu, Haotuo Liu, Bing Yang, Kezhang Shi, Mauro Antezza, Xiaohu Wu, Yasong Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced performance of MoS$_2$/SiO$_2$ field-effect transistors by hexamethyldisilazane (HMDS) encapsulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05885v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Scalable methods for improving the performance and stability of a field-effect transistor (FET) based on two-dimensional materials are crucial for its real applications. A scalable method of encapsulating the exfoliated MoS$ _{2} $ on SiO$ _{2} $/Si substrate by hexamethyldisilazane (HMDS) is explored here for reducing the influence of interface traps and ambient contaminants. This leads to twenty-five times reduction in trap density, three times decrease in subthreshold swing, three times increase in the peak field-effect mobility and a drastic reduction in hysteresis. This performance remains nearly the same after several weeks of ambient exposure of the device. This is attributed to the superhydrophobic nature of HMDS and the SiO$_2$ surface hydrophobization by the formation of covalent bonds between the methyl groups of HMDS and silanol groups of SiO$_{2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05885v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Santu Prasad Jana,  Shivangi, Suraina Gupta, Anjan K. Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonequilibrium Casimir-Polder Force between Nanoparticles and Graphene-Coated Silica Plate: Combined Effect of the Chemical Potential and Mass Gap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05983v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Casimir-Polder force between spherical nanoparticles and a graphene-coated silica plate is investigated in situations out of thermal equilibrium, i.e., with broken time-reversal symmetry. The response of graphene coating to the electromagnetic field is described on the basis of first principles of quantum electrodynamics at nonzero temperature using the formalism of the polarization tensor in the framework of the Dirac model. The nonequilibrium Casimir-Polder force is calculated as a function of the mass-gap parameter, chemical potential of graphene and temperature of the graphene-coated plate, which can be both higher and lower than that of the environment. It is shown that the force value increases with increasing chemical potential, and this increase is more pronounced when the temperature of a graphene-coated plate is lower than that of the environment. The nonequilibrium force also increases with increasing temperature of the graphene-coated plate. This increase is larger when the plate is hotter than the environment. The effect is revealed that the combined impact of the chemical potential $\mu$ and mass gap $\Delta$ of graphene coating depends on the relationship between $\Delta$ and 2$\mu$. If $2\mu&gt;\Delta$ the magnitude of the nonequilibrium force between nanoparticles and a cooled graphene-coated plate becomes much larger than for a graphene coating with $\mu=0$. The physical reasons explaining this effect are elucidated. Possible applications of the obtained results are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05983v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/sym16030320</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Symmetry, v.16, N3, (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Galina L. Klimchitskaya, Constantine C. Korikov, Vladimir M. Mostepanenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Defects Genome of 2D Janus Transition Metal Dichalcogenides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06165v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) Janus Transition Metal Dichalcogenides (TMDs) have attracted much interest due to their exciting quantum properties arising from their unique two-faced structure, broken-mirror symmetry, and consequent colossal polarisation field within the monolayer. While efforts have been made to achieve high-quality Janus monolayers, the existing methods rely on highly energetic processes that introduce unwanted grain-boundary and point defects with still unexplored effects on the material's structural and excitonic properties Through High-resolution scanning transmission electron microscopy (HRSTEM), density functional theory (DFT), and optical spectroscopy measurements; this work introduces the most encountered and energetically stable point defects. It establishes their impact on the material's optical properties. HRSTEM studies show that the most energetically stable point defects are single (Vs and Vse) and double chalcogen vacancy (Vs-Vse), interstitial defects (Mi), and metal impurities (MW) and establish their structural characteristics. DFT further establishes their formation energies and related localized bands within the forbidden band. Cryogenic excitonic studies on h-BN-encapsulated Janus monolayers offer a clear correlation between these structural defects and observed emission features, which closely align with the results of the theory. The overall results introduce the defect genome of Janus TMDs as an essential guideline for assessing their structural quality and device properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06165v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Sayyad, Jan Kopaczek, Carmem M. Gilardoni, Weiru Chen, Yihuang Xiong, Shize Yang, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Robert Kudrawiec, Geoffroy Hautier, Mete Atature, Sefaattin Tongay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of in-gap states in a two-dimensional CrI2/NbSe2 heterostructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06215</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06215v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Low-dimensional magnetic structures coupled with a superconductor are promising platforms for realizing Majorana zero modes, which are considered as novel non-Abelian anyons with potential applications in topological quantum computing. Here, we report the observation of in-gap edge states and zero-bias conductance peaks (ZBCPs) in a two-dimensional (2D) magnetic-superconducting heterostructure consisting of a single-layer chromium diiodide (CrI2) on a niobium diselenide (NbSe2) superconductor. Single-layer CrI2 nanosheets, which hold antiferromagnetic (AFM) ground states according to our first-principles calculations, were epitaxially grown on the layered NbSe2 substrate. By using scanning tunneling microscopy/spectroscopy, we observed robust in-gap states spatially located at the edge of the nanosheets and defect-induced ZBCPs inside the CrI2 nanosheets. Magnetic-flux vortices induced by an external field exhibit broken threefold rotational symmetry of the pristine NbSe2 superconductor, implying the efficient modulation of the interfacial superconducting states by the epitaxial CrI2 layer. A phenomenological model was proposed and suggested the existence of chiral edge states in a 2D AFM-superconducting hybrid system with an even Chern number, providing a qualitatively plausible understanding for our experimental observation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06215v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peigen Li, Jihai Zhang, Di Zhu, Cui-Qun Chen, Enkui Yi, Bing Shen, Yusheng Hou, Zhongbo Yan, Dao-Xin Yao, Donghui Guo, Dingyong Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-heating effect in nanoscale SOI Junctionless FinFET with different geometries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06271v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work we study the self-heating (1) effect (SHE) in nanoscale Silicon on Insulator Junctionless (SOI JL) FinFET transistor with fi cross section in rectangular, trapeze and triangle form. The lattice temperature dependence on the channel length as well as on buried oxide thickness is considered. It is shown that for considered transistor structure the lattice temperature in the middle of the channel is lower than at lateral sides, near source and drain. Also, we have found at the same conditions the lattice temperature depends on shape of channel cross section too</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06271v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/CDE52135.2021.9455728</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>A. E. Atamuratov, B. O. Jabbarova, M. M. Khalilloev, A. Yusupov, A. G. Loureriro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum perspective for the non-equilibrium fluctuation relation and its experimental testing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06296v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Non-equilibrium fluctuation theorems (NFTs) relate work performed on a system as its Hamiltonian varies with time, to equilibrium data of the intial and final states. Testing these remarkable relations is currently restricted to classical systems or to simple quantum systems whose energy state can be directly measured. Here we introduce the concept of a quantum work agent in thermodynamic processes, and suggest that it can allow to probe NFTs in general quantum systems. We elaborate on a simple model in the framework of mesoscopic systems, and discuss future applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06296v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheolhee Han, Doron Cohen, Eran Sela</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid-order topology with tunable chiral hinge modes and unpinned Dirac surface states in the altermagnetic insulator Eu$_{3}$In$_{2}$As$_{4}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06304v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The exploration of magnetic topological states is instrumental in exploring axion electrodynamics and intriguing transport phenomena, such as the quantum anomalous Hall effect. Here, we predict that the recently-synthesized material Eu$_{3}$In$_{2}$As$_{4}$ exhibits as both an axion insulator and a 3D Stiefel-Whitney insulator with an altermagnetic order. When spins align in the $ab$ plane, we find an unpinned surface Dirac cone on the $ab$ plane and chiral hinge states along the $c$ direction, where hinge states can generate a half-quantized surface anomalous Hall effect on the $ac$ and $bc$ facets. When spins align along $c$, we observe a mirror-protected topological crystalline insulator. Furthermore, the ferromagnetic phase, in which spins are aligned in the same direction by an external in-plane magnetic field, presents an ideal Weyl semimetal with a single pair of type-I Weyl points and no extra Fermi pocket. Our work predicts rich topological states tuned by magnetic structures in Eu$_{3}$In$_{2}$As$_{4}$, supporting the further study of the topological transport and Majorana fermions in proximity to a superconductor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06304v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yufei Zhao, Hyeonhu Bae, Yiyang Jiang, Yongkang Li, Chao-Xing Liu, Binghai Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Handedness manipulation of propagating antiferromagnetic magnons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06549v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Antiferromagnetic magnons possess a distinctive feature absent in their ferromagnetic counterparts: the presence of two distinct handedness modes, the right-handed (RH) and left-handed (LH) precession modes. The magnon handedness determines the sign of spin polarization carried by the propagating magnon, which is indispensable for harnessing the diverse functionalities. However, the control of coherently propagating magnon handedness in antiferromagnets has remained elusive so far. Here we demonstrate the manipulation and electrical readout of propagating magnon handedness in perpendicularly magnetized synthetic antiferromagnets (SAF). We find that the antiferromagnetic magnon handedness can be directly identified by measuring the inverse spin Hall effect (ISHE) voltage, which arises from the spin pumping effect caused by the propagating antiferromagnetic magnons in the SAF structure. The RH and LH modes of the magnon can be distinguishable particularly when the SAF structure is sandwiched by heavy metals with the same sign of spin Hall angle. Moreover, we succeed in controlling the handedness of propagating antiferromagnetic magnons by tuning the excitation microwave frequency. This work unveils promising avenues for harnessing magnon unique properties in antiferromagnet-based magnonic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06549v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoichi Shiota, Tomohiro Taniguchi, Daiju Hayashi, Hideki Narita, Shutaro Karube, Ryusuke Hisatomi, Takahiro Moriyama, Teruo Ono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum thermodynamics of driven-dissipative condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06861v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Polariton condensates occur away from thermal equilibrium, in an open system where heat and particles are continually exchanged with reservoirs. These phenomena have been extensively analyzed in terms of kinetic equations. Based on the collection of knowledge about polariton kinetics provided by these simulations and by experimental works, we constructed a few-level model that captures the main processes involved in the buildup of a ground-state population of polaritons. This allows condensation to be understood as the output of a heat engine and exposes the thermodynamic constraints on its occurrence. The model consists of a three-level system interacting with a field and connected to a hot and a cold thermal reservoir that represent a non-resonant pump and the lattice phonons. This subsystem can drive a condensate, through polariton-polariton scattering, which produces work in the form of coherent light emission from the microcavity. We obtain a phase diagram as a function of the temperatures of the two baths and investigate the possible types of phase transition that lead to the condensate phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06861v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luisa Toledo Tude, Paul R. Eastham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable multi-qubit intrinsic gates in quantum dot arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06894v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the multi-qubit quantum gates intrinsic to a general array of semiconductor quantum dots and investigate how they can be implemented in a scalable way. The intrinsic quantum gates refer to the class of natural-forming transformations in the qubit rotating-frame under direct exchange coupling, and can be recognized as the instruction set of a spin-qubit chip. Adopting an perturbative treatment, we can model intrinsic gates by first-order dynamics in the coupling strength. A general formalism is developed for identifying the multi-qubit intrinsic gates under arbitrary array connectivity. Factors influencing the fidelities of the multi-qubit intrinsic gates are discussed. The advantageous applications of intrinsic gates in quantum computing and quantum error correction are explored. We also propose a theoretical scheme to overcome the problem of inhomogeneous coupling using dynamical calibration of the connecting bonds. This scheme can be further combined with periodic dynamical decoupling for robust implementations of multi-qubit gates in large-scale quantum computers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06894v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaan Qi, Zhi-Hai Liu, Hongqi Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sj$\ddot{\text{o}}$qvist quantum geometric tensor of finite-temperature mixed states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.06944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.06944v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The quantum geometric tensor (QGT) reveals local geometric properties and associated topological information of quantum states. Here a generalization of the QGT to mixed quantum states at finite temperatures based on the Sj$\ddot{\text{o}}$qvist distance is developed. The resulting Sj$\ddot{\text{o}}$qvist QGT is invariant under gauge transformations of individual spectrum levels. A Pythagorean-like relation connects the distances and gauge transformations, which clarifies the role of the parallel-transport condition. The real part of the QGT naturally decomposes into a sum of the Fisher-Rao metric and Fubini-Study metrics, allowing a distinction between different contributions to the quantum distance. The imaginary part of the QGT is proportional to the weighted summation of the Berry curvatures, which leads to a geometric phase for mixed states under certain conditions. We present three examples of different dimensions to illustrate the temperature dependence of the QGT and a discussion on possible implications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.06944v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng Zhou, Xu-Yang Hou, Xin Wang, Jia-Chen Tang, Hao Guo, Chih-Chun Chien</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InAs-Al Hybrid Devices Passing the Topological Gap Protocol</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.02472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.02472v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present measurements and simulations of semiconductor-superconductor heterostructure devices that are consistent with the observation of topological superconductivity and Majorana zero modes. The devices are fabricated from high-mobility two-dimensional electron gases in which quasi-one-dimensional wires are defined by electrostatic gates. These devices enable measurements of local and non-local transport properties and have been optimized via extensive simulations to ensure robustness against non-uniformity and disorder. Our main result is that several devices, fabricated according to the design's engineering specifications, have passed the topological gap protocol defined in Pikulin et al. [arXiv:2103.12217]. This protocol is a stringent test composed of a sequence of three-terminal local and non-local transport measurements performed while varying the magnetic field, semiconductor electron density, and junction transparencies. Passing the protocol indicates a high probability of detection of a topological phase hosting Majorana zero modes as determined by large-scale disorder simulations. Our experimental results are consistent with a quantum phase transition into a topological superconducting phase that extends over several hundred millitesla in magnetic field and several millivolts in gate voltage, corresponding to approximately one hundred micro-electron-volts in Zeeman energy and chemical potential in the semiconducting wire. These regions feature a closing and re-opening of the bulk gap, with simultaneous zero-bias conductance peaks at both ends of the devices that withstand changes in the junction transparencies. The extracted maximum topological gaps in our devices are 20-60 $\mu$eV. This demonstration is a prerequisite for experiments involving fusion and braiding of Majorana zero modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.02472v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.107.245423</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Morteza Aghaee, Arun Akkala, Zulfi Alam, Rizwan Ali, Alejandro Alcaraz Ramirez, Mariusz Andrzejczuk, Andrey E Antipov, Pavel Aseev, Mikhail Astafev, Bela Bauer, Jonathan Becker, Srini Boddapati, Frenk Boekhout, Jouri Bommer, Esben Bork Hansen, Tom Bosma, Leo Bourdet, Samuel Boutin, Philippe Caroff, Lucas Casparis, Maja Cassidy, Anna Wulf Christensen, Noah Clay, William S Cole, Fabiano Corsetti, Ajuan Cui, Paschalis Dalampiras, Anand Dokania, Gijs de Lange, Michiel de Moor, Juan Carlos Estrada Salda\~na, Saeed Fallahi, Zahra Heidarnia Fathabad, John Gamble, Geoff Gardner, Deshan Govender, Flavio Griggio, Ruben Grigoryan, Sergei Gronin, Jan Gukelberger, Sebastian Heedt, Jes\'us Herranz Zamorano, Samantha Ho, Ulrik Laurens Holgaard, William Hvidtfelt Padk{\ae}r Nielsen, Henrik Ingerslev, Peter Jeppesen Krogstrup, Linda Johansson, Jeffrey Jones, Ray Kallaher, Farhad Karimi, Torsten Karzig, Evelyn King, Maren Elisabeth Kloster, Christina Knapp, Dariusz Kocon, Jonne Koski, Pasi Kostamo, Mahesh Kumar, Tom Laeven, Thorvald Larsen, Kongyi Li, Tyler Lindemann, Julie Love, Roman Lutchyn, Michael Manfra, Elvedin Memisevic, Chetan Nayak, Bas Nijholt, Morten Hannibal Madsen, Signe Markussen, Esteban Martinez, Robert McNeil, Andrew Mullally, Jens Nielsen, Anne Nurmohamed, Eoin O'Farrell, Keita Otani, Sebastian Pauka, Karl Petersson, Luca Petit, Dima Pikulin, Frank Preiss, Marina Quintero Perez, Katrine Rasmussen, Mohana Rajpalke, Davydas Razmadze, Outi Reentila, David Reilly, Richard Rouse, Ivan Sadovskyy, Lauri Sainiemi, Sydney Schreppler, Vadim Sidorkin, Amrita Singh, Shilpi Singh, Sarat Sinha, Patrick Sohr, Toma\v{s} Stankevi\v{c}, Lieuwe Stek, Henri Suominen, Judith Suter, Vicky Svidenko, Sam Teicher, Mine Temuerhan, Nivetha Thiyagarajah, Raj Tholapi, Mason Thomas, Emily Toomey, Shivendra Upadhyay, Ivan Urban, Saulius Vaitiek\.enas, Kevin Van Hoogdalem, Dmitrii V. Viazmitinov, Steven Waddy, David Van Woerkom, Dominik Vogel, John Watson, Joseph Weston, Georg W. Winkler, Chung Kai Yang, Sean Yau, Daniel Yi, Emrah Yucelen, Alex Webster, Roland Zeisel, Ruichen Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Mechanical Comparison between Lithiated and Sodiated Silicon Nanowires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.07462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.07462v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This computational research study will compare the specific charge capacity (SCC) between lithium ions inserted into crystallize silicon (c-Si) nanowires versus sodium ions inserted into amorphous silicon (a-Si) nanowires. It will be demonstrated that the potential energy V(r) within the lithium-silicon nanowire supports a coherent energy state model with discrete electron particles while the sodium-silicon nanowire potential energy will be discovered to be essentially zero and thus the electron current that travels through the sodiated silicon nanowire will be modeled as free electron with wave-like characteristics. This is due to the vast differences in the electric fields of the lithiated and sodiated silicon nanowires where the electric fields are of the order of 10^(+10)V/m and 10^(-15) V/m respectively. The main reason for the great disparity in electric fields are due to the present of optical amplification within lithium ions and the absence of this process within sodium ions. It will be shown that optical amplification develops coherent optical interactions which is the primary reason for the surge of specific charge capacity in the lithiated silicon nanowire. Conversely, the lack of optical amplification is the reason for the incoherent optical interactions within sodium ions which is the reason for the low presence of SCC in sodiated silicon nanowires.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.07462v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donald C. Boone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital Origin of Intrinsic Planar Hall Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.05978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.05978v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent experiments reported an antisymmetric planar Hall effect, where the Hall current is odd in the in-plane magnetic field and scales linearly with both electric and magnetic fields applied. Existing theories rely exclusively on a spin origin, which requires spin-orbit coupling to take effect. Here, we develop a general theory for the intrinsic planar Hall effect (IPHE), highlighting a previously unknown orbital mechanism and connecting it to a band geometric quantity -- the anomalous orbital polarizability (AOP). Importantly, the orbital mechanism does not request spin-orbit coupling, so sizable IPHE can occur and is dominated by orbital contribution in systems with weak spin-orbit coupling. Combined with first-principles calculations, we demonstrate our theory with quantitative evaluation for bulk materials $\mathrm{TaSb_{2}}$, $\mathrm{NbAs_{2}}$, and $\mathrm{SrAs_{3}}$. We further show that AOP and its associated orbital IPHE can be greatly enhanced at topological band crossings, offering a new way to probe topological materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.05978v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.132.056301</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 132, 056301 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hui Wang, Yue-Xin Huang, Huiying Liu, Xiaolong Feng, Jiaojiao Zhu, Weikang Wu, Cong Xiao, Shengyuan A. Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of giant nonreciprocal charge transport from quantum Hall states in topological insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.08917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.08917v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Symmetry breaking in quantum materials is of great importance and leads to novel nonreciprocal charge transport. The topological insulator system provides a unique platform to study nonreciprocal charge transport due to the exotic surface states, especially the quantum Hall states under external magnetic field. Here, we report the observation of novel nonreciprocal charge transport mediated by the quantum Hall state in intrinsic topological insulator Sn-Bi1.1Sb0.9Te2S devices, which is attributed to the asymmetric scattering between the edge state and the Landau orbits. A giant nonreciprocal coefficient of up to 2.26*10^5 A^-1 is also found. Our work not only reveals the properties of nonreciprocal charge transport of quantum Hall states in topological insulators, but also paves the way for future electronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.08917v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chunfeng Li, Rui Wang, Shuai Zhang, Yuyuan Qin, Zhe Ying, Boyuan Wei, Zheng Dai, Fengyi Guo, Wei Chen, Rong Zhang, Baigeng Wang, Xuefeng Wang, Fengqi Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Activating the fluorescence of a Ni(II) complex by energy transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.09984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.09984v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Luminescence of open-shell 3d metal complexes is often quenched due to ultrafast intersystem crossing (ISC) and cooling into a dark metal-centered excited state. We demonstrate successful activation of fluorescence from individual nickel phthalocyanine (NiPc) molecules in the junction of a scanning tunneling microscope (STM) by resonant energy transfer from other metal phthalocyanines at low temperature. By combining STM, scanning tunneling spectroscopy, STM- induced luminescence, and photoluminescence experiments as well as time-dependent density functional theory, we provide evidence that there is an activation barrier for the ISC, which in most experimental conditions is overcome. We show that this is also the case in an electroluminescent tunnel junction where individual NiPc molecules adsorbed on an ultrathin NaCl decoupling film on a Ag(111) substrate are probed. However, when placing an MPc (M = Zn, Pd, Pt) molecule close to NiPc by means of STM atomic manipulation, resonant energy transfer can excite NiPc without overcoming the ISC activation barrier, leading to Q-band fluorescence. This work demonstrates that the thermally activated population of dark metal-centered states can be avoided by a designed local environment at low temperatures paired with a directed molecular excitation into vibrationally cold electronic states. Thus, we can envisage the use of luminophores based on more abundant transition metal complexes that do not rely on Pt or Ir.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.09984v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/jacs.3c07716</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Tzu-Chao Hung, Yokari Godinez-Loyola, Manuel Steinbrecher, Brian Kiraly, Alexander A. Khajetoorians, Nikos L. Doltsinis, Cristian A. Strassert, Daniel Wegner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kubo formula for dc conductivity: generalization to systems with spin-orbit coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.06416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.06416v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revise the Kubo formula for the electric dc conductivity in the presence of spin-orbit coupling (SOC). We discover that each velocity operator that enters this formula differs from $\partial H/\partial \boldsymbol p$, where $H$ is the Hamiltonian and $\boldsymbol p$ is the canonical momentum. Moreover, we find an additional contribution to the Hall dc conductivity from noncommuting coordinates that is missing in the conventional Kubo-Streda formula. This contribution originates from the "electron-positron" matrix elements of the velocity and position operators. We argue that the widely used Rashba model does in fact provide a finite anomalous Hall dc conductivity in the metallic regime (in the noncrossing approximation) if SOC-corrections to the velocity and position operators are properly taken into account. While we focus on the response of the charge current to the electric field, linear response theories of other SOC-related effects should be modified similarly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.06416v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.L012057</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 6, L012057 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>I. A. Ado, M. Titov, Rembert A. Duine, Arne Brataas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incorporation of random alloy GaBi$_{x}$As$_{1-x}$ barriers in InAs quantum dot molecules: alloy strain and orbital effects towards enhanced tunneling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.10115v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Self-assembled InAs quantum dots (QDs), which have long hole-spin coherence times and are amenable to optical control schemes, have long been explored as building blocks for qubit architectures. One such design consists of vertically stacking two QDs to create a quantum dot molecule (QDM). The two dots can be resonantly tuned to form "molecule-like" coupled hole states from the hybridization of hole states otherwise localized in each respective dot. Furthermore, spin-mixing of the hybridized states in dots offset along their stacking direction enables qubit rotation to be driven optically, allowing for an all-optical qubit control scheme. Increasing the magnitude of this spin mixing is important for optical quantum control protocols. To enhance the tunnel coupling and spin-mixing across the dots, we introduce Bi in the GaAs inter-dot barrier. Previously, we showed how to model InAs/GaBiAs in an atomistic tight-binding formalism, and how the dot energy levels are affected by the alloy. In this paper, we discuss the lowering of the tunnel barrier, which results in a three fold increase of hole tunnel coupling strength in the presence of a 7% alloy. Additionally, we show how an asymmetric strain between the two dots caused by the alloy shifts the resonance. Finally, we discuss device geometries for which the introduction of Bi is most advantageous.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.10115v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arthur Lin, Matthew F. Doty, Garnett W. Bryant</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital Pumping by Magnetization Dynamics in Ferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.14817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.14817v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show that dynamics of the magnetization in ferromagnets can pump the orbital angular momentum, which we denote by orbital pumping. This is the reciprocal phenomenon to the orbital torque that induces magnetization dynamics by the orbital angular momentum in non-equilibrium. The orbital pumping is analogous to the spin pumping established in spintronics but requires the spin-orbit coupling for the orbital angular momentum to interact with the magnetization. We develop a formalism that describes the generation of the orbital angular momentum by magnetization dynamics within the adiabatic perturbation theory. Based on this, we perform first-principles calculation of the orbital pumping in prototypical $3d$ ferromagnets, Fe, Co, and Ni. The results show that the ratio between the orbital pumping and the spin pumping ranges from 5 to 15 percents, being smallest in Fe and largest in Ni. This implies that ferromagnetic Ni is a good candidate for measuring the orbital pumping. Implications of our results on experiments are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.14817v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dongwook Go, Kazuya Ando, Armando Pezo, Stefan Bl\"ugel, Aur\'elien Manchon, Yuriy Mokrousov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineering Majorana bound states in coupled quantum dots in a two-dimensional electron gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03208v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Artificial Kitaev chains can be used to engineer Majorana bound states (MBSs) in superconductor-semiconductor hybrids. In this work, we realize a two-site Kitaev chain in a two-dimensional electrongas by coupling two quantum dots through a region proximitized by a superconductor. We demonstrate systematic control over inter-dot couplings through in-plane rotations of the magnetic field and via electrostatic gating of the proximitized region. This allows us to tune the system to sweet spots in parameter space, where robust correlated zero bias conductance peaks are observed in tunnelling spectroscopy. To study the extent of hybridization between localized MBSs, we probe the evolution of the energy spectrum with magnetic field and estimate the Majorana polarization, an important metric for Majorana-based qubits. The implementation of a Kitaev chain on a scalable and flexible 2D platform provides a realistic path towards more advanced experiments that require manipulation and readout of multiple MBSs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03208v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastiaan L. D. ten Haaf, Qingzhen Wang, A. Mert Bozkurt, Chun-Xiao Liu, Ivan Kulesh, Philip Kim, Di Xiao, Candice Thomas, Michael J. Manfra, Tom Dvir, Michael Wimmer, Srijit Goswami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inelastic scattering of transversely structured free electrons from nanophotonic targets: Theory and computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.08513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.08513v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent advancements in abilities to create and manipulate the electron's transverse wave function within the transmission electron microscope (TEM) and scanning TEM (STEM) have enabled vectorially-resolved electron energy loss (EEL) and gain (EEG) measurements of nanoscale and quantum material responses using pre- and post-selected free electron states. This newfound capability is prompting renewed theoretical interest in quantum mechanical treatments of inelastic electron scattering observables and the information they contain. Here, we present a quantum mechanical treatment of the inelastic scattering of free electrons between pre- and post-selected transverse states with fully-retarded electron-sample interactions for both spontaneous EEL and continuous-wave laser-stimulated EEG measurements. General expressions for the state-resolved energy loss and gain rates are recast in forms amenable to numerical calculation using the method of coupled dipoles. We numerically implement our theory within the $e$-DDA code, and use it to investigate specific examples that highlight its versatility regarding the number, size, geometry, and material composition of the target specimen, as well as its ability to describe matter-wave diffraction from finite nanoscopic targets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.08513v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Austin G. Nixon, Matthieu Chalifour, Marc R. Bourgeois, Michael Sanchez, David J. Masiello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interferometric Single-Shot Parity Measurement in an InAs-Al Hybrid Device</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09549v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The fusion of non-Abelian anyons or topological defects is a fundamental operation in measurement-only topological quantum computation. In topological superconductors, this operation amounts to a determination of the shared fermion parity of Majorana zero modes. As a step towards this, we implement a single-shot interferometric measurement of fermion parity in indium arsenide-aluminum heterostructures with a gate-defined nanowire. The interferometer is formed by tunnel-coupling the proximitized nanowire to quantum dots. The nanowire causes a state-dependent shift of these quantum dots' quantum capacitance of up to 1 fF. Our quantum capacitance measurements show flux h/2e-periodic bimodality with a signal-to-noise ratio of 1 in 3.7 $\mu$s at optimal flux values. From the time traces of the quantum capacitance measurements, we extract a dwell time in the two associated states that is longer than 1 ms at in-plane magnetic fields of approximately 2 T. These results are consistent with a measurement of the fermion parity encoded in a pair of Majorana zero modes that are separated by approximately 3 $\mu$m and subjected to a low rate of poisoning by non-equilibrium quasiparticles. The large capacitance shift and long poisoning time enable a parity measurement error probability of 1%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09549v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Morteza Aghaee, Alejandro Alcaraz Ramirez, Zulfi Alam, Rizwan Ali, Mariusz Andrzejczuk, Andrey Antipov, Mikhail Astafev, Amin Barzegar, Bela Bauer, Jonathan Becker, Umesh Kumar Bhaskar, Alex Bocharov, Srini Boddapati, David Bohn, Jouri Bommer, Leo Bourdet, Arnaud Bousquet, Samuel Boutin, Lucas Casparis, Benjamin James Chapman, Sohail Chatoor, Anna Wulff Christensen, Cassandra Chua, Patrick Codd, William Cole, Paul Cooper, Fabiano Corsetti, Ajuan Cui, Paolo Dalpasso, Juan Pablo Dehollain, Gijs de Lange, Michiel de Moor, Andreas Ekefj\"ard, Tareq El Dandachi, Juan Carlos Estrada Salda\~na, Saeed Fallahi, Luca Galletti, Geoff Gardner, Deshan Govender, Flavio Griggio, Ruben Grigoryan, Sebastian Grijalva, Sergei Gronin, Jan Gukelberger, Marzie Hamdast, Firas Hamze, Esben Bork Hansen, Sebastian Heedt, Zahra Heidarnia, Jes\'us Herranz Zamorano, Samantha Ho, Laurens Holgaard, John Hornibrook, Jinnapat Indrapiromkul, Henrik Ingerslev, Lovro Ivancevic, Thomas Jensen, Jaspreet Jhoja, Jeffrey Jones, Konstantin V. Kalashnikov, Ray Kallaher, Rachpon Kalra, Farhad Karimi, Torsten Karzig, Cameron King, Maren Elisabeth Kloster, Christina Knapp, Dariusz Kocon, Jonne Koski, Pasi Kostamo, Mahesh Kumar, Tom Laeven, Thorvald Larsen, Jason Lee, Kyunghoon Lee, Grant Leum, Kongyi Li, Tyler Lindemann, Matthew Looij, Julie Love, Marijn Lucas, Roman Lutchyn, Morten Hannibal Madsen, Nash Madulid, Albert Malmros, Michael Manfra, Devashish Mantri, Signe Brynold Markussen, Esteban Martinez, Marco Mattila, Robert McNeil, Antonio B. Mei, Ryan V. Mishmash, Gopakumar Mohandas, Christian Mollgaard, Trevor Morgan, George Moussa, Chetan Nayak, Jens Hedegaard Nielsen, Jens Munk Nielsen, William Hvidtfelt Padk{\ae}r Nielsen, Bas Nijholt, Mike Nystrom, Eoin O'Farrell, Thomas Ohki, Keita Otani, Brian Paquelet W\"utz, Sebastian Pauka, Karl Petersson, Luca Petit, Dima Pikulin, Guen Prawiroatmodjo, Frank Preiss, Eduardo Puchol Morejon, Mohana Rajpalke, Craig Ranta, Katrine Rasmussen, David Razmadze, Outi Reentila, David J. Reilly, Yuan Ren, Ken Reneris, Richard Rouse, Ivan Sadovskyy, Lauri Sainiemi, Irene Sanlorenzo, Emma Schmidgall, Cristina Sfiligoj, Mustafeez Bashir Shah, Kevin Simoes, Shilpi Singh, Sarat Sinha, Thomas Soerensen, Patrick Sohr, Tomas Stankevic, Lieuwe Stek, Eric Stuppard, Henri Suominen, Judith Suter, Sam Teicher, Nivetha Thiyagarajah, Raj Tholapi, Mason Thomas, Emily Toomey, Josh Tracy, Michelle Turley, Shivendra Upadhyay, Ivan Urban, Kevin Van Hoogdalem, David J. Van Woerkom, Dmitrii V. Viazmitinov, Dominik Vogel, John Watson, Alex Webster, Joseph Weston, Georg W. Winkler, Di Xu, Chung Kai Yang, Emrah Yucelen, Roland Zeisel, Guoji Zheng, Justin Zilke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Terahertz plasmonic resonances in coplanar graphene nanoribbon structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.03912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.03912v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We analyze plasmonic oscillations in the coplanar graphene nanoribbon (GNR) structures induced by the applied terahertz (THz) signals and calculate the GNR impedance. The plasmonic oscillations in the CNR structures are associated with the electron and hole inductances and the lateral inter-CNR capacitance. A relatively low inter-GNR capacitance enables the resonant excitation of the THz plasmonic oscillations in the CNR structures with long GNRs. The GNR structures under consideration can be used in different THz devices as the resonant structures incorporated in THz detectors, THz sources using resonant-tunneling diodes, photomixers, and surface acoustic wave sensors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.03912v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Ryzhii, C. Tang, T. Otsuji, M. Ryzhii, M. S. Shur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of Interface on Density and Elastic Moduli of $\textbf{Al/C}_{60}$ Nanocomposites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.08326v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The paper analyzes theoretically the influence of fullerenes on the characteristics of $\mathrm{Al/C}_{60}$ composites. The molecular dynamics method is used to study the dependences of density and stiffness constants on the concentration of inclusions, and to calculate the values of the bulk and shear moduli for isotropic polycrystalline nanocomposites. The analysis shows that interfacial interaction significantly affects the properties of nanocomposites. This effect can be taken into account within the framework of the theory of heterogeneous media using the interphase layer model. The properties of the interphase layer are determined by interfacial interaction and can be calculated by approximating the results of molecular dynamics calculations. Using assumptions about the simplified form of the two-particle distribution function allows the interfacial interaction energy to be calculated and the interphase layer properties to be assessed analytically. The paper compares numerical results and analytical estimates, and discusses the validity of the approximations used. The analysis performed on the example of an $\mathrm{Al/C}_{60}$ composite material demonstrates the feasibility of using the analytical model of the interphase layer to estimate the effective density and elastic moduli of heterogeneous media with nano-inhomogeneities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.08326v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. V. Reshetniak, A. V Aborkin, A. V. Filippov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral spin liquid phase in an optical lattice at mean-field level</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.16466v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study an optical Raman square lattice with $\mathrm{U}(1)$ synthetic gauge flux to show chiral spin liquid (CSL) phase for cold atoms based on slave-rotor theory and spinon mean-field theory, respectively. An effective U($1$) gauge flux generated by Raman potentials plays a major role in realizing the CSL phase. By using slave-rotor techniques we find CSL phase at intermediate on-site Fermi Hubbard interacting regime. For the strong interacting regime we derive an effective spin model including up to the four spin interactions. By spinon mean-field analysis it is shown that CSL phase is stabilized in the case of strong magnetic frustration. The two mean-field approximation methods give consistent phase diagrams and provide qualitative numerical evidence of the CSL phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.16466v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Yang, Xiong-Jun Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning the Intrinsic Spin Hall Effect by Charge Density Wave Order in Topological Kagome Metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.06230</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.06230v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Kagome metals are topological materials with a rich phase diagram featuring various charge density wave orders and even unconventional superconductivity. However, little is still known about possible spin-polarized responses in these non-magnetic compounds. Here, we perform ab-initio calculations of the intrinsic spin Hall effect (SHE) in the kagome metals AV$_3$Sb$_5$ (A=Cs, Rb, K), CsTi$_3$Bi$_5$ and ScV$_6$Sn$_6$. We report large spin Hall conductivities, comparable with the Weyl semimetal TaAs. Additionally, in CsV$_3$Sb$_5$ the SHE is strongly renormalized by the CDW order. We can understand these results based on the topological properties of band structures, demonstrating that the SHE is dominated by the position and shape of the Dirac nodal lines in the kagome sublattice. Our results suggest kagome materials as a promising, tunable platform for future spintronics applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.06230v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.108.205203</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Diana Golovanova, Hengxin Tan, Tobias Holder, Binghai Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductor-altermagnet memory functionality without stray fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.10939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.10939v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A novel class of antiferromagnets, dubbed altermagnets, exhibit a non-relativistically spin-split band structure reminiscent of $d$-wave superconductors, despite the absence of net magnetization. This unique characteristic enables utilization in cryogenic stray-field-free memory devices, offering the possibility of achieving high storage densities. In this Letter, we determine how a proximate altermagnet influences the critical temperature $T_c$ of a conventional $s$-wave singlet superconductor. Considering both a bilayer and trilayer, we show that such hybrid structures may serve as stray-field free memory devices where the critical temperature is controlled by rotating the N\'eel vector of one altermagnet, providing infinite magnetoresistance. Furthermore, our study reveals that altermagnetism can coexist with superconductivity up to a critical strength of the altermagnetic order as well as robustness of the altermagnetic influence on the conduction electrons against non-magnetic impurities, ensuring the persistence of the proximity effect under realistic experimental conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.10939v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hans Gl{\o}ckner Giil, Jacob Linder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proximity-induced gapless superconductivity in two-dimensional Rashba semiconductor in magnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.09347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.09347v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Two-dimensional semiconductor-superconductor heterostructures form the foundation of numerous nanoscale physical systems. However, measuring the properties of such heterostructures, and characterizing the semiconductor in-situ is challenging. A recent experimental study [arXiv:2107.03695] was able to probe the semiconductor within the heterostructure using microwave measurements of the superfluid density. This work revealed a rapid depletion of superfluid density in semiconductor, caused by the in-plane magnetic field which in presence of spin-orbit coupling creates so-called Bogoliubov Fermi surfaces. The experimental work used a simplified theoretical model that neglected the presence of non-magnetic disorder in the semiconductor, hence describing the data only qualitatively. Motivated by experiments, we introduce a theoretical model describing a disordered semiconductor with strong spin-orbit coupling that is proximitized by a superconductor. Our model provides specific predictions for the density of states and superfluid density. Presence of disorder leads to the emergence of a gapless superconducting phase, that may be viewed as a manifestation of Bogoliubov Fermi surface. When applied to real experimental data, our model showcases excellent quantitative agreement, enabling the extraction of material parameters such as mean free path and mobility, and estimating $g$-tensor after taking into account the orbital contribution of magnetic field. Our model can be used to probe in-situ parameters of other superconductor-semiconductor heterostructures and can be further extended to give access to transport properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.09347v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Serafim S. Babkin, Andrew P. Higginbotham, Maksym Serbyn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In situ coherent X-ray scattering reveals polycrystalline structure and discrete annealing events in strongly-coupled nanocrystal superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.06103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.06103v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Solution-phase bottom up self-assembly of nanocrystals into superstructures such as ordered superlattices is an attractive strategy to generate functional materials of increasing complexity, including very recent advances that incorporate strong interparticle electronic coupling. While the self-assembly kinetics in these systems have been elucidated and related to the product characteristics, the weak interparticle bonding interactions suggest the superstructures formed could continue to order within the solution long after the primary nucleation and growth have occurred, even though the mechanism of annealing remains to be elucidated. Here, we use a combination of Bragg coherent diffractive imaging and X-ray photon correlation spectroscopy to create real-space maps of supercrystalline order along with a real-time view of the strain fluctuations in aging strongly coupled nanocrystal superlattices while they remain suspended and immobilized in solution. By combining the results, we deduce that the self-assembled superstructures are polycrystalline, initially comprising multiple nucleation sites, and that shear avalanches at grain boundaries continue to increase crystallinity long after growth has substantially slowed. This multimodal approach should be generalizable to characterize a breadth of materials in situ in their native chemical environments, thus extending the reach of high-resolution coherent X-ray characterization to the benefit of a much wider range of physical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.06103v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew J. Hurley, Christian P. N. Tanner, Joshua Portner, James K. Utterback, Igor Coropceanu, Garth J. Williams, Avishek Das, Andrei Fluerasu, Yanwen Sun, Sanghoon Song, Leo M. Hamerlynck, Alexander H. Miller, Priyadarshini Bhattacharyya, Dmitri V. Talapin, Naomi S. Ginsberg, Samuel W. Teitelbaum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermi Surface Geometry and Optical Conductivity of a 2D Electron Gas near an Ising-Nematic Quantum Critical Point</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.17392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.17392v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyze optical conductivity of a clean two-dimensional electron system in a Fermi liquid regime near a $T=0$ Ising-nematic quantum critical point (QCP), and extrapolate the results to a QCP. We employ direct perturbation theory up to the two-loop order to elucidate how the Fermi surface's geometry (convex vs. concave) and fermionic dispersion (parabolic vs. non-parabolic) affect the scaling of the optical conductivity, $\sigma(\omega)$, with frequency $\omega$ and correlation length $\xi$. We find that for a convex Fermi surface the leading terms in the optical conductivity cancel out, leaving a sub-leading contribution $\sigma (\omega) \propto \omega^2 \xi^4 \mathcal{L}$, where $\mathcal{L} = \mathrm{const}$ for a parabolic dispersion and $\mathcal{L} \propto \log{\omega \xi^3}$ in a generic case. For a concave Fermi surface, the leading terms do not cancel, and $\sigma (\omega) \propto \xi^2$. We extrapolate these results to a QCP and obtain $\sigma (\omega) \propto \omega^{2/3}$ for a convex Fermi surface and $\sigma (\omega) \propto 1/\omega^{2/3}$ for a concave Fermi surface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.17392v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yasha Gindikin, Andrey V. Chubukov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Agnostic Phase Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00054v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The goal of quantum metrology is to improve measurements' sensitivities by harnessing quantum resources. Metrologists often aim to maximize the quantum Fisher information, which bounds the measurement setup's sensitivity. In studies of fundamental limits on metrology, a paradigmatic setup features a qubit (spin-half system) subject to an unknown rotation. One obtains the maximal quantum Fisher information about the rotation if the spin begins in a state that maximizes the variance of the rotation-inducing operator. If the rotation axis is unknown, however, no optimal single-qubit sensor can be prepared. Inspired by simulations of closed timelike curves, we circumvent this limitation. We obtain the maximum quantum Fisher information about a rotation angle, regardless of the unknown rotation axis. To achieve this result, we initially entangle the probe qubit with an ancilla qubit. Then, we measure the pair in an entangled basis, obtaining more information about the rotation angle than any single-qubit sensor can achieve. We demonstrate this metrological advantage using a two-qubit superconducting quantum processor. Our measurement approach achieves a quantum advantage, outperforming every entanglement-free strategy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00054v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingrui Song, Flavio Salvati, Chandrashekhar Gaikwad, Nicole Yunger Halpern, David R. M. Arvidsson-Shukur, Kater Murch</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
