<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 01:58:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>RKKY interaction in helical higher-order topological insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the RKKY interaction in helical higher-order topological insulators (HOTIs), revealing distinct behaviors mediated by hinge and Dirac-type bulk carriers. Our findings show that hinge-mediated interactions consist of Heisenberg, Ising, and Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya (DM) terms, exhibiting a decay with impurity spacing z and oscillations with Fermi energy {\epsilon}F . These interactions demonstrate ferromagnetic behaviors for the Heisenberg and Ising terms and alternating behavior for the DM term. In contrast, bulk-mediated interactions include Heisenberg, twisted Ising, and DM terms, with a conventional cubic oscillating decay. This study highlights the nuanced interplay between hinge and bulk RKKY interactions in HOTIs, offering insights into the design of next-generation quantum devices based on the HOTIs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10243v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sha Jin, Jian Li, Qing-Xu Li, Jia-Ji Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical sensing of charge and spin current fluctuations in centrosymmetric semiconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10397v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a time-resolved optical measurement scheme for sampling transient charge and spin currents in a bulk centrosymmetric semiconductor. The technique relies on emission of second harmonic light triggered by a pulsed below-gap optical excitation and a spontaneous intraband polarization arising from spin or charge motion, mediated by a $\chi^(3)$-based nonlinear optical process. Our proposal uses homodyne amplification to boost the weak second harmonic signal, making it detectable with conventional electronics, calculated for charge current in a room temperature GaAs semiconductor. This all-optical technique requires neither electrical contact nor bias fields and the signal is estimated at a few percent relative to the shot noise of the probe. This proposal motivates a novel method for exploring thermal and quantum fluctuations in the solid state in a non-invasive manner.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10397v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amin Lakhal, St\'ephane Virally, Jacob B. Khurgin, Denis V. Seletskiy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning photoacoustics with nanotransducers via Thermal Boundary Resistance and Laser Pulse Duration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10480v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The photoacoustic effect in liquids, generated by metal nanoparticles excited with short laser pulses, offers high contrast imaging and promising medical treatment techniques. Understanding the role of the thermal boundary resistance (TBR) and the laser pulse duration in the generation mechanism of acoustic waves is essential to implement efficient photoacoustic nanotransducers. This work theoretically investigates, for the paradigmatic case of water-immersed gold nanocylinders, the role of the TBR and of laser pulse duration in the competition between the launching mechanisms: the thermophone and the mechanophone. In the thermophone, the nanoparticle acts as a nanoheater and the wave is launched by water thermal expansion. In the mechanophone, the nanoparticle directly acts as a nanopiston. Specifically, for a gold-water interface, the thermophone prevails under ns light pulse irradiation, while the mechanophone dominates shortening the pulse to the 10 ps regime. For a graphene-functionalized gold-water interface, instead, the mechanophone dominates over the entire range of explored laser pulse durations. Results point to high-TBR, liquid-immersed nanoparticles as potentially efficient photoacoustic nanogenerators, with the advantage of keeping the liquid environment temperature unaltered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10480v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0135147</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Appl. Phys. Lett. 121, 252201 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michele Diego, Marco Gandolfi, Stefano Giordano, Fabien Vialla, Aur\'elien Crut, Fabrice Vall\'ee, Paolo Maioli, Natalia Del Fatti, Francesco Banfi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feedback-voltage driven chaos in three-terminal spin-torque oscillator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10493v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent observations of chaos in nanomagnet suggest a possibility of new spintronics applications such as random-number generator and neuromorphic computing. However, large amount of electric current and/or magnetic field are necessary for the excitation of chaos, which are unsuitable for energy-saving applications. Here, we propose an excitation of chaos in three-terminal spin-torque oscillator (STO). The driving force of the chaos is voltage-controlled magnetic anisotropy (VCMA) effect, which enables us to manipulate magnetization dynamics without spending electric current or magnetic field, and thus, energy efficient. In particular, we focus on the VCMA effect generated by feedback signal from the STO since feedback effect is known to be effective in exciting chaos in dynamical system. Solving the Landau-Lifshitz-Gilbert (LLG) equation numerically and applying temporal and statistical analyses to its solution, the existence of the chaotic and transient-chaotic magnetization dynamics driven by the feedback VCMA effect is identified.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10493v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomohiro Taniguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast nano generation of acoustic waves in water via a single carbon nanotube</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10509</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10509v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generation of ultra high frequency acoustic waves in water is key to nano resolution sensing, acoustic imaging and theranostics. In this context water immersed carbon nanotubes (CNTs) may act as an ideal optoacoustic source, due to their nanometric radial dimensions, peculiar thermal properties and broad band optical absorption. The generation mechanism of acoustic waves in water, upon excitation of both a single-wall (SW) and a multi-wall (MW) CNT with laser pulses of temporal width ranging from 5 ns down to ps, is theoretically investigated via a multi-scale approach. We show that, depending on the combination of CNT size and laser pulse duration, the CNT can act as a thermophone or a mechanophone. As a thermophone, the CNT acts as a nanoheater for the surrounding water, which, upon thermal expansion, launches the pressure wave. As a mechanophone, the CNT acts as a nanopiston, its thermal expansion directly triggering the pressure wave in water. Activation of the mechanophone effect is sought to trigger few nanometers wavelength sound waves in water, matching the CNT acoustic frequencies. This is at variance with respect to the commonly addressed case of water-immersed single metallic nano-objects excited with ns laser pulses, where only the thermophone effect significantly contributes. The present findings might be of impact in fields ranging from nanoscale non-destructive testing to water dynamics at the meso- to nano-scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10509v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.pacs.2022.100407</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Photoacoustics 28, 100407 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michele Diego, Marco Gandolfi, Alessandro Casto, Francesco Maria Bellussi, Fabien Vialla, Aur\'elien Crut, Stefano Roddaro, Matteo Fasano, Fabrice Vall\'ee, Natalia Del Fatti, Paolo Maioli, Francesco Banfi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synaptic-Like Plasticity in 2D Nanofluidic Memristor from Competitive Bicationic Transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10510v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Synaptic plasticity, the dynamic tuning of signal transmission strength between neurons, serves as a fundamental basis for memory and learning in biological organisms. This adaptive nature of synapses is considered one of the key features contributing to the superior energy efficiency of the brain. In this study, we utilize molecular dynamics simulations to demonstrate synaptic-like plasticity in a subnanoporous 2D membrane. We show that a train of voltage spikes dynamically modifies the membrane's ionic permeability in a process involving competitive bicationic transport. This process is shown to be repeatable after a given resting period. Due to a combination of sub-nm pore size and the atomic thinness of the membrane, this system exhibits energy dissipation of 0.1--100 aJ per voltage spike, which is several orders of magnitude lower than 0.1--10 fJ per spike in the human synapse. We reveal the underlying physical mechanisms at molecular detail and investigate the local energetics underlying this apparent synaptic-like behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10510v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yechan Noh, Alex Smolyanitsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photonic realization of chiral hinge states in a Chern-insulator stack</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10637v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Higher-order topological insulators, as a novel family of topological phases, are a hot frontier in condensed matter physics due to their adherence to unconventional bulk-boundary correspondence. A three-dimensional second-order topological insulator can support one-dimensional modes along its hinges (dubbed as hinge states). Here, we present a simple and direct method to construct chiral hinge modes based on a Chern-insulator stack. We analyze the existence of the hinge modes through the nontrivial quadrupole indices, and then design a photonic crystal to realize the specific flowing pattern of the hinge mode in our model. The experimental results align well with full-wave simulations, clearly demonstrating the existence of chiral hinge states. We also verify the robustness of these hinge states against defects in our photonic system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10637v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han-Rong Xia, Jia-Zheng Li, Si-Yu Yuan, Meng Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interlayer Fermi polarons of excited exciton states in quantizing magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10642v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The study of exciton-polarons has offered profound insights into the many-body interactions between bosonic excitations and their immersed Fermi sea within layered heterostructures. However, little is known about the properties of exciton polarons with interlayer interactions. Here through magneto-optical reflectance contrast measurements, we experimentally investigate interlayer Fermi polarons for 2s excitons in WSe$_2$/graphene heterostructures, where the excited exciton states (2s) in the WSe$_2$ layer are dressed by free charge carriers of the adjacent graphene layer in the Landau quantization regime. First, such a system enables an optical detection of integer and fractional quantum Hall states (e.g. $\nu=\pm1/3$, $\pm$2/3) of monolayer graphene. Furthermore, we observe that the 2s state evolves into two distinct branches, denoted as attractive and repulsive polarons, when graphene is doped out of the incompressible quantum Hall gaps. Our work paves the way for the understanding of the excited composite quasiparticles and Bose-Fermi mixtures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10642v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.nanolett.4c01658</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nano Letters 24, 7077-7083 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Huiying Cui, Qianying Hu, Xuan Zhao, Liguo Ma, Feng Jin, Qingming Zhang, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Jie Shan, Kin Fai Mak, Yongqing Li, Yang Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic and magnetic properties of graphene-fluorographene nanoribbons: controllable semiconductor-metal transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10754v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the electronic and magnetic properties of graphene channels ($2$-$4$ nm wide) embedded within fluorographene, focusing on two distinct interfaces: the fully-fluorinated $\alpha$ interface and the half-fluorinated $\beta$ interface. Density Functional Theory (DFT) calculations reveal that $\alpha\alpha$ systems exhibit semiconducting behavior with antiferromagnetic ordering, closely resembling pristine zigzag graphene nanoribbons. In contrast, $\alpha\beta$ systems display ferromagnetism and a width-dependent semiconductor-to-metal transition. To enable the study of larger systems, we develop and validate effective Hubbard models for both $\alpha\alpha$ and $\alpha\beta$ channels. Building upon DFT results and a Wannier function analysis, these models accurately reproduce the electronic structure and magnetic ordering observed in DFT calculations. Crucially, our $\alpha\beta$ model successfully captures the semiconductor-to-metal transition. Application of this model to larger systems reveals the persistence of a ferromagnetic state with spin polarization localized at the $\alpha$ edge. Our results demonstrate the potential of fluorination for targeted property engineering and provide a basis for exploring graphene-fluorographene systems in device applications ranging from microelectronics to spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10754v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. M. Guzm\'an-Arellano, A. D. Hern\'andez-Nieves, F. M. Peeters, Gonzalo Usaj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Majorana qubit readout by a point-contact detector under finite bias voltages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10812v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we revisit the problem of four Majorana-zero-modes (4-MZMs) qubit readout by a point-contact (PC) detector. The logic states of the 4-MZMs qubit are converted to different charge occupations of a tunnel-coupled quantum dot (QD), which is further measured by a nearby PC detector. This type of measurement in principle requires that the PC detector is to be biased at small voltages, which should be comparable to the energy scales of the QD level and its coupling to the qubit. Going beyond existing studies on this problem, we present a unified treatment for both the steady-state current and the current power spectrum, which allow us to infer the qubit state information from either the QD occupation or the characteristic peak at the oscillation frequency. Moreover, we carry out the peak-to-pedestal ratio of each single characteristic peak (associated with each logic state of the qubit) and the signal-to-noise ratio of the two peaks. From these two figures of merit, we reveal the optimal bias voltage window for the PC detector at low temperature limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10812v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huizi Xie, Sirui Yu, Hong Mao, Jinshuang Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Formulation of Atomistic Electromagnetic Models for Plasmonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10926</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10926v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Investigating nanoplasmonics using time-dependent approaches permits shedding light on the dynamic optical properties of plasmonic structures, which are intrinsically connected with their potential applications in photochemistry and photoreactivity. This work proposes a real-time extension of our recently developed fully atomistic approaches $\omega$FQ and $\omega$FQF$\mu$. These methods successfully reproduce quantum size effects in metal nanoparticles, including plasmon shifts for both simple and $d$-metals, even below the quantum size limit. Also, thanks to their atomistic nature and the phenomenological inclusion of quantum tunneling effects, they can effectively describe the optical response of subnanometer junctions. By incorporating real-time dynamics, the approach provides an efficient framework for studying the time-dependent optical behavior of metal nanostructures, including the decoherence of plasmon excitations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10926v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piero Lafiosca, Luca Nicoli, Silvio Pipolo, Stefano Corni, Tommaso Giovannini, Chiara Cappelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological phases of commensurate or incommensurate non-Hermitian Su-Schrieffer-Heeger lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate topological features of a one-dimensional Su-Schrieffer-Heeger lattice with modulating non-Hermitian on-site potentials containing four sublattices per unit cell. The lattice can be either commensurate or incommensurate. In the former case, the entire lattice can be mapped by supercells completely. While in the latter case, there are two extra lattice points, thereby making the last cell incomplete. We find that an anti-PT transition occurs at exceptional points of edge states at certain parameters, which does not coincide with the conventional topological phase transition characterized by the Berry phase, provided the imaginary on-site potential is large enough. Interestingly, when the potential exceeds a critical value, edge states appear even in the regime with a trivial Berry phase. To characterize these novel edge states we present topological invariants associated with the system's parity. Finally, we analyze the dynamics for initial states with different spatial distributions, which exhibit distinct dynamics for the commensurate and incommensurate cases, depending on the imaginary part of edge state energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11072v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.205142</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 205142 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Milad Jangjan, Linhu Li, Luis E. F. Foa Torres, Mir Vahid Hosseini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable Fano and Dicke resonant tunneling of double quantum dots sandwiched between topological insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11165v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the resonant tunneling in double quantum dots (DQD) sandwiched between surfaces of topological insulator (TI) Bi$_2$Te$_3$, which possess strong spin-orbit coupling (SOC) and $^{d}C_{3v}$ double group symmetry. Distinct from the spin-conserved case with two-dimensional electron gas (2DEG) electrodes, the conductance displays an asymmetrical double-peak Fano-type lineshape rather than Dicke-type lineshape in the zero-field cases. While a Landau-Zener-like lineshape trajectory, which is identified as a signal of competition effect, could be developed by increasing the strength of interdot hopping. Furthermore, when applying an in-plane Zeeman field, we find that the conductance lineshape crossover between Fano and Dicke type could be driven by tilting the field orientation. Moreover, the rotational symmetry of the system could also be revealed from the lineshape trajectory. Our findings will contribute to a better understanding of the resonant tunneling in the presence of electrode SOC and may be confirmed experimentally in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11165v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuan Hong, Zhen-Guo Fu, Zhou-Wei-Yu Chen, Feng Chi, Zhigang Wang, Wei Zhang, Ping Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Definition and Frequency Dependence of Intrinsic Nonlinear Current</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11180</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11180v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the three commonly employed approaches that define the same intrinsic linear anomalous Hall response actually lead to different results for intrinsic nonlinear transport. The difference arises from an intrinsic anomalous distribution. It originates from scattering, but its value is completely independent of scattering, because it represents the local equilibration of electron wave packets with field corrected energy. As a manifestation, we find that under ac driving, the intrinsic contributions in rectified component and in double-frequency component exhibit distinct frequency dependence, which can be probed in experiment. Using first-principles calculations, we estimate the signals that can be probed in antiferromagnetic CuMnAs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11180v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cong Xiao, Jin Cao, Qian Niu, Shengyuan A. Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantized Andreev conductance in semiconductor nanowires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11211v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Clean one-dimensional electron systems can exhibit quantized conductance. The plateau conductance doubles if the transport is dominated by Andreev reflection. Here, we report quantized conductance observed in both Andreev and normal-state transports in PbTe-Pb and PbTe-In hybrid nanowires. The Andreev plateau is observed at $4e^2/h$, twice of the normal plateau value of $2e^2/h$. In comparison, Andreev conductance in the best-optimized III-V nanowires is non-quantized due to mode-mixing induced dips (a disorder effect), despite the quantization of normal-state transport. The negligible mode mixing in PbTe hybrids indicates an unprecedented low-disorder transport regime for nanowire devices, beneficial for Majorana researches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11211v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yichun Gao, Wenyu Song, Yuhao Wang, Zuhan Geng, Zhan Cao, Zehao Yu, Shuai Yang, Jiaye Xu, Fangting Chen, Zonglin Li, Ruidong Li, Lining Yang, Zhaoyu Wang, Shan Zhang, Xiao Feng, Tiantian Wang, Yunyi Zang, Lin Li, Dong E. Liu, Runan Shang, Qi-Kun Xue, Ke He, Hao Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planar Hall Plateau in Magnetic Weyl Semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11273v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite the rapid progress in the study of planar Hall effect (PHE) in recent years, all the previous works only showed that the PHE is connected to local geometric quantities, such as Berry curvature. Here, for the first time, we point out that the PHE in magnetic Weyl semimetals is directly related to a global quantity, namely, the Chern number of the Weyl point. This leads to a remarkable consequence that the PHE observation predicted here is robust against many system details, including the Fermi energy. The main difference between non-magnetic and magnetic Weyl points is that the latter breaks time-reversal symmetry T, thus generally possessing an energy tilt. Via semiclassical Boltzmann theory, we investigate the PHE in generic magnetic Weyl models with energy tilt and arbitrary Chern number. We find that by aligning the magnetic and electric fields in the same direction, the trace of the PHE conductivity contributed from Berry curvature and orbital moment is proportional to the Chern number and the energy tilt of the Weyl points, resulting in previously undiscovered quantized PHE plateau by varying Fermi energy. We further confirm the existence of PHE plateaus in a more realistic lattice model without T symmetry. By proposing a new quantized physical quantity, our work not only provides a new tool for extracting the topological character of the Weyl points but also suggests that the interplay between topology and magnetism can give rise to intriguing physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11273v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Li, Chaoxi Cui, Run-Wu Zhang, Zhi-Ming Yu, Yugui Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Disentangling electric field effect on spin waves in ferromagnetic insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11352v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we extend the micromagnetic theory of magnetostatic surface waves in insulating ferromagnetic thin films to include the applied electric field effects. We start by identifying the two main effects on the dispersion relation: the first one is of relativistic nature and emerges as a consequence of the Ahronov-Casher effect, while the second one is a consequence of the electric field induced symmetry breaking operating at the level of magnetic exchange interactions. We support our theory by comparing its predictions with experimental data on ittrium iron garnet thin films taken from the literature. The main result is to evidence the limitations of using the same value of the applied electric field to address both effects and to emphasize that crystal symmetry breaking due to the applied electric field brings about the contributions of the crystal field and determines different amplitudes for the two effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11352v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physb.2023.415422</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physica B 671 (2023) 415422</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Vittorio Basso, Patrizio Ansalone, Adriano Di Pietro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coherence of an Electronic Two-Level System under Continuous Charge Sensing by a Quantum Dot Detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11383v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate experimentally the quantum coherence of an electronic two-level system in a double quantum dot under continuous charge detection. The charge-state of the two-level system is monitored by a capacitively coupled single quantum dot detector that imposes a back-action effect to the system. The measured back-action is well described by an additional decoherence rate, approximately linearly proportional to the detector electron tunneling rate. We provide a model for the decoherence rate arising due to level detuning fluctuations induced by detector charge fluctuations. The theory predicts a factor of two lower decoherence rate than observed in the experiment, suggesting the need for a more elaborate theory accounting for additional sources of decoherence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11383v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhomoy Haldar, Morten Munk, Harald Havir, Waqar Khan, Sebastian Lehmann, Claes Thelander, Kimberly A. Dick, Peter Samuelsson, Patrick P. Potts, Ville F. Maisi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Layer-dependent electromechanical response in twisted graphene moir\'e superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11442v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The coupling of mechanical deformation and electrical stimuli at the nanoscale has been a subject of intense investigation in the realm of materials science. Recently, twisted van der Waals (vdW) materials have emerged as a platform to explore exotic quantum states. These states are intimately tied to the formation of moir\'e superlattices, which can be visualized directly exploiting the electromechanical response. However, the origin of the response, even in twisted bilayer graphene (tBLG), remains unsettled. Here, employing lateral piezoresponse force microscopy (LPFM), we investigate the electromechanical responses of marginally twisted graphene moir\'e superlattices with different layer thicknesses. We observe distinct LPFM amplitudes and spatial profiles in tBLG and twisted monolayer-bilayer graphene (tMBG), exhibiting effective in-plane piezoelectric coefficients of 0.05 pm/V and 0.35 pm/V, respectively. Force tuning experiments further underscore a marked divergence in their responses. The contrasting behaviors suggest different electromechanical couplings in tBLG and tMBG. In tBLG, the response near the domain walls is attributed to the flexoelectric effect, while in tMBG, the behaviors can be comprehended within the context of piezoelectric effect. Our results not only provide insights to electromechanical and corporative effects in twisted vdW materials with different stacking symmetries, but may also show their potential for engineering them at the nanoscale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11442v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanhao Zhang, Yuanhao Wei, Yuhao Li, Shengsheng Lin, Jiarui Wang, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Jiangyu Li, Yi Shi, Xinran Wang, Yan Shi, Zaiyao Fei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bloch sphere representation for Rabi oscillation driven by Rashba field in the two-dimensional harmonic confinement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11444v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We studied the dynamical properties of Rabi oscillations driven by an alternating Rashba field applied to a two-dimensional (2D) harmonic confinement system. We solve the time-dependent (TD) Schr\"{o}dinger equation numerically and rewrite the resulting TD wavefunction onto the Bloch sphere (BS) using two BS parameters of the zenith ($\theta_B$) and azimuthal ($\phi_B$) angles, extracting the phase information $\phi_B$ as well as the mixing ratio $\theta_B$ between the two BS-pole states.
  We employed a two-state rotating wave (TSRW) approach and studied the fundamental features of $\theta_B$ and $\phi_B$ over time. The TSRW approach reveals a triangular wave formation in $\theta_B$. Moreover, at each apex of the triangular wave, the TD wavefunction passes through the BS pole, and the state is completely replaced by the opposite spin state. The TSRW approach also elucidates a linear change in $\phi_B$. The slope of $\phi_B$ vs. time is equal to the difference between the dynamical terms, leading to a confinement potential in the harmonic system. The TSRW approach further demonstrates a jump in the phase difference by $\pi$ when the wavefunction passes through the BS pole.
  The alternating Rashba field causes multiple successive Rabi transitions in the 2D harmonic system. We then introduce the effective BS (EBS) and transform these complicated transitions into an equivalent "single" Rabi one. Consequently, the EBS parameters $\theta_B^{\mathrm{eff}}$ and $\phi_B^{\mathrm{eff}}$ exhibit mixing and phase difference between two spin states $\alpha$ and $\beta$, leading to a deep understanding of the TD features of multi-Rabi oscillations. Furthermore, the combination of the BS representation with the TSRW approach successfully reveals the dynamical properties of the Rabi oscillation, even beyond the TSRW approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11444v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaichi Arai, Tatsuki Tojo, Kyozaburo Takeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sliding-dependent electronic structures of alternating-twist tetralayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the electronic structure of alternating-twist tetralayer graphene, especially near its magic angle $\theta = 1.75^\circ$, for different AA, AB, and SP sliding geometries at their middle interface that divides two twisted bilayer graphenes. This sliding dependence is shown for the bandwidths, bandgaps, and $K$-valley Chern numbers of the lowest-energy valence and conduction bands as a function of twist angle and interlayer potential difference. Our analysis reveals that the AA sliding is most favorable for narrow bands and gaps, and the AB sliding is most prone to developing finite valley Chern numbers. We further analyze the linear longitudinal optical absorptions as a function of photon energy and the absorption map in the moir\'{e} Brillouin zone for specific transition energies. A self-consistent Hartree calculation reveals that the AA system's electronic structure is most sensitive to variations in carrier density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11527v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyungjin Shin, Jiseon Shin, Yoonsung Lee, Hongki Min, Jeil Jung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capacitive detection of the topological magnetoelectric effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11591v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The topological magnetoelectric effect (TME) is a defining property of 3-dimensional $\mathbb{Z}_{2}$ topological insulators that was predicted on theoretical grounds more than a decade ago, but has still not been directly measured. In this Letter we propose a strategy for direct measurement of the TME, and discuss the precision of the effect in real devices with charge and spin disorder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11591v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Lei, Perry T. Mahon, C. M. Canali, A. H. MacDonald</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A hybrid graphene-siliconnitride nanomembrane as a versatile and ultra-widely tunable mechanical device</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11596v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Integration of 2D materials in nanoelectromechanical systems (NEMS) marries the robustness of silicon-based materials with exceptional electrical controllability in 2D materials, drastically enhancing system performance which now is the key for many advanced applications in nanotechnology. Here, we experimentally demonstrate and theoretically analyze a powerful on-chip graphene integrated NEMS device consisting of a hybrid graphene/silicon-nitride membrane with metallic leads that enables an extremely large static and dynamic parameter regulation. When a static voltage is applied to the leads, the force induced by the thermal expansion difference between the leads and the membrane results in ultra-wide frequency tuning, deformation (post-buckling transition) and regulation of mechanical properties. Moreover, by injecting an alternating voltage to the leads, we can excite the resonator vibrating even far beyond its linear regime without a complex and space consuming actuation system. Our results prove that the device is a compact integrated system possessing mechanical robustness, high controllability, and fast response. It not only expands the limit of the application range of NEMS devices but also pushes multidimensional nanomechanical resonators into working in the nonlinear regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11596v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengqi Fu, Bojan Bo\v{s}njak, Zhan Shi, Jannik Dornseiff, Robert H. Blick, Elke Scheer, Fan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-equillibrium ultrafast optical excitation as a stimulus for ultra-small field-free magnetic skyrmions in ferrimagnetic GdFeCo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11615v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generating and manipulating magnetic skyrmions at ultrafast time scales is essential for future skyrmionbased racetrack memory and logic gate applications. Using the atomistic spin dynamics simulations, we demonstrate the nucleation of ultra-small field-free magnetic skyrmions in amorphous GdFeCo at picosecond timescales by femtosecond laser heating. The ultrafast nature of laser heating and subsequent cooling from a high-temperature state is crucial for forming magnetic skyrmion. The magnon localization and magnon coalescence are the key driving mechanisms responsible for stabilizing the magnetic skyrmions at zero field conditions. The polarization and, hence, the topological charge can be switched by exploiting the all-optical switching observed in GdFeCo. The skyrmion sizes and numbers can be controlled by varying pulse width and fluence of incident laser pulses. Applying an external magnetic field provides an additional degree of freedom to tune the skyrmion radius during the ultrafast optical creation of magnetic skyrmions. Our results provide a detailed understanding of the ultrafast creation of magnetic skyrmions using femtosecond laser pulses, a vital step in advancing next-generation skyrmion-based memory technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11615v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Syam Prasad P, Jyoti Ranjan Mohanty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum criticality and optical conductivity in a two-valley system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10503v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate that the optical conductivity of a Fermi liquid (FL) in the absence of umklapp scattering is dramatically affected by the topology of the Fermi surface (FS). Specifically, electron-electron (ee) scattering leads to rapid current relaxation in systems with multiple, or multiply connected, FSs, provided the valleys have different effective masses. This effect results from intervalley drag. We microscopically derive the optical conductivity of a two-valley system, both within the FL regime and near a quantum critical point (QCP) of the Ising-nematic type. In the FL regime, intervalley drag restores the Gurzhi-like scaling of the conductivity, $\mathrm{Re} \sigma(\omega) \sim \omega^0$. This dependence contrasts sharply with the previously identified sub-leading contribution to the conductivity of a two-dimensional FL with a single convex FS, where $\mathrm{Re} \sigma(\omega) \sim \omega^2 \ln |\omega|$. The vanishing of the leading term in the optical conductivity is a signature of geometric constraints on ee scattering channels, which are lifted for a multiply connected FS. A large differential response, $d \mathrm{Re} \sigma/d \mu$ with $\mu$ being the chemical potential, is predicted at the Lifshitz transition from a single-valley to a multi-valley FS, which should be observable within the experimentally accessible frequency range. Near a QCP, intervalley drag leads to a $|\omega|^{-2/3}$ scaling of $\mathrm{Re} \sigma(\omega)$ in 2D, thus providing a specific current-relaxing process for this long-standing conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10503v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yasha Gindikin, Songci Li, Alex Levchenko, Alex Kamenev, Andrey V. Chubukov, Dmitrii L. Maslov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion Models Are Promising for Ab Initio Structure Solutions from Nanocrystalline Powder Diffraction Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10796v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A major challenge in materials science is the determination of the structure of nanometer sized objects. Here we present a novel approach that uses a generative machine learning model based on a Diffusion model that is trained on 45,229 known structures. The model factors both the measured diffraction pattern as well as relevant statistical priors on the unit cell of atomic cluster structures. Conditioned only on the chemical formula and the information-scarce finite-size broadened powder diffraction pattern, we find that our model, PXRDnet, can successfully solve simulated nanocrystals as small as 10 angstroms across 200 materials of varying symmetry and complexity, including structures from all seven crystal systems. We show that our model can determine structural solutions with up to $81.5\%$ accuracy, as measured by structural correlation. Furthermore, PXRDnet is capable of solving structures from noisy diffraction patterns gathered in real-world experiments. We suggest that data driven approaches, bootstrapped from theoretical simulation, will ultimately provide a path towards determining the structure of previously unsolved nano-materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10796v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabe Guo, Tristan Saidi, Maxwell Terban, Simon JL Billinge, Hod Lipson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unrevealing the structure and properties of {$\alpha$}-sheet-based bilayer borophenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10860v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent experimental realizations of bilayer boron materials motivated us to study the structure and properties of $\alpha$-sheet-based bilayer borophenes with interlayer covalent bonds. As shown here, at least three stacking variations are possible: AA, AB, and AB$'$. The on-top AA-stacking has been obtained experimentally. The AB-stacking is the most stable among neutral freestanding structures, whereas the AA and AB$'$ stacking sequences are very close in energy, both for neutral and negatively charged cases. The studied bilayer borophenes exhibit extraordinarily high electric conductivity with values as high as ${\sim} 10^7\mathrm{~S}/\mathrm{m}$ for the experimentally observed AA-stacking. The highly stable AB-stacking bilayer, reported here for the first time, exhibits an anisotropic conductivity with an average value of $6.0 \times 10^6~\mathrm{S/m}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10860v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subrata Rakshit, Nevill Gonzalez Szwacki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gateway to all-optical spin switching in Heusler ferrimagnets: Pancharatnam-Berry tensor and magnetic moment ratio</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: All-optical spin switching (AOS) is a new phenomenon found in a small group of magnetic media, where a single laser pulse can switch spins from one direction to another, without assistance of a magnetic field, on a time scale much shorter than existing magnetic technology. However, despite intensive efforts over a decade, its underlying working principle remains elusive. Here through manganese-based Heusler ferrimagnets, we show that a group of flat bands around the Fermi level act as gateway states to form efficient channels or spin switching, where their noncentrosymmetry allows us to correlate the spin dynamics to the second-order optical response. To quantify their efficacy, we introduce the third-rank Pancharatnam-Berry tensor (PB tensor), $\boldsymbol{\eta}^{(3)}=\langle i |{\bf p} |m\rangle \langle m|{\bf p} |f\rangle \langle f|{\bf p} |i\rangle,$ where $|i\rangle$, $|m\rangle$ and $|f\rangle$ are initial, intermediate and final band states, respectively, and ${\bf p}$ is the momentum operator. A picture emerges: Those which show AOS, such as the recently discovered Mn$_2$RuGa, always have a large PB tensor element} but have a small sublattice spin moment ratio, consistent with the prior experimental small remanence criterion. This does not only reveal that the delicate balance between the large PB tensor element and the small sublattice spin ratio plays a decisive role in AOS, but also, conceptually, connects the $n$th-order nonlinear optics to $(n+1)$th-rank PB tensors in general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11099v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.L220401</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>G. P. Zhang, Y. Q. Liu, M. S. Si, Nicholas Allbritton, Y. H. Bai, Wolfgang H\"ubner, Thomas F. George</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field-free Josephson diode effect in a d-wave superconductor heterostructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11127v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study superconductor/normal region/superconductor (S|N|S) Josephson junction formed using superconductors with d, d + id', and d + is superconducting pairings. We show that the quality factor of the Josephson diode effect and its sign can be substantially tuned by the external magnetic field, gate voltage, and the length of the junction for all three types of pairings. We also identify the conditions under which the anomalous Josephson and Josephson diode effects can appear in the junction by analyzing appropriate symmetries. In particular, by breaking a {\pi}-rotation symmetry, we show how a large field-free Josephson diode effect can be realized even in the absence of spin-orbit coupling. We also study the role of edge states appearing in the case of chiral superconductor with d + id' pairing. Our results demonstrate that the Josephson diode effect in a planar geometry can be used as a signature of unconventional superconducting pairings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11127v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hamed Vakili, Moaz Ali, Alexey A. Kovalev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral dichroism in resonant metasurfaces with monoclinic lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11300</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11300v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We reveal that chiral response can be achieved in resonant metasurfaces with a monoclinic lattice symmetry (the so-called Bravais oblique lattices) where the mirror symmetry is broken by the lattice asymmetry and by a substrate, while each individual meta-atom remains fully achiral. We describe the underlying mechanism by introducing the mode chirality parameter as a quantitative measure of the lattice chiral eigenmodes. We confirm experimentally selective linear and nonlinear chiral interaction of resonant silicon metasurfaces with circularly polarized light.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11300v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan Toftul, Pavel Tonkaev, Kirill Koshelev, Fangxing Lai, Qinghai Song, Maxim Gorkunov, Yuri Kivshar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantized orbital angular momentums of dipolar magnons and magnetoelectric cavity polaritons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11359v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnons are viewed as local deviations from the ordered state. Usually, the spin magnetic moment of magnons is considered. In a 3D-confined structure of a magnetic insulator with magnetodipolar mode (MDM) oscillations, an orbital angular momentum (OAM) as well as a spin angular momentum (SAM) can be observed along a static magnetic field. In such a confined structure as quasi-2D ferrite disk, energy levels of MDM oscillations are quantized. Quantum confinement is characterized by a half-integer internal OAM, which is also associated with a circulating energy flow. The observation of MDM resonances in the 3D-confined structure of a magnetic insulator is due to the interaction of two subsystems: ferromagnetic and electric polarization orders. The coupling states of these two concurrent orders, caused by OAMs, are considered as magnetoelectric (ME) states. The fields in the vicinity of MDM resonators are characterized by simultaneous violation of time reversal and inversion symmetry. This plays a significant role in the problems of strong light-matter interaction regime and quantum atmosphere. The analysis of SAM and OAM in 3D-confined magnetic insulators becomes very important for the realization of ME meta-atomic structures. Current interest lies in considering such artificial systems as subwavelength ME quantum emitters of electromagnetic radiation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11359v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. O. Kamenetskii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enabling Ab-Initio Molecular Dynamics under Bias: The CP2K+SMEAGOL Interface for Integrating Density Functional Theory and Non-Equilibrium Green Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11494v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Density functional theory (DFT) combined with non-equilibrium Greens functions (NEGF) is a powerful approach to model quantum transport under external bias potentials, at reasonable computational cost. In this work we present a new interface between the popular mixed Gaussian/plane wave electronic structure package CP2K and the NEGF code SMEAGOL, the most feature-rich implementation of DFT-NEGF available for CP2K to-date. The CP2K+SMEAGOL interface includes the implementation of current induced forces. We verify this implementation for a variety of systems: an infinite 1D Au wire, a parallel-plate capacitor and a Au-H2-Au junction. We find good agreement with SMEAGOL calculations performed with SIESTA for the same systems, and with the example of a solvated Au wire demonstrate for the first time that DFT-NEGF can be used to perform molecular dynamics simulations under bias of large-scale condensed phase systems under realistic operating conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11494v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian S. Ahart, Sergey Chulkov, Clotilde S. Cucinotta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissecting van der Waals interactions with Density Functional Theory -- Wannier-basis approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11658v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A new scheme for the computation of dispersive interactions from first principles is presented. This cost-effective approach relies on a Wannier function representation compatible with density function theory descriptions. This is an electronic-based many-body method that captures the full electronic and optical response properties of the materials. It provides the foundation to discern van der Waals and induction energies as well as the role of anisotropy and different stacking patterns when computing dispersive interactions in systems. Calculated results for binding energies in layered materials, such as graphite, hBN, and MoS$_2$ give encouraging comparisons with available experimental data. Strategies for broadened computational descriptions of dispersive interactions are also discussed. Our investigation aims at stimulating new experimental studies to measure van der Waals energies in a wider range of materials, especially in layered systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11658v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diem Thi-Xuan Dang, Dai-Nam Le, Lilia M. Woods</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photoinduced Patterning of Oxygen Vacancies to Promote the Ferroelectric Phase of $\mathrm{Hf_{0.5}Zr_{0.5}O_2}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11763v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Photoinduced reductions in the oxygen vacancy concentration were leveraged to increase the ferroelectric phase fraction of $\mathrm{Hf_{0.5}Zr_{0.5}O_2}$ (HZO) thin-films. Modest ($\sim 0.02-0.77~\mathrm{mJ/\mu m^2}$) laser doses of visible light (488 nm, 2.54 eV) spatially patterned the concentration of oxygen vacancies as monitored by photoluminescence imaging. Local, tip-based, near-field, nanoFTIR measurements showed that the photoinduced oxygen vacancy concentration reduction promoted formation of the ferroelectric phase (space group $Pca2_1$) resulting in an increase in the piezoelectric response measured by piezoresponse force microscopy. Photoinduced vacancy tailoring provides, therefore, a spatially prescriptive, post-synthesis, and low-entry method to modify phase in \hfo-based materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11763v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0186481</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Appl. Phys. Lett. 124, 062902 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thomas E Beechem (School of Mechanical Engineering and Birck Nanotechnology Center, Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN, USA), Fernando Vega (School of Mechanical Engineering and Birck Nanotechnology Center, Purdue University, West Lafayette, IN, USA), Samantha T. Jaszewski (Department of Materials Science and Engineering, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA, USA), Benjamin L. Aronson (Department of Materials Science and Engineering, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA, USA), Kyle P. Kelley (Center for Nanophase Materials Sciences, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, TN, USA), Jon F. Ihlefeld (Department of Materials Science and Engineering, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA, USA, Department of Materials Science and Engineering, University of Virginia, Charlottesville, VA, USA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stochastic theory of nonlinear electrical circuits in thermal equilibrium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11796v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We revisit the theory of dissipative mechanics in RLC circuits, allowing for circuit elements to have nonlinear constitutive relations, and for the circuit to have arbitrary topology. We systematically generalize the dissipationless Hamiltonian mechanics of an LC circuit to account for resistors and incorporate the physical postulate that the resulting RLC circuit thermalizes with its environment at a constant positive temperature. Our theory explains stochastic fluctuations, or Johnson noise, which are mandated by the fluctuation-dissipation theorem. Assuming Gaussian Markovian noise, we obtain exact expressions for multiplicative Johnson noise through nonlinear resistors in circuits with convenient (parasitic) capacitors and/or inductors. With linear resistors, our formalism is describable using a Kubo-Martin-Schwinger-invariant Lagrangian formalism for dissipative thermal systems. Generalizing our technique to quantum circuits could lead to an alternative way to study decoherence in nonlinear superconducting circuits without the Caldeira-Leggett formalism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11796v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Osborne, Andrew Lucas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Angle-resolved optically detected magnetic resonance as a tool for strain determination in nanostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.06451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2106.06451v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we apply the angle-resolved Optically Detected Magnetic Resonance (ODMR) technique to study series of strained (Cd, Mn)Te/(Cd, Mg)Te quantum wells (QWs) produced by molecular beam epitaxy. By analyzing characteristic features of ODMR angular scans, we determine strain-induced axial-symmetry spin Hamiltonian parameter D with neV precision. Furthermore, we use low-temperature optical reflectivity measurements and X-ray diffraction scans to evaluate the local strain present in QW material. In our analysis, we take into account different thermal expansion coefficients of GaAs substrate and CdTe buffer. The additional deformation due to the thermal expansion effects has the same magnitude as deformation origination from the different compositions of the samples. Based on the evaluated deformations and values of strain-induced axial-symmetry spin Hamiltonian parameter D, we find strain spin-lattice coefficient G11 = (72.2 +- 1.9) neV for Mn2+ in CdTe and shear deformation potential b = (-0.94 +- 0.11) eV for CdTe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2106.06451v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.105.075412</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>A. Bogucki, M. Goryca, A. {\L}opion, W. Pacuski, K. E. Po{\l}czy\'nska, J. Domaga{\l}a, M. Tokarczyk, T. F\k{a}s, A. Golnik, P. Kossacki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moire-enabled topological superconductivity in twisted bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.04605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.04605v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Twisted van der Waals materials have risen as highly tunable platform for realizing unconventional superconductivity. Here we demonstrate how a topological superconducting state can be driven in a twisted graphene multilayer at a twist angle of approximately 1.6 degrees proximitized to other 2D materials. We show that an encapsulated twisted bilayer subject to induced Rashba spin-orbit coupling, s-wave superconductivity and exchange field generates a topological superconducting state enabled by the moire pattern. We demonstrate a variety of topological states with different Chern numbers highly tunable through doping, strain and bias voltage. Our proposal does not depend on a fine tuning of the twist angle, but solely on the emergence of moire minibands and is applicable for twist angles between 1.3 and 3 degrees. Our results establish the potential of twisted graphene bilayers to create artificial topological superconductivity without requiring ultraflat dispersions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.04605v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/2053-1583/ad3b0c</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2D Materials 11 (3), 035012 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Maryam Khosravian, Elena Bascones, Jose L. Lado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermion-parity qubit in a proximitized double quantum dot</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.05678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.05678v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bound states in quantum dots coupled to superconductors can be in a coherent superposition of states with different electron number but with the same fermion parity. Electrostatic gating can tune this superposition to a sweet spot, where the quantum dot has the same mean electric charge independent of its electron-number parity. Here, we propose to encode quantum information in the local fermion parity of two tunnel-coupled quantum dots embedded in a Josephson junction. At the sweet spot, the qubit states have zero charge dipole moment. This protects the qubit from dephasing due to charge noise acting on the potential of each dot, as well as fluctuations of the (weak) inter-dot tunneling. At weak inter-dot tunneling, relaxation is suppressed because of disjoint qubit states. On the other hand, for strong inter-dot tunneling the system is protected against noise affecting each quantum dot separately (energy level noise, dot-superconductor tunneling fluctuations, and hyperfine interactions). Finally, we describe initialization and readout as well as single-qubit and two-qubit gates by pulsing gate voltages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.05678v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.023281</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 6, 023281 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Max Geier, Rub\'en Seoane Souto, Jens Schulenborg, Serwan Asaad, Martin Leijnse, Karsten Flensberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry, topology, and geometry: The many faces of the topological magnetoelectric effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.09282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.09282v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A delicate tension complicates the relationship between the topological magnetoelectric effect (TME) in three-dimensional (3D) $\mathbb{Z}_2$ topological insulators (TIs) and time-reversal symmetry (TRS). TRS underlies a particular $\mathbb{Z}_2$ topological classification of the electronic ground state of crystalline band insulators and the associated quantization of the magnetoelectric response coefficient calculated using bulk linear response theory but, according to standard symmetry arguments, simultaneously forbids a nonzero magnetoelectric coefficient in any physical finite-size system. This contrast between theories of magnetoelectric response in formal bulk models and in real finite-sized materials originates from the distinct approaches required to introduce notions of (electronic) polarization and orbital magnetization in these fundamentally different environments. In this work we argue for a modified interpretation of the bulk linear response calculations in non-magnetic $\mathbb{Z}_2$ TIs that is more plainly consistent with TRS, and use this interpretation to discuss the effect's observation - still absent over a decade after its prediction. Motivated by analytical results, we conjecture a type of microscopic bulk-boundary correspondence: a bulk insulator with (generalized) TRS supports a magnetoelectric coefficient that is purely itinerant (which is generically related to the geometry of the ground state) if and only if magnetic surface dopants are required for the TME to manifest in finite samples thereof. We conclude that in non-magnetic $\mathbb{Z}_2$ TIs the TME is activated by magnetic surface dopants, that the charge density response to a uniform dc magnetic field is localized at the surface and specified by the configuration of those dopants, and that the TME is qualitatively less robust against disorder than the integer quantum Hall effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.09282v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.023289</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 6, 023289 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Perry T. Mahon, Chao Lei, Allan H. MacDonald</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct observation of current-induced nonlinear spin torque in Pt-Py bilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.11156v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We experimentally observe nonlinear spin torque in metallic bilayers of platinum and permalloy by means of spin-torque ferromagnetic-resonance (ST-FMR) under massive dc current injection. The observed nonlinear spin torque exerted to permalloy magnetization is attributed primarily to nonlinear spin polarization. Additional origin of the nonlinear spin torque is magnon generation (annihilation) followed by shrinkage (expansion) of effective magnetization, which is reveled by STFMR and unidirectional spin Hall magnetoresistance measurements. The present study paves a way to spin-Hall effect based nonlinear spintronic devices as well as time-varying nonlinear magnetic metamaterials with tailor-made permeability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.11156v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.214419</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Toshiyuki Kodama, Nobuaki Kikuchi, Takahiro Chiba, Satoshi Okamoto, Seigo Ohno, Satoshi Tomita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On-chip multi-degree-of-freedom control of two-dimensional quantum and nonlinear materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12030v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two-dimensional materials (2DM) and their derived heterostructures have electrical and optical properties that are widely tunable via several approaches, most notably electrostatic gating and interfacial engineering such as twisting. While electrostatic gating is simple and has been ubiquitously employed on 2DM, being able to tailor the interfacial properties in a similar real-time manner represents the next leap in our ability to modulate the underlying physics and build exotic devices with 2DM. However, all existing approaches rely on external machinery such as scanning microscopes, which often limit their scope of applications, and there is currently no means of tuning a 2D interface that has the same accessibility and scalability as electrostatic gating. Here, we demonstrate the first on-chip platform designed for 2D materials with in situ tunable interfacial properties, utilizing a microelectromechanical system (MEMS). Each compact, cost-effective, and versatile device is a standalone micromachine that allows voltage-controlled approaching, twisting, and pressurizing of 2DM with high accuracy. As a demonstration, we engineer synthetic topological singularities, known as merons, in the nonlinear optical susceptibility of twisted hexagonal boron nitride (h-BN), via simultaneous control of twist angle and interlayer separation. The chirality of the resulting moire pattern further induces a strong circular dichroism in the second-harmonic generation. A potential application of this topological nonlinear susceptibility is to create integrated classical and quantum light sources that have widely and real-time tunable polarization. Our invention pushes the boundary of available technologies for manipulating low-dimensional quantum materials, which in turn opens up the gateway for designing future hybrid 2D-3D devices for condensed-matter physics, quantum optics, and beyond.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12030v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoning Tang, Yiting Wang, Xueqi Ni, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Pablo Jarillo-Herrero, Shanhui Fan, Eric Mazur, Amir Yacoby, Yuan Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiphoton-pumped UV-Vis transient absorption spectroscopy of 2D materials: basic concepts and recent applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.13098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.13098v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: 2D materials are considered a key element in the development of next-generation electronics (nanoelectronics) due to their extreme thickness in the nanometer range and unique physical properties. The ultrafast dynamics of photoexcited carriers in such materials are strongly influenced by their interfaces, since the thickness of 2D materials is much smaller than the typical depth of light penetration into their bulk counterparts and the mean free path of photoexcited carriers. The resulting collisions of photoexcited carriers with interfacial potential barriers of 2D materials in the presence of a strong laser field significantly alter the overall dynamics of photoexcitation, allowing laser light to be directly absorbed by carriers in the conduction/valence band through the inverse bremsstrahlung mechanism. The corresponding ultrafast carrier dynamics can be monitored using multiphoton-pumped UV-Vis transient absorption spectroscopy. In this review, we discuss the basic concepts and recent applications of this spectroscopy for a variety of 2D materials, including transition-metal dichalcogenide monolayers, topological insulators, and other 2D semiconductor structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.13098v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-648X/ad56eb</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yuri D Glinka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photoinduced metallic Volkov-Pankratov states in semi-Dirac material</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.16120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.16120v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the emergence of interfacial modes between the two regions of a semi-Dirac type material, which are illuminated by the left and right circularly polarized light, respectively. We show that a smooth boundary between the two regions give rise to an interfacial quantum well which is sensitive to the incoming electron's momentum. The quantum well is found to host the Volkov-Pankratov states which are gapless metallic in nature. Contrary to the inverted mass term, it is the inverted velocity term that induces such states across the boundary. We also note that incident electron can fully pass over the interfacial well without any reflection only at certain light parameters-known as {\it Ramsauer-Townsend} effect. Moreover, we also observe that such modes can even exist across the interface between the irradiated and non-irradiated regions under certain condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.16120v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.109.235416</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 109, 235416 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>SK Firoz Islam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature dependence of microwave losses in lumped-element resonators made from superconducting nanowires with high kinetic inductance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.02943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.02943v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the response of several microwave resonators made from superconducting NbTiN thin-film meandering nanowires with large kinetic inductance, having different circuit topology and coupling to the transmission line. Reflection measurements reveal the parameters of the circuit and analysis of their temperature dependence in the range 1.7-6 K extract the superconducting energy gap and critical temperature. The lumped-element LC resonator, valid in our frequency range of interest, allows us to predict the quasiparticle contribution to internal loss, independent of circuit topology and characteristic impedance. Our analysis shows that the internal quality factor is limited not by thermal-equilibrium quasiparticles, but an additional temperature-dependent source of internal microwave loss.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.02943v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6668/ad4d5c</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Supercond. Sci. Technol. 37 075013 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ermes Scarano, Elisabet K. Arvidsson, August K. Roos, Erik Holmgren, David B. Haviland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic Kerr amplification for microwave electromechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00802v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Electromechanical transduction gain of 21 dB is realized in a micro-cantilever resonant force sensor operated in the unresolved-sideband regime. Strain-dependent kinetic inductance weakly couples cantilever motion to a superconducting nonlinear resonant circuit. A single pump generates motional sidebands and parametrically amplifies them via four-wave mixing. We study the gain and added noise, and we analyze potential benefits of this integrated amplification process in the context force sensitivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00802v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0201936</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Appl. Phys. Lett. 124, 243503 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ermes Scarano, Elisabet K. Arvidsson, August K. Roos, Erik Holmgren, David B. Haviland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated boundary integral analysis of energy eigenvalues for confined electron states in quantum semiconductor heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04276v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel and efficient approach for the computation of energy eigenvalues in quantum semiconductor heterostructures. Accurate determination of the electronic states in these heterostructures is crucial for understanding their optical and electronic properties, making it a key challenge in semiconductor physics. The proposed method is based on utilizing series expansions of zero-order Bessel functions to numerically solve the Schr\"odinger equation using boundary integral method for bound electron states in a computationally efficient manner. To validate the proposed technique, we applied it to address previously explored issues by other research groups. The results clearly demonstrate the computational efficiency and high precision of our approach. Notably, the proposed technique significantly reduces the computational time compared to the conventional method for searching the energy eigenvalues in quantum structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04276v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. D. Phan, A. -V. Phan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fermi arcs mediated transport in inversion symmetry-broken Weyl semimetal nanowire and its hybrid junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.07490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.07490v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The emergence of gapless surface states, known as Fermi arcs (FAs), is one of the unique properties of the novel topological Weyl semimetal (WSM). However, extracting the signatures of FAs from the bulk states has always been a challenge as both of them are gapless in nature and connected to each other. We capture the signatures of FAs via transport in an inversion symmetry (IS)-broken WSM. We study the band structure and the properties of FAs like shape, spin polarization considering slab and nanowire (NW) geometry, and then compute the two-terminal conductance in WSM NW in terms of the scattering coefficients within the Landauer formalism. We find the FA-mediated conductance to be quantized in units of $2e^2/h$. We extend our study to the transport in WSM/Weyl superconductor (WSC) NW hybrid junction using the Blonder-Tinkham-Klapwijk (BTK) formalism. We show that due to the intricate spin textures, the signatures of the FAs can be captured via Andreev reflection process. We also show that our results of conductance are robust against delta-correlated quenched disorder and thus enhancing the experimental feasibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.07490v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 109, 235419 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Amartya Pal, Paramita Dutta, Arijit Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of Superconductivity in Twisted Graphene Multilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00903v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The group of moir\'e graphene superconductors keeps growing, and by now it contains twisted graphene multilayers and twisted double bilayers. We analyze the contribution of long range charge fluctuations in the superconductivity of twisted double graphene bilayers and helical trilayers, and compare the results to twisted bilayer graphene. We apply a diagrammatic approach which depends on a few, well known parameters. We find that the critical temperature and the order parameter differ significantly between twisted double bilayers and helical trilayers on one hand, and twisted bilayer graphene on the other. We show that this trend, consistent with experiments, can be associated to the role played by moir\'e Umklapp processes in the different systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00903v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Min Long, Alejandro Jimeno-Pozo, Hector Sainz-Cruz, Pierre A. Pantaleon, Francisco Guinea</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gapless Edge-Modes and Topology in the Qi-Wu-Zhang Model: A Real-Space Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.01576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.01576v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The topological phase transition in the Qi-Wu-Zhang model is studied using a real-space approach. An effective Hamiltonian for the topologically protected edge-modes in a finite-size system is developed. The topological phase transition is understood in terms of a global perturbation to the system which lifts the degeneracy of the edge-modes. The effective Hamiltonian method is also applied to a one-dimensional system with spatially varying hopping strengths to understand the impact of disorder on the edge-modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.01576v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arjo Dasgupta, Indra Dasgupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Substrate, temperature and magnetic field dependence of electric polarisation in mixed-stacking tetralayer graphenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09354v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Polytypes of tetralayer graphene (TLG: Bernal, rhombohedral and mixed stacking) are crystalline structures with different symmetries. Among those, mixed-stacking tetralayers lack inversion symmetry, which allows for intrinsic spontaneous out-of-plane electrical polarisation, inverted in the mirror-image pair, ABCB and ABAC stackings. Here, we compare the intrinsic polarisation of such TLGs with the symmetry-breaking effect of a substrate, which can also generate out-of-plane electric dipole moments with different sizes in all four polytypes, including ABCB and ABAC twins. We analyse their temperature and magnetic field dependence, in view of understanding the origin of the recently measured Kelvin probe force microscopy maps of tetralayer flakes, and notice that the intrinsic contribution could be singled out based on magnetic field dependence of polarisation measured at low temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09354v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Johansen Sarsfield, Aitor Garcia-Ruiz, Vladimir I. Fal'ko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topology in a one-dimensional plasmonic crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19576v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we study the topology of the bands of a plasmonic crystal composed of graphene and of a metallic grating. Firstly, we derive a Kronig-Penney type of equation for the plasmonic bands as function of the Bloch wavevector and discuss the propagation of the surface plasmon polaritons on the polaritonic crystal using a transfer-matrix approach considering a finite relaxation time. Second, we reformulate the problem as a tight-binding model that resembles the Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) Hamiltonian, one difference being that the hopping amplitudes are, in this case, energy dependent. In possession of the tight-binding equations it is a simple task to determine the topology (value of the winding number) of the bands. This allows to determine the existense or absence of topological end modes in the system. Similarly to the SSH model, we show that there is a tunable parameter that induces topological phase transitions from trivial to non-trivial. In our case, it is the distance d between the graphene sheet and the metallic grating. We note that d is a parameter that can be easily tuned experimentally simply by controlling the thickness of the spacer between the grating and the graphene sheet. It is then experimentally feasible to engineer devices with the required topological properties. Finally, we suggest a scattering experiment allowing the observation of the topological states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19576v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. A. Miranda, Y. V. Bludov, N. Asger Mortensen, N. M. R. Peres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gate- and flux-tunable sin(2$\varphi$) Josephson element with proximitized Ge-based junctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14695v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hybrid superconductor-semiconductor Josephson field-effect transistors (JoFETs) function as Josephson junctions with a gate-tunable critical current. Additionally, they can feature a non-sinusoidal current-phase relation (CPR) containing multiple harmonics of the superconducting phase difference, a so-far underutilized property. In this work, we exploit this multi-harmonicity to create a Josephson circuit element with an almost perfectly $\pi$-periodic CPR, indicative of a largely dominant charge-4e supercurrent transport. Such a Josephson element was recently proposed as the basic building block of a protected superconducting qubit. Here, it is realized using a superconducting quantum interference device (SQUID) with low-inductance aluminum arms and two nominally identical JoFETs. The latter are fabricated from a SiGe/Ge/SiGe quantum-well heterostructure embedding a high-mobility two-dimensional hole gas. By carefully adjusting the JoFET gate voltages and finely tuning the magnetic flux through the SQUID close to half a flux quantum, we achieve a regime where the $\sin(2\varphi)$ component accounts for more than \SI{95}{\percent} of the total supercurrent. This result demonstrates a new promising route for the realization of superconducting qubits with enhanced coherence properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14695v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Axel Leblanc, Chotivut Tangchingchai, Zahra Sadre Momtaz, Elyjah Kiyooka, Jean-Michel Hartmann, Frederic Gustavo, Jean-Luc Thomassin, Boris Brun, Vivien Schmitt, Simon Zihlmann, Romain Maurand, Etienne Dumur, Silvano De Franceschi, Francois Lefloch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge transport through the multiple end zigzag edge states of armchair graphene nanoribbons and heterojunctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17758</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17758v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This comprehensive study investigates charge transport through the multiple end zigzag edge states of finite-size armchair graphene nanoribbons/boron nitride nanoribbons (n-AGNR/w-BNNR) junctions under a longitudinal electric field, where n and w denote the widths of the AGNRs and the BNNRs, respectively. In 13-atom wide AGNR segments, the edge states exhibit a blue Stark shift in response to the electric field, with only the long decay length zigzag edge states showing significant interaction with the red Stark shift subband states. Charge tunneling through such edge states assisted by the subband states is elucidated in the spectra of the transmission coefficient. In the 13-AGNR/6-BNNR heterojunction, notable influences on the energy levels of the end zigzag edge states of 13-AGNRs induced by BNNR segments are observed. We demonstrate the modulation of these energy levels in resonant tunneling situations, as depicted by bias-dependent transmission coefficient spectra. Intriguing nonthermal broadening of tunneling current shows a significant peak-to-valley ratio. Our findings highlight the promising potential of n-AGNR/w-BNNR heterojunctions with long decay length edge states in the realm of GNR-based single electron transistors at room temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17758v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David M T Kuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Utilizing and extending superconducting circuit toolbox to simulate analog quantum gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.01261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.01261v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: There has been considerable effort to simulate quantum gravity features in solid state systems, such as analog black holes or wormholes. However, superconducting circuits have so far received only limited attention in this regard. Moreover, for quantum superpositions of spacetime geometries - a highly contentious notion within the quantum gravity community itself - there currently exist no solid state blueprints. We here show how quantum circuit hardware can implement a variety of classical and quantum spacetime geometries on lattices, by both using established circuit elements and introducing new ones. We demonstrate the possibility of a metric sharply changing within a single lattice point, thus entering a regime where the spacetime curvature itself is trans-Planckian, and the Hawking temperature ill-defined. In fact, our approach suggests that stable, thermal event horizons are incompatible with strictly discrete lattice models. We thus propose to directly probe the evaporation of a wormhole by tracking the accumulation of charge and phase quantum fluctuations over short time scales, which are a robust signature even in the presence of a dissipative environment. Moreover, we present a loop-hole for the typical black/while hole ambiguity in lattice simulations: the existence of exceptional points in the dispersion relation allows for the creation of pure black (or white) hole horizons - at the expense of radically changing the interior wormhole dynamics. Finally, based on multistable Josephson junctions, we introduce the notion of quantum inductors: circuit elements that can be prepared in a superposition of different inductance values. Such inductors realise regions with a quantum superposition of analog spacetime. The entanglement of signals with the quantum spacetime can be probed by a type of delayed-choice experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.01261v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Javed, D. Kruti, A. Kenawy, T. Herrig, C. Koliofoti, O. Kashuba, R. -P. Riwar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Skyrmions: from lumps to supercompactons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.03941v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The magnetic Skyrmion is described by one control parameter and one length scale. We study the two extreme limits of the control parameter - infinitely large and vanishing - and find that the magnetic Skyrmion becomes a "restricted" magnetic Skyrmion and an O(3) sigma model lump, respectively. Depending on the potential under consideration, the restricted limit manifests differently. In the case of the Zeeman term, the restricted magnetic Skyrmion becomes a "supercompacton" that develops a discontinuity, whereas for the Zeeman term to the power 3/2 it becomes a normal compacton. In both the lump and the restricted limit the solution is given in exact explicit form. We observe that the case of the Zeeman term squared, which can also be understood as a special combination of the Zeeman term and the easy-plane potential - realizable in the laboratory, the analytically exact solution for all values of the coupling - including the BPS case - is also of the lump type. Finally, we notice that certain materials (e.g. Fe$_{1-x}$Co$_x$Si or Mn$_{1-x}$Fe$_x$Ge) have a rather large control parameter $\epsilon$ of order 100, making the restricted limit a suitable rough approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.03941v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Bolognesi, Sven Bjarke Gudnason, Roberto Menta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gatemonium: A Voltage-Tunable Fluxonium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09002v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a new fluxonium qubit design, gatemonium, based on an all superconductor-semiconductor hybrid platform exhibiting gate voltage tunability of $E_J$. We first show the principle of fluxonium operation in epitaxial Al/InAs heterostructure where the single Josephson junction can be controlled using gate voltage control, effectively tuning the "weight" of the fictitious phase particle. The spectroscopy of the qubit shows tunability between plasmons to fluxons and their hybrid spectrum. We study two gatemonium devices with different charging energies and extract inductance of InAs-based Josephson junctions array. We also discuss future directions implementing a gate voltage tunable superinductance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09002v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William M. Strickland, Bassel Heiba Elfeky, Lukas Baker, Andrea Maiani, Jaewoo Lee, Ido Levy, Jacob Issokson, Andrei Vrajitoarea, Javad Shabani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic skyrmions under confinement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.00058</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.00058v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a variational treatment of confined magnetic skyrmions in a minimal micromagnetic model of ultrathin ferromagnetic films with interfacial Dzylashinksii-Moriya interaction (DMI) in competition with the exchange energy, with a possible addition of perpendicular magnetic anisotropy. Under Dirichlet boundary conditions that are motivated by the asymptotic treatment of the stray field energy in the thin film limit we prove existence of topologically non-trivial energy minimizers that concentrate on points in the domain as the DMI strength parameter tends to zero. Furthermore, we derive the leading order non-trivial term in the $\Gamma$-expansion of the energy in the limit of vanishing DMI strength that allows us to completely characterize the limiting magnetization profiles and interpret them as particle-like states whose radius and position are determined by minimizing a renormalized energy functional. In particular, we show that in our setting the skyrmions are strongly repelled from the domain boundaries, which imparts them with stability that is highly desirable for applications. We provide explicit calculations of the renormalized energy for a number of basic domain geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.00058v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00220-023-04864-w</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Commun. Math. Phys. 404, 1571-1605 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Antonin Monteil, Cyrill B. Muratov, Theresa M. Simon, Valeriy V. Slastikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended-localized transition in diffusive quasicrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.06765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.06765v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Compared to periodic systems, quasicrystals without translational invariance exhibit unexpected localization properties. The extended-localized transition in quasicrystals has been observed in both quantum and classical wave systems. However, its manifestation in diffusion systems, which serve as novel platforms for exploring phases of matter in condensed matter physics, remains unexplored. Here, we present the implementation of the extended-localized transition in a diffusive quasicrystal based on the coupled ring chain structure. By modulating the thermal conductivities of rings, we obtain the diffusive one-dimensional Aubry-Andr\'e-Harper (AAH) model, which exhibits an extended-localized transition. Thanks to the ring-shaped chain, we clearly demonstrate the extended-localized transition under the uniform excitation through temperature field simulations. For the localized state, the temperature field clearly demonstrates a multiple localization centers phenomenon, which has no counterpart in wave systems. We also quantitatively investigate the temperature evolution and size effect of this transition. Furthermore, the local excitation has been adopted to demonstrate the temperature field for both the extended and localized states. Besides, we implement the non-Hermitian diffusive AAH model by rotating rings, whose temperature field shows a moving multiple localization centers phenomenon in the localized phase. Finally, we give the experimental suggestions for the diffusive AAH model and propose a potential application named as double-trace distributed generator. Our results can facilitate the design of flexible thermal devices and efficient heat management.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.06765v2</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevApplied.21.064035</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Appl. 21, 064035 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhoufei Liu, Pei-Chao Cao, Ying Li, Jiping Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thomas-Fermi theory of out-of-plane charge screening in graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.02103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.02103v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper provides a variational treatment of the effect of external charges on the free charges in an infinite free-standing graphene sheet within the Thomas-Fermi theory. We establish existence, uniqueness and regularity of the energy minimizers corresponding to the free charge densities that screen the effect of an external electrostatic potential at the neutrality point. For the potential due to one or several off-layer point charges, we also prove positivity and a precise universal asymptotic decay rate for the screening charge density, as well as an exact charge cancellation by the graphene sheet. We also treat a simpler case of the non-zero background charge density and establish similar results in that case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.02103v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vitaly Moroz, Cyrill B. Muratov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reduced energies for thin ferromagnetic films with perpendicular anisotropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.07634</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.07634v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive four reduced two-dimensional models that describe, at different spatial scales, the micromagnetics of ultrathin ferromagnetic materials of finite spatial extent featuring perpendicular magnetic anisotropy and interfacial Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction. Starting with a microscopic model that regularizes the stray field near the material's lateral edges, we carry out an asymptotic analysis of the energy by means of $\Gamma$-convergence. Depending on the scaling assumptions on the size of the material domain vs. the strength of dipolar interaction, we obtain a hierarchy of the limit energies that exhibit progressively stronger stray field effects of the material edges. These limit energies feature, respectively, a renormalization of the out-of-plane anisotropy, an additional local boundary penalty term forcing out-of-plane alignment of the magnetization at the edge, a pinned magnetization at the edge, and, finally, a pinned magnetization and an additional field-like term that blows up at the edge, as the sample's lateral size is increased. The pinning of the magnetization at the edge restores the topological protection and enables the existence of magnetic skyrmions in bounded samples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.07634v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Di Fratta, C. B. Muratov, V. V. Slastikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A proposal for detecting the spin of a single electron in superfluid helium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.07174v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The electron bubble in superfluid helium has two degrees of freedom that may offer exceptionally low dissipation: the electron's spin and the bubble's motion. If these degrees of freedom can be read out and controlled with sufficient sensitivity, they would provide a novel platform for realizing a range of quantum technologies and for exploring open questions in the physics of superfluid helium. Here we propose a practical scheme for accomplishing this by trapping an electron bubble inside a superfluid-filled opto-acoustic cavity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.07174v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinyong Ma, Y. S. S. Patil, Jiaxin Yu, Yiqi Wang, J. G. E. Harris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scale and conformal invariance in rotating interacting few-fermion systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.12216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.12216v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that rotating two-dimensional Fermi gases possess a nonrelativistic scale and conformal invariance at weak but nonzero interactions, where the scale invariance of universal short-range interactions is not yet broken by quantum effects. We demonstrate the symmetry in the excitation spectrum of few-fermion ensembles in a harmonic trap obtained by exact diagonalization. The excitation spectrum is shown to split in a set of primary states and derived excited states that consist of breathing modes as well as two different center-of-mass excitations, which describe cyclotron and guiding-center excitations of the total particle cloud. Furthermore, the conformal symmetry is manifest in the many-body wave function, where it dictates the form of the hyperradial component, which we demonstrate using Monte Carlo sampling of few-body wave functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.12216v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.6.023279</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 6, 023279 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Viktor Bekassy, Johannes Hofmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Immersed boundary method for dynamic simulation of polarizable colloids of arbitrary shape in explicit ion electrolytes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.04865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.04865v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a computational method for modeling electrostatic interactions of arbitrarily-shaped, polarizable objects on colloidal length scales, including colloids/nanoparticles, polymers, and surfactants, dispersed in explicit ion electrolytes and nonionic solvents. Our method computes the nonuniform polarization charge distribution induced in a colloidal particle by both externally applied electric fields and local electric fields arising from other charged objects in the dispersion. This leads to expressions for electrostatic energies, forces, and torques that enable efficient molecular dynamics and Brownian dynamics simulations of colloidal dispersions in electrolytes, which can be harnessed to accurately predict structural and transport properties. We describe an implementation in which colloidal particles are modeled as rigid composites of small spherical beads that tessellate the surface of the particle. The electrostatics calculations are accelerated using a spectrally-accurate particle-mesh-Ewald technique implemented on a graphics processing unit (GPU) and regularized such that the electrostatic calculations are well-defined even for overlapping bodies. We demonstrate the effectiveness of this approach through a series of calculations, including the induced dipole moments and forces for one, two, and lattices of spherical colloids in an electric field; the induced dipole moment and torque for anisotropic particles in an electric field; the equilibrium distribution of ions in the double layer around charged colloids; the dynamics of charged colloids; and ions in the double layer around a polarizable colloid exposed to an electric field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.04865v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emily Krucker-Velasquez, James W. Swan, Zachary Sherman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab initio property characterisation of thousands of previously unknown 2D materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.02783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.02783v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We perform extensive density functional theory (DFT) calculations to determine the stability and elementary properties of 4249 previously unexplored monolayer crystals. The monolayers comprise the most stable subset (energy within 0.1 eV/atom of the convex hull) of a larger portfolio of two-dimensional (2D) materials recently discovered using a deep generative model and systematic lattice decoration schemes. The relaxed 2D structures are run through the basic property workflow of the Computational 2D Materials Database (C2DB) to evaluate the dynamical stability and obtain the stiffness tensor, piezoelectric tensor, deformation potentials, Born and Bader charges, electronic band structure, effective masses, plasma frequency, Fermi surface, projected density of states, magnetic moments, magnetic exchange couplings, magnetic anisotropy, topological indices, optical- and infrared polarisability. We provide statistical overviews of the property data and highlight a few specific examples of interesting materials. Our work exposes previously unknown parts of the 2D chemical space and provides a basis for the discovery of 2D materials with specific properties. All data is available in the C2DB.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.02783v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/2053-1583/ad53dc</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2D Mater. 11 035030 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Peder Lyngby, Kristian Sommer Thygesen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A classical density functional theory for solvation across length scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.02873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.02873v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A central aim of multiscale modeling is to use results from the Schr\"odinger Equation to predict phenomenology on length scales that far exceed those of typical molecular correlations. In this work, we present a new approach rooted in classical density functional theory (cDFT) that allows us to accurately describe the solvation of apolar solutes across length scales. Our approach builds on the Lum, Chandler and Weeks (LCW) theory of hydrophobicity [J. Phys. Chem. B 103, 4570 (1999)] by constructing a free energy functional that uses a slowly-varying component of the density field as a reference. From a practical viewpoint, the theory we present is numerically simpler and generalizes to solutes with soft-core repulsion more easily than LCW theory. Furthermore, by assessing the local compressibility and its critical scaling behavior, we demonstrate that our LCW-style cDFT approach contains the physics of critical drying, which has been emphasized as an essential aspect of hydrophobicity by recent theories. As our approach is parameterized on the two-body direct correlation function of the uniform fluid and the liquid-vapor surface tension, it straightforwardly captures the temperature dependence of solvation. Moreover, we use our theory to describe solvation at a first-principles level, on length scales that vastly exceed what is accessible to molecular simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.02873v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna T. Bui, Stephen J. Cox</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Selective-Area Epitaxy of Bulk-Insulating (Bi$_x$Sb$_{1-x}$)$_2$Te$_3$ Films and Nanowires by Molecular Beam Epitaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08427v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The selective-area epitaxy (SAE) is a useful technique to grow epitaxial films with a desired shape on a pre-patterned substrate. Although SAE of patterned topological-insulator (TI) thin films has been performed in the past, there has been no report of SAE-grown TI structures that are bulk-insulating. Here we report the successful growth of Hall-bars and nanowires of bulk-insulating TIs using the SAE technique. Their transport properties show that the quality of the selectively-grown structures is comparable to that of bulk-insulating TI films grown on pristine substrates. In SAE-grown TI nanowires, we were able to observe Aharonov-Bohm-like magnetoresistance oscillations that are characteristic of the quantum-confined topological surface states. The availability of bulk-insulating TI nanostructures via the SAE technique opens the possibility to fabricate intricate topological devices in a scalable manner.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08427v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gertjan Lippertz, Oliver Breunig, Rafael Fister, Anjana Uday, Andrea Bliesener, Jens Brede, Alexey Taskin, Yoichi Ando</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
