<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 04:00:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay of Rashba and valley-Zeeman splittings in weak localization of spin-orbit coupled graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18332v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Weak localization theory is developed for graphene heterostructures with transition metal dichalcogenides and topological insulators where the Rashba and valey-Zeeman spin-splittings of the energy spectrum are large enough. The anomalous magnetoresistance in low fields caused by weak localization is calculated. It is shown that the valley-Zeeman splitting has no effect on weak localization in the absence of Rashba splitting but it results in the change of the magnetoconductivity sign in the Rashba-coupled graphene. Inter-valley scattering also affects the quantum correction to the conductivity resulting in its sign reversal. Analytical expressions are obtained for the anomalous magnetoconductivity at arbitrary relations between the Rashba and valley-Zeeman splittings as well as the inter-valley scattering rates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18332v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. E. Golub</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin currents in crystals with spin-orbit coupling: multi-band effects in an effective Hamiltonian formalism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18363</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18363v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: When focusing on a few essential bands in an effective description of a material to calculate observable quantities, the respective operators have to be adjusted accordingly. Ignoring contributions arising from integrating out remote bands can lead to qualitatively wrong results. We present a detailed analysis of the interband mixing effects on spin currents. Specifically, we calculate the intrinsic spin current in a time-reversal invariant noncentrosymmetric crystal in the presence of electron-lattice spin-orbit coupling. Starting from formally exact microscopic expressions, we derive the spin current operator restricted to one or more essential bands by iterative elimination of the contributions from distant bands. We show that the standard definition of the spin current operator in terms of the group velocity obtained from an effective band Hamiltonian cannot be justified using a microscopic theory. The modified expression for the spin current operator contains additional terms, which dominate the equilibrium spin current in a uniform crystal. We show that the magnitude of these additional terms can considerably exceed the spin current obtained using the standard definition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18363v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. V. Samokhin, M. Sigrist, M. H. Fischer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation of pure, spin polarized, and unpolarized charge currents at the few cycle limit of circularly polarized light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18432v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In certain members of the transition metal dichalcogenide (TMDC) family, laser pulses of oppositely circularly polarized light excite electrons of opposite spin. Here we show that in the few cycle limit such pulses generate not only a spin density excitation, but also a spin current excitation. Employing the example of the TMDC WSe$_2$ we show that pure spin currents, the flow of spin in the absence of net charge flow, 100% spin polarized currents, and charge currents are all accessible and controllable by tuning the amplitude of ~ 5 femtosecond gap tuned light pulses. Underpinning this physics is a symmetry lowering of the valley charge excitation from C3 at long duration to C2 in the few cycle limit, imbuing the excitation with net current. Our results both highlight the emergence of a rich light-spin current coupling at ultrafast times in the TMDC family, as well presenting a route to the all-optical generation of pure spin currents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18432v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deepika Gill, Sangeeta Sharma, Sam Shallcross</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain-Tuned Optical Properties of a Two-Dimensional Hexagonal Lattice: Exploiting Saddle Degrees of Freedom and Saddle Filtering Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18539v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The deformation of hexagonal lattices has attracted considerable attention due to its promising applications in straintronics. This study employs the tight-binding model to investigate the anisotropic spectrum, where electronic transport can be manipulated by the degree of deformation. The longitudinal conductivities, light transmittance, and absorbance are analyzed, revealing enhancement along one direction and suppression along the other. The findings indicate that the direction and magnitude of strain can be determined by measuring transmittance and absorbance, showing significant deviations from the unstrained condition. Furthermore, a strong absorbance is observed due to the interband transition of electrons near the M-point saddles, linked to van Hove singularities for specific values of nearest and next-nearest hoping energy. The unexpected characteristics of saddle polarization-analogous to valley polarization at K- and K'-become particularly prominent when strain affects the selection of M-point saddle. Notably, the demonstration indicates that a highly efficient M-point saddle filtering effect takes place, induced by linearly polarized light. This model paves the way for exploring the optical properties of anisotropic hexagonal lattices, such as black phosphorus and borophene oxide. These results also open a pathway to strain-programmable optoelectronic devices, such as polarization-selective photodetectors, tunable absorbers, and ultrathin optical filters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18539v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phusit Nualpijit, Bumned Soodchomshom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex Frequency Fingerprint: Interacting Driven Non-Hermitian Skin Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18828</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18828v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The excitation properties of quantum many-body systems are encoded in their response functions. These functions define an associated response Hamiltonian, which is intrinsically non-Hermitian due to the dissipative nature of retarded responses, even in closed systems. By analyzing its eigenvalues and eigenstates, one obtains a unique characterization of the system, referred to as the complex frequency fingerprint. Using this framework, we demonstrate that interactions alone can give rise to both point-gap topology and the non-Hermitian skin effect. Unlike the dissipation-induced skin effect, this interaction-driven phenomenon exhibits pronounced frequency dependence. We further introduce a complex-frequency density of states framework that distinctly separates non-Hermitian skin modes from topological edge modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18828v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhesen Yang, Zihan Wang, Juntao Huang, Zijian Zheng, Jiangping Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic-perturbation induced anomalous higher-order boundary states in non-Hermitian systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18952v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The behavior of higher-order boundary states in non-Hermitian systems is elusive and thereby finding the mechanism behind these states is both essential and significant. Here, we uncover a novel mechanism that induces anomalous higher-order boundary states. The mechanism originates from the sensitivity of the non-normal boundary Hamiltonian to intrinsic perturbations, where intrinsic perturbations here refer to the influence of the bulk on the topological boundaries. Based on the mechanism, we reveal a new kind of phase transition, i.e., the transition between hybrid skin-topological states and scale-free topological boundary states. We also find that scale-free topological boundary states exhibit size-dependent spectra, influencing the existence of higher-order topological boundary states. Unlike conventional hybrid skin-topological states or higher-order non-Hermitian skin effect, the above two kinds of anomalous higher-order boundary states exhibit size-dependent characteristics. Our work opens a new horizon for the control of higher-order boundary states and topological properties of non-Hermitian systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18952v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/1bvp-p2cz</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, L241112 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hui-Qiang Liang, Zuxuan Ou, Linhu Li, Guo-Fu Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum oscillations between excitonic and quantum spin Hall insulators in moir\'e WSe2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19287v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantum spin Hall insulators (QSHIs) and excitonic insulators (EIs) are prototypical topological and correlated states of matter, respectively. The topological phase transition between the two has attracted much theoretical interest but experimental studies have been hindered by the availability of tunable materials that can access such a transition. Here, by utilizing the interaction-enhanced g-factor and the flat moir\'e bands in twisted bilayer WSe2 (tWSe2), we realize tunable electron-like and hole-like Landau levels (LLs) in the opposite valleys of tWSe2 under a perpendicular magnetic field. At half-band-filling, which corresponds to electron-hole charge neutrality, periodic oscillations between QSHIs (for fully filled LLs) and EIs (for half-filled LLs) are observed due to the interplay between the cyclotron energy and the intervalley correlation; QSHIs with up to four pairs of helical edge states can be resolved. We further analyze the effect of Fermi surface nesting on the stability of EIs via electric field-tuning of the moir\'e band structure. Our results demonstrate a novel QSHI-to-EI topological phase transition and provide a comprehensive understanding of the fermiology of tWSe2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19287v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhongdong Han, Yiyu Xia, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Kin Fai Mak, Jie Shan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SU(4) Kondo Lattice in Semiconductor Moir\'e Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18247v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by recent advances in transition metal dichalcogenide (TMD) moir\'e materials, we propose TMD moir\'e multilayers as a platform for realizing an approximately SU(4)-symmetric triangular Kondo lattice, generalizing the concept of the double quantum dot model. Our model extends the conventional Kondo lattice by incorporating a three-site exchange of SU(4) local moments, which drives spontaneous time-reversal and lattice symmetry breaking. Using a parton mean-field approach, we map out the phase diagram as a function of three-site exchange and hole doping. In the Kondo-unscreened regime, we identify Mott insulating phases, including bond-ordered states and a chiral spin liquid. With increasing doping, Kondo hybridization gives rise to a heavy Fermi liquid that exhibits distinct patterns of lattice symmetry breaking, with or without topological responses. We conclude with directions for future study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18247v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sunghoon Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Localization and topological signatures under periodic twisting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18248v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We theoretically explore a dynamical generalization of the Aubry-Andr\'e model in two dimensions formed by superimposing two square-lattice potentials. Motivated by the rich physics emerging at different twist angles between the two lattices at equilibrium, we introduce periodic twisting by continuously rotating one of the lattices with respect to the other in the plane. We demonstrate that the distinct time-dependent twisting in this system gives rise to an intricate form of periodic multi-frequency driving that changes with the distance from the rotation axis. We find that the incommensurate nature of the potential no longer plays the pivotal role as it does in the static case. Rather, the tunneling can be understood in terms of a local, spatially varying dynamical localization effect, which we show to yield ring-shaped states localized within the bulk that have interesting transport signatures. Quantifying the eigenstates with the Bott index and local Chern marker, we find that there is a zoo of states with non-trivial topological signatures, the most ubiquitous of which result in relatively uniform ring-shaped regions of the Chern marker. We investigate the origin of these effects from various angles and identify that hybridization between different delocalized ring states plays a vital role. Lastly, we discuss possible experimental realizations in quantum simulation settings. Our results open a new avenue of investigation with periodic twisting inducing a spatially varying multi-frequency drive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18248v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Walkling, Antonio \v{S}trkalj, F. Nur \"Unal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Obtaining the Spectral Function of Moir\'e Graphene Heavy-Fermions Using Iterative Perturbation Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18256v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The spectral functions of twisted bilayer graphene (TBG) in the absence of strain have recently been investigated in both the symmetric and symmetry-broken phases using dynamical mean-field theory (DMFT). The theoretically predicted Mott-Hubbard bands and gapless semimetallic state at half-filling have since been confirmed experimentally. Here, we develop several second-order perturbation theory approaches to the topological heavy-fermion (THF) model of TBG and twisted symmetric trilayer graphene (TSTG). In the symmetric phase, we adapt, implement, and benchmark an iterative perturbation theory (IPT) impurity solver within DMFT, enabling computationally efficient yet accurate spectral function calculations. We present momentum- and energy-resolved spectra over a broad range of temperatures and fillings for both symmetric and symmetry-broken states. In addition, we derive analytic expressions for the spectral function within the ``Hubbard-I'' approximation of the THF model and, as expected, find that while it provides a tractable description of Mott physics, it does not capture the low-energy Kondo peak or the finite lifetime broadening of the bands. Our methodology can be extended to include strain, lattice relaxation, and parameter variations, thereby allowing systematic predictions of TBG and TSTG spectral properties across a wide range of physical regimes. Because our perturbative approaches are far less computationally intensive than DMFT with numerically exact impurity solvers, they can be used to efficiently benchmark and scan extensive phase diagrams of the THF parameters, paving the way for full DMFT analyses of the TBG spectral function in the presence of strain and relaxation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18256v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dumitru C\u{a}lug\u{a}ru, Haoyu Hu, Lorenzo Crippa, Gautam Rai, Nicolas Regnault, Tim O. Wehling, Roser Valent\'i, Giorgio Sangiovanni, B. Andrei Bernevig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Er$_\mathrm{Al}$:Al$_2$O$_3$ for Telecom-Band Photonics: Electronic Structure and Optical Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18409v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Er-doped Al$_2$O$_3$ is a promising host for telecom-band integrated photonics. Here we combine ab initio calculations with a symmetry-resolved analysis to elucidate substitutional Er on the Al site (Er$_\mathrm{Al}$) in $\alpha$-Al$_2$O$_3$. First-principles relaxations confirm the structural stability of Er$_\mathrm{Al}$. We then use the local trigonal crystal-field symmetry to classify the Er-derived impurity levels by irreducible representations and to derive polarization-resolved electric-dipole selection rules, explicitly identifying the symmetry-allowed $f$\textendash$d$ hybridization channels. Kubo--Greenwood absorption spectra computed from Kohn--Sham states quantitatively corroborate these symmetry predictions. Furthermore, we connect the calculated intra-$4f$ line strengths to Judd--Ofelt theory, clarifying the role of $4f$\textendash$5d$ admixture in enabling optical activity. Notably, we predict a characteristic absorption near $1.47~\mu\mathrm{m}$ (telecom band), relevant for on-chip amplification and emission. To our knowledge, a symmetry-resolved first-principles treatment of Er:Al$_2$O$_3$ with an explicit Judd--Ofelt interpretation has not been reported, providing a transferable framework for tailoring rare-earth dopants in wide-band-gap oxides for integrated photonics. Our results for the optical spectra are in good agreement with experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18409v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahtab A. Khan, Jayden D. Craft, Hari P. Paudel, Yuhua Duan, Dirk R. Englund, Michael N. Leuenberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation via spin Seebeck effect of macroscopic magnetic transport from emergent magnetic monopoles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18422v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnetic monopoles, elusive in high-energy physics, have been realised as emergent quasiparticles in solid-state systems, where their unique properties hold promise for novel spintronic applications. Magnetic monopoles have been invoked in diverse platforms, including skyrmion lattices, chiral magnets, soft ferromagnets, aritifical nanomagnets. Yet, a demonstration of their role in magnetic transport has remained elusive. Here, we report such an observation via the spin Seebeck effect in the bulk insulating pyrochlore oxide, spin ice $\mathrm{Dy_2Ti_2O_7}$. By applying a thermal gradient perpendicular to a $[111]$-oriented magnetic field, we detect a transverse spin Seebeck voltage marked by a dominant peak at the onset of monopole proliferation, accompanied by a secondary feature and frequency-dependent behavior. Our findings establish a direct link between monopole dynamics and magnetic transport in an insulating medium, establishing a new pathway for probing fractionalized excitations and advancing towards novel spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18422v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nan Tang, Stephan Glamsch, Aisha Aqeel, Ludwig Scheuchenpflug, Michael Schulze, Christoph Liebald, Daniel Rytz, Christo Guguschev, Manfred Albrecht, Philipp Gegenwart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Overcoming limitations on gate fidelity in noisy static exchange-coupled surface qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18737v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent experiments demonstrated that the spin state of individual atoms on surfaces can be quantum-coherently controlled through all-electric electron spin resonance. By constructing interacting arrays of atoms this results in an atomic-scale qubit platform. However, the static exchange coupling between qubits, limited lifetime and polarization of the initial state, impose significant limits on high-fidelity quantum control. We address this issue using open quantum systems simulation and quantum optimal control theory. We demonstrate the conditions under which high-fidelity operations ($\mathcal{F} \gtrsim 0.9$) are feasible in this qubit platform, and show how the Krotov method of quantum optimal control theory adapts to specific noise sources to outperform the conventional Rabi drivings. Finally, we re-examine the experimental setup used in the initial demonstration of this qubit platform and propose optimized experimental designs to maximize gate fidelity in this platform.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18737v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hoang-Anh Le, Saba Taherpour, Denis Jankovi\'c, Christoph Wolf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signature of chiral superconducting order parameter evidenced in mesoscopic superconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18781v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Chiral superconductivity is a novel superconducting phase characterized by order parameters that break the time-reversal symmetry, endowing the state with a definite handedness. Unlike conventional superconductors, the Cooper pairs in a chiral superconductor carry nonzero orbital angular momentum. Through coupling with an external magnetic field, the finite angular momentum of the Cooper pair modulates the temperature-magnetic field phase boundary in a distinctive way, which could serve as an experimental signature of the chiral superconducting state. Here we demonstrate that the chiral signature can be detected in mesoscopic superconducting rings of $\beta$-Bi$_2$Pd, manifesting as a linear-in-field modulation of the critical temperature in the Little-Parks effect. Our findings establish a new experimental method for detecting the chiral superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18781v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoying Xu, Wei Qin, Yuelin Shen, Zixuan Huang, Zhuoya Zhou, Zirao Wang, Yufan Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soft X-ray Ptychography with SOPHIE: Guide and Instrumentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18805v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Soft X-ray ptychography is becoming a key synchrotron microscopy technique in the fields of condensed matter physics, chemistry, environmental and life sciences. Its attractiveness across broad disciplinary fields is owed to the favorable combination of high spatial resolution and strong contrast mechanisms. The SOft X-ray Ptychography Highly Integrated Endstation (SOPHIE) at the Swiss Light Source (SLS) was developed to accommodate soft X-ray ptychography experiments requiring high spatial resolution, in addition to high chemical and ferroic sensitivities. An introduction to soft X-ray ptychography with SOPHIE aimed at prospective users is provided. Furthermore, an overview of the instrumentation of SOPHIE is given along with an example of the imaging capabilities, which demonstrate the achievement of a sub-5 nm spatial resolution at a photon energy of 706 eV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18805v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim A. Butcher, Simone Finizio, Lars Heller, Nicholas W. Phillips, Blagoj Sarafimov, Carlos A. F. Vaz, Armin Kleibert, Benjamin Watts, Mirko Holler, J\"org Raabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-electrodynamical time-dependent density functional theory description of molecules in optical cavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19036v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A quantum electrodynamical time-dependent density functional theory framework is applied to describe strongly coupled light--matter interactions in cavity environments. The formalism utilizes a tensor product approach, coupling real-space electronic wave functions with Fock space photonic states. Various molecular systems serve as test cases to examine how coupling parameters and cavity frequencies affect molecular geometry, polaritonic spectra, and intermolecular binding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19036v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yetmgeta Aklilu, Matthew Shepherd, Cody L. Covington, Kalman Varga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First principles band structure of interacting phosphorus and boron/aluminum $\delta$-doped layers in silicon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19205v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Silicon can be heavily doped with phosphorus in a single atomic layer (a $\delta$ layer), significantly altering the electronic structure of the conduction bands within the material. Recent progress has also made it possible to further dope silicon with acceptor-based $\delta$ layers using either boron or aluminum, making it feasible to create devices with interacting $\delta$ layers with opposite polarity. It is not known, however, how these $\delta$ layers will interact, particularly at small separation distances. Using Density Functional Theory, we calculate the electronic structure of a phosphorus-based $\delta$ layer interacting with a boron or aluminum $\delta$ layer, varying the distances between the $\delta$ layers. At separations 10 \AA\ and smaller, the dopant potentials overlap and largely cancel each other out, leading to an electronic structure closely mimicking bulk silicon. At separations greater than 10 \AA, the two layers behave independently of one another, forming a p-n diode with an intrinsic layer taking the place of the depletion region. One mechanism for charge transfer between $\delta$ layers at larger distances could be tunneling, where we see a greater than 3\% probability for tunneling between a phosphorus and boron layer at 20 \AA\ separation. This tunneling rate exceeds what would be seen for a standard silicon 1.1 eV triangular barrier, indicating that the interaction between delta layers creates enhanced tunneling at larger separation distances compared to a traditional junction. These calculations provide a foundation for the design of silicon-based electronics based on interacting $\delta$ layers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19205v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quinn T. Campbell, Andrew D. Baczewski, Shashank Misra, Evan M. Anderson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-equilibrium Dynamics of Two-level Systems directly after Cryogenic Alternating Bias</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19223v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two-level systems (TLSs) are tunneling states commonly found in amorphous materials that electrically couple to qubits, resonators, and vibrational modes in materials, leading to energy loss in those systems. Recent studies suggest that applying a large alternating electric field changes the oxide structure, potentially improving the performance of qubits and resonators. In this study, we probe the effect of alternating bias at cryogenic temperatures on TLS dynamics within amorphous oxide parallel-plate capacitors operating in the strongly coupled regime. We bias the TLSs in the capacitors using an electric field. This allows us to spectroscopically image TLSs and extract their densities and dipole moments. When an in-situ alternating bias is applied, the steady-state spectra from the standard TLS model disappear. Post-alternating bias TLS spectroscopy reveals transient behavior, in which the TLS frequency fluctuates on the order of minutes. Thermal cycling above 10 K reverses these effects, restoring the TLS spectrum to its original state, indicating a reversible mechanism. Importantly, the intrinsic loss tangent of the LC oscillator remains unchanged before and after the application of the alternating bias. We propose that the disappearance of the steady-state spectrum are caused by non-equilibrium energy build up from strain in the oxide film introduced by the pulsed voltage bias sequence. Understanding this non-equilibrium energy could inform future models of time-dependent TLS dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19223v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Iaia, E. S. Joseph, S. Im, N. Hagopian, S. O'Kelley, C. Kim, N. Materise, S. Patra, V. Lordi, M. A. Eriksson, P. M. Voyles, K. G. Ray, Y. J. Rosen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Domain Wall Networks as Skyrmion Crystals in Chiral Magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04007</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04007v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the ground states of a chiral magnet with a square anisotropy and show that it supports domain wall networks as stable ground states. A domain wall junction in the domain wall network turns out to be a skyrmion with half topological charge and, therefore, the found domain wall network has a second topological nature, a skyrmion crystal. More specifically, we present a ground-state phase diagram of the chiral magnet with varying anisotropy parameters consisting of skyrmion lattices, chiral soliton lattices, and ferromagnetic states. In the presence of the square anisotropy, the skyrmion crystal forms a domain wall network. The size of domains in the domain wall network is shown to be tunable by an external magnetic field, offering a way to realize experimentally detectable domain wall networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04007v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/6j6b-sfjh</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 064422 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Seungho Lee, Toshiaki Fujimori, Muneto Nitta, Se Kwon Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Weyl-like points in periodically modulated systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04352v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate a three-dimensional (3D) topological phase resembling a Weyl semimetal, modulated by a periodic potential and engineered through Floquet dynamics. This system is constructed by stacking two-dimensional Chern insulators and hosts Weyl-like points defined in the parameter space $(k_x, k_y, z)$, distinct from conventional Weyl points in momentum space $(k_x, k_y, k_z)$. The Weyl-semimetal-like phase exhibits characteristics akin to those of Weyl semimetals, including linear dispersion near the Weyl-like points, nontrivial bulk topology, the presence of Fermi arcs connecting the Weyl-like points, and the Berry monopoles. Unlike traditional Weyl semimetals, these features manifest in real space rather than momentum space. Furthermore, we calculate the local density of states, the layer Hall conductance, and the total 3D Hall conductivity, demonstrating that the Weyl-semimetal-like phase remains stable under weak and moderate interlayer couplings. The influence of disorder is also examined: Beyond a critical disorder strength, the Weyl-like points destabilize and the topological phase collapses. Moreover, by computing the Floquet Chern number, we demonstrate that the locations of the Weyl-like points can be tuned via high-frequency laser pumping. Finally, we show that both type-I and II Weyl-like behaviors can arise in a tilted Weyl-like model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04352v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/g25n-phmj</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 115432 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fang Qin, Rui Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermoelectric energy conversion in molecular junctions out of equilibrium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.06129v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding time-resolved quantum transport is crucial for developing next-generation quantum technologies, particularly in nano- and molecular junctions subjected to time-dependent perturbations. Traditional steady-state approaches to quantum transport are not designed to capture the transient dynamics necessary for controlling electronic behavior at ultrafast time scales. In this work, we present a non-equilibrium Green's function formalism, within the recently-developed iterated generalized Kadanoff-Baym ansatz ($i$GKBA), to study thermoelectric quantum transport beyond the wide-band limit approximation (WBLA). We employ the Meir-Wingreen formula for both charge and energy currents and analyze the transition from Lorentzian line-width functions to the WBLA, identifying unphysical divergences in the latter. Our results highlight the importance of finite-bandwidth effects and demonstrate the efficiency of the $i$GKBA approach in modeling time-resolved thermoelectric transport, also providing benchmark comparisons against the full Kadanoff-Baym theory. We exemplify the developed theory in the calculation of time-resolved thermopower and thermoelectric energy conversion efficiency in a cyclobutadiene molecular junction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.06129v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Tuovinen, Y. Pavlyukh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced thermoelectric effects in a driven one-dimensional system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.22329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.22329v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the thermoelectric properties of a one-dimensional quantum system in the presence of an external driving. We employ Floquet scattering theory to calculate linear-response stationary thermoelectric figures of merit in a single-channel conductor subjected to a periodically varying delta-like potential barrier. We also include a step barrier in one of the leads as a model of a nanoscale inhomogeneous semiconducting system. In the absence of a step barrier, we found that external driving can significantly enhance the Seebeck coefficient, particularly at low temperatures, with a relative increase of up to 200% at high frequencies compared to the static case. In the presence of a step barrier, we found that the thermoelectric Onsager coefficient for the driven case is also enhanced compared to the static case, with a significant photon-assisted effect at low temperatures when the chemical potential is within the semiconductor's gap. Our results demonstrate that external driving can be used to tune and enhance the thermoelectric capabilities of low-electron-density nanodevices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.22329v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. X. Zhang, Alessandro Braggio, Alessandro Romito, Fabio Taddei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of electron-electron interactions in $M$-valley twisted transition metal dichalcogenides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.14283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.14283v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the role of long-range Coulomb interactions in $M$-valley moir\'es using the self-consistent Hartree-Fock approximation. This platform was recently proposed [Nature 643, 376 (2025) and arXiv:2411.18828 (2024)] as a new class of experimentally realizable moir\'e materials using twisted transition metal dichalcogenides homobilayers with the 1T structure. While these seminal studies considered the noninteracting theory without an electric displacement field, this work shows that both electron-electron interactions at finite doping and an interlayer bias strongly modify the moir\'e bands. For small twists ($\lesssim 5^\circ$) the density of states versus filling and interlayer bias displays qualitatively different behavior for twisting near aligned ($0^\circ$) and antialigned ($60^\circ$) stacking with tunable Van Hove singularities (VHSs). Moreover, interactions pin the VHS to the Fermi energy over a finite range of doping both at zero and finite bias depending on the stacking type, an effect known to enhance both superconductivity and strongly correlated states. At half filling, we obtain the phase diagram as a function of interaction strength, interlayer bias, and twist angle. We find a competition driven by band mixing between an isotropic ferromagnet and an antiferromagnet that are nearly degenerate over a wide range of experimentally accessible parameters. Our work demonstrates that correlated states in $M$-valley 1T tTMDs can be strongly tuned in situ both by applying an electric displacement field and by electron doping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.14283v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christophe De Beule, Liangtao Peng, E. J. Mele, Shaffique Adam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transitioning from Silicon to Carbon Nanotube based transistors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.00947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.00947v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Carbon Nanotubes have shown to be an attractive option in the race to find a replacement to silicon-based transistors, due to its high electrical conductivity, extraordinary mechanical strength, and thermal conductivity. However, challenges with regards to controlling the purity and chirality of CNTs have raised doubts if the mass production of these transistors are even viable. This paper explores the challenges of scalability and proposes methods such as Liquid and Gas phase oxidative methods and microwave heating to tackle the problem of metal impurities found within CNTs and the methods of Catalyst Engineering and Chemical Vapor Deposition to control the chirality of CNTs. It also suggests techniques such as Lithography, Screen Printing and Stack Engineering to facilitate the large-scale production of CNT transistors. This paper also attempts to explore the methods of Laser Ablation and Arc Discharge that allows for the synthesis of CNTs of pure quality and high yield further facilitating the rise of mass production of CNT transistors. The feasibility and challenges relating to the integration of CNT transistors with already pre-existing circuitry was also investigated and the methods of annealing and potassium doping were studied and analyzed. The main aim of this paper is providing a comprehensive guide to allow for the mass production and rapid integration of CNT transistors into the semi-conductor market.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.00947v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suhas Suresh Bharadwaj, Reuben Thomas Thovelil, Rohith Chembattammal, Sradha Mishra, Sunit Sahoo, Himnish Dave, Karthik S., Kabir Jaisinghani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic solution and thermodynamic properties of graphene in the presence of minimal length</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.12793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.12793v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Graphene is a zero-gap semiconductor, where the electrons propagating inside are described by the ultra-relativistic Dirac equation normally reserved for very high energy massless particles. In this work, we show that graphene under a magnetic field in the presence of a minimal length has a hidden $su(1,1)$ symmetry. This symmetry allows us to construct the spectrum algebraically. In fact, a generalized uncertainty relation, leading to a non-zero minimum uncertainty on the position, would be closer to physical reality and allow us to control or create bound states in graphene. Using the partition function based on the Epstein zeta function, the thermodynamic properties are well determined. We find that the Dulong-Petit law is verified and the heat capacity is independent of the deformation parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.12793v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5488/CMP.28.33601</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Condensed Matter Physics, 2025, Vol. 28, No. 3, 33601</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>J. Gb\`etoho, F. A. Dossa, G. Y. H. Avossevou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-tronics: from temporal printed circuit board to quantum computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06387v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Time crystalline structures can be created in periodically driven systems. They are temporal lattices which can reveal different condensed matter behaviours ranging from Anderson localization in time to temporal analogues of many-body localization or topological insulators. However, the potential practical applications of time crystalline structures have yet to be explored. Here, we pave the way for time-tronics where temporal lattices are like printed circuit boards for realization of a broad range of quantum devices. The elements of these devices can correspond to structures of dimensions higher than three and can be arbitrarily connected and reconfigured at any moment. Moreover, our approach allows for the construction of a quantum computer, enabling quantum gate operations for all possible pairs of qubits. Our findings indicate that the limitations faced in building devices using conventional spatial crystals can be overcome by adopting crystalline structures in time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06387v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krzysztof Giergiel, Peter Hannaford, Krzysztof Sacha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal response of the Nieh-Yan term</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18592v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We reinterpret the Nieh-Yan (NY) anomaly using holography, finding that the U(1) axial symmetry remains unbroken and the axial current coupling to an external gauge field is conserved. Instead, the anomaly arises from a breakdown of Hodge duality relations between fermion bilinears due to symmetry constraints on one-form currents. We show that the axial response associated with the NY term is distinct from the chiral vortical effect and exhibits a characteristic $T^2$ dependence. Torsion-induced axial transport decouples spin and axial charge dynamics, thereby clarifying the physical significance of the NY anomaly and motivating further field-theoretic and holographic studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18592v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/kcdm-vvzv</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Hoyos, Niko Jokela, Jos\'e Manuel Penin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid optimal work extraction from a quantum-dot information engine</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06916v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The conversion of thermal energy into work is usually more efficient in the slow-driving regime, where the power output is vanishingly small. Efficient work extraction for fast driving protocols remains an outstanding challenge at the nanoscale, where fluctuations play a significant role. In this Letter, we use a quantum-dot Szilard engine to extract work from thermal fluctuations with maximum efficiency over two decades of driving speed. We design and implement a family of optimised protocols ranging from the slow- to the fast-driving regime, and measure the engine's efficiency as well as the mean and variance of its power output in each case. These optimised protocols exhibit significant improvements in power and efficiency compared to the naive approach. Our results also show that, when optimising for efficiency, boosting the power output of a Szilard engine inevitably comes at the cost of increased power fluctuations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06916v4</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/q3dx-kyqj</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kushagra Aggarwal, Alberto Rolandi, Yikai Yang, Joseph Hickie, Daniel Jirovec, Andrea Ballabio, Daniel Chrastina, Giovanni Isella, Mark T. Mitchison, Mart\'i Perarnau-Llobet, Natalia Ares</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral properties of disordered insulating lattice under nonlinear electric field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09539v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quenched disorder in a solid state system can result in Anderson localization, where electrons are exponentially localized and the system behaves like an insulator. By solving exactly a disordered electronic lattice model out of equilibrium, we investigate the effect of a DC electric field on Anderson localization in an open system, and provide a minimal platform to study disorder-nonequilibrium interplay in electronic lattice systems. We perform steady-state Keldysh Green's function calculations on an infinite lattice with a finite-range of disorder-active region that are coupled to fermion reservoirs. Our solutions out of a fully electronic model verify Mott's temperature scaling of the variable-range-hopping transport and the Lifshitz tail, well-corroborated by the coherent-potential approximation. We further reveal that a nonequilibrium electronic lattice creates a statistical evolution that shows a counterintuitive shift of the distribution edge in the opposite direction of the band edge. The rich evolution of non-thermal statistics highlights the importance of an explicit band structure and the impurity correlations in strong nonequilibrium theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09539v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/85cy-7rpc</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kunal Mozumdar (University at Buffalo, SUNY, Buffalo, NY), Herbert F. Fotso (University at Buffalo, SUNY, Buffalo, NY), Jong E. Han (University at Buffalo, SUNY, Buffalo, NY)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron transport in disordered insulating lattice under nonlinear electric field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17628v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Transport in disordered systems often occurs via the variable range hopping (VRH) in the dilute carrier density limit, where electrons hop between randomly distributed localized levels. We study the nonequilibrium transport by a uniform DC electric field on a one-dimensional insulating tight-binding chain with the on-site disorder, using a disordered-lattice calculation and the coherent potential approximation. We develop a theory of electric-field-assisted variable range hopping as a mechanism for nonlinear transport in a disordered chain. Our disordered-lattice calculations of the electron propagation distance and the electron mobility determine the range of the variable range hopping as $\Delta &lt; W \lesssim 2\Delta$ in the gap $\Delta$. We further propose a nonlinear scaling of the conductivity by an electric field by extending Mott's variable range hopping. The nonlinear conductivity of an electronic lattice model follows the scaling law $\sigma(E) \propto \exp[-(E_0/E)^{\nu}]$ with the exponent $\nu = 1/3$ in one dimension for the VRH. We also discuss the experimental relevance of temperature-dependent nonlinear current-voltage relation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17628v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/sh3p-vk6l</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kunal Mozumdar, Herbert F. Fotso, Jong E. Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ex Situ Fabrication of Superconducting Nanostructures for Low-Temperature STM</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14092v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nanofabrication of topological insulator (TI) devices is essential for accessing edge and interface states, but conventional lithography and etching compromise the atomically clean surfaces required for scanning tunneling microscopy and spectroscopy (STM/STS). We demonstrate a fabrication strategy that combines ex situ lithographic patterning with in situ ultrahigh-vacuum cleaving and flipping, yielding atomically clean, nanopatterned TI-superconductor heterostructures suitable for STM/STS. In Design I, nanoribbons were defined by etching trenches into a TI film and capping with Nb. This enabled spectroscopy on large areas, although edge quality was limited by etch debris. In Design II, local thinning defined buried nanoribbons within a continuous TI film, producing pristine planar surfaces. STM/STS revealed well-developed superconducting gaps in the surrounding film, with suppressed gaps on the nanoribbons, consistent with vertical proximity coupling. This approach establishes a reproducible pathway for high-resolution STM/STS studies of proximitized nanostructures, providing a scalable platform for exploring topological superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14092v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Greichgauer, Roozbeh Yazdanpanah, Alexey Taskin, Oliver Breunig, Yoichi Ando, Jens Brede</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Finite-Time Thermodynamics of Effective Two-Level Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.19341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.19341v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The optimization of the conversion of thermal energy into work and the minimization of dissipation for nano- and mesoscopic systems is a complex challenge because of the important role fluctuations play on the dynamics of small systems. We generalize the work of Esposito et al. EPL 89, 20003 (2010) to optimize at all driving speeds the control needed to extract the maximum amount of work from any effective two-level systems. These emerge when one coarse-grains degrees of freedom, which is often unavoidable to obtain "real-world" two-level systems. In particular, we allow even for the system to have underlying quantum dynamics, as long as these allow for a coarse-graining that leads to a Markovian master equation. We analyze the finite-time thermodynamics of these systems and find the thermodynamically optimal protocols, which depend on the size of the coarse-graining needed to obtain a two-level system. Furthermore, we use these results to derive speed-limits for any transformation performed on an effective two-level system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.19341v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Rolandi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Tomography of Suspended Carbon Nanotubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.01858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.01858v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present an all-mechanical protocol for coherent control and full quantum-state reconstruction of the fundamental flexural mode of a suspended carbon nanotube (CNT). Calibrated impulses from a nearby atomic force microscope (AFM) tip serve a dual role: they implement mechanical pi/2 rotations for Ramsey interferometry and realize phase-space displacements for Wigner function tomography via displaced-parity sampling. The same actuator thus unifies control and tomography while avoiding optical heating and eliminating on-chip microwave drive lines at the resonator. We derive explicit control pulse sequences and a master-equation description that map measured signals onto the energy-relaxation and phase-coherence times, as well as onto parity-based quantum signatures, including negative regions of the Wigner function. The approach is compatible with several readout modalities: direct AFM deflection, dispersive coupling to a Cooper-pair box, and dispersive microwave cavity probing. Together, these techniques provide complete access to populations, coherence, and parity within a single device architecture. This minimal scheme provides a practical route to all-mechanical quantum control and state-resolved characterization of decoherence in mesoscopic mechanical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.01858v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jialiang Chang, Nicholas Pietrzak, Cristian Staii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A scalable method for cavity-enhanced solid-state quantum sensors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04760</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04760v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Photoluminescent color centers in diamond and hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) are powerful nanoscale solid-state quantum sensors that are explored in a plethora of quantum technologies. Methods for integrating them into macroscopic structures that improve their sensitivity and enable their large-scale deployment are highly sought after. Here, we demonstrate cavity-enhanced photoluminescence (PL) of fluorescent nanodiamonds (FNDs) and hBN nanoparticles (NPs) embedded in polymer-based thin-film optical cavities on the centimeter scale. The cavity resonances efficiently modulate the spectral PL peak position of nitrogen-vacancy (NV) centers in FNDs across the NV PL spectrum and lead to an up to 2.9-fold Purcell-enhancement of the NV PL decay rate. The brightness of hBN NPs increases by up to a factor of three and the PL decay rate is enhanced by up to 13-fold inside the cavities. Finally, we find a 4.8 times improved magnetic field sensitivity of 20 nm FNDs in thin-film cavities due to cavity-enhanced optically detected magnetic resonance contrast and PL brightness. Our study demonstrates a low-cost and scalable method for the fabrication of quantum sensor-doped thin-film cavities, which is an important step toward the development of advanced quantum sensing technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04760v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel J. Tibben, Roy Styles, David A. Broadway, Jean-Philippe Tetienne, Daniel E. G\'omez, Philipp Reineck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giant Splitting of Folded Dirac Bands in Kekul\'{e}-ordered Graphene with Eu Intercalation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05633v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Kekul\'{e}-ordered graphene on SiC realized by intercalating two-dimensional metal layers offers a versatile platform for exploring intriguing quantum states and phenomena. Here, we achieve the intercalation of $(\mathrm{\sqrt{3}\times\sqrt{3}})\mathit{R}30^\circ$-ordered Eu layer between epitaxial graphene and SiC substrate, realizing a Kekul\'{e} graphene with large local magnetic moments of intercalated Eu atoms. Combining angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) and density functional theory (DFT) calculations, we revealed that the Kekul{\'{e}} order folds the Dirac cones of graphene from the corners to the Brillouin zone center via intervalley scattering, forming the replica Dirac bands with gap opening. More intriguingly, the Dirac fermions in the replica Dirac bands show a strong exchange coupling with the localized magnetic moments of Eu $4f$ orbitals, resulting in a giant splitting of the folded Dirac bands. The observation of strong coupling between Dirac fermions and local magnetic moments of Eu $4f$ electrons via Kekul\'{e} order pave a new way for generating Dirac band splitting in graphene, advancing the potential applications of Kekul\'{e}-ordered graphene in spintronics, as well as exploring intriguing physical properties and correlation states for quantum technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05633v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaodong Qiu, Tongshuai Zhu, Zhenjie Fan, Kaili Wang, Yuyang Mu, Bin Yang, Di Wu, Haijun Zhang, Can Wang, Huaiqiang Wang, Yi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
