<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 02:55:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Preserving Twist-Angle in Marginally Twisted Double-Bilayer Graphene Devices During Fabrication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Twisted van der Waals heterostructures provide a platform for studying a wide range of electron correlation phenomena, including unconventional superconductivity and correlated insulating states. However, fabricating such devices is challenging due to the difficulty in achieving and maintaining homogeneous twist-angles. Here, we present a fabrication method to preserve the twist-angle with minimal deformation. We fabricated marginally twisted double-bilayer graphene (mTDBG) stacks and directly imaged the resulting triangular superlattice periodicity via scattering-type scanning near-field optical microscopy (s-SNOM). This technique enabled us to monitor twist-angle deformation at each fabrication step, paving the way for more reliable device fabrication and facilitating the exploration of twist-angle-dependent physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05527v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyeon-Woo Jeong, Jiho Kim, Boknam Chae, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Gil-Ho Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum kinetic theory of semiclassical Boltzmann equation with side jump and skew scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05544v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The semiclassical Boltzmann equation is widely used to study transport effects. It is usually introduced in an intuitive fashion, which could cause confusion, e.g., over the collision integral with skew scattering. Actually, the Boltzmann equation is closely linked to the quantum density matrix, although term-by-term correspondence between the two is yet to be established. Here we start from the quantum Liouville equation in the interactive picture and show that the diagonal components of the equation yield the Boltzmann equation in homogeneous systems in an applied uniform electric field in the semiclassical limit, while the off-diagonal components give the anomalous velocity induced by Berry curvature and the side-jump velocity. The skew-scattering contribution is obtained when we include corrections beyond the first-Born approximation. The result derived from the denstiy matrix agrees with the semiclassical one from wave-packet analysis, showing that the semiclassical Boltzmann equation is more than an equation built from intuition, and it can be derived with the density matrix. Our work further clarifies the origin of the equation and eliminates the puzzles surrounding it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05544v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Da Ma, Zhi-Fan Zhang, Hua Jiang, X. C. Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engineered Chirality of One-Dimensional Nanowires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05671v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The origin and function of chirality in DNA, proteins, and other building blocks of life represent a central question in biology. Observations of spin polarization and magnetization associated with electron transport through chiral molecules, known collectively as the chiral induced spin selectivity (CISS) effect, suggest that chirality improves electron transfer by inhibiting backscattering. Meanwhile, the role of coherence in the electron transport within chiral nanowires is believed to be important but is challenging to investigate experimentally. Using reconfigurable nanoscale control over conductivity at the LaAlO$_3$/SrTiO$_3$ interface, we create chiral electron potentials that explicitly lack mirror symmetry. Quantum transport measurements on these chiral regions that constitute effective nanowires for the electrons reveal oscillatory transmission resonances as a function of both magnetic field and chemical potential. We interpret these resonances as arising from an engineered axial spin-orbit interaction within the chiral region. The ability to create 1D effective electron waveguides with this specificity and complexity creates new opportunities to test, via analog quantum simulation, theories about the relationship between chirality and spin-polarized electron transport in one-dimensional geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05671v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Megan Briggeman, Elliott Mansfield, Johannes Kombe, Fran\c{c}ois Damanet, Hyungwoo Lee, Yuhe Tang, Muqing Yu, Sayanwita Biswas, Jianan Li, Mengchen Huang, Chang-Beom Eom, Patrick Irvin, Andrew J. Daley, Jeremy Levy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulation study on Conservative Join (C-join) in Skyrmion Brownian circuit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05700v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetic skyrmions, which exhibit Brownian motion in solid-state systems, are promising candidates as signal carriers for Brownian computing. However, successfully implementing such systems requires two critical components: a Hub to connect multiple wires and a C-join to synchronize the skyrmion signal carriers. While the former has been successfully addressed, the latter remains a significant challenge. In this study, we propose a novel solution by decomposing the C-join into two sub-circuits, the Join and Fork, and validate their functionality using a particle simulation approach. Our results demonstrate that the C-join can effectively synchronize skyrmion signals within 6.8{\mu}s with a 99.9% success rate at low temperatures. Additionally, we construct the Half-adder in a crossing-free architecture utilizing the C-join circuits. These findings pave the way for the realization of skyrmion-based Brownian computing systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05700v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Imanishi, E. Tamura, S. Miki, R. Ishikawa, H. Nomura, M. Goto, Y. Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Importance of Pure Dephasing in the Optical Response of Excitons in High-quality van der Waals Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05885</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05885v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Excitons in monolayer transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) dominate their optical response due to exceptionally large binding energies arising from their two-dimensional nature. Several theoretical models have been proposed to describe this excitonic behavior, however, it remains unclear which model most accurately captures the underlying physical properties of the response. In this work, we experimentally measure the optical response of high-quality monolayer TMD heterostructures and compare the results with the different theoretical models to address this uncertainty. We find that in high-quality heterostructures, quantum mechanical interactions in the form of pure dephasing plays a dominant role, which has been challenging to isolate experimentally in previous studies. Furthermore, accounting for an additional decay rate to the commonly used radiative and non-radiative rates is found to be important for the accurate description of the excitonic response. These findings establish a robust framework for understanding and predicting the optical properties of TMD-based heterostructures, crucial for both fundamental research and optoelectronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05885v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anabel Atash Kahlon, Matan Meshulam, Tomer Eini, Thomas Poirier, James H. Edgar, Seth Ariel Tongay, Itai Epstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microwave-regime demonstration of plasmonic non-reciprocity in a flowing two-dimensional electron gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The speed of a plasmonic wave in the presence of electron drift in a conductor depends on the wave's propagation direction, with the wave traveling along the drift (`forward wave') faster than the wave traveling against the drift (`backward wave'). Phenomena related to this plasmonic non-reciprocity -- which is relatively more pronounced in two-dimensional conductors than in bulk conductors and could lead to solid-state device applications -- have been studied in THz and optical spectral regimes. Here we demonstrate the plasmonic non-reciprocity at microwave frequencies (10 $\sim$ 50 GHz). Concretely, we conduct, at 4K, a microwave network analysis on a gated GaAs two-dimensional electron gas with electron drift (i.e., DC current), directly measuring out forward and backward wave speeds via their propagation phase delays. We resolve, for example, forward and backward wave speeds of $4.26 \times 10^{-3} \pm 8.97 \times 10^{-6}$ (normalized to the speed of light). Sufficient consistency between the electron drift speed obtained from the microwave measurement and that alternatively estimated by a DC transport theory further confirms the non-reciprocity. We conclude this paper with a discussion on how to enhance the non-reciprocity for real-world applications, where degeneracy pressure would play an important role.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05904v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingyee Chee, Han Sae Jung, Shannon Harvey, Kenneth West, Loren Pfeiffer, Amir Yacoby, Donhee Ham</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Even denominator fractional quantum Hall states in the zeroth Landau level of monolayer-like band of ABA trilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06245v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The fractional quantum Hall (FQH) effect is a macroscopic manifestation of strong electron-electron interactions. Even denominator FQH states (FQHSs) at half-filling are particularly interesting as they are predicted to host non-Abelian excitations with non-trivial braiding statistics. Such states are predominantly observed in the $N=1$ Landau level (LL) of semiconductors such as GaAs. In this Letter, we report the unanticipated observation of even-denominator FQHSs in the $N=0$ LL of ABA trilayer graphene (TLG), a system characterized by tunable LL mixing and the absence of inversion symmetry. Notably, we find robust FQHSs at $\nu=5/2$ and $\nu=7/2$ when two LLs, originating from a monolayer-like band of TLG with different isospin indices, cross each other. These are flanked by the Levin-Halperin daughter states at $\nu=7/13$ and $\nu=9/17$, respectively, and further away, the standard series of Jain-sequence of composite fermions (CFs) is observed. The even-denominator FQHSs and their accompanying daughter states become stronger with increasing magnetic fields, while concomitantly, a weakening of the CF states is observed. We posit that the absence of inversion symmetry in the system gives rise to additional isospin interactions, which enhance LL mixing and soften the short-range part of the Coulomb repulsion, stabilizing the even-denominator FQHSs. In addition, we demonstrate that these states, along with their daughter states, can be finely tuned with an external displacement field that serves as an important tool to control the LL mixing in the system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06245v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tanima Chanda, Simrandeep Kaur, Harsimran Singh, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Manish Jain, Udit Khanna, Ajit C. Balram, Aveek Bid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transmission through rectangular potentials in semimetals featuring quadratic dispersion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06265v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We revisit the problem of transmission of quasiparticles through a rectangular potential barrier for semimetals featuring quadratic-in-momentum band-crossings at a nodal point. Although this was considered in Annals of Physics 419 (2020) 168235, the solutions corresponding to evanescent waves were missed, leading to a partial fulfillment of the boundary conditions required to determine the piecewise-continuous wavefunctions. In this paper, our aim is to correct those shortcomings, recompute the transmission coefficients, and show the resulting behaviour of the conductivity and the Fano factor for some representative parameter values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06265v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ipsita Mandal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brightening dark excitons and trions in systems with a Mexican-hat energy dispersion: example of InSe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06473v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the properties of momentum-dark excitons and trions formed in two-dimensional (2D) materials that exhibit an inverted Mexican-hat-shaped dispersion relation, taking monolayer InSe as an example. We employ variational techniques to obtain the momentum-dark and bright ground-states (non-zero and zero quasiparticle momenta, respectively). These states are of particular interest due to their peaks in the quasiparticle density of states, the largest contribution comes from the momentum-dark ground state due to the presence of a van Hove singularity (VHS). These momentum-dark systems require a physical process to provide the necessary momentum to become bright. We study the brightening of this state due to coupling with phonons and compute the resulting photoluminescence spectrum. This work opens new avenues of research, such as exploiting dark excitons in solar cells and other semiconductor-based optoelectronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06473v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lewis J. Burke, Mark T. Greenaway, Joseph J. Betouras</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable exciton polaritons in biased bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06640v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By harnessing the unique properties of bilayer graphene, we present a flexible platform for achieving electrically tunable exciton polaritons within a microcavity. Using a semiclassical approach, we solve Maxwell's equations within the cavity, approximating the optical conductivity of bilayer graphene through its excitonic response as described by the Elliott formula. Transitioning to a quantum mechanical framework, we diagonalize the Hamiltonian governing excitons and cavity photons, revealing the resulting polariton dispersions, Hopfield coefficients and Rabi splittings. Our analysis predicts that, under realistic exciton lifetimes, the exciton-photon interaction reaches the strong coupling regime. Furthermore, we explore the integration of an epsilon-near-zero material within the cavity, demonstrating that such a configuration can further enhance the light-matter interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06640v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.075411</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 075411 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>V. G. M. Duarte, P. Ninhos, C. Tserkezis, N. Asger Mortensen, N. M. R. Peres, A. J. Chaves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Persistent spin grids with spin-orbit coupled 2D electron gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06745v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the diffusive spin dynamics of a 2D electron gas with spin-orbit coupling confined within a grid of narrow channels. We show that the lifetime of certain spin distributions in such grids greatly exceeds that in an unconfined 2D electron gas and diverges as the channel width approaches zero. Such persistent spin grids occur if the electron spin orientation remains invariant after diffusion around the grid plaquette. We establish a topological $\mathbb{Z}_2$ classification for persistent spin grids and speculate that the setup can be used to simulate non-Abelian lattice gauge theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06745v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Poshakinskiy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visualization of topological shear polaritons in gypsum thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19242v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Low symmetry crystals have recently emerged as a platform for exploring novel light-matter interactions in the form of hyperbolic shear polaritons. These excitations exhibit unique optical properties such as frequency-dispersive optical axes and asymmetric light propagation and energy dissipation, which arise from the presence of non-orthogonal resonances. However, only non-vdW materials have been demonstrated to support hyperbolic shear polaritons, limiting their exotic properties and potential applications. Here we introduce for the first time novel shear phenomena in low symmetry crystal thin films by demonstrating the existence of elliptical and canalized shear phonon polaritons in gypsum, an exfoliable monoclinic sulphate mineral. Our results unveil a topological transition from hyperbolic shear to elliptical shear polaritons, passing through a canalization regime with strong field confinement. Importantly, we observe a significant slowdown of group velocity, reaching values as low as 0.0005c, highlighting the potential of gypsum for "slow light" applications and extreme light-matter interaction control. These findings expand the application scope of low-symmetry crystals with the benefits that an exfoliable material provides, such as stronger field confinement, tunability, and versatility for its incorporation in complex photonic devices that might unlock new optical phenomena at the nanoscale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19242v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo D\'iaz-N\'u\~nez, Christian Lanza, Ziwei Wang, Vasyl G. Kravets, Jiahua Duan, Jos\'e \'Alvarez-Cuervo, Aitana Tarazaga Mart\'in-Luengo, Alexander N. Grigorenko, Qian Yang, Alexander Paarmann, Joshua Caldwell, Pablo Alonso-Gonz\'alez, Artem Mishchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Transitions in Nonreciprocal Driven-Dissipative Condensates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05267v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the influence of boundaries and spatial nonreciprocity on nonequilibrium driven-dissipative phase transitions. We focus on a one-dimensional lattice of nonlinear bosons described by a Lindblad master equation, where the interplay between coherent and incoherent dynamics generates nonreciprocal interactions between sites. Using a mean-field approach, we analyze the phase diagram under both periodic and open boundary conditions. For periodic boundaries, the system always forms a condensate at nonzero momentum and frequency, resulting in a time-dependent traveling wave pattern. In contrast, open boundaries reveal a far richer phase diagram, featuring multiple static and dynamical phases, as well as exotic phase transitions, including the spontaneous breaking of particle-hole symmetry associated with a critical exceptional point and phases with distinct bulk and edge behavior. Our model avoids post-selection or unphysical non-Hermitian Hamiltonians and is experimentally realizable in platforms such as superconducting circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05267v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ron Belyansky, Cheyne Weis, Ryo Hanai, Peter B. Littlewood, Aashish A. Clerk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is attention all you need to solve the correlated electron problem?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05383v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The attention mechanism has transformed artificial intelligence research by its ability to learn relations between objects. In this work, we explore how a many-body wavefunction ansatz constructed from a large-parameter self-attention neural network can be used to solve the interacting electron problem in solids. By a systematic neural-network variational Monte Carlo study on a moir\'e quantum material, we demonstrate that the self-attention ansatz provides an accurate, efficient, and unbiased solution. Moreover, our numerical study finds that the required number of variational parameters scales roughly as $N^2$ with the number of electrons, which opens a path towards efficient large-scale simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05383v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Max Geier, Khachatur Nazaryan, Timothy Zaklama, Liang Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperparameter Optimization and Force Error Correction of Neuroevolution Potential for Predicting Thermal Conductivity of Wurtzite GaN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05580v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As a representative of wide-bandgap semiconductors, wurtzite gallium nitride (GaN) has been widely utilized in high-power devices due to high breakdown voltage and low specific on resistance. Accurate prediction of wurtzite GaN thermal conductivity is a prerequisite for designing effective thermal management systems of electronic applications. Machine learning driven molecular dynamics simulation offers a promising approach to predicting the thermal conductivity of large-scale systems without requiring predefined parameters. However, these methods often underestimate the thermal conductivity of materials with inherently high thermal conductivity due to the large predicted force error compared with first-principle calculation, posing a critical challenge for their broader application. In this study, we successfully developed a neuroevolution potential for wurtzite GaN and accurately predicted its thermal conductivity, 259 W/m-K at room temperatue, achieving excellent agreement with reported experimental measurements. The hyperparameters of neuroevolution potential (NEP) were optimized based on systematic analysis of reproduced energy and force, structural feature, computational efficiency. Furthermore, a force prediction error correction method was implemented, effectively reducing the error caused by the additional force noise in the Langevin thermostat by extrapolating to the zero-force error limit. This study provides valuable insights and hold significant implication for advancing efficient thermal management technologies in wide bandgap semiconductor devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05580v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuo Chen, Yuejin Yuan, Wenyang Ding, Shouhang Li, Meng An, Gang Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Softening of Vibrational Modes and Anharmonicity Induced Thermal Conductivity Reduction in a-Si:H at High Temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05584v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hydrogenated amorphous silicon (a-Si:H) has garnered considerable attention in the semiconductor industry, particularly for its use in solar cells and passivation layers for high performance silicon solar cells, owing to its exceptional photoelectric properties and scalable manufacturing processes. A comprehensive understanding of thermal transport mechanism in a-Si:H is essential for optimizing thermal management and ensuring the reliable operation of these devices. In this study, we developed a neuroevolution machine learning potential based on first-principles calculations of energy, forces, and virial, which enables accurate modeling of interatomic interactions in both a-Si:H and a-Si systems. Using the homogeneous nonequilibrium molecular dynamics (HNEMD) method, we systematically investigated the thermal conductivity of a-Si:H and a-Si across a temperature range of 300-1000 K and hydrogen concentrations ranging from 6 to 12 at%. Our simulation results found that thermal conductivity of a-Si:H with 12 at% hydrogen was significantly reduced by 12% compared to that of a-Si at 300 K. We analyzed the spectral thermal conductivity, vibrational density of states and lifetimes of vibrational modes, and revealed the softening of vibrational modes and anharmonicity effects contribute to the reduction of thermal conductivity as temperature and hydrogen concentration increase. Furthermore, the influence of hydrogen concentration and temperature on diffuson and propagon contribution to thermal conductivity of a-Si:H was revealed. This study provides valuable insights for developing thermal management strategies in silicon-based semiconducting devices and advances the understanding of thermal transport in amorphous systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05584v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuo Chen, Yuejin Yuan, Yanzhou Wang, Penghua Ying, Shouhang Li, Cheng Shao, Wenyang Ding, Gang Zhang, Meng An</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological doublon edge states induced by the spatially modulated interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05847v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The topological properties of the one-dimensional interacting systems with spatially modulated interaction in two-particle regime are theoretically investigated. Taking the boson-Hubbard model and spinless fermion interacting model as examples, we show that the energy spectra for doublon (known as two-particle pair) as a function of modulated period exhibit the butterfly-like structure for strongly-correlated limit, whose topological features can be decoded by the topological invariants and topological nontrivial doublon bound edge states. When the nearest-neighbor hopping evolves stronger, the doublon bands could intersect with scattering bands, the one-dimensional interacting systems display the phases of topological insulators and two-particle bound states in the continuum. For a sufficiently larger nearest-neighbor hopping, the doublon collapse takes place, where both the bulk doublon states and topological doublon edge states become unstable and could dissociate into two weakly interacting bosons. For the mapped two-dimensional single-particle systems, numerical calculations manifest the existence of the topological insulator and topological metal phases with corner states located in only one or two corners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05847v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng-Wei Zuo, Wanwan Shi, Haisheng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An exactly solvable tight-binding billiard in graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06092v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A triangular graphenic billiard is defined as a planar carbon polymer in the H\"uckeloid approximation of $\pi-$band electrons. It is shown that the equilateral triangle of arbitrary size and zig-zag edges allows for exact solutions of the associated spectral problem. This is done by a construction of wave superpositions similar to the Lam\'e solution of the Helmholtz equation in a triangular cavity, revisited by Pinsky. Exact wave functions, eigenvalues, degeneracies, and edge states are provided. The edge states are also obtained by a non-periodic construction of waves with vanishing energy. A comment on its connection with recent molecular models, such as triangulene, is given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06092v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Condado, E. Sadurn\'i</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinearity-induced Fractional Thouless Pumping of Solitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06131</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06131v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent studies have shown that a soliton can be {\it fractionally} transported by slowly varying a system parameter over one period in a nonlinear system. This phenomenon is attributed to the nontrivial topology of the corresponding energy bands of a linear Hamiltonian. Here we find the occurrence of fractional Thouless pumping of solitons in a nonlinear off-diagonal Aubry-Andr\'{e}-Harper model. Surprisingly, this happens despite the fact that all the energy bands of the linear Hamiltonian are topologically trivial, indicating that nonlinearity can induce fractional Thouless pumping of solitons. Specifically, our results show that a soliton can be pumped across one unit cell over one, two, three or four pump periods, implying an average displacement of $1$, $1/2$, $1/3$ or $1/4$ unit cells per cycle, respectively. We attribute these behaviors to changes in on-site potentials induced by a soliton solution, leading to the nontrivial topology for the modified linear Hamiltonian. Given that our model relies solely on varying nearest-neighbor hoppings, it is readily implementable on existing state-of-the-art photonic platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06131v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Liang Tao, Yongping Zhang, Yong Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dispersion of backward-propagating waves in a surface defect on a 3D photonic band gap crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06369v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We experimentally study the dispersion relation of waves in a two-dimensional (2D) defect layer with periodic nanopores that sits on a three-dimensional (3D) photonic band gap crystal made from silicon by CMOS-compatible methods. The nanostructures are probed by momentum-resolved broadband near-infrared imaging of p-polarized reflected light that is collected inside the light cone as a function of off-axis wave vectors. We identify surface defect modes at frequencies inside the band gap with a narrow relative linewidth ($\Delta\omega/\omega$ = 0.028), which are absent in defect-free 3D crystals. We calculate the dispersion of modes with relevant mode symmetries using a plane-wave-expansion supercell method with no free parameters. The calculated dispersion matches very well with the measured data. The dispersion is negative in one of the off-axis directions, corresponding to backward-propagating waves where the phase velocity and the group velocity point in opposite directions, as confirmed by finite-difference time-domain simulations. We also present an analytic model of a 2D grating sandwiched between vacuum and a negative real $\epsilon'$ &lt; 0 that mimics the 3D photonic band gap. The model's dispersion agrees with the experiments and with the fuller theory and shows that the backward propagation is caused by the surface grating. We discuss possible applications, including a device that senses the output direction of photons emitted by quantum emitters in response to their frequency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06369v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timon J. Vreman, Melissa J. Goodwin, Lars J. Corbijn van Willenswaard, William L. Barnes, Ad Lagendijk, Willem L. Vos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charging a Dimerized Quantum XY Chain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06503v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum batteries are quantum systems designed to store energy and release it on demand. The optimization of their performance is an intensively studied topic within the realm of quantum technologies. Such optimization forces the question: how do quantum many-body systems work as quantum batteries? To address this issue, we rely on symmetry and symmetry breaking via quantum phase transitions. Specifically, we analyze a dimerized quantum XY chain in a transverse field as a prototype of an energy storage device. This model, which is characterized by ground states with different symmetries depending on the Hamiltonian parameters, can be mapped onto a spinless fermionic chain with superconducting correlations, displaying a rich quantum phase diagram. We show that the stored energy strongly depends on the quantum phase diagram of the model when large charging times are considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06503v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/sym17020220</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Symmetry 2025, 17(2), 220</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Riccardo Grazi, Fabio Cavaliere, Niccol\`o Traverso Ziani, Dario Ferraro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-bound states in the continuum in finite waveguide grating couplers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06524v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Finite-size effects occurring for quasi-bound states in the continuum (qBIC) formed in symmetric and asymmetric all-dielectric waveguide grating couplers are investigated using numerical simulations for different configuration parameters. We find that the beam size plays a crucial role in the formation of additional qBIC resonances originating in forbidden for plane-wave incidence BIC resonances, whose manifestation is strongly influenced by the beam divergence. Another parameter is the strength of Bragg reflection, determining the spatial extension of a distributed Bragg resonator (DBR): in configurations with strong Bragg reflection, the excited and Bragg reflected counterpropagating waveguide modes are confined within the footprint of the incident beam. Conversely, the DBR formed in configurations with weak Bragg reflection extends well beyond the incident beam footprint, resulting in high sensitivity of the system response to the grating width and incident beam position. We believe that our findings provide valuable insights for optimizing photonic devices that leverage qBIC resonances in finite-sized structures under realistic excitation conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06524v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Torgom Yezekyan, Roza Gabrielyan, Sergey I. Bozhevolnyi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compact Quantum Dot Models for Analog Microwave co-Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.06690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.06690v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Scalable solid-state quantum computers will require integration with analog and digital electronics. Efficiently simulating the quantum-classical electronic interface is hence of paramount importance. Here, we present Verilog-A compact models with a focus on quantum-dot-based systems, relevant to semiconductor- and Majorana-based quantum computing. Our models are capable of faithfully reproducing coherent quantum behavior within a standard electronic circuit simulator, enabling compromise-free co-simulation of hybrid quantum devices. In particular, we present results from co-simulations performed in Cadence Spectre, showcasing coherent quantum phenomena in circuits with both quantum and classical components using an industry-standard electronic design and automation tool. Our work paves the way for a new paradigm in the design of quantum systems, which leverages the many decades of development of electronic computer-aided design and automation tools in the semiconductor industry to now simulate and optimize quantum processing units, quantum-classical interfaces, and hybrid quantum-analog circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.06690v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Peri, Alberto Gomez-Saiz, Christopher J. B. Ford, M. Fernando Gonzalez-Zalba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrical detection of interfacial exchange field at the (ferromagnetic insulator)|(normal metal) interface using spin-dependent scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.13855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.13855v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The spin-orbit field and interfacial exchange field are two major interface phenomena, and the detection and manipulation of these fields can enable a variety of nanoscale spintronics devices. Optimizing the interfacial exchange field, which governs the spin-dependent scattering asymmetry at (ferromagnetic insulator)-(normal metal) interfaces, will pave the way for next-generation nanoscale, low-power insulator spintronics devices. Here, we demonstrate an experimental pathway to detect an interfacial exchange field between insulating ferromagnet EuS and non-magnetic Cu using an all-electrical method, and show that the spin-dependent scattering at the common interface can lead to a significant current-in-plane magnetoresistance in Py|Cu|EuS trilayer Hall-bar devices. Our experiment suggests that simple measurements can be used to experimentally detect the interfacial exchange field and thereby the magnetic state of a ferromagnetic insulator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.13855v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prasanta Muduli, Na\"emi Leo, Mingran Xu, Zheng Zhu, Jorge Puebla, Christian Ortiz, Hironari Isshiki, YoshiChika Otani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graphene-like nanoribbons connected by four-/five- membered rings on pentacene/picene precursors, Au(110) surface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.10889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.10889v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The rapid development of fabrication of functional high-quality graphene-like nanoribbons has increasingly reliant on integration of diverse nanofabrication platforms. The demand for innovative techniques to enable the exploration and precise manipulation of graphene-like nanoribbons. Herein, we present an on-surface synthesis approach for graphene-like nanoribbons, achieved through the self-assembly and annealing of pentacene/picene monomers on an one-dimensional(1D) Au(110) substrate. Scanning tunneling microscope(STM) analysis reveals that the formation of four- and eight- membered rings between adjacent molecules. Furthermore, we demonstrate a technique for manipulating pentacene dimer without breaking structural integrity by STM tip manipulation. Our results exhibit a potential platform for the development of next-generation graphene-based quantum computing architectures, as well as a technique for fabricating functional graphene-like nanoribbons with exceptional precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.10889v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Yao, Yu Wang, Shuangxiang Wu, Qiang Zhang, Yifan Wang, Hui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-valley locked excited states spectroscopy in a one-particle bilayer graphene quantum dot</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12949v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Current semiconductor qubits rely either on the spin or on the charge degree of freedom to encode quantum information. By contrast, in bilayer graphene the valley degree of freedom, stemming from the crystal lattice symmetry, is a robust quantum number that can therefore be harnessed for this purpose. The simplest implementation of a valley qubit would rely on two states with opposite valleys as in the case of a single-carrier bilayer graphene quantum dot immersed in a small perpendicular magnetic field ($B_\perp\lesssim 100$mT). However, the single-carrier quantum dot excited states spectrum has not been resolved to date in the relevant magnetic field range. Here, we fill this gap, by measuring the parallel and perpendicular magnetic field dependence of this spectrum with an unprecedented resolution of $4\mu$eV. We use a time-resolved charge detection technique that gives us access to individual tunnel events. Our results come as a direct verification of the predicted spectrum and establish a new upper-bound on inter-valley mixing, equal to our energy resolution. Our charge detection technique opens the door to measuring the relaxation time of a valley qubit in a single-carrier bilayer graphene quantum dot.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12949v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-024-54121-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Communications 15, 9717 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hadrien Duprez, Solenn Cances, Andraz Omahen, Michele Masseroni, Max J. Ruckriegel, Christoph Adam, Chuyao Tong, Jonas Gerber, Rebekka Garreis, Wister Huang, Lisa G\"achter, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Thomas Ihn, Klaus Ensslin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrical control of a Kondo spin screening cloud</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11955v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantitative analysis of quantum many-body systems, consisting of numerous itinerant electrons that interact with localized spins or electrons, is a long-standing issue. The Kondo cloud, a quantum many-body object of conduction electrons that screens a single localized spin, is the building block of such strongly correlated electronic systems. While quantitative analysis of the Kondo cloud associated with a single magnetic impurity is well established for uniform conduction electrons, the fundamental properties of a deformed Kondo cloud influenced by conduction electrons with a modulated density of states remain unsolved. Here we report engineering of the Kondo cloud deformation by confining a part of the cloud into a quantum box called the Kondo box that mimics realistic material systems. We demonstrate quantitative control of the Kondo cloud by developing a way of tuning quantum interference in the box and monitoring the Kondo entanglement. The temperature dependence of the entanglement reveals counterintuitively that the cloud shape is altered mainly outside the box although the quantum interference in the box is tuned. Our work provides a way to simulate various strongly correlated systems by integrating the Kondo cloud, which is not possible in the current theoretical framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11955v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ngoc Han Tu, Donghoon Kim, Minsoo L. Kim, Jeongmin Shim, Ryo Ito, David Pomaranski, Ivan V. Borzenets, Arne Ludwig, Andreas D. Wieck, Heung-Sun Sim, Michihisa Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinguishing Majorana bound states from Andreev bound states through differential conductance and current noise spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.14193</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.14193v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the quantum transport through a quantum dot coupled with a superconducting (SC) nanowire. By elaborating the differential conductance and current noise spectrum, we focus on the distinct characteristics of the topological Majorana bound states (MBSs) and trivial Andereev bound states (ABSs) hosted in SC wire. For MBSs with a topological quality factor $q=1$, we observe the degenerate features manifested as the zero-bias peak (ZBP) in differential conductance and the Rabi dips degeneracy (RDD) in noise spectrum. In contrast, for ABSs with $q&lt;1$, the splitting of these degenerate features depends on the linewidth, arising from realistic measurement conditions. Furthermore, we identify the critical quality factors $q_{\rm c}$ and $q_{\rm s}$ associated with the emergences of ZBP and RDD, respectively. The value of $q_{\rm c}$ is temperature-dependent, and we establish a suitable temperature window to ensure the visibility of single ZBP in the experiments. Whereas, $q_{\rm c}$ depends on the coupling strength rather than the temperature. Typical values for these quality factors are approximately $q_{\rm c}\approx 0.93$ and $q_{\rm s}\approx 0.99$. Our results suggest that the degenerate Rabi spectrum signal could serve as a hallmark for the presence of MBSs, which goes beyond the scope of differential conductance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.14193v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1367-2630/ada9ab</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>New J. Phys. 27 (2025) 023006</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Huajin Zhao, Junrong Wang, Hong Mao, Jinshuang Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wannier center spectroscopy to identify boundary-obstructed topological insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14465v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The hallmark of topological crystalline insulators is the emergence of a robust electronic state in a bandgap localized at the boundary of the material. However, end, edge, and surface states can also have a non-topological origin. Unfortunately, topological invariants such as the winding number and Zak-phase are often not directly experimentally accessible for solids. In addition to topological invariants, the position of the Wannier centers provides a fingerprint for the topological character of a material. Here, we demonstrate a method to experimentally determine the location of Wannier centers in artificial lattices made of Cs/InAs(111)A by integrating the density of states. We determine the locations of the Wannier centers for various 1D chains, topological and trivial, and corroborate our findings with tight-binding simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14465v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. A. M. Ligthart, M. A. J. Herrera, A. Visser, A. Vlasblom, D. Bercioux, I. Swart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement Generation and Stabilization by Coherent Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16029v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Collision is a useful tool for revealing quantum effects and realizing quantum informational tasks. We demonstrate that repeated collisions by itinerant electrons can dissipatively drive two remote spin qubits into an entangled state in a generic collisional framework. A coherent spin exchange with either qubit facilitates entanglement generation. When combined with proper local driving, these collisions induce an entangled steady state in most collision configurations. Particularly, the collision which is symmetric for the two qubits results in a unique steady state close to a maximally entangled state. Due to the dissipative nature of the process, the entanglement persists in the presence of decoherence, provided the collision frequency exceeds the decoherence rate. Our model can be experimentally implemented using single-electron sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16029v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.7.013145</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 013145 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. Mert Bozkurt, Rosa L\'opez, Sungguen Ryu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting winding and Chern numbers in topological matter using spectral function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.20550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.20550v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a method to directly probe bulk topological quantum numbers in topological matter by measuring the momentum-space single-particle spectral function (SPSF). Angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) can detect SPSF and is often used to determine the bulk band structure of quantum materials. Here, we show that while one part of the momentum-space SPSF gives band structure, it also contains the knowledge of winding and Chern numbers of various topological materials. For this, we derive SPSF in different models of topological systems, such as the Kitaev model of topological superconductors, the long-range Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model, the Qi-Wu-Zhang model, the Haldane model on a hexagonal lattice and a four-band model that is a physical realization of the Kitaev chain and explain how to extract the winding or Chern numbers in different topological phases from the SPSF. Such information from SPSF seems experimentally accessible due to the recent advancement of ARPES and scanning tunneling spectroscopy techniques. While the detection of bulk topological quantum numbers using the SPSF works well for one-dimensional systems, it has certain limitations for higher-dimensional systems, where it must be complementary with another measurement to ensure the matter under investigation is topological, i.e., having a non-zero Chern number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.20550v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.085406</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 085406 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kiran Babasaheb Estake, Dibyendu Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Berry curvature and shift vector effects at high-order wave mixing in biased bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06269v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we present a microscopic quantum theory that elucidates the nonlinear and nonperturbative optical response of biased bilayer graphene subjected to bichromatic strong laser fields. This response is analyzed using a four-band Hamiltonian derived from \textit{ab initio} calculations. For the laser-stimulated dynamics, we employ structure gauge-invariant evolutionary equations to accurately describe the evolution of the single-particle density matrix across the entire Brillouin zone. The resonant generation of electron-hole pairs by the high-frequency component of the field, combined with the induction of high-order harmonic generation and high-order wave mixing by the strong low-frequency field component, leads to significant alterations in the resulting spectra. These changes are driven by the effects of Berry curvature and the shift vector, which modify the relative contributions of interband and intraband channels, thereby fundamentally reshaping the radiation spectra at high-order frequency multiplication. The numerical results are further supported by approximate analytical calculations, demonstrating that high-order wave mixing can be modeled using the classical trajectory analysis of electron-hole pairs, with Berry curvature and the shift vector significantly influencing the saddle-point equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06269v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.045415</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111 (2025) 045415</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>H. K. Avetissian, H. H. Matevosyan, G. F. Mkrtchian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transverse voltage in anisotropic hydrodynamic conductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16088v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Weak momentum dissipation in ultra-clean metals gives rise to novel non-Ohmic current flow, including ballistic and hydrodynamic regimes. Recently, hydrodynamic flow has attracted intense interest because it presents a valuable window into the electronic correlations and the longest lived collective modes of quantum materials. However, diagnosing viscous flow is difficult as the macroscopic observables of ballistic and hydrodynamic transport such as the average current distribution can be deceptively similar, even if their respective microscopics deviate notably. Based on kinetic Boltzmann theory, here we propose to address this issue via the transverse channel voltage at zero magnetic field, which can efficiently detect hydrodynamic flow in a number of materials. To this end, we show that the transverse voltage is sensitive to the interplay between anisotropic fermiology and boundary scattering, resulting in a non-trivial behavior in narrow channels along crystalline low-symmetry directions. We discuss several materials where the channel-size dependent stress of the quantum fluid leads to a characteristic sign change of the transverse voltage as a new hallmark of the cross-over from the ballistic to the hydrodynamic regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16088v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.L081402</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PhysRevB.111.L081402(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kaize Wang, Chunyu Guo, Philip J. W. Moll, Tobias Holder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anisotropic conductivity for the type-I and type-II phases of Weyl/multi-Weyl semimetals in planar Hall set-ups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05028v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute the non-Drude part of the conductivity tensor in planar Hall set-ups, for tilted Weyl and multi-Weyl semimetals, considering both the type-I and type-II phases. We do so in three distinct set-ups, taking into account the possible relative orientations of the plane spanned by the electric and magnetic fields ($\mathbf E $ and $\mathbf B $) and the direction of the tilt-axis. We derive the analytical expressions for the response tensor, including the effects of the Berry curvature (BC) and the orbital magnetic moment (OMM), both of which arise due to a nontrivial topology of the three-dimensional manifold defined by the Brillouin zone. We exhibit the interplay of the BC-only and the OMM-dependent parts in the nonzero components of the magnetoelectric conductivity, and outline whether the contributions from the former or the latter dominate the overall response. Our results also show that, depending on the configuration of the planar Hall set-up, one may or may not get terms which have a linear-in-$ B$ dependence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05028v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ipsita Mandal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-Order Van Hove Singularities in Kagome Topological Bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07000v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Motivated by the growing interest in band structures featuring higher-order Van Hove singularities (HOVHS), we investigate a spinless fermion kagome system characterized by nearest-neighbor (NN) and next-nearest-neighbor (NNN) hopping amplitudes. While NN hopping preserves time-reversal symmetry, NNN hopping, akin to chiral hopping on the Haldane lattice, breaks time-reversal symmetry and leads to the formation of topological bands with Chern numbers ranging from $C = \pm 1$ to $ \pm 4$. We perform analytical and numerical analysis of the energy bands near the high-symmetry points $\boldsymbol{\Gamma}$, $\pm \boldsymbol{K}$, and $\boldsymbol{M_i}$ ($i=1,2,$ and $3$), which uncover a rich and complex landscape of HOVHS, controlled by the magnitude and phase of the NNN hopping. We observe power-law divergences in the density of states (DOS), $\rho(\epsilon) \sim |\epsilon|^{-\nu}$, with exponents $\nu = 1/2, 1/3, 1/4$, which can significantly affect the anomalous Hall response at low temperatures when the Fermi level crosses the HOVHS. Additionally, the NNN hopping induces the formation of higher Chern number bands $C = \pm 2, \pm 4$ in the middle of the spectrum obeying a sublattice interference whereupon electronic states are maximally localized in each of the sublattices when the momentum approaches the three high-symmetry points $\boldsymbol{M_i}$ ($i=1,2,$ and $3$) on the Brillouin zone boundary. This classification of HOVHS in kagome systems provides a platform to explore unconventional electronic orders induced by electronic correlations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07000v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.075114</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>E. Wang, L. Pullasseri, and L. H. Santos, Higher-order Van-Hove singularities in kagome topological bands, Phys. Rev. B 111, 075114 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Edrick Wang, Lakshmi Pullasseri, Luiz H. Santos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning Accelerated Quantum Transport Simulations in Nanoelectronics: From Break Junctions to Field-Effect Transistors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08800v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Quantum transport calculations are essential for understanding and designing nanoelectronic devices, yet the trade-off between accuracy and computational efficiency has long limited their practical applications. We present a general framework that combines the deep learning tight-binding Hamiltonian (DeePTB) approach with the non-equilibrium Green's Function (NEGF) method, enabling efficient quantum transport calculations while maintaining first-principles accuracy. We demonstrate the capabilities of the DeePTB-NEGF framework through two representative applications: comprehensive simulation of break junction systems, where conductance histograms show good agreement with experimental measurements in both metallic contact and single-molecule junction cases; and simulation of carbon nanotube field effect transistors through self-consistent NEGF-Poisson calculations, capturing essential physics including the electrostatic potential and transfer characteristic curves under finite bias conditions. This framework bridges the gap between first-principles accuracy and computational efficiency, providing a powerful tool for high-throughput quantum transport simulations across different scales in nanoelectronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08800v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jijie Zou, Zhanghao Zhouyin, Dongying Lin, Linfeng Zhang, Shimin Hou, Qiangqiang Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Third-order and fifth-order nonlinear spin-current generation in $g$-wave and $i$-wave altermagnets, and perfectly nonreciprocal spin-current in $f$-wave magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16036v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A prominent feature of $d$-wave altermagnets is the pure spin current generated in the absence of spin-orbit interactions. In the context of symmetry, there are the $s$-wave, the $p$-wave, the $d$-wave, the $f$-wave, the $g$-wave and the $i$-wave magnets. In this paper, making an analytic study of two-band Hamiltonian systems coupled with electrons, we demonstrate unexpectedly that only the $\ell $-th order nonlinear transverse spin current proportional to $E^{\ell }$ is generated in higher-wave symmetric magnets when the number of the nodes is $\ell +1$. Here $E$ is applied electric field. The nonlinear spin current is essential provided the linear spin current is absent. Indeed, only the third-order nonlinear spin current is generated in $g$-wave altermagnets, while only the fifth-order spin current is generated in $i$-wave altermagnets. In particular, only the second-order nonlinear spin current is generated in $f$-wave magnets, which leads to a perfect nonreciprocal spin current. On the other hand, there is no spin-current generation in $p$-wave magnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16036v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Motohiko Ezawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-aligned multilayered nitrogen vacancy diamond nanoparticles for high spatial resolution magnetometry of microelectronic currents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11796v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nitrogen Vacancy diamond nanoparticles (NVNPs) are increasingly integrated with methods for optical detection of magnetic resonance (ODMR), providing new opportunities in magnetic characterization that span the visualization of magnetic fields in microelectronic circuits, environmental sensing and biology. However, only a small number of studies utilize aggregates of NVNPs for surface-wide magnetometry being that spin orientations in aggregate NVNPs are inherently misaligned, precluding their use for proper magnetic field detection compared with expensive monocrystalline diamonds. A postprocessing method for layering NVNPs with aligned NV center orientations can potentially facilitate superior NV magnetometry by allowing sensitive detection combined with simplified probe preparation. We present a novel technology for creating densely stacked monolayers of NVNP with inherent interlayer alignment for sensitive measurement of local magnetic field perturbations in microelectronic traces. We establish spatial characteristics of deposited aggregates and demonstrate their ability to capture magnetic dipoles from conducting microwires via ODMR. Our approach forms a novel accessible protocol that can be used for broad applications in micromagnetometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11796v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yash Gokhale, Brandon S Coventry, Tsani Rogers, Maya Lines, Anna Vena, Jack Phillips, Tianxiang Zhu, Ilhan Bok, Dariana J. Troche, Mitchell Glodowski, Adam Vareberg, Suyash Bhatt, Alireza Ashtiani, Kevin W. Eliceiri, Aviad Hai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Signatures of the Optical Bound on Maximal Berry Curvature: Applications to Two-Dimensional Time-Reversal-Symmetric Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17671v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Unlike broken time-reversal symmetric (TRS) systems with a defined Chern number, directly measuring the bulk $Z_{2}$ invariant and Berry curvature (if nonzero) in topological insulators and their higher-order topological families remains an unsolved problem. Here, based on the refined trace-determinant inequality (TDI) involving the trace and determinant of the quantum metric and maximal Berry curvature (MBC), we establish an optical bound on the MBC for two-dimensional TRS insulators. By utilizing experimental data on linearly polarized optical conductivity within a certain energy range, the topological signatures can be identified by integrating the optical bound. We illustrate our approach using three representative topological models: the Kane-Mele model, mirror-protected insulator, and quadrupole insulator. We find that the resulting momentum integration of the refined TDI provides an intrinsic relationship between quantum volume (QV) variations and topological phase transitions. We argue that double QV can be treated as an upper bound on the number of boundary states. Our findings offer a method for extracting the topological signatures of TRS insulators using optical conductivity data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17671v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pok Man Chiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrostatic field-driven supercurrent suppression in ionic-gated metallic Josephson nanotransistors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2107.00935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2107.00935v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent experiments have shown the possibility of tuning the transport properties of metallic nanosized superconductors through a gate voltage. These results renewed the longstanding debate on the interaction between electrostatic fields and superconductivity. Indeed, different works suggested competing mechanisms as the cause of the effect: an unconventional electric field-effect or quasiparticle injection. Here, we provide conclusive evidence for the electrostatic-field-driven control of the supercurrent in metallic nanosized superconductors, by realizing ionic-gated superconducting field-effect nanotransistors (ISFETs) where electron injection is impossible. Our Nb ISFETs show giant suppression of the superconducting critical current of up to 45%. Moreover, the bipolar supercurrent suppression observed in different ISFETs, together with invariant critical temperature and normal-state resistance, also excludes conventional charge accumulation/depletion. Therefore, the microscopic explanation of this effect calls upon a novel theory able to describe the nontrivial interaction of static electric fields with conventional superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2107.00935v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.nanolett.1c03481</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nano Lett. 21, 10309-10314 (2021)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Federico Paolucci, Francesco Cris\`a, Giorgio De Simoni, Lennart Bours, Claudio Puglia, Elia Strambini, Stefano Roddaro, Francesco Giazotto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interaction-induced topological phase transition at finite temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04779v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate the existence of topological phase transitions in interacting, symmetry-protected quantum matter at finite temperatures. Using a combined numerical and analytical approach, we study a one-dimensional Su-Schrieffer-Heeger model with added Hubbard interactions, where no thermodynamic phase transition occurs at finite temperatures. The transition is signalled by a quantized, non-local bulk topological order parameter. It is driven by defects, which are enabled by the combination of interaction and thermal activation, with no counterpart in the non-interacting limit. The defects localize topological zero modes, which, when sufficiently abundant, cause the order parameter to vanish. This phenomenon, interpreted via bulk-boundary correspondence, reflects the loss of a topological edge mode at a well-defined critical temperature in the thermodynamic limit. Unlike zero-temperature topological transitions, these finite-temperature transitions lack thermodynamic signatures but remain observable in controlled quantum systems, such as ultracold fermionic atoms in optical lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04779v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.053002</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 134, 053002 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ze-Min Huang, Sebastian Diehl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy exchange and fluctuations between a dissipative qubit and a monitor under continuous measurement and feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09452v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Continuous quantum measurement and feedback induce energy exchange between a dissipative qubit and a monitor even in the steady state, as a measurement backaction. Using the Lindblad equation, we identified the maximum and minimum values of the steady-state energy flow as the measurement and feedback states vary, and we demonstrate the qubit cooling induced by these processes. Turning our attention to quantum trajectories under continuous measurement and feedback, we observe that the energy flow fluctuates around the steady-state values. We reveal that the fluctuations are strongly influenced by the measurement backaction, distinguishing them from the standard Poisson noise typically observed in electronic circuits. Our results offer potential application in the development of quantum refrigerators controlled by continuous measurement and feedback, and provide deep insight into quantum thermodynamics from the perspective of fluctuation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09452v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.21468/SciPostPhysCore.8.1.016</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SciPost Phys. Core 8, 016 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tsuyoshi Yamamoto, Yasuhiro Tokura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deformation assisted precipitation in binary alloys: A competition of time-scales</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06099v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the process of precipitation in binary alloys in the presence of mechanical deformation. It is commonly observed that mechanical deformation prior to or during precipitation leads to microstructure with excess defects, which allows for enhanced precipitate nucleation and growth rates \cite{Weiss1979,Okaguchi1992,Deschamps2003}. To investigate this phenomenon, we employ a two-dimensional phase-field crystal alloy model endowed with a temperature dependent mobility, making it capable of recovering isothermal transformation (TTT) diagrams with a characteristic inflection point (nose) about a critical temperature. We examine the variation in the time-scale of precipitation and its connection to the time-scale of the applied deformation, focusing on the roles of atomic defects in the processes involved. Our results indicate that precipitation is initially delayed through application of a deformation until a critical strain is achieved, beyond which precipitation proceeds more rapidly, assisted by plastic deformation such as grain boundary serration or dislocation nucleation. We show that the evolution of the precipitated fraction, $f(t)$, departs from classical Avrami behaviour. Specifically, $df/dt$ develops two peaks indicative of a ``plateau"-like inflection in $f(t)$, signalling the transition to defect assisted precipitate nucleation. We analyze these plateaus as a function of the deformation rate and demonstrate that the they exhibit a discontinuous bifurcation as the time-scale of applied deformation is increased. These findings are compared to and found to be consistent with experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06099v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Mamaev, Duncan Burns, Nikolas Provatas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-dependent radiative heat flux after the beginning of thermal radiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07931v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a theoretical formalism for time-dependent radiative heat flux from one object to another in the case where the former starts radiating at a certain time. The time dependence is demonstrated for the heat flux between two isolated nanoparticles. After one particle starts radiating, the emitted energy first reaches the other one with a delay according to electromagnetic retardation, and afterwards the flux exhibits oscillatory exponential relaxation to its stationary value. For the room- or higher-temperature radiation, the oscillation period and relaxation time are determined by the resonance frequency and damping rate of the particle polarizability, respectively, being equal to dozens of femtoseconds and one picosecond for silicon carbide particles. At cryogenic temperatures, the relaxation time depends on the thermal wavelength.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07931v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.075408</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 075408 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kiryl Asheichyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Corrugation-dominated mechanical softening of defect-engineered graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.05194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.05194v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We measure the two-dimensional elastic modulus $E^\text{2D}$ of atomically clean defect-engineered graphene with a known defect distribution and density in correlated ultra-high vacuum experiments. The vacancies are introduced via low-energy (&lt; 200 eV) Ar ion irradiation and the atomic structure is obtained via semi-autonomous scanning transmission electron microscopy and image analysis. Based on atomic force microscopy nanoindentation measurements, a decrease of $E^\text{2D}$ from 286 to 158 N/m is observed when measuring the same graphene membrane before and after an ion irradiation-induced vacancy density of $1.0\times 10^{13}$ cm$^{-2}$. This decrease is significantly greater than what is predicted by most theoretical studies and in stark contrast to some measurements presented in the literature. With the assistance of atomistic simulations, we show that this softening is mostly due to corrugations caused by local strain at vacancies with two or more missing atoms, while the influence of single vacancies is negligible. We further demonstrate that the opposite effect can be measured when surface contamination is not removed before defect engineering</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.05194v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wael Joudi, Rika Saskia Windisch, Alberto Trentino, Diana Propst, Jacob Madsen, Toma Susi, Clemens Mangler, Kimmo Mustonen, Florian Libisch, Jani Kotakoski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermomagnetic anomalies in quantum magnon transport caused by tunable junction geometries in cold atomic systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10147v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study magnon-driven spin and heat transport in a magnetic linear junction (MLJ) formed by two ferromagnets in optical lattices linked via linearly aligned bonds. Using the Schwinger-Keldysh formalism, we uncover that under weak effective Zeeman fields, where Bose-Einstein statistics of magnons dominate, magnonic criticality dramatically enhances spin and thermal conductances. These singular transport properties depend on the junction geometry, and the transport properties qualitatively differ between the linear junction in this study and the point contact in our previous work. The quantum-enhanced conductances result in the breakdown of the magnonic Wiedemann-Franz (WF) law. In the classical regime at temperatures much lower than magnon energy gaps, we find that a magnonic Lorenz number becomes independent of temperature yet dependent on junction geometry, sharply contrasting with the universal WF law for Fermi liquids. We also find that the interface geometry of MLJ decouples spin and heat relaxations between ferromagnets with decay times insensitive to temperature and effective Zeeman fields. These dynamics reveal junction-geometry-sensitive magnon transport distinct from Fermi liquids, paving the way for new avenues in thermomagnetic research leveraging the tunability of cold atomic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10147v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuta Sekino, Yuya Ominato, Hiroyuki Tajima, Shun Uchino, Mamoru Matsuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
