<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 04:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the Miniband Structure of Graphene Moir\'e Superlattices via Gate-dependent Terahertz Photocurrent Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16927v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Moir\'e superlattices formed at the interface between stacked two-dimensional atomic crystals offer limitless opportunities to design materials with widely tunable properties and engineer intriguing quantum phases of matter. However, despite progress, precise probing of the electronic states and tantalizingly complex band textures of these systems remain challenging. Here, we present gate-dependent terahertz photocurrent spectroscopy as a robust technique to detect, explore and quantify intricate electronic properties in graphene moir\'e superlattices. Specifically, using terahertz light at different frequencies, we demonstrate distinct photocurrent regimes evidencing the presence of avoided band crossings and tiny (~1-20 meV) inversion-breaking global and local energy gaps in the miniband structure of minimally twisted graphene and hexagonal boron nitride heterostructures, key information that is inaccessible by conventional electrical or optical techniques. In the off-resonance regime, when the radiation energy is smaller than the gap values, enhanced zero-bias responsivities arise in the system due to the lower Fermi velocities and specific valley degeneracies of the charge carriers subjected to moir\'e superlattice potentials. In stark contrast, above-gap excitations give rise to bulk photocurrents -- intriguing optoelectronic responses related to the geometric Berry phase of the constituting electronic minibands. Besides their fundamental importance, these results place moir\'e superlattices as promising material platforms for advanced, sensitive and low-noise terahertz detection applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16927v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsnano.5c05306</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ACS Nano 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Juan A. Delgado-Notario, Stephen R. Power, Wojciech Knap, Manuel Pino, JinLuo Cheng, Daniel Vaquero, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Jes\'us E. Vel\'azquez-P\'erez, Yahya M. Meziani, Pablo Alonso-Gonz\'alez, Jos\'e M. Caridad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graphene Frontiers: Recent Advancements in Energy and Electronics Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17028</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17028v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This review article explores the synthesis, characterization, and potential applications of graphene, a two-dimensional material with exceptional properties. Graphene's versatility in energy and electronics applications is highlighted, with its high conductivity and huge surface area facilitating improved energy storage capabilities in supercapacitors and batteries. In electronics, graphene is revolutionizing the industry by enabling the development of flexible displays, high-speed transistors, and improved thermal management systems. The integration of graphene into composite materials presents opportunities for stronger, lighter, and more conductive materials. The study provides a comprehensive overview of graphene's current and future impact on technology, emphasizing its transformative potential in energy solutions and electronic advancements. In the energy sector, graphene's integration into batteries, energy storage systems, capacitors, fuel cells, and renewable energy technologies signifies a leap forward in efficiency, capacity, and sustainability. In the electronics sector, graphene's unique characteristics are utilized in RFID, sensors, and EMI shielding, leading to advancements in communication, security, and device miniaturization. The study underscores graphene's potential to spearhead future innovations, reinforcing its status as a pivotal material in the ongoing technological evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17028v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdallah M. Abdeldaiem, Abdulrhman M. Alaraj, Ahmed K. Abozaid, Habiba E. Elsayegh, Mohamed A. Khamis, Mohamed M. Kedra, Mahmoud A. Elqassas, Ahmed M. Dowidar, Aya A. Esmaeil, Nora H. El mowafy, Fayza R. Ramadan, Walid J. Hamouda, Sara R. Ghazal, Haneen A. Saad, Naglaa M. Zian, Fatma Sameh, Alshimaa M. Rizk, Mena K. Selema, Aml F. Dawood, Ebrahem H. Abdelaal, Walid Ismail, Mahmoud Abdelfatah, Swellam W. Sharshir, Abdelhamid El-Shaer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Zero Modes in Non-Hermitian Topolectrical Systems: Size and Impedance Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17227v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the size-dependent behavior of topological zero modes (TZMs) in finite non-Hermitian Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) chains implemented on a topolectrical circuit platform. By deriving exact analytical solutions for the eigenenergies and band gaps of TZMs, we reveal their sensitivity to system size and non-Hermitian parameters, such as asymmetric coupling and onsite gain or loss. Our results show that non-Hermiticity enables the recovery of exactly zero-energy TZMs at a critical system size, unlike Hermitian systems where finite-size effects cause energy splitting. These zero-energy modes produce pronounced impedance peaks in the circuit's admittance spectrum, providing a measurable signature of topological states. Additionally, a tunable grounding capacitor enables precise control of TZM energies at a fixed resonance frequency, enhancing practical tunability. Our findings offer insights into finite-size effects in non-Hermitian topological systems and guide the design of robust, reconfigurable topolectrical circuits for sensing and energy transfer applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17227v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S M Rafi-Ul-Islam, Zhuo Bin Siu, Md. Saddam Hossain Razo, Mansoor B. A. Jalil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond symmetry protection: Robust feedback-enforced edge states in non-Hermitian stacked quantum spin Hall systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17295</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17295v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Conventional wisdom holds that strongly coupling two QSH layers yields a trivial $\mathbb{Z}_2$ phase and no protected topological edge states. We demonstrate that, in a regime with intermediate inter-layer coupling (neither in the strong or weak coupling regimes) and competitive non-Hermitian directed amplification, bulk modes are suppressed while arbitrary bulk excitations inevitably accumulate into robust helical edge transport modes - without relying on any symmetry protection. Our feedback-enforced mechanism persists over broad parameter ranges and remains robust even on fractal or irregular boundaries. These findings challenge the traditional view of stacked QSH insulators as inevitably trivial, and open up new avenues for designing helical topological devices that exploit feedback-enforced non-Hermitian engineering, instead of symmetry-enforced robustness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17295v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengjie Yang, Ching Hua Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissociation of one-dimensional excitons by static electric field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17337v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The quantum states of an electron-hole pair in one-dimensional semiconductors under a static electric field are theoretically analyzed using a two-band model with on-site Coulomb interaction. In the absence of static field, the electron and hole are always bound, forming an exciton regardless of the Coulomb interaction strength, in contrast to what occurs in higher-dimensional semiconductors. The static field modifies the wave function of the electron-hole pair, turning bound states into continuum states. However, at low static fields, the linear optical spectra resemble those of the unbiased semiconductor, exhibiting a quadratic redshift of the main exciton absorption line as the field increases. When the static field exceeds a critical threshold, the exciton dissociates and the linear optical spectra exhibit signatures of the Wannier-Stark ladder with squally spaced peaks, making them a valuable tool for experimentally probing exciton dissociation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17337v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adriana Garc\'ia, Alexander L\'opez, Jorge Quereda, Francisco Dom\'inguez-Adame</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure-tunable phase transitions in atomically thin Chern insulator MnBi$_2$Te$_4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17449v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological insulators lacking time-reversal symmetry can exhibit the quantum anomalous Hall effect. Odd-layer thick MnBi$_2$Te$_4$ is a promising platform due to its intrinsic magnetic nature, however, quantization is rarely observed in it. Our magnetoresistance measurements in the anti-ferromagnetic phase indicate, instead of a quantum anomalous Hall insulator, the presence of a trivial insulator state likely due to disorder, while at high magnetic field a Chern insulator state appears. By applying hydrostatic pressure we are able to tune the magnetic interactions and the characteristic energy scales in the phase diagram. The trivial band gap is reduced, suggesting the role of disorder decreases with the compression of the layers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17449v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Albin Marffy, Endre Tovari, Yu-Fei Liu, Anyuan Gao, Tianye Huang, Laszlo Oroszlany, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Su-Yang Xu, Peter Makk, Szabolcs Csonka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic-Field Tunable M\"{o}bius and Higher-Order Topological Insulators in Three-Dimensional Layered Octagonal Quasicrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17497v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose that three-dimensional layered octagonal quasicrystals can host magnetic-field-tunable M\"{o}bius insulators and various higher-order topological insulators (HOTIs), enabled by the interplay of quasicrystalline symmetry and magnetic order. By constructing a minimal model based on stacked Ammann-Beenker tilings with magnetic exchange coupling and octagonal warping, we demonstrate that an A-type antiferromagnetic (AFM) configuration yields a topological phase protected by an effective time-reversal symmetry $\mathcal{S}=\mathcal{T}\tau_{1/2}$. Breaking $\mathcal{S}$ via an in-plane magnetic field induced canting of the AFM order while preserving a nonsymmorphic glide symmetry $\mathcal{G}_n=\tau_{1/2}\mathcal{M}_n$ leads to M\"{o}bius-twisted surface states, realizing a M\"{o}bius insulator in an aperiodic 3D system. Furthermore, we show that the quasicrystal with a general magnetic configuration supports multiple HOTI phases characterized by distinct hinge mode configurations that can be switched by rotating the magnetic field. A low-energy effective theory reveals that these transitions are driven by mass kinks between adjacent surfaces. Our work establishes a platform for realizing symmetry-protected topological phases unique to quasicrystals and highlights the tunability of hinge and surface states via magnetic control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17497v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxiao Chen, Zhiming Xu, Citian Wang, Huaqing Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge states at the boundary of graphene-like and Lieb lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17612</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17612v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Properties of the boundary of two conductors in a quantizing magnetic field are studied: with conventional Dirac charge carriers and so-called pseudospin-1 fermions, which are realized in graphene-like and Lieb lattices respectively. It is shown that edge states arise that relate the properties of conductors to the trivial and nontrivial Berry phase. These edge states lead to the appearance of a characteristic series of root features in the density of states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17612v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. V. Kozlov, Yu. A. Kolesnichenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum superposition in ultra-high mobility 2D photo-transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17630</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17630v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the striking properties that magnetoresistance of irradiated two-dimensional electron systems presents when their mobility is ultrahigh and temperature is low (T =0.5 K). Such as, an abrupt magnetoresistance collapse at low magnetic field and a resonance peak shift to the second harmonic (2wc = w), wc and w being the cyclotron and radiation frequencies respectively. We appeal to the principle of quantum superposition of coherent states and obtain that Schrodinger cat states (even and odd) are key to explain magnetoresistance at these extreme mobilities. On the one hand, the Schodinger cat states system oscillates with 2wc, thus being responsible of the resonance peak shift. On the other hand, we obtain that Schrodinger cat states-based scattering processes give rise to a destructive effect when the odd states are involved, leading to a magnetoresistance collapse. The Aharonov-Bohm effect plays a central role in the latter, turning even cat states into odd ones. We show that ultra-high mobility two-dimensional electron systems could make a promising bosonic mode-based platform for quantum computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17630v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jesus Inarrea</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-hidden magnetic order in a multi-orbital Mott insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17146v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Photo-excited quantum materials can be driven into thermally inaccessible metastable states that exhibit structural, charge, spin, topological and superconducting orders. Metastable states typically emerge on timescales set by the intrinsic electronic and phononic energy scales, ranging from femtoseconds to picoseconds, and can persist for weeks. Therefore, studies have primarily focused on ultrafast or quasi-static limits, leaving the intermediate time window less explored. Here we reveal a metastable state with broken glide-plane symmetry in photo-doped Ca$_2$RuO$_4$ using time-resolved optical second-harmonic generation and birefringence measurements. We find that the metastable state appears long after intralayer antiferromagnetic order has melted and photo-carriers have recombined. Its properties are distinct from all known states in the equilibrium phase diagram and are consistent with intralayer ferromagnetic order. Furthermore, model Hamiltonian calculations reveal that a non-thermal trajectory to this state can be accessed via photo-doping. Our results expand the search space for out-of-equilibrium electronic matter to metastable states emerging at intermediate timescales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17146v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41567-024-02752-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Physics 21, 451-457 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xinwei Li, Iliya Esin, Youngjoon Han, Yincheng Liu, Hengdi Zhao, Honglie Ning, Cora Barrett, Jun-Yi Shan, Kyle Seyler, Gang Cao, Gil Refael, David Hsieh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mott Criticality as the Confinement Transition of a Pseudogap-Mott Metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17201v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The phenomenon of Mott insulation involves the localization of itinerant electrons due to strong local repulsion. Upon doping, a pseudogap (PG) phase emerges - marked by selective gapping of the Fermi surface without conventional symmetry breaking in spin or charge channels. A key challenge is understanding how quasiparticle breakdown in the Fermi liquid gives rise to this enigmatic state, and how it connects to both the Mott insulating and superconducting phases. Here, we develop a renormalization-based construction of strongly correlated lattice models that captures the emergence of the pseudogap phase and its transition to a Mott insulator. Applying a many-body tiling scheme to the fixed-point impurity model uncovers a lattice model with electron interactions and Kondo physics. At half-filling, the interplay between Kondo screening and bath charge fluctuations in the impurity model leads to Fermi liquid breakdown. This reveals a pseudogap phase characterized by a non-Fermi liquid (the Mott metal) residing on nodal arcs, gapped antinodal regions of the Fermi surface, and an anomalous scaling of the electronic scattering rate with frequency. The eventual confinement of holon-doublon excitations of this exotic metal obtains a continuous transition into the Mott insulator. Our results identify the pseudogap as a distinct long-range entangled quantum phase, and offer a new route to Mott criticality beyond the paradigm of local quantum criticality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17201v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhirup Mukherjee, S. R. Hassan, Anamitra Mukherjee, N. S. Vidhyadhiraja, A. Taraphder, Siddhartha Lal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fingerprints of collective magnetic excitations in inelastic electron tunneling spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17263v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spin-flip inelastic electron tunneling spectroscopy allows magnetic materials to be probed at the single-atom level via scanning tunneling microscopy. Previously, the local spectral weight of spin excitations of small systems has been deduced from discrete steps in the differential conductance. However, this is not viable for large systems. We show that the local spin density of states can be measured via the double differential conductance. This contrasts with elastic measurements where the local density of electronic states is deduced from the differential conductance. We study the tunneling currents of the spin-1/2 and -1 Heisenberg chains and propose a method to probe zero-frequency modes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17263v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Finnian Rist, Henry L. Nourse, Ben J. Powell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the Impact of Single-Vacancy Defects on Electronic Properties of Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17410</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17410v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While defects are generally considered to be unavoidable in experiments, engineering them is also a way of manipulating the physical properties of materials. In this study, the role of periodically arranged single vacancy defects in graphene is studied using the tight-binding method. Our numerical results show that single vacancy (SV) defects can exhibit predictable electronic behavior when they reside on the same sublattices (SS), following the armchair graphene nanoribbons (AGNRs) electronic band structure depending on the spacing between SVs. AGNRs are known to their tunable electronic band gap. However, when they are located on different sublattices (DS), the interaction between the defect-induced states becomes strong and can introduce anisotropy into the electronic band structure, demonstrating that the relative position of the SVs can also act as an additional degree of freedom for tuning the electronic properties. Interestingly, the behavior is independent of the density of SVs; for a system fully defected with SVs, the electronic properties depend heavily on the sublattices involved. The results provide a novel insight into sublattice-based defect engineering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17410v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammadamir Bazrafshan, Thomas. D. K\"uhne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universality of Alpha-Relaxation in Glasses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17490</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17490v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the vicinity of the glass transition, the characteristic relaxation time (e.g., the alpha-relaxation time in dielectric spectroscopy) of a glass-former exhibits a strongly super-Arrhenius temperature dependence, as compared to the classical Arrhenius behavior at high temperatures. A comprehensive description of both regions thus requires five parameters. Here, we demonstrate that many glass-formers exhibit a universal scaling, with only two material-specific parameters setting the timescale and the temperature scale; the other three being universal constants. Furthermore, we show that the master curve can be described by the recently developed two-state, two-(time) scale (TS2) theory (Soft Matter 2020, 16, 810) and regress the universal TS2 parameters. We also show the connection between the TS2 model and the Hall-Wolynes elastic relaxation theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17490v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valeriy V. Ginzburg, Oleg Gendelman, Riccardo Casalini, Alessio Zaccone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement dynamics in minimal Kitaev chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17586v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Minimal Kitaev chains host Majorana quasiparticles, which, although not topologically protected, exhibit spatial nonlocality and hence expected to be useful for quantum information tasks. In this work, we consider two- and three-site Kitaev chains and investigate the dynamics of bipartite and multipartite entanglement by means of concurrence and geometric measure of entanglement. In two-site Kitaev chains, we find that maximally entangled states can robustly emerge, with their stability and periodicity highly controllable by the interplay between the superconducting pair potential and the onsite energies. At the finely tuned sweet spot, where Majorana quasiparticles appear, the system exhibits oscillations between separable and entangled states, whereas detuning introduces tunable valleys in the entanglement dynamics. Extending to the three-site Kitaev chain, we uncover rich bipartite and multipartite entanglement by generalizing the concepts of concurrence and geometric measure of entanglement. At the sweet spot, the Majorana quasiparticles emerging at the edges suppress concurrence between the edges, while a finite detuning is able to restore it. Depending on the initial state, the three-site Kitaev chain can dynamically generate either a maximally entangled Greenberger-Horne-Zeilinger state or an imperfect W-type state exhibiting multipartite entanglement, although a (maximally entangled) pure W state cannot be realised due to parity constraints. Our results provide a resource for generating and characterising highly entangled states in minimal Kitaev chains, with potential relevance for quantum applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17586v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vimalesh Kumar Vimal, Jorge Cayao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning-Assisted Nano-imaging and Spectroscopy of Phase Coexistence in a Wide-Bandgap Semiconductor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17677v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Wide bandgap semiconductors with high room temperature mobilities are promising materials for high-power electronics. Stannate films provide wide bandgaps and optical transparency, although electron-phonon scattering can limit mobilities. In SrSnO3, epitaxial strain engineering stabilizes a high-mobility tetragonal phase at room temperature, resulting in a threefold increase in electron mobility among doped films. However, strain relaxation in thicker films leads to nanotextured coexistence of tetragonal and orthorhombic phases with unclear implications for optoelectronic performance. The observed nanoscale phase coexistence demands nano-spectroscopy to supply spatial resolution beyond conventional, diffraction-limited microscopy. With nano-infrared spectroscopy, we provide a comprehensive analysis of phase coexistence in SrSnO3 over a broad energy range, distinguishing inhomogeneous phonon and plasma responses arising from structural and electronic domains. We establish Nanoscale Imaging and Spectroscopy with Machine-learning Assistance (NISMA) to map nanotextured phases and quantify their distinct optical responses through a robust quantitative analysis, which can be applied to a broad array of complex oxide materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17677v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alyssa Bragg, Fengdeng Liu, Zhifei Yang, Nitzan Hirshberg, Madison Garber, Brayden Lukaskawcez, Liam Thompson, Shane MacDonald, Hayden Binger, Devon Uram, Ashley Bucsek, Bharat Jalan, Alexander McLeod</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Birth Quota of Non-Generic Degeneracy Points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.05825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.05825v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Weyl points are generic and stable features in the energy spectrum of Hamiltonians that depend on a three-dimensional parameter space. Non-generic isolated two-fold degeneracy points, such as multi-Weyl points, split into Weyl points upon a generic perturbation that removes the fine-tuning or protecting symmetry. The number of the resulting Weyl points is at least $|Q|$, where $Q$ is the topological charge associated to the non-generic degeneracy point. Here, we show that such a non-generic degeneracy point also has a birth quota, i.e., a maximum number of Weyl points that can be born from it upon any perturbation. The birth quota is a local multiplicity associated to the non-generic degeneracy point, an invariant of map germs known from singularity theory. This holds not only for the case of a three-dimensional parameter space with a Hermitian Hamiltonian, but also for the case of a two-dimensional parameter space with a chiral-symmetric Hamiltonian. We illustrate the power of this result for band structures of two- and three-dimensional crystals. Our work establishes a strong and powerful connection between singularity theory and topological band structures, and more broadly, parameter-dependent quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.05825v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gerg\H{o} Pint\'er, Gy\"orgy Frank, D\'aniel Varjas, Andr\'as P\'alyi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrically-tunable graphene nanomechanical resonators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14468v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The excellent mechanical properties make graphene promising for realizing nanomechanical resonators with high resonant frequencies, large quality factors, strong nonlinearities, and the capability to effectively interface with various physical systems. Equipped with gate electrodes, it has been demonstrated that these exceptional device properties can be electrically manipulated, leading to a variety of nanomechanical/acoustic applications. Here, we review the recent progress of graphene nanomechanical resonators with a focus on their electrical tunability. First, we provide an overview of different graphene nanomechanical resonators, including their device structures, fabrication methods, and measurement setups. Then, the key mechanical properties of these devices, for example, resonant frequencies, nonlinearities, dissipations, and mode coupling mechanisms, are discussed, with their behaviors upon electrical gating being highlighted. After that, various potential classical/quantum applications based on these graphene nanomechanical resonators are reviewed. Finally, we briefly discuss challenges and opportunities in this field to offer future prospects of the ongoing studies on graphene nanomechanical resonators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14468v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/0256-307X/42/7/070803</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chinese Physics Letters 42, 070803 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Bo Wang, Zhuo-Zhi Zhang, Chen-Xu Wu, Yu-Shi Zhang, Guo-Sheng Lei, Xiang-Xiang Song, Guo-Ping Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrical probe of spin-spiral order in quantum spin Hall/spin-spiral magnet van der Waals heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02383v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two-dimensional spin-spiral magnets provide promising building blocks for van der Waals heterostructures due to their tunable spin textures and potential for novel functionalities for quantum devices. However, due to its vanishing magnetization and two-dimensional nature, it is challenging to detect the existence of its noncollinear magnetization. Here, we show that a van der Waals junction based on a spin-spiral magnet and a quantum spin Hall insulator enables obtaining signatures of noncollinear magnetization directly from electrical measurements. Our strategy exploits the sensitivity of helical states to local breaking of time-reversal symmetry, potentially enabling the detection of local magnetic orders even in the absence of net magnetization. We show that the combination of spin-spiral order and nonmagnetic disorder gives rise to scattering in the helical channels that can be directly associated with the spiral exchange coupling and residual nonmagnetic disorder strength. Our results show how electrical transport measurement may offer a way to detect spin-spiral magnets by leveraging helical states in van der Waals heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02383v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/2v3v-3l7p</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 024430 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fedor Nigmatulin, Jose L. Lado, Zhipei Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excitonic bound states in the continuum in van der Waals heterostructure metasurfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09037v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the formation of excitonic bound states in the continuum in van der Waals (vdW) heterostructures composed of two-dimensional excitonic vdW layers and an optically resonant patterned vdW thin film. We show that the radiative losses of the exciton can be completely suppressed - not through conventional methods such as total internal reflection, Bragg mirrors, or metallic layers - but instead via destructive interference of exciton emission rates to distinct optical modes of the metasurface. We formulate the general conditions of excitonic BICs as a vanishing Purcell factor with non-vanishing vacuum local density of states at the exciton frequency. We propose a mechanism to achieve excitonic quasi-BICs with almost complete suppression of radiation via exciton coupling with a guided-mode resonance and multiple Fabry-P\'{e}rot modes. We show that in unpatterned vdW slabs, the Purcell factor suppression is defined exclusively by the slab's permittivity achieved via positioning the 2D exciton layer in the minimum of the mode electric field. We confirm through numerical simulations that, in periodically patterned heterostructure metasurfaces, the Purcell factor can be suppressed by more than five orders of magnitude, and this effect is not due to vanishing local electric fields. Our results demonstrate the formation of excitonic quasi-BICs and their potential for advancing quantum optics and information processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09037v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Polina Pantyukhina, Andrey Bogdanov, Kirill Koshelev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of the honeycomb spin-lattice on topological magnons and edge states in ferromagnetic 2D skyrmion crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02192v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnons have been intensively studied in two-dimensional (2D) ferromagnetic (FM) skyrmion crystals (SkXs) stabilized on Bravais lattices, particularly triangular and square lattices, where the first two magnon gaps are topologically trivial and do not support topological edge states (TESs). Meanwhile, the third gap can host TESs, which may be trivialized through field-induced topological phase transitions (TPTs), enabling controlled magnonic edge transport. However, the magnon topology in non-Bravais spin lattices remains largely unexplored. In this work, we theoretically investigate the influence of the honeycomb lattice structure on magnon band topology and associated TESs in FM SkXs, employing realistic parameters for monolayer CrI$_3$ and CrBr$_3$. We reveal unique magnonic topological features arising specifically from the honeycomb lattice. Characteristic magnon modes, such as elliptical and triangular distortion modes, acquire nontrivial Chern numbers, contrasting their trivial counterparts in triangular-based SkXs. Moreover, the second magnon gap in honeycomb-based SkXs consistently hosts TESs at low magnetic fields, unlike triangular SkXs. These TESs can be trivialized above a critical magnetic field. Conversely, the third gap is generally trivial at higher magnetic fields but becomes topological at low fields only when the SkX periodicity falls below a critical threshold dependent on Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction (DMI) strength and magnetic anisotropy. Our study further demonstrates a rich magnonic topological phase diagram accessible by magnetic fields, potentially enabling selective control of low-energy chiral edge modes. These findings underscore the pivotal role of lattice geometry in shaping the topology of magnons in noncollinear spin textures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02192v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Doried Ghader, Bilal Jabakhanji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Space Group Symmetry of Chiral Fe-deficient van der Waals Magnet $\text{Fe}_{\text{3-x}}\text{GeTe}_{\text{2}}$ Probed by Convergent Beam Electron Diffraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.16944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.16944v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Crystal structure symmetry of Fe-deficient $\text{Fe}_{\text{2.9}}\text{GeTe}_{\text{2}}$ at room temperature has been investigated by a combination of selected-area electron diffraction (SAED) and convergent-beam electron diffraction (CBED). By symmetry analysis of CBED patterns along different zone axis, the space group of $\text{Fe}_{\text{2.9}}\text{GeTe}_{\text{2}}$ at room-temperature has been identified as $P6_3mc$ (No.186), which derives from the high-symmetry parent system $\text{Fe}_{\text{3}}\text{GeTe}_{\text{2}}$ ($P6_3/mmc$) by breaking the mirror symmetry along the six-fold rotation axis. The $P3m1$ (No.156) space group previously reported for $\text{Fe}_{\text{2.9}}\text{GeTe}_{\text{2}}$ is a subgroup of $P6_3mc$ suggesting further possible symmetry breaks in this non-stochiometric system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.16944v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Subakti (Leibniz Institute for Solid State and Materials Research Dresden, Germany), D. Wolf (Leibniz Institute for Solid State and Materials Research Dresden, Germany), O. Zaiets (Leibniz Institute for Solid State and Materials Research Dresden, Germany, Institute of Solid State and Materials Physics, TU Dresden, Germany), S. Parkin (Department for Nano-Systems from Ions, Spins, and Electrons), A. Lubk (Leibniz Institute for Solid State and Materials Research Dresden, Germany, Institute of Solid State and Materials Physics, TU Dresden, Germany, W\"urzburg--Dresden Cluster of Excellence ct.qmat, TU Dresden, Germany)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dislocation saturation in slip rate driven processes and initial microstructure effects for large plastic deformation of crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02413v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dislocation-density-based crystal plasticity (CP) models are introduced to account for the microstructural changes throughout the deformation process, enabling more quantitative predictions of the deformation process compared to slip-system resistance-based plasticity models. In this work, we present a stability analysis of slip-rate-driven processes for some established dislocation density-based models, including the Kocks and Mecking (KM) model and its variants. Our analysis can be generalized to any type of dislocation density model, providing a broader framework for understanding the stability of such systems. We point out the existence of saturation dislocation densities and the essential role of initial dislocation density in distinguishing between hardening and softening responses. Since the initial microstructure, modeled through the dislocation density, could be related to the size or the sample preparation process, implicit size-dependent effects can also be inferred. To further explore these phenomena, we conduct numerical simulations of pillar compression using an Eulerian crystal plasticity framework. Our results show that dislocation-density-based CP models effectively capture microstructural evolution in small-scale materials, offering critical insights for the design of miniaturized mechanical devices and advanced materials in nanotechnology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02413v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jalal Smiri, Oguz Umut Salman, Ioan R. Ionescu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing excited-state properties of two-dimensional materials using a dielectric-dependent hybrid functional</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17261v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Predicting accurate band gaps and optical properties of lower-dimensional materials, including two-dimensional van der Waals (vdW) materials and their heterostructures, remains a challenge within density functional theory (DFT) due to their unique screening compared to their bulk counterparts. Additionally, accurate treatment of the dielectric response is crucial for developing and applying screened-exchange dielectric-dependent range-separated hybrid functionals (SE-DD-RSH) for vdW materials. In this work, we introduce a SE-DD-RSH functional to the 2D vdW materials like MoS2, WS2, hBN, black phosphorus (BP), and \b{eta}-InSe. By accounting for in-plane and out-of-plane dielectric responses, our method achieves accuracy comparable to advanced many-body techniques like G0 W0 and BSE@G0 W0 at a lower computational cost. We demonstrate improved band gap predictions and optical absorption spectra for both bulk and layered structures, including some heterostructures like MoS2/WS2 . This approach offers a practical and precise tool for exploring electronic and optical phenomena in 2D materials, paving the way for efficient computational studies of layered systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17261v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/8vvn-k9p3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 045128 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arghya Ghosh, Subrata Jana, Manoar Hossain, Dimple Rani, Szymon \'Smiga, Prasanjit Samal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid quantum lattice model: Polaritons, photons, and spin waves propagation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12319v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Controlling the propagation of quantum excitations in low-dimensional systems is pivotal for quantum technologies, including communication networks and quantum simulators. We propose a one-dimensional hybrid quantum lattice model, where each lattice unit integrates a single-mode resonator that interacts with a two-level system (TLS), featuring direct coupling between adjacent TLSs. This configuration enables the coherent propagation of polaritons, spin waves, and photons, depending on the interplay between light-matter coupling and qubit-qubit interactions. Employing the time-evolving block decimation (TEBD) algorithm, we simulate the dynamics of various excitation configurations and analyze their transport characteristics using local observables. Our analysis reveals the importance of matching impedance and resonance conditions via system parameters for the propagation of different types of excitations or swapping the nature of excitations along the hybrid lattice. These findings offer insights into designing controllable quantum links and single-excitation swaps in low-dimensional quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12319v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maritza Ahumada, Natalia Valderrama-Quinteros, Diego Tancara, Guillermo Romero</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
