<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mes-hall updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mes-hall" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 05:01:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Nonreciprocity of hydrodynamic electron transport in noncentrosymmetric conductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01955v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the nonreciprocity of hydrodynamic electron transport in noncentrosymmetric conductors with broken time-reversal symmetry (TRS) is significantly enhanced compared to the disorder-dominated regime. This enhancement is caused by the linear dependence of the viscosity of the electron liquid on the flow velocity, which is allowed in the absence of TRS and Galilean invariance. The resulting nonlinear flows do not possess dynamical similarity and are characterized by two dimensionless parameters: the Reynolds number and the nonreciprocity number. The latter is linear in velocity but independent of system size. We determine the nonlinear conductance of a Hall bar and show that the nonreciprocal correction to the current can be of comparable magnitude to its reciprocal counterpart.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01955v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Kirkinis, L. Bonds, A. Levchenko, A. V. Andreev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconducting qubit based on a single molecule: the carbon nanotube gatemon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.01978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.01978v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gate-tunable transmon qubits are based on quantum conductors used as weak links within hybrid Josephson junctions. These gatemons have been implemented in just a handful of systems, all relying on extended conductors, namely epitaxial semiconductors or exfoliated graphene. Here we present the coherent control of a gatemon based on a single molecule, a one-dimensional carbon nanotube, which is integrated into a circuit quantum electrodynamics architecture. The measured qubit spectrum can be tuned with a gate voltage and reflects the quantum dot behaviour of the nanotube. Our ultraclean integration, using a hexagonal boron nitride substrate, results in record coherence times of 200ns for such a qubit. Furthermore, we investigate its decoherence mechanisms, thus revealing a strong gate dependence and identifying charge noise as a limiting factor. On top of positioning carbon nanotubes as contenders for future quantum technologies, our work paves the way for studying microscopic fermionic processes in low-dimensional quantum conductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.01978v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Riechert, S. Annabi, A. Peugeot, H. Duprez, M. Hantute, K. Watanabe, T. Taniguchi, E. Arrighi, J. Griesmar, J. -D. Pillet, L. Bretheau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sliding-induced topological transitions in bilayer biphenylene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02145v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sliding-induced topological transitions in biphenylene bilayers are investigated, considering various stacking configurations which are analyzed from a symmetry perspective and described in detail,highlighting the intricate patterns of type-II Dirac cone crossings. Topological changes in the Fermi surface are assessed via the Euler characteristic, linking each transition to its corresponding symmetry, which can be experimentally tested by conductance measurements. Moreover, the ability to tune these topological properties by sliding the layers provides a simpler and more effective way to observe such phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02145v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. L. Lage, S. Bravo, O. Arroyo-Gasc\'on, Leonor Chico, A. Latg\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin injection and detection in all-van der Waals 2D devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02471</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02471v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we report efficient out-of-plane spin injection and detection in an all-van der Waals based heterostructure using only exfoliated 2D materials. We demonstrate spin injection by measuring spin-valve and Hanle signals in non-local transport in a stack of Fe$_3$GeTe$_2$ (FGT), hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) and graphene layers. FGT flakes form the spin aligning electrodes necessary to inject and detect spins in the graphene channel. The hBN tunnel barrier provides a high-quality interface between the ferromagnetic electrodes and graphene, eliminating the conductivity mismatch problem, thus ensuring efficient spin injection and detection with spin injection efficiencies of up to $P=40$\,\%. Our results demonstrate that FGT/hBN/graphene heterostructures form a promising platform for realizing 2D van der Waals spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02471v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan B\"arenf\"anger, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Jonathan Eroms, Dieter Weiss, Mariusz Ciorga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling the microscopic quantum pathways for ultrafast charge transfer in van der Waals heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02564</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02564v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Efficient charge separation in van der Waals (vdW) heterostructures is crucial for optimizing light-harvesting and detection applications. However, precise control over the microscopic pathways governing ultrafast charge transfer remains an open challenge. These pathways are intrinsically linked to charge transfer states with strongly delocalized wave functions that appear at various momenta in the Brillouin zone. Here, we use time- and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (trARPES) to investigate the possibility of steering carriers through specific charge transfer states in a prototypical WS2-graphene heterostructure. By selectively exciting electron-hole pairs at the K-point and close to the Q-point of WS2 with different pump photon energies, we find that charge separation is faster at higher excitation energies. We attribute this to distinct tunneling mechanisms dictated by the momentum where the initial excitation takes place. Our findings introduce a novel strategy for controlling charge transfer dynamics in vdW heterostructures, paving the way for more efficient optoelectronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02564v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Hofmann, Johannes Gradl, Leonard Weigl, Stiven Forti, Camilla Coletti, Isabella Gierz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing the breakdown of the quantum anomalous Hall effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02633v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The creation of topologically non-trivial matter across electronic, mechanical, cold-atom, and photonic platforms is advancing rapidly, yet understanding the breakdown of topological protection remains a major challenge. In this work, we use magnetic imaging combined with global electrical transport measurements to visualize the current-induced breakdown of the quantum anomalous Hall effect (QAHE) in a magnetically doped topological insulator. We find that dissipation emerges at localized hot spots near electrical contacts, where an abrupt change in Hall angle leads to significant distortions of the current density. Using the local magnetization as a proxy for electron temperature, we directly observe that the electrons are driven out of equilibrium with the lattice at the hot spots and throughout the device in the breakdown regime. By characterizing energy relaxation processes in our device, we show that the breakdown of quantization is governed entirely by electron heating, and that a vanishing thermal relaxation strength at millikelvin temperatures limits the robustness of the QAHE. Our findings provide a framework for diagnosing energy relaxation in topological materials and will guide realizing robust topological protection in magnetic topological insulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02633v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George M. Ferguson, Run Xiao, Anthony R. Richardella, Austin Kaczmarek, Nitin Samarth, Katja C. Nowack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Phases in Fractals: Local Spin Chern Marker in the Sierpinski carpet Kane-Mele-Rashba Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02754v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the spectral properties and local topology of the Kane-Mele-Rashba model on a Sierpinski Carpet (SC) fractal, constructed from a rectangular flake with an underlying honeycomb arrangement and open boundary conditions. When the system parameters correspond to a topologically trivial phase, the energy spectrum is characterized solely by bulk states that are not significantly modified by the system's fractality. For parameters corresponding to the quantum spin Hall insulator (QSHI) phase, in addition to bulk states, the energy spectrum exhibits in-gap topological states that are strongly influenced by the fractal geometry. As the fractal generation increases, the in-gap topological states acquire a staircase profile, which translates into sharp peaks in the density of states. We also show that both the QSHI and the trivial phase exhibit a large gap in the valence-projected spin spectrum, allowing the use of the local spin Chern marker (LSCM) to index the local topology of the system. Fractality does not affect this gap, allowing the application of LSCM to higher fractal generations. Our results explore the LSCM versatility, showing its potential to access local topology in complex geometries such as fractal systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02754v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. L. Lage, A. B. F\'elix, S. dos A. Sousa-J\'unior, A. Latg\'e, Tarik P. Cysne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetoelectric Control of Helical Light Emission in a Moir\'e Chern Magnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02810</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02810v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetoelectric effects and their coupling to light helicity are important for both fundamental science and applications in sensing, communication, and data storage. Traditional approaches require complex device architectures, involving separate spin-injection, ferromagnetic, and optically active layers. Recently, the emergence of 2D semiconductor moir\'e superlattices with flat Chern bands and strong light-matter interactions has established a simple yet powerful platform for exploring the coupling between photon, electron, and spin degrees of freedom. Here, we report efficient current control of spontaneous ferromagnetism and associated helicity of light emission in moir\'e MoTe2 bilayer - a system which hosts a rich variety of topological phases, including newly discovered zero-field fractional Chern insulators. We show that the current control is effective over a wide range of doping of the first moir\'e Chern band, implying the uniformity of the Berry curvature distribution over the flat band. By setting the system into the anomalous Hall metal phase, a current as small as 10nA is sufficient to switch the magnetic order, a substantial improvement over both conventional spin torque architectures and other moir\'e systems. The realized current control of ferromagnetism leads to continuous tuning of trion photoluminescence helicity from left to right circular via spin/valley Hall torque at zero magnetic field. Our results pave the way for topological opto-spintronics based on semiconductors with synthetic flat Chern bands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02810v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Anderson, Heonjoon Park, Kaijie Yang, Jiaqi Cai, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Liang Fu, Ting Cao, Di Xiao, Xiaodong Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable Non-Equilibrium Magic and Minimum Twist Angles in AA-Stacked Twisted Multilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02070v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the discovery of a series of non-equilibrium magic angles at which isolated topological flat quasienergy bands form in AA-stacked twisted multilayer graphene under circularly polarized light. These non-equilibrium magic angles can be traced back to specific static twist angles where the bandwidth reaches a minimum \textit{without} the formation of isolated flat bands. We refer to these as minimum twist angles, in contrast to the magic angles observed in twisted bilayer graphene. We show that an applied displacement field can further flatten the optically induced topological flat bands accompanied by larger non-equilibrium magic angles. The discovery of these electrically tunable topological flat quasienergy bands is expected to open up a new avenue of exploring exotic Floquet-driven phenomena in AA-stacked twisted multilayer graphene.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02070v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yantao Li, Wang-Kong Tse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid confinement techniques for polariton simulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02355</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02355v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Exciton-polaritons in III-V semiconductor microcavities offer a robust platform for emulating complex Hamiltonians, enabling advancements in photonic applications and quantum simulation. Here, two novel fabrication techniques designed to overcome the limitations of traditional photonic confinement methods are introduced. The two distinct approaches - etch-and-oversputter (EnS) and deposit-and-oversputter (DnS) - are both based on a structured, locally elongated semiconductor cavity, leading to a deep and highly controllable spatially dependent potential. By utilizing an all-dielectric sputtered top mirror, sample iteration time, workflow complexity and expense is reduced while increasing the overall yield compared to methods such as deep ion etching. Employing a Kagome lattice and its flatband and Dirac-cone dispersions as a benchmark, high quality optical band structures are achieved, which so far have not been realized using a deep etching approach. To highlight the precise control over the lattice couplings, the eigenmodes in a two-dimensional breathing Kagome lattice are studied and polariton lasing from a zerodimensional corner mode is observed. This confirms the effectiveness of the methods presented in this paper for generating well-controlled, deep and homogeneous trapping potentials. These pave the way for fabricating intricate lattices, such as higher-order topological insulators, or on-chip quantum emitters utilizing the polariton blockade mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02355v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Gagel, Johannes D\"ureth, David Laibacher, Oleg A. Egorov, Simon Widmann, Simon Betzold, Monika Emmerling, Siddhartha Dam, Alexia Landry, Christian G. Mayer, Aniela Woyciechowska, Barbara Pi\k{e}tka, Ulf Peschel, Sven H\"ofling, Sebastian Klembt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin valve effect in junctions with a single ferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02462v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spin valves are essential components in spintronic memory devices, whose conductance is modulated by controlling spin-polarized electron tunneling through the alignment of the magnetization in ferromagnetic elements. Whereas conventional spin valves unavoidably require at least two ferromagnetic elements, here we demonstrate a van der Waals spin valve based on a tunnel junction that comprises only one such ferromagnetic layer. Our devices combine a Fe3GeTe2 electrode acting as spin injector together with a paramagnetic tunnel barrier, formed by a CrBr3 multilayer operated above its Curie temperature. We show that these devices exhibit a conductance modulation with values comparable to that of conventional spin valves. A quantitative analysis of the magnetoconductance that accounts for the field-induced magnetization of CrBr3, and that includes the effect of exchange interaction, confirms that the spin valve effect originates from the paramagnetic response of the barrier, in the absence of spontaneous magnetization in CrBr3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02462v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fengrui Yao, Volodymyr Multian, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Ignacio Gutierrez Lezama, Alberto F. Morpurgo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable Thermal Conductivity and Mechanical Properties of Metastable Silicon by Phase Engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02561v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The extensive applications of cubic silicon in flexible transistors and infrared detectors are much hindered by its intrinsic properties. Metastable silicon phases, such as Si-III, IV and XII prepared using extreme pressure method, provide a unique "genetic bank" with diverse structures and exotic characteristics, however, exploration on their inherent physical properties remains immature. Herein, we demonstrate the phase engineering strategy to modulate the thermal conductivity and mechanical properties of metastable silicon. The thermal conductivity obtained via Raman optothermal approach presents the broad tunability across various Si-I, III, XII and IV phases. The hardness and Young's modulus of Si-IV are remarkably greater than those of Si-III/XII mixture, confirmed by nanoindentation technique. Moreover, it was found that the pressure-induced structural defects can substantially degrade the thermal and mechanical properties of silicon. This systematic investigation can offer feasible route to design novel semiconductors and further advance their desirable applications in advanced nanodevices and mechanical transducers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02561v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yubing Du, Guoshuai Du, Zhixi Zhu, Jiaohui Yan, Jiayin Li, Tiansong Zhang, Lina Yang, Ke Jin, Yabin Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extreme Terahertz Nonlinearity of AlGaN/GaN-based Grating-Gate Plasmonic Crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02562v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a novel approach to enhance THz nonlinearity by the resonant excitation of two-dimensional plasmons in grating-gate plasmonic crystals. Using a high-electric-field THz pump-THz probe technique, we investigate the nonlinear interaction of spectrally narrow THz pulses with plasmon oscillations in a two-dimensional electron gas on an AlGaN/GaN interface integrated with metallic grating. Nonlinear effects are observed as ultrafast, pump-induced changes in THz transmission, with relative transparency strongly dependent on plasmonic mode excitation and saturating at pump fluences of about 200 nJ cm-2. The maximal relative transparency, reaching 45 % at 350 nJ cm -2, occurs under resonant excitation of a localized plasmon mode at the strong electrostatic modulation of 2DEG concentration. Transient dynamics reveal ultrafast relaxation times of 15-20 ps, while the effects can be observed at elevated temperatures of up to 150 K. A nonlinear model of plasmonic crystal, based on finite-difference time-domain electrodynamic simulations coupled with viscous hydrodynamic electron transport model, elucidates key nonlinear mechanisms, including near-field effects under metallic gratings, electron heating, plasmon resonance broadening, and redshift. These results demonstrate that even conventional semiconductors such as AlGaN/GaN can achieve nonlinear THz responses comparable to or exceeding those of graphene, showing strong potential for ultrafast THz modulation and nonlinear photonics applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02562v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavlo Sai, Vadym V. Korotyeyev, Dmytro B. But, Maksym Dub, Dmitriy Yavorskiy, Jerzy {\L}usakowski, Mateusz S{\l}owikowski, Serhii Kukhtaruk, Yurii Liashchuk, Jeong Woo Han, Christoph B\"ottger, Alexej Pashkin, Stephan Winnerl, Wojciech Knap, Martin Mittendorff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-component nonlinear wave solutions of the sixth-order generalised Boussinesq-type equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02576v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two different versions of cubic sixth-order generalised Boussinesq-type wave equations are considered in this study. A generalised perturbation reduction method is used to solve these equations, which allows the reduction of considered equations to coupled nonlinear Schrodinger equations. Two-component nonlinear wave solutions are obtained. The profiles and parameters of these solutions for both nonlinear equations are presented and compared. These solutions coincide with the vector 0 \pi pulse of self-induced transparency, which was previously studied in several known nonlinear wave equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02576v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. T. Adamashvili</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generation of polarization-entangled photon pairs from two interacting quantum emitters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02739v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Entangled photon pairs are key elements in quantum communication and quantum cryptography. State-of-the-art sources of entangled photons are mainly based on parametric-down conversion from nonlinear crystals, which is probabilistic in nature, and on cascade emission from biexciton quantum dots, which finds difficulties in generating entangled photons in the visible regime. Here, we provide a proof-of-principle demonstration that polarization-entangled photon pairs can be emitted from two interacting quantum emitters with two-level-system behaviour and perpendicular transition dipole moments. These emitters can represent a large variety of systems (e.g., organic molecules, quantum dots and diamond-color centers) offering a large technological versatility, for example in the spectral regime of the emission. We show that a highly entangled photon pair can be post-selected from this system by including optical filters. Additionally, we verify that the photon entanglement is not significantly affected by small changes in the detection directions and in the orientation between the dipole moments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02739v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adri\'an Juan-Delgado, Geza Giedke, Javier Aizpurua, Ruben Esteban</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomistic tight-binding Hartree-Fock calculations of multielectron configurations in P-doped silicon devices: wavefunction reshaping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02843v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Donor-based quantum devices in silicon are attractive platforms for universal quantum computing and analog quantum simulations. The nearly-atomic precision in dopant placement promises great control over the quantum properties of these devices. We present atomistic calculations and a detailed analysis of many-electron states in a single phosphorus atom and selected phosphorus dimers in silicon. Our self-consistent method involves atomistic calculations of the electron energies utilizing representative tight-binding Hamiltonians, computations of Coulomb and exchange integrals without any reference to an atomic orbital set, and solutions to the associated Hartree-Fock equations. First, we assess the quality of our tight-binding Hartree-Fock protocol against Configuration-Interaction calculations for two electrons in a single phosphorus atom, finding that our formalism provides an accurate estimation of the electron-electron repulsion energy requiring smaller computational boxes and single-electron wavefunctions. Then, we compute charging and binding energies in phosphorus dimers observing their variation as a function of impurity-impurity separation. Our calculations predict an antiferromagnetic ground state for the two-electron system and a weakly bound three-electron state in the range of separations considered. We rationalize these results in terms of the single-electron energies, charging energies, and the wavefunction reshaping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02843v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maicol A. Ochoa, Keyi Liu, Piotr R\'o\.za\'nski, Micha{\l} Zieli\'nski, Garnett W. Bryant</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematic Modulation of Charge and Spin in Graphene Nanoribbons on MgO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.03927v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Graphene nanostructures can be engineered with atomic precision to display customized electronic states with application in spintronics or quantum technologies. In order to take advantage of their full potential, their charge and spin state must be precisely controlled. Graphene systems exchange charge to reach thermodynamic equilibrium with their environment, requiring external gating potentials to tune their ground state. Alternative strategies like intrinsic doping or substrate modifications provided small variations of their equilibrium charge and poor control over their spin. Here, we show systematic manipulation of the electron occupation in graphene nanoribbons (GNRs) laying on MgO layers grown on Ag(001). Owing to the extraordinary decoupling properties of MgO, and the electropositive character of the substrate, GNRs are found to host an integer number of electron charges that depend on their length and shape. This results in the alternation between a non-magnetic closed-shell state and an open-shell paramagnetic system for even and odd electron occupations respectively. For the odd case, we found the spectral fingerprint of a narrow Coulomb correlation gap, which is the smoking gun of its spin 1/2 paramagnetic state. Comparisons of scanning tunnelling microscopy (STM) data with mean-field Hubbard (MFH) simulations confirm the practical discretization of the GNR electronic states and point to charge excess of up to 19 electrons in a single ribbon. We anticipate that GNRs supported by MgO ultra-thin insulating films can open the door to customized devices for quantum sensing and quantum processing applications..</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.03927v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amelia Dom\'inguez-Celorrio, Leonard Edens, Sof\'ia Sanz, Manuel Vilas-Varela, Jose Martinez-Castro, Diego Pe\~na, V\'eronique Langlais, Thomas Frederiksen, Jos\'e I. Pascual, David Serrate</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diverging entanglement of critical magnons in easy-axis antiferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02338v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the instability of antiferromagnets with easy-axis anisotropy under a magnetic field, uncovering single or even multiple phase transitions at the boundary between non-collinear and collinear spin orderings. Near the phase boundary, the entanglement between the sublattice magnons diverges due to the interplay among antiferromagnetic exchange interaction, anisotropy, and magnetic field. Furthermore, our study reveals that this magnetic criticality extends to a superradiant phase transition within cavity magnonics systems. The magnon-photon interaction results in diverging cavity photon numbers and squeezing in the ground state at the transition points between spin orderings. This investigation not only elucidates the criticality of multi-component squeezed magnons in antiferromagnets, but also proposes cavity photon measurements as a viable method for detecting magnetic phase transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02338v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.094402</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 094402 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jongjun M. Lee, Hyun-Woo Lee, Myung-Joong Hwang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Giant Rabi frequencies between qubit and excited hole states in silicon quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05526v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Holes in Si quantum dots are being investigated for the implementation of electrically addressable spin qubits. In this perspective, the attention has been focused on the electric-field induced transitions between the eigenstates belonging to the ground doublet. Here we theoretically extend the analysis to the first excited doublet. We show that - in a prototypical quantum dot structure - transitions involving the lowest excited states display Rabi frequencies that are several orders of magnitude larger than those occurring in the ground doublet. A clear relation with the symmetries of the eigenstates emerges, as well as a wide tunability of the Rabi frequencies by means of the applied bias. A preliminary discussion on the possible implications of the present results for multilevel manipulation schemes and for multi-hole qubit encodings is provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05526v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Fanucchi, G. Forghieri, A. Secchi, P. Bordone, F. Troiani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Band Curvature Effects on Quantum Transport of Spin-1 Chiral Fermion Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.19159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.19159v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We theoretically investigate the quantum transport properties of three-dimensional spin-1 chiral fermion systems with a curved trivial band. In the multiband system with two distinct characters--a linear Dirac band and a quadratic trivial band--the hybridization induced by impurity effects leads to pronounced energy and temperature dependences in the electrical conductivity. We show that the conductivity is suppressed by the trivial band in the low-energy regime near the threefold degenerate point and enhanced in the band-crossing point of the Dirac and trivial bands. These results are derived using the self-consistent Born approximation within the framework of linear response theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.19159v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Risako Kikuchi, Ai Yamakage</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reduced Wannier Representation for Topological Bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17084v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Bands with non-trivial topological indices have a topological obstruction preventing them from being represented by exponentially localized Wannier states. Here, we propose a procedure to construct exponentially localized Wannier functions that span a subspace of topologically obstructed bands through the use of the projection method. These Wannier functions form what we refer to as a "reduced Wannier representation," indicating that the Wannier functions necessarily do not span the full topological manifold. By constructing supercells, we obtain reduced Wannier functions that break the primitive translational symmetry while capturing a substantial portion of the topologically obstructed manifold. This approach effectively decomposes the topological manifold into two subspaces: an itinerant subspace inheriting the topology and a localized trivial subspace represented by reduced Wannier functions. We consider the Haldane and Kane-Mele tight-binding models as the platforms for our investigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17084v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Trey Cole, David Vanderbilt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Launching Focused and Spatially Confined Phonon-Polaritons in Hexagonal Boron Nitride</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01319v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Phonon-polaritons offer significant opportunities for low-loss, subdiffractional light guiding at the nanoscale. Despite extensive efforts to enhance control in polaritonic media, focused and spatially confined phonon-polariton waves have only been realized in in-plane-anisotropic crystals (e.g., MoO$_3$) and remain elusive in in-plane-isotropic materials (e.g., hexagonal boron nitride, hBN). In this study, we introduce a novel approach to launching phonon-polaritons by leveraging hBN subwavelength cavities at the Au/SiO$_2$ interface, enabling efficient coupling of cavities to the far-field component of mid-infrared light. Utilizing standard lithographic techniques, we fabricated subwavelength cavities of various shapes and sizes, demonstrating strong field enhancement, resonant mode localization, and generation of propagating phonon-polaritons with well-defined spatial structure. The cavity geometry governs wavefront curvature, spatial confinement, and polariton focusing, providing control over their propagation and achieving record-high in-plane confinement up to $\lambda/70$. Scattering-type scanning near-field optical microscopy reveals the real-space optical contrast of these cavity-launched modes, allowing for detailed characterization. We believe that our cavity-based approach to phonon-polariton focusing in isotropic media will pave the way for advanced nanophotonic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01319v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bogdan Borodin, Sergey Lepeshov, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Petr Stepanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarons and Exciton-Polarons in Two-Dimensional Polar Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03657v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a macroscopic theory of optical phonons, Fr{\"o}hlich polarons, and exciton-polarons in two-dimensional (2D) polar crystalline monolayers. Our theory extends the classical macroscopic formulation of the electron-phonon problem in three-dimensional (3D) polar crystals to the new generation of 2D materials. Similarly to the 3D case, in our approach, the effective electron-phonon Hamiltonian is parametrized solely in terms of macroscopic experimentally accessible quantities -- 2D polarizabilities of the monolayer at low and high frequencies. We derive the dispersion of long wave length longitudinal optical (LO) phonons, which can be viewed as a 2D form of the Lyddane-Sachs-Teller relation, and study the formation of 2D Fr{\"o}hlich polarons by adopting the intermediate coupling approximation. Finally, we apply this approach to excitons in polar 2D crystals and derive an effective potential of the electron-hole interaction dressed by LO phonons. Due to a specific dispersion of LO phonons, polarons and exciton-polarons in 2D materials exhibit unique features not found in their 3D counterparts. As an illustration, the polaron and exciton-polaron binding energies are computed for a representative set of 2D polar crystals, demonstrating the interplay between dimensionality, polarizability of materials, and electron-phonon coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03657v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. Shahnazaryan, A. Kudlis, I. V. Tokatly</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic Exact Solution for Driven Landau Levels in Two-dimensional Electron Gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.18010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.18010v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Controlling quantum systems with time-dependent fields opens avenues for engineering novel states of matter and exploring non-equilibrium phenomena. Landau levels in two-dimensional electron gases (2DEGs), with their discrete energy spectrum and characteristic cyclotron dynamics, provide an important platform for realizing and studying such driven quantum systems. While exact solutions for driven Landau levels exist, they have been limited to specific gauges or representations. In this work, we present an algebraic, gauge- and representation-independent exact solution for driven Landau levels in 2DEGs subject to arbitrary time-dependent electromagnetic fields. Our approach, based on a time-dependent unitary transformation via the displacement operator, provides clear physical insights into the driven quantum dynamics. We apply this method to derive the exact Floquet states and quasienergies for periodically driven Landau levels, and we extend our analysis to the resonant driving regime, where the Floquet picture breaks down and the electron wavefunction exhibits unbounded spatial spreading. Furthermore, we calculate the instantaneous energy absorption rate, revealing distinct absorption behaviors between coherent states and Fock or thermal states, stemming from quantum interference effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.18010v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Li-kun Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin waves in the bilayer van der Waals magnet CrSBr</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20797</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20797v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We derive analytical expressions for the spin wave frequencies and precession amplitudes in monolayer and antiferromagnetically coupled bilayer CrSBr under in-plane external magnetic fields. The analysis covers the antiferromagnetic, ferromagnetic, and canted phases, demonstrating that the spin wave frequencies in all phases are tunable by the applied magnetic field. We discuss the roles of intra- and interlayer exchange interactions, triaxial anisotropy, and intralayer dynamic dipolar fields in controlling the magnetization dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20797v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rob den Teuling, Ritesh Das, Artem V. Bondarenko, Elena V. Tartakovskaya, Gerrit E. W. Bauer, Yaroslav M. Blanter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic Computing via Autonomous Quantum Thermal Machines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.15905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.15905v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a physics-based model for classical computation based on autonomous quantum thermal machines. These machines consist of few interacting quantum bits (qubits) connected to several environments at different temperatures. Heat flows through the machine are here exploited for computing. The process starts by setting the temperatures of the environments according to the logical input. The machine evolves, eventually reaching a non-equilibrium steady state, from which the output of the computation can be determined via the temperature of an auxilliary finite-size reservoir. Such a machine, which we term a ``thermodynamic neuron'', can implement any linearly-separable function, and we discuss explicitly the cases of NOT, 3-MAJORITY and NOR gates. In turn, we show that a network of thermodynamic neurons can perform any desired function. We discuss the close connection between our model and artificial neurons (perceptrons), and argue that our model provides an alternative physics-based analogue implementation of neural networks, and more generally a platform for thermodynamic computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.15905v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1126/sciadv.adm879</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Science Advances 10, eadm8792 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Patryk Lipka-Bartosik, Mart\'i Perarnau-Llobet, Nicolas Brunner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2D hydrodynamic simulation of TeraFETs beyond the gradual-channel approximation for transient, large-signal or ultrahigh-frequency simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18764v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the past decade, detection of THz radiation by plasma-wave-assisted frequency mixing in antenna-coupled field-effect transistors (TeraFETs) -- implemented in various semiconductor material systems (Si CMOS, GaN/AlGaN, GaAs/AlGaAs, graphene, etc.) -- has matured and led to a practically applied detector technology. This has been supported by the development of powerful device simulation tools which take into account relevant collective carrier dynamics and mixing processes in various approximations. These tools mostly model carrier transport in 1D and they are usually geared towards continuous-wave illumination of the device and small-signal response. Depending on their implementation, it may not be possible readily to simulate large-signal and pulsed operation. Another approximation which may lead to unsatisfactory results is the 1D restriction to calculate only the longitudinal electric field components. Especially at the edges of the gate electrode, solving of the 2D Poisson equation promises better results. This contribution introduces a stable way to solve the 2D Poisson equation self-consistently with the hydrodynamic transport equations including the numerically challenging convection term. We employ a well-balanced approximate Harten-Lax-van-Leer-Contact Riemann solver. The approach is well suited for a future treatment of transient and large-signal cases. The 2D treatment also generically extends the model beyond the gradual-channel approximation and allows to calculate the FET's response at high THz frequencies where the gate-to-channel potential acquires a non-local character. Model calculations are performed for the exemplary case of a 65-nm Si CMOS TeraFET in the isothermal approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18764v3</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian Ludwig, Hartmut G. Roskos, Raul Borsche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Training a multilayer dynamical spintronic network with standard machine learning tools to perform time series classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02835v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The ability to process time-series at low energy cost is critical for many applications. Recurrent neural network, which can perform such tasks, are computationally expensive when implementing in software on conventional computers. Here we propose to implement a recurrent neural network in hardware using spintronic oscillators as dynamical neurons. Using numerical simulations, we build a multi-layer network and demonstrate that we can use backpropagation through time (BPTT) and standard machine learning tools to train this network. Leveraging the transient dynamics of the spintronic oscillators, we solve the sequential digits classification task with $89.83\pm2.91~\%$ accuracy, as good as the equivalent software network. We devise guidelines on how to choose the time constant of the oscillators as well as hyper-parameters of the network to adapt to different input time scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02835v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erwan Plouet, D\'edalo Sanz-Hern\'andez, Aymeric Vecchiola, Julie Grollier, Frank Mizrahi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ephemeral Superconductivity Atop the False Vacuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.02992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.02992v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A many body system in the vicinity of a first-order phase transition may get trapped in a local minimum of the free energy landscape. These so-called false-vacuum states may survive for exceedingly long times if the barrier for their decay is high enough. The rich phase diagram obtained in graphene multilayer devices presents a unique opportunity to explore transient superconductivity on top of a correlated false vacuum. Specifically, we consider superconductors which are terminated by an apparent first-order phase transition to a correlated phase with different symmetry. We propose that quenching across this transition leads to a non-equilibrium ephemeral superconductor, readily detectable using straightforward transport measurements. Besides enabling a simple detection scheme, the transient superconductor also generically enhances the false vacuum lifetime, potentially by orders of magnitude. In several scenarios, the complimentary effect takes place as well: superconductivity is temporarily emboldened in the false vacuum, albeit ultimately decaying. We demonstrate the applicability of these claims for two different instances of superconductivity terminated by a first order transition in rhombohedral graphene. The obtained decay timescales position this class of materials as a promising playground to unambiguously realize and measure non-equilibrium superconductivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.02992v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-57227-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Communications 16, 2047 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gal Shavit, Stevan Nadj-Perge, Gil Refael</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large inverse Faraday effect for Rydberg states of free atoms and isolated donors in semiconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08088v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report on the induction of magnetization in Rydberg systems by means of the inverse Faraday effect, and propose the appearance of the effect in two such systems, Rydberg atoms proper and shallow dopants in semiconductors. Rydberg atoms are characterized by a large orbital radius. This large radius gives such excited states a large angular moment, which when driven with circularly polarized light, translates to a large effective magnetic field ${B}_{\text{eff}}$. We calculate this effect to generate effective magnetic fields of $O(1\,\mu\text{T})\times\left( \frac{\omega}{1\,\text{THz}} \right)^{-1} \left( \frac{I}{10\,\text{W cm}^{-2}} \right) n^4$ in the Rydberg states of atoms such as Rb and Cs for off-resonant photon beams with frequency omega and intensity ${I}$ expressed in units of the denominators and $n$ the principal quantum number. Additionally, terahertz spectroscopy of phosphorus doped silicon reveals a large cross-section for excitation of shallow dopants to Rydberg-like states, which even for small $n$ have the potential to be driven similarly with circularly polarized light to produce an even larger magnetization. Our theoretical calculations estimate ${B}_{\text{eff}}$ as $O(10^2\,\text{T})$ for Si:P with a beam intensity of $10^8\,\text{W cm}^{-2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08088v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.064425</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 064425 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Patrick J. Wong, Ivan M. Khaymovich, Gabriel Aeppli, Alexander V. Balatsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moment method and continued fraction expansion in Floquet Operator Krylov Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.15223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.15223v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recursion methods such as Krylov techniques map complex dynamics to an effective non-interacting problem in one dimension. For example, the operator Krylov space for Floquet dynamics can be mapped to the dynamics of an edge operator of the one-dimensional Floquet inhomogeneous transverse field Ising model (ITFIM), where the latter, after a Jordan-Wigner transformation, is a Floquet model of non-interacting Majorana fermions, and the couplings correspond to Krylov angles. We present an application of this showing that a moment method exists where given an autocorrelation function, one can construct the corresponding Krylov angles, and from that the corresponding Floquet-ITFIM. Consequently, when no solutions for the Krylov angles are obtained, it indicates that the autocorrelation is not generated by unitary dynamics. We highlight this by studying certain special cases: stable $m$-periodic dynamics derived using the method of continued fractions, exponentially decaying and power-law decaying stroboscopic dynamics. Remarkably, our examples of stable $m$-periodic dynamics correspond to $m$-period edge modes for the Floquet-ITFIM where deep in the chain, the couplings correspond to a critical phase. Our results pave the way to engineer Floquet systems with desired properties of edge modes and also provide examples of persistent edge modes in gapless Floquet systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.15223v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.125103</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 125103 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hsiu-Chung Yeh, Aditi Mitra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-split flat bands at the band edge and two-dimensional hole gases towards quantum Hall effect in altermagnetic CoF$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16188v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Altermagnetic phase is recently found as a new magnetic phase in addition to the conventional collinear spin orders, and great efforts have been made to explore novel effects and potential applications in such materials. Here, we show that there are robust altermagnetic spin-split flat bands near the valence band edge in rutile CoF$_2$ through first-principles investigation. It is uncovered that the magnetic moments can remain in the z axis because of the magnetocrystalline energy due to the spin-orbits coupling and the spin orientation can be made more stable by magnetic field applied in the xy plane. We describe the spin-dependent band structure (including the flat bands) near the Fermi level by a spin-resolved effective low-energy model, and reveal that they can host spin-dependent two-dimensional hole gases. Importantly, we find spin-dependent quantum Hall effects in the two-dimensional hole gases by applying the magnetic field in the xy plane, and then explore the dependence of Hall conductivity and Hall resistance on the Fermi level and the magnetic field (both magnitude and direction) and related longitudinal carrier transport properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16188v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bo-Wen Yu, Bang-Gui Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
