<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ins-det updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det</link>
    <description>physics.ins-det updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 04:00:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Electron Scattering at the Intensity Frontier with SoLID</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16037v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Solenoidal Large Intensity Device (SoLID) is a large acceptance spectrometer capable of operating at the luminosity frontier. It is proposed to fully exploit the scientific potential of the continuous electron beam accelerator facility (CEBAF) 12 GeV energy upgrade at Jefferson Lab. Its conceptual design is mature, having passed multiple reviews and been validated by a successful pre-R\&amp;D phase. The envisioned scientific program consists of three avenues of research, namely the 3D momentum imaging of the structure of the nucleon, the origin of the proton mass through the gluonic gravitational form factors (GFFs), and the search of physics beyond the standard model of particle physics. These avenues are complemented by a growing supplemental list of run group experiments that address a variety of important topics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16037v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zein-Eddine Meziani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Validation of Thin-foil proton recoil neutron spectrometer prototype for application in high yield DT fusion devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The use of Thin-foil Proton Recoil (TPR) spectrometers for application in neutron spectroscopy is of high relevance for future fusion devices such as ITER, where neutron spectroscopy will play a crucial role in fuel content monitoring. Existing research based on simulations of the performance of TPR spectrometers at ITER has demonstrated positive results. However, experimental validation of the simulations would greatly benefit the reliability of conclusions. In this study, we designed and constructed a prototype TPR neutron spectrometer and employed a DT neutron generator as a neutron source to perform measurements. We compared the experimental results with the simulation results using the Geant4 model of the experiment. The simulation and experimental results match within silicon detector intrinsic energy resolution. This approach ensures the experimental validation of the Geant4 based simulations of the TPR spectrometer. The experimental results demonstrated the feasibility of utilizing nuclear reactions measured in silicon detectors, specifically $^{28}$Si(n,d) and $^{28}$Si(n,$\alpha$), for energy calibration purposes. A comparison of the experiment and the simulation shows that the mean peak energy and full width at half maximum are within 150 keV. The calculated detector efficiency underestimates the experimentally determined efficiency up to 33\%. Discrepancies in the measured energy spectrum indicate the need for a more refined model and experiment control. Overall, the successful validation of the developed Geant4 simulation model against the experimentally measured energy spectra increases confidence in the applicability of such simulation results in other devices. The demonstrated energy calibration highlights new possibilities for neutron spectrometer monitoring during operation at ITER.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16093v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Marcinkevicius, E. Andersson Sunden, G. Ericsson, A. Hjalmarsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infrared thermal imaging camera to measure low temperature thermal fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16165v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To measure low-temperature thermal fields, we have developed a single-element cooled thermal imaging camera for a spectral range of 8{\div}14 {\mu}m with an internal shutter for radiometric calibration. To improve the accuracy of measuring the temperature of cold objects, we used a shutter with a combined emissivity as an internal reference source of radiation at the input of the device optical unit. With this aim a small mirror was fixed in the center on its surface covered black, thereby ensuring an efficient reflection of radiation in a wide spectral range of wavelengths. When processing the signal for each pixel of the thermal image, the differential value of the detector response to the shutter blackened and mirror areas was used as a reference. A relative measurement error of 3 percent was obtained for the studied objects with a temperature of -150 {\deg}C. The device was successfully used for remote study of thermal field dynamics during freeze-thawing of biological tissues in vivo.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16165v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0188276</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rev. Sci. Instrum. 95, 035116 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>E. Gordiyenko (B.Verkin Institute for Low Temperature Physics and Engineering NAS of Ukraine), Yu. Fomenko (B.Verkin Institute for Low Temperature Physics and Engineering NAS of Ukraine), G. Shustakova (B.Verkin Institute for Low Temperature Physics and Engineering NAS of Ukraine), G. Kovalov (Institute for Problems of Cryobiology and Cryomedicine NAS of Ukraine), S. Shevchenko (B.Verkin Institute for Low Temperature Physics and Engineering NAS of Ukraine)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Bi-polar Current Source with High Short-term Stability for Tsinghua Tabletop Kibble Balance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16405v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A high-precision current source, capable of supporting weighing measurements with a relative uncertainty at the $10^{-9}$ level, is essential for Kibble balance experiments. However, most current sources utilized in Kibble balances to date are homemade and not commercially available. In this paper, we introduce a digital-feedback, two-stage current source designed for the Tsinghua tabletop Kibble balance, relying solely on commercially available sources and voltmeters. A high-resolution, small-range current source is employed to digitally compensate for current output fluctuations from a large-range current source. Experimental tests show the proposal can offer an easy realization of a current source with nA/A stability to support Kibble balance measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16405v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kang Ma, Xiaohu Liu, Wei Zhao, Songling Huang, Shisong Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Li$_2$MnCl$_4$ single crystal: new candidate for red-emitting neutron scintillator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16178v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Novel red-emitting scintillator Li$_2$MnCl$_4$ is proposed as a candidate for thermal neutron detection. It features high Li content, low density, low effective atomic number, and emission in red-NIR region. These characteristics make it an interesting candidate for long distance neutron detection in harsh enviroments e. g. decomisioning of nuclear powerplants. The absorption spectrum is thoroughly investigated in the scope of Tanabe-Sugano diagram. Luminescence mechanism in the undoped Li$_2$MnCl$_4$ is studied in depth. Doping by Eu$^{2+}$ and Ce$^{3+}$ is introduced as a trial to improve the scintillation efficiency. We show in the Eu$^{2+}$ and Ce$^{3+}$ doped Li$_2$MnCl$_4$ that luminescence mechanism involves energy transfer from the dopants to Mn$^{2+}$, and propose the local lattice distortion around the dopant and a possible charge compensation mechanisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16178v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vojtech Vanecek, Robert Kral, Katerina Krehlikova, Romana Kuverkova, Vladimir Babin, Petra Zemenova, Jan Rohlicek, Zuzana Malkova, Terezia Jurkovicova, Martin Nikl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development and Implementation of Advanced Beam Diagnostic and Abort Systems in SuperKEKB</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16184v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The SuperKEKB/Belle II experiment aims to collect high-statistics data of B meson pairs to explore new physics beyond the Standard Model (SM). SuperKEKB, an upgraded version of the KEKB accelerator, has achieved a world-record luminosity of $4.71 \times 10^{34} \, \mathrm{cm^{-2}s^{-1}}$ in 2022 but continues to strive for higher luminosities. One of the major obstacles is Sudden Beam Loss (SBL) events, which cause substantial beam losses and damage to the Belle~II detector. To find a hint for addressing SBL challenges, advanced beam diagnostic systems and enhanced beam abort systems have been developed. The diagnostic system aims to accurately pinpoint the start of beam losses, while the upgraded abort system quickly disposes of anomalous beams to minimize damage.
  This paper details the development and implementation of these systems, including high-speed loss monitors, time synchronization with the White Rabbit system, and data acquisition systems. Efforts to understand the mechanisms of SBL events, using acoustic sensors to detect discharges, are also discussed. These measures aim to improve the operational stability and luminosity of SuperKEKB, contributing to the experiment's success.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16184v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keisuke Yoshihara, Tetsuro Abe, Michele Aversano, Alexander Gale, Hitomi Ikeda, Hiroshi Kaji, Hidekazu Kakuno, Taichiro Koga, Toru Iijima, Shinnosuke Kato, Ami Kusudo, Yuxin Liu, Akane Maeda, Sayan Mitra, Gaku Mitsuka, Kenkichi Miyabayashi, Isamu Nakamura, Hiroyuki Nakayama, Yu Nakazawa, Riku Nomaru, Iori Okada, Xiao-Dong Shi, Shuji Tanaka, Kenta Uno, Yutaka Ushiroda, Bela Urbschat, Rui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Digital stabilization of an IQ modulator in the carrier suppressed single side-band (CS-SSB) mode for atom interferometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16678v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an all-digital method for stabilising the phase biases in an electro-optic I/Q modulator for carrier-suppressed single-sideband modulation. Building on the method presented in S. Wald \ea, Appl. Opt. \textbf{62}, 1-7 (2023), we use the Red Pitaya STEMlab 125-14 platform to digitally generate and demodulate an auxiliary radio-frequency tone whose beat with the optical carrier probes the I/Q modulator's phase imbalances. We implement a multiple-input, multiple-output integral feedback controller which accounts for unavoidable cross-couplings in the phase biases to lock the error signals at exactly zero where optical power fluctuations have no impact on phase stability. We demonstrate $&gt;23\,\rm dB$ suppression of the optical carrier relative to the desired sideband at $+3.4\,\rm GHz$ over a period of $15$ hours and over temperature variations of $20^\circ\rm C$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16678v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arif Ullah, Samuel Legge, John D. Close, Simon A. Haine, Ryan J. Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the first test of the Weak Equivalence Principle in low Earth orbit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.06400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.06400v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Weak Equivalence Principle is the founding pillar of General Relativity and as such should be verified as precisely as possible. The Microscope experiment tested it in low Earth orbit, finding that Pt and Ti test masses fall toward Earth with the same acceleration to about 1e-15, an improvement of about two orders of magnitude over ground tests. Space missions, even if small, are expensive and hard to replicate; yet, the essence of physics is repeatability. This work is an assessment of the Microscope results based on the laws of physics and knowledge from previous experiments, focusing on the limiting thermal noise and the treatment of acceleration outliers. Thermal noise reveals anomalies that we explain by stray sub-microVolt potentials caused by patch charges, giving rise to an unstable zero. The measurements were affected by numerous acceleration spikes occurring at the synodic frequencies relative to the Earth (the signal frequency) and the Sun, which we interpret as evidence of a thermal origin. In Microscope authors' analysis, the spikes were removed and the resulting gaps replaced with artificial data (up to 35, 40 per cent of the sessions data), which retain memory of the gaps and may simulate or cancel an effect (signal or systematic). An alternative approach based exclusively on real measured data would avoid any ambiguity. The lessons of Microscope are crucial to any futures improved mission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.06400v5</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna M. Nobili, Alberto Anselmi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomaly detection with flow-based fast calorimeter simulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11618v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, several normalizing flow-based deep generative models have been proposed to accelerate the simulation of calorimeter showers. Using CaloFlow as an example, we show that these models can simultaneously perform unsupervised anomaly detection with no additional training cost. As a demonstration, we consider electromagnetic showers initiated by one (background) or multiple (signal) photons. The CaloFlow model is designed to generate single photon showers, but it also provides access to the shower likelihood. We use this likelihood as an anomaly score and study the showers tagged as being unlikely. As expected, the tagger struggles when the signal photons are nearly collinear, but is otherwise effective. This approach is complementary to a supervised classifier trained on only specific signal models using the same low-level calorimeter inputs. While the supervised classifier is also highly effective at unseen signal models, the unsupervised method is more sensitive in certain regions and thus we expect that the ultimate performance will require a combination of these approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11618v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Claudius Krause, Benjamin Nachman, Ian Pang, David Shih, Yunhao Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
