<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ins-det updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det</link>
    <description>physics.ins-det updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 04:01:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Development of a Dual-Spectroscopic System to Rapidly Measure Diisopropyl Methyl Phosphonate (DIMP) Decomposition and Temperature in a Reactive Powder Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11066</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11066v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The development of systems to measure and optimize emerging energetic material performance is critical for CWA defeat. This study documents a combination of two spectroscopic systems designed to monitor decomposition of a CWA simulant and temperature. The first system is a custom benchtop Polygonal Rotating Mirror Infrared Spectrometer (PRiMIRS) incorporating a fully customizable sample cell to observe decomposition of DIMP as it interacts with combusting composite metal particles. The second is TDLAS used to monitor increases in background gas temperatures as the composite metal powders combust. The PRiMIRS system demonstrates a very high SNR at Hz, reasonable SNR when operating at 100 Hz, and capabilities of resolving spectral features with a FWHM resolution of 15 cm^-1. TDLAS was able to monitor temperature rises between room temperature and 230C +/- 5C at 100 Hz.For testing, liquid DIMP was inserted in a preheated SS cell to generate DIMP vapor and (Al-8Mg):Zr metal powders were ignited in a SS mount with a resistively heated nichrome wire at one end of the cell. The ignited particles propagated across the cell containing DIMP vapor. The path averaged gas temperature in the preheated SS cell rises rapidly (100ms) and decays slowly (&lt; 5 s) but remains below 230C during particle combustion, a temperature at which the thermal decomposition of DIMP is not observed over similarly short timescales (seconds). However, when combusting particles were introduced to the DIMP vapor (heterogenous environment), spectral signatures indicative of decomposition products such as IMP and IPA were observed within seconds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11066v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Preetom Borah, Milad Alemohammad, Mark Foster, Timothy P. Weihs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Highly Sensitive Differential Microwave Sensor for Soil Moisture Measurement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11068v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a highly sensitive differential soil moisture sensor (DSMS) using a microstrip line loaded with triangular two turn resonator(T2 SR) and complementary of the rectangular two turn spiral resonator(CR2 SR),simultaneously.Volumetric Water Content (VWC) or permittivity sensing is conducted by loading the T2 SR side with dielectric samples.Two transmission notches are observed for identical loads relating to T2 SR and CR2 SR.The CR2 SR notch at 4.39 GHz is used as a reference for differential permittivity measurement method.Further, the resonance frequency of T2 SR is measured relative to the reference value. Based on this frequency difference,the permittivity of soil is calculated which is related to the soil VWC.Triangular two turn resonator (T2 SR) resonance frequency changes from 4 to 2.38 GHz when VWC varies 0 percent to 30 percent.The sensor's operation principle is described through circuit model analysis and simulations.To validate the differential sensing concept, prototype of the designed 3 cell DSMS is fabricated and measured.The proposed sensor exhibits frequency shift of 110 MHz for 1 percent change at the highest soil moisture content (30 percent) for sandy type soil.This work proves the differential microwave sensing concept for precision agriculture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11068v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rasool Keshavarz, Justin Lipman, Dominique Schreurs, Negin Shariati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-Based Approaches for Rapid Construction of Magnetic Fields in NV Magnetometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11069v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the second quantum revolution underway, quantum-enhanced sensors are moving from laboratory demonstrations to field deployments, providing enhanced and even new capabilities. Signal processing and operational software are becoming integral parts of these emerging sensing systems to reap the benefits of this progress. This paper looks into widefield Nitrogen Vacancy Center-based magnetometry and focuses on estimating the magnetic field from the Optically Detected Magnetic Resonances (ODMR) signal, a crucial output for various applications. Mapping the shifts of ODMR signals to phase estimation, a computationally efficient Fourier Transform-based approach is proposed, which also involves linear curve fit and Estimation of Signal Parameters via Rotational Invariant Techniques (ESPRIT) as additional steps. The existing methods in the quantum sensing literature take different routes for determining magnetic field maps. To showcase the functionality and effectiveness of the suggested technique, relevant results, based on experimental data are provided, which shows a significant reduction in computational time with the proposed method over existing method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11069v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prabhat Anand, Ankit Khandelwal, Achanna Anil Kumar, M Girish Chandra, Pavan K Reddy, Anuj Bathla, Dasika Shishir, Kasturi Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear scintillation effects in the intrinsic luminescence from Sc$_{1.318}$Y$_{0.655}$Si$_{1.013}$O$_{4.987}$ crystal excited by electrons and gamma-quanta</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11070v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The spectral and kinetic properties of intrinsic luminescence from (Y$_2$Sc$_1$)$_{0.(3)}$(Sc)[Si]O$_5$ crystal are studied. The emission is excited by electrons and gamma-quanta. The composition (Y$_2$Sc$_1$)$_{0.(3)}$(Sc)[Si]O$_5$ is the congruent one for Sc$_2$SiO$_5$-Y$_2$SiO$_5$ solid solutions. It is found, that the crystal emits fairly bright intrinsic cathodololuminescence (CL) and radioluminescence (RL) at room temperature. In particular, the light yield of scintillation excited by -quanta with the energies of 661.7 keV is of 12000 photons/MeV. An increase in the beam flux by $\sim$20 times leads to the shift in the maximum CL energy spectral density from 315 to 340 nm and to the decrease in the CL decay time at 415 nm from 1377 +/- 3 ns to 1165 +/- 1 ns. Simultaneously, the decay time of RL excited by a photoelectron with the energy of 644.7 keV is of 1310 +/- 10 ns while a Compton electron with the energy of 477 keV excites RL with the decay time of 1050 +/- 10 ns. Also, we observed differences in the CL yield dependencies on the volume-averaged density of electronic excitations (EEs) at different wavelengths. An explanation of the results is given considering the nonlinear scintillation phenomena induced by an interaction between EEs. It is based on a conception that an increase in EE volume density leads to an increase in EEs nonradiative quenching due to these interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11070v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. V. Belov, V. A. Kozlov, N. V. Pestovskii, S. Yu. Savinov, V. S. Tskhay, V. I. Vlasov, A. I. Zagumennyi, Yu. D. Zavartsev, M. V. Zavertyaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calorimetry for the ePIC Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11075v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The EIC will deliver collisions of electrons with protons and nuclei at a wide variety of energies and at luminosities up to 1000 times higher than HERA. Precise measurement of both the scattered electron and the hadronic final state is crucial for the physics of the EIC, necessitating unique designs for the electromagnetic and hadronic calorimeters in the backward, central, and forward regions. To ensure maximal containment of energy and acceptance for the required physics processes, the ePIC detector employs calorimetry over almost the entire polar angle. These proceedings provide an overview of the current calorimeter designs being employed in ePIC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11075v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henry T. Klest</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Transition Edge Sensor Operated in Coincidence with a High Sensitivity Phonon Veto for Photon Coupled Rare Event Searches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11158v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Experimental searches for axions or dark photons that couple to the standard model photon require photosensors with low noise, broadband sensitivity, and near zero backgrounds. Here, we introduce a Transition Edge Sensor (TES) based photon sensor with a high sensitivity athermal phonon sensor coupled to the substrate on which the TES is deposited. We show that single photons absorbed locally in the TES have $\sim$35% energy deposition in the electronic system of the TES, with $\sim$26% of the photon energy absorbed by the athermal photon sensor (due to athermal phonons leaking out of the TES during the downconversion process). Backgrounds are observed to be largely coupled to either the TES or phonon system. At high energies, these backgrounds can be efficiently discriminated from TES photon absorption events, while at low energies, their leakage into the passage band is well modeled. With significant sensitivity improvements to both the photon and phonon channel, this coincidence technique could be used to suppress backgrounds in bosonic dark matter searches down to energies near the superconducting bandgap of the sensor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11158v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roger K. Romani, Yen-Yung Chang, Rupak Mahapatra, Mark Platt, Maggie Reed, Ivar Rydstrom, Bernard Sadoulet, Bruno Serfass, Matt Pyle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Heavy Ion Monitor on a Chip Based on a Non-Volatile Memory Architecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11245v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The performance of a particle detector derived from nitride read-only memory (NROM) technology is evaluated, with immediate applications in space-based heavy ion radiation monitoring and detection. Irradiation exposures are performed using 40 MeV/u $^{78}$Kr and 10 MeV/u $^4$He particle beams at the Texas A&amp;M University Cyclotron Institute. The results show a strong sensitivity to high-Z heavy ions, and medium sensitivity to low-Z heavy ions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11245v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dale Julson, Will Flanagan, Mike Youngs, Aidan Medcalf, Benedict Anderson, Sharanya Palit, Tim Hossain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of a gaseous time projection chamber with an internal \ce{^{37}Ar} source</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11734</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11734v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report on a systematic characterization of a gaseous time projection chamber based on Micromegas using an internal \ce{^{37}Ar} source. The \ce{^{37}Ar} is a fast-decaying and low-energy calibration source that provides a mono-energetic peak of 2.82 keV. Gaseous \ce{^{37}Ar} source is injected and uniformly distributed in argon-(2.5${\rm \%}$)isobutane mixtures. Key performance parameters of the detector, such as electron transmission, gain, energy resolution, gain uniformity, and drift field evolution, are effectively and quickly calibrated. The maximum attainable gain is up to thousands at pressures from 0.3 to 10 bar. The gain uniformity, related to the homogeneity of the avalanche gap of Micromegas, is calibrated quickly thanks to the event-by-event position reconstruction and quasi-point energy deposition of \ce{^{37}Ar}. The energy resolution is improved with the obtained gain uniformity map. The most noticeable improvement in energy resolution from 44.9\% to 35.4\% is observed at 7 bar working pressure. The internal calibration source is also used to characterize the dependence of the detector's electric field distortion on the drift field. An electrostatic field simulation confirms our measured dependence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11734v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenming Zhang, Yuanchun Liu, Ke Han, Shaobo Wang, Xiaopeng Zhou, Xunan Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Framework for Synchrotron Radiation Studies in the EIC Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11709</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11709v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Electron-Ion Collider (EIC) is a cutting-edge particle accelerator aimed at investigating the fundamental structure of matter by colliding high-energy polarized electron beams with ions. To explore dense gluon systems and uncover the origins of nucleon mass and spin, the EIC will operate at high beam currents and luminosities. However, this approach raises beam-induced background rates, notably from synchrotron radiation (SR), which poses significant challenges to the performance and longevity of the Electron-Proton/Ion Collider (ePIC) general-purpose spectrometer placed at the interaction point (IP).
  This paper presents a newly developed Monte-Carlo simulation framework for accurately modeling SR backgrounds in the detector, focusing on the reflection of X-ray photons on vacuum-metal interfaces. Utilizing the extensive capabilities of Geant4 for particle-matter interactions and propagation through the geometry, the study provides first estimates of SR rates in ePIC. The results also propose countermeasures to protect sensitive electronics, ensuring stable and reliable detector operation within the EIC environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11709v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrii Natochii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical simulation of autoresonant ions oscillations in an anharmonic electrostatic trap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11722v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work presents the results of modelling the ion dynamics in the ART-MS (Autoresonant Trap Mass Spectrometry) device in the quasi-static approximation. This instrument utilizes an anharmonic, purely electrostatic trap for ion confinement and a radio frequency (RF) voltage source with decrementally varying frequency for selective ion extraction. The autoresonant interaction between the oscillatory motion of the ion and the RF voltage causes an increase in the amplitude of certain confined ions, allowing their selective extraction. Numerical modelling shows that the extraction of ions with a given mass occurs not only at the fundamental frequency but also at its harmonics. This effect reduces the selective properties of devices of this type because along with the main mass component for a given frequency, it is possible to enter the detector channel of ions with another mass, for which this frequency corresponds to the second or higher harmonics, even a superposition of some of these harmonics of different ions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11722v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. E. L\'opez, C. J. Paez-Gonz\'alez, A. Hern\'andez, E. A. Orozco, P. Tsygankov, F. F. Parada-Becerra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light Response of Poly(ethylene 2,6-napthalate) to Neutrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.02866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.02866v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: There is increasing necessity for low background active materials as ton-scale, rare-event and cryogenic detectors are developed. Poly(ethylene-2,6-naphthalate) (PEN) has been considered for these applications because of its robust structural characteristics, and its scintillation light in the blue wavelength region. Radioluminescent properties of PEN have been measured to aid in the evaluation of this material. In this article we present a measurement of PEN's quenching factor using three different neutron sources; neutrons emitted from spontaneous fission in $^{252}$Cf, neutrons generated from a DD generator, and neutrons emitted from the $^{13}$C($\alpha$,n)$^{16}$O and the $^{7}$Li(p,n)$^{7}$Be nuclear reactions. The fission source used time-of-flight to determine the neutron energy, and the neutron energy from the nuclear reactions was defined using thin targets and reaction kinematics. The Birk's factor and scintillation efficiency were found to be $kB = 0.12 \pm 0.01$ mm MeV$^{-1}$ and $S = 1.31\pm0.09$ MeV$_{ee}$ MeV$^{-1}$ from a simultaneous analysis of the data obtained from the three different sources. With these parameters, it is possible to evaluate PEN as a viable material for large-scale, low background physics experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.02866v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brennan Hackett, Richard deBoer, Yuri Efremenko, Michael Febbraro, Jason Nattress, Dan Bardayan, Chevelle Boomershine, Kristyn Brandenburg, Stefania Dede, Joseph Derkin, Ruoyu Fang, Adam Fritsch, August Gula, Gyurky Gyorgy, Gula Hamad, Yenuel Jones-Alberty, Beka Kelmar, Khachatur Manukyan, Miriam Matney, John McDonaugh, Shane Moylan, Patrick O'Malley, Shahina Shahina, Nisha Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detector and physics simulation using heavy ion collisions at NICA-SPD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.00997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.00997v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The space-time picture of hadron formation in high-energy collisions with nuclear targets is still poorly known. The tests of hadron formation was suggested for the first stage of SPD running. They will require measuring charged pion and proton spectra with the precision better than 10\%. A research has been carried out to check feasibility of such studies at SPD. In this work, $^{12}C-{^{12}C}$ and $^{40}Ca-{^{40}Ca}$ heavy ion collisions at center of mass energy of 11 GeV/nucleon were simulated using the SMASH event generator. Firstly, the generator-level events were studied. The distribution of track multiplicities and momentum distributions of different types of charged particles were obtained. Secondly, the generated events passed through the full reconstruction using the SpdRoot framework. At this stage, particles were identified using $dE/dx$ measurement and time-of-flight information. It allowed us to estimate charge track multiplicities in the tracking system and purities of charge particles spectra. The results on multiplicity are important to estimate occupancies in the tracking system, while the results on the pion and proton momentum spectra show that particle identification should be acceptable for validation of hadron formation models. This is the first study of moderate ion collisions for the SPD Experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.00997v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Pandey</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscale torsion resonators for short-range gravity experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13020v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Measuring gravitational interactions on sub-100-$\mu$m length scales offers a window into physics beyond the Standard Model. However, short-range gravity experiments are limited by the ability to position sufficiently massive objects to within small separation distances. Here we propose mass-loaded silicon nitride ribbons as a platform for testing the gravitational inverse square law at separations currently inaccessible with traditional torsion balances. These microscale torsion resonators benefit from low thermal noise due to strain-induced dissipation dilution while maintaining compact size (&lt;100$\,\mu$g) to allow close approach. Considering an experiment combining a 40$\,\mu$g torsion resonator with a source mass of comparable size (130$\,\mu$g) at separations down to 25$\,\mu$m, and including limits from thermomechanical noise and systematic uncertainty, we predict these devices can set novel constraints on Yukawa interactions within the 1-100$\,\mu$m range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13020v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Manley, C. A. Condos, S. Schlamminger, J. R. Pratt, D. J. Wilson, W. A. Terrano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Use of current-potential patches to obtain fundamental improvements to the coils of magnetic fusion devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19123v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A central issue in the design of tokamaks or stellarators is the coils that produce the external magnetic fields. The freedom that remains unstudied in the design of coils is enormous. This freedom could be quickly studied computationally at low cost with high reliability. In particular, the space between toroidal field or modular coils that block access to the plasma chamber could be increased by a large factor. The concept of current-potential patches, which was developed in Todd Elder's thesis, provides a method for separating the study of the feasibility of coils with attractive physics properties from the engineering design of specific coils.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19123v3</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Allen H Boozer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of the Effect of Tilted Corner Cube Reflector Arrays on Lunar Laser Ranging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.09260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.09260v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper primarily investigates the effect of the tilt of corner cube reflector (CCR) arrays on lunar laser ranging (LLR). A mathematical model was established to study the random errors caused by the tilt of the CCR arrays. The study found that, ideally, when the laser ranging pulse width is 10 picoseconds or less, it is possible to distinguish from which specific corner cubes within the CCR array each peak in the echo signal originates. Consequently, partial data from the echo can be extracted for signal processing, significantly reducing random errors and improving the single-shot precision of LLR. The distance obtained by extracting part of the echo can be reduced to the center position of the array, thereby providing multiple higher-precision ranging results from each measurement. This not only improves the precision of LLR but also increases the data volume. A simulation experiment based on the 1.2 m laser ranging system at Yunnan Observatories was conducted. By extracting one peak for signal processing, the single-shot precision improved from 32.24 mm to 2.52 mm, validating the theoretical analysis results. Finally, an experimental laser ranging system based on a 53 cm binocular telescope system was established for ground experiments. The experimental results indicated that the echo signal could identify the tilt state of the CCR array. By extracting the peak returned by the central CCR for signal processing, the ranging precision was greatly improved. Through theoretical analyses, simulation experiments, and ground experiments, a solution to reduce the random errors caused by the tilt of the CCR array was provided. This offers an approach to enhance the single-shot precision of future LLR and provides a reference for upgrading ground-based equipment at future laser ranging stations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.09260v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/rs16163030</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Remote Sens. 2024, 16(16), 3030</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jin Cao (Yunnan Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, China, College of Mathematics and Physics, Leshan Normal University, Leshan, China, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China), Rufeng Tang (Yunnan Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, China), Kai Huang (Yunnan Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, China, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China), Zhulian Li (Yunnan Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, China), Yongzhang Yang (Yunnan Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, China), Kai Huang (Yunnan Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, China, University of Chinese Academy of Sciences, Beijing, China), Jintao Li (Yunnan Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, China), Yuqiang Li (Yunnan Observatories, Chinese Academy of Sciences, Kunming, China)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
