<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ins-det updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det</link>
    <description>physics.ins-det updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2024 04:00:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 25 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Neurophotonics beyond the Surface: Unmasking the Brain's Complexity Exploiting Optical Scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14809v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The intricate nature of the brain necessitates the application of advanced probing techniques to comprehensively study and understand its working mechanisms. Neurophotonics offers minimally invasive methods to probe the brain using optics at cellular and even molecular levels. However, multiple challenges persist, especially concerning imaging depth, field of view, speed, and biocompatibility. A major hindrance to solving these challenges in optics is the scattering nature of the brain. This perspective highlights the potential of complex media optics, a specialized area of study focused on light propagation in materials with intricate heterogeneous optical properties, in advancing and improving neuronal readouts for structural imaging and optical recordings of neuronal activity. Key strategies include wavefront shaping techniques and computational imaging and sensing techniques that exploit scattering properties for enhanced performance. We discuss the potential merger of the two fields as well as potential challenges and perspectives toward longer term in vivo applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14809v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fei Xia, Caio Vaz Rimoli, Walther Akemann, Cathie Ventalon, Laurent Bourdieu, Sylvain Gigan, Hilton B de Aguiar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing Electrical Properties of A Silicon Nanocrystal Thin Film Using X-ray Photoelectron Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14865v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We performed X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS) measurements on a thin film of Si nanocrystals (SiNCs) while applying DC or AC external biases to extract the resistance and the capacitance of the thin film. The measurement consists of the application of 10 V DC or square wave pulses of 10 V amplitude to the sample at various frequencies ranging from 0.01 Hz to 1 MHz while recording X-ray photoemission data. To analyze the data, we propose three different models with varying degrees of accuracy. The calculated capacitance of SiNCs agrees with the experimental value in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14865v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0090166</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rev. Sci. Instrum. 93, 083906 (2022)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Amrit Laudari, Sameera Pathiranage, Salim A. Thomas, Reed J. Petersen, Kenneth J. Anderson, Todd A. Pringle, Erik K. Hobbie, Nuri Oncel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Offline tagging of radon-induced backgrounds in XENON1T and applicability to other liquid xenon detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14878v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper details the first application of a software tagging algorithm to reduce radon-induced backgrounds in liquid noble element time projection chambers, such as XENON1T and XENONnT. The convection velocity field in XENON1T was mapped out using $^{222}\text{Rn}$ and $^{218}\text{Po}$ events, and the root-mean-square convection speed was measured to be $0.30 \pm 0.01$ cm/s. Given this velocity field, $^{214}\text{Pb}$ background events can be tagged when they are followed by $^{214}\text{Bi}$ and $^{214}\text{Po}$ decays, or preceded by $^{218}\text{Po}$ decays. This was achieved by propagating a point cloud as directed by the velocity field, and searching for $^{214}\text{Bi}$ and $^{214}\text{Po}$ decays or $^{218}\text{Po}$ decays within a volume defined by the point cloud. In XENON1T, this tagging system achieved a $^{214}\text{Pb}$ background reduction of $6.2^{+0.4}_{-0.9}\%$ with an exposure loss of $1.8\pm 0.2 \%$. The tagging algorithm was also used to produce a population of tagged events with a large enhancement in the $^{214}\text{Pb}$ fraction. We show that the performance can be improved in XENONnT, and that the performance of such a software-tagging approach can be expected to be further improved in a diffusion-limited scenario. Finally, a similar method might be useful to tag the cosmogenic $^{137}\text{Xe}$ background, which is relevant to the search for neutrinoless double-beta decay.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14878v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Aprile, J. Aalbers, K. Abe, S. Ahmed Maouloud, L. Althueser, B. Andrieu, E. Angelino, J. R. Angevaare, D. Ant\'on Martin, F. Arneodo, L. Baudis, A. L. Baxter, M. Bazyk, L. Bellagamba, R. Biondi, A. Bismark, E. J. Brookes, A. Brown, G. Bruno, R. Budnik, T. K. Bui, J. M. R. Cardoso, A. P. Cimental Chavez, A. P. Colijn, J. Conrad, J. J. Cuenca-Garc\'ia, V. D'Andrea, L. C. Daniel Garcia, M. P. Decowski, C. Di Donato, P. Di Gangi, S. Diglio, K. Eitel, A. Elykov, A. D. Ferella, C. Ferrari, H. Fischer, T. Flehmke, M. Flierman, W. Fulgione, C. Fuselli, P. Gaemers, R. Gaior, M. Galloway, F. Gao, S. Ghosh, R. Glade-Beucke, L. Grandi, J. Grigat, H. Guan, M. Guida, R. Hammann, A. Higuera, C. Hils, L. Hoetzsch, N. F. Hood, M. Iacovacci, Y. Itow, J. Jakob, F. Joerg, A. Joy, Y. Kaminaga, M. Kara, P. Kavrigin, S. Kazama, M. Kobayashi, A. Kopec, F. Kuger, H. Landsman, R. F. Lang, L. Levinson, I. Li, S. Li, S. Liang, Y. T. Lin, S. Lindemann, M. Lindner, K. Liu, J. Loizeau, F. Lombardi, J. Long, J. A. M. Lopes, T. Luce, Y. Ma, C. Macolino, J. Mahlstedt, A. Mancuso, L. Manenti, F. Marignetti, T. Marrod\'an Undagoitia, K. Martens, J. Masbou, E. Masson, S. Mastroianni, A. Melchiorre, M. Messina, A. Michael, K. Miuchi, A. Molinario, S. Moriyama, K. Mor{\aa}, Y. Mosbacher, M. Murra, J. M\"uller, K. Ni, U. Oberlack, B. Paetsch, J. Palacio, Y. Pan, Q. Pellegrini, R. Peres, C. Peters, J. Pienaar, M. Pierre, G. Plante, T. R. Pollmann, L. Principe, J. Qi, J. Qin, D. Ram\'irez Garc\'ia, M. Rajado, J. Shi, R. Singh, L. Sanchez, J. M. F. dos Santos, I. Sarnoff, G. Sartorelli, J. Schreiner, D. Schulte, P. Schulte, H. Schulze Ei{\ss}ing, M. Schumann, L. Scotto Lavina, M. Selvi, F. Semeria, P. Shagin, S. Shi, M. Silva, H. Simgen, A. Takeda, P. -L. Tan, A. Terliuk, D. Thers, F. Toschi, G. Trinchero, C. Tunnell, F. T\"onnies, K. Valerius, S. Vecchi, S. Vetter, G. Volta, C. Weinheimer, M. Weiss, D. Wenz, C. Wittweg, T. Wolf, V. H. S. Wu, Y. Xing, D. Xu, Z. Xu, M. Yamashita, L. Yang, J. Ye, L. Yuan, G. Zavattini, M. Zhong, T. Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimisation of photodetectors design: comparison between Montecarlo and Genetic Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14913v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present Montecarlo and Genetic Algorithm optimisations applied to the design of photodetectors based on a transimpedance amplifier and a photodiode. The circuit performance is evaluated with a merit function and the systematic search method is used as a reference. The design parameters are the feedback network components and the photodiode bias voltage. To evaluate the optimisations, we define the relative difference between its merit and the optimum merit obtained by the systematic search. In both algorithms, the relative difference decreases with the number of evaluations, following a power law. The power-law exponent for the Genetic Algorithm is larger than that of Montecarlo (0.74 vs. 0.50). We conclude that both algorithms are advantageous compared to the systematic search method, and that the Genetic Algorithm shows a better performance than Montecarlo.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14913v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patricia M. E. V\'azquez, Ligia Ciocci Brazzano, Francisco E. Veiras, Patricio A. Sorichetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design of an atmospheric muon tomographer for material identification based on CORSIKA+GEANT4 simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14948</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14948v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent years, muon tomography has turned into a powerful and innovative technique for non-invasive imaging of large and small structures with applications in different areas like geology, archaeology, security, etc. We present the design and simulation of a transportable and easy to construct detector based on plastic scintillator and Silicon photomultipliers current technology. From a flux of cosmic rays reaching the atmosphere we simulated atmospheric muons at ground using CORSIKA. The detector and the object to analyze are simulated with GEANT4, where the previously obtained muon flux is transported. We use two methods for muon tomography to differentiate objects made of different materials: absorption and scattering. The statistical differences for several object sizes and materials are quantified. Using a threshold of 3 $\sigma$ in the first method, we conclude that materials made of lead can be differentiated from objects made of other materials. The observation time needed to differentiate an object made of lead from one of aluminum was 4.9 and 9.9 days using the first and second method, respectively. In general, the absorption method gives the best results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14948v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. A. Rengifo, J. L. Bazo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Broad Instantaneous Bandwidth Microwave Spectrum Analyzer with a Microfabricated Atomic Vapor Cell</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15155v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report on broad instantaneous bandwidth microwave spectrum analysis with hot $^{87}\mathrm{Rb}$ atoms in a microfabricated vapor cell in a large magnetic field gradient. The sensor is a MEMS atomic vapor cell filled with isotopically pure $^{87}\mathrm{Rb}$ and $\mathrm{N}_2$ buffer gas to localize the motion of the atoms. The microwave signals of interest are coupled through a coplanar waveguide to the cell, inducing spin flip transitions between optically pumped ground states of the atoms. A static magnetic field with large gradient maps the $\textit{frequency spectrum}$ of the input microwave signals to a position-dependent $\textit{spin-flip pattern}$ on absorption images of the cell recorded with a laser beam onto a camera. In our proof-of-principle experiment, we demonstrate a microwave spectrum analyzer that has $\approx$ 1 GHz instantaneous bandwidth centered at 13.165 GHz, 3 MHz frequency resolution, 2 kHz refresh rate, and a -23 dBm single-tone microwave power detection limit in 1 s measurement time. A theoretical model is constructed to simulate the image signals by considering the processes of optical pumping, microwave interaction, diffusion of $^{87}\mathrm{Rb}$ atoms, and laser absorption. We expect to reach more than 25 GHz instantaneous bandwidth in an optimized setup, limited by the applied magnetic field gradient. Our demonstration offers a practical alternative to conventional microwave spectrum analyzers based on electronic heterodyne detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15155v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongqi Shi, Thomas Ruster, Melvyn Ho, Sylvain Karlen, Jacques Haesler, Philipp Treutlein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The sPHENIX Micromegas Outer Tracker</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13789v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The sPHENIX Time Projection Chamber Outer Tracker (TPOT) is a Micromegas based detector. It is a part of the sPHENIX experiment that aims to facilitate the calibration of the Time Projection Chamber, in particular the correction of the time-averaged and beam-induced distortions of the electron drift. This paper describes the detector mission, setup, construction, installation, commissioning and performance during the first year of sPHENIX data taking.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13789v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Aune, B. Azmoun, A. Bonenfant, S. Boose, M. Bregant, D. Cacace, R. W. da Silva, R. Feder, A. Francisco, C. Goblin, A. Grabas, J. S. Haggerty, R. A. Hernandez, H. D. H. Herrera, J. Huang, J. Kelsey, I. Kotov, J. Kuczewski, I. Mandjavidze, T. A. Martins, J. Mead, J. Mills, A. Oskarsson, H. Pereira Da Costa, C. Pinkenburg, R. Pisani, T. Protzman, M. L. Purschke, E. Renner, R. Ruggiero, T. Sakaguchi, B. C. S. Sanches, B. Sayki, D. Silvermyr, W. Sondheim, M. Vandenbroucke, W. A. M. Van Noije, J. Vasquez, C. Vidal, A. Wils</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of ambient radon progeny decay rates and energy spectra in liquid argon using the MicroBooNE detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.03102</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.03102v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report measurements of radon progeny in liquid argon within the MicroBooNE time projection chamber (LArTPC). The presence of specific radon daughters in MicroBooNE's 85 metric tons of active liquid argon bulk is probed with newly developed charge-based low-energy reconstruction tools and analysis techniques to detect correlated $^{214}$Bi-$^{214}$Po radioactive decays. Special datasets taken during periods of active radon doping enable new demonstrations of the calorimetric capabilities of single-phase neutrino LArTPCs for $\beta$ and $\alpha$ particles with electron-equivalent energies ranging from 0.1 to 3.0 MeV. By applying $^{214}$Bi-$^{214}$Po detection algorithms to data recorded over a 46-day period, no statistically significant presence of radioactive $^{214}$Bi is detected, and a limit on the activity is placed at $&lt;0.35$ mBq/kg at the 95% confidence level. This bulk $^{214}$Bi radiopurity limit -- the first ever reported for a liquid argon detector incorporating liquid-phase purification -- is then further discussed in relation to the targeted upper limit of 1 mBq/kg on bulk $^{222}$Rn activity for the DUNE neutrino detector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.03102v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.052007</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 052007 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> MicroBooNE collaboration, P. Abratenko, O. Alterkait, D. Andrade Aldana, L. Arellano, J. Asaadi, A. Ashkenazi, S. Balasubramanian, B. Baller, G. Barr, D. Barrow, J. Barrow, V. Basque, O. Benevides Rodrigues, S. Berkman, A. Bhanderi, A. Bhat, M. Bhattacharya, M. Bishai, A. Blake, B. Bogart, T. Bolton, J. Y. Book, L. Camilleri, Y. Cao, D. Caratelli, I. Caro Terrazas, F. Cavanna, G. Cerati, Y. Chen, J. M. Conrad, M. Convery, L. Cooper-Troendle, J. I. Crespo-Anadon, R. Cross, M. Del Tutto, S. R. Dennis, P. Detje, A. Devitt, R. Diurba, Z. Djurcic, R. Dorrill, K. Duffy, S. Dytman, B. Eberly, P. Englezos, A. Ereditato, J. J. Evans, R. Fine, O. G. Finnerud, B. T. Fleming, N. Foppiani, W. Foreman, D. Franco, A. P. Furmanski, D. Garcia-Gamez, S. Gardiner, G. Ge, S. Gollapinni, O. Goodwin, E. Gramellini, P. Green, H. Greenlee, W. Gu, R. Guenette, P. Guzowski, L. Hagaman, O. Hen, R. Hicks, C. Hilgenberg, G. A. Horton-Smith, Z. Imani, B. Irwin, R. Itay, C. James, X. Ji, L. Jiang, J. H. Jo, R. A. Johnson, Y. J. Jwa, D. Kalra, N. Kamp, G. Karagiorgi, W. Ketchum, M. Kirby, T. Kobilarcik, I. Kreslo, M. B. Leibovitch, I. Lepetic, J. -Y. Li, K. Li, Y. Li, K. Lin, B. R. Littlejohn, H. Liu, W. C. Louis, X. Luo, C. Mariani, D. Marsden, J. Marshall, N. Martinez, D. A. Martinez Caicedo, S. Martynenko, A. Mastbaum, N. McConkey, V. Meddage, J. Micallef, K. Miller, K. Mistry, T. Mohayai, A. Mogan, M. Mooney, A. F. Moor, C. D. Moore, L. Mora Lepin, M. Moudgalya, S. Mulleria Babu, D. Naples, A. Navrer-Agasson, N. Nayak, M. Nebot-Guinot, J. Nowak, N. Oza, O. Palamara, N. Pallat, V. Paolone, A. Papadopoulou, V. Papavassiliou, H. Parkinson, S. F. Pate, N. Patel, Z. Pavlovic, E. Piasetzky, I. Ponce-Pinto, I. Pophale, X. Qian, J. L. Raaf, V. Radeka, A. Rafique, M. Reggiani-Guzzo, L. Ren, L. Rochester, J. Rodriguez Rondon, M. Rosenberg, M. Ross-Lonergan, C. Rudolph von Rohr, I. Safa, G. Scanavini, D. W. Schmitz, A. Schukraft, W. Seligman, M. H. Shaevitz, R. Sharankova, J. Shi, E. L. Snider, M. Soderberg, S. Soldner-Rembold, J. Spitz, M. Stancari, J. St. John, T. Strauss, A. M. Szelc, W. Tang, N. Taniuchi, K. Terao, C. Thorpe, D. Torbunov, D. Totani, M. Toups, Y. -T. Tsai, J. Tyler, M. A. Uchida, T. Usher, B. Viren, M. Weber, H. Wei, A. J. White, Z. Williams, S. Wolbers, T. Wongjirad, M. Wospakrik, K. Wresilo, N. Wright, W. Wu, E. Yandel, T. Yang, L. E. Yates, H. W. Yu, G. P. Zeller, J. Zennamo, C. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
