<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ins-det updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det</link>
    <description>physics.ins-det updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 04:00:58 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Threshold bounce -- occupancy-dependent modulation of the discriminating threshold in silicon detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10747v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The front-end electronics of silicon detectors are typically designed to ensure optimal noise performance for the expected input charge. A combination of preamplifiers and shaper circuits result in a nontrivial response of the front-end to injected charge, and the magnitude of the response may be sizeable in readout windows subsequent to that in which the charge was initially injected. The modulation of the discriminator threshold due to the superposition of the front-end response across multiple readout windows is coined "threshold bounce".
  In this paper, we report a measurement of threshold bounce using silicon modules built for the Phase-II Upgrade of the ATLAS detector at the Large Hadron Collider. These modules utilize ATLAS Binary Chips for their hit readout. The measurement was performed using a micro-focused 15 keV photon beam at the Diamond Light Source synchrotron. The effect of the choice of photon flux and discriminator threshold on the magnitude of the threshold bounce is studied. A Monte Carlo simulation which accounts for the front-end behaviour of the silicon modules is developed, and its predicted hit efficiency is found to be in good agreement with the measured hit efficiency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10747v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. J. Basso, E. Buchanan, B. J. Gallop, J. J. John, J. Kaplon, P. T. Keener, P. W. Phillips, L. Poley, C. A. Sawyer, D. Sperlich, M. Warren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implementing dynamic high-performance computing supported workflows on Scanning Transmission Electron Microscope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11018v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scanning Transmission Electron Microscopy (STEM) coupled with Electron Energy Loss Spectroscopy (EELS) presents a powerful platform for detailed material characterization via rich imaging and spectroscopic data. Modern electron microscopes can access multiple length scales and sampling rates far beyond human perception and reaction time. Recent advancements in machine learning (ML) offer a promising avenue to enhance these capabilities by integrating ML algorithms into the STEM-EELS framework, fostering an environment of active learning. This work enables the seamless integration of STEM with High-Performance Computing (HPC) systems. We present several implemented workflows that exemplify this integration. These workflows include sophisticated techniques such as object finding and Deep Kernel Learning (DKL). Through these developments, we demonstrate how the fusion of STEM-EELS with ML and HPC enhances the efficiency and scope of material characterization for 70% STEM available globally. The codes are available at GitHub link.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11018v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Utkarsh Pratiush, Austin Houston, Sergei V Kalinin, Gerd Duscher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GRAPH -- An readout ASIC for large MCP based detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11067v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a programmable 16 channel, mixed signal, low power readout ASIC, having the project historically named Gigasample Recorder of Analog waveforms from a PHotodetector (GRAPH). It is designed to read large aperture single photon imaging detectors using micro channel plates for charge multiplication, and measuring the detector's response on crossed strips anodes to extrapolate the incoming photon position. Each channel consists of a fast, low power and low noise charge sensitive amplifier, which provides a myriad of coarse and fine programmable options for gain and shaping settings. Further, the amplified signal is recorded using, to our knowledge novel, the Hybrid Universal sampLing Architecture (HULA), a mixed signal double buffer memory, that enables concurrent waveform recording, and selected event digitized data extraction. The sampling frequency is freely adjustable between few~kHz up to 125~MHz, while the chip's internal digital memory holds a history 2048 samples for each channel, with a digital headroom of 12 bits. An optimized region of interest sample-read algorithm allows to extract the information just around the event pulse peak, while selecting the next event, thus substantially reducing the operational dead time. The chip is designed in 130~$n$m TSMC CMOS technology, and its power consumption is around 47~$m$W per channel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11067v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrej Seljak, John Vallerga, Gang Liu, Rick Raffanti, Gary S. Varner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In Situ Dynamic Four-Dimensional Strong Field Ionization Tomography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10233v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an approach for in situ dynamic four-dimensional (4D=3D space + 1D time) laser induced strong field ionization tomography, particularly suited for measuring far-from-equilibrium systems, such as supersonic and hypersonic pulsed gas jets. The inherent physical nature of strong-field interaction leads to significantly enhanced spatial resolution, with unique intensity-resolution coupling and localization of measurement depth. By employing femtosecond laser, temporal resolution is primarily limited by electronic jitter, typically to a few tens of picoseconds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10233v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noam Shlomo, Eugene Frumker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astronomical Spectroscopy with Skipper CCDs: First Results from a Skipper CCD Focal Plane Prototype at SIFS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10756v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the first on-sky results from an ultra-low-readout-noise Skipper CCD focal plane prototype for the SOAR Integral Field Spectrograph (SIFS). The Skipper CCD focal plane consists of four 6k x 1k, 15 $\mu$m pixel, fully-depleted, p-channel devices that have been thinned to ~250 $\mu$m, backside processed, and treated with an anti-reflective coating. These Skipper CCDs were configured for astronomical spectroscopy, i.e., single-sample readout noise &lt; 4.3 e- rms/pixel, the ability to achieve multi-sample readout noise $\ll$ 1 e- rms/pixel, full-well capacities ~40,000-65,000 e-, low dark current and charge transfer inefficiency (~2 x 10$^{-4}$ e-/pixel/s and 3.44 x 10$^{-7}$, respectively), and an absolute quantum efficiency of $\gtrsim$ 80% between 450 nm and 980 nm ($\gtrsim$ 90% between 600 nm and 900 nm). We optimized the readout sequence timing to achieve sub-electron noise (~0.5 e- rms/pixel) in a region of 2k x 4k pixels and photon-counting noise (~0.22 e- rms/pixel) in a region of 220 x 4k pixels, each with a readout time of $\lesssim$ 17 min. We observed two quasars (HB89 1159+123 and QSO J1621-0042) at redshift z ~ 3.5, two high-redshift galaxy clusters (CL J1001+0220 and SPT-CL J2040-4451), an emission line galaxy at z = 0.3239, a candidate member star of the Bo\"{o}tes II ultra-faint dwarf galaxy, and five CALSPEC spectrophotometric standard stars (HD074000, HD60753, HD106252, HD101452, HD200654). We present charge-quantized, photon-counting observations of the quasar HB89 1159+123 and show the detector sensitivity increase for faint spectral features. We demonstrate signal-to-noise performance improvements for SIFS observations in the low-background, readout-noise-dominated regime. We outline scientific studies that will leverage the SIFS-Skipper CCD data and new detector architectures that utilize the Skipper floating gate amplifier with faster readout times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10756v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edgar Marrufo Villalpando, Alex Drlica-Wagner, Brandon Roach, Marco Bonati, Abhishek Bakshi, Julia Campa, Gustavo Cancelo, Braulio Cancino, Claudio R. Chavez, Fernando Chierchie, Juan Estrada, Guillermo Fernandez Moroni, Luciano Fraga, Manuel E. Gaido, Stephen E. Holland, Rachel Hur, Michelle Jonas, Peter Moore, Eduardo Paolini, Andr\'es A. Plazas Malag\'on, Leandro Stefanazzi, Javier Tiffenberg, Ken Treptou, Sho Uemura, Neal Wilcer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spinning Hall Probe magnetic compass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11487v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a large range of physics and space experiments, the direction of the magnetic field needs to be determined with an accuracy on the level of one milli radian or better. We have proposed a new type of magnetic compass - a rotation-based one, which provides an alternating signal from the Hall probe proportional to the value of the magnetic field transverse to the axis of rotation. The spinning Hall probe device has been realized. Alignment of the spinning axis for a minimum (zero) value of the signal allows us to find the direction of the magnetic field. The device does not require calibration and is free of any drift problems. The measurement of the rotation axis direction was accomplished by means of a laser and a flat mirror attached to the rotor. The constructed prototype achieved an accuracy for the magnetic field direction in the experiment with the polarized He-3 target on the level of one milli radian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11487v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Wojtsekhowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monte-Carlo ray-tracing studies of multiplexed prismatic graphite analyzers for the cold-neutron triple-axis spectrometer at the High Flux Isotope Reactor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.03233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.03233v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A modern cold triple-axis spectrometer to study quantum condensed matter systems is planned for the High Flux Isotope Reactor (HFIR) at Oak Ridge National Laboratory. Here, we describe the conceptual principles and design of a secondary spectrometer using a multiplexed, prismatic analyzer system relying on graphite crystals and inspired by the successful implementation of the Continuous Angle Multiple Energy Analysis (CAMEA) spectrometers at the Paul Scherrer Institute. This project is currently known as MANTA for Multi-analyzer Neutron Triple-Axis. We report Monte-Carlo ray-tracing simulations on a simple but realistic sample scattering kernel to further illustrate the prismatic analyzer concept's workings, calibration, and performance. Then, we introduce a new statistical analysis approach based on the prismatic analyzer concept to improve the number of final energies measured on the spectrometer. We also study possible evolutions in the CAMEA design relevant for MANTA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.03233v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nima.2024.169508</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Adit S. Desai, Travis J. Williams, Marcus Daum, Gabriele Sala, Adam A. Aczel, Garrett E. Granroth, Martin Mourigal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Waveform Simulation for Scintillation Characteristics of NaI(Tl) Crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.17125v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The lowering of the energy threshold in the NaI detector is crucial not only for comprehensive validation of DAMA/LIBRA but also for exploring new possibilities in the search for low-mass dark matter and observing coherent elastic scattering between neutrino and nucleus. Alongside hardware enhancements, extensive efforts have focused on refining event selection to discern noise, achieved through parameter development and the application of machine learning. Acquiring pure, unbiased datasets is crucial in this endeavor, for which a waveform simulation was developed. The simulation data were compared with the experimental data using several pulse shape discrimination parameters to test its performance in describing the experimental data. Additionally, we present the outcomes of multi-variable machine learning trained with simulation data as a scintillation signal sample. The distributions of outcomes for experimental and simulation data show a good agreement. As an application of the waveform simulation, we validate the trigger efficiency alongside estimations derived from the minimally biased measurement data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.17125v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nima.2024.169489</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>NIM A 1065, 169489 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>J. J. Choi, C. Ha, E. J. Jeon, K. W. Kim, S. K. Kim, Y. D. Kim, Y. J. Ko, B. C. Koh, H. S. Lee, S. H. Lee, S. M. Lee, B. J. Park, G. H. Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signal Response Model in PandaX-4T</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04239v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: PandaX-4T experiment is a deep-underground dark matter direct search experiment that employs a dual-phase time projection chamber with a sensitive volume containing 3.7 tonne of liquid xenon. The detector of PandaX-4T is capable of simultaneously collecting the primary scintillation and ionization signals, utilizing their ratio to discriminate dark matter signals from background sources such as gamma rays and beta particles. The signal response model plays a crucial role in interpreting the data obtained by PandaX-4T. It describes the conversion from the deposited energy by dark matter interactions to the detectable signals within the detector. The signal response model is utilized in various PandaX-4T results. This work provides a comprehensive description of the procedures involved in constructing and parameter-fitting the signal response model for the energy range of approximately 1 keV to 25 keV for electronic recoils and 6 keV to 90 keV for nuclear recoils. It also covers the signal reconstruction, selection, and correction methods, which are crucial components integrated into the signal response model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04239v3</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunyang Luo, Zihao Bo, Shibo Zhang, Abdusalam Abdukerim, Chen Cheng, Wei Chen, Xun Chen, Yunhua Chen, Zhaokan Cheng, Xiangyi Cui, Yingjie Fan, Deqing Fang, Changbo Fu, Mengting Fu, Lisheng Geng, Karl Giboni, Linhui Gu, Xuyuan Guo, Chencheng Han, Ke Han, Changda He, Jinrong He, Di Huang, Yanlin Huang, Zhou Huang, Ruquan Hou, Xiangdong Ji, Yonglin Ju, Chenxiang Li, Jiafu Li, Mingchuan Li, Shu Li, Shuaijie Li, Qing Lin, Jianglai Liu, Xiaoying Lu, Lingyin Luo, Wenbo Ma, Yugang Ma, Yajun Mao, Nasir Shaheed, Yue Meng, Xuyang Ning, Ningchun Qi, Zhicheng Qian, Xiangxiang Ren, Changsong Shang, Xiaofeng Shang, Guofang Shen, Lin Si, Wenliang Sun, Andi Tan, Yi Tao, Anqing Wang, Meng Wang, Qiuhong Wang, Shaobo Wang, Siguang Wang, Wei Wang, Xiuli Wang, Zhou Wang, Yuehuan Wei, Mengmeng Wu, Weihao Wu, Jingkai Xia, Mengjiao Xiao, Xiang Xiao, Pengwei Xie, Binbin Yan, Xiyu Yan, Jijun Yang, Yong Yang, Chunxu Yu, Jumin Yuan, Ying Yuan, Zhe Yuan, Xinning Zeng, Dan Zhang, Minzhen Zhang, Peng Zhang, Shu Zhang, Tao Zhang, Yingxin Zhang, Yuanyuan Zhang, Li Zhao, Qibin Zheng, Jifang Zhou, Ning Zhou, Xiaopeng Zhou, Yong Zhou, Yubo Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On-chip multi-degree-of-freedom control of two-dimensional quantum and nonlinear materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.12030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.12030v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Two-dimensional materials (2DM) and their derived heterostructures have electrical and optical properties that are widely tunable via several approaches, most notably electrostatic gating and interfacial engineering such as twisting. While electrostatic gating is simple and has been ubiquitously employed on 2DM, being able to tailor the interfacial properties in a similar real-time manner represents the next leap in our ability to modulate the underlying physics and build exotic devices with 2DM. However, all existing approaches rely on external machinery such as scanning microscopes, which often limit their scope of applications, and there is currently no means of tuning a 2D interface that has the same accessibility and scalability as electrostatic gating. Here, we demonstrate the first on-chip platform designed for 2D materials with in situ tunable interfacial properties, utilizing a microelectromechanical system (MEMS). Each compact, cost-effective, and versatile device is a standalone micromachine that allows voltage-controlled approaching, twisting, and pressurizing of 2DM with high accuracy. As a demonstration, we engineer synthetic topological singularities, known as merons, in the nonlinear optical susceptibility of twisted hexagonal boron nitride (h-BN), via simultaneous control of twist angle and interlayer separation. The chirality of the resulting moire pattern further induces a strong circular dichroism in the second-harmonic generation. A potential application of this topological nonlinear susceptibility is to create integrated classical and quantum light sources that have widely and real-time tunable polarization. Our invention pushes the boundary of available technologies for manipulating low-dimensional quantum materials, which in turn opens up the gateway for designing future hybrid 2D-3D devices for condensed-matter physics, quantum optics, and beyond.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.12030v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoning Tang, Yiting Wang, Xueqi Ni, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Pablo Jarillo-Herrero, Shanhui Fan, Eric Mazur, Amir Yacoby, Yuan Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of a cubic cavity resonator for gravitational waves detection in the microwave frequency range</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.02270v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The direct detection of gravitational waves (GWs) of frequencies above MHz has recently received considerable attention. In this work we present a precise study of the reach of a cubic cavity resonator to GWs in the microwave range, using for the first time tools allowing to perform realistic simulations. Concretely, the BI-RME 3D method, which allows us to obtain not only the detected power but also the detected voltage (magnitude and phase), is used here. After analyzing three cubic cavities for different frequencies and working simultaneously with three different degenerate modes at each cavity, we conclude that the sensitivity of the experiment is strongly dependent on the polarization and incidence angle of the GW. The presented experiment can reach sensitivities up to $ 1 \cdot 10^{-19}$ at 100\, MHz, $ 2 \cdot 10^{-20}$ at 1\, GHz, and $ 6 \cdot 10^{-19}$ at 10\, GHz for optimal angles and polarizations, and where in all cases we assumed an integration time of $\Delta t = 1$ ms. These results provide a strong case for further developing the use of cavities to detect GWs. Moreover, the possibility of analyzing the detected voltage (magnitude and phase) opens a new interferometric detection scheme based on the combination of the detected signals from multiple cavities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.02270v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Navarro, Benito Gimeno, Juan Monz\'o-Cabrera, Alejandro D\'iaz-Morcillo, Diego Blas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autonomous programmable microscopic electronic lablets optimized with digital control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20110v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Lablets are autonomous microscopic particles with programmable CMOS electronics that can control electrokinetic phenomena and electrochemical reactions in solution via actuator and sensor microelectrodes. In this paper, we describe the design and fabrication of optimized singulated lablets (CMOS3) with dimensions 140x140x50 micrometers carrying an integrated coplanar encapsulated supercapacitor as a rechargeable power supply. The lablets are designed to allow docking to one another or to a smart surface for interchange of energy, electronic information, and chemicals. The paper focusses on the digital and analog design of the lablets to allow significant programmable functionality in a microscopic footprint, including the control of autonomous actuation and sensing up to the level of being able to support a complete lablet self-reproduction life cycle, although experimentally this remains to be proven. The potential of lablets in autonomous sensing and control and for evolutionary experimentation are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20110v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Maeke, John McCaskill, Dominic Funke, Pierre Mayr, Abhishek Sharma, Uwe Tangen, J\"urgen Oehm</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
