<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ins-det updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det</link>
    <description>physics.ins-det updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 04:00:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An extreme thermal cycling reliability test of ATLAS ITk Strips barrel modules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06370</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06370v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: At the end of Run 3 of the Large Hadron Collider (LHC), the accelerator complex will be upgraded to the High-Luminosity LHC (HL-LHC) in order to increase the total amount of data provided to its experiments. To cope with the increased rates of data, radiation, and pileup, the ATLAS detector will undergo a substantial upgrade, including a replacement of the Inner Detector with a future Inner Tracker, called the ITk. The ITk will be composed of pixel and strip sub-detectors, where the strips portion will be composed of 17,888 silicon strip detector modules. During the HL-LHC running period, the ITk will be cooled and warmed a number of times from about ${-35}^\circ$C to room temperature as part of the operational cycle, including warm-ups during yearly shutdowns. To ensure ITk Strips modules are functional after these expected temperature changes, and to ensure modules are mechanically robust, each module must undergo ten thermal cycles and pass a set of electrical and mechanical criteria before it is placed on a local support structure. This paper describes the thermal cycling Quality Control (QC) procedure, and results from the barrel pre-production phase (about 5% of the production volume). Additionally, in order to assess the headroom of the nominal QC procedure of 10 cycles and to ensure modules don't begin failing soon after, four representative ITk Strips barrel modules were thermally cycled 100 times - this study is also described.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06370v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Tishelman-Charny, A. Affolder, F. Capocasa, E. Duden, V. Fadeyev, M. Gignac, C. Helling, H. Herde, J. Johnson, D. Lynn, M. Morii, A. Mitra, L. Poley, G. Sciolla, S. Stucci, P. Sharma, G. Van Nieuwenhuizen, E. Wallin, A. Wang, S. Wonsak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra-stable 3D-printed precision voltage divider for calibrations and experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06700v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents the concept of an ultra-stable, thermally independent precision voltage divider tailored for direct current (DC) voltages up to 60 kV. Key features of this voltage divider include minimal voltage dependence, excellent stability, and resistance to external temperature variations. The innovative approach involves its fabrication using 3D printing technology, allowing easy replication by project partners. This precision voltage divider leverages commercially available precision resistors, drawing upon successful outcomes from the FutureEnergy 19ENG02 and HVDC ENG07 Projects. In these experiments, which involve ion acceleration and laser probing of electronic transitions, voltage dividers are integrated into setups such as COALA (TU Darmstadt), BECOLA (Michigan State University), COLLAPS (CERN/ISOLDE), and ATLANTIS (Argonne National Laboratory). Monitoring the applied acceleration potential, these dividers allow one to consider and counteract long-term drifts and thereby improving measurement accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06700v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephan Passon, Kristian K\"onig, Florian Schilling, Bernhard Maa{\ss}, Johann Meisner, Wilfried N\"ortersh\"auser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Back-End Electronics Based on Fiber Communication for Small to Medium-Scale Physics Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many small and medium-sized physics experiments are being conducted worldwide. These experiments have similar requirements for readout electronics, especially the back-end electronics. Some experiments need a trigger logic unit(TLU) to provide timing and synchronous control signals. This paper introduces a back-end electronics design for small and medium-sized physics experiments; it adopts a daughter-motherboard structure integrated TLU function to provide greater flexibility. Different interfaces and protocols can be flexibly selected according to data bandwidth requirements. It supports 32 optical fiber interfaces based on a field-programmable gate array (FPGA) of normal IOs with 400Mbps of data bandwidth for each channel. At the same time, it supports 16 high-speed communication interfaces based on GTX port with several Gbps data bandwidth of each channel. For the TLU function, this design has 8 HDMI interfaces and one RJ45 interface to provide synchronous triggers and other control signals, and it has six analog LEMOs and four digital LEMOs to accept asynchronous signals from an external source. These design specifications can meet the needs of most small and medium-sized experiments. This set of back-end electronics has been successfully used in experiments such as PandaX-III, VLAST, and moungraphy. Moreover, it has successfully conducted beam tests with a readout of the data of VLAST detectors at CERN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06786v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianguo Liu, Yu Wang, Changqing Feng, Shubin Liu, Qian Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Frequency Mixing using an NV Diamond Microscope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.07025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.07025v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Wide-field magnetic microscopy using nitrogen-vacancy (NV) centers in diamond can yield high-quality magnetic images of DC and AC magnetic fields. The unique combination of micron-scale spatial resolution of scalar or vector fields at room temperature and parallel camera readout make this an appealing technique for applications in biology, geology, condensed-matter physics, and electronics. However, while NV magnetic microscopy has achieved great success in these areas, historically the accessible frequency range has been limited. In this paper, we overcome this limitation by implementing the recently developed technique of quantum frequency mixing. With this approach, we generate wide-field magnetic images of test structures driven by alternating currents up to 70 MHz, well outside the reach of DC and Rabi magnetometry methods. With further improvements, this approach could find utility in hyperspectral imaging for electronics power spectrum analysis, electronics diagnostics and troubleshooting, and quantum computing hardware validation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.07025v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel J. Karlson, Pauli Kehayias, Jennifer M. Schloss, Andrew C. Maccabe, David F. Phillips, Guoqing Wang, Paola Cappellaro, Danielle A. Braje</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The impact of microwave phase noise on diamond quantum sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06465</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06465v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Precision optical measurements of the electron-spin precession of nitrogen-vacancy (NV) centers in diamond form the basis of numerous applications. The most sensitivity-demanding applications, such as femtotesla magnetometry, require the ability to measure changes in GHz spin transition frequencies at the sub-millihertz level, corresponding to a fractional resolution of better than 10^{-12}. Here we study the impact of microwave (MW) phase noise on the response of an NV sensor. Fluctuations of the phase of the MW waveform cause undesired rotations of the NV spin state. These fluctuations are imprinted in the optical readout signal and, left unmitigated, are indistinguishable from magnetic field noise. We show that the phase noise of several common commercial MW generators results in an effective pT s^{1/2}-range noise floor that varies with the MW carrier frequency and the detection frequency of the pulse sequence. The data are described by a frequency domain model incorporating the MW phase noise spectrum and the filter-function response of the sensing protocol. For controlled injection of white and random-walk phase noise, the observed NV magnetic noise floor is described by simple analytic expressions that accurately capture the scaling with pulse sequence length and the number of pi pulses. We outline several strategies to suppress the impact of MW phase noise and implement a version, based on gradiometry, that realizes a &gt;10-fold suppression. Our study highlights an important challenge in the pursuit of sensitive diamond quantum sensors and is applicable to other qubit systems with a large transition frequency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06465v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andris Berzins, Maziar Saleh Ziabari, Yaser Silani, Ilja Fescenko, Joshua T. Damron, John F. Barry, Andrey Jarmola, Pauli Kehayias, Bryan A. Richards, Janis Smits, Victor M. Acosta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Neutron Spectrometry for Fusion Plasmas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06743v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is very important to measure the plasma performances of fusion reactors such as fuel ion density, plasma temperature, fusion power, fast neutron energy, and neutron flux. Various diagnostic systems are needed to measure fast neutron properties in fusion plasmas. Generally, various types of neutron cameras and monitors are used. These systems are sensitive to neutron as well as gamma-ray radiation. Therefore, monitor systems that distinguish between neutron and gamma rays should be used. In this study, the NE-213 liquid scintillation detector was selected, and Pulse Shape Discriminator (PSD) NIM unit was used for the neutron/gamma-ray discrimination. True spectrum was found by unfolding the spectrum obtained by the reaction of neutrons to the protons in the detector with the FERD-PC computer code. In this study, the energy spectrum of fast neutrons produced in a neutron generator was measured by the unfolding method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06743v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Iskender Atilla Reyhancan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Xenon-gas ionization chamber to improve particle identification of heavy ion beams with Z&gt;70</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.08679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.08679v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In conventional ionization chambers (ICs) using P-10 (Ar+CH4) gas, as the atomic number (Z) of the ion beams increases in the energy region of 200-300 MeV/u, the Z resolution deteriorates rapidly when Z&gt;70. This degradation is attributed to substantial energy loss straggling caused by charge state fluctuation when the beams traverse a gas medium. The energy loss straggling increases when the beams cannot attain charge state equilibrium in the IC gas. In this study, a xenon-based gas (Xe+CH4), exhibiting a sufficiently large charge state changing cross section, was used in the IC to reach charge state equilibrium. The responses of ICs with P-10 and the xenon-based gases were examined using 238U beams and cocktail radioactive isotope (RI) beams with Z=40-90 at the RI Beam Factory (RIBF). For 238U beams at 165-344 MeV/u, the P-10 gas IC yielded an energy resolution of 1.9-3.0% in full width at half maximum (FWHM), which proved inadequate for Z identification in the uranium region. In contrast, the xenon-based gas IC demonstrated a satisfactory energy resolution of 1.4-1.6%. When using cocktail RI beams, a Z resolution of 1.28 and 0.74 was achieved by the P-10 and the xenon-based gas ICs, respectively, for beams with Z=84-88 at 200 MeV/u. The contrast in Z resolutions between the P-10 and the xenon-based gas ICs was effectively elucidated by the energy loss straggling model, incorporating collisional straggling and straggling due to charge state changes in the IC gases. The xenon-based gas IC, with more than 3sigma Z separation across a broad Z range (Z=40-90), emerged as a practical solution for Z identification of heavy ion beams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.08679v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masahiro Yoshimoto, Naoki Fukuda, Riku Matsumura, Daiki Nishimura, Hideaki Otsu, Yohei Shimizu, Toshiyuki Sumikama, Hiroshi Suzuki, Hiroyuki Takahashi, Hiroyuki Takeda, Junki Tanaka, Koichi Yoshida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanical detection of nuclear decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.13257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.13257v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the detection of individual nuclear $\alpha$ decays through the mechanical recoil of the entire micron-sized particle in which the decaying nuclei are embedded. Momentum conservation ensures that such measurements are sensitive to any particles emitted in the decay, including neutral particles that may otherwise evade detection with existing techniques. Detection of the minuscule recoil of an object more than $10^{12}$ times more massive than the emitted particles is made possible by recently developed techniques in levitated optomechanics, which enable high-precision optical control and measurement of the mechanical motion of optically trapped particles. Observation of a change in the net charge of the particle coincident with the recoil allows decays to be identified with background levels at the micro-Becquerel level. The techniques developed here may find use in fields ranging from nuclear forensics to dark matter and neutrino physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.13257v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.023602</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 023602 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxiang Wang, T. W. Penny, Juan Recoaro, Benjamin Siegel, Yu-Han Tseng, David C. Moore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low latency optical-based mode tracking with machine learning deployed on FPGAs on a tokamak</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.00128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.00128v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Active feedback control in magnetic confinement fusion devices is desirable to mitigate plasma instabilities and enable robust operation. Optical high-speed cameras provide a powerful, non-invasive diagnostic and can be suitable for these applications. In this study, we process fast camera data, at rates exceeding 100kfps, on $\textit{in situ}$ Field Programmable Gate Array (FPGA) hardware to track magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) mode evolution and generate control signals in real-time. Our system utilizes a convolutional neural network (CNN) model which predicts the $n$=1 MHD mode amplitude and phase using camera images with better accuracy than other tested non-deep-learning-based methods. By implementing this model directly within the standard FPGA readout hardware of the high-speed camera diagnostic, our mode tracking system achieves a total trigger-to-output latency of 17.6$\mu$s and a throughput of up to 120kfps. This study at the High Beta Tokamak-Extended Pulse (HBT-EP) experiment demonstrates an FPGA-based high-speed camera data acquisition and processing system, enabling application in real-time machine-learning-based tokamak diagnostic and control as well as potential applications in other scientific domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.00128v3</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>cs.AR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0190354</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rev. Sci. Instrum. 95, 073509 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yumou Wei, Ryan F. Forelli, Chris Hansen, Jeffrey P. Levesque, Nhan Tran, Joshua C. Agar, Giuseppe Di Guglielmo, Michael E. Mauel, Gerald A. Navratil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurements of low-energy nuclear recoil quenching factors for Na and I recoils in the NaI(Tl) scintillator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.15122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.15122v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Elastic scattering off nuclei in target detectors, involving interactions with dark matter and coherent elastic neutrino nuclear recoil (CE$\nu$NS), results in the deposition of low energy within the nuclei, dissipating rapidly through a combination of heat and ionization. The primary energy loss mechanism for nuclear recoil is heat, leading to consistently smaller measurable scintillation signals compared to electron recoils of the same energy. The nuclear recoil quenching factor (QF), representing the ratio of scintillation light yield produced by nuclear recoil to that of electron recoil at the same energy, is a critical parameter for understanding dark matter and neutrino interactions with nuclei. The low energy QF of NaI(Tl) crystals, commonly employed in dark matter searches and CE$\nu$NS measurements, is of substantial importance. Previous low energy QF measurements were constrained by contamination from photomultiplier tube (PMT)-induced noise, resulting in an observed light yield of approximately 15 photoelectrons per keVee (kilo-electron-volt electron-equivalent energy) and nuclear recoil energy above 5 keVnr (kilo-electron-volt nuclear recoil energy). Through enhanced crystal encapsulation, an increased light yield of around 26 photoelectrons per keVee is achieved. This improvement enables the measurement of the nuclear recoil QF for sodium nuclei at an energy of 3.8 $\pm$ 0.6 keVnr with a QF of 11.2 $\pm$ 1.7%. Furthermore, a reevaluation of previously reported QF results is conducted, incorporating enhancements in low energy events based on waveform simulation. The outcomes are generally consistent with various recent QF measurements for sodium and iodine.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.15122v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. H. Lee, H. W. Joo, H. J. Kim, K. W. Kim, S. K. Kim, Y. D. Kim, Y. J. Ko, H. S. Lee, J. Y. Lee, H. S. Park, Y. S. Yoon</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
