<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ins-det updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det</link>
    <description>physics.ins-det updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 02:47:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Projected background and sensitivity of AMoRE-II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09698v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: AMoRE-II aims to search for neutrinoless double beta decay with an array of 423 Li$_2$$^{100}$MoO$_4$ crystals operating in the cryogenic system as the main phase of the Advanced Molybdenum-based Rare process Experiment (AMoRE). AMoRE has been planned to operate in three phases: AMoRE-pilot, AMoRE-I, and AMoRE-II. AMoRE-II is currently being installed at the Yemi Underground Laboratory, located approximately 1000 meters deep in Jeongseon, Korea. The goal of AMoRE-II is to reach up to $T^{0\nu\beta\beta}_{1/2}$ $\sim$ 6 $\times$ 10$^{26}$ years, corresponding to an effective Majorana mass of 15 - 29 meV, covering all the inverted mass hierarchy regions. To achieve this, the background level of the experimental configurations and possible background sources of gamma and beta events should be well understood. We have intensively performed Monte Carlo simulations using the GEANT4 toolkit in all the experimental configurations with potential sources. We report the estimated background level that meets the 10$^{-4}$counts/(keV$\cdot$kg$\cdot$yr) requirement for AMoRE-II in the region of interest (ROI) and show the projected half-life sensitivity based on the simulation study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09698v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Agrawal, V. V. Alenkov, P. Aryal, J. Beyer, B. Bhandari, R. S. Boiko, K. Boonin, O. Buzanov, C. R. Byeon, N. Chanthima, M. K. Cheoun, J. S. Choe, Seonho Choi, S. Choudhury, J. S. Chung, F. A. Danevich, M. Djamal, D. Drung, C. Enss, A. Fleischmann, A. M. Gangapshev, L. Gastaldo, Y. M. Gavrilyuk, A. M. Gezhaev, O. Gileva, V. D. Grigorieva, V. I. Gurentsov, C. Ha, D. H. Ha, E. J. Ha, D. H. Hwnag, E. J. Jeona, J. A. Jeon, H. S. Jo, J. Kaewkhao, C. S. Kang, W. G. Kang, V. V. Kazalov, S. Kempf, A. Khan, S. Khan, D. Y. Kim, G. W. Kim, H. B. Kim, Ho-Jong Kim, H. J. Kim, H. L. Kim, H. S. Kim, M. B. Kim, S. C. Kim, S. K. Kim, S. R. Kim, W. T. Kim, Y. D. Kim, Y. H. Kim, K. Kirdsiri, Y. J. Ko, V. V. Kobychev, V. Kornoukhov V. V. Kuzminov, D. H. Kwon, C. H. Lee, DongYeup Lee, E. K. Lee, H. J. Lee, H. S. Lee, J. Lee, J. Y. Lee, K. B. Lee, M. H. Lee, M. K. Lee, S. W. Lee, Y. C. Lee, D. S. Leonard, H. S. Lim, B. Mailyan, E. P. Makarov, P. Nyanda, Y. Oh, S. L. Olsen, S. I. Panasenko, H. K. Park, H. S. Park, K. S. Park, S. Y. Park, O. G. Polischuk, H. Prihtiadi, S. Ra, S. S. Ratkevich G. Rooh, M. B. Sari, J. Seob, K. M. Seo, B. Sharma, K. A. Shin, V. N. Shlegel, K. Siyeon, J. So, N. V. Sokur, J. K. Son, J. W. Song, N. Srisittipokakun, V. I. Tretyak, R. Wirawan, K. R. Woo, H. J. Yeon, Y. S. Yoon, Q. Yue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MKIDGen3: Energy-Resolving, Single-Photon-Counting MKID Readout on an RFSoC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09764v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Building large, cryogenic MKID arrays requires processing highly-multiplexed, wideband readout signals in real time; a task that has previously required large, heavy, and power-intensive custom electronics. In this work, we present the third-generation UVOIR MKID readout system (Gen3) which is capable of reading out twice as many detectors with a fifth the weight and power and an order of magnitude less volume and cost-per-pixel as compared to the previous system. Gen3 leverages the Xilinx RFSoC4x2 platform to read out 2048, 1 MHz MKID channels per board. The system takes a modern approach to FPGA design using Vitis High-Level Synthesis (HLS) to specify signal processing blocks in C/C++, Vivado ML Intelligent Design Runs (IDR) to inform implementation stragety and close timing, and Python Productivity for ZYNQ (PYNQ) to simplify interacting with and programming the FPGA using Python. This design suite and tool flow allows general users to contribute to and maintain the design and positions Gen3 to rapidly migrate to future platforms as they become available. In this work, we describe the system requirements, design, and implementation. We also provide performance characterization details and show that the system achieves detector-limited resolving power in the case of few readout tones and minimal degradation with all 2048 tones. Planned upgrades and future work are also discussed. The Gen3 MKID readout system is fully open-source and is expected to facilitate future array scaling to megapixel-sized formats and increase the feasibility of deploying UVOIR MKIDs in space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09764v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jennifer Pearl Smith, John I. Bailey,  III., Aled Cuda, Nicholas Zobrist, Benjamin A. Mazin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computational generation of tailored radionuclide libraries for alpha-particle and gamma-ray spectrometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09560v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Radionuclide identification is a radioanalytical method employed in various scientific disciplines that utilize alpha-particle or gamma-ray spectrometric assays, ranging from astrophysics to nuclear medicine. Radionuclide libraries in conventional radionuclide identification systems are crafted in a manual fashion, accompanying labor-intensive and error-prone user tasks and hindering library customization. This research presents a computational algorithm and the architecture of its dedicated software that can automatically generate tailored radionuclide libraries. Progenitor-progeny recurrence relations were modeled to enable recursive computation of radionuclide subsets. This theoretical concept was incorporated into open-source software called RecurLib and validated against four actinide decay series and twelve radioactive substances, including a uranium-glazed legacy Fiestaware, natural uranium and thorium sources, a $^{226}$Ra sample, and the medical radionuclides $^{225}$Ac, $^{177}$Lu, and $^{99\text{m}}$Tc. The developed algorithm yielded radionuclide libraries for all the tested specimens within minutes, demonstrating its efficiency and applicability across diverse scenarios. The proposed approach introduces a framework for computerized radionuclide library generation, thereby trivializing library-driven radionuclide identification and facilitating the spectral recognition of unregistered radionuclides in radiation spectrometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09560v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaewoong Jang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving neutrino energy estimation of charged-current interaction events with recurrent neural networks in MicroBooNE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10123v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a deep learning-based method for estimating the neutrino energy of charged-current neutrino-argon interactions. We employ a recurrent neural network (RNN) architecture for neutrino energy estimation in the MicroBooNE experiment, utilizing liquid argon time projection chamber (LArTPC) detector technology. Traditional energy estimation approaches in LArTPCs, which largely rely on reconstructing and summing visible energies, often experience sizable biases and resolution smearing because of the complex nature of neutrino interactions and the detector response. The estimation of neutrino energy can be improved after considering the kinematics information of reconstructed final-state particles. Utilizing kinematic information of reconstructed particles, the deep learning-based approach shows improved resolution and reduced bias for the muon neutrino Monte Carlo simulation sample compared to the traditional approach. In order to address the common concern about the effectiveness of this method on experimental data, the RNN-based energy estimator is further examined and validated with dedicated data-simulation consistency tests using MicroBooNE data. We also assess its potential impact on a neutrino oscillation study after accounting for all statistical and systematic uncertainties and show that it enhances physics sensitivity. This method has good potential to improve the performance of other physics analyses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10123v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> MicroBooNE collaboration, P. Abratenko, O. Alterkait, D. Andrade Aldana, L. Arellano, J. Asaadi, A. Ashkenazi, S. Balasubramanian, B. Baller, A. Barnard, G. Barr, D. Barrow, J. Barrow, V. Basque, J. Bateman, O. Benevides Rodrigues, S. Berkman, A. Bhanderi, A. Bhat, M. Bhattacharya, M. Bishai, A. Blake, B. Bogart, T. Bolton, J. Y. Book, M. B. Brunetti, L. Camilleri, Y. Cao, D. Caratelli, F. Cavanna, G. Cerati, A. Chappell, Y. Chen, J. M. Conrad, M. Convery, L. Cooper-Troendle, J. I. Crespo-Anadon, R. Cross, M. Del Tutto, S. R. Dennis, P. Detje, R. Diurba, Z. Djurcic, R. Dorrill, K. Duffy, S. Dytman, B. Eberly, P. Englezos, A. Ereditato, J. J. Evans, R. Fine, B. T. Fleming, W. Foreman, D. Franco, A. P. Furmanski, F. Gao, D. Garcia-Gamez, S. Gardiner, G. Ge, S. Gollapinni, E. Gramellini, P. Green, H. Greenlee, L. Gu, W. Gu, R. Guenette, P. Guzowski, L. Hagaman, O. Hen, C. Hilgenberg, G. A. Horton-Smith, Z. Imani, B. Irwin, M. S. Ismail, C. James, X. Ji, J. H. Jo, R. A. Johnson, Y. J. Jwa, D. Kalra, N. Kamp, G. Karagiorgi, W. Ketchum, M. Kirby, T. Kobilarcik, I. Kreslo, N. Lane, I. Lepetic, J. -Y. Li, Y. Li, K. Lin, B. R. Littlejohn, H. Liu, W. C. Louis, X. Luo, C. Mariani, D. Marsden, J. Marshall, N. Martinez, D. A. Martinez Caicedo, S. Martynenko, A. Mastbaum, I. Mawby, N. McConkey, V. Meddage, J. Mendez, J. Micallef, K. Miller, K. Mistry, T. Mohayai, A. Mogan, M. Mooney, A. F. Moor, C. D. Moore, L. Mora Lepin, M. M. Moudgalya, S. Mulleria Babu, D. Naples, A. Navrer-Agasson, N. Nayak, M. Nebot-Guinot, J. Nowak, N. Oza, O. Palamara, N. Pallat, V. Paolone, A. Papadopoulou, V. Papavassiliou, H. Parkinson, S. F. Pate, N. Patel, Z. Pavlovic, E. Piasetzky, K. Pletcher, I. Pophale, X. Qian, J. L. Raaf, V. Radeka, A. Rafique, M. Reggiani-Guzzo, L. Ren, L. Rochester, J. Rodriguez Rondon, M. Rosenberg, M. Ross-Lonergan, I. Safa, G. Scanavini, D. W. Schmitz, A. Schukraft, W. Seligman, M. H. Shaevitz, R. Sharankova, J. Shi, E. L. Snider, M. Soderberg, S. Soldner-Rembold, J. Spitz, M. Stancari, J. St. John, T. Strauss, A. M. Szelc, W. Tang, N. Taniuchi, K. Terao, C. Thorpe, D. Torbunov, D. Totani, M. Toups, A. Trettin, Y. -T. Tsai, J. Tyler, M. A. Uchida, T. Usher, B. Viren, M. Weber, H. Wei, A. J. White, S. Wolbers, T. Wongjirad, M. Wospakrik, K. Wresilo, W. Wu, E. Yandel, T. Yang, L. E. Yates, H. W. Yu, G. P. Zeller, J. Zennamo, C. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$^6$Li-loaded liquid scintillators produced by direct dissolution of compounds in diisopropylnaphthalene (DIPN)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.16127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.16127v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The paper describes preparation of $^6$Li-loaded liquid scintillators by methods involving direct dissolution of $^6$Li salts in the commercial diisopropylnaphthalene (DIPN) solvent, without the formation of water-in-oil emulsions. Methods include incorporation of $^6$Li that, unlike previously reported formulations, does not require additions of water or a strong acid such as hydrochloric acid (HCl). Results of the conducted experiments show that dissolution of aromatic and aliphatic $^6$Li salts in DIPN can be easily achieved at 0.1- 0.3% by weight of atomic $^6$Li, using small additions of waterless surfactants, or mild carboxylic acids. An alternative way suggests incorporation of $^6$Li as a part of a surfactant molecule that can be dissolved in DIPN without any solubilizing additions. Proposed methods enable preparation of efficient $^6$Li-loaded liquid scintillators that, at a large scale of 50 cm, exhibit good pulse shape discrimination (PSD) properties combined with up to 107% of light output and up to 115% of the attenuation length measured relative to standard undoped EJ-309 liquid scintillator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.16127v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nima.2023.168389</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nucl.Instrum.Meth.A 1054 (2023) 168389</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>N. P. Zaitseva, M. L. Carman, M. J. Ford, A. M. Glenn, C. Roca, S. Durham, F. Sutanto, S. A. Dazeley, N. S. Bowden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Superconducting Quasiparticle-Amplifying Transmon: A Qubit-Based Sensor for meV Scale Phonons and Single THz Photons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.01345v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With great interest from the quantum computing community, an immense amount of R&amp;D effort has been invested into improving superconducting qubits. The technologies developed for the design and fabrication of these qubits can be directly applied to applications for ultra-low threshold particle detectors, e.g. low-mass dark matter and far-IR photon sensing. We propose a novel sensor based on the transmon qubit architecture combined with a signal-enhancing superconducting quasiparticle amplification stage. We refer to these sensors as SQUATs: Superconducting Quasiparticle-Amplifying Transmons. We detail the operating principle and design of this new sensor and predict that with minimal R&amp;D effort, solid-state based detectors patterned with these sensors can achieve sensitivity to single THz photons, and sensitivity to $1\,\mathrm{meV}$ phonons in the detector absorber substrate on the $\mu\mathrm{s}$ timescale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.01345v3</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caleb W. Fink, Chiara P. Salemi, Betty A. Young, David I. Schuster, Noah A. Kurinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Liquid $^3$He Detectors for Neutrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.10258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.10258v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The $^3$He(n,p) process is excellent for neutron detection between thermal and $\sim$4\,MeV because of the high cross section and near-complete energy transfer from the neutron to the proton. Traditional gaseous $^3$He detectors using this process typically have high levels of radiogenic backgrounds so that they cannot measure the small neutron fluxes present in underground labs for dark matter experiments. I propose a cryogenic liquid $^3$He detector that can be designed with tiny radiogenic backgrounds and efficiently measure neutron fluxes in low-flux environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.10258v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>0.1007/s10909-024-03149-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>A. N. Villano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Novel Diamond-like Carbon based photocathode for PICOSEC Micromegas detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.08712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.08712v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The PICOSEC Micromegas (MM) detector is a precise timing gaseous detector based on a MM detector operating in a two-stage amplification mode and a Cherenkov radiator. Prototypes equipped with cesium iodide (CsI) photocathodes have shown promising time resolutions as precise as 24 picoseconds (ps) for Minimum Ionizing Particles. However, due to the high hygroscopicity and susceptibility to ion bombardment of the CsI photocathodes, alternative photocathode materials are needed to improve the robustness of PICOSEC MM. Diamond-like Carbon (DLC) film have been introduced as a novel robust photocathode material, which have shown promising results. A batch of DLC photocathodes with different thicknesses were produced and evaluated using ultraviolet light. The quantum efficiency measurements indicate that the optimized thickness of the DLC photocathode is approximately 3 nm. Furthermore, DLC photocathodes show good resistance to ion bombardment in aging test compared to the CsI photocathode. Finally, a PICOSEC MM prototype equipped with DLC photocathodes was tested in muon beams. A time resolution of around 42 ps with a detection efficiency of 97% for 150 GeV/c muons were obtained. These results indicate the great potential of DLC as a photocathode for the PICOSEC MM detector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.08712v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>X. Wang, R. Aleksan, Y. Angelis, J. Bortfeldt, F. Brunbauer, M. Brunoldi, E. Chatzianagnostou, J. Datta, K. Degmelt, G. Fanourakis, D. Fiorina, K. J. Floethner, M. Gallinaro, F. Garcia, I. Giomataris, K. Gnanvo, F. J. Iguaz, D. Janssens, A. Kallitsopoulou, M. Kovacic, B. Kross, P. Legou, M. Lisowska, J. Liu, I. Maniatis, J. McKisson, Y. Meng, H. Muller, E. Oliveri, G. Orlandini, A. Pandey, T. Papaevangelou, M. Pomorski, L. Ropelewski, D. Sampsonidis, L. Scharenberg, T. Schneider, L. Shang, M. Shao, L. Sohl, M. van Stenis, Y. Tsipolitis, S. E. Tzamarias, A. Utrobicic, I. Vai, R. Veenhof, P. Vitulo, S. White, W. Xi, Z. Zhang, Y. Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the first test of the Weak Equivalence Principle in low Earth orbit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.06400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.06400v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Weak Equivalence Principle is the founding pillar of General Relativity and as such should be verified as precisely as possible. The Microscope experiment tested it in low Earth orbit, finding that Pt and Ti test masses fall toward Earth with the same acceleration to about 1e-15, an improvement of about two orders of magnitude over ground tests. Space missions, even if small, are expensive and hard to replicate; yet, the essence of physics is repeatability. This work is an assessment of the Microscope results based on the laws of physics and knowledge from previous experiments, focusing on the limiting thermal noise and the treatment of acceleration outliers. Thermal noise reveals anomalies that we explain by stray sub-microVolt potentials caused by patch charges, giving rise to an unstable zero. The measurements were affected by numerous acceleration spikes occurring at the synodic frequencies relative to the Earth (the signal frequency) and the Sun, which we interpret as evidence of a thermal origin. In Microscope authors' analysis, the spikes were removed and the resulting gaps replaced with artificial data (up to 35, 40 per cent of the sessions data), which retain memory of the gaps and may simulate or cancel an effect (signal or systematic). An alternative approach based exclusively on real measured data would avoid any ambiguity. The lessons of Microscope are crucial to any futures improved mission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.06400v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna M. Nobili, Alberto Anselmi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Measurement of Correlated Charge Noise in Superconducting Qubits at an Underground Facility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04642v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We measure space- and time-correlated charge jumps on a four-qubit device, operating 107 meters below the Earth's surface in a low-radiation, cryogenic facility designed for the characterization of low-threshold particle detectors. The rock overburden of this facility reduces the cosmic ray muon flux by over 99% compared to laboratories at sea level. Combined with 4$\pi$ coverage of a movable lead shield, this facility enables quantifiable control over the flux of ionizing radiation on the qubit device. Long-time-series charge tomography measurements on these weakly charge-sensitive qubits capture discontinuous jumps in the induced charge on the qubit islands, corresponding to the interaction of ionizing radiation with the qubit substrate. The rate of these charge jumps scales with the flux of ionizing radiation on the qubit package, as characterized by a series of independent measurements on another energy-resolving detector operating simultaneously in the same cryostat with the qubits. Using lead shielding, we achieve a minimum charge jump rate of 0.19$^{+0.04}_{-0.03}$ mHz, almost an order of magnitude lower than that measured in surface tests, but a factor of roughly eight higher than expected based on reduction of ambient gammas alone. We operate four qubits for over 22 consecutive hours with zero correlated charge jumps at length scales above three millimeters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04642v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Bratrud, S. Lewis, K. Anyang, A. Col\'on Cesan\'i, T. Dyson, H. Magoon, D. Sabhari, G. Spahn, G. Wagner, R. Gualtieri, N. A. Kurinsky, R. Linehan, R. McDermott, S. Sussman, D. J. Temples, S. Uemura, C. Bathurst, G. Cancelo, R. Chen, A. Chou, I. Hernandez, M. Hollister, L. Hsu, C. James, K. Kennard, R. Khatiwada, P. Lukens, V. Novati, N. Raha, S. Ray, R. Ren, A. Rodriguez, B. Schmidt, K. Stifter, J. Yu, D. Baxter, E. Figueroa-Feliciano, D. Bowring</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
