<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ins-det updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det</link>
    <description>physics.ins-det updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Proton Irradiation on the Performance of Skipper CCDs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12949v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Skipper CCDs are a mature detector technology that has been suggested for future space telescope instruments requiring sub-electron readout noise in the near-ultraviolet to the near-infrared. While modern skipper CCDs inherit from the radiation-tolerant p-channel detectors developed by LBNL, the effects of high doses of ionizing radiation on skipper CCDs (such as those expected in space) remains largely unmeasured. We report preliminary results on the performance of p-channel skipper CCDs following irradiation with 217-MeV protons at the Northwestern Medicine Proton Center. The total nonionizing energy loss (NIEL) experienced by the detectors exceeds 6 years at the Sun-Earth Lagrange Point 2 (L2). We demonstrate that the skipper amplifier continues to function as expected following this irradiation. Owing to the low readout noise of these detectors, controlled irradiation tests can be used to sensitively characterize the charge transfer inefficiency, dark current, and the density and time constants of charge traps as a function of proton fluence. We conclude with a brief outlook toward future tests of these detectors at other proton and gamma-ray facilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12949v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brandon Roacha (Kavli Institute for Cosmological Physics, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA), Brenda A. Cervantes Vergara (Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory, Batavia, IL, USA), Santiago Perez (Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory, Batavia, IL, USA, CONICET - Universidad de Buenos Aires, Instituto de Fisica de Buenos Aires), Alex Drlica-Wagner (Kavli Institute for Cosmological Physics, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA, Department of Astronomy and Astrophysics, University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA), Juan Estrada (Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory, Batavia, IL, USA), Abhishek Bakshi (Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory, Batavia, IL, USA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Angular dependent measurement of electron-ion recombination in liquid argon for ionization calorimetry in the ICARUS liquid argon time projection chamber</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12969v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper reports on a measurement of electron-ion recombination in liquid argon in the ICARUS liquid argon time projection chamber (LArTPC). A clear dependence of recombination on the angle of the ionizing particle track relative to the drift electric field is observed. An ellipsoid modified box (EMB) model of recombination describes the data across all measured angles. These measurements are used for the calorimetric energy scale calibration of the ICARUS TPC, which is also presented. The impact of the EMB model is studied on calorimetric particle identification, as well as muon and proton energy measurements. Accounting for the angular dependence in EMB recombination improves the accuracy and precision of these measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12969v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> ICARUS collaboration, P. Abratenko, N. Abrego-Martinez, A. Aduszkiewicz, F. Akbar, L. Aliaga Soplin, M. Artero Pons, J. Asaadi, W. F. Badgett, B. Baibussinov, B. Behera, V. Bellini, R. Benocci, S. Berkman, S. Bertolucci, M. Betancourt, M. Bonesini, T. Boone, B. Bottino, A. Braggiotti, D. Brailsford, S. J. Brice, V. Brio, C. Brizzolari, H. S. Budd A. Campani, A. Campos, D. Carber, M. Carneiro, I. Caro Terrazas, H. Carranza, F. Castillo Fernandez, A. Castro, S. Centro, G. Cerati, A. Chatterjee, D. Cherdack, S. Cherubini, N. Chitirasreemadam, M. Cicerchia, T. Coan, A. Cocco, M. R. Convery, L. Cooper-Troendle, S. Copello, A. A. Dange, A. De Roeck, L. Di Noto, C. Di Stefano, D. DiFerdinando, M. Diwan, S. Dolan, L. Domine, S. Donati, F. Drielsma, J. Dyer, S. Dytman, A. Falcone, C. Farnese, A. Fava, A. Ferrari, N. Gallice, F. G. Garcia, C. Gatto, D. Gibin, A. Gioiosa, W. Gu, A. Guglielmi, G. Gurung, H. Hausner, A. Heggestuen, B. Howard, R. Howell, I. Ingratta, C. James, W. Jang, Y. -J. Jwa, L. Kashur, W. Ketchum, J. S. Kim, D. -H. Koh, J. Larkin, Y. Li, C. Mariani, C. M. Marshall, S. Martynenko, N. Mauri, K. S. McFarland, D. P. M\'endez, A. Menegolli, G. Meng, O. G. Miranda, A. Mogan, N. Moggi, E. Montagna, C. Montanari, A. Montanari, M. Mooney, G. Moreno-Granados, J. Mueller, M. Murphy, D. Naples, V. C. L. Nguyen, S. Palestini, M. Pallavicini, V. Paolone, R. Papaleo, L. Pasqualini, L. Patrizii, L. Paudel, G. Petrillo, C. Petta, V. Pia, F. Pietropaolo, F. Poppi, M. Pozzato, G. Putnam, X. Qian, A. Rappoldi, G. L. Raselli, S. Repetto, F. Resnati, A. M. Ricci, G. Riccobene, E. Richards, M. Rosenberg, M. Rossella, P. Roy, C. Rubbia, M. Saad, S. Saha, P. Sala, S. Samanta, P. Sapienza, A. Scaramelli, A. Scarpelli, D. Schmitz, A. Schukraft, D. Senadheera, S-H. Seo, F. Sergiampietri, G. Sirri, J. S. Smedley, J. Smith, L. Stanco, J. Stewart, H. A. Tanaka, F. Tapia, M. Tenti, K. Terao, F. Terranova, V. Togo, D. Torretta, M. Torti, F. Tortorici, R. Triozzi, Y. -T. Tsai, S. Tufanli, T. Usher, F. Varanini, S. Ventura, M. Vicenzi, C. Vignoli, B. Viren, Z. Williams, R. J. Wilson, P. Wilson, J. Wolfs, T. Wongjirad, A. Wood, E. Worcester, M. Worcester, M. Wospakrik, H. Yu, J. Yu, A. Zani, J. Zennamo, J. C. Zettlemoyer, C. Zhang, S. Zucchelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design, fabrication and testing of Al/p-Si Schottky and pn junctions for radiation studies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13705</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13705v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strip and pixels sensors, fabricated on high resistivity silicon substrate, normally of p-type, are used in detectors for High Energy Physics (HEP) typically in a hybrid detector assembly. Furthermore, and owing to their inherent advantages over hybrid sensors, Monolithic Active Pixel Sensors (MAPS) fabricated in CMOS technology have been increasingly implemented in HEP experiments. In all cases, their use in higher radiation areas (HL-LHC and beyond) will require options to improve their radiation hardness and time resolution. These aspects demand a deep understanding of their radiation damage and reliable models to predict their behaviours at high fluences. As a first step, we fabricated several Schottky and n-on-p diodes, to allow a comparison of results and provide a backup solution for test devices, on 6 or 4-inch p-type silicon wafers with 50 {\mu}m epitaxial thickness and of doping concentration as they are normally used in HEP detectors and CMOS MAPS devices. In this paper, details of the design and fabrication process, along with test results of the fabricated devices before irradiation, will be provided. Additional test results on irradiated devices will be provided in subsequent publications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13705v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Giulio Villani, Dengfeng Zhang, Adnan Malik, Trevor Vickey, Yebo Chen, Matthew G. Kurth, Peilian Liu, Hongbo Zhu, Thomas Koffas, Christoph Thomas Klein, Robert Vandusen, Rodney Aiton, Angela Mccormick, Garry Tarr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of the fractional radiation length of a pixel module for the CMS Phase-2 upgrade via the multiple scattering of positrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13721</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13721v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-luminosity particle collider experiments such as the ones planned at the High-Luminosity Large Hadron Collider require ever-greater vertexing precision of the tracking detectors, necessitating also reductions in the material budget of the detectors. Traditionally, the fractional radiation length ($x/X_0$) of detectors is either estimated using known properties of the constituent materials, or measured in dedicated runs of the final detector. In this paper, we present a method of direct measurement of the material budget of a CMS prototype module designed for the Phase-2 upgrade of the CMS detector using a 40-65 MeV positron beam. A total of 630 million events were collected at the Paul Scherrer Institut PiE1 experimental area using a three-plane telescope consisting of the prototype module as the central plane, surrounded by two MALTA monolithic pixel detectors. Fractional radiation lengths were extracted from scattering angle distributions using the Highland approximation for multiple scattering. A statistical technique recovered runs suffering from trigger desynchronisation, and several corrections were introduced to compensate for local inefficiencies related to geometric and beam shape constraints. An overall average $x/X_0$ of (0.84 $\pm$ 0.10)% across the surveyed regions was measured, which is compatible with an empirical estimate of 0.825% computed from known material properties. Higher-granularity maps of the fractional radiation length were produced for both rectangular regions and regions of uniform material composition. The results bode well for the CMS Phase-2 upgrade modules, which will play a key role in the minimisation of the material budget of the upgraded detector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13721v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> The Tracker Group of the CMS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concrete Shielding Requirements for PET Facilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12991v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study aims to determine the protective concrete shielding thickness requirements in concrete walls of positron emission tomography (PET) and computed tomography (CT) facilities. Consider the most commonly used PET radiotracer, the radioisotope F18, which emits two back-to-back 511 keV photons. Photon transmission measurements were carried out through an Israeli B30 strength ordinary concrete wall (3 meter high, 20 cm thick) using photons emitted from an F18 source into a cone having a 24 degree FWHM dose aperture angle. The source, positioned 3 meters from the wall, yielded a 0.64 m beam disk radius on the wall. Our measurement setup roughly simulates radiation emitted from a patient injected with F18. Dose rates were measured by an Atomtex Radiation Survey Meter, positioned at distances 0.05 to 3 meters from the far side of the wall. For a wide-beam, thick-shielding setup, there is a buildup effect, as photons having reduced energies may reach the detector from Compton scattering in the wall. In concrete, the Compton scattering cross section accounts for 99% of the total interaction cross section. The buildup factor B accounts for the increase of observed radiation transmission through shielding material due to scattered radiation. We measured a narrow-beam transmission coefficient T=3.0 +- 0.9 %, consistent with the theoretical value 2% calculated from NIST photon attenuation data without buildup. We measured a wide-beam transmission coefficient of 8.6 +- 1.8%; in good agreement with two available wide-beam Monte Carlo (MC) simulations. We confirm by experiment, complementing MC simulations, that for a 20 cm thick concrete wall, due to buildup, about four times thicker shielding is required to achieve a designated level of radiation protection, compared to that calculated using narrow-beam, thin-shielding transmission coefficients.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12991v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Steiner, Aviv Malki, Tzafrir Ben Yehuda, Murray Moinester</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design of an 8-Channel 40 GS/s 20 mW/Ch Waveform Sampling ASIC in 65 nm CMOS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09575v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: 1 ps timing resolution is the entry point to signature based searches relying on secondary/tertiary vertices and particle identification. We describe a preliminary design for PSEC5, an 8-channel 40 GS/s waveform-sampling ASIC in the TSMC 65 nm process targetting 1 ps resolution at 20 mW power per channel. Each channel consists of four fast and one slow switched capacitor arrays (SCA), allowing ps time resolution combined with a long effective buffer. Each fast SCA is 1.6 ns long and has a nominal sampling rate of 40 GS/s. The slow SCA is 204.8 ns long and samples at 5 GS/s. Recording of the analog data for each channel is triggered by a fast discriminator capable of multiple triggering during the window of the slow SCA. To achieve a large dynamic range, low leakage, and high bandwidth, the SCA sampling switches are implemented as 2.5 V nMOSFETs controlled by 1.2 V shift registers. Stored analog data are digitized by an external ADC at 10 bits or better. Specifications on operational parameters include a 4 GHz analog bandwidth and a dead time of 20 microseconds, corresponding to a 50 kHz readout rate, determined by the choice of the external ADC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09575v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinseo Park, Evan Angelico, Andrew Arzac, Davide Braga, Ahan Datta, Troy England, Camden Ertley, Farah Fahim, Henry J. Frisch, Mary Heintz, Eric Oberla, Nathaniel J. Pastika, Hector D. Rico-Aniles, Paul M. Rubinov, Xiaoran Wang, Yui Man Richmond Yeung, Tom N. Zimmerman</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
