<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ins-det updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det</link>
    <description>physics.ins-det updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 05:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Heliometric stereo: a new frontier in surface profilometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14833v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate and reliable measurements of three-dimensional surface structures are important for a broad range of technological and research applications, including materials science, nanotechnology, and biomedical research. Scanning helium microscopy (SHeM) uses low-energy (64 meV) neutral helium atoms as the imaging probe particles, providing a highly sensitive and delicate approach to measuring surface topography. To date, topographic SHeM measurements have been largely qualitative, but with the advent of the heliometric stereo method - a technique that combines multiple images to create a 3D representation of a surface - quantitative maps of surface topography may now be acquired with SHeM. Here, we present and discuss two different implementations of heliometric stereo on two separate instruments, a single detector SHeM and a multiple-detector SHeM. Both implementations show good accuracy (5% and 10% respectively) for recovering the shape of a surface. Additionally, we discuss where heliometric stereo is most applicable, identify contrast features that can limit its accuracy, and discuss how to mitigate these limitations with careful design and sample choices that be readily implemented on current instruments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14833v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandar Radic, Sam Lambrick, Chenyang Zhao, Nick von Jeinsen, Andrew Jardine, David Ward, Paul Dastoor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ICEBERG Test Stand for DUNE Cold Electronics Development</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14838v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: ICEBERG is a liquid argon time projection chamber at Fermilab for the purpose of testing detector components and software for the Deep Underground Neutrino Experiment (DUNE). The detector features a 1.15m x 1m anode plane following the specifications of the DUNE horizontal drift far detector and a newly installed X-ARAPUCA photodetector. The status of ICEBERG is reported along with analysis of noise, pulser, and cosmic ray data from the ninth run beginning May 2024 with the goal of advising the DUNE collaboration on the optimal wire readout electronics configuration. In addition, development of an absolute energy scale calibration method is currently underway using known sources such as cosmic ray muon Michel electrons at the ~10 MeV scale and $^{39}$Ar decay electrons at the ~100keV scale. Research into AI-based identification of such events at the data acquisition level is introduced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14838v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Yankelevich (for the DUNE collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the resolution of dual readout calorimeters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15329v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Dual readout calorimeters allow state-of-the-art resolutions for hadronic energy measurements. Their various incarnations are leading candidates for the calorimeter systems for future colliders. In this paper, we present a simple formula for the resolution of a dual readout calorimeter, which we verify with a toy simulation and with full simulation results. This formula can help those new to dual readout calorimetry understand its strengths and limitations. The paper also highlights that the dual readout correction works not just to compensate for binding energy loss, but also for energies escaping the calorimeter or clustering algorithm. Formulae are also presented for approximate resolutions and energy scales in terms of different sources of response.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15329v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Eno, L. Wu, M. Y. Aamir, S. V. Chekanov, S. Nabili, C. Palmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DUNE-PRISM: Reducing neutrino interaction model dependence with a movable neutrino detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14811</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14811v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Deep Underground Neutrino Experiment (DUNE) is a next-generation long-baseline neutrino oscillation experiment designed to make precision measurements in the world's most powerful neutrino beam. Neutrinos are measured at two detector facilities: a near detector (ND) located at Fermilab close to where the beam is produced and a far detector (FD) at SURF. The Precision Reaction Independent Spectrum Measurement (PRISM) system allows for the measurement of different neutrino energy spectra by moving the near detector away from the central axis of the neutrino beam. These off-axis neutrino energy spectra provide a new degree of freedom that can be used to develop a deeper understanding of the relationship between the observable energy deposits in the detector and the energy of the interacting neutrino. This can benefit DUNE by significantly reducing the impact of systematic uncertainties in the neutrino interaction model. One possible use of the PRISM system is to perform a novel neutrino oscillation analysis that linearly combines off-axis neutrino energy spectra at the near detector to produce data-driven predictions of the far detector energy spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14811v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ciaran Hasnip</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proposal of the KOTO II experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14827v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The KOTO II experiment is proposed to measure the branching ratio of the decay $K_L\to\pi^0\nu\bar{\nu}$ at J-PARC. With a beamline to extract long-lived neutral kaons at 5 degrees from a production target, the single event sensitivity of the decay is $8.5\times 10^{-13}$, which is much smaller than the Standard Model prediction $3\times 10^{-11}$. This allows searches for new physics beyond the Standard Model and the first discovery of the decay with a significance exceeding $5\sigma$. As the only experiment proposed in the world dedicated to rare kaon decays, KOTO II will be indispensable in the quest for a complete understanding of flavor dynamics in the quark sector. Moreover, by combining efforts from the kaon community worldwide, we plan to develop the KOTO II detector further and expand the physics reach of the experiment to include measurements of the branching ratio of the $K_L\to\pi^0\ell^+\ell^-$ decays, studies of other $K_L$ decays, and searches for dark photons, axions, and axion-like particles. KOTO II will therefore obtain a comprehensive understanding of $K_L$ decays, providing further constraints on new physics scenarios with existing $K^+$ results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14827v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jung Keun Ahn, Antonella Antonelli, Giuseppina Anzivino, Emile Augustine, Laura Bandiera, Jianming Bian, Francesco Brizioli, Stefano De Capua, Gabriella Carini, Veronika Chobanova, Giancarlo D'Ambrosio, John Bourke Dainton, Babette D\H{o}brich, John Fry, Alberto Gianoli, Alexander Glazov, Mario Gonzalez, Martin Gorbahn, Evgueni Goudzovski, Mei Homma, Yee B. Hsiung, Tom\'a\v{s} Husek, David Hutchcroft, Abhishek Iyer, Roger William Lewis Jones, Mai Katayama, Yuto Kawata, Eun-Joo Kim, Chong Kim, Takeshi Komatsubara, Katsushige Kotera, Michal Kreps, Gianluca Lamanna, Cristina Lazzeroni, Samet Lezki, GeiYoub Lim, Sanghoon Lim, Chieh Lin, Farvah Mahmoudi, Victoria Martin, Karim Massri, Toru Matsumura, Luigi Montalto, Matthew Moulson, Hajime Nanjo, Matthew Needham, Siavash Neshatpour, Tadashi Nomura, Daiki Ogawa, Keita Ono, Monica Pepe, Letizia Peruzzo, Jacopo Pinzino, Dan Protopopescu, Claire Prouve, Thomas Reddel, Joseph Redeker, Daniele Rinaldi, Marco Romagnoni, Angela Romano, Armine Rostomyan, Jack Sanders, Diego Mart\'inez Santos, Ivano Sarra, Artur Shaikhiev, Koji Shiomi, Ryota Shiraishi, Mattia Soldani, Marco Sozzi, Benjamin Stillwell, Yi-Ting Su, Joel Swallow, Yasuhisa Tajima, Adam Tomczak, Yu-Chen Tung, Yau Wah, Rainer Wanke, Hiroaki Watanabe, John Wendel, Tong Wu, Maresa Wynd, Guang Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A plethora of long-range neutrino interactions probed by DUNE and T2HK</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14835</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14835v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The next-generation neutrino oscillation experiments would be sensitive to the new neutrino interactions that would strengthen the search for physics beyond the Standard Model. In this context, we explore the capabilities of the two leading future long-baseline neutrino oscillation experiments, DUNE and T2HK, to search for new flavor-dependent neutrino interactions with electrons, protons, and neutrons that could potentially modify neutrino flavor transitions. We forecast their sensitivities in the context of long-range neutrino interactions mediated by a neutral vector boson lighter than $10^{-10}$ eV and sourced by the vast amount of nearby and distant matter in the Earth, Moon, Sun, Milky Way, and local Universe. For the first time, we explore a plethora of $U(1)^\prime$ symmetries inducing the new interactions built from the combination of lepton and baryon numbers. We find that in all cases, DUNE and T2HK may constrain or discover the existence of new long-range neutrino interaction, and in some favorable cases, may identify the new $U(1)^\prime$ symmetry responsible for it. In this short proceeding, we only summarize the prospects of constraining the new interaction in case of all our candidate $U(1)^\prime$ symmetries, which have been discussed in JHEP 09 (2024) 055.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14835v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanjib Kumar Agarwalla, Mauricio Bustamante, Masoom Singh, Pragyanprasu Swain</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Origin of performance enhancement of superconducting nanowire single-photon detectors by He-ion irradiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14965</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14965v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Superconducting nanowire single-photon detectors (SNSPDs) are indispensable in fields such as quantum science and technology, astronomy, and biomedical imaging, where high detection efficiency, low dark count rates and high timing accuracy are required. Recently, helium (He) ion irradiation was shown to be a promising method to enhance SNSPD performance. Here, we study how changes in the underlying superconducting NbTiN film and the SiO2/Si substrate affect device performance. While irradiated and unirradiated NbTiN films show similar crystallinity, we observe He bubble formation below the SiO2/Si interface and an amorphization of the Si substrate. Both reduce the thermal conductance between the superconducting thin film and the substrate from 210 W/m^2/K^4 to 70 W/m^2/K^4 after irradiation with 2000 ions/nm^2. This effect, combined with the lateral straggle of He ions in the substrate, allows the modification of the superconductor-to-substrate thermal conductance of an SNSPD by selectively irradiating the regions around the nanowire. With this approach, we achieved an increased plateau width of saturating intrinsic detection efficiency of 9.8 uA compared to 3.7 uA after full irradiation. Moreover, the critical current remained similar to that of the unirradiated reference device (59 uA versus 60.1 uA), while full irradiation reduced it to 22.4 uA. Our results suggest that the irradiation-induced reduction of the thermal conductance significantly enhances SNSPD sensitivity, offering a novel approach to locally engineer substrate properties for improved detector performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14965v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Strohauer, Fabian Wietschorke, Markus D\"oblinger, Christian Schmid, Stefanie Grotowski, Lucio Zugliani, Bj\"orn Jonas, Kai M\"uller, Jonathan J. Finley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Advanced Muon Facility: a proposed multi-purpose muon facility at Fermilab</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.15664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.15664v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Charged lepton flavor violation (CLFV) is expected in a diverse set of new physics scenarios. The current generation of experiments probe CLFV in the muon sector in three complementary channels: $\mu^-N \rightarrow e^- N$ (Mu2e, COMET), $\mu^+ \rightarrow e^+ \gamma$ (MEG-II), and $\mu^+ \rightarrow e^+e^+e^-$s (Mu3e). These experiments aim to enhance existing limits by several orders-of-magnitude in the coming decade and offer discovery potential to many new physics models. The proposed Advanced Muon Facility (AMF) would be a multi-purpose muon facility based at Fermilab and introduces an innovative approach based on a muon storage ring to enable a full suite of muon CLFV experiments. AMF would host CLFV experiments with sensitivities orders-of-magnitude beyond the present era. In the event of a signal in these currently planned experiments, AMF would enable additional measurements to elucidate the nature of the new physics observed. The design and R$\&amp;$D for AMF is in its infancy. This article outlines the motivations for AMF, detailing on-going R$\&amp;$D efforts, and highlighting potential synergies with the proposed muon collider.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.15664v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sophie Middleton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of Structured State Space Models to High energy physics with locality-sensitive hashing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16237v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modern high-energy physics (HEP) experiments are increasingly challenged by the vast size and complexity of their datasets, particularly regarding large-scale point cloud processing and long sequences. In this study, to address these challenges, we explore the application of structured state space models (SSMs), proposing one of the first trials to integrate local-sensitive hashing into either a hybrid or pure Mamba Model. Our results demonstrate that pure SSMs could serve as powerful backbones for HEP problems involving tasks for long sequence data with local inductive bias. By integrating locality-sensitive hashing into Mamba blocks, we achieve significant improvements over traditional backbones in key HEP tasks, surpassing them in inference speed and physics metrics while reducing computational overhead. In key tests, our approach demonstrated promising results, presenting a viable alternative to traditional transformer backbones by significantly reducing FLOPS while maintaining robust performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16237v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Jiang, Sitian Qian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-Imaging Ion-Cyclotron-Resonance Mass Spectrometry with the Canadian Penning Trap at CARIBU</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13802</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13802v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Canadian Penning Trap mass spectrometer (CPT) has conducted precision mass measurements of neutron-rich nuclides from the CAlifornium Rare Isotope Breeder Upgrade (CARIBU) of the Argonne Tandem Linac Accelerator System (ATLAS) facility at Argonne National Laboratory using the Phase-Imaging Ion-Cyclotron-Resonance (PIICR) technique for over half a decade. Here we discuss the CPT system, and methods to improve accuracy and precision in mass measurement using PI-ICR including some optimization techniques and recently studied systematic effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13802v4</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Ray, A. A. Valverde, M. Brodeur, F. Buchinger, J. A. Clark, B. Liu, G. E. Morgan, R. Orford, W. S. Porter, G. Savard, K. S. Sharma, X. L. Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluorescence emission of the JUNO liquid scintillator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09988v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: JUNO is a huge neutrino detector that will use 20 kton of organic liquid scintillator as its detection medium. The scintillator is a mixture of linear alkyl benzene (LAB), 2.5 g/L of 2,5-diphenyloxazole (PPO) and 3 mg/L of 1,4-Bis(2-methylstyryl)benzene (Bis-MSB). The main goal of JUNO is to determine the Neutrino Mass Ordering [1, 2, 3]. In order to achieve this purpose, good energy and position reconstruction is required, hence a complete understanding of the optical characteristics of the liquid scintillator is mandatory. In this paper we present the measurements on the JUNO scintillator emission spectrum, absorption length and fluorescence time distribution performed respectively with a spectrofluorimeter, a spectrophotometer and a custom made setup</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09988v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Beretta, F. Houria, F. Ferraro, D. Basilico, A. Brigatti, B. Caccianiga, A. Caslini, C. Landini, P. Lombardi, L. Pelicci, E. Percalli, G. Ranucci, A. C. Re, C. Clementi, F. Ortica, A. Romani, V. Antonelli, M. G. Giammarchi, L. Miramonti, P. Saggese, M. D. C. Torri, S. Aiello, G. Andronico, A. Barresi, A. Bergnoli, M. Borghesi, R. Brugnera, R. Bruno, A. Budano, A. Cammi, V. Cerrone, R. Caruso, D. Chiesa, C. Coletta, L. V. D\'Auria, S. Dusini, A. Fabbri, G. Felici, A. Garfagnini, N. Giudice, A. Gavrikov, M. Grassi, N. Guardone, L. Lastrucci, I. Lippi, L. Loi, C. Lombardo, F. Mantovani, S. M. Mari, A. Martini, M. Montuschi, M. Nastasi, D. Orestano, A. Paoloni, F. Petrucci, E. Previtali, B. Ricci, G. Sava, A. Serafini, C. Sirignano, M. Sisti, L. Stanco, E. Stanescu Farilla, V. Strati, C. Tuv\'e, C. Venettacci, G. Verde, L. Votano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potential of RES-NOVA as Dark Matter observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12409v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The RES-NOVA project is an experimental initiative aimed at detecting neutrinos from the next galactic supernova using PbWO$_{4}$ cryogenic detectors, operated at low temperatures in a low-background environment. By utilizing archaeological lead (Pb) as the target material, RES-NOVA leverages its high radiopurity, large nuclear mass, and the natural abundance of $^{207}$Pb, making it well-suited for exploring both spin-independent and spin-dependent Dark Matter (DM) interactions via nuclear scattering. This work presents a background model developed for the RES-NOVA technology demonstrator and evaluates its implications for Dark Matter detection. Detailed calculations of nuclear matrix elements, combined with the unique properties of archaeological Pb, demonstrate RES-NOVA's potential as a complementary tool to existing direct detection experiments for studying Dark Matter interactions. The experiment will conduct DM searches over a broad mass range spanning 4 orders of magnitude, from sub-GeV/$c^2$ to TeV/$c^2$. In the most optimistic scenario, RES-NOVA is expected to probe DM-nucleon cross-sections down to 1$\times 10^{-43}$ cm$^2$ and 2$\times 10^{-46}$ cm$^2$ for candidates with masses of 2 GeV/$c^2$ and 20 GeV/$c^2$, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12409v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Alloni, G. Benato, P. Carniti, M. Cataldo, L. Chen, M. Clemenza, M. Consonni, G. Croci, I. Dafinei, F. A. Danevich, D. Di Martino, E. Di Stefano, N. Ferreiro Iachellini, F. Ferroni, F. Filippini, S. Ghislandi, A. Giachero, L. Gironi, P. Gorla, C. Gotti, D. L. Helis, D. V. Kasperovych, V. V. Kobychev, G. Marcucci, A. Melchiorre, A. Menegolli, S. Nisi, M. Musa, L. Pagnanini, L. Pattavina, G. Pessina, S. Pirro, O. G. Polischuk, S. Pozzi, M. C. Prata, A. Puiu, S. Quitadamo, M. P. Riccardi, M. Rossella, R. Rossini, F. Saliu, A. Salvini, A. P. Scherban, D. A. Solopikhin, V. I. Tretyak, D. Trotta, H. Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of Radon-222 concentration in N2 using an activated charcoal trap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14559</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14559v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Radon-222 is a limiting background in many leading dark matter and low energy neutrino experiments. One way to mitigate Radon-222 is to fill external experimental components with a clean cover gas such as N2. At the SNOLAB facility in Canada, the 222Rn concentration in the cover gas systems of the experiments are monitored using a radon assay board developed by the SNO collaboration. To improve the sensitivity of N2 assays, a new trapping mechanism based on activated charcoal has been developed. The trap was purified and tested at SNOLAB. The methods for determining the efficiency, background, and sensitivity of the trap were described. Additionally, as part of the efficiency measurement, a radon calibration source was developed and characterized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14559v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. Fatemighomi, Y. Ahmed, S. M. A. Hussain, J. Lu, A. Pearson, J. Suys</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparison of Kikuchi Diffraction Geometries in Scanning Electron Microscope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.13018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.13018v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent advances in scanning electron microscope (SEM) based Kikuchi diffraction have demonstrated the important potential for reflection and transmission methods, like transmission Kikuchi diffraction (TKD) and electron backscatter diffraction (EBSD). Furthermore, with the advent of compact direct electron detectors (DED) it has been possible to place the detector in a variety of configurations within the SEM chamber. This motivates the present work where we explore the similarities and differences of the different geometries that include on-axis TKD &amp; off-axis TKD using electron transparent samples, as well as more conventional EBSD. Furthermore, we compare these with the newest method called "reflection Kikuchi diffraction" RKD where the sample is placed flat in the chamber and the detector is placed below the pole piece. Through remapping collected diffraction patterns, all these methods can be used to generate an experimental "diffraction sphere" that can be used to explore diffraction from any scattering vector from the unit cell, as well as the ability to perform band profile analysis. This diffraction sphere approach enables us to further probe specific differences between the methods, including for example thickness effects in TKD that can result in the generation of diffraction spots, as well as electron scattering path length effects that result in excess and deficiency variations, as well as inversion of bands in experimental patterns.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.13018v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianbi Zhang, Lukas Berners, Jakub Holzer, T. Ben Britton</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
