<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ins-det updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det</link>
    <description>physics.ins-det updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 04:01:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Simple Apparatus for Testing PMT Humidity Tolerance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13545v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report on a low-cost apparatus to extend a photomultiplier tube (PMT) testing setup to operations at high humidity and/or at an elevated temperature. This setup allows a determination of whether a PMT can successfully operate for an extended period of time in a high-humidity environment, such as the waterline of a water Cherenkov detector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13545v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Germer, K. Park, C. Skuse, C. Yang, D. S. Parno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4H-SiC PIN detector for alpha particles from room temperature to 90 {\deg}C</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13815v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the field of high-energy particle detection, detectors operating in high-radiation environments primarily face high costs associated with power consumption and cooling systems. Therefore, the development of particle detectors capable of stable operation at room temperature or even elevated temperatures is of great significance. Silicon carbide (SiC) exhibits significant potential for particle detector applications due to its exceptional carrier mobility, radiation hardness, and thermal stability. Over the past decade, significant breakthroughs in silicon carbide epitaxial growth technology and device processing techniques have enabled the development of SiC-based particle detectors, providing a new technological pathway for particle detection in high-temperature environments.
  In this work, we fabricate a 4H-SiC PIN detector, named SIlicon CARbide (SICAR) and characterize its leakage current, capacitance, and charge collection across varying temperatures. The results indicate that the detector maintains a very low leakage current (&lt; 10 nA) at 90 C, with no degradation in depletion capacitance or charge collection performance. Additionally, it achieves a fast rise time of 333 ps at 90 C, confirming its potential for high-temperature radiation detection applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13815v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingchen Li, Sen Zhao, Mengke Cai, Suyu Xiao, Congcong Wang, Weimin Song, Xin Shi, Xiyuan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Muon tracking in a LiquidO opaque scintillator detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: LiquidO is an innovative radiation detector concept. The core idea is to exploit stochastic light confinement in a highly scattering medium to self-segment the detector volume. In this paper, we demonstrate event-by-event muon tracking in a LiquidO opaque scintillator detector prototype. The detector consists of a 30 mm cubic scintillator volume instrumented with 64 wavelength-shifting fibres arranged in an 8$\times$8 grid with a 3.2 mm pitch and read out by silicon photomultipliers. A wax-based opaque scintillator with a scattering length of approximately 0.5 mm is used. The tracking performance of this LiquidO detector is characterised with cosmic-ray muons and the position resolution is demonstrated to be 450 $\mu$m per row of fibres. These results highlight the potential of LiquidO opaque scintillator detectors to achieve fine spatial resolution, enabling precise particle tracking and imaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13864v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> LiquidO Collaboration, J. Apilluelo, L. Asquith, E. F. Bannister, N. P. Barradas, C. L. Baylis, J. L. Beney, M. Berberan e Santos, X. de la Bernardie, T. J. C. Bezerra, M. Bongrand, C. Bourgeois, D. Breton, J. Busto, A. Cabrera, A. Cadiou, E. Calvo, M. de Carlos Generowicz, E. Chauveau, B. J. Cattermole, M. Chen, P. Chimenti, D. F. Cowen, S. Kr. Das, S. Dusini, A. Earle, M. Felizardo, C. Frigerio Martins, J. Gal\'an, J. A. Garc\'ia, A. Gibson-Foster, C. Girard-Carillo, W. C. Griffith, J. J. G\'omez-Cadenas, M. Guiti\`ere, F. Haddad, J. Hartnell, A. Holin, I. G. Irastorza, I. Jovanovic, A. Kling, L. Koch, P. Lasorak, J. F. Le Du, F. Lefevre, P. Loaiza, J. A. Lock, G. Luz\'on, J. Maalmi, J. P. Malhado, F. Mantovani, J. G. Marques, C. Marquet, M. Mart\'inez, J. T. Moffat, D. Navas-Nicol\'as, H. Nunokawa, J. P. Ochoa-Ricoux, T. Palmeira, C. Palomares, D. Petyt, P. Pillot, A. Pin, J. C. C. Porter, M. S. Pravikoff, S. Richards, N. Rodrigues, M. Roche, R. Rosero, B. Roskovec, M. L. Sarsa, S. Schoppmann, A. Serafini, C. Shepherd-Themistocleous, W. Shorrock, M. Silva, L. Simard, S. R. Soleti, D. Stocco, V. Strati, J. S. Stutzmann, F. Suekane, N. Tuccori, A. Verdugo, B. Viaud, S. M. Wakely, A. Weber, G. Wendel, A. S. Wilhelm, A. W. R. Wong, M. Yeh, F. Yermia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Powered, Ultra-thin, Flexible, and Scalable Ultraviolet Detector Utilizing Diamond-MoS$_2$ Heterojunction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The escalating demand for ultraviolet (UV) sensing in space exploration, environmental monitoring, and agricultural productivity necessitates detectors that are both environmentally and mechanically resilient. Diamond, featuring its high bandgap and UV absorption, exceptional mechanical/chemical robustness, and excellent thermal stability, emerges as a highly promising material for next-generation UV detection in various scenarios. However, conventional diamond-based UV detectors are constrained by rigid bulk architectures and reliance on external power supplies, hindering their integration with curved and flexible platforms and complicating device scalability due to auxiliary power requirements. To tackle these challenges, herein, we firstly demonstrated a large-scale, self-powered, and flexible diamond UV detector by heterogeneously integrating a MoS$_2$ monolayer with an ultrathin, freestanding diamond membrane. The fabricated device operates at zero external bias, and simultaneously exhibits a high responsivity of 94 mA W$^{-1}$ at 220 nm, and detectivity of 5.88 x 109 Jones. Notably, mechanical bending enables strain-induced bandgap modulation of the diamond membrane, allowing dynamically tunable photoresponse-a capability absent in rigid diamond counterparts. To validate its practicality and scalability, a proof-of-concept UV imager with 3x3 pixels was demonstrated. This newly developed configuration will undoubtedly open up new routes toward scalable, integrable, flexible, and cost-effective UV sensing solutions for emerging technologies</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13909v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yicheng Wang, Jixiang Jing, Yumeng Luo, Xiaomin Wang, Kuan Liang, Changsheng Chen, Dong-Keun Ki, Ye Zhu, Zhongqiang Wang, Qi Wang, Kwai Hei Li, Zhiqin Chu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cryogenic Performance Evaluation of Commercial SP4T Microelectromechanical Switch for Quantum Computing Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13574</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13574v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Superconducting quantum computers have emerged as a leading platform for next-generation computing, offering exceptional scalability and unprecedented computational speeds. However, scaling these systems to millions of qubits for practical applications poses substantial challenges, particularly due to interconnect bottlenecks. To address this challenge, extensive research has focused on developing cryogenic multiplexers that enable minimal wiring between room-temperature electronics and quantum processors. This paper investigates the viability of commercial microelectromechanical system (MEMS) switches for cryogenic multiplexers in large-scale quantum computing systems. DC and RF characteristics of the MEMS switches are evaluated at cryogenic temperatures (&lt; 10 K) through finite element simulations and experimental measurements. Our results demonstrate that MEMS switches exhibit improved on-resistance, lower operating voltage, and superior RF performance at cryogenic temperatures, with reliable operation over 100 million cycles. Furthermore, stable single-pole four-throw (SP4T) switching and logical operations, including NAND and NOR gates, are demonstrated at cryogenic temperatures, validating their potential for quantum computing. These results underscore the promise of MEMS switches in realizing large-scale quantum computing systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13574v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yong-Bok Lee, Connor Devitt, Xu Zhu, Nicholas Yost, Yabei Gu, Sunil A. Bhave</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploiting scattering-based point spread functions for snapshot 5D and modality-switchable lensless imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13813v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Snapshot multi-dimensional imaging offers a promising alternative to traditional low-dimensional imaging techniques by enabling the simultaneous capture of spatial, spectral, polarization, and other information in a single shot for improved imaging speed and acquisition efficiency. However, existing snapshot multi-dimensional imaging systems are often hindered by their large size, complexity, and high cost, which constrain their practical applicability. In this work, we propose a compact lensless diffuser camera for snapshot multi-dimensional imaging (Diffuser-mCam), which can reconstruct five-dimensional (5-D) images from a single-shot 2D recording of speckle-like measurement under incoherent illumination. By employing both the scattering medium and the space-division multiplexing strategy to extract high-dimensional optical features, we show that the multi-dimensional data (2D intensity distribution, spectral, polarization, time) of the desired light field can be encoded into a snapshot speckle-like pattern via a diffuser, and subsequently decoded using a compressed sensing algorithm at the sampling rate of 2.5%, eliminating the need for multi-scanning processes. We further demonstrate that our method can be flexibly switched between 5D and selectively reduced-dimensional imaging, providing an efficient way of reducing computational resource demands. Our work presents a compact, cost-effective, and versatile framework for snapshot multi-dimensional imaging and opens up new opportunities for the design of novel imaging systems for applications in areas such as medical imaging, remote sensing, and autonomous systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13813v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ze Zheng, Baolei Liu, Jiaqi Song, Muchen Zhu, Yao Wang, Menghan Tian, Ying Xiong, Zhaohua Yang, Xiaolan Zhong, David McGloin, Fan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shot-to-shot acquisition ultrafast electron diffraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02540v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We demonstrate a novel shot-to-shot acquisition method for optical pump - keV electron energy probe in ultrafast scattering experiments. We integrate a phase-locked acquisition scheme at a repetition rate of 20kHz in a conventional ultrafast electron diffraction (UED) setup. We proceed to a full characterization of the noise level in different configurations and for realistic scenarios. The shot-to-shot acquisition improves the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) by one order of magnitude and can be readily implemented in other high-repetition rate electron diffraction and spectroscopy setups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02540v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Remi Claude, Michele Puppin, Bruce Weaver, Paolo Usai, Thomas LaGrange, Fabrizio Carbone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Foundation Models for Experimental Readout Systems Combining Discrete and Continuous Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08736v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a (proto) Foundation Model for Nuclear Physics, capable of operating on low-level detector inputs from Imaging Cherenkov Detectors at the future Electron Ion Collider. Building upon established next-token prediction approaches, we aim to address potential challenges such as resolution loss from existing tokenization schemes and limited support for conditional generation. We propose four key innovations: (i) separate vocabularies for discrete and continuous variates, combined via Causal Multi-Head Cross-Attention (CMHCA), (ii) continuous kinematic conditioning through prepended context embeddings, (iii) scalable and simple, high-resolution continuous variate tokenization without joint vocabulary inflation, and (iv) class conditional generation through a Mixture of Experts. Our model enables fast, high-fidelity generation of pixel and time sequences for Cherenkov photons, validated through closure tests in the High Performance DIRC. We also show our model generalizes to reconstruction tasks such as pion/kaon identification, and noise filtering, in which we show its ability to leverage fine-tuning under specific objectives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08736v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Giroux, Cristiano Fanelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
