<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ins-det updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det</link>
    <description>physics.ins-det updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 01:39:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Electron-Gamma Coincidence Setup DAGOBERT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02072v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The QCLAM electron spectrometer at the S-DALINAC electron accelerator at Technische Universit\"at Darmstadt has been extended by the DAGOBERT $\gamma$-detector array consisting of fast timing and high efficiency LaBr$_3$:Ce detectors to perform electron-gamma coincidence measurements. The functionality of the setup and data acquisition system was demonstrated in a commissioning measurement on $^{12}\textrm{C}$ observing the $4.44\,$MeV and $15.11\,$MeV states. A medium-heavy nucleus, $^{96}\textrm{Ru}$, has been studied for the first time up to excitation energies of $15\,$MeV using the $(e,e'\gamma)$ reaction. In particular, the angular distribution of the $2_1^+$ state and the $\gamma$-decay branching ratios of the mixed-symmetric $2_3^+$ state were observed. DAGOBERT@QCLAM is a new and worldwide unique setup for nuclear structure studies of excitation and decay using purely electromagnetic probes, with a significantly improved sensitivity compared to previous experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02072v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nima.2025.170574</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nuclear Instruments and Methods in Physics Research Section A: Accelerators, Spectrometers, Detectors and Associated Equipment 1078, 170574 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>B. Hesbacher, G. Steinhilber, J. Isaak, N. Pietralla, J. Birkhan, M. L. Cort\'es, D. H. Jakubassa-Amundsen, I. Jurosevic, P. von Neumann-Cosel, M. Rech, X. Roca-Maza, D. Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of Hoyle State Decay Branches in Active Target Time Projection Chamber using Neural Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02506v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A multi-class convolutional neural network (CNN) model has been developed using Keras deep learning library in Python for image-based classification of $^{12}$C Hoyle state decay branches from tracking information, recorded by Saha Active Target Time Projection Chamber, SAT-TPC (currently under development). The nuclear events, produced by the 30 MeV $\alpha$-particle beam in the SAT-TPC, filled with Ar + CO$_2$ (90:10) gas mixture at atmospheric pressure, have been considered for training and validation of the models. The elastic scattering and Hoyle state sequential and direct decay events in the interaction of $\alpha$-particle with $^{40}$Ar, $^{12}$C, $^{16}$O nuclei have been generated through Monte-Carlo simulation. The three-dimensional tracks, produced by the scattering and decay products through primary ionization of gaseous medium, have been simulated with Geant4. The primary tracks, distributed on the beam-plane, have been convoluted with electron diffusion, obtained with Magboltz, to produce the final tracking information. The classification performance of the proposed model for different readout segmentation schemes of the SAT-TPC has been discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02506v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pralay Kumar Das, Nayana Majumdar, Supratik Mukhopadhyay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensitivity of a Gigahertz Fabry-P\'erot Resonator for Axion Dark Matter Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03091v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Axions are hypothetical pseudo-Nambu Goldstone bosons that could explain the observed cold dark matter density and solve the strong CP problem of quantum chromodynamics (QCD). Haloscope experiments commonly employ resonant cavities to search for a conversion of axion dark matter into photons in external magnetic fields. As the expected signal power degrades with increasing frequency, this approach becomes challenging at frequencies beyond tens of Gigahertz. Here, we propose a novel haloscope design based on an open Fabry-P\'erot resonator. Operating a small-scale resonator at cryogenic temperatures and at modest magnetic fields should already lead to an unparalleled sensitivity for photon-axion couplings $g_{a\gamma} \gtrsim 3\times10^{-12}\,\mathrm{GeV}^{-1}$ at 35GHz. We demonstrate how this sensitivity could be further improved using graded-phase mirrors and sketch possibilities to probe benchmark models of the QCD axion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03091v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacob Egge, Manuel Meyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Luminescence thermometry based on time gates: highly sensitive approach for real time sensing and imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.01978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.01978v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Undoubtedly, one of the most significant advantages of luminescence thermometry is its ability to be used not only for spot temperature measurements but also for imaging temperature changes. Among the commonly proposed approaches, luminescence thermometry based on luminescence kinetics holds particular promise. However, most thermometric studies rely on the analysis of luminescence decay profiles, a method that significantly hinders, if not entirely precludes, real-time thermal imaging. In this paper, we propose an alternative approach based on the luminescence intensity ratio integrated over two temporal gates. Tests conducted on two representative phosphors, Ba2LaNbO6:1%Mn4+ and Ca2LaNbO6:1%Mn4+, demonstrate that the proposed method not only enables thermal imaging but also achieves substantially higher relative sensitivity, reaching SR=17.1 % K-1 for Ba2LaNbO6:1%Mn4+ and SR=9.4 % K-1 for Ca2LaNbO6:1%Mn4+, compared to the conventional lifetime-based approach (SR=4.2 % K-1 for Ba2LaNbO6:1%Mn4+ and SR=1.2 % K-1 for Ca2LaNbO6:1%Mn4+). Furthermore, careful selection of gate lengths allows optimization of the thermometric performance of the proposed luminescent thermometers. This approach enables expansion of the thermal operating range at the cost of relative sensitivity, providing versatility to adapt the thermometer for specific applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.01978v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Szymczak, D. Szymanski, M. Piasecki, M. Brik, L. Marciniak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing NN reduction in an atom interferometer network for GW detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02087v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The sensitivity of an atom gradiometer aiming to detect gravitational waves (GW) is impacted by fluctuations of Earth's gravity field also called Newtonian Noise (NN). Sensor arrays have proved to be a promising technique for NN reduction. In our study, we further investigate the benefits of Atom Interferometer (AI) networks by improving their geometry and the extraction of the GW signal. We focus on Seismic Newtonian Noise in the frequency band from 0.1 to 10 Hz. On one hand, we show that using a specific detector geometry, a better NN rejection can occur optimizing the number of gradiometers in the network. On the other hand, we show that carrying out optimization in sub frequency bands - which results in using various detector geometries from a common network - allows even higher NN rejection while keeping a similar number of interferometers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02087v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Q. Cojean Palasso\'e, A. Bertoldi, A. Landragin, B. Canuel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Olfactory Inertial Odometry: Methodology for Effective Robot Navigation by Scent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02373v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Olfactory navigation is one of the most primitive mechanisms of exploration used by organisms. Navigation by machine olfaction (artificial smell) is a very difficult task to both simulate and solve. With this work, we define olfactory inertial odometry (OIO), a framework for using inertial kinematics, and fast-sampling olfaction sensors to enable navigation by scent analogous to visual inertial odometry (VIO). We establish how principles from SLAM and VIO can be extrapolated to olfaction to enable real-world robotic tasks. We demonstrate OIO with three different odour localization algorithms on a real 5-DoF robot arm over an odour-tracking scenario that resembles real applications in agriculture and food quality control. Our results indicate success in establishing a baseline framework for OIO from which other research in olfactory navigation can build, and we note performance enhancements that can be made to address more complex tasks in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02373v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kordel K. France, Ovidiu Daescu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design, performance and future prospects of vertex detectors at the FCC-ee</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02675v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The CERN proposed $e^+e^-$ Future Circular Collider (FCC-ee) is an electroweak, flavour, Higgs and top factory with unprecedented luminosities. Many measurements at the FCC-ee will rely on precisely determining the particle production vertices using dedicated vertex detectors. All vertex detector designs use Monolithic Active Pixel Sensors (MAPS) with a single-hit resolution of $\approx$ 3 $\mu$m and a material budget as low as 0.3% of a radiation length per detection layer, which is within specifications for most of the physics analyses. This contribution presents the status of the fully engineered vertex detectors and their integration with the collider beam pipe and discusses their predicted performance using the DD4hep full simulation. A concept for an ultra-light vertex detector using curved wafer-scale MAPS is also presented, which allows reducing the material budget by almost a factor of three. This improves the vertexing capabilities, especially for heavy flavour decays, such as $B^0 \rightarrow K^{*0} \tau^+ \tau^-$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02675v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.22323/1.476.1062</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PoS(ICHEP2024)1062</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Armin Ilg, Fabrizio Palla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-analytical modeling of receive transfer function and thermal noise of integrated photonic ultrasound transducers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02817v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultrasound transducers (UTs) are extensively used in several applications across a multitude of disciplines. A new type of UTs namely integrated photonic ultrasound transducers (IPUTs) possess superior performance due to the presence of optical interrogation systems, avoiding electric crosstalk and thermal electronic noise of the sensor. However, a major component of the IPUT's noise floor is its thermal acoustic noise. Several studies have been proposed to characterize IPUTs' behavior; nevertheless, these are either incomplete (model only the thermal noise) or targeted to characterize specific responses such as static behavior, in which the modeled receive transfer function (RTF) is about two orders lower than the experiments. In this study, we develop semi-analytical models based on time-domain finite element analysis and analytical expressions to characterize the RTF and thermal noise-induced noise equivalent pressure of IPUTs. We validate the models by comparing them with the literature, where we obtain a close match between them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02817v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sabiju Valiya Valappil, Peter Harmsma, Maurits van der Heiden, Martin Verweij, Paul van Neer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measured gain suppression in FBK LGADs with different active thicknesses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02244</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02244v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In recent years, the gain suppression mechanism has been studied for large localized charge deposits in Low-Gain Avalanche Detectors (LGADs). LGADs are a thin silicon detector with a highly doped gain layer that provides moderate internal signal amplification. Using the CENPA Tandem accelerator at the University of Washington, the response of LGADs with different thicknesses to MeV-range energy deposits from a proton beam were studied. Three LGAD prototypes of 50~$\mu$m, 100~$\mu$m, 150~$\mu$m were characterized. The devices' gain was determined as a function of bias voltage, incidence beam angle, and proton energy. This study was conducted in the scope of the PIONEER experiment, an experiment proposed at the Paul Scherrer Institute to perform high-precision measurements of rare pion decays. LGADs are considered for the active target (ATAR) and energy linearity is an important property for particle ID capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02244v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Yang, S. Braun, Q. Buat, J. Ding, M. Harrison, P. Kammel, S. M. Mazza, F. McKinney-Martinez, A. Molnar, J. Ott, A. Seiden, B. Schumm, Y. Zhao, Y. Zhang, V. Tishchenko, A. Bisht, M. Centis-Vignali, G. Paternoster, M. Boscardin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel method for measuring the attenuation length and the group velocity of transparent liquids in a variable length cavity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16811</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16811v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The transparency of liquid scintillators or water is an important parameter for many detectors in particle and astroparticle physics. In this work, the Cavity Enhanced Long Light Path Attenuation Length Screening (CELLPALS) method for the determination of the attenuation length is presented for the first time. The method is based on an experimental setup similar to a Fabry-P\'erot interferometer but adding up multiple-reflected intensities of a modulated light source. CELLPALS was developed to measure the attenuation length of highly transparent liquids (&gt; 10 m) with significantly lower uncertainties than with UV-Vis spectroscopy, which is a standard method for determining the attenuation length. In addition to the attenuation length, the group velocity of light in the sample can also be derived from the free spectral range of the cavity, which is not provided by any conventional method for determining the attenuation length. In this work, the CELLPALS method, its achievable precision and an experimental setup to demonstrate its feasibility are discussed. The attenuation lengths and group velocities of several transparent liquids were measured at wavelengths between 420 nm and 435 nm. In addition, the attenuation length and group velocity of linear alkylbenzene (LAB) samples after different purification stages and a purified LAB-based liquid scintillator were measured at a wavelength of 425 nm. The results confirmed the potential of CELLPALS to determine the attenuation length with an uncertainty of ~ 2 %. The group velocity of light in the sample can be determined with an uncertainty of ~ 0.03 %.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16811v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nima.2025.170507</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nucl. Instrum. Methods Phys. Res. A 1056 (2025) 170507</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jessica Eck, Dhanushka Bandara, Gina Gr\"unauer, Tobias Heinz, Tobias Lachenmaier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>XENONnT WIMP Search: Signal &amp; Background Modeling and Statistical Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13638v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The XENONnT experiment searches for weakly-interacting massive particle (WIMP) dark matter scattering off a xenon nucleus. In particular, XENONnT uses a dual-phase time projection chamber with a 5.9-tonne liquid xenon target, detecting both scintillation and ionization signals to reconstruct the energy, position, and type of recoil. A blind search for nuclear recoil WIMPs with an exposure of 1.1 tonne-years (4.18 t fiducial mass) yielded no signal excess over background expectations, from which competitive exclusion limits were derived on WIMP-nucleon elastic scatter cross sections, for WIMP masses ranging from 6 GeV/$c^2$ up to the TeV/$c^2$ scale. This work details the modeling and statistical methods employed in this search. By means of calibration data, we model the detector response, which is then used to derive background and signal models. The construction and validation of these models is discussed, alongside additional purely data-driven backgrounds. We also describe the statistical inference framework, including the definition of the likelihood function and the construction of confidence intervals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13638v2</guid>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.103040</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator> XENON Collaboration, E. Aprile, J. Aalbers, K. Abe, S. Ahmed Maouloud, L. Althueser, B. Andrieu, E. Angelino, D. Ant\'on Martin, F. Arneodo, L. Baudis, M. Bazyk, L. Bellagamba, R. Biondi, A. Bismark, K. Boese, A. Brown, G. Bruno, R. Budnik, J. M. R. Cardoso, A. P. Cimental Ch\'avez, A. P. Colijn, J. Conrad, J. J. Cuenca-Garc\'ia, V. D'Andrea, L. C. Daniel Garcia, M. P. Decowski, C. Di Donato, P. Di Gangi, S. Diglio, K. Eitel, A. Elykov, A. D. Ferella, C. Ferrari, H. Fischer, T. Flehmke, M. Flierman, W. Fulgione, C. Fuselli, P. Gaemers, R. Gaior, M. Galloway, F. Gao, S. Ghosh, R. Giacomobono, R. Glade-Beucke, L. Grandi, J. Grigat, H. Guan, M. Guida, P. Gyoergy, R. Hammann, A. Higuera, C. Hils, L. Hoetzsch, N. F. Hood, M. Iacovacci, Y. Itow, J. Jakob, F. Joerg, Y. Kaminaga, M. Kara, P. Kavrigin, S. Kazama, M. Kobayashi, A. Kopec, F. Kuger, H. Landsman, R. F. Lang, L. Levinson, I. Li, S. Li, S. Liang, Y. -T. Lin, S. Lindemann, M. Lindner, K. Liu, J. Loizeau, F. Lombardi, J. Long, J. A. M. Lopes, T. Luce, Y. Ma, C. Macolino, J. Mahlstedt, A. Mancuso, L. Manenti, F. Marignetti, T. Marrod\'an Undagoitia, K. Martens, J. Masbou, E. Masson, S. Mastroianni, A. Melchiorre, M. Messina, A. Michael, K. Miuchi, A. Molinario, S. Moriyama, K. Mor{\aa}, Y. Mosbacher, M. Murra, J. M\"uller, K. Ni, U. Oberlack, B. Paetsch, Y. Pan, Q. Pellegrini, R. Peres, C. Peters, J. Pienaar, M. Pierre, G. Plante, T. R. Pollmann, L. Principe, J. Qi, J. Qin, D. Ram\'irez Garc\'ia, M. Rajado, R. Singh, L. Sanchez, J. M. F. dos Santos, I. Sarnoff, G. Sartorelli, J. Schreiner, D. Schulte, P. Schulte, H. Schulze Ei{\ss}ing, M. Schumann, L. Scotto Lavina, M. Selvi, F. Semeria, P. Shagin, S. Shi, J. Shi, M. Silva, H. Simgen, A. Takeda, P. -L. Tan, A. Terliuk, D. Thers, F. Toschi, G. Trinchero, C. D. Tunnell, F. T\"onnies, K. Valerius, S. Vecchi, S. Vetter, F. I. Villazon Solar, G. Volta, C. Weinheimer, M. Weiss, D. Wenz, C. Wittweg, V. H. S. Wu, Y. Xing, D. Xu, Z. Xu, M. Yamashita, L. Yang, J. Ye, L. Yuan, G. Zavattini, M. Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnon spectroscopy in the electron microscope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02908v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The miniaturisation of transistors is approaching its limits due to challenges in heat management and information transfer speed. To overcome these obstacles, emerging technologies such as spintronics are being developed, which leverage the electron's spin in addition to its charge. Local phenomena at interfaces or structural defects will greatly influence the efficiency of spin-based devices, making the ability to study and control spin wave propagation at the nano- and atomic scales a key challenge. The development of high-spatial-resolution tools to probe spin waves, also called magnons, at relevant lengthscales is thus essential to understand how their properties are affected by such local features. Here, we show the first experimental detection of bulk magnons at the nanoscale using scanning transmission electron microscopy. By employing high-resolution electron energy loss spectroscopy with hybrid-pixel direct electron detectors optimized for low acceleration voltages, we successfully overcome the challenges posed by weak signals and identify magnon excitations in a thin NiO nanocrystal. Advanced inelastic electron scattering simulations corroborate our findings. These results open new avenues for detecting magnons, exploring their dispersions and their modifications arising from nanoscale structural or chemical defects. This marks an important milestone in magnonics and presents exciting opportunities for the future development of spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02908v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Demie Kepaptsoglou, Jos\'e \'Angel Castellanos-Reyes, Adam Kerrigan, J\'ulio Alves Do Nascimento, Paul M. Zeiger, Khalil El Hajraoui, Juan Carlos Idrobo, Budhika G. Mendis, Anders Bergman, Vlado K. Lazarov, J\'an Rusz, Quentin M. Ramasse</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error-Free Demodulation of Pixelated Interferograms: Updated review and circumstantial evidence of plagiarism by 4D Technology Corporation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14927v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper examines the historical development that led to error-free phase demodulation of pixelated spatial-carrier interferograms between 2004 and 2010. It also evaluates evidence suggesting that 4D Technology Corporation (4DTC), in their SPIE 7790 publication [18], may have adopted key concepts from a manuscript submitted by Servin and collaborators, which at that time was still under peer review [17]. We analyze 4DTC algorithms based on 2x2 and 3x3 spatial convolution phase shifting algorithms (SC-PSA), developed from 2004 to 2009 [9-15], and show that they were fundamentally limited to narrow bandwidth fringe demodulation. Notably, only one 4DTC's paper [13] acknowledged major phase errors when these methods were applied to wideband pixelated fringes, but the problem remained unsolved. In 2010, the team at Centro de Investigaciones en Optica (CIO), led by Servin, entered the field [16,17]. At that point, CIO and 4DTC were the only two known groups pursuing error free demodulation of wideband pixelated interferograms. In June 2010, Servin et al submitted to Optics Express [17] a definitive error-free solution introducing a new method: the complex fringe-carrier product followed by step-edge low-pass Fourier filtering. This approach fully superseded the 2x2 and 3x3 kernels used by 4DTC [9-15], reaching the theoretical slope limit for pixelated sensors. Given the notable phase demodulation similarities between papers [17] and [18], and that the presentation of [18] was just seven weeks after Servin submission [17], it is plausible that 4DTC or an affiliate had early access to the submission. The circumstantial evidence suggests that core ideas from [17] were incorporated into 4DTC August presentation [18]. This paper retraces that scientific path and examines the ethical implications of uncredited appropriation in optical research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14927v4</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel Servin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
