<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ins-det updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det</link>
    <description>physics.ins-det updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 02:02:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Studies of Directed Flow with Event Plane Method in the HIRFL-CSR External-target Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22774v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Cooling-Storage-Ring External-target Experiment (CEE) at Heavy Ion Research Facility in Lanzhou (HIRFL) is designed to study the properties of nuclear matter created in heavy-ion collisions at a few hundred MeV/$u$ to 1 GeV/$u$ beam energies, facilitating the research of quantum chromodynamics phase structure in the high-baryon-density region. Collective flow is one of the most important observables in heavy-ion collision experiments to study the bulk behavior of the created matter. Even though the standard event plane method has been widely used for collective flow measurements, it remains crucial to validate and optimize this method for the CEE spectrometer. In this paper, we study the experimental procedures of measuring directed flow in $^{238}$U+$^{238}$U collisions at 500 MeV/$u$ using event planes reconstructed by Multi Wire Drift Chamber and Zero Degree Calorimeter, respectively. Jet AA Microscopic (JAM) transport generator is used to generate events, and the detector response is simulated by the CEE Fast Simulation (CFS) package. Finally, the optimal kinetic region for proton directed flow measurements is discussed for the future CEE experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22774v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wanlong Wu, Xionghong He, Yanyu Ren, Diyu Shen, Shusu Shi, Xu Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The DUNE Phase II Detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23293v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The international collaboration designing and constructing the Deep Underground Neutrino Experiment (DUNE) at the Long-Baseline Neutrino Facility (LBNF) has developed a two-phase strategy for the implementation of this leading-edge, large-scale science project. The 2023 report of the US Particle Physics Project Prioritization Panel (P5) reaffirmed this vision and strongly endorsed DUNE Phase I and Phase II, as did the previous European Strategy for Particle Physics. The construction of DUNE Phase I is well underway. DUNE Phase II consists of a third and fourth far detector module, an upgraded near detector complex, and an enhanced &gt; 2 MW beam. The fourth FD module is conceived as a 'Module of Opportunity', aimed at supporting the core DUNE science program while also expanding the physics opportunities with more advanced technologies. The DUNE collaboration is submitting four main contributions to the 2026 Update of the European Strategy for Particle Physics process. This submission to the 'Detector instrumentation' stream focuses on technologies and R&amp;D for the DUNE Phase II detectors. Additional inputs related to the DUNE science program, DUNE software and computing, and European contributions to Fermilab accelerator upgrades and facilities for the DUNE experiment, are also being submitted to other streams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23293v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> DUNE Collaboration, A. Abed Abud, R. Acciarri, M. A. Acero, M. R. Adames, G. Adamov, M. Adamowski, D. Adams, M. Adinolfi, C. Adriano, A. Aduszkiewicz, J. Aguilar, F. Akbar, F. Alemanno, N. S. Alex, K. Allison, M. Alrashed, A. Alton, R. Alvarez, T. Alves, A. Aman, H. Amar, P. Amedo, J. Anderson, D. A. Andrade, C. Andreopoulos, M. Andreotti, M. P. Andrews, F. Andrianala, S. Andringa, F. Anjarazafy, D. Antic, M. Antoniassi, M. Antonova, A. Aranda-Fernandez, L. Arellano, E. Arrieta Diaz, M. A. Arroyave, J. Asaadi, M. Ascencio, A. Ashkenazi, D. Asner, L. Asquith, E. Atkin, D. Auguste, A. Aurisano, V. Aushev, D. Autiero, D. \'Avila G\'omez, M. B. Azam, F. Azfar, A. Back, H. Back, J. J. Back, I. Bagaturia, L. Bagby, D. Baigarashev, S. Balasubramanian, A. Balboni, P. Baldi, W. Baldini, J. Baldonedo, B. Baller, B. Bambah, R. Banerjee, F. Barao, D. Barbu, G. Barenboim, P. \ Barham Alz\'as, G. J. Barker, W. Barkhouse, G. Barr, J. Barranco Monarca, A. Barros, N. Barros, D. Barrow, J. L. Barrow, A. Basharina-Freshville, A. Bashyal, V. Basque, D. Basu, C. Batchelor, L. Bathe-Peters, J. B. R. Battat, F. Battisti, F. Bay, M. C. Q. Bazetto, J. L. L. Bazo Alba, J. F. Beacom, E. Bechetoille, B. Behera, E. Belchior, B. Bell, G. Bell, L. Bellantoni, G. Bellettini, V. Bellini, O. Beltramello, C. Benitez Montiel, D. Benjamin, F. Bento Neves, J. Berger, S. Berkman, J. Bernal, P. Bernardini, A. Bersani, E. Bertolini, S. Bertolucci, M. Betancourt, A. Betancur Rodr\'iguez, Y. Bezawada, A. T. Bezerra, A. Bhat, V. Bhatnagar, J. Bhatt, M. Bhattacharjee, M. Bhattacharya, S. Bhuller, B. Bhuyan, S. Biagi, J. Bian, K. Biery, B. Bilki, M. Bishai, A. Blake, F. D. Blaszczyk, G. C. Blazey, E. Blucher, B. Bogart, J. Bogenschuetz, J. Boissevain, S. Bolognesi, T. Bolton, L. Bomben, M. Bonesini, C. Bonilla-Diaz, A. Booth, F. Boran, R. Borges Merlo, N. Bostan, G. Botogoske, B. Bottino, R. Bouet, J. Boza, J. Bracinik, B. Brahma, D. Brailsford, F. Bramati, A. Branca, A. Brandt, J. Bremer, S. J. Brice, V. Brio, C. Brizzolari, C. Bromberg, J. Brooke, A. Bross, G. Brunetti, M. B. Brunetti, N. Buchanan, H. Budd, J. Buergi, A. Bundock, D. Burgardt, S. Butchart, G. Caceres V., T. Cai, R. Calabrese, R. Calabrese, J. Calcutt, L. Calivers, E. Calvo, A. Caminata, A. F. Camino, W. Campanelli, A. Campani, A. Campos Benitez, N. Canci, J. Cap\'o, I. Caracas, D. Caratelli, D. Carber, J. M. Carceller, G. Carini, B. Carlus, M. F. Carneiro, P. Carniti, I. Caro Terrazas, H. Carranza, N. Carrara, L. Carroll, T. Carroll, A. Carter, E. Casarejos, D. Casazza, J. F. Casta\~no Forero, F. A. Casta\~no, A. Castillo, C. Castromonte, E. Catano-Mur, C. Cattadori, F. Cavalier, F. Cavanna, S. Centro, G. Cerati, C. Cerna, A. Cervelli, A. Cervera Villanueva, J. Chakrani, M. Chalifour, A. Chappell, A. Chatterjee, B. Chauhan, C. Chavez Barajas, H. Chen, M. Chen, W. C. Chen, Y. Chen, Z. Chen, D. Cherdack, S. S. Chhibra, C. Chi, F. Chiapponi, R. Chirco, N. Chitirasreemadam, K. Cho, S. Choate, G. Choi, D. Chokheli, P. S. Chong, B. Chowdhury, D. Christian, M. Chung, E. Church, M. F. Cicala, M. Cicerchia, V. Cicero, R. Ciolini, P. Clarke, G. Cline, A. G. Cocco, J. A. B. Coelho, A. Cohen, J. Collazo, J. Collot, J. M. Conrad, M. Convery, K. Conway, S. Copello, P. Cova, C. Cox, L. Cremonesi, J. I. Crespo-Anad\'on, M. Crisler, E. Cristaldo, J. Crnkovic, G. Crone, R. Cross, A. Cudd, C. Cuesta, Y. Cui, F. Curciarello, D. Cussans, J. Dai, O. Dalager, W. Dallaway, R. D'Amico, H. da Motta, Z. A. Dar, R. Darby, L. Da Silva Peres, Q. David, G. S. Davies, S. Davini, J. Dawson, R. De Aguiar, P. De Almeida, P. Debbins, M. P. Decowski, A. de Gouv\^ea, P. C. De Holanda, P. De Jong, P. Del Amo Sanchez, G. De Lauretis, A. Delbart, D. Delepine, M. Delgado, A. Dell'Acqua, G. Delle Monache, N. Delmonte, P. De Lurgio, R. Demario, G. De Matteis, J. R. T. de Mello Neto, A. P. A. De Mendonca, D. M. DeMuth, S. Dennis, C. Densham, P. Denton, G. W. Deptuch, A. De Roeck, V. De Romeri, J. P. Detje, J. Devine, R. Dharmapalan, M. Dias, A. Diaz, J. S. D\'iaz, F. D\'iaz, F. Di Capua, A. Di Domenico, S. Di Domizio, S. Di Falco, L. Di Giulio, P. Ding, L. Di Noto, E. Diociaiuti, V. Di Silvestre, C. Distefano, R. Diurba, M. Diwan, Z. Djurcic, S. Dolan, M. Dolce, F. Dolek, M. J. Dolinski, D. Domenici, S. Donati, Y. Donon, S. Doran, D. Douglas, T. A. Doyle, F. Drielsma, L. Duarte, D. Duchesneau, K. Duffy, K. Dugas, P. Dunne, B. Dutta, H. Duyang, D. A. Dwyer, A. S. Dyshkant, S. Dytman, M. Eads, A. Earle, S. Edayath, D. Edmunds, J. Eisch, W. Emark, P. Englezos, A. Ereditato, T. Erjavec, C. O. Escobar, J. J. Evans, E. Ewart, A. C. Ezeribe, K. Fahey, A. Falcone, M. Fani', C. Farnese, S. Farrell, Y. Farzan, J. Felix, Y. Feng, M. Ferreira da Silva, G. Ferry, E. Fialova, L. Fields, P. Filip, A. Filkins, F. Filthaut, G. Fiorillo, M. Fiorini, S. Fogarty, W. Foreman, J. Fowler, J. Franc, K. Francis, D. Franco, J. Freeman, J. Fried, A. Friedland, M. Fucci, S. Fuess, I. K. Furic, K. Furman, A. P. Furmanski, R. Gaba, A. Gabrielli, A. M. Gago, F. Galizzi, H. Gallagher, M. Galli, N. Gallice, V. Galymov, E. Gamberini, T. Gamble, R. Gandhi, S. Ganguly, F. Gao, S. Gao, D. Garcia-Gamez, M. \'A. Garc\'ia-Peris, F. Gardim, S. Gardiner, D. Gastler, A. Gauch, P. Gauzzi, S. Gazzana, G. Ge, N. Geffroy, B. Gelli, S. Gent, L. Gerlach, A. Ghosh, T. Giammaria, D. Gibin, I. Gil-Botella, S. Gilligan, A. Gioiosa, S. Giovannella, A. K. Giri, C. Giugliano, V. Giusti, D. Gnani, O. Gogota, S. Gollapinni, K. Gollwitzer, R. A. Gomes, L. V. Gomez Bermeo, L. S. Gomez Fajardo, D. Gonzalez-Diaz, M. C. Goodman, S. Goswami, C. Gotti, J. Goudeau, E. Goudzovski, C. Grace, E. Gramellini, R. Gran, E. Granados, P. Granger, C. Grant, D. R. Gratieri, G. Grauso, P. Green, S. Greenberg, J. Greer, W. C. Griffith, K. Grzelak, L. Gu, W. Gu, V. Guarino, M. Guarise, R. Guenette, M. Guerzoni, D. Guffanti, A. Guglielmi, B. Guo, F. Y. Guo, V. Gupta, G. Gurung, D. Gutierrez, P. Guzowski, M. M. Guzzo, S. Gwon, A. Habig, L. Haegel, R. Hafeji, L. Hagaman, A. Hahn, J. Hakenm\"uller, T. Hamernik, P. Hamilton, J. Hancock, M. Handley, F. Happacher, D. A. Harris, A. L. Hart, J. Hartnell, T. Hartnett, J. Harton, T. Hasegawa, C. M. Hasnip, R. Hatcher, S. Hawkins, J. Hays, M. He, A. Heavey, K. M. Heeger, A. Heindel, J. Heise, P. Hellmuth, L. Henderson, K. Herner, V. Hewes, A. Higuera, C. Hilgenberg, A. Himmel, E. Hinkle, L. R. Hirsch, J. Ho, J. Hoefken Zink, J. Hoff, A. Holin, T. Holvey, C. Hong, E. Hoppe, S. Horiuchi, G. A. Horton-Smith, R. Hosokawa, T. Houdy, B. Howard, R. Howell, I. Hristova, M. S. Hronek, H. Hua, J. Huang, R. G. Huang, X. Huang, Z. Hulcher, G. Iles, N. Ilic, A. M. Iliescu, R. Illingworth, G. Ingratta, A. Ioannisian, B. Irwin, M. Ismerio Oliveira, C. M. Jackson, V. Jain, E. James, W. Jang, B. Jargowsky, D. Jena, I. Jentz, X. Ji, C. Jiang, J. Jiang, A. Jipa, J. H. Jo, F. R. Joaquim, W. Johnson, C. Jollet, R. Jones, N. Jovancevic, M. Judah, C. K. Jung, K. Y. Jung, T. Junk, Y. Jwa, M. Kabirnezhad, A. C. Kaboth, I. Kadenko, O. Kalikulov, D. Kalra, M. Kandemir, D. M. Kaplan, G. Karagiorgi, G. Karaman, A. Karcher, Y. Karyotakis, S. P. Kasetti, L. Kashur, A. Kauther, N. Kazaryan, L. Ke, E. Kearns, P. T. Keener, K. J. Kelly, R. Keloth, E. Kemp, O. Kemularia, Y. Kermaidic, W. Ketchum, S. H. Kettell, N. Khan, A. Khvedelidze, D. Kim, J. Kim, M. J. Kim, S. Kim, B. King, M. King, M. Kirby, A. Kish, J. Klein, J. Kleykamp, A. Klustova, T. Kobilarcik, L. Koch, K. Koehler, L. W. Koerner, D. H. Koh, M. Kordosky, T. Kosc, V. A. Kosteleck\'y, K. Kothekar, I. Kotler, M. Kovalcuk, R. Kralik, M. Kramer, L. Kreczko, F. Krennrich, T. Kroupova, S. Kubota, M. Kubu, V. A. Kudryavtsev, G. Kufatty, S. Kuhlmann, J. Kumar, M. Kumar, P. Kumar, P. Kumar, S. Kumaran, J. Kunzmann, R. Kuravi, V. Kus, T. Kutter, J. Kvasnicka, T. Labree, T. Lackey, I. Lal{\u{a}}u, A. Lambert, B. J. Land, C. E. Lane, N. Lane, K. Lang, T. Langford, M. Langstaff, F. Lanni, J. Larkin, P. Lasorak, D. Last, A. Laundrie, G. Laurenti, E. Lavaut, P. Laycock, I. Lazanu, R. LaZur, M. Lazzaroni, T. Le, S. Leardini, J. Learned, T. LeCompte, G. Lehmann Miotto, R. Lehnert, M. Leitner, H. Lemoine, D. Leon Silverio, L. M. Lepin, J. -Y. Li, S. W. Li, Y. Li, H. Liao, R. Lima, C. S. Lin, D. Lindebaum, S. Linden, R. A. Lineros, A. Lister, B. R. Littlejohn, H. Liu, J. Liu, Y. Liu, S. Lockwitz, I. Lomidze, K. Long, T. V. Lopes, J. Lopez, I. L\'opez de Rego, N. L\'opez-March, J. M. LoSecco, W. C. Louis, A. Lozano Sanchez, X. -G. Lu, K. B. Luk, X. Luo, E. Luppi, A. A. Machado, P. Machado, C. T. Macias, J. R. Macier, M. MacMahon, S. Magill, C. Magueur, K. Mahn, A. Maio, A. Major, K. Majumdar, A. Malige, S. Mameli, M. Man, R. C. Mandujano, J. Maneira, S. Manly, A. Mann, K. Manolopoulos, M. Manrique Plata, S. Manthey Corchado, V. N. Manyam, L. Manzanillas-Velez, M. Marchan, A. Marchionni, W. Marciano, D. Marfatia, C. Mariani, J. Maricic, F. Marinho, A. D. Marino, T. Markiewicz, F. Das Chagas Marques, C. Marquet, M. Marshak, C. M. Marshall, J. Marshall, L. Martina, J. Mart\'in-Albo, N. Martinez, D. A. Martinez Caicedo, M. Martinez-Casales, F. Mart\'inez L\'opez, P. Mart\'inez Mirav\'e, S. Martynenko, V. Mascagna, A. Mastbaum, M. Masud, F. Matichard, G. Matteucci, J. Matthews, C. Mauger, N. Mauri, K. Mavrokoridis, I. Mawby, F. Mayhew, R. Mazza, T. McAskill, N. McConkey, K. S. McFarland, C. McGrew, A. McNab, C. McNulty, J. Mead, L. Meazza, V. C. N. Meddage, M. Mehmood, B. Mehta, P. Mehta, F. Mei, P. Melas, L. Mellet, O. Mena, H. Mendez, D. P. M\'endez, A. Menegolli, G. Meng, A. C. E. A. Mercuri, A. Meregaglia, M. D. Messier, S. Metallo, W. Metcalf, M. Mewes, H. Meyer, T. Miao, J. Micallef, A. Miccoli, G. Michna, R. Milincic, F. Miller, G. Miller, W. Miller, A. Minotti, L. Miralles Verge, C. Mironov, S. Miryala, S. Miscetti, C. S. Mishra, P. Mishra, S. R. Mishra, A. Mislivec, D. Mladenov, I. Mocioiu, A. Mogan, R. Mohanta, T. A. Mohayai, N. Mokhov, J. Molina, L. Molina Bueno, E. Montagna, A. Montanari, C. Montanari, D. Montanari, D. Montanino, L. M. Monta\~no Zetina, M. Mooney, A. F. Moor, M. Moore, Z. Moore, D. Moreno, G. Moreno-Granados, O. Moreno-Palacios, L. Morescalchi, R. Moretti, C. Morris, C. Mossey, E. Motuk, C. A. Moura, G. Mouster, W. Mu, L. Mualem, J. Mueller, M. Muether, F. Muheim, A. Muir, Y. Mukhamejanov, A. Mukhamejanova, M. Mulhearn, D. Munford, L. J. Munteanu, H. Muramatsu, J. Muraz, M. Murphy, T. Murphy, J. Muse, A. Mytilinaki, J. Nachtman, Y. Nagai, S. Nagu, D. Naples, S. Narita, J. Nava, A. Navrer-Agasson, N. Nayak, M. Nebot-Guinot, A. Nehm, J. K. Nelson, O. Neogi, J. Nesbit, M. Nessi, D. Newbold, M. Newcomer, R. Nichol, F. Nicolas-Arnaldos, A. Nielsen, A. Nikolica, J. Nikolov, E. Niner, X. Ning, K. Nishimura, A. Norman, A. Norrick, P. Novella, A. Nowak, J. A. Nowak, M. Oberling, J. P. Ochoa-Ricoux, S. Oh, S. B. Oh, A. Olivier, T. Olson, Y. Onel, Y. Onishchuk, A. Oranday, M. Osbiston, J. A. Osorio V\'elez, L. O'Sullivan, L. Otiniano Ormachea, L. Pagani, G. Palacio, O. Palamara, S. Palestini, J. M. Paley, M. Pallavicini, C. Palomares, S. Pan, M. Panareo, P. Panda, V. Pandey, W. Panduro Vazquez, E. Pantic, V. Paolone, A. Papadopoulou, R. Papaleo, D. Papoulias, S. Paramesvaran, S. Parke, S. Parsa, Z. Parsa, S. Parveen, M. Parvu, D. Pasciuto, S. Pascoli, L. Pasqualini, J. Pasternak, J. L. Paton, C. Patrick, L. Patrizii, R. B. Patterson, T. Patzak, A. Paudel, L. Paulucci, Z. Pavlovic, G. Pawloski, D. Payne, A. Peake, V. Pec, E. Pedreschi, S. J. M. Peeters, W. Pellico, E. Pennacchio, A. Penzo, O. L. G. Peres, L. P\'erez-Molina, C. Pernas, J. Perry, D. Pershey, G. Pessina, G. Petrillo, C. Petta, R. Petti, M. Pfaff, V. Pia, L. Pickering, L. Pierini, F. Pietropaolo, V. L. Pimentel, G. Pinaroli, S. Pincha, J. Pinchault, K. Pitts, K. Pletcher, K. Plows, C. Pollack, T. Pollmann, F. Pompa, X. Pons, N. Poonthottathil, V. Popov, F. Poppi, J. Porter, L. G. Porto Paix{\~a}o, M. Potekhin, M. Pozzato, R. Pradhan, T. Prakash, M. Prest, F. Psihas, D. Pugnere, D. Pullia, X. Qian, J. Queen, J. L. Raaf, M. Rabelhofer, V. Radeka, J. Rademacker, B. Radics, F. Raffaelli, A. Rafique, E. Raguzin, A. Rahe, S. Rajagopalan, M. Rajaoalisoa, I. Rakhno, L. Rakotondravohitra, M. A. Ralaikoto, L. Ralte, M. A. Ramirez Delgado, B. Ramson, S. S. Randriamanampisoa, A. Rappoldi, G. Raselli, T. Rath, P. Ratoff, R. Ray, H. Razafinime, R. F. Razakamiandra, E. M. Rea, J. S. Real, B. Rebel, R. Rechenmacher, J. Reichenbacher, S. D. Reitzner, E. Renner, S. Repetto, S. Rescia, F. Resnati, C. Reynolds, M. Ribas, S. Riboldi, C. Riccio, G. Riccobene, J. S. Ricol, M. Rigan, A. Rikalo, E. V. Rinc\'on, A. Ritchie-Yates, S. Ritter, D. Rivera, A. Robert, A. Roberts, E. Robles, J. L. Rocabado Rocha, M. Roda, D. Rodas Rodr\'iguez, M. J. O. Rodrigues, J. Rodriguez Rondon, S. Rosauro-Alcaraz, P. Rosier, D. Ross, M. Rossella, M. Rossi, M. Ross-Lonergan, N. Roy, P. Roy, P. Roy, C. Rubbia, D. Rudik, A. Ruggeri, G. Ruiz Ferreira, K. Rushiya, B. Russell, S. Sacerdoti, N. Saduyev, S. K. Sahoo, N. Sahu, S. Sakhiyev, P. Sala, G. Salmoria, S. Samanta, N. Samios, M. C. Sanchez, A. S\'anchez Bravo, A. S\'anchez-Castillo, P. Sanchez-Lucas, D. A. Sanders, S. Sanfilippo, D. Santoro, N. Saoulidou, P. Sapienza, I. Sarcevic, I. Sarra, G. Savage, V. Savinov, G. Scanavini, A. Scaramelli, A. Scarff, T. Schefke, H. Schellman, S. Schifano, P. Schlabach, D. Schmitz, A. W. Schneider, K. Scholberg, A. Schukraft, B. Schuld, S. Schwartz, A. Segade, E. Segreto, C. R. Senise, J. Sensenig, S. H. Seo, D. Seppela, M. H. Shaevitz, P. Shanahan, P. Sharma, R. Kumar, S. Sharma Poudel, K. Shaw, T. Shaw, K. Shchablo, J. Shen, C. Shepherd-Themistocleous, J. Shi, W. Shi, S. Shin, S. Shivakoti, A. Shmakov, I. Shoemaker, D. Shooltz, R. Shrock, M. Siden, J. Silber, L. Simard, J. Sinclair, G. Sinev, Jaydip Singh, J. Singh, L. Singh, P. Singh, V. Singh, S. Singh Chauhan, R. Sipos, C. Sironneau, G. Sirri, K. Siyeon, K. Skarpaas, J. Smedley, J. Smith, P. Smith, J. Smolik, M. Smy, M. Snape, E. L. Snider, P. Snopok, M. Soares Nunes, H. Sobel, M. Soderberg, C. J. Solano Salinas, S. S\"oldner-Rembold, N. Solomey, V. Solovov, W. E. Sondheim, M. Sorbara, M. Sorel, J. Soto-Oton, A. Sousa, K. Soustruznik, D. Souza Correia, F. Spinella, J. Spitz, N. J. C. Spooner, D. Stalder, M. Stancari, L. Stanco, J. Steenis, R. Stein, H. M. Steiner, A. F. Steklain Lisb\^oa, J. Stewart, B. Stillwell, J. Stock, T. Stokes, M. Strait, T. Strauss, L. Strigari, A. Stuart, J. G. Suarez, J. Subash, A. Surdo, L. Suter, K. Sutton, Y. Suvorov, R. Svoboda, S. K. Swain, C. Sweeney, B. Szczerbinska, A. M. Szelc, A. Sztuc, A. Taffara, N. Talukdar, J. Tamara, H. A. Tanaka, S. Tang, N. Taniuchi, A. M. Tapia Casanova, A. Tapper, S. Tariq, E. Tarpara, E. Tatar, R. Tayloe, D. Tedeschi, A. M. Teklu, K. Tellez Giron Flores, J. Tena Vidal, P. Tennessen, M. Tenti, K. Terao, F. Terranova, G. Testera, T. Thakore, A. Thea, S. Thomas, A. Thompson, C. Thorn, C. Thorpe, S. C. Timm, E. Tiras, V. Tishchenko, S. Tiwari, N. Todorovi\'c, L. Tomassetti, A. Tonazzo, D. Torbunov, D. Torres Mu\~noz, M. Torti, M. Tortola, Y. Torun, N. Tosi, D. Totani, M. Toups, C. Touramanis, V. Trabattoni, D. Tran, R. Travaglini, J. Trevor, E. Triller, S. Trilov, D. Trotta, J. Truchon, D. Truncali, W. H. Trzaska, Y. Tsai, Y. -T. Tsai, Z. Tsamalaidze, K. V. Tsang, N. Tsverava, S. Z. Tu, S. Tufanli, C. Tunnell, M. Tuzi, J. Tyler, E. Tyley, M. Tzanov, M. A. Uchida, J. Ure\~na Gonz\'alez, J. Urheim, T. Usher, H. Utaegbulam, S. Uzunyan, M. R. Vagins, P. Vahle, G. A. Valdiviesso, V. Vale, E. Valencia, R. Valentim, Z. Vallari, E. Vallazza, J. W. F. Valle, R. Van Berg, D. V. Forero, A. Vannozzi, M. Van Nuland-Troost, F. Varanini, D. Vargas Oliva, N. Vaughan, K. Vaziri, A. V\'azquez-Ramos, J. Vega, J. Vences, S. Ventura, A. Verdugo, S. Vergani, M. Verzocchi, K. Vetter, M. Vicenzi, H. Vieira de Souza, C. Vignoli, C. Vilela, E. Villa, S. Viola, B. Viren, G. V. Stenico, R. Vizarreta, A. P. Vizcaya Hernandez, S. Vlachos, G. Vorobyev, Q. Vuong, A. V. Waldron, M. Wallach, J. Walsh, T. Walton, L. Wan, B. Wang, H. Wang, J. Wang, L. Wang, M. H. L. S. Wang, X. Wang, Y. Wang, K. Warburton, D. Warner, L. Warsame, M. O. Wascko, D. Waters, A. Watson, K. Wawrowska, A. Weber, C. M. Weber, M. Weber, H. Wei, A. Weinstein, S. Westerdale, M. Wetstein, K. Whalen, A. White, L. H. Whitehead, D. Whittington, F. Wieler, J. Wilhlemi, M. J. Wilking, A. Wilkinson, C. Wilkinson, F. Wilson, R. J. Wilson, P. Winter, J. Wolcott, J. Wolfs, T. Wongjirad, A. Wood, K. Wood, E. Worcester, M. Worcester, K. Wresilo, M. Wright, M. Wrobel, S. Wu, W. Wu, W. Wu, M. Wurm, J. Wyenberg, B. M. Wynne, Y. Xiao, I. Xiotidis, B. Yaeggy, N. Yahlali, E. Yandel, G. Yang, J. Yang, T. Yang, A. Yankelevich, L. Yates, K. Yonehara, T. Young, B. Yu, H. Yu, J. Yu, Y. Yu, W. Yuan, R. Zaki, J. Zalesak, L. Zambelli, B. Zamorano, A. Zani, O. Zapata, L. Zazueta, G. P. Zeller, J. Zennamo, J. Zettlemoyer, K. Zeug, C. Zhang, S. Zhang, M. Zhao, E. Zhivun, E. D. Zimmerman, S. Zucchelli, V. Zutshi, R. Zwaska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of muon absorption tomography in imaging of civil structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The research focuses on the non-invasive imaging technique using cosmic muon absorption tomography to monitor the internals of archaeological / civil / industrial structures of intermediate size. It integrates experimental measurements and numerical simulations with Geant4, ascertaining the reliability and precision of muon absorption tomography using easily available components for the stated purpose. The experiment probes muon interactions across a range of materials including those commonly used in building civil and industrial structures. An experiment, fondly named MARS (Muon Absorption in Rigid Structures), was carried out to explore the possibility of using overlapped scintillation paddles for improved mapping of inhomogeneities in structures made of concrete. Good correlation of experimental and simulated results for all tests indicates that this simple approach can be implemented for non-destructive evaluations of structures of civil and industrial interest</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23558v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piyush Pallav, Purba Bhattacharya, Supratik Mukhopadhyay, Nayana Majumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sample-based subsampling strategies to identify microplastics in the presence of a high number of particles using quantum-cascade laser-based infrared imaging</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23784v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Microplastics (MPs) are ubiquitous in all ecosystems, affecting wildlife and, ultimately, human health. The complexity of natural samples plus the unspecificity of their treatments to isolate polymers renders the characterization of thousands of particles impractical for environmental monitoring using conventional spectroscopic techniques. Two primary solutions are to analyze a small fraction of the sample or to measure only a subset of particles present over a holder, known as subsampling. A strategy to subsample reflective Kevley slides and gold-coated filters using quantum-cascade laser-based infrared imaging is proposed here, as this technology is a promising tool for MPs monitoring. In contrast to most previous approaches that struggle to propose general subsampling schemes, we introduce the concept of sample-based subsampling. This can be applied ex-ante always and it highlights the best subsampling areas for a sample after a preliminary assay to count the total number of particles on a holder. The error at this stage acts as a proxy to minimize errors when evaluating the number of particles and MPs, significantly enhancing the feasibility of large-scale MPs monitoring. The predictive ability of the approach was tested for fibres and fragments, for total amounts of particles and MPs. Further, the evaluations were disaggregated by size and polymer type. In most situations the reference values were contained in the confidence intervals of the predicted values (often within the 68 % ones) and relative errors were lower than 25 %. Exceptions occurred when very scarce (one or two) items of a given size or polymer were present on the overall holder. The approach was compared to other systematic ad-hoc strategies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23784v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.talanta.2025.127915</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Talanta 292 (2025) 127915</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Lopez-Rosales, Jose Andrade, Borja Ferreiro, Soledad Muniategui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reviewing the fundamentals and best practices to characterize microplastics using state-of-the-art quantum-cascade laser reflectance-absorbance spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23789v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Microplastic pollution studies depend on reliable identification of the suspicious particles. Out of the various analytical techniques available to characterize them, infrared transflectance using a tuneable mid-IR quantum cascade laser is a high-throughput state-of-the-art imaging option, specifically Agilent QCL-LDIR (Quantum Cascade Laser Direct Infrared imaging). Its conceptual grounds are reviewed, instrumental developments are discussed, along with a review of applications and best practices to overcome obstacles/difficulties in routine measurements, namely: the spectral range, the variation of some peak intensities with the particles size, effects of the size of the particles, processing speed, and avoiding the use of measurement aliquots. Objective procedures to avoid too many false positives when identifying spectra and to distinguish fibers and fragments are given. These practices open a path to QCL-LDIR measurement standardization and potential use for microplastics monitoring, as requested by many governmental bodies in charge of setting environmental protection rules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23789v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.trac.2025.118229</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>TrAC Trends in Analytical Chemistry 188 (2025) 118229</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Lopez-Rosales, Borja Ferreiro, Jose Andrade, Andreas Kerstan, Darren Robey, Soledad Muniategui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NUMEXO2: a versatile digitizer for nuclear physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24082v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: NUMEXO2 is a 16 channels 14bit/200MHz digitizer and processing board initially developed for gamma-ray spectroscopy (for EXOGAM: EXOtic nuclei GAMma ray). Numexo2 has been gradually extended and improved as a general purpose digitizer to fulfill various needs in nuclear physics detection at GANIL. This was possible thanks to reprogrammable components like FPGAs and the optimization of different algorithms. The originality of this work compared to similar systems is that all numerical operations follow the digital data flow from ADCs, without any storage step of samples. Some details are given on digital processing of the signals, delivered by a large variety of detectors: HPGe, silicon strip detector, ionisation chamber, liquid and plastic scintillators read-out with photomultipliers, Multi Wire Proportional Counter and drift chamber.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24082v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Houarner, A. Boujrad, M. Tripon, M. Bezard, M. Blaizot, P. Bourgault, S. Coudert, B. Duclos, F. J. Egea, G de France, A. Gadea, A. Lemasson, L. Martina, C. Maugeais, J. Pancin, B. Raine, F. Saillant, A. Triossi, G. Wittwer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>United States Early Career Researchers in Collider Physics input to the European Strategy for Particle Physics Update</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22834v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This document represents a contribution of the United States early career collider physics community to the 2025--2026 update to the European Strategy for Particle Physics. Preferences with regard to different future collider options and R&amp;D priorities were assessed via a survey. The early career community was defined as anyone who is a graduate student, postdoctoral researcher, untenured faculty member, or research scientist under 40 years of age. In total, 105 participants responded to the survey between February and March 10th, 2025. Questions were formulated primarily to gauge the enthusiasm and preferences for different collider options in line with the recommendations of the United States' P5 report, relevant to the European Strategy Update.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22834v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oz Amram, Grace Cummings</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Concept and Demonstration of a Low-cost Compact Electron Microscope Enabled by a Photothermionic Carbon Nanotube Cathode</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.22910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.22910v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The scanning electron microscope (SEM) delivers high resolution, high depth of focus and an image quality as if microscopic objects are seen by the naked eye. This makes it not only a powerful scientific instrument, but a tool inherently applicable to nearly all fields of study and curiosity involving the small scale. However, SEMs have remained complex, expensive, and beyond the reach of many. To broaden access, we demonstrate an SEM using simple, low-cost, off-the-shelf components, and hobby-level electromechanics; this has been enabled by a unique thermionic electron source based on a carbon nanotube array excited by low optical power. The instrument offers sub-micrometer resolution, a depth of focus of several hundred micrometers, and an image quality comparable to commercial SEMs; it also tolerates poor vacuum and moist specimens, making it broadly applicable. It has a flexible design that lends itself to easy customization for different use scenarios. We provide the conceptual approach and high-level design in this paper; the detailed blueprints of our specific implementation will be provided separately online. We hope that specialists and non-specialists alike will build variations that fit their own needs and interests, helping electron microscopy expand into diverse new sectors of society and industry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.22910v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Casimir Kuzyk, Alexander Dimitrakopoulos, Alireza Nojeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Construction and characterisation of a coded-mask gamma camera for beam range monitoring in proton therapy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23528v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The major advantage of proton therapy over conventional radiotherapy is the dose deposition pattern, enabling precise coverage of the tumour volume while sparing nearby healthy tissues. However, accurate control of the proton beam range online during patient irradiation is still considered a challenge. Thus, there are extensive efforts to develop a detector capable of in vivo beam range monitoring for proton therapy, among them, the coded-mask gamma camera developed by the SiFi-CC group. The assembly of this detector, as well as its first test under clinical conditions, are the subject of this thesis. The detector consists of a tungsten collimator and a stack of thin scintillation fibres, read out at both ends by SiPMs. Such a design allows for efficient detection of prompt gammas (PG) and reconstruction of a PG depth profile, which is strongly correlated with the proton beam range. The readout system was selected in an extensive comparison study of five different systems. After assembly, the detector was tested under clinical conditions: a phantom was irradiated with proton beams of energies from 70.51 MeV to 108.15 MeV, the detector response was processed with low-level reconstruction software, and the MLEM algorithm was applied to reconstruct the PG depth profiles (images). The distal falloff positions of these profiles were determined and compared with the calculated proton ranges. The image reconstruction parameters were optimised in terms of accuracy of proton range shift determination. The results obtained were checked against a Geant4 simulation, showing good consistency. The statistical precision was found to be 1.7 mm for $10^8$ protons. The result is comparable to similar systems investigated by other research groups. However, simulation results suggest that certain hardware amendments to the detector can increase that precision about four times.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23528v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Magdalena Ko{\l}odziej</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DUNE Software and Computing Research and Development</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23743v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The international collaboration designing and constructing the Deep Underground Neutrino Experiment (DUNE) at the Long-Baseline Neutrino Facility (LBNF) has developed a two-phase strategy toward the implementation of this leading-edge, large-scale science project. The ambitious physics program of Phase I and Phase II of DUNE is dependent upon deployment and utilization of significant computing resources, and successful research and development of software (both infrastructure and algorithmic) in order to achieve these scientific goals. This submission discusses the computing resources projections, infrastructure support, and software development needed for DUNE during the coming decades as an input to the European Strategy for Particle Physics Update for 2026. The DUNE collaboration is submitting four main contributions to the 2026 Update of the European Strategy for Particle Physics process. This submission to the 'Computing' stream focuses on DUNE software and computing. Additional inputs related to the DUNE science program, DUNE detector technologies and R&amp;D, and European contributions to Fermilab accelerator upgrades and facilities for the DUNE experiment, are also being submitted to other streams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23743v1</guid>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> DUNE Collaboration, A. Abed Abud, R. Acciarri, M. A. Acero, M. R. Adames, G. Adamov, M. Adamowski, D. Adams, M. Adinolfi, C. Adriano, A. Aduszkiewicz, J. Aguilar, F. Akbar, F. Alemanno, N. S. Alex, K. Allison, M. Alrashed, A. Alton, R. Alvarez, T. Alves, A. Aman, H. Amar, P. Amedo, J. Anderson, D. A. Andrade, C. Andreopoulos, M. Andreotti, M. P. Andrews, F. Andrianala, S. Andringa, F. Anjarazafy, D. Antic, M. Antoniassi, M. Antonova, A. Aranda-Fernandez, L. Arellano, E. Arrieta Diaz, M. A. Arroyave, J. Asaadi, M. Ascencio, A. Ashkenazi, D. Asner, L. Asquith, E. Atkin, D. Auguste, A. Aurisano, V. Aushev, D. Autiero, D. \'Avila G\'omez, M. B. Azam, F. Azfar, A. Back, H. Back, J. J. Back, I. Bagaturia, L. Bagby, D. Baigarashev, S. Balasubramanian, A. Balboni, P. Baldi, W. Baldini, J. Baldonedo, B. Baller, B. Bambah, R. Banerjee, F. Barao, D. Barbu, G. Barenboim, P. \ Barham Alz\'as, G. J. Barker, W. Barkhouse, G. Barr, J. Barranco Monarca, A. Barros, N. Barros, D. Barrow, J. L. Barrow, A. Basharina-Freshville, A. Bashyal, V. Basque, D. Basu, C. Batchelor, L. Bathe-Peters, J. B. R. Battat, F. Battisti, F. Bay, M. C. Q. Bazetto, J. L. L. Bazo Alba, J. F. Beacom, E. Bechetoille, B. Behera, E. Belchior, B. Bell, G. Bell, L. Bellantoni, G. Bellettini, V. Bellini, O. Beltramello, C. Benitez Montiel, D. Benjamin, F. Bento Neves, J. Berger, S. Berkman, J. Bernal, P. Bernardini, A. Bersani, E. Bertolini, S. Bertolucci, M. Betancourt, A. Betancur Rodr\'iguez, Y. Bezawada, A. T. Bezerra, A. Bhat, V. Bhatnagar, J. Bhatt, M. Bhattacharjee, M. Bhattacharya, S. Bhuller, B. Bhuyan, S. Biagi, J. Bian, K. Biery, B. Bilki, M. Bishai, A. Blake, F. D. Blaszczyk, G. C. Blazey, E. Blucher, B. Bogart, J. Bogenschuetz, J. Boissevain, S. Bolognesi, T. Bolton, L. Bomben, M. Bonesini, C. Bonilla-Diaz, A. Booth, F. Boran, R. Borges Merlo, N. Bostan, G. Botogoske, B. Bottino, R. Bouet, J. Boza, J. Bracinik, B. Brahma, D. Brailsford, F. Bramati, A. Branca, A. Brandt, J. Bremer, S. J. Brice, V. Brio, C. Brizzolari, C. Bromberg, J. Brooke, A. Bross, G. Brunetti, M. B. Brunetti, N. Buchanan, H. Budd, J. Buergi, A. Bundock, D. Burgardt, S. Butchart, G. Caceres V., T. Cai, R. Calabrese, R. Calabrese, J. Calcutt, L. Calivers, E. Calvo, A. Caminata, A. F. Camino, W. Campanelli, A. Campani, A. Campos Benitez, N. Canci, J. Cap\'o, I. Caracas, D. Caratelli, D. Carber, J. M. Carceller, G. Carini, B. Carlus, M. F. Carneiro, P. Carniti, I. Caro Terrazas, H. Carranza, N. Carrara, L. Carroll, T. Carroll, A. Carter, E. Casarejos, D. Casazza, J. F. Casta\~no Forero, F. A. Casta\~no, A. Castillo, C. Castromonte, E. Catano-Mur, C. Cattadori, F. Cavalier, F. Cavanna, S. Centro, G. Cerati, C. Cerna, A. Cervelli, A. Cervera Villanueva, J. Chakrani, M. Chalifour, A. Chappell, A. Chatterjee, B. Chauhan, C. Chavez Barajas, H. Chen, M. Chen, W. C. Chen, Y. Chen, Z. Chen, D. Cherdack, S. S. Chhibra, C. Chi, F. Chiapponi, R. Chirco, N. Chitirasreemadam, K. Cho, S. Choate, G. Choi, D. Chokheli, P. S. Chong, B. Chowdhury, D. Christian, M. Chung, E. Church, M. F. Cicala, M. Cicerchia, V. Cicero, R. Ciolini, P. Clarke, G. Cline, A. G. Cocco, J. A. B. Coelho, A. Cohen, J. Collazo, J. Collot, J. M. Conrad, M. Convery, K. Conway, S. Copello, P. Cova, C. Cox, L. Cremonesi, J. I. Crespo-Anad\'on, M. Crisler, E. Cristaldo, J. Crnkovic, G. Crone, R. Cross, A. Cudd, C. Cuesta, Y. Cui, F. Curciarello, D. Cussans, J. Dai, O. Dalager, W. Dallaway, R. D'Amico, H. da Motta, Z. A. Dar, R. Darby, L. Da Silva Peres, Q. David, G. S. Davies, S. Davini, J. Dawson, R. De Aguiar, P. De Almeida, P. Debbins, M. P. Decowski, A. de Gouv\^ea, P. C. De Holanda, P. De Jong, P. Del Amo Sanchez, G. De Lauretis, A. Delbart, D. Delepine, M. Delgado, A. Dell'Acqua, G. Delle Monache, N. Delmonte, P. De Lurgio, R. Demario, G. De Matteis, J. R. T. de Mello Neto, A. P. A. De Mendonca, D. M. DeMuth, S. Dennis, C. Densham, P. Denton, G. W. Deptuch, A. De Roeck, V. De Romeri, J. P. Detje, J. Devine, R. Dharmapalan, M. Dias, A. Diaz, J. S. D\'iaz, F. D\'iaz, F. Di Capua, A. Di Domenico, S. Di Domizio, S. Di Falco, L. Di Giulio, P. Ding, L. Di Noto, E. Diociaiuti, V. Di Silvestre, C. Distefano, R. Diurba, M. Diwan, Z. Djurcic, S. Dolan, M. Dolce, F. Dolek, M. J. Dolinski, D. Domenici, S. Donati, Y. Donon, S. Doran, D. Douglas, T. A. Doyle, F. Drielsma, L. Duarte, D. Duchesneau, K. Duffy, K. Dugas, P. Dunne, B. Dutta, H. Duyang, D. A. Dwyer, A. S. Dyshkant, S. Dytman, M. Eads, A. Earle, S. Edayath, D. Edmunds, J. Eisch, W. Emark, P. Englezos, A. Ereditato, T. Erjavec, C. O. Escobar, J. J. Evans, E. Ewart, A. C. Ezeribe, K. Fahey, A. Falcone, M. Fani', C. Farnese, S. Farrell, Y. Farzan, J. Felix, Y. Feng, M. Ferreira da Silva, G. Ferry, E. Fialova, L. Fields, P. Filip, A. Filkins, F. Filthaut, G. Fiorillo, M. Fiorini, S. Fogarty, W. Foreman, J. Fowler, J. Franc, K. Francis, D. Franco, J. Freeman, J. Fried, A. Friedland, M. Fucci, S. Fuess, I. K. Furic, K. Furman, A. P. Furmanski, R. Gaba, A. Gabrielli, A. M. Gago, F. Galizzi, H. Gallagher, M. Galli, N. Gallice, V. Galymov, E. Gamberini, T. Gamble, R. Gandhi, S. Ganguly, F. Gao, S. Gao, D. Garcia-Gamez, M. \'A. Garc\'ia-Peris, F. Gardim, S. Gardiner, D. Gastler, A. Gauch, P. Gauzzi, S. Gazzana, G. Ge, N. Geffroy, B. Gelli, S. Gent, L. Gerlach, A. Ghosh, T. Giammaria, D. Gibin, I. Gil-Botella, S. Gilligan, A. Gioiosa, S. Giovannella, A. K. Giri, C. Giugliano, V. Giusti, D. Gnani, O. Gogota, S. Gollapinni, K. Gollwitzer, R. A. Gomes, L. V. Gomez Bermeo, L. S. Gomez Fajardo, D. Gonzalez-Diaz, M. C. Goodman, S. Goswami, C. Gotti, J. Goudeau, E. Goudzovski, C. Grace, E. Gramellini, R. Gran, E. Granados, P. Granger, C. Grant, D. R. Gratieri, G. Grauso, P. Green, S. Greenberg, J. Greer, W. C. Griffith, K. Grzelak, L. Gu, W. Gu, V. Guarino, M. Guarise, R. Guenette, M. Guerzoni, D. Guffanti, A. Guglielmi, B. Guo, F. Y. Guo, V. Gupta, G. Gurung, D. Gutierrez, P. Guzowski, M. M. Guzzo, S. Gwon, A. Habig, L. Haegel, R. Hafeji, L. Hagaman, A. Hahn, J. Hakenm\"uller, T. Hamernik, P. Hamilton, J. Hancock, M. Handley, F. Happacher, D. A. Harris, A. L. Hart, J. Hartnell, T. Hartnett, J. Harton, T. Hasegawa, C. M. Hasnip, R. Hatcher, S. Hawkins, J. Hays, M. He, A. Heavey, K. M. Heeger, A. Heindel, J. Heise, P. Hellmuth, L. Henderson, K. Herner, V. Hewes, A. Higuera, C. Hilgenberg, A. Himmel, E. Hinkle, L. R. Hirsch, J. Ho, J. Hoefken Zink, J. Hoff, A. Holin, T. Holvey, C. Hong, E. Hoppe, S. Horiuchi, G. A. Horton-Smith, R. Hosokawa, T. Houdy, B. Howard, R. Howell, I. Hristova, M. S. Hronek, H. Hua, J. Huang, R. G. Huang, X. Huang, Z. Hulcher, G. Iles, N. Ilic, A. M. Iliescu, R. Illingworth, G. Ingratta, A. Ioannisian, B. Irwin, M. Ismerio Oliveira, C. M. Jackson, V. Jain, E. James, W. Jang, B. Jargowsky, D. Jena, I. Jentz, X. Ji, C. Jiang, J. Jiang, A. Jipa, J. H. Jo, F. R. Joaquim, W. Johnson, C. Jollet, R. Jones, N. Jovancevic, M. Judah, C. K. Jung, K. Y. Jung, T. Junk, Y. Jwa, M. Kabirnezhad, A. C. Kaboth, I. Kadenko, O. Kalikulov, D. Kalra, M. Kandemir, D. M. Kaplan, G. Karagiorgi, G. Karaman, A. Karcher, Y. Karyotakis, S. P. Kasetti, L. Kashur, A. Kauther, N. Kazaryan, L. Ke, E. Kearns, P. T. Keener, K. J. Kelly, R. Keloth, E. Kemp, O. Kemularia, Y. Kermaidic, W. Ketchum, S. H. Kettell, N. Khan, A. Khvedelidze, D. Kim, J. Kim, M. J. Kim, S. Kim, B. King, M. King, M. Kirby, A. Kish, J. Klein, J. Kleykamp, A. Klustova, T. Kobilarcik, L. Koch, K. Koehler, L. W. Koerner, D. H. Koh, M. Kordosky, T. Kosc, V. A. Kosteleck\'y, K. Kothekar, I. Kotler, M. Kovalcuk, R. Kralik, M. Kramer, L. Kreczko, F. Krennrich, T. Kroupova, S. Kubota, M. Kubu, V. A. Kudryavtsev, G. Kufatty, S. Kuhlmann, J. Kumar, M. Kumar, P. Kumar, P. Kumar, S. Kumaran, J. Kunzmann, R. Kuravi, V. Kus, T. Kutter, J. Kvasnicka, T. Labree, T. Lackey, I. Lal\u{a}u, A. Lambert, B. J. Land, C. E. Lane, N. Lane, K. Lang, T. Langford, M. Langstaff, F. Lanni, J. Larkin, P. Lasorak, D. Last, A. Laundrie, G. Laurenti, E. Lavaut, P. Laycock, I. Lazanu, R. LaZur, M. Lazzaroni, T. Le, S. Leardini, J. Learned, T. LeCompte, G. Lehmann Miotto, R. Lehnert, M. Leitner, H. Lemoine, D. Leon Silverio, L. M. Lepin, J. -Y Li, S. W. Li, Y. Li, H. Liao, R. Lima, C. S. Lin, D. Lindebaum, S. Linden, R. A. Lineros, A. Lister, B. R. Littlejohn, H. Liu, J. Liu, Y. Liu, S. Lockwitz, I. Lomidze, K. Long, T. V. Lopes, J. Lopez, I. L\'opez de Rego, N. L\'opez-March, J. M. LoSecco, W. C. Louis, A. Lozano Sanchez, X. -G. Lu, K. B. Luk, X. Luo, E. Luppi, A. A. Machado, P. Machado, C. T. Macias, J. R. Macier, M. MacMahon, S. Magill, C. Magueur, K. Mahn, A. Maio, A. Major, K. Majumdar, A. Malige, S. Mameli, M. Man, R. C. Mandujano, J. Maneira, S. Manly, A. Mann, K. Manolopoulos, M. Manrique Plata, S. Manthey Corchado, V. N. Manyam, L. Manzanillas-Velez, M. Marchan, A. Marchionni, W. Marciano, D. Marfatia, C. Mariani, J. Maricic, F. Marinho, A. D. Marino, T. Markiewicz, F. Das Chagas Marques, C. Marquet, M. Marshak, C. M. Marshall, J. Marshall, L. Martina, J. Mart\'in-Albo, N. Martinez, D. A. Martinez Caicedo, M. Martinez-Casales, F. Mart\'inez L\'opez, P. Mart\'inez Mirav\'e, S. Martynenko, V. Mascagna, A. Mastbaum, M. Masud, F. Matichard, G. Matteucci, J. Matthews, C. Mauger, N. Mauri, K. Mavrokoridis, I. Mawby, F. Mayhew, R. Mazza, T. McAskill, N. McConkey, K. S. McFarland, C. McGrew, A. McNab, C. McNulty, J. Mead, L. Meazza, V. C. N. Meddage, M. Mehmood, B. Mehta, P. Mehta, F. Mei, P. Melas, L. Mellet, O. Mena, H. Mendez, D. P. M\'endez, A. Menegolli, G. Meng, A. C. E. A. Mercuri, A. Meregaglia, M. D. Messier, S. Metallo, W. Metcalf, M. Mewes, H. Meyer, T. Miao, J. Micallef, A. Miccoli, G. Michna, R. Milincic, F. Miller, G. Miller, W. Miller, A. Minotti, L. Miralles Verge, C. Mironov, S. Miryala, S. Miscetti, C. S. Mishra, P. Mishra, S. R. Mishra, A. Mislivec, D. Mladenov, I. Mocioiu, A. Mogan, R. Mohanta, T. A. Mohayai, N. Mokhov, J. Molina, L. Molina Bueno, E. Montagna, A. Montanari, C. Montanari, D. Montanari, D. Montanino, L. M. Monta\~no Zetina, M. Mooney, A. F. Moor, M. Moore, Z. Moore, D. Moreno, G. Moreno-Granados, O. Moreno-Palacios, L. Morescalchi, R. Moretti, C. Morris, C. Mossey, E. Motuk, C. A. Moura, G. Mouster, W. Mu, L. Mualem, J. Mueller, M. Muether, F. Muheim, A. Muir, Y. Mukhamejanov, A. Mukhamejanova, M. Mulhearn, D. Munford, L. J. Munteanu, H. Muramatsu, J. Muraz, M. Murphy, T. Murphy, J. Muse, A. Mytilinaki, J. Nachtman, Y. Nagai, S. Nagu, D. Naples, S. Narita, J. Nava, A. Navrer-Agasson, N. Nayak, M. Nebot-Guinot, A. Nehm, J. K. Nelson, O. Neogi, J. Nesbit, M. Nessi, D. Newbold, M. Newcomer, R. Nichol, F. Nicolas-Arnaldos, A. Nielsen, A. Nikolica, J. Nikolov, E. Niner, X. Ning, K. Nishimura, A. Norman, A. Norrick, P. Novella, A. Nowak, J. A. Nowak, M. Oberling, J. P. Ochoa-Ricoux, S. Oh, S. B. Oh, A. Olivier, T. Olson, Y. Onel, Y. Onishchuk, A. Oranday, M. Osbiston, J. A. Osorio V\'elez, L. O'Sullivan, L. Otiniano Ormachea, L. Pagani, G. Palacio, O. Palamara, S. Palestini, J. M. Paley, M. Pallavicini, C. Palomares, S. Pan, M. Panareo, P. Panda, V. Pandey, W. Panduro Vazquez, E. Pantic, V. Paolone, A. Papadopoulou, R. Papaleo, D. Papoulias, S. Paramesvaran, S. Parke, S. Parsa, Z. Parsa, S. Parveen, M. Parvu, D. Pasciuto, S. Pascoli, L. Pasqualini, J. Pasternak, J. L. Paton, C. Patrick, L. Patrizii, R. B. Patterson, T. Patzak, A. Paudel, L. Paulucci, Z. Pavlovic, G. Pawloski, D. Payne, A. Peake, V. Pec, E. Pedreschi, S. J. M. Peeters, W. Pellico, E. Pennacchio, A. Penzo, O. L. G. Peres, L. P\'erez-Molina, C. Pernas, J. Perry, D. Pershey, G. Pessina, G. Petrillo, C. Petta, R. Petti, M. Pfaff, V. Pia, L. Pickering, L. Pierini, F. Pietropaolo, V. L. Pimentel, G. Pinaroli, S. Pincha, J. Pinchault, K. Pitts, K. Pletcher, K. Plows, C. Pollack, T. Pollmann, F. Pompa, X. Pons, N. Poonthottathil, V. Popov, F. Poppi, J. Porter, L. G. Porto Paix\~ao, M. Potekhin, M. Pozzato, R. Pradhan, T. Prakash, M. Prest, F. Psihas, D. Pugnere, D. Pullia, X. Qian, J. Queen, J. L. Raaf, M. Rabelhofer, V. Radeka, J. Rademacker, B. Radics, F. Raffaelli, A. Rafique, E. Raguzin, A. Rahe, S. Rajagopalan, M. Rajaoalisoa, I. Rakhno, L. Rakotondravohitra, M. A. Ralaikoto, L. Ralte, M. A. Ramirez Delgado, B. Ramson, S. S. Randriamanampisoa, A. Rappoldi, G. Raselli, T. Rath, P. Ratoff, R. Ray, H. Razafinime, R. F. Razakamiandra, E. M. Rea, J. S. Real, B. Rebel, R. Rechenmacher, J. Reichenbacher, S. D. Reitzner, E. Renner, S. Repetto, S. Rescia, F. Resnati, C. Reynolds, M. Ribas, S. Riboldi, C. Riccio, G. Riccobene, J. S. Ricol, M. Rigan, A. Rikalo, E. V. Rinc\'on, A. Ritchie-Yates, S. Ritter, D. Rivera, A. Robert, A. Roberts, E. Robles, J. L. Rocabado Rocha, M. Roda, D. Rodas Rodr\'iguez, M. J. O. Rodrigues, J. Rodriguez Rondon, S. Rosauro-Alcaraz, P. Rosier, D. Ross, M. Rossella, M. Rossi, M. Ross-Lonergan, N. Roy, P. Roy, P. Roy, C. Rubbia, D. Rudik, A. Ruggeri, G. Ruiz Ferreira, K. Rushiya, B. Russell, S. Sacerdoti, N. Saduyev, S. K. Sahoo, N. Sahu, S. Sakhiyev, P. Sala, G. Salmoria, S. Samanta, N. Samios, M. C. Sanchez, A. S\'anchez Bravo, A. S\'anchez-Castillo, P. Sanchez-Lucas, D. A. Sanders, S. Sanfilippo, D. Santoro, N. Saoulidou, P. Sapienza, I. Sarcevic, I. Sarra, G. Savage, V. Savinov, G. Scanavini, A. Scaramelli, A. Scarff, T. Schefke, H. Schellman, S. Schifano, P. Schlabach, D. Schmitz, A. W. Schneider, K. Scholberg, A. Schukraft, B. Schuld, S. Schwartz, A. Segade, E. Segreto, C. R. Senise, J. Sensenig, S. H. Seo, D. Seppela, M. H. Shaevitz, P. Shanahan, P. Sharma, R. Kumar, S. Sharma Poudel, K. Shaw, T. Shaw, K. Shchablo, J. Shen, C. Shepherd-Themistocleous, J. Shi, W. Shi, S. Shin, S. Shivakoti, A. Shmakov, I. Shoemaker, D. Shooltz, R. Shrock, M. Siden, J. Silber, L. Simard, J. Sinclair, G. Sinev, Jaydip Singh, J. Singh, L. Singh, P. Singh, V. Singh, S. Singh Chauhan, R. Sipos, C. Sironneau, G. Sirri, K. Siyeon, K. Skarpaas, J. Smedley, J. Smith, P. Smith, J. Smolik, M. Smy, M. Snape, E. L. Snider, P. Snopok, M. Soares Nunes, H. Sobel, M. Soderberg, C. J. Solano Salinas, S. S\"oldner-Rembold, N. Solomey, V. Solovov, W. E. Sondheim, M. Sorbara, M. Sorel, J. Soto-Oton, A. Sousa, K. Soustruznik, D. Souza Correia, F. Spinella, J. Spitz, N. J. C. Spooner, D. Stalder, M. Stancari, L. Stanco, J. Steenis, R. Stein, H. M. Steiner, A. F. Steklain Lisb\^oa, J. Stewart, B. Stillwell, J. Stock, T. Stokes, M. Strait, T. Strauss, L. Strigari, A. Stuart, J. G. Suarez, J. Subash, A. Surdo, L. Suter, K. Sutton, Y. Suvorov, R. Svoboda, S. K. Swain, C. Sweeney, B. Szczerbinska, A. M. Szelc, A. Sztuc, A. Taffara, N. Talukdar, J. Tamara, H. A. Tanaka, S. Tang, N. Taniuchi, A. M. Tapia Casanova, A. Tapper, S. Tariq, E. Tarpara, E. Tatar, R. Tayloe, D. Tedeschi, A. M. Teklu, K. Tellez Giron Flores, J. Tena Vidal, P. Tennessen, M. Tenti, K. Terao, F. Terranova, G. Testera, T. Thakore, A. Thea, S. Thomas, A. Thompson, C. Thorn, C. Thorpe, S. C. Timm, E. Tiras, V. Tishchenko, S. Tiwari, N. Todorovi\'c, L. Tomassetti, A. Tonazzo, D. Torbunov, D. Torres Mu\~noz, M. Torti, M. Tortola, Y. Torun, N. Tosi, D. Totani, M. Toups, C. Touramanis, V. Trabattoni, D. Tran, R. Travaglini, J. Trevor, E. Triller, S. Trilov, D. Trotta, J. Truchon, D. Truncali, W. H. Trzaska, Y. Tsai, Y. -T. Tsai, Z. Tsamalaidze, K. V. Tsang, N. Tsverava, S. Z. Tu, S. Tufanli, C. Tunnell, M. Tuzi, J. Tyler, E. Tyley, M. Tzanov, M. A. Uchida, J. Ure\~na Gonz\'alez, J. Urheim, T. Usher, H. Utaegbulam, S. Uzunyan, M. R. Vagins, P. Vahle, G. A. Valdiviesso, V. Vale, E. Valencia, R. Valentim, Z. Vallari, E. Vallazza, J. W. F. Valle, R. Van Berg, D. V. Forero, A. Vannozzi, M. Van Nuland-Troost, F. Varanini, D. Vargas Oliva, N. Vaughan, K. Vaziri, A. V\'azquez-Ramos, J. Vega, J. Vences, S. Ventura, A. Verdugo, S. Vergani, M. Verzocchi, K. Vetter, M. Vicenzi, H. Vieira de Souza, C. Vignoli, C. Vilela, E. Villa, S. Viola, B. Viren, G. V. Stenico, R. Vizarreta, A. P. Vizcaya Hernandez, S. Vlachos, G. Vorobyev, Q. Vuong, A. V. Waldron, M. Wallach, J. Walsh, T. Walton, L. Wan, B. Wang, H. Wang, J. Wang, L. Wang, M. H. L. S. Wang, X. Wang, Y. Wang, K. Warburton, D. Warner, L. Warsame, M. O. Wascko, D. Waters, A. Watson, K. Wawrowska, A. Weber, C. M. Weber, M. Weber, H. Wei, A. Weinstein, S. Westerdale, M. Wetstein, K. Whalen, A. White, L. H. Whitehead, D. Whittington, F. Wieler, J. Wilhlemi, M. J. Wilking, A. Wilkinson, C. Wilkinson, F. Wilson, R. J. Wilson, P. Winter, J. Wolcott, J. Wolfs, T. Wongjirad, A. Wood, K. Wood, E. Worcester, M. Worcester, K. Wresilo, M. Wright, M. Wrobel, S. Wu, W. Wu, W. Wu, M. Wurm, J. Wyenberg, B. M. Wynne, Y. Xiao, I. Xiotidis, B. Yaeggy, N. Yahlali, E. Yandel, G. Yang, J. Yang, T. Yang, A. Yankelevich, L. Yates, K. Yonehara, T. Young, B. Yu, H. Yu, J. Yu, Y. Yu, W. Yuan, R. Zaki, J. Zalesak, L. Zambelli, B. Zamorano, A. Zani, O. Zapata, L. Zazueta, G. P. Zeller, J. Zennamo, J. Zettlemoyer, K. Zeug, C. Zhang, S. Zhang, M. Zhao, E. Zhivun, E. D. Zimmerman, S. Zucchelli, V. Zutshi, R. Zwaska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>European Contributions to Fermilab Accelerator Upgrades and Facilities for the DUNE Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23744v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Proton Improvement Plan (PIP-II) to the FNAL accelerator chain and the Long-Baseline Neutrino Facility (LBNF) will provide the world's most intense neutrino beam to the Deep Underground Neutrino Experiment (DUNE) enabling a wide-ranging physics program. This document outlines the significant contributions made by European national laboratories and institutes towards realizing the first phase of the project with a 1.2 MW neutrino beam. Construction of this first phase is well underway. For DUNE Phase II, this will be closely followed by an upgrade of the beam power to &gt; 2 MW, for which the European groups again have a key role and which will require the continued support of the European community for machine aspects of neutrino physics. Beyond the neutrino beam aspects, LBNF is also responsible for providing unique infrastructure to install and operate the DUNE neutrino detectors at FNAL and at the Sanford Underground Research Facility (SURF). The cryostats for the first two Liquid Argon Time Projection Chamber detector modules at SURF, a contribution of CERN to LBNF, are central to the success of the ongoing execution of DUNE Phase I. Likewise, successful and timely procurement of cryostats for two additional detector modules at SURF will be critical to the success of DUNE Phase II and the overall physics program. The DUNE Collaboration is submitting four main contributions to the 2026 Update of the European Strategy for Particle Physics process. This paper is being submitted to the 'Accelerator technologies' and 'Projects and Large Experiments' streams. Additional inputs related to the DUNE science program, DUNE detector technologies and R&amp;D, and DUNE software and computing, are also being submitted to other streams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23744v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> DUNE Collaboration, A. Abed Abud, R. Acciarri, M. A. Acero, M. R. Adames, G. Adamov, M. Adamowski, D. Adams, M. Adinolfi, C. Adriano, A. Aduszkiewicz, J. Aguilar, F. Akbar, F. Alemanno, N. S. Alex, K. Allison, M. Alrashed, A. Alton, R. Alvarez, T. Alves, A. Aman, H. Amar, P. Amedo, J. Anderson, D. A. Andrade, C. Andreopoulos, M. Andreotti, M. P. Andrews, F. Andrianala, S. Andringa, F. Anjarazafy, D. Antic, M. Antoniassi, M. Antonova, A. Aranda-Fernandez, L. Arellano, E. Arrieta Diaz, M. A. Arroyave, J. Asaadi, M. Ascencio, A. Ashkenazi, D. Asner, L. Asquith, E. Atkin, D. Auguste, A. Aurisano, V. Aushev, D. Autiero, D. \'Avila G\'omez, M. B. Azam, F. Azfar, A. Back, H. Back, J. J. Back, I. Bagaturia, L. Bagby, D. Baigarashev, S. Balasubramanian, A. Balboni, P. Baldi, W. Baldini, J. Baldonedo, B. Baller, B. Bambah, R. Banerjee, F. Barao, D. Barbu, G. Barenboim, P. Barham Alz\'as, G. J. Barker, W. Barkhouse, G. Barr, J. Barranco Monarca, A. Barros, N. Barros, D. Barrow, J. L. Barrow, A. Basharina-Freshville, A. Bashyal, V. Basque, D. Basu, C. Batchelor, L. Bathe-Peters, J. B. R. Battat, F. Battisti, F. Bay, M. C. Q. Bazetto, J. L. L. Bazo Alba, J. F. Beacom, E. Bechetoille, B. Behera, E. Belchior, B. Bell, G. Bell, L. Bellantoni, G. Bellettini, V. Bellini, O. Beltramello, C. Benitez Montiel, D. Benjamin, F. Bento Neves, J. Berger, S. Berkman, J. Bernal, P. Bernardini, A. Bersani, E. Bertolini, S. Bertolucci, M. Betancourt, A. Betancur Rodr\'iguez, Y. Bezawada, A. T. Bezerra, A. Bhat, V. Bhatnagar, J. Bhatt, M. Bhattacharjee, M. Bhattacharya, S. Bhuller, B. Bhuyan, S. Biagi, J. Bian, K. Biery, B. Bilki, M. Bishai, A. Blake, F. D. Blaszczyk, G. C. Blazey, E. Blucher, B. Bogart, J. Bogenschuetz, J. Boissevain, S. Bolognesi, T. Bolton, L. Bomben, M. Bonesini, C. Bonilla-Diaz, A. Booth, F. Boran, R. Borges Merlo, N. Bostan, G. Botogoske, B. Bottino, R. Bouet, J. Boza, J. Bracinik, B. Brahma, D. Brailsford, F. Bramati, A. Branca, A. Brandt, J. Bremer, S. J. Brice, V. Brio, C. Brizzolari, C. Bromberg, J. Brooke, A. Bross, G. Brunetti, M. B. Brunetti, N. Buchanan, H. Budd, J. Buergi, A. Bundock, D. Burgardt, S. Butchart, G. Caceres V., T. Cai, R. Calabrese, R. Calabrese, J. Calcutt, L. Calivers, E. Calvo, A. Caminata, A. F. Camino, W. Campanelli, A. Campani, A. Campos Benitez, N. Canci, J. Cap\'o, I. Caracas, D. Caratelli, D. Carber, J. M. Carceller, G. Carini, B. Carlus, M. F. Carneiro, P. Carniti, I. Caro Terrazas, H. Carranza, N. Carrara, L. Carroll, T. Carroll, A. Carter, E. Casarejos, D. Casazza, J. F. Casta\~no Forero, F. A. Casta\~no, A. Castillo, C. Castromonte, E. Catano-Mur, C. Cattadori, F. Cavalier, F. Cavanna, S. Centro, G. Cerati, C. Cerna, A. Cervelli, A. Cervera Villanueva, J. Chakrani, M. Chalifour, A. Chappell, A. Chatterjee, B. Chauhan, C. Chavez Barajas, H. Chen, M. Chen, W. C. Chen, Y. Chen, Z. Chen, D. Cherdack, S. S. Chhibra, C. Chi, F. Chiapponi, R. Chirco, N. Chitirasreemadam, K. Cho, S. Choate, G. Choi, D. Chokheli, P. S. Chong, B. Chowdhury, D. Christian, M. Chung, E. Church, M. F. Cicala, M. Cicerchia, V. Cicero, R. Ciolini, P. Clarke, G. Cline, A. G. Cocco, J. A. B. Coelho, A. Cohen, J. Collazo, J. Collot, J. M. Conrad, M. Convery, K. Conway, S. Copello, P. Cova, C. Cox, L. Cremonesi, J. I. Crespo-Anad\'on, M. Crisler, E. Cristaldo, J. Crnkovic, G. Crone, R. Cross, A. Cudd, C. Cuesta, Y. Cui, F. Curciarello, D. Cussans, J. Dai, O. Dalager, W. Dallaway, R. D'Amico, H. da Motta, Z. A. Dar, R. Darby, L. Da Silva Peres, Q. David, G. S. Davies, S. Davini, J. Dawson, R. De Aguiar, P. De Almeida, P. Debbins, M. P. Decowski, A. de Gouv\^ea, P. C. De Holanda, P. De Jong, P. Del Amo Sanchez, G. De Lauretis, A. Delbart, D. Delepine, M. Delgado, A. Dell'Acqua, G. Delle Monache, N. Delmonte, P. De Lurgio, R. Demario, G. De Matteis, J. R. T. de Mello Neto, A. P. A. De Mendonca, D. M. DeMuth, S. Dennis, C. Densham, P. Denton, G. W. Deptuch, A. De Roeck, V. De Romeri, J. P. Detje, J. Devine, R. Dharmapalan, M. Dias, A. Diaz, J. S. D\'iaz, F. D\'iaz, F. Di Capua, A. Di Domenico, S. Di Domizio, S. Di Falco, L. Di Giulio, P. Ding, L. Di Noto, E. Diociaiuti, V. Di Silvestre, C. Distefano, R. Diurba, M. Diwan, Z. Djurcic, S. Dolan, M. Dolce, F. Dolek, M. J. Dolinski, D. Domenici, S. Donati, Y. Donon, S. Doran, D. Douglas, T. A. Doyle, F. Drielsma, L. Duarte, D. Duchesneau, K. Duffy, K. Dugas, P. Dunne, B. Dutta, H. Duyang, D. A. Dwyer, A. S. Dyshkant, S. Dytman, M. Eads, A. Earle, S. Edayath, D. Edmunds, J. Eisch, W. Emark, P. Englezos, A. Ereditato, T. Erjavec, C. O. Escobar, J. J. Evans, E. Ewart, A. C. Ezeribe, K. Fahey, A. Falcone, M. Fani', C. Farnese, S. Farrell, Y. Farzan, J. Felix, Y. Feng, M. Ferreira da Silva, G. Ferry, E. Fialova, L. Fields, P. Filip, A. Filkins, F. Filthaut, G. Fiorillo, M. Fiorini, S. Fogarty, W. Foreman, J. Fowler, J. Franc, K. Francis, D. Franco, J. Freeman, J. Fried, A. Friedland, M. Fucci, S. Fuess, I. K. Furic, K. Furman, A. P. Furmanski, R. Gaba, A. Gabrielli, A. M. Gago, F. Galizzi, H. Gallagher, M. Galli, N. Gallice, V. Galymov, E. Gamberini, T. Gamble, R. Gandhi, S. Ganguly, F. Gao, S. Gao, D. Garcia-Gamez, M. \'A. Garc\'ia-Peris, F. Gardim, S. Gardiner, D. Gastler, A. Gauch, P. Gauzzi, S. Gazzana, G. Ge, N. Geffroy, B. Gelli, S. Gent, L. Gerlach, A. Ghosh, T. Giammaria, D. Gibin, I. Gil-Botella, S. Gilligan, A. Gioiosa, S. Giovannella, A. K. Giri, C. Giugliano, V. Giusti, D. Gnani, O. Gogota, S. Gollapinni, K. Gollwitzer, R. A. Gomes, L. V. Gomez Bermeo, L. S. Gomez Fajardo, D. Gonzalez-Diaz, M. C. Goodman, S. Goswami, C. Gotti, J. Goudeau, E. Goudzovski, C. Grace, E. Gramellini, R. Gran, E. Granados, P. Granger, C. Grant, D. R. Gratieri, G. Grauso, P. Green, S. Greenberg, J. Greer, W. C. Griffith, K. Grzelak, L. Gu, W. Gu, V. Guarino, M. Guarise, R. Guenette, M. Guerzoni, D. Guffanti, A. Guglielmi, B. Guo, F. Y. Guo, V. Gupta, G. Gurung, D. Gutierrez, P. Guzowski, M. M. Guzzo, S. Gwon, A. Habig, L. Haegel, R. Hafeji, L. Hagaman, A. Hahn, J. Hakenm\"uller, T. Hamernik, P. Hamilton, J. Hancock, M. Handley, F. Happacher, D. A. Harris, A. L. Hart, J. Hartnell, T. Hartnett, J. Harton, T. Hasegawa, C. M. Hasnip, R. Hatcher, S. Hawkins, J. Hays, M. He, A. Heavey, K. M. Heeger, A. Heindel, J. Heise, P. Hellmuth, L. Henderson, K. Herner, V. Hewes, A. Higuera, C. Hilgenberg, A. Himmel, E. Hinkle, L. R. Hirsch, J. Ho, J. Hoefken Zink, J. Hoff, A. Holin, T. Holvey, C. Hong, E. Hoppe, S. Horiuchi, G. A. Horton-Smith, R. Hosokawa, T. Houdy, B. Howard, R. Howell, I. Hristova, M. S. Hronek, H. Hua, J. Huang, R. G. Huang, X. Huang, Z. Hulcher, G. Iles, N. Ilic, A. M. Iliescu, R. Illingworth, G. Ingratta, A. Ioannisian, B. Irwin, M. Ismerio Oliveira, C. M. Jackson, V. Jain, E. James, W. Jang, B. Jargowsky, D. Jena, I. Jentz, X. Ji, C. Jiang, J. Jiang, A. Jipa, J. H. Jo, F. R. Joaquim, W. Johnson, C. Jollet, R. Jones, N. Jovancevic, M. Judah, C. K. Jung, K. Y. Jung, T. Junk, Y. Jwa, M. Kabirnezhad, A. C. Kaboth, I. Kadenko, O. Kalikulov, D. Kalra, M. Kandemir, D. M. Kaplan, G. Karagiorgi, G. Karaman, A. Karcher, Y. Karyotakis, S. P. Kasetti, L. Kashur, A. Kauther, N. Kazaryan, L. Ke, E. Kearns, P. T. Keener, K. J. Kelly, R. Keloth, E. Kemp, O. Kemularia, Y. Kermaidic, W. Ketchum, S. H. Kettell, N. Khan, A. Khvedelidze, D. Kim, J. Kim, M. J. Kim, S. Kim, B. King, M. King, M. Kirby, A. Kish, J. Klein, J. Kleykamp, A. Klustova, T. Kobilarcik, L. Koch, K. Koehler, L. W. Koerner, D. H. Koh, M. Kordosky, T. Kosc, V. A. Kosteleck\'y, K. Kothekar, I. Kotler, M. Kovalcuk, R. Kralik, M. Kramer, L. Kreczko, F. Krennrich, T. Kroupova, S. Kubota, M. Kubu, V. A. Kudryavtsev, G. Kufatty, S. Kuhlmann, J. Kumar, M. Kumar, P. Kumar, P. Kumar, S. Kumaran, J. Kunzmann, R. Kuravi, V. Kus, T. Kutter, J. Kvasnicka, T. Labree, T. Lackey, I. Lal\u{a}u, A. Lambert, B. J. Land, C. E. Lane, N. Lane, K. Lang, T. Langford, M. Langstaff, F. Lanni, J. Larkin, P. Lasorak, D. Last, A. Laundrie, G. Laurenti, E. Lavaut, P. Laycock, I. Lazanu, R. LaZur, M. Lazzaroni, T. Le, S. Leardini, J. Learned, T. LeCompte, G. Lehmann Miotto, R. Lehnert, M. Leitner, H. Lemoine, D. Leon Silverio, L. M. Lepin, J. -Y. Li, S. W. Li, Y. Li, H. Liao, R. Lima, C. S. Lin, D. Lindebaum, S. Linden, R. A. Lineros, A. Lister, B. R. Littlejohn, H. Liu, J. Liu, Y. Liu, S. Lockwitz, I. Lomidze, K. Long, T. V. Lopes, J. Lopez, I. L\'opez de Rego, N. L\'opez-March, J. M. LoSecco, W. C. Louis, A. Lozano Sanchez, X. -G. Lu, K. B. Luk, X. Luo, E. Luppi, A. A. Machado, P. Machado, C. T. Macias, J. R. Macier, M. MacMahon, S. Magill, C. Magueur, K. Mahn, A. Maio, A. Major, K. Majumdar, A. Malige, S. Mameli, M. Man, R. C. Mandujano, J. Maneira, S. Manly, A. Mann, K. Manolopoulos, M. Manrique Plata, S. Manthey Corchado, V. N. Manyam, L. Manzanillas-Velez, M. Marchan, A. Marchionni, W. Marciano, D. Marfatia, C. Mariani, J. Maricic, F. Marinho, A. D. Marino, T. Markiewicz, F. Das Chagas Marques, C. Marquet, M. Marshak, C. M. Marshall, J. Marshall, L. Martina, J. Mart\'in-Albo, N. Martinez, D. A. Martinez Caicedo, M. Martinez-Casales, F. Mart\'inez L\'opez, P. Mart\'inez Mirav\'e, S. Martynenko, V. Mascagna, A. Mastbaum, M. Masud, F. Matichard, G. Matteucci, J. Matthews, C. Mauger, N. Mauri, K. Mavrokoridis, I. Mawby, F. Mayhew, R. Mazza, T. McAskill, N. McConkey, K. S. McFarland, C. McGrew, A. McNab, C. McNulty, J. Mead, L. Meazza, V. C. N. Meddage, M. Mehmood, B. Mehta, P. Mehta, F. Mei, P. Melas, L. Mellet, O. Mena, H. Mendez, D. P. M\'endez, A. Menegolli, G. Meng, A. C. E. A. Mercuri, A. Meregaglia, M. D. Messier, S. Metallo, W. Metcalf, M. Mewes, H. Meyer, T. Miao, J. Micallef, A. Miccoli, G. Michna, R. Milincic, F. Miller, G. Miller, W. Miller, A. Minotti, L. Miralles Verge, C. Mironov, S. Miryala, S. Miscetti, C. S. Mishra, P. Mishra, S. R. Mishra, A. Mislivec, D. Mladenov, I. Mocioiu, A. Mogan, R. Mohanta, T. A. Mohayai, N. Mokhov, J. Molina, L. Molina Bueno, E. Montagna, A. Montanari, C. Montanari, D. Montanari, D. Montanino, L. M. Monta\~no Zetina, M. Mooney, A. F. Moor, M. Moore, Z. Moore, D. Moreno, G. Moreno-Granados, O. Moreno-Palacios, L. Morescalchi, R. Moretti, C. Morris, C. Mossey, E. Motuk, C. A. Moura, G. Mouster, W. Mu, L. Mualem, J. Mueller, M. Muether, F. Muheim, A. Muir, Y. Mukhamejanov, A. Mukhamejanova, M. Mulhearn, D. Munford, L. J. Munteanu, H. Muramatsu, J. Muraz, M. Murphy, T. Murphy, J. Muse, A. Mytilinaki, J. Nachtman, Y. Nagai, S. Nagu, D. Naples, S. Narita, J. Nava, A. Navrer-Agasson, N. Nayak, M. Nebot-Guinot, A. Nehm, J. K. Nelson, O. Neogi, J. Nesbit, M. Nessi, D. Newbold, M. Newcomer, R. Nichol, F. Nicolas-Arnaldos, A. Nielsen, A. Nikolica, J. Nikolov, E. Niner, X. Ning, K. Nishimura, A. Norman, A. Norrick, P. Novella, A. Nowak, J. A. Nowak, M. Oberling, J. P. Ochoa-Ricoux, S. Oh, S. B. Oh, A. Olivier, T. Olson, Y. Onel, Y. Onishchuk, A. Oranday, M. Osbiston, J. A. Osorio V\'elez, L. O'Sullivan, L. Otiniano Ormachea, L. Pagani, G. Palacio, O. Palamara, S. Palestini, J. M. Paley, M. Pallavicini, C. Palomares, S. Pan, M. Panareo, P. Panda, V. Pandey, W. Panduro Vazquez, E. Pantic, V. Paolone, A. Papadopoulou, R. Papaleo, D. Papoulias, S. Paramesvaran, S. Parke, S. Parsa, Z. Parsa, S. Parveen, M. Parvu, D. Pasciuto, S. Pascoli, L. Pasqualini, J. Pasternak, J. L. Paton, C. Patrick, L. Patrizii, R. B. Patterson, T. Patzak, A. Paudel, L. Paulucci, Z. Pavlovic, G. Pawloski, D. Payne, A. Peake, V. Pec, E. Pedreschi, S. J. M. Peeters, W. Pellico, E. Pennacchio, A. Penzo, O. L. G. Peres, L. P\'erez-Molina, C. Pernas, J. Perry, D. Pershey, G. Pessina, G. Petrillo, C. Petta, R. Petti, M. Pfaff, V. Pia, L. Pickering, L. Pierini, F. Pietropaolo, V. L. Pimentel, G. Pinaroli, S. Pincha, J. Pinchault, K. Pitts, K. Pletcher, K. Plows, C. Pollack, T. Pollmann, F. Pompa, X. Pons, N. Poonthottathil, V. Popov, F. Poppi, J. Porter, L. G. Porto Paix\~ao, M. Potekhin, M. Pozzato, R. Pradhan, T. Prakash, M. Prest, F. Psihas, D. Pugnere, D. Pullia, X. Qian, J. Queen, J. L. Raaf, M. Rabelhofer, V. Radeka, J. Rademacker, B. Radics, F. Raffaelli, A. Rafique, E. Raguzin, A. Rahe, S. Rajagopalan, M. Rajaoalisoa, I. Rakhno, L. Rakotondravohitra, M. A. Ralaikoto, L. Ralte, M. A. Ramirez Delgado, B. Ramson, S. S. Randriamanampisoa, A. Rappoldi, G. Raselli, T. Rath, P. Ratoff, R. Ray, H. Razafinime, R. F. Razakamiandra, E. M. Rea, J. S. Real, B. Rebel, R. Rechenmacher, J. Reichenbacher, S. D. Reitzner, E. Renner, S. Repetto, S. Rescia, F. Resnati, C. Reynolds, M. Ribas, S. Riboldi, C. Riccio, G. Riccobene, J. S. Ricol, M. Rigan, A. Rikalo, E. V. Rinc\'on, A. Ritchie-Yates, S. Ritter, D. Rivera, A. Robert, A. Roberts, E. Robles, J. L. Rocabado Rocha, M. Roda, D. Rodas Rodr\'iguez, M. J. O. Rodrigues, J. Rodriguez Rondon, S. Rosauro-Alcaraz, P. Rosier, D. Ross, M. Rossella, M. Rossi, M. Ross-Lonergan, N. Roy, P. Roy, P. Roy, C. Rubbia, D. Rudik, A. Ruggeri, G. Ruiz Ferreira, K. Rushiya, B. Russell, S. Sacerdoti, N. Saduyev, S. K. Sahoo, N. Sahu, S. Sakhiyev, P. Sala, G. Salmoria, S. Samanta, N. Samios, M. C. Sanchez, A. S\'anchez Bravo, A. S\'anchez-Castillo, P. Sanchez-Lucas, D. A. Sanders, S. Sanfilippo, D. Santoro, N. Saoulidou, P. Sapienza, I. Sarcevic, I. Sarra, G. Savage, V. Savinov, G. Scanavini, A. Scaramelli, A. Scarff, T. Schefke, H. Schellman, S. Schifano, P. Schlabach, D. Schmitz, A. W. Schneider, K. Scholberg, A. Schukraft, B. Schuld, S. Schwartz, A. Segade, E. Segreto, C. R. Senise, J. Sensenig, S. H. Seo, D. Seppela, M. H. Shaevitz, P. Shanahan, P. Sharma, R. Kumar, S. Sharma Poudel, K. Shaw, T. Shaw, K. Shchablo, J. Shen, C. Shepherd-Themistocleous, J. Shi, W. Shi, S. Shin, S. Shivakoti, A. Shmakov, I. Shoemaker, D. Shooltz, R. Shrock, M. Siden, J. Silber, L. Simard, J. Sinclair, G. Sinev, Jaydip Singh, J. Singh, L. Singh, P. Singh, V. Singh, S. Singh Chauhan, R. Sipos, C. Sironneau, G. Sirri, K. Siyeon, K. Skarpaas, J. Smedley, J. Smith, P. Smith, J. Smolik, M. Smy, M. Snape, E. L. Snider, P. Snopok, M. Soares Nunes, H. Sobel, M. Soderberg, C. J. Solano Salinas, S. S\"oldner-Rembold, N. Solomey, V. Solovov, W. E. Sondheim, M. Sorbara, M. Sorel, J. Soto-Oton, A. Sousa, K. Soustruznik, D. Souza Correia, F. Spinella, J. Spitz, N. J. C. Spooner, D. Stalder, M. Stancari, L. Stanco, J. Steenis, R. Stein, H. M. Steiner, A. F. Steklain Lisb\^oa, J. Stewart, B. Stillwell, J. Stock, T. Stokes, M. Strait, T. Strauss, L. Strigari, A. Stuart, J. G. Suarez, J. Subash, A. Surdo, L. Suter, K. Sutton, Y. Suvorov, R. Svoboda, S. K. Swain, C. Sweeney, B. Szczerbinska, A. M. Szelc, A. Sztuc, A. Taffara, N. Talukdar, J. Tamara, H. A. Tanaka, S. Tang, N. Taniuchi, A. M. Tapia Casanova, A. Tapper, S. Tariq, E. Tarpara, E. Tatar, R. Tayloe, D. Tedeschi, A. M. Teklu, K. Tellez Giron Flores, J. Tena Vidal, P. Tennessen, M. Tenti, K. Terao, F. Terranova, G. Testera, T. Thakore, A. Thea, S. Thomas, A. Thompson, C. Thorn, C. Thorpe, S. C. Timm, E. Tiras, V. Tishchenko, S. Tiwari, N. Todorovi\'c, L. Tomassetti, A. Tonazzo, D. Torbunov, D. Torres Mu\~noz, M. Torti, M. Tortola, Y. Torun, N. Tosi, D. Totani, M. Toups, C. Touramanis, V. Trabattoni, D. Tran, R. Travaglini, J. Trevor, E. Triller, S. Trilov, D. Trotta, J. Truchon, D. Truncali, W. H. Trzaska, Y. Tsai, Y. -T. Tsai, Z. Tsamalaidze, K. V. Tsang, N. Tsverava, S. Z. Tu, S. Tufanli, C. Tunnell, M. Tuzi, J. Tyler, E. Tyley, M. Tzanov, M. A. Uchida, J. Ure\~na Gonz\'alez, J. Urheim, T. Usher, H. Utaegbulam, S. Uzunyan, M. R. Vagins, P. Vahle, G. A. Valdiviesso, V. Vale, E. Valencia, R. Valentim, Z. Vallari, E. Vallazza, J. W. F. Valle, R. Van Berg, D. V. Forero, A. Vannozzi, M. Van Nuland-Troost, F. Varanini, D. Vargas Oliva, N. Vaughan, K. Vaziri, A. V\'azquez-Ramos, J. Vega, J. Vences, S. Ventura, A. Verdugo, S. Vergani, M. Verzocchi, K. Vetter, M. Vicenzi, H. Vieira de Souza, C. Vignoli, C. Vilela, E. Villa, S. Viola, B. Viren, G. V. Stenico, R. Vizarreta, A. P. Vizcaya Hernandez, S. Vlachos, G. Vorobyev, Q. Vuong, A. V. Waldron, M. Wallach, J. Walsh, T. Walton, L. Wan, B. Wang, H. Wang, J. Wang, L. Wang, M. H. L. S. Wang, X. Wang, Y. Wang, K. Warburton, D. Warner, L. Warsame, M. O. Wascko, D. Waters, A. Watson, K. Wawrowska, A. Weber, C. M. Weber, M. Weber, H. Wei, A. Weinstein, S. Westerdale, M. Wetstein, K. Whalen, A. White, L. H. Whitehead, D. Whittington, F. Wieler, J. Wilhlemi, M. J. Wilking, A. Wilkinson, C. Wilkinson, F. Wilson, R. J. Wilson, P. Winter, J. Wolcott, J. Wolfs, T. Wongjirad, A. Wood, K. Wood, E. Worcester, M. Worcester, K. Wresilo, M. Wright, M. Wrobel, S. Wu, W. Wu, W. Wu, M. Wurm, J. Wyenberg, B. M. Wynne, Y. Xiao, I. Xiotidis, B. Yaeggy, N. Yahlali, E. Yandel, G. Yang, J. Yang, T. Yang, A. Yankelevich, L. Yates, K. Yonehara, T. Young, B. Yu, H. Yu, J. Yu, Y. Yu, W. Yuan, R. Zaki, J. Zalesak, L. Zambelli, B. Zamorano, A. Zani, O. Zapata, L. Zazueta, G. P. Zeller, J. Zennamo, J. Zettlemoyer, K. Zeug, C. Zhang, S. Zhang, M. Zhao, E. Zhivun, E. D. Zimmerman, S. Zucchelli, V. Zutshi, R. Zwaska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Creation of a black hole bomb instability in an electromagnetic system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24034</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24034v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The amplification and generation of electromagnetic radiation by a rotating metallic or lossy cylinder, first theorized by Zeldovich in the 1970s, is tightly connected to the concepts of quantum friction, energy extraction from rotating black holes and runaway mechanisms such as black hole bombs. Despite recent advances including acoustic analogues of the Zeldovich effect and the observation of a negative resistance in a low-frequency electromagnetic model, actual positive signal amplitude gain, the spontaneous generation of electromagnetic waves and runaway amplifi- cation effects have never been experimentally verified. Here, we demonstrate experimentally that a mechanically rotating metallic cylinder not only definitively acts as an amplifier of a rotating elec- tromagnetic field mode but also, when paired with a low-loss resonator, becomes unstable and acts as a generator, seeded only by noise. The system exhibits an exponential runaway amplification of spontaneously generated electromagnetic modes thus demonstrating the electromagnetic analogue of Press and Teukolskys black hole bomb. The exponential amplification from noise supports theoretical investigations into black hole instabilities and is promising for the development of future experiments to observe quantum friction in the form of the Zeldovich effect seeded by the quantum vacuum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24034v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marion Cromb, Maria Chiara Braidotti, Andrea Vinante, Daniele Faccio, Hendrik Ulbricht</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing and software for LHCb Upgrade II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24106v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A second major upgrade of the LHCb experiment is necessary to allow full exploitation of the High Luminosity LHC for flavour physics. The new experiment will operate in Run 5 of the LHC at a luminosity up to $1.5\times 10^{34}cm^{-2}s^{-1}$. The experiment will therefore experience extremely high particle fluences and data rates, posing a high challenge not only for the detector but also for the software and computing resources needed to readout, reconstruct, select and analyse the data. This document presents these challenges and the ongoing and future R&amp;D programme necessary to address them. This programme will benefit not only the LHCb Upgrade II experiment, but the whole particle physics community as similar challenges will be faced by the next generation of experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24106v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> LHCb Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beijing Normal University 12-meter Interferometric kHz GW Detector Prototype: Design and Scientific Prospects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24178v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gravitational wave (GW) astronomy has opened a new window into the universe, enabling the study of extreme astrophysical phenomena that are otherwise obscured in traditional electromagnetic observations. While global efforts have predominantly focused on low- and mid-frequency GW detection, the high-frequency regime, particularly in the kilohertz (kHz) range, remains underexplored despite its potential to reveal critical insights into compact binary mergers, neutron star physics, and other exotic astrophysical sources. In this context, the Beijing Normal University (BNU) prototype represents a pioneering effort to develop a dedicated kHz GW detector. Featuring a 12-meter L-shaped resonator within a two-arm vacuum system, the BNU prototype is designed to test innovative configurations and address key technical challenges for kHz GW detection. Beyond its primary focus on being a technology testbed and demonstrator for kHz detection, the prototype is also being evaluated for its own sensitivity in the megahertz (MHz) range, offering the potential to explore even higher-frequency signals from e.g., primordial black holes and geontropic fluctuations. This paper provides a comprehensive overview of the BNU prototype, detailing its design, key components, and scientific objectives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24178v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengyao Wang, Fan Zhang, Xinyao Guo, Haixing Miao, Huan Yang, Yiqiu Ma, Haoyu Wang, Teng Zhang, Mengdi Cao, Yuchao Chen, Xiaoman Huang, Junlang Li, Fangfei Liu, Jianyu Liu, Yuan Pan, Yulin Xia, Jianbo Xing, Yujie Yu, Chenjie Zhou, Zong-hong Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Visible optical vortices measured with bulk lateral shearing interferometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.24218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.24218v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultrafast pulse optical vortices are spatiotemporal structures with a diverse range of applications. There are different ways to generate them, often restricted to a wavelength range. Likewise, characterization techniques frequently possess similar limitations. In this work, we first generate ultrashort optical vortices in the near infrared from Ti:sapphire laser pulses by means of structured waveplates and beam manipulation. Then, we produce the visible vortices through up-conversion using a second-harmonic generation crystal. The resulting beams require spatiotemporal characterization, which are performed by bulk lateral shearing interferometry. The reference pulse is temporally characterized with the amplitude swing technique. In this manner, we present the generation of these pulses in the visible range, which are experimentally validated, and demonstrate that bulk lateral shearing interferometry can be used for pulsed beams across widely different spectral regions with the same setup. This finding is significant for future applications of the technique with various sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.24218v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel L\'opez-Ripa, \'I\~nigo Sola, Benjam\'in Alonso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gas contamination and mitigation in a 100 m$^3$ / 10 bar argon TPC with optical readout: a viability study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05791v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Gaseous Optical Time Projection Chambers (OTPCs) aimed at Neutrino Physics and Rare Event Searches will likely exceed the tonne scale during the next decade. This will make their performance sensitive to gas contamination levels as low as 100 ppb, that is challenging at room temperature due to outgassing from structural materials. In this work we discuss gas distribution and impurity mitigation in a 5 m-length/5 m-diameter 10 bar TPC filled with Ar/CF$_4$ admixed at 99/1 per volume (1.75 tonne), loaded with technical plastics in order to enhance light collection and readout. Different distributor topologies, outgassing and flow rates are discussed. Specifically, our work is aimed at illustrating the conceptual viability of the optical readout of ND-GAr's TPC (within the DUNE Near-Detector complex), in terms of material compatibility. For our proposal, with perforated distributors aligned with the electric field, and under realistic assumptions, the concentration of contaminants can be controlled within a week after chamber filling. In the case of N$_2$, injection of fresh gas at %-level seems to represent the safest strategy to keep the concentration within operability limits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05791v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. J. Fern\'andez-Posada, D. Gonz\'alez-D\'iaz, J. Baldonedo, J. Collazo, E. Casarejos, P. Hamacher-Baumann, P. Amedo, J. Llerena</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Installation and performance of the 3rd Veto plane at the SND@LHC detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10188v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: During 2022/2023 the optimal inefficiency of the Veto system of the SND@LHC detector was measured to be $(7.8\pm2.8)\times10^{-8}$. To reduce this inefficiency, a third Veto plane was installed during the 2023-2024 Year End Technical Stop. In addition, the Veto system was lowered to cover the target fully, thereby increasing acceptance. This paper describes how the inefficiency of the Veto system was reduced from $7.8\times10^{-8}$ with an acceptance of about $64\%$ of the target area in 2022-2023 to $(8.7\pm3.5)\times10^{-9}$ on the full area in 2024.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10188v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> LHC Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development and commissioning of a new readout system for the gas flow of the Belle II $K_L^0$ and muon detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10261v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We have designed and commissioned a new readout board to detect photosensor signals from gas-bubbler panels to continuously monitor the gas flow through the resistive plate chambers of the $K_L^0$ and muon detector of Belle II. The gas flow measurements have been integrated into Belle II's alarm system. The bubbler-monitoring system was first employed during the February 2024 to July 2024 Belle II data-taking period.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10261v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nima.2025.170427</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nucl. Instrum. Methods A 1076 (2025) 170427</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Travis Applegate, Noah Brenny, Chunhui Chen, Seema Choudhury, James Cochran, Shuaiyan Kang, Avinash Khatri, Haruki Kindo, Tommy Lam, Sayan Mitra, Adil Mubarak, Leo Piilonen, Soeren Prell, Michele Veronesi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Limits on Light Dark Matter Interactions in a Low Threshold Two Channel Athermal Phonon Detector from the TESSERACT Collaboration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03683v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present results of a search for spin-independent dark matter-nucleon interactions in a 1 cm$^2$ by 1 mm thick (0.233 gram) high-resolution silicon athermal phonon detector operated above ground. For interactions in the substrate, this detector achieves a r.m.s. baseline energy resolution of 361.5 $\pm$ 0.4 MeV/$c^2$, the best for any athermal phonon detector to date. With an exposure of 0.233g $\times$ 12 hours, we place the most stringent constraints on dark matter masses between 44 and 87 MeV/$c^2$, with the lowest unexplored cross section of 4 $\times 10^{-32}$ cm$^2$ at 87 MeV/$c^2$. We employ a conservative salting technique to reach the lowest dark matter mass ever probed via direct detection experiment. This constraint is enabled by two-channel rejection of low-energy backgrounds that are coupled to individual sensors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03683v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. L. Chang, Y. -Y. Chang, L. Chaplinsky, C. W. Fink, M. Garcia-Sciveres, W. Guo, S. A. Hertel, X. Li, J. Lin, M. Lisovenko, R. Mahapatra, W. Matava, D. N. McKinsey, V. Novati, P. K. Patel, B. Penning, H. D. Pinckney, M. Platt, M. Pyle, Y. Qi, M. Reed, G. R. C Rischbieter, R. K. Romani, B. Sadoulet, B. Serfass, P. Sorensen, A. Suzuki, V. Velan, G. Wang, Y. Wang, S. L. Watkins, M. R. Williams, J. K. Wuko, T. Aramaki, P. Cushman, N. N. Gite, A. Gupta, M. E. Huber, N. A. Kurinsky, J. S. Mammo, B. von Krosigk, A. J. Mayer, J. Nelson, S. M. Oser, L. Pandey, A. Pradeep, W. Rau, T. Saab</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-enabled Rydberg atomic polarimetry of radio-frequency fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17997v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Rydberg atoms efficiently link photons between the radio-frequency (RF) and optical domains. They furnish a medium in which the presence of an RF field imprints on the transmission of a probe laser beam by altering the coherent coupling between atomic quantum states. The immutable atomic energy structure underpins quantum-metrological RF field measurements and has driven intensive efforts to realize inherently self-calibrated sensing devices. Here we investigate spectroscopic signatures owing to the angular momentum quantization of the atomic states utilized in an electromagnetically-induced transparency (EIT) sensing scheme for linearly-polarized RF fields. Specific combinations of atomic terms are shown to give rise to universal, distinctive fingerprints in the detected optical fields upon rotating the RF field polarization. Using a dressed state picture, we identify two types of angular momentum ladders that display strikingly disparate spectroscopic signatures, including the absence or presence of a central spectral EIT peak. We verify our predicted complementary response in rubidium vapour cell experiments and through density matrix calculations. Our study adds important insights into the prospects of Rydberg atomic polarimetry for quantum metrological electric field characterization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17997v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Cloutman, Matthew Chilcott, Alexander Elliott, J. Susanne Otto, Amita B. Deb, Niels Kj{\ae}rgaard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Linear Collider Vision for the Future of Particle Physics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19983v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we review the physics opportunities at linear $e^+e^-$ colliders with a special focus on high centre-of-mass energies and beam polarisation, take a fresh look at the various accelerator technologies available or under development and, for the first time, discuss how a facility first equipped with a technology mature today could be upgraded with technologies of tomorrow to reach much higher energies and/or luminosities. In addition, we will discuss detectors and alternative collider modes, as well as opportunities for beyond-collider experiments and R\&amp;D facilities as part of a linear collider facility (LCF). The material of this paper will support all plans for $e^+e^-$ linear colliders and additional opportunities they offer, independently of technology choice or proposed site, as well as R\&amp;D for advanced accelerator technologies. This joint perspective on the physics goals, early technologies and upgrade strategies has been developed by the LCVision team based on an initial discussion at LCWS2024 in Tokyo and a follow-up at the LCVision Community Event at CERN in January 2025. It heavily builds on decades of achievements of the global linear collider community, in particular in the context of CLIC and ILC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19983v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Abramowicz, E. Adli, F. Alharthi, M. Almanza-Soto, M. M. Altakach, S Ampudia Castelazo, D. Angal-Kalinin, R. B. Appleby, O. Apsimon, A. Arbey, O. Arquero, A. Aryshev, S. Asai, D. Atti\'e, J. L. Avila-Jimenez, H. Baer, J. A. Bagger, Y. Bai, I. R. Bailey, C. Balazs, T Barklow, J. Baudot, P. Bechtle, T. Behnke, A. B. Bellerive, S. Belomestnykh, Y. Benhammou, J. Berenguer-Antequera, M. Berger, M. Berggren, M. Bertucci, M. Besan\c{c}on, T. Biek\"otter, S. Bilanishvili, B. Bilki, B. Bilki, J. Bj\"orklund Svensson, V. M. Bjelland, C. Blanch, M. Boehler, S. Boogert, M. Boronat, V. Boudry, D. Bourilkov, I. Bozovic, J. Braathen, J. E. Brau, C. Breuning, J. -C. Brient, I. Brock, B. Brudnowski, K. Buesser, E. Bulyak, P. N. Burrows, A. Caldwell, F. G. Celiberto, E. Cenni, I. Chaikovska, R. Chehab, J. B. B. Chen, G. Chen, T. Chikamatsu, V. Cilento, P. Colas, M. Coman, F. Cornet, F. Cornet-Gomez, F. Corriveau, J. Cvach, R. D'Arcy, C. Damerell, A. Das, S. Dasu, J. de Blas, E. Del Core, M. Demarteau, H. Denizli, R. Dermisek, A. Dhar, S. Dittmaier, F. Djurabekova, E. M. Donegani, A. Doyle, P. Drobniak, T. A. du Pree, B. Dudar, H. Duran Yildiz, G. Durieux, J. Dutta, S. Easo, G. Eckerlin, U. Einhaus, E. Esarey, D. Espriu, L. R Evans, J. Farmer, A. Faus Golfe, M. Fernandez, J. C. Fernandez-Ortega, M. Formela, A. Formenti, B. Foster, N. Fourches, M. C. Fouz, A. Freitas, C. D. Fu, K. Fujii, J. Fujimoto, B. Fuks, J. Fuster, N. Fuster-Mart\'inez, F. Gaede, M. Galletti, E. Gallo, S. Ganjour, M. V. Garzelli, R. L. Geng, S. Gessner, I. D. Gialamas, B. Gimeno, J. Goldstein, M. Goncerz, F. J. Gonzalez, D. Gonz\'alez-Iglesias, S. G. Gori, J. Grames, P. Grannis, L. Gray, G. Grenier, H. Guler, H. E. Haber, K. Hamaguchi, N. Hamann, O. Hartbrich, G. H\"utsi, S. Heinemeyer, G. Heinrich, C. Hensel, K. Hidaka, S. Hirose, A. H. Hoang, M. J. Hogan, W. Hollik, Y. Horii, R. Hosokawa, S. Huang, D. Hynds, M. I. Idzik, S. Iguro, Y. Iiyama, K. Ikematsu, A. Irles, A. Ishikawa, M. Ishino, I. P. Ivanov, Y. Iwashita, M. Jacewicz, R. Jaramillo, D. Jeans, C. Jing, R. M Jones, W. Kaabi, M. Kagan, J. Kalinowski, D. K Kalvik, J. Kaminski, S. Kanemura, K. Kannike, A. Karam, Y. Kato, K. Kawagoe, D. K\"afer, L. Kennedy, J. Kersten, S. A. Khan, V. A. Khoze, W. Kilian, J. Klamka, P. Kluit, K. Kong, P. Koppenburg, A. Korsun, A. V. Kotwal, S. Kraml, K. Kr\"uger, K. Kubo, T. Kubo, M. Kucharczyk, N. Kumar, A. Kumar, M. Kurata, Y. Kurihara, J. Kvasnicka, K. Kyoya, I. Laktineh, A. Latina, F. LeDiberder, A. Levy, M. Liepe, C. A. Lindstr{\o}m, B. List, J. List, M. Litos, V. N. Litvinenko, A. Lopez-Virto, X. Lu, T. Luo, M. Lupberger, B. Madison, T. Madlener, J. Maeda, F. Mahmoudi, E. Maina, N. Majernik, R. Margraf-O'Neal, P. Mart\'in-Luna, A. Martens, V. J. Martin, L. Marzola, V. I. Maslov, K. T. Matchev, S. Matsumoto, K. Mawatari, J. P. M\'arquez, M. M. M\"uhlleitner, P. A. McIntosh, K. Mekala, D. Melini, F. Meloni, A. Men\'endez, S. Michizono, K. Mimasu, V. Miralles, W. Mitaroff, V. A. Mitsou, L. Monaco, G. Moortgat-Pick, M. Moreno-Ll\'acer, T. Mori, J. M. Moron, S. Morton, D. Moya, M. Mulder, E. Musumeci, V. V. Mytrochenko, N. Nagata, E. Nagy, T. Nakada, J. Nakajima, K. Nakamura, E. A. Nanni, E. Nardi, S. Narita, M. T. N\'u\~nez Pardo de Vera, M. Nojiri, D. Ntounis, A. Ody, O. M. Ogreid, Y. Okada, C. Oleari, M. Olveg{\aa}rd, M. Omet, T. Omori, Y. Onel, H. Ono, W. Ootani, C. Orero, J. Osborne, K. Osterberg, J. Osterhoff, M. Ouchemhou, Q. Ouyang, S. Pagan Griso, R. Paparella, S. C. Park, J. Pata, J. R. Patterson, R. P\"oschl, F. Pe\~na, L. K Pedraza-Motavita, M. E. Peskin, F. Pilat, P. Piot, S. Pl\"atzer, I. Polak, W. Porod, K. Potamianos, C. T. Potter, P. Poulose, J. G. Power, D. Protopopescu, H. R. Qi, J. Rabara Bailey, M. Raidal, J. P. Ralston, A. Rastogi, L. Reichenbach, J. Reuter, F. Richard, S. Riemann, R. A. Rimmer, T. Robens, A. Robson, G. Rodrigo, C. S. Rogan, J. Rojo, M. Q. Ruan, S. Rudrabhatla, A. Ruiz Jimeno, T. Saeki, H. Sakai, Y. Sakaki, F. Salvatore, T. Sanuki, S. Sasikumar, T Sch\"orner, S. Schroeder, C. B. Schroeder, I. Schulthess, M. Schumacher, A. Schwartzman, Y. Seiya, A. Senol, H. Sert, D. Sertore, A. Seryi, T. Shidara, K. Sjobak, I. Smiljanic, S. Spannagel, M. Spira, M. Stanitzki, S. Stapnes, D. Storey, J. Strube, A. Subba, A. Subba, T. Suehara, H. Sugawara, K. Sugizaki, Z. Sun, R. Szafron, T. Takahashi, T. Takeshita, T. Tauchi, G. Taylor, N. Terunuma, D. Terzani, T. Teubner, J. Tian, J. Timmermans, M. Titov, R. Tomas Garcia, T. Tong, J. M. Torndal, M. Trautwein, A. Tricoli, K. Tsumura, B. Tuchming, D. Tuckler, M. Tytgat, A. Ukleja, C. Vallee, R. Van Kooten, J. van Tilborg, A. Vauth, M. Vellasco, C. Vernieri, L. Verra, M. Vicente Barreto Pinto, I. Vidakovic, H. Videau, E. Viklund, I. Vila, M. Villaplana, M. Vos, N. Vukasinovic, N. Walker, K. Wandall-Christensen, Y. Wang, Z. Was, T. Watanabe, N. K. Watson, G. Weiglein, J. D. Wells, H. Wennl\"of, M. Wenskat, S. Westhoff, J. W. Wetzel, A. P. White, P. H. Williams, M. Williams, G. W. Wilson, M. Wing, A. Winter, M. Winter, T. Wojton, J. C. Wood, X. Xia, K. Yagyu, H. Yamamoto, A. Yamamoto, K. Yamamoto, Y. Yamamoto, S. Yamashita, M. Yamauchi, K. Yokoya, M. Yoshioka, J. Zalesak, A. F. Zarnecki, K. Zembaczynski, D. Zerwas, Y. Zhang, J. Zhang, M. Zielinski, M. Zobov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
