<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ins-det updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det</link>
    <description>physics.ins-det updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 01:34:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>First direct search for light dark matter interactions in a transition-edge sensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18982v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose the use of transition-edge sensor (TES) single-photon detectors as a simultaneous target and sensor for direct dark matter searches, and report results from the first search of this kind. We perform a 489 h science run with a TES device optimized for the detection of 1064 nm photons, with a mass of ~0.2 ng and an energy threshold of ~0.3 eV, and set new limits on dark matter interactions with both electrons and nucleons for dark matter with mass below the MeV scale. With their excellent energy resolution, TESs enable search strategies that are complementary to recent results from superconducting nanowire single-photon detectors and kinetic inductance detectors. We show that next-generation TES arrays hold promise to probe new regions of light dark matter parameter space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18982v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christina Schwemmbauer, Guy Daniel Hadas, Yonit Hochberg, Katharina-Sophie Isleif, Friederike Januschek, Benjamin V. Lehmann, Axel Lindner, Adriana E. Lita, Manuel Meyer, Gulden Othman, Elmeri Rivasto, Jos\'e Alejandro Rubiera Gimeno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Making the $\mu$OST of the Muon Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19301v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Muon Collider, recently highlighted as Recommendation 1 in the U.S. National Academies report on Elementary Particle Physics, offers a unique opportunity for fixed-target experiments with high energy and luminosity. This paper outlines some of the challenges and possibilities for fixed-target experiments to study the multi-dimensional structure of hadrons at the Muon Collider. We present a sketch of an experiment making use of the high-energy muon beam from the Muon Collider that could serve as the next-generation hadronic physics experiment after the Electron-Ion Collider.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19301v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henry T. Klest</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cryogenic cesium iodide as a potential PET material</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13598v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Total Body PET (TBPET) scanners have recently demonstrated the ability to significantly reduce both acquisition time and the administered radioactive dose, thanks to their increased sensitivity. However, their widespread adoption is limited by the high costs associated with the current available systems. Cesium iodide (CsI), though historically less favored for PET due to its lower stopping power and light yield compared to crystals like LYSO, shows remarkable improvement when operated at cryogenic temperatures ($\sim$100 K). Under these conditions, CsI light yield rises dramatically to about 100 photons/keV, providing excellent energy resolution and good coincidence time resolution at a lower cost - typically 3 to 5 times cheaper than other crystals at parity of radiation length. In our study, we measured the light yield, the energy resolution and the coincidence time resolution as a function of temperature for two pure CsI crystals read out by a pair of silicon photomultipliers (SiPMs). An energy resolution of 6.3% FWHM and a coincidence time resolution of 1.84 ns at 511 keV were achieved at a temperature of 104 K. These results point towards the potential of cryogenic CsI as a cost-effective, high-performance material for TBPET scanners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13598v5</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1748-0221/20/06/P06038</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JINST 20 P06038 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S. R. Soleti, A. Castillo, J. I. Collar, M. del Barrio-Torregrosa, C. Echeverria, M. Seemann, D. Zerzion, J. J. G\'omez Cadenas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear and Nonlinear Ultra-Short Pulse Looped Antennas: Radiation and Parametric Oscillations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18600v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Modern optical systems send and receive ultra-short temporal pulses (USP). While ultra-broad band antennas do exist in the microwave region (e.g., log-periodic antennas), their short temporal response is typically limited by the antenna's large dispersion, hence, resulting in a substantial pulse broadening. The issue becomes more severe when one considers both the transmitted and received pulses. Through simulations and experiments one can show that properly designed loop antennas, either thick loops or 3-loop antennas, exhibit USP attributes, 280 ps upon transmission and 380 ps upon reception (or, an overall equivalent coherent channel exceeding 2.5 GHz). Finally, most parametric amplifiers are narrow band and one may ask if a broadband amplification is possible. A loop inside a loop system, coupled by a nonlinear impedance element exhibits a line narrowing and signal amplification with large bandwidth, which is inversely scalable with the loops' diameter. In all, these elements could be advantageous for applications such as ultra-wide bandwidth communication and non-linear quantum information systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18600v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Grebel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detection of subsurface structures with a vehicle-based atom gravity gradiometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18506v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-precision mobile gravity gradiometers are very useful in geodesy and geophysics. Atom gravity gradiometers (AGGs) could be among the most accurate mobile gravity gradiometers but are currently constrained by the trade-off between portability and sensitivity. Here, we present a high-sensitivity mobile AGG featuring an ultra-compact sensor head with a volume of only 94 L. In the laboratory, it achieves a sensitivity of 77 E/$\sqrt{Hz}$ (1 E=1$\times10^{-9}$/s$^2$) and a long-term stability of better than 0.5 E. We integrated the instrument in a minivan, enabling efficient mobile field surveys with excellent maneuverability in confined spaces. Using this vehicular system, we surveyed the gravitational field over a set of subsurface structures within a small wooded area, successfully resolving their structural signatures with a signal-to-noise ratio of 57 and quantifying the water depth in a reservoir with an accuracy of $\pm$0.23 m. Compared with previous observations using a CG-5 gravimeter, the superior spatial resolution inherent in gradiometry is clearly demonstrated. This work paves the way for bring AGGs to practical field applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18506v3</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaowei Zhang, Jiaqi Zhong, Muyan Wang, Huilin Wan, Hui Xiong, Dandan Jiang, Zhi Li, Dekai Mao, Bin Gao, Biao Tang, Xi Chen, Jin Wang, Mingsheng Zhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
