<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.ins-det updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det</link>
    <description>physics.ins-det updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.ins-det" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 05:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of external cross-talk from silicon photomultipliers in a liquid xenon detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15991v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Light-only Liquid Xenon experiment (LoLX) employs a small-scale detector equipped with 96 Hamamatsu VUV4 silicon photomultipliers (SiPMs) submerged in 5 kg of liquid xenon (LXe) to perform characterization measurements of light production, transport and detection in xenon. In this work, we perform a novel measurement of the "external cross-talk" (ExCT) of SiPMs, where photons produced in the avalanche process escape the device and produce correlated signals on other SiPMs. SiPMs are the photodetector technology of choice for next generation rare-event search experiments; understanding the sources and effects of correlated noise in SiPMs is critical for producing accurate estimates of detector performance and sensitivity projections. We measure the probability to observe ExCT through timing correlation of detected photons in low-light conditions within LoLX. Measurements of SiPM ExCT are highly detector dependent; thus the ExCT process is simulated and modelled using the Geant4 framework. Using the simulation, we determine the average transport and detection efficiency for ExCT photons within LoLX, a necessary input to extract the expected ExCT probability from the data. For an applied overvoltage of 4 V and 5 V, we measure a mean number of photons emitted into the LXe per avalanche of $0.5^{+0.3}_{-0.2}$ and $0.6^{+0.3}_{-0.2}$, respectively. Using an optical model to describe photon transmission through the SiPM surface, this corresponds to an estimated photon yield inside the bulk silicon of $20^{+11}_{-9}$ and $25^{+12}_{-9}$ photons per avalanche. The relative increase in intensity of SiPM ExCT emission between 4 V and 5 V is consistent with expectation for the linear increase of gain with respect to overvoltage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15991v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D Gallacher, A. de St. Croix, S. Bron, B. M. Rebeiro, T. McElroy, S. Al Kharusi, T. Brunner, C. Chambers, B. Chana, Z. Charlesworth, E. Egan, M. Francesconi, L. Galli, P. Giampa, D. Goeldi, S. Lavoie, J. Lefebvre, X. Li, C. Malbrunot, P. Margetak, N. Massacret, S. C. Nowicki, H. Rasiwala, K. Raymond, F. Reti\`ere, S. Rottoo, L. Rudolph, M. A. T\'etrault, S. Viel, N. V. H. Viet, L. Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Test System for the JUNO 20-inch PMTs Prior to Installation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16146v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The JUNO experiment requires an excellent energy resolution of 3\% at 1 MeV. To achieve this objective, a total of 20,012 20-inch photomultiplier tubes (PMTs) will be deployed for JUNO, comprising 15,012 multi-channel plate (MCP) PMTs and 5,000 dynode PMTs. Currently, JUNO is in the process of detector installation, with PMTs being installed from the top to the bottom of the stainless-steel structure located in the underground experimental hall. In order to validate the functionality of the PMTs and ensure there are no malfunctions prior to installation, a test system has been established at the JUNO site, and testing is being conducted. This paper presents an overview of the test system and reports on the initial test results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16146v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoyuan Peng, Haojie Dong, Kaile Wen, Xinzhou Guo, Yanfeng Li, Songyi Li, Zeyuan Feng, Wan Xie, Shenghui Liu, Chao Chen, Xiaochuan Xie, Jun Hu, Lei Fan, Zhonghua Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi Crystal based Circular Patch Antenna with Artificial Magnetic Conductor for Breast Cancer Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16269</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16269v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Design and simulation of Quasi Crystal based Artificial Magnetic Conductor (AMC) Circular Microstrip Patch Antenna for tumor detection is discussed. Initially, a Circular Microstrip patch antenna is designed with a resonant frequency of $2.45 \, \text{GHz}$. The performance of the designed antenna can be improved by incorporating AMC in order to avoid surface waves. In this paper, we propose a novel technique for detecting malignant tissues in a more focusing manner using a Penrose patterned Quasi crystal. Quasi crystals act as a focusing device as it can transmit electromagnetic waves in a narrow direction. The tumor of size $3 \, \text{mm}$ is placed at a particular location specifically at $(0,0,10)$ in the breast phantom model. Our aim is the proposed model could identify the exact tumor location or the nearest co-ordinates of the actual location. Scattering parameters $S_{11}$ and $S_{22}$ obtained at $-10.30 \, \text{dB}$ and $-9.15 \, \text{dB}$ respectively at the tumor location $(0,-4,30)$ without the presence of Quasi crystal. Results were compared in each stage with and without Penrose Quasi crystal based patch antenna. The Quasi crystal based model was simulated and the results $S_{11}$ and $S_{22}$ parameters got improved at $-10.02 \, \text{dB}$ and $-9.37 \, \text{dB}$ respectively at the tumor location $(-1, -1, 13)$. The total specific absorption rate (SAR) of the proposed model is $0.139 \, \text{W/kg}$. Hence the proposed model is highly bio-compatible and safely applicable for human body.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16269v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vishnupriya Leena, Nikhil Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of proton-induced damage in thick, p-channel skipper-CCDs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16350v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we characterize the radiation-induced damage in two thick, p-channel skipper-CCDs irradiated unbiased and at room temperature with 217-MeV protons. We evaluate the overall performance of the sensors and demonstrate their single-electron/single-photon sensitivity after receiving a fluence on the order of 10$^{10}$~protons/cm$^2$. Using the pocket-pumping technique, we quantify and characterize the proton-induced defects from displacement damage. We report an overall trap density of 0.134~traps/pixel for a displacement damage dose of $2.3\times10^7$~MeV/g. Three main proton-induced trap species were identified, V$_2$, C$_i$O$_i$ and V$_n$O$_m$, and their characteristic trap energies and cross sections were extracted. We found that while divacancies are the most common proton-induced defects, C$_i$O$_i$ defects have a greater impact on charge integrity at typical operating temperatures because their emission-time constants are comparable or larger than typical readout times. To estimate ionization damage, we measure the characteristic output transistor curves. We found no threshold voltage shifts after irradiation. Our results highlight the potential of skipper-CCDs for applications requiring high-radiation tolerance and can be used to find the operating conditions in which effects of radiation-induced damage are mitigated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16350v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brenda A. Cervantes-Vergara, Santiago E. Perez, Claudio R. Chavez, Fernando Chierchie, Brandon Roach, Juan Estrada, Alex Drlica-Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A muon tagging with Flash ADC waveform baselines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16384v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This manuscript describes an innovative method to tag the muons using the baseline information of the Flash ADC (FADC) waveform of PMTs in the JSNS1 (J-PARC Sterile Neutrino Search at J-PARC Spallation Neutron Source) experiment. This experiment is designed for the search for sterile neutrinos, and a muon tagging is an essential key component for the background rejection since the detector of the experiment is located over-ground, where is the 3rd floor of the J-PARC Material and Life experimental facility (MLF). Especially, stopping muons inside the detector create the Michel electrons, and they are important background to be rejected. Utilizing this innovative method, more than 99.8% of Michel electrons can be rejected even without a detector veto region. This technique can be employed for any experiments which uses the similar detector configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16384v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. H. Lee, M. K. Cheoun, J. H. Choi, J. Y. Choi, T. Dodo, J. Goh, K. Haga, M. Harada, S. Hasegawa, W. Hwang, T. Iida, H. I. Jang, J. S. Jang, K. K. Joo, D. E. Jung, S. K. Kang, Y. Kasugai, T. Kawasaki, E. M. Kim, S. B. Kim, S. Y. Kim, H. Kinoshita, T. Konno, C. Little, T. Maruyama, E. Marzec, S. Masuda, S. Meigo, D. H. Moon, T. Nakano, M. Niiyama, K. Nishikawa, M. Y. Pac, B. J. Park, H. W. Park, J. B. Park, Jisu Park, J. S. Park, R. G. Park, S. J. M. Peeters, C. Rott, J. W. Ryu, K. Sakai, S. Sakamoto, T. Shima, C. D. Shin, J. Spitz, F. Suekane, Y. Sugaya, K. Suzuya, Y. Takeuchi, W. Wang, W. Wei, Y. Yamaguchi, M. Yeh, I. S. Yeo, I. Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Monitoring Method for the Ice Shape and the Freeze-Thaw Process of Ice Accretion on Transmission Lines Based on Circular FBG Plane Principal Strain Sensor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16798v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As a key infrastructure for China's "West-to-East Power Transmission" project, transmission lines (TL) face the threat of ice accretion under complex microclimatic conditions. This study proposes a plane principal strain sensing method based on a fiber Bragg grating circular array, achieving synchronous monitoring of 6 strains (ranging from -2000 to 2000 {\mu}{\epsilon}) across the TL cross-section. Through finite element simulation experiments, a mapping relationship between the bending of TL and the plane principal strain has been established. After completing the sensor calibration, an experimental platform for the freeze-thaw process of ice accretion on the TL was built. The relationships between ice mass and bending strain, as well as the ice shape on the TL cross-section (C-shaped and circular ice) and plane principal strain, were studied. Furthermore, a BP neural network model was developed to determine the 4 states of the icing process (no ice/freeze/stable/thaw), achieving an accuracy of 91.23%. This study provides effective monitoring of the freeze-thaw process of ice accretion on the TL, offering important technical support for the prevention and control of ice accretion in power grid.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16798v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuoke Qin, Bin Jia, Xiahui Shen, Lizhen Zhang, Honggang Lu, Chao Du, Liqin Cui, Li Zhang, Xiao Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development of a picosecond-timing Cherenkov detector using gaseous photomultiplification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17025v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Photosensitive gaseous detectors with a simple photoelectron multiplication mechanism as resistive plate chambers are expected to offer both large photo coverage and excellent time resolution while keeping costs low. We have developed a gaseous photomultiplier (GasPM) and demonstrated that a single-photon time resolution is $25\pm1.1~\rm{ps}$ at the gain of $3.3\times10^6$ with a $\rm {LaB_6}$ photocathode, which has an extremely low quantum efficiency. We then developed a Cherenkov detector using GasPM with a $\rm{CsI}$ photocathode aiming for an application in time-of-flight measurements with a resolution below 10~$\rm{ps}$ for particle identification. We performed a test using the 3 GeV electron beam at the PF-AR test beamline located at KEK, Japan. As a result, the resolution of time-of-flight between the detector and an MCP-PMT is measured to be $\sigma=73.0\pm2.4~\rm{ps}$. The obtained resolution is worse than the target because of the lower gap voltage compared to the design. However, it is consistent with the expectation from the applied gap voltage. It is an important milestone for achieving the designed resolution by increasing the gap voltage and photon detection efficiency in future development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17025v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Okubo, K. Matsuoka, T. Iijima, K. Inami, Y. Horii, K. Suzuki, K. Sumi, T. Ichikawa, K. Ueda, S. Koji, A. Kondo, K. Chiba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An experimental platform for levitated mechanics in space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17108v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Conducting levitated mechanical experiments in extreme conditions has long been the aim of researchers, as it allows for the investigation of new fundamental physics phenomena. One of the great frontiers has been sending these experiments into the micro-g environment of space, with multiple proposals calling for such a platform. At the same time, levitated sensors have demonstrated a high sensitivity to external stimuli which will only improve in low-vibrational conditions. conditions This paper describes the development of a technology demonstrator for optical and magnetic trapping experiments in space. Our payload represents the first concrete step towards future missions with aims of probing fundamental physical questions: matter-wave interferometry of nanoparticles to probe the limits of macroscopic quantum mechanics, detection of Dark Matter candidates and gravitational waves to test physics beyond the Standard Model, and accelerometry for Earth-observation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17108v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jack Homans, Elliot Simcox, Jakub Wardak, Laura da Palma Barbara, Tim M. Fuchs, Rafael Muffato, Florence Concepcion, Andrei Dragomir, Christian Vogt, Peter Nisbet-Jones, Christopher Bridges, Hendrik Ulbricht</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monitoring the tagging efficiency of the Low-Energy Muon beamline through background analysis: Insights into the long-term performance of ultrathin carbon foils</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17280v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The efficient tagging of individual muons, along with the stability of the involved ultrathin carbon foil, is critical for ensuring fast, reliable and reproducible low-energy muon spin rotation (LE-$\mathrm{\mu}$SR) measurements. At the Paul Scherrer Institute's Low-Energy Muon (LEM) beamline, we developed a method to monitor the tagging efficiency of the beamline using routinely collected muon decay histograms. This method leverages background comparison before and after the arrival time of the muons at the sample to extract the tagging efficiency, eliminating the need for additional detectors or measurements. By analyzing data collected between 2018 and 2024, we confirm the method's reliability and validate its results using independent reference measurements. Furthermore, we establish a correlation between the tagging efficiency and foil thickness by investigating the impact of contamination and outgassing on the carbon foil, as well as the restoration effects of laser cleaning. The findings underscore the importance of monitoring the carbon foil's condition to maintain consistent beamline performance and reproducibility. This method offers a practical approach for detector efficiency monitoring, applicable to other beamlines employing similar setups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17280v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gianluca Janka, Herman Ishchenko, Zaher Salman, Andreas Suter, Thomas Prokscha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaging and Spectral Performance of a Wide-gap CdTe Double-Sided Strip Detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15899</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15899v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The fourth flight of the Focusing Optics X-ray Solar Imager sounding rocket experiment (FOXSI-4) aimed to achieve the first imaging spectroscopic observations of mid-to-large class ( &gt;= GOES C5 class) solar flares, in contrast to the previous three flights that targeted relatively quiet regions of the Sun. To meet the emerging requirements for hard X-ray focal plane detectors for providing simultaneous diagnostics of spectrally (&lt;1 keV FWHM) and spatially (&lt;50 um) separated coronal and chromospheric emissions from solar flares, we developed a new strip-configuration detector called the wide-gap CdTe semiconductor double-sided strip detector (CdTe-DSD). The wide-gap CdTe-DSD employs a unique design principle to enhance position resolution. This enhancement is realized by expanding the gaps between electrodes to induce charge-sharing across adjacent strip electrodes and using this sharing energy information for position reconstruction to a level finer than the strip-pitch. However, the detector response becomes complex and requires consideration of various factors, such as the charge loss due to wider gaps and the dependence on the depth of photon interaction. Thus, we developed an energy reconstruction method that fully leverages the energy information between adjacent strips and from both the cathode and anode sides, achieving an energy resolution of 0.75 keV (FWHM) at 14 keV. Furthermore, we conducted an X-ray scanning experiment using a synchrotron beam at Spring-8 to evaluate the detector response with a fine scale of 10 um. Based on these results, we established a sub-strip position reconstruction method, demonstrating that X-rays interacting at the center of the gap can be determined with an accuracy of 20 um, and even those at the strip center can be determined with an accuracy of 50 um.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15899v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunsaku Nagasawa, Takahiro Minami, Shin Watanabe, Tadayuki Takahashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Realization of discretized response in rare-earth vanadates accessed by AC susceptibility and magnetocaloric methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16327v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This report presents a new technique to probe the quantitative dynamical response of the magnetic field induced heating/cooling process in rare-earth vanadium materials. The approach combines AC susceptibility and AC caloric measurements to reveal the intrinsic timescale associated with the magnetic relaxation process of rare-earth ions at low temperatures. Utilizing the well-known crystal field effect in YbVO4, we prove and demonstrate a discretized thermal analysis through a common spin-lattice relaxation phenomenon. The demonstration experiment presented in this study provides a general approach to quantitatively address multiple measured quantities in one unified discretized thermal circuit analysis. It can be extended to study other magnetic, dielectric, and elastic materials exhibiting a complex response to an external driving field in the presence of intrinsic interactions and fluctuations, particularly when an energy dissipation process is within an accessible frequency regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16327v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuntian Li, Linda Ye, Mark P. Zic, Matthias S. Ikeda, Arkady Shekhter, Ian R. Fisher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>femto-PIXAR: a neural network method for reconstruction of femtosecond X-ray free electron laser pulse energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16392v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: X-ray Free Electron Lasers (X-FELs) operate in a wide range of lasing configurations for a broad variety of scientific applications at ultrafast time-scales such as structural biology, materials science, and atomic and molecular physics. Shot-by-shot characterization of the X-FEL pulses is crucial for analysis of many experiments as well as tuning the X-FEL performance, but an outstanding challenge exist for monochromatic multi-bunch studies, such as those needed for the study of fluctuations in quantum materials. In particular, there is no current method for reliably resolving the pulse intensity profile at sub-picosecond time separation between pulses. Here we show that a physics-based U-net model can reconstruct the individual pulse power profiles on the sub-picoseond pulse separation time. Using experimental data from weak X-FEL pulse pairs, we demonstrate we can learn the pulse characteristics on a shot-by-shot basis when conventional methods fail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16392v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gesa Goetzke, Rajan Plumley, Gregor Hartmann, Tim Maxwell, Franz-Josef Decker, Alberto Lutman, Mike Dunne, Daniel Ratner, Joshua J. Turner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commercial scanning nitrogen vacancy magnetometer in a closed-cycle cryostat</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.16599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.16599v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The ability to measure magnetic fields on the nanometre scale at cryogenic temperatures is key to understand magnetism on the quantum level and to develop materials for new storage devices or quantum computers. Nitrogen vacancy (NV) centres in diamond have proven to be a robust means to harness quantum sensing for such applications. We have developed an instrument to measure the magnetic stray field of a sample with nanometre resolution from 2 K to 300 K and that accepts samples without additional preparation, especially the need to prepare a microwave line on the sample. The instrument features a software-interface for controlling and synchronising all included optical, mechanical and electronic devices and which analyses the acquired information in real time.
  We present the key features and measurement results achieved with atomic force microscopy (AFM) tips hosting an NV centre and a fully remote controllable microscope platform. The magnetometer is commercially available, and a first demonstrator has been installed in a research facility. We show micro Tesla per square root Hertz sensitivity, low noise AFM tip control and optically detected resonance scans in a closed-cycle cryostat.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.16599v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Clemens Sch\"afermeier, Christopher Kelvin von Grundherr, Patrick Ebermann, Dominik Irber, Khaled Karra\"i, Andrea Morales, Jan Rhensius, Gabriel Puebla-Hellmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutron multiplicity measurement in muon capture on oxygen nuclei in the Gd-loaded Super-Kamiokande detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17002v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent neutrino detectors, neutrons produced in neutrino reactions play an important role. Muon capture on oxygen nuclei is one of the processes that produce neutrons in water Cherenkov detectors. We measured neutron multiplicity in the process using cosmic ray muons that stop in the gadolinium-loaded Super-Kamiokande detector. For this measurement, neutron detection efficiency is obtained with the muon capture events followed by gamma rays to be $50.2^{+2.0}_{-2.1}\%$. By fitting the observed multiplicity considering the detection efficiency, we measure neutron multiplicity in muon capture as $P(0)=24\pm3\%$, $P(1)=70^{+3}_{-2}\%$, $P(2)=6.1\pm0.5\%$, $P(3)=0.38\pm0.09\%$. This is the first measurement of the multiplicity of neutrons associated with muon capture without neutron energy threshold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17002v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Kamiokande Collaboration, S. Miki, K. Abe, S. Abe, Y. Asaoka, C. Bronner, M. Harada, Y. Hayato, K. Hiraide, K. Hosokawa, K. Ieki, M. Ikeda, J. Kameda, Y. Kanemura, R. Kaneshima, Y. Kashiwagi, Y. Kataoka, S. Mine, M. Miura, S. Moriyama, M. Nakahata, S. Nakayama, Y. Noguchi, K. Okamoto, G. Pronost, K. Sato, H. Sekiya, H. Shiba, K. Shimizu, M. Shiozawa, Y. Sonoda, Y. Suzuki, A. Takeda, Y. Takemoto, A. Takenaka, H. Tanaka, S. Watanabe, T. Yano, T. Kajita, K. Okumura, T. Tashiro, T. Tomiya, X. Wang, S. Yoshida, G. D. Megias, P. Fernandez, L. Labarga, N. Ospina, B. Zaldivar, B. W. Pointon, C. Yanagisawa, E. Kearns, J. L. Raaf, L. Wan, T. Wester, J. Bian, B. Cortez, N. J. Griskevich, S. Locke, M. B. Smy, H. W. Sobel, V. Takhistov, A. Yankelevich, J. Hill, M. C. Jang, S. H. Lee, D. H. Moon, R. G. Park, B. S. Yang, B. Bodur, K. Scholberg, C. W. Walter, A. Beauch\^ene, O. Drapier, A. Ershova, A. Giampaolo, Th. A. Mueller, A. D. Santos, P. Paganini, C. Quach, B. Quilain, R. Rogly, T. Nakamura, J. S. Jang, R. P. Litchfield, L. N. Machado, F. J. P. Soler, J. G. Learned, K. Choi, N. Iovine, S. Cao, L. H. V. Anthony, D. Martin, N. W. Prouse, M. Scott, A. A. Sztuc, Y. Uchida, V. Berardi, N. F. Calabria, M. G. Catanesi, E. Radicioni, N. F. Calabria, A. Langella, G. De Rosa, G. Collazuol, M. Feltre, F. Iacob, M. Lamoureux, M. Mattiazzi, L. Ludovici, M. Gonin, L. P\'eriss\'e, B. Quilain, C. Fujisawa, S. Horiuchi, M. Kobayashi, Y. M. Liu, Y. Maekawa, Y. Nishimura, R. Okazaki, R. Akutsu, M. Friend, T. Hasegawa, T. Ishida, T. Kobayashi, M. Jakkapu, T. Matsubara, T. Nakadaira, K. Nakamura, Y. Oyama, A. Portocarrero Yrey, K. Sakashita, T. Sekiguchi, T. Tsukamoto, N. Bhuiyan, G. T. Burton, F. Di Lodovico, J. Gao, A. Goldsack, T. Katori, J. Migenda, R. M. Ramsden, Z. Xie, S. Zsoldos, Y. Kotsar, H. Ozaki, A. T. Suzuki, Y. Takagi, Y. Takeuchi, H. Zhong, J. Feng, L. Feng, S. Han, J. R. Hu, Z. Hu, M. Kawaue, T. Kikawa, M. Mori, T. Nakaya, T. V. Ngoc, R. A. Wendell, K. Yasutome, S. J. Jenkins, N. McCauley, P. Mehta, A. Tarrant, M. J. Wilking, Y. Fukuda, Y. Itow, H. Menjo, K. Ninomiya, Y. Yoshioka, J. Lagoda, M. Mandal, P. Mijakowski, Y. S. Prabhu, J. Zalipska, M. Jia, J. Jiang, C. K. Jung, W. Shi, M. J. Wilking, Y. Hino, H. Ishino, H. Kitagawa, Y. Koshio, F. Nakanishi, S. Sakai, T. Tada, T. Tano, T. Ishizuka, G. Barr, D. Barrow, L. Cook, S. Samani, D. Wark, A. Holin, F. Nova, S. Jung, B. S. Yang, J. Y. Yang, J. Yoo, J. E. P. Fannon, L. Kneale, M. Malek, J. M. McElwee, T. Peacock, P. Stowell, M. D. Thiesse, L. F. Thompson, S. T. Wilson, H. Okazawa, S. M. Lakshmi, S. B. Kim, E. Kwon, M. W. Lee, J. W. Seo, I. Yu, A. K. Ichikawa, K. D. Nakamura, S. Tairafune, K. Nishijima, A. Eguchi, S. Goto, Y. Mizuno, T. Muro, K. Nakagiri, Y. Nakajima, S. Shima, N. Taniuchi, E. Watanabe, M. Yokoyama, P. de Perio, S. Fujita, C. Jes\'us-Valls, K. Martens, Ll. Marti, K. M. Tsui, M. R. Vagins, J. Xia, M. Kuze, S. Izumiyama, R. Matsumoto, K. Terada, R. Asaka, M. Ishitsuka, H. Ito, T. Kinoshita, Y. Ommura, N. Shigeta, M. Shinoki, T. Suganuma, K. Yamauchi, T. Yoshida, J. F. Martin, H. A. Tanaka, T. Towstego, Y. Nakano, F. Cormier, R. Gaur, V. Gousy-Leblanc, M. Hartz, A. Konaka, X. Li, B. R. Smithers, S. Chen, Y. Wu, B. D. Xu, A. Q. Zhang, B. Zhang, M. Girgus, P. Govindaraj, M. Posiadala-Zezula, S. B. Boyd, R. Edwards, D. Hadley, M. Nicholson, M. O'Flaherty, B. Richards, A. Ali, B. Jamieson, S. Amanai, A. Minamino, G. Pintaudi, S. Sano, R. Shibayama, R. Shimamura, S. Suzuki, K. Wada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pulse Shape Discrimination in JSNS$^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03679v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: JSNS$^2$ (J-PARC Sterile Neutrino Search at J-PARC Spallation Neutron Source) is an experiment that is searching for sterile neutrinos via the observation of $\bar{\nu}_{\mu} \rightarrow \bar{\nu}_e$ appearance oscillations using neutrinos with muon decay-at-rest. For this search, rejecting cosmic-ray-induced neutron events by Pulse Shape Discrimination (PSD) is essential because the JSNS$^2$ detector is located above ground, on the third floor of the building. We have achieved 95$\%$ rejection of neutron events while keeping 90$\%$ of signal, electron-like events using a data driven likelihood method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03679v3</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/ptep/ptaf016</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PTEP 2025 023H02 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>T. Dodo, M. K. Cheoun, J. H. Choi, J. Y. Choi, J. Goh, K. Haga, M. Harada, S. Hasegawa, W. Hwang, T. Iida, H. I. Jang, J. S. Jang, K. K. Joo, D. E. Jung, S. K. Kang, Y. Kasugai, T. Kawasaki, E. J. Kim, J. Y. Kim, S. B. Kim, W. Kim, H. Kinoshita, T. Konno, D. H. Lee, I. T. Lim, C. Little, E. Marzec, T. Maruyama, S. Masuda, S. Meigo, D. H. Moon, T. Nakano, M. Niiyama, K. Nishikawa, M. Y. Pac, H. W. Park, J. S. Park, R. G. Park, S. J. M. Peeters, C. Rott, K. Sakai, S. Sakamoto, T. Shima, C. D. Shin, J. Spitz, F. Suekane, Y. Sugaya, K. Suzuya, Y. Takeuchi, Y. Yamaguchi, M. Yeh, I. S. Yeo, C. Yoo, I. Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance studies of the CE-65v2 MAPS prototype structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04070v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the next upgrade of the ALICE inner tracking system (ITS3) as its primary focus, a set of small MAPS test structures have been developed in the 65 nm TPSCo CMOS process. The CE-65 focuses on the characterisation of the analogue charge collection properties of this technology. The latest iteration, the CE-65v2, was produced in different processes (standard, with a low-dose n-type blanket, and blanket with gap between pixels), pixel pitches (15, 18, 22.5 $\mu$m), and pixel arrangements (square or staggered). The comparatively large pixel array size of $48\times24$ pixels in CE-65v2 allows the uniformity of the pixel response to be studied, among other benefits.
  The CE-65v2 chip was characterised in a test beam at the CERN SPS. A first analysis showed that hit efficiencies of $\geq 99\%$ and spatial resolution better than 5 $\mu$m can be achieved for all pitches and process variants. For the standard process, thanks to larger charge sharing, even spatial resolutions below 3 $\mu$m are reached, in line with vertex detector requirements for the FCC-ee.
  This contribution further investigates the data collected at the SPS test beam. Thanks to the large sensor size and efficient data collection, a large amount of statistics was collected, which allows for detailed in-pixel studies to see the efficiency and spatial resolution as a function of the hit position within the pixels. Again, different pitches and process variants are compared.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04070v5</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Ilg (University of Zurich), A. Lorenzetti (University of Zurich), H. Baba (University of Tokyo), J. Baudot (Universit\'e de Strasbourg), A. Besson (Universit\'e de Strasbourg), S. Bugiel (Universit\'e de Strasbourg), T. Chujo (University of Tsukuba), C. Colledani (Universit\'e de Strasbourg), A. Dorokhov (Universit\'e de Strasbourg), Z. El Bitar (Universit\'e de Strasbourg), M. Goffe (Universit\'e de Strasbourg), T. Gunji (University of Tokyo), C. Hu-Guo (Universit\'e de Strasbourg), K. Jaaskelainen (Universit\'e de Strasbourg), T. Katsuno (Hiroshima University), A. Kluge (European Organization for Nuclear Research), A. Kostina (Czech Technical University), A. Kumar (Universit\'e de Strasbourg), A. Macchiolo (University of Zurich), M. Mager (European Organization for Nuclear Research), J. Park (University of Tsukuba), E. Ploerer (University of Zurich, Vrije Universiteit Brussel), S. Sakai (University of Tsukuba), S. Senyukov (Universit\'e de Strasbourg), H. Shamas (Universit\'e de Strasbourg), D. Shibata (University of Tsukuba), W. Snoeys (European Organization for Nuclear Research), P. Stanek (Czech Technical University), M. Suljic (European Organization for Nuclear Research), L. Tomasek (Czech Technical University), I. Valin (Universit\'e de Strasbourg), R. Wada (Hiroshima University), Y. Yamaguchi (Hiroshima University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring dark currents in multiple cryogenic SiPMs with sub-pA sensitivity using an automated IV multiplexer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15494v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the design of an automated current-voltage (IV) multiplexer (MUX) that enables accurate measurement of the dark current in cryogenic silicon photomultipliers (SiPMs), achieving a sensitivity equivalent to detecting less than one avalanche per second. Dynamic pulse-counting measurements were used as a benchmark for reconstructing the dark current in static IV measurements. The IV-MUX features 15 channels on a single board and up to seven boards can be connected in parallel under the control of one Arduino microcontroller. To minimize leakage and enhance performance, the layout includes guard rings and high-isolation relays, enabling resolution of currents as small as 49 fA. The IV-MUX can be integrated into systems designed for IV or pulse-counting measurements, enabling seamless switching between IV and pulse-counting modes. Moreover, the IV-MUX is vacuum-compatible, validated by testing an SiPM array in a cryostat. This feature reduces the need for multiple feedthroughs when testing sensor arrays in vacuum. The design is open source and can be used to facilitate rapid and automated testing of SiPMs or similar low-current devices in one measurement cycle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15494v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Darroch, Eamon Egan, Marc-Antoine Leclerc, Thomas McElroy, Thomas Brunner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expected Tracking Performance of the ATLAS Inner Tracker at the High-Luminosity LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.15090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.15090v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The high-luminosity phase of LHC operations (HL-LHC), will feature a large increase in simultaneous proton-proton interactions per bunch crossing up to 200, compared with a typical leveling target of 64 in Run 3. Such an increase will create a very challenging environment in which to perform charged particle trajectory reconstruction, a task crucial for the success of the ATLAS physics program, and will exceed the capabilities of the current ATLAS Inner Detector (ID). A new all-silicon Inner Tracker (ITk) will replace the current ID in time for the start of the HL-LHC. To ensure successful use of the ITk capabilities in Run 4 and beyond, the ATLAS tracking software has been successfully adapted to achieve state-of-the-art track reconstruction in challenging high-luminosity conditions with the ITk detector. This paper presents the expected tracking performance of the ATLAS ITk based on the latest available developments since the ITk technical design reports.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.15090v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1748-0221/20/02/P02018</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JINST 20 (2025) P02018</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator> ATLAS Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impulse measurements enhanced with squeezed readout light</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05168v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We quantify how squeezed light can reduce quantum measurement noise to levels below the standard quantum limit in impulse measurements with mechanical detectors. The broadband nature of the signal implies that frequency-dependent squeezing performs better than frequency-independent squeezing. We calculate the optimal scaling of the impulse sensitivity with the squeezing strength, and quantify degradations due to photodetection losses. Even for lossless measurement, we find there exists a fundamental limit to the benefit of squeezing that depends only on the system's mechanical properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05168v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsai-Chen Lee, Jacob L. Beckey, Giacomo Marocco, Daniel Carney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Readout Optimization of Multi-Amplifier Sensing Charge-Coupled Devices for Single-Quantum Measurement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10508v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The non-destructive readout capability of the Skipper Charge Coupled Device (CCD) has been demonstrated to reduce the noise limitation of conventional silicon devices to levels that allow single-photon or single-electron counting. The noise reduction is achieved by taking multiple measurements of the charge in each pixel. These multiple measurements come at the cost of extra readout time, which has been a limitation for the broader adoption of this technology in particle physics, quantum imaging, and astronomy applications. This work presents recent results of a novel sensor architecture that uses multiple non-destructive floating-gate amplifiers in series to achieve sub-electron readout noise in a thick, fully-depleted silicon detector to overcome the readout time overhead of the Skipper-CCD. This sensor is called the Multiple-Amplifier Sensing Charge-Coupled Device (MAS-CCD) can perform multiple independent charge measurements with each amplifier, and the measurements from multiple amplifiers can be combined to further reduce the readout noise. We will show results obtained for sensors with 8 and 16 amplifiers per readout stage in new readout operations modes to optimize its readout speed. The noise reduction capability of the new techniques will be demonstrated in terms of its ability to reduce the noise by combining the information from the different amplifiers, and to resolve signals in the order of a single photon per pixel. The first readout operation explored here avoids the extra readout time needed in the MAS-CCD to read a line of the sensor associated with the extra extent of the serial register. The second technique explore the capability of the MAS-CCD device to perform a region of interest readout increasing the number of multiple samples per amplifier in a targeted region of the active area of the device.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10508v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1117/12.3019411</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings Volume 13103, X-Ray, Optical, and Infrared Detectors for Astronomy XI; 1310311 (2024). Event: SPIE Astronomical Telescopes + Instrumentation, 2024, Yokohama, Japan</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ana M. Botti, Brenda A. Cervantes-Vergara, Claudio R. Chavez, Fernando Chierchie, Alex Drlica-Wagner, Juan Estrada, Guillermo Fernandez Moroni, Stephen E. Holland, Blas J. Irigoyen Gimenez, Agustin J. Lapi, Edgar Marrufo Villalpando, Miguel Sofo Haro, Javier Tiffenberg, Sho Uemura, Kenneth Lin, Armin Karcher, Julien Guy, Peter E. Nugent</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
