<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.TH updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH</link>
    <description>econ.TH updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 Sep 2024 01:45:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Extreme Points of Fusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10779</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10779v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Our work explores fusions, the multidimensional counterparts of mean-preserving contractions and their extreme and exposed points. We reveal an elegant geometric/combinatorial structure for these objects. Of particular note is the connection between Lipschitz-exposed points (measures that are unique optimizers of Lipschitz-continuous objectives) and power diagrams, which are divisions of a space into convex polyhedral ``cells'' according to a weighted proximity criterion. These objects are frequently seen in nature--in cell structures in biological systems, crystal and plant growth patterns, and territorial division in animal habitats--and, as we show, provide the essential structure of Lipschitz-exposed fusions. We apply our results to several questions concerning categorization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10779v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Kleiner, Benny Moldovanu, Philipp Strack, Mark Whitmeyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Rationality: Unveiling the Role of Animal Spirits and Inflation Extrapolation in Central Bank Communication of the US</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10938v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modern macroeconomic models, particularly those grounded in Rational Expectation Dynamic Stochastic General Equilibrium (DSGE), operate under the assumption of fully rational decision-making. This paper examines the impact of behavioral factors, particularly 'animal spirits' (emotional and psychological influences on economic decisions) and 'inflation extrapolators', on the communication index/sentiment index of the US Federal Reserve. Utilizing simulations from a behavioral New Keynesian model alongside real-world data derived from Federal Reserve speeches, the study employs an Auto-Regressive Distributed Lag (ARDL) technique to analyze the interplay between these factors. The findings indicate that while the fraction of inflation extrapolators do not significantly affect the Fed's sentiment index, various aspects of animal spirits exert a notable impact. This suggests that not only is the US output gap influenced by animal spirits, but the Federal Reserve's communication is also substantially shaped by these behavioral factors. This highlights the limitations of rational expectation DSGE models and underscores the importance of incorporating behavioral insights to achieve a more nuanced understanding of economic dynamics and central bank communication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10938v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpan Chakraborty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Expert Classification Aggregation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11033</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11033v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the problem where a set of individuals has to classify $m$ objects into $p$ categories by aggregating the individual classifications, and no category can be left empty. An aggregator satisfies \emph{Expertise} if individuals are decisive either over the classification of a given object, or the classification into a given category. We show that requiring an aggregator to satisfy \emph{Expertise} and be either unanimous or independent leads to numerous impossibility results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11033v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Fioravanti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximately Optimal Auctions With a Strong Bidder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.11048</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.11048v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider auctions with N+1 bidders. Of these, N are symmetric and N+1 is "sufficiently strong" relative to the others. The auction is a "tournament" in which the first N players bid to win the right to compete with N+1. The bids of the first N players are binding and the highest bidder proceeds to a second-price competition with N+1.
  When N+1's values converge in distribution to an atom above the upper end of the distribution of the N bidders and the rest of the distribution is drained away from low values sufficiently slowly, the auction's expected revenue is arbitrarily close to the one obtained in a Myerson (1981) optimal auction.
  The tournament design is "detail free" in the sense that no specific knowledge of the distributions is needed in addition to the fact that bidder N+1 is stronger than the others as required. In particular, no additional information about the value of the atom is needed. This is important since mis-calibrating by a small amount an attempt to implement the optimal auction can lead to large losses in revenue.
  We provide an interpretation of these results as possibly providing guidelines to a seller on how to strategically "populate" auctions with a single bidder even when only weaker bidders are available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.11048v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Anderlini, GaOn Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Occupational segregation in a Roy model with composition preferences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.04485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2012.04485v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a model of labor market sector self-selection that combines comparative advantage, as in the Roy model, and sector composition preference. Two groups choose between two sectors based on heterogeneous potential incomes and group compositions in each sector. Potential incomes incorporate group specific human capital accumulation and wage discrimination. Composition preferences are interpreted as reflecting group specific amenity preferences as well as homophily and aversion to minority status. We show that occupational segregation is amplified by the composition preferences and we highlight a resulting tension between redistribution and diversity. The model also exhibits tipping from extreme compositions to more balanced ones. Tipping occurs when a small nudge, associated with affirmative action, pushes the system to a very different equilibrium, and when the set of equilibria changes abruptly when a parameter governing the relative importance of pecuniary and composition preferences crosses a threshold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2012.04485v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoning Chen, Miaomiao Dong, Marc Henry, Ivan Sidorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interest Rate Dynamics and Commodity Prices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.07577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.07577v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In economic studies and popular media, interest rates are routinely cited as a major factor behind commodity price fluctuations. At the same time, the transmission channels are far from transparent, leading to long-running debates on the sign and magnitude of interest rate effects. Purely empirical studies struggle to address these issues because of the complex interactions between interest rates, prices, supply changes, and aggregate demand. To move this debate to a solid footing, we extend the competitive storage model to include stochastically evolving interest rates. We establish general conditions for existence and uniqueness of solutions and provide a systematic theoretical and quantitative analysis of the interactions between interest rates and prices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.07577v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christophe Gouel, Qingyin Ma, John Stachurski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Source Biases: Multisource Misspecifications and Their Impact on Predictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.08740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.08740v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study how a Bayesian decision maker (DM) learns about the biases of novel information sources to predict a random state. Absent frictions, the DM uses familiar sources as yardsticks to accurately discern the biases of novel sources. We derive the distortion of the DM's long-run prediction when he holds misspecified beliefs about the biases of several familiar sources. The distortion aggregates misspecifications across familiar sources independently of the number and nature of the novel sources the DM learns about. This has implications for labor market discrimination, media bias, and project finance and oversight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.08740v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junnan He, Lin Hu, Matthew Kovach, Anqi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Aggregating Incomplete Rankings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.16309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.16309v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study considers the method to derive a ranking of alternatives by aggregating the rankings submitted by several individuals who may not evaluate all of them. The collection of subsets of alternatives that individuals (can) evaluate is referred to as an evaluability profile. For a given evaluability profile, we define an aggregating ranking function whose inputs are the rankings of individuals on the alternatives they evaluate. We investigate the properties of aggregating ranking functions, which are modifications of those introduced in previous studies. Whether an aggregating ranking function satisfying a combination of properties exists depends on the evaluability profile. Thus, we identify the necessary and sufficient conditions on evaluability profiles to ensure the existence of the functions satisfying four different combinations of properties. Furthermore, to examine how frequently possible or impossible evaluability profiles occur, we derive the proportion of each type in specific cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.16309v4</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yasunori Okumura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Decentralized Market Mechanism for Energy Communities under Operating Envelopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.17201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.17201v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose an operating envelopes (OEs) aware energy community market mechanism that dynamically charges/rewards its members based on two-part pricing. The OEs are imposed exogenously by a regulated distribution system operator (DSO) on the energy community's revenue meter and is subject to a generalized net energy metering (NEM) tariff design. By formulating the interaction of the community operator and its members as a Stackelberg game, we show that the proposed two-part pricing achieves a Nash equilibrium and maximizes the community's social welfare in a decentralized fashion while ensuring that the community's operation abides by the OEs. The market mechanism conforms with the cost-causation principle and guarantees community members a surplus level no less than their maximum surplus when they autonomously face the DSO. The dynamic and uniform community price is a monotonically decreasing function of the community's aggregate renewable generation. We also analyze the impact of exogenous parameters such as NEM rates and OEs on the value of joining the community. Lastly, through numerical studies, we showcase the community's welfare, and pricing, and compare its members' surplus to customers under the DSO's regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.17201v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed S. Alahmed, Guido Cavraro, Andrey Bernstein, Lang Tong</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
