<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.TH updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH</link>
    <description>econ.TH updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 01:42:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 13 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Limits of Personalization in Assortment Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.14861</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.14861v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To study the limits of personalization, we introduce the notion of a clairvoyant firm that can read the mind of consumers and sell them the highest revenue product that they are willing to buy. We show how to compute the expected revenue of the clairvoyant firm for a class of rational discrete choice models, and develop prophet-type inequalities that provide performance guarantees for the expected revenue of the traditional assortment optimization firm (a TAOP firm) relative to the clairvoyant firm, and therefore to any effort to personalize assortments. In particular, we show that the expected revenue of the clairvoyant firm cannot exceed twice the expected revenue of the TAOP for the RCS model, the MNL, the GAM and the Nested Logit Model. On the other hand, there are random utility models for which personalized assortments can earn up to $n$ times more than a TAOP firm, where $n$ is the number of products. Our numerical studies indicate that when the mean utilities of the products are heterogeneous among consumer types, and the variance of the utilities is small, firms can gain substantial benefits from personalized assortments. We support these observations, and others, with theoretical findings. While the consumers surplus can potentially be larger under personalized assortments, clairvoyant firms with pricing power can extract all surplus, and earn arbitrarily more than traditional firms that optimize over prices but do not personalize them. For the price-aware MNL, however, a clairvoyant firm can earn at most $e$ times more than a traditional firm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.14861v5</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guillermo Gallego, Gerardo Berbeglia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Community Enforcement with Endogenous Records</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.00839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.00839v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: I study repeated games with anonymous random matching where players endogenously decide whether to disclose signals about their past actions. I establish an-anti folk theorem, that when players are sufficiently long-lived, they will almost always play their dominant actions and will almost never cooperate. When players' expected lifespans are intermediate, they can sustain some cooperation if their actions are substitutes but cannot sustain any cooperation if their actions are complements. Therefore, the maximal level of cooperation a community can sustain is not monotone with respect to its members' expected lifespans and the complementarity of players' actions can undermine their abilities to sustain cooperation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.00839v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harry Pei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monotonic Mechanisms for Selling Multiple Goods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.17150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.17150v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Maximizing the revenue from selling two or more goods has been shown to require the use of $nonmonotonic$ mechanisms, where a higher-valuation buyer may pay less than a lower-valuation one. Here we show that the restriction to $monotonic$ mechanisms may not just lower the revenue, but may in fact yield only a $negligible$ $fraction$ of the maximal revenue; more precisely, the revenue from monotonic mechanisms is no more than k times the simple revenue obtainable by selling the goods separately, or bundled (where k is the number of goods), whereas the maximal revenue may be arbitrarily larger. We then study the class of monotonic mechanisms and its subclass of allocation-monotonic mechanisms, and obtain useful characterizations and revenue bounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.17150v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ran Ben-Moshe, Sergiu Hart, Noam Nisan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-token vs Two-token Blockchain Tokenomics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15429v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider long-term equilibria that arise in the tokenomics design of proof-of-stake (PoS) blockchain systems that comprise of users and validators, both striving to maximize their own utilities. Validators are system maintainers who get rewarded with tokens for performing the work necessary for the system to function properly, while users compete and pay with such tokens for getting a desired portion of the system service.
  We study how the system service provision and suitable rewards schemes together can lead to equilibria with desirable characteristics (1) viability: the system keeps parties engaged, (2) decentralization: multiple validators are participating, (3) stability: the price path of the underlying token used to transact with the system does not change widely over time, and (4) feasibility: the mechanism is easy to implement as a smart contract, i.e., it does not require fiat reserves on-chain for buy back of tokens or to perform bookkeeping of exponentially growing token holdings. Our analysis enables to put forward a novel generic mechanism for blockchain ``monetary policy'' that we call {\em quantitative rewarding} (QR). We investigate how to implement QR in single-token and two-token proof of stake (PoS) blockchain systems. The latter are systems that utilize one token for the users to pay the transaction fees and a different token for the validators to participate in the PoS protocol and get rewarded. Our approach demonstrates a concrete advantage of the two-token setting in terms of the ability of the QR mechanism to be realized effectively and provide good equilibria. Our analysis also reveals an inherent limitation of the single token setting in terms of implementing an effective blockchain monetary policy - a distinction that is, to the best of our knowledge, highlighted for the first time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15429v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aggelos Kiayias, Philip Lazos, Paolo Penna</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
