<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.TH updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH</link>
    <description>econ.TH updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Persuasion and Optimal Stopping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12278</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12278v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide a unified analysis of how dynamic information should be designed in optimal stopping problems: a principal controls the flow of information about a payoff relevant state to persuade an agent to stop at the right time, in the right state, and choose the right action. We further show that for arbitrary preferences, intertemporal commitment is unnecessary: optimal dynamic information designs can always be made revision-proof.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12278v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Koh, Sivakorn Sanguanmoo, Weijie Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strategy-proof Selling: a Geometric Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12279v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider one buyer and one seller. For a bundle $(t,q)\in [0,\infty[\times [0,1]=\mathbb{Z}$, $q$ either refers to the wining probability of an object or a share of a good, and $t$ denotes the payment that the buyer makes. We define classical and restricted classical preferences of the buyer on $\mathbb{Z}$; they incorporate quasilinear, non-quasilinear, risk averse preferences with multidimensional pay-off relevant parameters. We define rich single-crossing subsets of the two classes, and characterize strategy-proof mechanisms by using monotonicity of the mechanisms and continuity of the indirect preference correspondences. We also provide a computationally tractable optimization program to compute the optimal mechanism. We do not use revenue equivalence and virtual valuations as tools in our proofs. Our proof techniques bring out the geometric interaction between the single-crossing property and the positions of bundles $(t,q)$s. Our proofs are simple and provide computationally tractable optimization program to compute the optimal mechanism. The extension of the optimization program to the $n-$ buyer environment is immediate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12279v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mridu Prabal Goswami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data Trade and Consumer Privacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12457v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies optimal mechanisms for collecting and trading data. Consumers benefit from revealing information about their tastes to a service provider because this improves the service. However, the information is also valuable to a third party as it may extract more revenue from the consumer in another market called the product market. The paper characterizes the constrained optimal mechanism for the service provider subject to incentive feasibility. It is shown that the service provider sometimes sells no information or only partial information in order to preserve profits in the service market. In a general setup, the service provision distortion and no-price discrimination in the product market are exclusive. Moreover, a ban on data trade may reduce social welfare because it makes it harder to price discriminate in the product market.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12457v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiadong Gu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Bailouts in Diversified Financial Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12818v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Widespread default involves substantial deadweight costs which could be countered by injecting capital into failing firms. Injections have positive spillovers that can trigger a repayment cascade. But which firms should a regulator bailout so as to minimize the total injection of capital while ensuring solvency of all firms? While the problem is, in general, NP-hard, for a wide range of networks that arise from a stochastic block model, we show that the optimal bailout can be implemented by a simple policy that targets firms based on their characteristics and position in the network. Specific examples of the setting include core-periphery networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12818v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Krishna Dasaratha, Santosh Venkatesh, Rakesh Vohra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monopoly, Product Quality, and Flexible Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.09985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2202.09985v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A seller offers a buyer a schedule of transfers and associated product qualities. After observing this schedule, the buyer chooses a flexible costly signal about his type. We show it is without loss to focus on a class of mechanisms that compensate the buyer for his learning costs. Using these mechanisms, we prove that when marginal costs of quality are strictly increasing, quality always lies strictly below the efficient level at all types strictly below the highest possible type under the prior. When learning costs are sufficiently steep, it follows the monopolist optimum distorts quality downward even "at the top" of the buyer's chosen signal structure. Moreover, when marginal costs of quality are constant, interior buyer types obtain interior qualities. These results stand in contrast to the exogenous information case, which features "no distortion at the top" when marginal production costs are increasing, and serving the maximal quality to all types above some threshold when marginal product costs are constant. We also show that when learning costs are steep, the monopolist finds it optimal to offer a simple menu that contains at most two purchasing options. Under appropriate curvature conditions, offering a single purchasing option is optimal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2202.09985v5</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey Mensch, Doron Ravid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Desirable Rankings: A New Method for Ranking Outcomes of a Competitive Process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.11684</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.11684v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the problem of aggregating individual preferences over alternatives into a social ranking. A key feature of the problems that we consider - and the one that allows us to obtain positive results, in contrast to negative results such as Arrow's Impossibililty Theorem - is that the alternatives to be ranked are outcomes of a competitive process. Examples include rankings of colleges or academic journals. The foundation of our ranking method is that alternatives that agents rank higher than the one they receive (and thus have been rejected by) should also be ranked higher in the aggregate ranking. We introduce axioms to formalize this idea, and call any ranking that satisfies our axioms a desirable ranking. We show that as the market grows large, any desirable ranking coincides with the true underlying ranking of colleges by quality. Last, we provide an algorithm for constructing desirable rankings, and show that the outcome of this algorithm is the unique ranking of the colleges that satisfy our axioms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.11684v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thayer Morrill, Peter Troyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Obvious Manipulability of the Rank-Minimizing Mechanism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.11359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.11359v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In assignment problems, the rank distribution of assigned objects is often used to evaluate match quality. Rank-minimizing (RM) mechanisms directly optimize for average rank. While appealing, a drawback is RM mechanisms are not strategyproof. This paper investigates whether RM satisfies the weaker incentive notion of non-obvious manipulability (NOM, Troyan and Morrill, 2020). I show any RM mechanism with full support - placing positive probability on all rank-minimizing allocations - is NOM. In particular, uniform randomization satisfies this condition. Without full support, whether an RM mechanism is NOM or not depends on the details of the selection rule.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.11359v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jmateco.2024.103015</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Mathematical Economics (2024), 113:103015</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Peter Troyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A dual approach to nonparametric characterization for random utility models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04328v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper develops a novel characterization for random utility models (RUM), which turns out to be a dual representation of the characterization by Kitamura and Stoye (2018, ECMA). For a given family of budgets and its "patch" representation \'a la Kitamura and Stoye, we construct a matrix $\Xi$ of which each row vector indicates the structure of possible revealed preference relations in each subfamily of budgets. Then, it is shown that a stochastic demand system on the patches of budget lines, say $\pi$, is consistent with a RUM, if and only if $\Xi\pi \geq \mathbb{1}$, where the RHS is the vector of $1$'s. In addition to providing a concise quantifier-free characterization, especially when $\pi$ is inconsistent with RUMs, the vector $\Xi\pi$ also contains information concerning (1) sub-families of budgets in which cyclical choices must occur with positive probabilities, and (2) the maximal possible weights on rational choice patterns in a population. The notion of Chv\'atal rank of polytopes and the duality theorem in linear programming play key roles to obtain these results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04328v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nobuo Koida, Koji Shirai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speed, Accuracy, and Complexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11240v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper re-examines the use of response time to infer problem complexity. It revisits a canonical Wald model of optimal stopping, taking signal-to-noise ratio as a measure of problem complexity. While choice quality is monotone in problem complexity, expected stopping time is inverse U-shaped. Indeed, decisions are fast in both very simple and very complex problems: in simple problems, it is quick to understand which alternative is best, while in complex problems it would be too costly -- an insight which extends to general costly information acquisition models. This non-monotonicity also underlies an ambiguous relationship between response time and ability, whereby higher ability entails slower decisions in very complex problems, but faster decisions in simple problems. Finally, this paper proposes a new method to correctly infer problem complexity based on the finding that distorting incentives in favour of an alternative has a greater effect on choices in more complex problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11240v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Duarte Gon\c{c}alves</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$\alpha$-Rank-Collections: Analyzing Expected Strategic Behavior with Uncertain Utilities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.10317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.10317v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Game theory relies heavily on the availability of cardinal utility functions, but in fields such as matching markets, only ordinal preferences are typically elicited. The literature focuses on mechanisms with simple dominant strategies, but many real-world applications lack dominant strategies, making the intensity of preferences between outcomes important for determining strategies. Even though precise information about cardinal utilities is not available, some data about the likelihood of utility functions is often accessible. We propose to use Bayesian games to formalize uncertainty about the decision-makers' utilities by viewing them as a collection of normal-form games. Instead of searching for the Bayes-Nash equilibrium, we study how uncertainty in utilities is reflected in uncertainty of strategic play. To do this, we introduce a novel solution concept called $\alpha$-Rank-collections, which extends $\alpha$-Rank to Bayesian games. This allows us to analyze strategic play in, for example, non-strategyproof matching markets, for which appropriate solution concepts are currently lacking. $\alpha$-Rank-collections characterize the expected probability of encountering a certain strategy profile under replicator dynamics in the long run, rather than predicting a specific equilibrium strategy profile. We experimentally evaluate $\alpha$-Rank-collections using instances of the Boston mechanism, finding that our solution concept provides more nuanced predictions compared to Bayes-Nash equilibria. Additionally, we prove that $\alpha$-Rank-collections are invariant to positive affine transformations, a standard property for a solution concept, and are efficient to approximate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.10317v3</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian R. Pieroth, Martin Bichler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Unfairness of $\varepsilon$-Fairness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.09360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.09360v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fairness in decision-making processes is often quantified using probabilistic metrics. However, these metrics may not fully capture the real-world consequences of unfairness. In this article, we adopt a utility-based approach to more accurately measure the real-world impacts of decision-making process. In particular, we show that if the concept of $\varepsilon$-fairness is employed, it can possibly lead to outcomes that are maximally unfair in the real-world context. Additionally, we address the common issue of unavailable data on false negatives by proposing a reduced setting that still captures essential fairness considerations. We illustrate our findings with two real-world examples: college admissions and credit risk assessment. Our analysis reveals that while traditional probability-based evaluations might suggest fairness, a utility-based approach uncovers the necessary actions to truly achieve equality. For instance, in the college admission case, we find that enhancing completion rates is crucial for ensuring fairness. Summarizing, this paper highlights the importance of considering the real-world context when evaluating fairness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.09360v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tolulope Fadina, Thorsten Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
