<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.TH updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH</link>
    <description>econ.TH updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 04:13:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Risk Sharing Without Preference Convexity: An Aggregate Convexity Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08832</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08832v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the optimal risk sharing problem with a continuum of agents, modeled via a non-atomic measure space. Individual preferences are not assumed to be convex. We show the multiplicity of agents induces the value function to be convex, allowing for the application of convex duality techniques to risk sharing without preference convexity. The proof in the finite-dimensional case is based on aggregate convexity principles emanating from Lyapunov convexity, while the infinite-dimensional case uses the finite-dimensional results conjoined with approximation arguments particular to a class of law invariant risk measures, although the reference measure is allowed to vary between agents. Finally, we derive a computationally tractable formula for the conjugate of the value function, yielding an explicit dual representation of the value function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08832v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vasily Melnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collateral and Reputation in a Model of Strategic Defaults</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08849v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper builds a finite-horizon model to study the role of physical collateral in a model of strategic defaults, when the borrower can develop reputation for honesty. Asset ownership increases attractiveness of the reputational channel: the borrower who would prefer to remain in autarky in the absence of the asset prefers to apply for collateralized debt. Pledging the asset as collateral facilitates reputation building, which is especially successful at the times of asset price drops, because these are the times when default is most tempting. The complementarity between secured and unsecured lending is especially pronounced when the ratio of the borrower's financial to non-financial income is neither too large nor too small.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08849v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jedc.2023.104755</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Economic Dynamics &amp; Control 156 (2023) 104755</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Georgy Lukyanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Public Communication with Externalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08850</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08850v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper develops a model in which a sender strategically communicates with a group of receivers whose payoffs depend on the sender's information. It is shown that aggregate payoff externalities create an endogenous conflict of interests between the sender and the receivers, rendering full information revelation, in general infeasible. We demonstrate that an exogenous bias in the sender's preferences can improve public information provision and raise welfare. Two applications of the setup are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08850v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.geb.2022.09.003</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Games and Economic Behavior 136 (2022) 177-196</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Georgy Lukyanov, Konstantin Shamruk, Tong Su, Ahmed Wakrim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Belief Diversity and Cooperation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08851v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies a two-player game in which the players face uncertainty regarding the nature of their partner. In this variation of the standard Prisoner's Dilemma, players may encounter an 'honest' type who always cooperates. Mistreating such a player imposes a moral cost on the defector. This situation creates a trade-off, resolved in favor of cooperation if the player's trust level, or belief in their partner's honesty, is sufficiently high. We investigate whether an environment where players have explicit beliefs about each other's honesty is more or less conducive to cooperation, compared to a scenario where players are entirely uncertain about their partner's beliefs. We establish that belief diversity hampers cooperation in environments where the level of trust is relatively low and boosts cooperation in environments with a high level of trust.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08851v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jebo.2024.106815</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Economic Behavior &amp; Organization 229 (2025) 106815</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Georgy Lukyanov, David Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The value of conceptual knowledge</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09170v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We formalize what it means to have conceptual knowledge about a statistical decision-making environment. Such knowledge tells agents about the structural relationships among unknown, payoff-relevant states. It allows agents to represent states as combinations of features. Conceptual knowledge is more valuable when states are more "reducible": when their prior variances are explained by fewer features. Its value is non-monotone in the quantity and quality of available data, and vanishes with infinite data. Agents with deeper knowledge can attain the same welfare with less data. This is especially true when states are highly reducible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09170v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Davies, Anirudh Sankar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Credible Scores</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09621</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09621v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study cheap talk with simple language, where the sender communicates using a score that aggregates a multidimensional state. Both the sender and the receiver share the same payoffs, given by a quadratic loss function. We show that the restriction to scores introduces strategic considerations. First, equilibrium payoffs can be strictly lower than those achievable under commitment to a scoring rule. Second, we prove that any equilibrium score must be either linear or discrete. Finally, assuming normally distributed states, we fully characterize the set of equilibrium linear scores, which includes both the ex-ante best and the worst linear scores.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09621v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacopo Bizzotto, Nathan Hancart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heterogeneous Agents in the Data Economy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09656v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this short paper, we define the investment ability of data investors in the data economy and its heterogeneity. We further construct an analytical heterogeneous agent model to demonstrate that differences in data investment ability lead to divergent economic results for data investors. The analytical results prove that: Investors with higher data investment ability can obtain greater utility through data investment, and thus have stronger incentives to invest in a larger scale of data to achieve higher productivity, technological progress, and experience lower financial frictions. We aim to propose a prerequisite theory that extends the analytical framework of the data economy from the currently prevalent representative agent model to a heterogeneous agent model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09656v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongheng Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Persuasion Gains and Losses from Peer Communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a Bayesian persuasion setting in which a sender wants to persuade a critical mass of receivers by revealing partial information about the state to them. The homogeneous binary-action receivers are located on a communication network, and each observes the private messages sent to them and their immediate neighbors. We examine how the sender's expected utility varies with increased communication among receivers. We show that for general families of networks, extending the network can strictly benefit the sender. Thus, the sender's gain from persuasion is not monotonic in network density. Moreover, many network extensions can achieve the upper bound on the sender's expected utility among all networks, which corresponds to the payoff in an empty network. This is the case in networks reflecting a clear informational hierarchy (e.g., in global corporations), as well as in decentralized networks in which information originates from multiple sources (e.g., influencers in social media). Finally, we show that a slight modification to the structure of some of these networks precludes the possibility of such beneficial extensions. Overall, our results caution against presuming that more communication necessarily leads to better collective outcomes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09099v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Toygar T. Kerman, Anastas P. Tenev, Konstantin Zabarnyi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equal Pay for Similar Work</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.17111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.17111v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Equal pay laws increasingly require that workers doing "similar" work are paid equal wages within firm. We study such "equal pay for similar work" (EPSW) policies theoretically and test our model's predictions empirically using evidence from a 2009 Chilean EPSW. When EPSW only binds across protected class (e.g., no woman can be paid less than any similar man, and vice versa), firms segregate their workforce by gender. When there are more men than women in a labor market, EPSW increases the gender wage gap. By contrast, EPSW that is not based on protected class can decrease the gender wage gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.17111v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diego GentilePassaro, Fuhito Kojima, Bobak Pakzad-Hurson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reputational Conservatism in Expert Advice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04036v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a tractable career-concerns model of expert recommendations with a continuous private signal. In equilibrium, advice obeys a cutoff rule: the expert recommends the risky option if and only if the signal exceeds a threshold. Under a mild relative-diagnosticity condition, the threshold is (weakly) increasing in reputation, yielding reputational conservatism. Signal informativeness and success priors lower the cutoff, while stronger career concerns raise it. A success-contingent bonus implements any target experimentation rate via a one-to-one mapping, providing an implementable design lever.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04036v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgy Lukyanov, Anna Vlasova</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
