<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.TH updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH</link>
    <description>econ.TH updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Subjective Causality in Choice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.05957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2106.05957v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Choices based on observational data depend on beliefs about which correlations reflect causality. An agent predicts the consequence of available actions using a dataset and her subjective beliefs about causality represented by a directed acyclic graph (DAG). We identify her DAG from her random choice rule. Her choices reveal the chains of causal reasoning that she undertakes and the confounding variables she adjusts for, and these pin down her model. When her choices generate the dataset used, her behavior affects her inferences, which in turn affect her choices. We provide necessary and sufficient conditions for testing whether her behavior is compatible with such a model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2106.05957v4</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Ellis, Heidi Christina Thysen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Engagement Maximization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.00685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.00685v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the management of information provision to maximize user engagement. A principal sequentially reveals signals to an agent who has a limited amount of information processing capacity and can choose to exit at any time. We identify a ``dilution'' strategy -- sending rare but highly informative signals -- that maximizes user engagement. The platform's engagement metric shapes the direction and magnitude of biases in provided information relative to a user-optimal benchmark. Even without intertemporal commitment, the platform replicates full-commitment revenue by inducing the user's belief to remain ``as uncertain as'' the prior until the rare, decisive signal arrives and induces stopping. We apply our results to two contexts: an ad-supported internet media platform and a teacher attempting to engage test-motivated students.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.00685v5</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin H\'ebert, Weijie Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Regret-free truth-telling voting rules</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.13853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.13853v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the ability of different classes of voting rules to induce agents to report their preferences truthfully, if agents want to avoid regret. First, we show that regret-free truth-telling is equivalent to strategy-proofness among tops-only rules. Then, we focus on three important families of (non-tops-only) voting methods: maxmin, scoring, and Condorcet consistent ones. We prove positive and negative results for both neutral and anonymous versions of maxmin and scoring rules. In several instances we provide necessary and sufficient conditions. We also show that Condorcet consistent rules that satisfy a mild monotonicity requirement are not regret-free truth-telling. Successive elimination rules fail to be regret-free truth-telling despite not satisfying the monotonicity condition. Lastly, we provide two characterizations for the case of three alternatives and two agents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.13853v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Pablo Arribillaga, Agustin G. Bonifacio, Marcelo Ariel Fernandez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heterogeneity, trade integration and spatial inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.09796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.09796v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the impact of economic integration on agglomeration in a model where all consumers are inter-regionally mobile and have heterogeneous preferences regarding their residential location choices. This heterogeneity is the unique dispersion force in the model. We show that, under reasonable values for the elasticity of substitution among varieties of consumption goods, a higher trade integration always promotes more symmetric spatial patterns, reducing the spatial inequality between regions, irrespective of the functional form of the dispersion force. We also show that an increase in the degree of heterogeneity in preferences for location leads to a more even spatial distribution of economic activities and thus also reduces the spatial inequality between regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.09796v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e M. Gaspar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Allocation with Peer Information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08954v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study allocation problems without monetary transfers where agents have correlated types, i.e., hold private information about one another. Such peer information is relevant in various settings, including science funding, allocation of targeted aid, or intra-firm allocation. Incentive compatibility requires that agents cannot improve their own allocation by misrepresenting the merits of allocating to others. We characterize optimal incentive-compatible mechanisms using techniques from the theory of perfect graphs. Optimal mechanisms improve on review panels commonly observed in practice by eliciting information directly from eligible agents and by using allocation lotteries to alleviate incentive constraints. Computational hardness results imply that exactly optimal mechanisms are impractically complex. We propose ranking-based mechanisms as a viable alternative and show that they are approximately optimal when agents are informationally small, i.e., when no single agent has information that is crucial for evaluating a large fraction of the other agents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08954v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Axel Niemeyer, Justus Preusser</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
