<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.TH updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH</link>
    <description>econ.TH updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 04:08:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Sustainability Transitions and Bending the Curve of Biodiversity Collapse in the Amazon Forest</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.06663</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.06663v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper undertakes an analysis of deforestation in the Amazon area using a pathways-based approach to sustainability. We ground the analysis primarily in the sustainability transitions literature but also draw a bridge with socio-ecological concepts which helps us to understand the nature of transitions in this context. The concept of a deforestation system is developed by examining the interplay of infrastructure, technologies, narratives, and institutions. Drawing on a literature review and an in-depth case study of Puerto Maldonado in Madre de Dios, Peru, the paper identifies three pathways for addressing deforestation: optimisation, natural capital, and regenerative change. We suggest that while the optimisation pathway provides partial solutions through mitigation and compensation strategies, it often reinforces extractivist logics. The study also underscores the limitations of natural capital frameworks, which tend to rely on centralised governance and market-based instruments while lacking broader social engagement. In contrast, our findings emphasise the potential of regenerative strategies rooted in local agency, community-led experimentation, and context-sensitive institutional arrangements. The paper contributes to ongoing debates on biodiversity governance by illustrating how the spatial and long-term dynamics of deforestation interact, and why inclusive, territorially grounded pathways are crucial for bending the curve of biodiversity loss.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.06663v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5281/zenodo.15830597</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Romero-Goyeneche Oscar Yandy, Ramirez Matias, Osorio-Garcia Ana Milena, Harman Canalle Ursula</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A monotone solution to the problem of bargaining with transfers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00308v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a solution to the problem of bargaining with transfers, along with an axiomatisation of the solution. Each player receives a weighted average of the claims of the coalitions to which she belongs minus a weighted average of the claims of the other coalitions, where a coalition's claim is determined by its best allocation in the bargaining set. The key axioms are additivity and a property we call allocation monotonicity, which states that increasing a player's payoff in an allocation of the bargaining set, either outright or by means of transfers from other players, must benefit that player.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00308v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gregorio Curello, Sam Jindani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ordered Probabilistic Choice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01227v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a novel perspective by linking ordered probabilistic choice to copula theory, a mathematical framework for modeling dependencies in multivariate distributions. Each representation of ordered probabilistic choice behavior can be associated with a copula, enabling the analysis of representations through established results from copula theory. We provide functional forms to describe the "extremal" representations of an ordered probabilistic choice behavior and their distinctive structural properties. The resulting functional forms act as an "identification method" that uniquely generates heterogeneous choice types and their weights. These results provide valuable tools for analysts to identify micro-level behavioral heterogeneity from macro-level observable data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01227v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher P. Chambers, Yusufcan Masatlioglu, Kemal Yildiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Maximum Implementable Improvements over Deferred Acceptance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12871v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Deferred Acceptance (DA) mechanism produces stable but Pareto-inefficient school assignments. While mechanisms like Efficiency-Adjusted DA address this inefficiency by asking students to waive priorities at unattainable schools, they can leave significant gains unrealized-sometimes improving only two students when all but one could benefit. Surprisingly, such mechanisms can be doubly dominated, creating fewer improvements while generating more justified envy.
  We introduce the Maximum Implementable Improvement over the DA mechanism (MIIDA), which maximizes the number of students made better off given priority-waiving consents. MIIDA weakly Pareto dominates DA, is never doubly dominated, and incentivizes students to consent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12871v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taylor Knipe, Josue Ortega</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Lagrangian Approach to Optimal Lotteries in Non-Convex Economies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15997v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a new method to efficiently solve for optimal lotteries in models with non-convexities. To employ a Lagrangian framework, we prove that the value of the saddle point that characterizes the optimal lottery is the same as the value of the dual of the deterministic problem. Our algorithm solves the dual of the deterministic problem via sub-gradient descent. We prove that the optimal lottery can be directly computed from the deterministic optima that are computed along the iterations. We analyze the computational complexity of our algorithm and show that the worst-case complexity is orders of magnitude better than the one arising from a linear programming approach. We apply the method to two canonical problems with private information. First, we solve a principal-agent moral-hazard problem, demonstrating that our approach delivers substantial improvements in speed and scalability over traditional linear programming methods. Second, we study an optimal taxation problem with multidimensional hidden types, which was previously considered computationally challenging, and examine under which conditions the optimal tax schedule will involve lotteries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15997v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengfeng Shen, Felix K\"ubler, Yucheng Yang, Zhennan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Risk Sharing Among Many: Implementing a Subgame Perfect and Optimal Equilibrium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.04122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.04122v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Can a welfare-maximising risk-sharing rule be implemented in a large, decentralised community? We revisit the price-and-choose (P\&amp;C) mechanism of Echenique and N\'u\~nez (2025), in which players post price schedules sequentially, and the final player selects an allocation. While P\&amp;C implements every Pareto-optimal allocation when the choice set is finite, realistic risk-sharing problems involve an infinite continuum of feasible allocations. We extend P\&amp;C to such infinite menus, modelling each allocation as a probability distribution that redistributes an aggregate loss $X=\sum_i X_i$. Every feasible allocation is comonotone, yet comonotonicity alone is not efficient when agents maximise monetary utility. We prove that our extended mechanism still implements the allocation that maximises aggregate utility, even when players entertain heterogeneous, uniformly tight credal sets over the distribution of $X$. Finally, we pair P\&amp;C with a simple auction introduced by Echenique and N\'u\~nez (2025) that chooses the first mover, equalising surplus among participants. The result is a decentralised, enforcement-free procedure that achieves both optimal and fair risk sharing under a multiple-priors environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.04122v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michiko Ogaku</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Tale of Two Monopolies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.06763v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We apply marginal analysis \`a la Bulow and Roberts (1989) to characterize the revenue-maximizing selling mechanism for a multiproduct monopoly. Specifically, we derive the revenue change due to a price perturbation on any subset of bundles holding the prices of other bundles fixed. In an optimal mechanism, total revenue must not increase with any small price change for bundles with positive demand, nor with a small price decrease for bundles with zero demand. For any symmetric two-dimensional type distribution satisfying mild regularity conditions, the marginal analysis fully characterizes the optimal mechanism, whether the buyer's valuations are additive or exhibit complementarity or substitutability. For general type distributions, the analysis identifies which bundles must carry positive or zero demand and provides conditions under which randomization is necessary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.06763v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yi-Chun Chen, Zhengqing Gui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capturing Misalignment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17176v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce and formalize misalignment, a phenomenon of interactive environments perceived from an analyst's perspective where an agent holds beliefs about another agent's beliefs that do not correspond to the actual beliefs of the latter. We demonstrate that standard frameworks, such as type structures, fail to capture misalignment, necessitating new tools to analyze this phenomenon. To this end, we characterize misalignment through non-belief-closed state spaces and introduce agent-dependent type structures, which provide a flexible tool to understand the varying degrees of misalignment. Furthermore, we establish that appropriately adapted modal operators on agent-dependent type structures behave consistently with standard properties, enabling us to explore the implications of misalignment for interactive reasoning. Finally, we show how speculative trade can arise under misalignment, even when imposing the corresponding assumptions that rule out such trades in standard environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17176v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierfrancesco Guarino, Gabriel Ziegler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fuzzy Classification Aggregation for a Continuum of Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05297v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove that any optimal, independent, and zero unanimous fuzzy classification aggregation function of a continuum of individual classifications of $m\ge 3$ objects into $2\le p\le m$ types must be a weighted arithmetic mean.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05297v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zijun Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
