<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.TH updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH</link>
    <description>econ.TH updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 05:00:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Endogenous Poverty Traps in Continuous Time: A Signaling Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.22836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.22836v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper embeds a signaling friction into the continuous-time heterogeneous agent framework. A continuum of producers operate Cobb-Douglas technologies with regime-specific productivity $A_j \in \{A_L, A_H\}$. Stochastic arrival of signaling opportunities and skill obsolescence risk generate an optimal stopping problem -- when to pay a lump-sum cost $\phi$ to upgrade productivity -- whose solution yields an endogenous Skiba threshold $k^*$. Diminishing returns create a stable interior attractor in each regime; the signaling cost separates the two basins, producing a poverty trap that is an interior optimum rather than a corner solution. The stationary distribution exhibits Twin Peaks, but its decomposition by regime reveals that agents in three distinct states -- structurally trapped, waiting to signal, and successfully upgraded -- coexist at the same wealth levels with different consumption behavior and mobility prospects. Capital alone is therefore insufficient to identify an agent's position in the polarization dynamics. We show that the joint observation of a low marginal propensity to consume out of wealth and a high average propensity to consume -- a combination invisible to standard Euler equation tests -- is the diagnostic signature of the structural trap, distinguishing it from both liquidity constraints and transitory shocks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.22836v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Massimo Giannini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(Ab)using Indifference: Purification in Communication and Repeated Games</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.23098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.23098v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent papers in communication games construct equilibria by conditioning an agent's strategy on private, payoff-irrelevant information. I prove this is impossible in general games if there is any amount of realistic privacy in agents' preferences, generalizing previous results from cheap talk games to mediated cheap talk and communication with receiver commitment. Applying the result to repeated games with public+conditionally independent private monitoring, all equilibria without private randomization are perfect public equilibria, and non-trivial belief free equilibria are impossible. This result can be avoided if information is slightly correlated, or pay-off relevant. Due to undesirable properties of public perfect equilibria in some settings, I argue for further study of belief-based equilibria to understand equilibria of repeated games with noisy monitoring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.23098v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alistair Barton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clarification of `Algorithmic Collusion without Threats'</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.22232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.22232v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This brief note clarifies that the scenario described in Arunachaleswaran et al. (2025) -- titled `Algorithmic Collusion without Threats' -- is not one of collusion, but one where one player is behaving non-competitively and the other is behaving competitively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.22232v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason Hartline</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Endogenous Attention and the Spread of False News</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11024v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the impact of endogenous attention in a dynamic social media model. Each period, a user observes a random story and decides whether to share it. Users like sharing true and interesting stories, but identifying false stories requires costly attention. Depending on parameters, the system exhibits either a unique limit or strong path dependence. Endogenous attention responds to changes in false story credibility, so reducing credibility can boost their prevalence. Increases in the exogenous production rate of false stories can be amplified by users' sharing decisions. Increasing users' capacity to reach others amplifies both true and false stories; we identify conditions under which the net effect favors truth over falsehood.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11024v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tuval Danenberg, Drew Fudenberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Task assignment as dynamic incentives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.05338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.05338v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study repeated task assignment as an instrument for providing effort incentives. Unlike traditional incentive instruments, assignment of a task both determines who produces and provides incentives, and incentives for one worker spill over to others because assignment is exclusive. We show that optimal incentives uniquely require a strict and evolving priority ranking through which workers are assigned the task. This ranking implies that workers' average workloads differ even when they are symmetric in all payoff-relevant respects. We characterize how workforce size, monitoring, and working conditions shape the scope of optimal incentive provision and the resulting inequality among workers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.05338v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yonghang Ji, Allen Vong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Private From Whom? Minimal Information Leakage in Auctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.10349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.10349v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In many auctions, bidders may be reluctant to reveal private information to the auctioneer and other bidders. Among deterministic bilateral communication protocols, reducing what bidders learn requires increasing what the auctioneer learns. A protocol implementing a given social choice rule is on the Privacy Frontier if no alternative protocol reveals less to both bidders and the auctioneer. For first-price auctions, the descending protocol and the sealed-bid protocol are both on the Privacy Frontier. For second-price auctions, the ascending protocol and the ascending-join protocol of Haupt and Hitzig (2025) are both on the Privacy Frontier, but the sealed-bid protocol is not. We provide sufficient conditions for a protocol to be on the Privacy Frontier and devise alternative protocols on the Privacy Frontier for first-price auctions that allow the designer to flexibly trade off between privacy from bidders and the auctioneer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.10349v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Gao, Eric Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A multi-self model of self-punishment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01421v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the choice of a decision maker (DM) who harms herself, by maximizing in each menu some distortion of her true preference, in which the first i alternatives are moved, in reverse order, to the bottom. This pattern has no empirical power, but it allows to define a degree of self-punishment, which measures the extent of the denial of pleasure adopted by the DM. We characterize irrational choices displaying the lowest degree of self-punishment, and we fully identify the preferences that explain the DM's picks by a minimal denial of pleasure. These datasets account for some well known selection biases, such as second-best procedures, and the handicapped avoidance. Necessary and sufficient conditions for the estimation of the degree of self-punishment of a choice are singled out. Moreover the linear orders whose harmful distortions justify choice data are partially elicited. Finally, we offer a simple characterization of the choice behavior that exhibits the highest degree of self-punishment, and we show that this subclass comprises almost all choices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01421v5</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angelo Enrico Petralia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social Cost of Greenhouse Gases -- OPTiMEM and the Heat Conjecture(s)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.06085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.06085v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Despite well-meaning scenarios that propose global CO2 emissions will decline presented in every IPCC report since 1988, the trend of global CO2 increase continues without significant change. Even if any individual nation manages to flatten its emissions, what matters is the trajectory of the globe. Together the gulf between climate science and climate economics, plus the urgent need for alternative methods of estimation, provided the incentives for development of our Ocean-Heat-Content (OHC) Physics and Time Macro Economic Model (OPTiMEM) system.
  To link NOAA damages to climate required creating a carbon consumption model to drive a physics model of climate. How fast could carbon be burned and how much coal, oil and natural gas was reasonably available? A carbon model driving climate meant burning the carbon, and modelling how the earth heated up. We developed this using the most recent best greenhouse gas equations and production models for CO2, CH4, N2O, and halogenated gases. This developed an ocean heat content model for the globe. Each step is validated against Known carbon consumption, CO2, temperature, and ocean heat content. This allows a physics founded model of climate costs to be projected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.06085v4</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brian P. Hanley (Butterfly Sciences), Pieter Tans (Institute of Arctic and Alpine Research University of Colorado Boulder), Edward A. G. Schuur (Center for Ecosystem Science and Society Northern Arizona University), Geoffrey Gardiner (London Institute of Banking and Finance), Steve Keen (Institute for Strategy, Resilience &amp; Security, University College London), Adam Smith (Climate Central)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using OPTiMEM and the Heat Conjecture to Estimate Future Social Cost of Greenhouse Gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.03009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.03009v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present an entirely new physics founded approach to estimating the social cost of carbon (SCC). For this, we developed our Ocean-Heat-Content Physics and Time Macro Economic Model (OPTiMEM) to estimate future heat content (separately published). The heat conjecture assumes that weather damages curves are stochastically proportional to ocean heat increase. We model carbon combustion, validate to datasets for greenhouse gas (GHG), temperature, and ocean heat content (OHC). We show that the social cost of 4 GHGs: CO2, CH4, N2O and halogenated hydrocarbons, cannot be single values, but must be represented by a kind of economic phase space.
  We propose very long-term carbon bonds to implement real discounting. This obviates the Gordian knot of the descriptivist versus prescriptivist discount disagreement that is unsolvable. Implementing these bonds leads to a new monitoring metric: real-dollar spending and bond discount rates compared to SC-GHG cost with variation on the discount scale, where the discount has no relationship to the pure rate of time preference (PRTP).
  This heat conjecture is based on OPTiMEM. OPTiMEM initiates from a fossil fuel consumption function to produce CO2, with 18 scenarios implemented to provide the uncertainty range. We provide 1:N year loss risk models (1:10, 1:100, 1:1000) that government, engineers, and actuaries should find useful.
  A scenario implementing DICE family of models carbon and growth assumptions shows +18{\deg} C is breached by 2210 CE, and +110{\deg} C by 2300 CE -- both of which outcomes are obviously not compatible with the fairly rosy conclusions of DICE models.
  Concerns are raised about having enough low-cost fossil fuel for conversion to minimal CO$_2$ maximal energy return on energy invested (EROEI) power if nations wait too long, and low EROEI power is questioned because monetary value is dependent on energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.03009v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brian Hanley, Pieter Tans, Edward A. G. Schuur, Geoffrey Gardiner, Steve Keen, Adam Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transaction Ordering Auctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02055</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.02055v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study equilibrium investment into bidding and latency reduction for different sequencing policies. For a batch auction design, we observe that bidders shade bids according to the likelihood that competing bidders land in the current batch. Moreover, in equilibrium, in the ex-ante investment stage before the auction, bidders invest into latency until they make zero profit in expectation.
  We compare the batch auction design to continuous time bidding policies (time boost) and observe that (depending on the choice of parameters) they obtain similar revenue and welfare guarantees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.02055v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christoph Schlegel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Succinct Ambiguous Contracts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02592v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Real-world contracts are often ambiguous. While recent work by D\"utting, Feldman, Peretz, and Samuelson (EC 2023, Econometrica 2024) demonstrates that ambiguous contracts can yield large gains for the principal, their optimal solutions often require deploying an impractically large menu of contracts. This paper investigates \emph{succinct} ambiguous contracts, which are restricted to consist of at most $k$ classic contracts. By letting $k$ range from $1$ to $n-1$, this yields an interpolation between classic contracts ($k=1$) and unrestricted ambiguous contracts ($k=n-1$). This perspective enables important structural and algorithmic results. First, we establish a fundamental separability property: for any number of actions $n$ and any succinctness level $k$, computing an optimal $k$-ambiguous contract reduces to finding optimal classic contracts over a suitable partition of the actions, up to an additive balancing shift acting as a base payment. Second, we show bounds on the principal's loss from using a $k$-ambiguous rather than an unrestricted ambiguous contract, which uncover a striking discontinuity in the principal's utility regarding contract size: lacking even a single contract option may cause the principal's utility to drop sharply by a multiplicative factor of $2$, a bound we prove to be tight. Finally, we characterize the tractability frontier of the optimal $k$-ambiguous contract problem. Our separability result yields a poly-time algorithm whenever the number of partitions of $n-1$ actions into $k$ sets is polynomial, recovering and extending known results for classic and unrestricted ambiguous contracts. We complement this with a tight hardness result, showing that the problem is \textsf{NP}-hard whenever the number of partitions is super-polynomial. Moreover, when $k \approx n/3$, the problem is even hard to approximate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02592v2</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Duetting, Michal Feldman, Yarden Rashti</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
