<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.TH updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH</link>
    <description>econ.TH updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Feb 2026 02:36:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Theory of Network Games Part 1: Utility Representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16071v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We demonstrate that a ubiquitous feature of network games, bilateral strategic interactions, is equivalent to having player utilities that are additively separable across opponents. We distinguish two formal notions of bilateral strategic interactions. Opponent independence means that player i's preferences over opponent j's action do not depend on what other opponents do. Strategic independence means that how opponent j's choice influences i's preference between any two actions does not depend on what other opponents do. If i's preferences jointly satisfy both conditions, then we can represent her preferences over strategy profiles using an additively separable utility. If i's preferences satisfy only strategic independence, then we can still represent her preferences over just her own actions using an additively separable utility. Common utilities based on a linear aggregate of opponent actions satisfy strategic independence and are therefore strategically equivalent to additively separable utilities--in fact, we can assume a utility that is linear in opponent actions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16071v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joseph Root, Evan Sadler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equity in auction design with unit-demand agents and non-quasilinear preferences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16211</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16211v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a model of auction design where a seller is selling a set of objects to a set of agents who can be assigned no more than one object. Each agent's preference over (object, payment) pair need not be quasilinear. If the domain contains all classical preferences, we show that there is a unique mechanism, the minimum Walrasian equilibrium price (MWEP) mechanism, which is strategy-proof, individually rational, and satisfies equal treatment of equals, no-wastage (every object is allocated to some agent), and no-subsidy (no agent is subsidized). This provides an equity-based characterization of the MEWP mechanism, and complements the efficiency-based characterization of the MWEP mechanism known in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16211v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomoya Kazumura, Debasis Mishra, Shigehiro Serizawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolutionary Systems Thinking -- From Equilibrium Models to Open-Ended Adaptive Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15957</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15957v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Complex change is often described as "evolutionary" in economics, policy, and technology, yet most system dynamics models remain constrained to fixed state spaces and equilibrium-seeking behavior. This paper argues that evolutionary dynamics should be treated as a core system-thinking problem rather than as a biological metaphor. We introduce Stability-Driven Assembly (SDA) as a minimal, non-equilibrium framework in which stochastic interactions combined with differential persistence generate endogenous selection without genes, replication, or predefined fitness functions. In SDA, longer-lived patterns accumulate in the population, biasing future interactions and creating feedback between population composition and system dynamics. This feedback yields fitness-proportional sampling as an emergent property, realizing a natural genetic algorithm driven solely by stability. Using SDA, we demonstrate why equilibrium-constrained models, even when simulated numerically, cannot exhibit open-ended evolution: evolutionary systems require population-dependent, non-stationary dynamics in which structure and dynamics co-evolve. We conclude by discussing implications for system dynamics, economics, and policy modeling, and outline how agent-based and AI-enabled approaches may support evolutionary models capable of sustained novelty and structural emergence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15957v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Adler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convergence rates of random-order best-response dynamics in public good games on networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15986</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15986v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study convergence rates of random-order best-response dynamics in games on networks with linear best responses and strategic substitutes. Combining formal analysis with numerical simulations we identify phenomena that lead to slow convergence. One of the key such phenomena is convergence to stable strategy profiles in parts of the network neighboring sets of nodes which remain inactive until the dynamics is close to converging and then switch to activity, initiating convergence to profiles with a new set of active agents and possibly leading to another iteration of such behavior. We identify structural properties of graphs which make such phenomena more likely. These properties go beyond the spectrum of a graph, which we demonstrate analyzing convergence rates on co-spectral mates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15986v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wojciech Misiak, Marcin Dziubi\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stackelberg Equilibria in Monopoly Insurance Markets with Probability Weighting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.16401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.16401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study Stackelberg Equilibria (Bowley optima) in a monopolistic centralized sequential-move insurance market, with a profit-maximizing insurer who sets premia using a distortion premium principle, and a single policyholder who seeks to minimize a distortion risk measure. We show that equilibria are characterized as follows: In equilibrium, the optimal indemnity function exhibits a layer-type structure, providing full insurance over any loss layer on which the policyholder is more pessimistic than the insurer's pricing functional about tail losses; and no insurance coverage over loss layers on which the policyholder is less pessimistic than the insurer's pricing functional about tail losses. In equilibrium, the optimal pricing distortion function is determined by the policyholder's degree of risk aversion, whereby prices never exceed the policyholder's marginal willingness to insure tail losses. Moreover, we show that both the insurance coverage and the insurer's expected profit increase with the policyholder's degree of risk aversion. Additionally, and echoing recent work in the literature, we show that equilibrium contracts are Pareto efficient, but they do not induce a welfare gain to the policyholder. Conversely, any Pareto-optimal contract that leaves no welfare gain to the policyholder can be obtained as an equilibrium contract. Finally, we consider a few examples of interest that recover some existing results in the literature as special cases of our analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.16401v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.RM</category>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <category>q-fin.MF</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Andraos, Mario Ghossoub, Bin Li, Benxuan Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Playing it Safe: Actions Attractive to the Risk Averse</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.17517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.17517v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a way to compare actions in decision problems. One action is safer than another if the set of beliefs at which the decision-maker prefers the safer action expands as the decision-maker becomes more risk averse. We provide a full characterization of this relation, show that it is equivalent to robust conceptions of single-crossing and second-order stochastic dominance, and reveal that in monotone decision problems it totally orders the decision-maker's set of actions. We discuss applications to games, insurance, investment hedging, and security design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.17517v3</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marilyn Pease, Mark Whitmeyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Persuasion with Ambiguous Communication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05504v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We explore whether ambiguous communication can be beneficial to the sender in a persuasion problem, when the receiver (and possibly the sender) is ambiguity averse. Our analysis highlights the necessity of using a collection of experiments that form a splitting of an obedient experiment. Some experiments in the collection must be Pareto-ranked in that both players agree on their payoff ranking. If an optimal Bayesian persuasion experiment can be split in this way, then any not-too-ambiguity-averse sender as well as the receiver benefit. There are no benefits when the receiver has only two actions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05504v4</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyu Cheng, Peter Klibanoff, Sujoy Mukerji, Ludovic Renou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calibrated Mechanism Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17858v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study mechanism design when a designer repeatedly uses a fixed mechanism to interact with strategic agents who learn from observing their allocations. We introduce a static framework, calibrated mechanism design, requiring mechanisms to remain incentive compatible given the information they reveal about an underlying state through repeated use. In single-agent settings, we prove implementable outcomes correspond to two-stage mechanisms: the designer discloses information about the state, then commits to a state-independent allocation rule. This yields a tractable procedure to characterize calibrated mechanisms, combining information design and mechanism design. In private values environments, full transparency is optimal and correlation-based surplus extraction fails. We provide a microfoundation by showing calibrated mechanisms characterize exactly what is implementable when an infinitely patient agent repeatedly interacts with the same mechanism. Dynamic mechanisms that condition on histories expand implementable outcomes only by weakening incentive constraints, but not by enriching the designer's ability to obfuscate learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17858v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura Doval, Alex Smolin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Affirmative Action in India with Hierarchical Reservations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.09189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.09189v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: India implements the world's most complex affirmative action program through vertical and horizontal reservations. Although applicants can belong to at most one vertical category, they can qualify for multiple horizontal reservation categories simultaneously. We examine resource allocation problems in India, where horizontal reservations follow a hierarchical structure within a one-to-all horizontal matching framework. We introduce the hierarchical choice rule and show that it selects the most meritorious set of applicants. We thoroughly analyze the properties of the aggregate choice rule, which comprises hierarchical choice rules across all vertical categories. We show that the generalized deferred acceptance mechanism, when coupled with this aggregate choice rule, is the unique stable and strategy-proof mechanism that eliminates justified envy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.09189v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Orhan Ayg\"un, Bertan Turhan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
