<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.TH updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH</link>
    <description>econ.TH updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.TH" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 05:00:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Credible Nash Bargaining Solution for Bilateral Trading Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.09198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.09198v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study surplus division in network constrained bilateral matching markets with transferable utility. We introduce a new solution concept, the credible bargaining solution, which refines stability by requiring that, for each matched pair of buyer and seller, surplus be divided according to the Nash bargaining solution with respect to credible outside options, defined as their payoffs in some stable outcome of the submarket obtained by removing their link. We establish general properties of the credible bargaining solution, prove existence, and provide a complete characterization in the unit-surplus case based on the notion of essential links.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.09198v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kang Rong, Qianfeng Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On click-fraud under pro-rata revenue sharing rule</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.09573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.09573v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Click-fraud is commonly seen as a key vulnerability of pro-rata revenue sharing on music streaming platforms, whereas user-centric is largely immune. This paper develops a tractable non-cooperative model in which artists can purchase fraud activity that generates undetectable fake streams up to a technological limit. We show that pro-rata can be fraud-robust: when fraud technology is weak, honesty is a strict dominant strategy, and an efficient fraud-free equilibrium obtains. When fraud technology is strong, a unique fraud equilibrium arises, yet aggregate fake streams remain bounded. Although fraud is inefficient, the resulting redistribution may improve fairness in some cases. To mitigate fraud without abandoning pro-rata, we introduce a parametric weighted rule that interpolates between pro-rata and user-centric, and characterize parameter ranges that restore a fraud-free equilibrium under technology constraint. We also discuss implications of Spotify's modernized royalty system for fraud incentives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.09573v1</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A multi-self model of self-punishment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.01421</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.01421v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the choice of a decision maker (DM) who harms herself, by maximizing in each menu some distortion of her true preference, in which the first i alternatives are moved, in reverse order, to the bottom. This pattern has no empirical power, but it allows to define a degree of self-punishment, which measures the extent of the denial of pleasure adopted by the DM. We characterize irrational choices displaying the lowest degree of self-punishment, and we fully identify the preferences that explain the DM's picks by a minimal denial of pleasure. These datasets account for some well known selection biases, such as second-best procedures, and the handicapped avoidance. Necessary and sufficient conditions for the estimation of the degree of self-punishment of a choice are singled out. Moreover the linear orders whose harmful distortions justify choice data are partially elicited. Finally, we offer a simple characterization of the choice behavior that exhibits the highest degree of self-punishment, and we show that this subclass comprises almost all choices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.01421v2</guid>
      <category>econ.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angelo Enrico Petralia</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
