<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Gas permeability and mechanical properties of dust grain aggregates at hyper- and zero-gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Particle-particle and particle-gas processes significantly impact planetary precursors such as dust aggregates and planetesimals. We investigate gas permeability ($\kappa$) in 12 granular samples, mimicking planetesimal dust regoliths. Using parabolic flights, this study assesses how gravitational compression -- and lack thereof -- influences gas permeation, impacting the equilibrium state of low-gravity objects. Transitioning between micro- and hyper-gravity induces granular sedimentation dynamics, revealing collective dust-grain aerodynamics. Our experiments measure $\kappa$ across Knudsen number (Kn) ranges, reflecting transitional flow. Using mass and momentum conservation, we derive $\kappa$ and calculate pressure gradients within the granular matrix. Key findings: 1. As confinement pressure increases with gravitational load and mass flow, $\kappa$ and average pore space decrease. This implies that a planetesimal's unique dust-compaction history limits sub-surface volatile outflows. 2. The derived pressure gradient enables tensile strength determination for asteroid regolith simulants with cohesion. This offers a unique approach to studying dust-layer properties when suspended in confinement pressures comparable to the equilibrium state on planetesimals surfaces, which will be valuable for modelling their collisional evolution. 3. We observe a dynamical flow symmetry breaking when granular material moves against the pressure gradient. This occurs even at low Reynolds numbers, suggesting that Stokes numbers for drifting dust aggregates near the Stokes-Epstein transition require a drag force modification based on permeability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12631v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae1898</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Holly L. Capelo, Jean-David Bod\'enan, Martin Jutzi, Jonas K\"uhn, Romain Cerubini, Bernhard Jost, Linus St\"ockli, Stefano Spadaccia, Clemence Herny, Bastian Gundlach, G\"unter Kargl, Cl\'ement Surville, Lucio Mayer, Maria Sch\"onb\"achler, Nicolas Thomas, Antoine Pommerol</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An automated method for finding the most distant quasars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12770</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12770v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Upcoming surveys such as Euclid, the Vera C. Rubin Observatory's Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) and the Nancy Grace Roman Telescope (Roman) will detect hundreds of high-redshift (z &gt; 7) quasars, but distinguishing them from the billions of other sources in these catalogues represents a significant data analysis challenge. We address this problem by extending existing selection methods by using both i) Bayesian model comparison on measured fluxes and ii) a likelihood-based goodness-of-fit test on images, which are then combined using an Fbeta statistic. The result is an automated, reproduceable and objective high-redshift quasar selection pipeline. We test this on both simulations and real data from the cross-matched Sloan Digital Sky Survey (SDSS) and UKIRT Infrared Deep Sky Survey (UKIDSS) catalogues. On this cross-matched dataset we achieve an AUC score of up to 0.795 and an F3 score of up to 0.79, sufficient to be applied to the Euclid, LSST and Roman data when available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12770v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lena Lenz, Daniel J. Mortlock, Boris Leistedt, Rhys Barnett, Paul C. Hewett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The FAST Core Array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12826v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Five-hundred-meter Aperture Spherical Radio Telescope (FAST) Core Array is a proposed extension of FAST, integrating 24 secondary 40-m antennas implanted within 5 km of the FAST site. This original array design will combine the unprecedented sensitivity of FAST with a high angular resolution (4.3" at a frequency of 1.4 GHz), thereby exceeding the capabilities at similar frequencies of next-generation arrays such as the Square Kilometre Array Phase 1 or the next-generation Very Large Array. This article presents the technical specifications of the FAST Core Array, evaluates its potential relatively to existing radio telescope arrays, and describes its expected scientific prospects. The proposed array will be equipped with technologically advanced backend devices, such as real-time signal processing systems. A phased array feed receiver will be mounted on FAST to improve the survey efficiency of the FAST Core Array, whose broad frequency coverage and large field of view (FOV) will be essential to study transient cosmic phenomena such as fast radio bursts and gravitational wave events, to conduct surveys and resolve structures in neutral hydrogen galaxies, to monitor or detect pulsars, and to investigate exoplanetary systems. Finally, the FAST Core Array can strengthen China's major role in the global radio astronomy community, owing to a wide range of potential scientific applications from cosmology to exoplanet science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12826v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.61977/ati2024012 10.61977/ati2024012</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Peng Jiang, Rurong Chen, Hengqian Gan, Jinghai Sun, Boqin Zhu, Hui Li, Weiwei Zhu, Jingwen Wu, Xuelei Chen, Haiyan Zhang, Tao An</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Performance evaluation of the high-voltage CMOS active pixel sensor AstroPix for gamma-ray space telescopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12891</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12891v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: AstroPix is a novel monolithic high-voltage CMOS active pixel sensor proposed for next generation medium-energy gamma-ray observatories like the All-sky Medium Energy Gamma-ray Observatory eXplorer (AMEGO-X). For AMEGO-X AstroPix must maintain a power consumption of less than $1.5~\rm{mW/{cm}^2}$ while having a pixel pitch of up to $500~\rm{\mu m}$. We developed the second and third versions of AstroPix, namely AstroPix2 and AstroPix3. AstroPix2 and AstroPix3 exhibit power consumptions of $3.4~\rm{mW/{cm}^2}$ and $4.1~\rm{mW/{cm}^2}$, respectively. While AstroPix2 has a pixel pitch of $250~\rm{\mu m}$, AstroPix3 achieves the desired size for AMEGO-X with a pixel pitch of $500~\rm{\mu m}$. Performance evaluation of a single pixel in an AstroPix2 chip revealed a dynamic range from 13.9 keV to 59.5 keV, with the energy resolution meeting the AMEGO-X target value ($&lt;10\%$ (FWHM) at 60 keV). We performed energy calibration on most of the pixels in an AstroPix3 chip, yielding a mean energy resolution of 6.2 keV (FWHM) at 59.5 keV, with 44.4% of the pixels satisfying the target value. The dynamic range of AstroPix3 was assessed to span from 22.2 keV to 122.1 keV. The expansion of the depletion layer aligns with expectations in both AstroPix2 and AstroPix3. Furthermore, radiation tolerance testing was conducted on AstroPix. An AstroPix2 chip was subjected to an equivalent exposure of approximately 10 Gy from a high-intensity $\rm{^{60}Co}$ source. The chip was fully operational after irradiation although a decrease in gain by approximately 4% was observed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12891v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nima.2024.169762</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yusuke Suda, Regina Caputo, Amanda L. Steinhebel, Nicolas Striebig, Manoj Jadhav, Yasushi Fukazawa, Masaki Hashizume, Carolyn Kierans, Richard Leys, Jessica Metcalfe, Michela Negro, Ivan Peri\'c, Jeremy S. Perkins, Taylor Shin, Hiroyasu Tajima, Daniel Violette, Norito Nakano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Velocity Aberration Effect of the CSST Main Survey Camera</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12929v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we conducted simulations to find the geometric aberrations expected for images taken by the Main Survey Camera (MSC) of the Chinese Space Station Telescope (CSST) due to its motion. As anticipated by previous work, our findings indicate that the geometric distortion of light impacts the focal plane's apparent scale, with a more pronounced influence as the size of the focal plane increases. Our models suggest that the effect consistently influences the pixel scale in both the vertical and parallel directions. The apparent scale variation follows a sinusoidal distribution throughout one orbit period. Simulations reveal that the effect is particularly pronounced in the center of the Galaxy and gradually diminishes along the direction of ecliptic latitude. At low ecliptic latitudes, the total aberration leads to about 0.94 pixels offset (a 20-minute exposure) and 0.26 pixels offset (a 300-second exposure) at the edge of the field of view, respectively. Appropriate processings for the geometric effect during the CSST pre- and post-observation phases are presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12929v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1674-4527/ad7078</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hui-Mei Feng, Zi-Huang Cao, Man I Lam, Ran Li, Hao Tian, Xin Zhang, Peng Wei, Xin-Feng Li, Wei Wang, Hugh R. A. Jones, Mao-Yuan Liu, Chao Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The UK Submillimetre and Millimetre Astronomy Roadmap 2024</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12975v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this Roadmap, we present a vision for the future of submillimetre and millimetre astronomy in the United Kingdom over the next decade and beyond. This Roadmap has been developed in response to the recommendation of the Astronomy Advisory Panel (AAP) of the STFC in the AAP Astronomy Roadmap 2022. In order to develop our stragetic priorities and recommendations, we surveyed the UK submillimetre and millimetre community to determine their key priorities for both the near-term and long-term future of the field. We further performed detailed reviews of UK leadership in submillimetre/millimetre science and instrumentation. Our key strategic priorities are as follows: 1. The UK must be a key partner in the forthcoming AtLAST telescope, for which it is essential that the UK remains a key partner in the JCMT in the intermediate term. 2. The UK must maintain, and if possible enhance, access to ALMA and aim to lead parts of instrument development for ALMA2040. Our strategic priorities complement one another: AtLAST (a 50m single-dish telescope) and an upgraded ALMA (a large configurable interferometric array) would be in synergy, not competition, with one another. Both have identified and are working towards the same overarching science goals, and both are required in order to fully address these goals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12975v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Pattle, P. S. Barry, A. W. Blain, M. Booth, R. A. Booth, D. L. Clements, M. J. Currie, D. Eden, G. A. Fuller, M. Griffin, P. G. Huggard, J. D. Ilee, J. Karoly, Z. A. Khan, N. Klimovich, E. Kontar, P. Klaassen, A. J. Rigby, P. Scicluna, S. Serjeant, B. -K. Tan, D. Ward-Thompson, T. G. Williams, T. A. Davis, J. Greaves, R. Ivison, J. Marin, M. Matsuura, J. M. C. Rawlings, A. Saintonge, G. Savini, M. W. L. Smith, D. J. Taylor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A rapid multi-modal parameter estimation technique for LISA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12764v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA) will observe gravitational-wave signals from a wide range of sources, including massive black hole binaries. Although numerous techniques have been developed to perform Bayesian inference for LISA, they are often computationally expensive; analyses often take at least $\sim 1$ month on a single CPU, even when using accelerated techniques. Not only does this make it difficult to concurrently analyse more than one gravitational-wave signal, it also makes it challenging to rapidly produce parameter estimates for possible electromagnetic follow-up campaigns. simple-pe was recently developed to produce rapid parameter estimates for gravitational-wave signals observed with ground-based gravitational-wave detectors. In this work, we extend simple-pe to produce rapid parameter estimates for LISA sources, including the effects of higher order multipole moments. We show that simple-pe infers the source properties of massive black hole binaries in zero-noise at least $\sim 100\times$ faster than existing techniques; $\sim 12$ hours on a single CPU. We further demonstrate that simple-pe can be applied before existing Bayesian techniques to mitigate biases in multi-modal parameter estimation analyses of MBHBs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12764v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charlie Hoy, Connor Weaving, Laura K. Nuttall, Ian Harry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Checking the Empirical Relations with the Current Localized Fast Radio Bursts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12983v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Although fast radio bursts (FRBs) were discovered more than a decade ago, and they have been one of the active fields in astronomy and cosmology, their origins are still unknown. An interesting topic closely related to the origins of FRBs is their classifications. On the other hand, FRBs are actually a promising probe to study cosmology. In the literature, some new classifications of FRBs different from repeaters and non-repeaters were suggested, and some tight empirical relations have been found for them. In particular, Guo and Wei suggested to classify FRBs into the ones associated with old or young populations, which have also some new empirical relations. They also proposed to use one of the empirical relations without dispersion measure (DM) to calibrate FRBs as standard candles for cosmology. This shows the potential of the new classification and the empirical relations for FRBs. Nowadays, more than 50 FRBs have been well localized, and hence their redshifts $z$ are observationally known. Thus, it is time to check the empirical relations with the current localized FRBs. We find that many empirical relations still hold, and in particular the one used to calibrate FRBs as standard candles for cosmology stands firm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12983v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lin-Yu Li, Jing-Yi Jia, Da-Chun Qiang, Hao Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photofragmentation of Corannulene (C20H10) and Sumanene (C21H12) cations in gas phase and its Astrophysical implications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13072</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13072v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The aromatic infrared Bands (AIBs) dominate the mid-infrared spectra of many galactic and extragalactic sources. These AIBs are generally attributed to fluorescent emission from aromatic molecules. Unified efforts from experimentalists and theoreticians to assign these AIB features have recently gotten additional impetus with the launch of the James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) as the Mid-InfraRed Instrument (MIRI) delivers mid-IR spectrum with greatly increased sensitivity and spectral resolution. PAHs in space can exist in either neutral or ionic forms, absorb UV photons and undergo fragmentation, becoming a rich source of small hydrocarbons. This top-down mechanism of larger PAHs fragmenting into smaller species is of utmost importance in photo-dissociation regions (PDR) in space. In this work, we experimentally and theoretically investigate the photo-fragmentation pathways of two astronomically significant PAH cations - corannulene (C20H10) and sumanene (C21H12) that are structural motifs of fullerene C60, to understand their sequential fragmentation pathways. The photo-fragmentation experiments exhibit channels that are much different from planar PAHs. The breakdown of carbon skeleton is found to have different pathways for C20H10 and C21H12 because of the number and positioning of pentagon rings; yet the most abundant low mass cations produced by these two species are found to be similar. The low mass cations showcased in this work could be of interest for their astronomical detections. For completeness, the qualitative photo fragmentation behaviour of the dicationic corannulene and sumanene have also been experimented, but the potential energy surface of these dications are beyond the scope of this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13072v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1039/D4CP01247J</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Chem. Chem. Phys., (2024), 26, 19332-19348</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>P. Sundararajan, A. Candian, J. Kamer, H. Linnartz, A. G. G. M. Tielens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A GPU-accelerated semi-coherent hierarchical search for stellar-mass binary inspiral signals in LISA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13170v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Searching for gravitational waves from stellar-mass binary black holes with LISA remains a challenging open problem. Conventional template-bank approaches to the search are impossible due to the prohibitive number of templates that would be required. This paper continues the development of a hierarchical semi-coherent stochastic search, extending it to a full end-to-end pipeline that is then applied to multiple mock LISA data streams which include simulated noise. Particle swarm optimization is used as a stochastic search algorithm, tracking multiple maxima of a semi-coherent search statistic defined over source parameter space. The pipeline is accelerated by the use of graphical processing units (GPUs). No prior information from observations by ground-based detectors is used; this is necessary in order to provide advance warning of the merger. We find that the pipeline is able to detect sources with signal-to-noise ratios as low as $\rho\sim 17$, we demonstrate that these searches can directly seed coarse parameter estimation in cases where the search trigger is loud. An example of how the false-alarm probability can be estimated for this type of GW search is also included.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13170v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diganta Bandopadhyay, Christopher J. Moore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planar near-field measurements of specular and diffuse reflection of millimeter-wave absorbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.04664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.04664v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mitigating the far sidelobes of a wide field-of-view telescope is one of the critical issues for polarization observation of the cosmic microwave background. Since even small reflections of stray light at the millimeter-wave absorbers inside the telescope may create nonnegligible far sidelobes, we have developed a method to measure the reflectance of millimeter-wave absorbers, including diffuse reflections. By applying the planar near-field measurement method to the absorbers, we have enabled two-dimensional diffuse-reflection measurements, in addition to characterizing specular reflection. We have measured the reflectance of five samples (TK RAM Large and Small Tiles and Eccosorb AN-72, HR-10, and LS-22) at two angles of incidence in the frequency range from 70 GHz to 110 GHz. Compared with conventional horn-to-horn measurements, we obtained a consistent specular reflectance with a higher precision, less affected by standing waves. We have demonstrated that the angular response and diffuse-to-specular reflectance ratio differ among various materials. The measurements also imply that some absorbers may affect the polarization direction when reflecting the incident waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.04664v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1364/AO.531654</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Applied Optics, 63, 6544-6552 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Fumiya Miura (Department of Physics and Engineering, Graduate School of Science and Engineering, Yokohama National University, Institute of Space and Astronautical Science), Hayato Takakura (Institute of Space and Astronautical Science), Yutaro Sekimoto (Institute of Space and Astronautical Science), Junji Inatani (Institute of Space and Astronautical Science), Frederick Matsuda (Institute of Space and Astronautical Science), Shugo Oguri (Institute of Space and Astronautical Science), Shogo Nakamura (Department of Physics and Engineering, Graduate School of Science and Engineering, Yokohama National University)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
