<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 04:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Selective Dynamical Imaging of Interferometric Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08321v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent developments in very long baseline interferometry (VLBI) have made it possible for the Event Horizon Telescope (EHT) to resolve the innermost accretion flows of the largest supermassive black holes on the sky. The sparse nature of the EHT's $(u, v)$-coverage presents a challenge when attempting to resolve highly time-variable sources. We demonstrate that the changing (u, v)-coverage of the EHT can contain regions of time over the course of a single observation that facilitate dynamical imaging. These optimal time regions typically have projected baseline distributions that are approximately angularly isotropic and radially homogeneous. We derive a metric of coverage quality based on baseline isotropy and density that is capable of ranking array configurations by their ability to produce accurate dynamical reconstructions. We compare this metric to existing metrics in the literature and investigate their utility by performing dynamical reconstructions on synthetic data from simulated EHT observations of sources with simple orbital variability. We then use these results to make recommendations for imaging the 2017 EHT Sgr A* data set.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08321v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/ac6615</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJL, Volume 930, L18, 2022</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Joseph Farah, Peter Galison, Kazunori Akiyama, Katherine L. Bouman, Geoffrey C. Bower, Andrew Chael, Antonio Fuentes, Jos\'e L. G\'omez, Mareki Honma, Michael D. Johnson, Yutaro Kofuji, Daniel P. Marrone, Kotaro Moriyama, Ramesh Narayan, Dominic W. Pesce, Paul Tiede, Maciek Wielgus, Guang-Yao Zhao, The Event Horizon Telescope Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Participatory Science and Machine Learning Applied to Millions of Sources in the Hobby-Eberly Telescope Dark Energy Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08359v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We are merging a large participatory science effort with machine learning to enhance the Hobby-Eberly Telescope Dark Energy Experiment (HETDEX). Our overall goal is to remove false positives, allowing us to use lower signal-to-noise data and sources with low goodness-of-fit. With six million classifications through Dark Energy Explorers, we can confidently determine if a source is not real at over 94% confidence level when classified by at least ten individuals; this confidence level increases for higher signal-to-noise sources. To date, we have only been able to apply this direct analysis to 190,000 sources. The full sample of HETDEX will contain around 2-3M sources, including nearby galaxies ([O II] emitters), distant galaxies (Lyman-alpha emitters or LAEs), false positives, and contamination from instrument issues. We can accommodate this tenfold increase by using machine learning with visually-vetted samples from Dark Energy Explorers. We have already increased by over ten-fold in number of sources that have been visually vetted from our previous pilot study where we only had 14,000 visually vetted LAE candidates. This paper expands on the previous work increasing the visually-vetted sample from 14,000 to 190,000. In addition, using our currently visually-vetted sample, we generate a real or false positive classification for the full candidate sample of 1.2 million LAEs. We currently have approximately 17,000 volunteers from 159 countries around the world. Thus, we are applying participatory or citizen scientist analysis to our full HETDEX dataset, creating a free educational opportunity that requires no prior technical knowledge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08359v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad782c</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Lindsay R. House, Karl Gebhardt, Keely Finkelstein, Erin Mentuch Cooper, Dustin Davis, Daniel J. Farrow, Donald P. Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GRAVITY+ Wavefront Sensors: High-Contrast, Laser Guide Star, Adaptive Optics systems for the VLTI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08438v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the Wavefront Sensor units of the Gravity Plus Adaptive Optics (GPAO) system, which will equip all 8m class telescopes of the VLTI and is an instrumental part of the GRAVITY+ project. It includes two modules for each Wavefront Sensor unit: a Natural Guide Star sensor with high-order 40x40 Shack-Hartmann and a Laser Guide Star 30x30 sensor. The state-of-the-art AO correction will considerably improve the performance for interferometry, in particular high-contrast observations for NGS observations and all-sky coverage with LGS, which will be implemented for the first time on VLTI instruments. In the following, we give an overview of the Wavefront Sensor units system after completion of their integration and characterization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08438v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SPIE Proceedings, Yokohama 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G. Bourdarot, F. Eisenhauer, S. Yaz{\i}c{\i}, H. Feuchtgruber, J-B Le Bouquin, M. Hartl, C. Rau, J. Graf, N. More, E. Wieprecht, F. Haussmann, F. Widmann, D. Lutz, R. Genzel, F. Gonte, S. Oberti, J. Kolb, J. Woillez, H. Bonnet, D. Schuppe, A. Brara, J. Hartwig, A. Goldbrunner, C. Furchtsam, F. Soller, S. Czempiel, J. Eibl, D. Huber, S. Uysal, I. Treffler, H. Ozdemir, V. Gopinatha, P. Bourget, A. Berdeu, S. Gillessen, T. Ott, P. Berio, O. Boebion, F. Millour, R. Dembet, C. Edouard, T. Gomes, T. Shimizu, A. Drescher, M. Fabricius, J. Shangguan, S. Lagarde, S. Robbe-Dubois, F. Allouche, H. Nowacki, D. Defrere, P. J. V. Garcia, S. Hoenig, L. Kreidbergg, T. Paumard, C. Straubmeier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Method of Searching for Rotations of the Polarization Position Angle of Quasars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08674v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Observations of quasars show that the polarization position angle of the emission coming from them varies greatly over time, including periods called rotations during which the angle changes in an orderly manner. The study proposes a method for identifying such events and assessing their statistical significance. The operation of the method is demonstrated using the example of long-term polarimetric observations of the blazars CTA 102, 3C 454.3, and OT 081. During the analysis of light curves, 51 rotations of the polarization position angle were found and it was shown that for CTA 102 and 3C 454.3 the rotations are predominantly oriented in one direction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08674v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1134/S1990341323600394</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Astrophysical Bulletin, Volume 79, Issue 2, pp. 186-202, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S. S. Savchenko, D. A. Morozova, S. G. Jorstad, D. A. Blinov, G. A. Borman, A. A. Vasilyev, T. S. Grishina, A. V. Zhovtan, E. N. Kopatskaya, E. G. Larionova, I. S. Troitskiy, Yu. V. Troitskaya, E. V. Shishkina, E. A. Shkodkina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development of a Compton Imager Setup</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08822v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hard X-ray photons with energies in the range of hundreds of keV typically undergo Compton scattering when they are incident on a detector. In this process, an incident photon deposits a fraction of its energy at the point of incidence and continues onward with a change in direction that depends on the amount of energy deposited. By using a pair of detectors to detect the point of incidence and the direction of the scattered photon, we can calculate the scattering direction and angle. The position of a source in the sky can be reconstructed using many Compton photon pairs from a source. We demonstrate this principle in the laboratory by using a pair of Cadmium Zinc Telluride detectors sensitive in the energy range of 20-200 keV. The laboratory setup consists of the two detectors placed perpendicular to each other in a lead-lined box. The detectors are read out by a custom-programmed Xilinx PYNQ FPGA board, and data is then transferred to a PC. The detectors are first calibrated using lines from $^{241}\mathrm{Am}$, $^{155}\mathrm{Eu}$ and $^{133}\mathrm{Ba}$ sources. We irradiated the detectors with a collimated $^{133}\mathrm{Ba}$ source and identified Compton scattering events for the 356 keV line. We run a Compton reconstruction algorithm and correctly infer the location of the source in the detector frame. This comprises a successful technology demonstration for a Compton imaging camera in the Hard X-ray regime. We present the details of our setup, the data acquisition process, and software algorithms, and showcase our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08822v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anuraag Arya, Harmanjeet Singh Bilkhu, Sandeep Vishwakarma, Hrishikesh Belatikar, Varun Bhalerao, Abhijeet Ghodgaonkar, Jayprakash G. Koyande, Aditi Marathe, N. P. S. Mithun, Sanjoli Narang, Sudhanshu Nimbalkar, Pranav Page, Sourav Palit, Arpit Patel, Amit Shetye, Siddharth Tallur, Shriharsh Tendulkar, Santosh Vadawale, Gaurav Waratkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Radio Technosignature Search of TRAPPIST-1 with the Allen Telescope Array</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08313v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Planet-planet occultations (PPOs) occur when one exoplanet occults another exoplanet in the same system as seen from the Earth's vantage point. PPOs may provide a unique opportunity to observe radio "spillover" from extraterrestrial intelligences' (ETIs) radio transmissions or radar being transmitted from the further exoplanet towards the nearer one for the purposes of communication or scientific exploration. Planetary systems with many tightly packed, low-inclination planets, such as TRAPPIST-1, are predicted to have frequent PPOs. Here, the narrowband technosignature search code turboSETI was used in combination with the newly developed NbeamAnalysis filtering pipeline to analyze 28 hours of beamformed data taken with the Allen Telescope Array (ATA) during late October and early November 2022, from 0.9--9.3~GHz, targeting TRAPPIST-1. During this observing window, 7 possible PPO events were predicted using the NbodyGradient code. The filtering pipeline reduced the original list of 25 million candidate signals down to 6 million by rejecting signals that were not sky-localized and, from these, identified a final list of 11127 candidate signals above a power law cutoff designed to segregate signals by their attenuation and morphological similarity between beams. All signals were plotted for visual inspection, 2264 of which were found to occur during PPO windows. We report no detection of signals of non-human origin, with upper limits calculated for each PPO event exceeding EIRPs of 2.17--13.3 TW for minimally drifting signals and 40.8--421 TW in the maximally drifting case. This work constitutes the longest single-target radio SETI search of TRAPPIST-1 to date.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08313v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nick Tusay (Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics, The Pennsylvania State University, Center for Exoplanets and Habitable Worlds, Penn State Extraterrestrial Intelligence Center), Sofia Z. Sheikh (Penn State Extraterrestrial Intelligence Center, Breakthrough Listen, University of California, Berkeley, SETI Institute), Evan L. Sneed (Department of Earth &amp; Planetary Sciences, University of California, Riverside, Breakthrough Listen, University of California, Berkeley, Penn State Extraterrestrial Intelligence Center), Wael Farah (Breakthrough Listen, University of California, Berkeley, SETI Institute), Alexander W. Pollak (SETI Institute), Luigi F. Cruz (SETI Institute), Andrew Siemion (Breakthrough Listen, University of California, Berkeley, SETI Institute, Department of Astronomy, University of California, Berkeley), David R. DeBoer (Department of Astronomy, University of California, Berkeley), Jason T. Wright (Department of Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics, The Pennsylvania State University, Center for Exoplanets and Habitable Worlds, Penn State Extraterrestrial Intelligence Center)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Atacama Cosmology Telescope: Systematic Transient Search of Single Observation Maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08429v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We conduct a systematic search for astrophysical transients using data from the Atacama Cosmology Telescope (ACT). The data were taken from 2017 to 2022 in three frequency bands spanning 77 GHz to 277 GHz. In this paper we present a pipeline for transient detection using single observation maps where each pixel of a map contains one observation with an integration time of approximately four minutes. We find 34 transient events at 27 unique locations. All but two of the transients are associated with Galactic stars and exhibit a wide range of properties. We also detect an event coincident with the classical nova, YZ Ret and one event consistent with a flaring active galactic nucleus. We notably do not detect any reverse shock emission from gamma ray bursts, a non-detection which is in tension with current models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08429v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emily K. Biermann, Yaqiong Li, Sigurd Naess, Steve K. Choi, Susan E. Clark, Mark Devlin, Jo Dunkley, P. A. Gallardo, Yilun Guan, Allen Foster, Matthew Hasselfield, Carlos Herv\'ias-Caimapo, Matt Hilton, Adam D. Hincks, Anna Y. Q. Ho, John C. Hood II, Kevin M. Huffenberger, Arthur Kosowsky, Michael D. Niemack, John Orlowski-Scherer, Lyman Page, Bruce Partridge, Maria Salatino, Crist\'obal Sif\'on, Suzanne T. Staggs, Cristian Vargas, Edward J. Wollack</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimum Safe Distances for DE-STAR Space Lasers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08873v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The prospect of phased laser arrays in space has received considerable attention in recent years, with applications to both planetary defence and space exploration. The most detailed investigation conducted into such a design is that of the DE-STAR phased array, standing for $\textbf{D}$irected $\textbf{E}$nergy $\textbf{S}$ystems for $\textbf{T}$argeting of $\textbf{A}$steroids and explo$\textbf{R}$ation. DE-STAR is a square modular design which exploits the energy created by banks of solar cells in space to generate and amplify the power of a laser beam. A specific DE-STAR design is expressed as DE-STAR n, where 'n' (typically in the range 0 - 4) equates to the log to base 10 of the side, in metres, of a square bank of lasers. With a DE-STAR 4 structure (10 km $\times$ 10 km square) capable of generating a laser beam on the order of tens of gigawatts, clearly there is the potential for such an asset to be deployed as a weapon by targeting locations on Earth. This naturally leads to the question of what effective ways can this possible misuse be removed or at least mitigated, to ensure these powerful space lasers can only be used for their intended purpose, and never malevolent reasons. One solution would be to locate the DE-STAR far enough away so that the laser flux at Earth would be too low. Results indicate that given they should lie 1 au from the Sun, there are feasible locations for DE-STAR 0-2 arrays where there is no danger to Earth. For DE-STAR 4-5, such is their power, safety measures other than those considered here would have to be adopted. Positions in the Solar System where the DE-STAR lasers have no direct line-of-sight with Earth tend to be unstable, and would require regular corrections using an on-board propulsion system, or preferably using push-back from the laser itself.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08873v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Hibberd</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predicting High Magnification Events in Microlensed Quasars in the Era of LSST using Recurrent Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08999v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Upcoming wide field surveys such as the Rubin Observatory's Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) will monitor thousands of strongly lensed quasars over a 10-year period. Many of these monitored quasars will undergo high magnification events (HMEs) through microlensing as the accretion disk crosses a caustic, places of infinite magnification. Microlensing allows us to map the inner regions of the accretion disk as it crosses a caustic, even at large cosmological distances. The observational cadences of LSST are not ideal for probing the inner regions of the accretion disk, so there is a need to predict HMEs as early as possible to trigger high-cadence multi-band or spectroscopic follow-up observations. Here we simulate a diverse and realistic sample of 10-year quasar microlensing light curves to train a recurrent neural network (RNN) to predict HMEs before they occur by classifying the location of the peaks at each time step. This is the first deep learning approach to predict HMEs. We give estimates at how well we expect to predict HME peaks during LSST and benchmark how our metrics change with different cadence strategies. With LSST-like observations, we can predict approximately 55% of HME peaks corresponding to tens to hundreds per year and a false positive rate of around 20% compared to the number of HMEs. Our network can be continuously applied throughout the LSST survey, providing crucial alerts to optimize follow-up resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08999v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Fagin, Eric Paic, Favio Neira, Henry Best, Timo Anguita, Martin Millon, Matthew O'Dowd, Dominique Sluse, Georgios Vernardos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Theory Informed Priors for Bayesian Inference: A Case Study with Early Dark Energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.09029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.09029v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cosmological models are often motivated and formulated in the language of particle physics, using quantities such as the axion decay constant, but tested against data using ostensibly physical quantities, such as energy density ratios, assuming uniform priors on the latter. This approach neglects priors on the model from fundamental theory, including from particle physics and string theory, such as the preference for sub-Planckian axion decay constants. We introduce a novel approach to learning theory-informed priors for Bayesian inference using normalizing flows (NF), a flexible generative machine learning technique that generates priors on model parameters when analytic expressions are unavailable or difficult to compute. As a test case, we focus on early dark energy (EDE), a model designed to address the Hubble tension. Rather than using uniform priors on the $\textit{phenomenological}$ EDE parameters $f_{\rm EDE}$ and $z_c$, we train a NF on EDE cosmologies informed by theory expectations for axion masses and decay constants. Our method recovers known constraints in this representation while being $\sim 300,000$ times more efficient in terms of total CPU compute time. Applying our NF to $\textit{Planck}$ and BOSS data, we obtain the first theory-informed constraints on EDE, finding $f_{\rm EDE} \lesssim 0.02$ at $95\%$ confidence with an $H_0$ consistent with $\textit{Planck}$, but in $\sim 6\sigma$ tension with SH0ES. This yields the strongest constraints on EDE to date, additionally challenging its role in resolving the Hubble tension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.09029v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael W. Toomey, Mikhail M. Ivanov, Evan McDonough</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A New Parameterization for Finding Solutions for Microlensing Exoplanet Light Curves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.15502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.15502v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The gravitational microlensing method of discovering exoplanets and multi-star systems can produce degenerate solutions, some of which require in-depth analysis to uncover. We propose a new parameter space that can be used to sample potential solutions more efficiently and is more robust at finding all degenerate solutions. We identified two new parameters, k and h, that can be sampled in place of the mass ratios and separations of the systems under analysis to identify degenerate solutions. The parameter k is related to the size of the central caustic, $\Delta\xi_c$, while h is related to the distance of a point along the k contour from log(s)=0, where s is the projected planet-host separation. In this work, we present the characteristics of these parameters and the tests we conducted to prove their efficacy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.15502v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1538-3873/ad70d7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PASP 136 094401 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kylie E. Hall, Jennifer C. Yee, In-Gu Shin, Hongjing Yang, Jiyuan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>XAMI -- A Benchmark Dataset for Artefact Detection in XMM-Newton Optical Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17323v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Reflected or scattered light produce artefacts in astronomical observations that can negatively impact the scientific study. Hence, automated detection of these artefacts is highly beneficial, especially with the increasing amounts of data gathered. Machine learning methods are well-suited to this problem, but currently there is a lack of annotated data to train such approaches to detect artefacts in astronomical observations. In this work, we present a dataset of images from the XMM-Newton space telescope Optical Monitoring camera showing different types of artefacts. We hand-annotated a sample of 1000 images with artefacts which we use to train automated ML methods. We further demonstrate techniques tailored for accurate detection and masking of artefacts using instance segmentation. We adopt a hybrid approach, combining knowledge from both convolutional neural networks (CNNs) and transformer-based models and use their advantages in segmentation. The presented method and dataset will advance artefact detection in astronomical observations by providing a reproducible baseline. All code and data are made available (https://github.com/ESA-Datalabs/XAMI-model and https://github.com/ESA-Datalabs/XAMI-dataset).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17323v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Sep 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elisabeta-Iulia Dima, Pablo G\'omez, Sandor Kruk, Peter Kretschmar, Simon Rosen, C\u{a}lin-Adrian Popa</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
