<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 04:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Representation of a Noisy Transmission Line</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10908v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We analyse a lossy transmission line and the Johnson-Nyquist noise generated therein. A representation as a noisy two-port with a voltage and a current noise sources on one end of a noiseless two-port is given. An expression for the noise properties is given for an arbitrary temperature profile along the transmission line. Agreement is demonstrated between the general expression found here and special cases calculable using thermodynamics. This work is motivated by the REACH experiment to observe the global 21 cm signal for which modelling noise with exquisite precision is essential for a reliable calibration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10908v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Bucher (Universit\'e Paris Cit\'e/CNRS), Daniel Molnar (University of Cambridge)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPHEREx: NASA's Near-Infrared Spectrophotmetric All-Sky Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11017</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11017v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: SPHEREx, the Spectro-Photometer for the History of the Universe, Epoch of Reionization, and ices Explorer, is a NASA MIDEX mission planned for launch in 2024. SPHEREx will carry out the first all-sky spectral survey at wavelengths between 0.75 micron and 5 micron with spectral resolving power ~40 between 0.75 and 3.8 micron and ~120 between 3.8 and 5 micron At the end of its two-year mission, SPHEREx will provide 0.75-to-5 micron spectra of each 6.2"x6.2" pixel on the sky - 14 billion spectra in all. This paper updates an earlier description of SPHEREx presenting changes made during the mission's Preliminary Design Phase, including a discussion of instrument integration and test and a summary of the data processing, analysis, and distribution plans.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11017v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1117/12.2567224</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Proceedings Volume 11443, Space Telescopes and Instrumentation 2020: Optical, Infrared, and Millimeter Wave; 114430I (2020)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Brendan P. Crill, Michael Werner, Rachel Akeson, Matthew Ashby, Lindsey Bleem, James J. Bock, Sean Bryan, Jill Burnham, Joyce Byunh, Tzu-Ching Chang, Yi-Kuan Chiang, Walter Cook, Asantha Cooray, Andrew Davis, Olivier Dor\'e, C. Darren Dowell, Gregory Dubois-Felsmann, Tim Eifler, Andreas Faisst, Salman Habib, Chen Heinrich, Katrin Heitmann, Grigory Heaton, Christopher Hirata, Viktor Hristov, Howard Hui, Woong-Seob Jeong, Jae Hwan Kang, Branislav Kecman, J. Davy Kirkpatrick, Phillip M. Korngut, Elisabeth Krause, Bomee Lee, Carey Lisse, Daniel Masters, Philip Mauskopf, Gary Melnick, Hiromasa Miyasaka, Hooshang Nayyeri, Hien Nguyen, Karin \"Oberg, Steve Padin, Roberta Paladini, Milad Pourrahmani, Jeonghyun Pyo, Roger Smith, Yong-Seong Song, Teresa Symons, Harry Teplitz, Volker Tolls, Steve Unwin, Rogier Windhorst, Yujin Yang, Michael Zemcov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High fidelity adaptive mirror simulations with reduced order models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11088v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the design process of large adaptive mirrors numerical simulations represent the first step to evaluate the system design compliance in terms of performance, stability and robustness. For the next generation of Extremely Large Telescopes increased system dimensions and bandwidths lead to the need of modeling not only the deformable mirror alone, but also all the system supporting structure or even the full telescope. The capability to perform the simulations with an acceptable amount of time and computational resources is highly dependent on finding appropriate methods to reduce the size of the resulting dynamic models. In this paper we present a framework developed together with the company Microgate to create a reduced order structural model of a large adaptive mirror as a preprocessing step to the control system simulations. The reduced dynamic model is then combined with the remaining system components allowing to simulate the full adaptive mirror in a computationally efficient way. We analyze the feasibility of our reduced models for Microgate's prototype of the adaptive mirror of the Giant Magellan Telescope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11088v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernadett Stadler, Roberto Biasi, Mauro Manetti, Andreas Obereder, Ronny Ramlau, Matteo Tintori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust parameter estimation within minutes on gravitational wave signals from binary neutron star inspirals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11397v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The gravitational waves emitted by binary neutron star inspirals contain information on nuclear matter above saturation density. However, extracting this information and conducting parameter estimation remains a computationally challenging and expensive task. Wong et al. introduced Jim arXiv:2302.05333, a parameter estimation pipeline that combines relative binning and jax features such as hardware acceleration and automatic differentiation into a normalizing flow-enhanced sampler for gravitational waves from binary black hole (BBH) mergers. In this work, we extend the Jim framework to analyze gravitational wave signals from binary neutron stars (BNS) mergers with tidal effects included. We demonstrate that Jim can be used for full Bayesian parameter estimation of gravitational waves from BNS mergers within a few tens of minutes, which includes the training of the normalizing flow and computing the reference parameters for relative binning. For instance, Jim can analyze GW170817 in 26 minutes (33 minutes) of total wall time using the TaylorF2 (IMRPhenomD_NRTidalv2) waveform, and GW190425 in around 21 minutes for both waveforms. We highlight the importance of such an efficient parameter estimation pipeline for several science cases as well as its ecologically friendly implementation of gravitational wave parameter estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11397v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thibeau Wouters, Peter T. H. Pang, Tim Dietrich, Chris Van Den Broeck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Directional Filter Design and Simulation for Superconducting On-chip Filter-banks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11417v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many superconducting on-chip filter-banks suffer from poor coupling to the detectors behind each filter. This is a problem intrinsic to the commonly used half wavelength filter, which has a maximum theoretical coupling of 50 %. In this paper we introduce a phase coherent filter, called a directional filter, which has a theoretical coupling of 100 %. In order to to study and compare different types of filter-banks, we first analyze the measured filter frequency scatter, losses, and spectral resolution of a DESHIMA 2.0 filter-bank chip. Based on measured fabrication tolerances and losses, we adapt the input parameters for our circuit simulations, quantitatively reproducing the measurements. We find that the frequency scatter is caused by nanometer-scale line-width variations and that variances in the spectral resolution is caused by losses in the dielectric only. Finally, we include these realistic parameters in a full filter-bank model and simulate a wide range of spectral resolutions and oversampling values. For all cases the directional filter-bank has significantly higher coupling to the detectors than the half-wave resonator filter-bank. The directional filter eliminates the need to use oversampling as a method to improve the total efficiency, instead capturing nearly all the power remaining after dielectric losses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11417v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis H. Marting, Kenichi Karatsu, Akira Endo, Jochem J. A. Baselmans, Alejandro Pascual Laguna</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of Quasi-particle Relaxation in Strongly Disordered Superconductor Resonators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10785v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the quasi-particle (QP) relaxation of strongly disordered superconducting resonators under optical illumination at different bath temperatures with the Rothwarf and Taylor equations and the gap-broadening theory described by the Usadal equation. The analysis is validated with various single-photon responses of Titanium Nitride (TiN) microwave kinetic inductance detectors (MKIDs) under pulsed 405~nm laser illumination. The QP relaxation in TiN is dominated by QPs with energy below the energy gap smeared by the disorder, and its duration is still inversely proportional to the QP density. The QP lifetime versus temperature can be fitted. The relaxation of the resonator can be further modeled with QP diffusion. The fitted QP diffusion coefficient of TiN is significantly smaller than expected. Our result also shows a significant increase in QP generation efficiency as the bath temperature increases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10785v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie Hu, Jean-Marc Matin, Paul Nicaise, Faouzi Boussaha, Christine Chaumont, Michel Piat, Pham Viet Dung, Piercarlo Bonifacio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The first degree-scale starlight-polarization-based tomography map of the magnetized interstellar medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10821</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10821v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the first degree-scale tomography map of the dusty magnetized interstellar medium (ISM) from stellar polarimetry and distance measurements. We used the RoboPol polarimeter at Skinakas Observatory to conduct a survey of starlight polarization in a region of the sky of 4 square degrees. We propose a Bayesian method to decompose the stellar-polarization source field along the distance to invert the 3D volume occupied by the observed stars. We used it to obtain the first 3D map of the dusty magnetized ISM. Specifically, we produced a tomography map of the orientation of the plane-of-sky (POS) component of the magnetic field threading the diffuse, dusty regions responsible for the stellar polarization. For the targeted region centered on Galactic coordinates $(l,b) \approx (103.3^\circ, 22.3^\circ)$, we identified several ISM clouds. Most of the lines of sight intersect more than one cloud. A very nearby component was detected in the foreground of a dominant component from which most of the polarization signal comes. Farther clouds, with a distance of up to 2~kpc, were similarly detected. Some of them likely correspond to intermediate-velocity clouds seen in HI spectra in this region of the sky. We found that the orientation of the POS component of the magnetic field changes along distance for most of the lines of sight. Our study demonstrates that starlight polarization data coupled to distance measures have the power to reveal the great complexity of the dusty magnetized ISM in 3D and, in particular, to provide local measurements of the POS component of the magnetic field. This demonstrates that the inversion of large data volumes, as expected from the PASIPHAE survey, will provide the necessary means to move forward in the modeling of the Galactic magnetic field and of the dusty magnetized ISM as a contaminant in observations of the cosmic microwave background polarization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10821v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202349015</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>V. Pelgrims, N. Mandarakas, R. Skalidis, K. Tassis, G. V. Panopoulou, V. Pavlidou, D. Blinov, S. Kiehlmann, S. E. Clark, B. S. Hensley, S. Romanopoulos, A. Basyrov, H. K. Eriksen, M. Falalaki, T. Ghosh, E. Gjerl{\o}w, J. A. Kypriotakis, S. Maharana, A. Papadaki, T. J. Pearson, S. B. Potter, A. N. Ramaprakash, A. C. S. Readhead, I. K. Wehus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Micro-arcsecond Astrometry Technology: Detector and Field Distortion Calibration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.08129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.08129v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Microarcsecond (uas) astrometry is an indispensable technique to detect earth-like exoplanets, fully characterize exoplanetary orbits, and measure their masses --information critical for assessing their habitability. Highly accurate astrometric measurements can also probe the nature of dark matter, the early universe, black holes, and neutron stars, thus providing unique data for new astrophysics. This paper presents technologies of calibrating detectors and field distortions for achieving narrow field uas relative astrometry with a focal plane array detector on a 6 m telescope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.08129v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1538-3873/ace3f4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PASP 135:074502 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michael Shao, Chengxing Zhai, Bijan Nemati, Inseob Hahn, Russell Trahan, Slava G. Turyshev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of a Far-Infrared Kinetic Inductance Detector Prototype for PRIMA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.03586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.03586v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The PRobe far-Infrared Mission for Astrophysics (PRIMA) is under study as a potential far-IR space mission, featuring actively cooled optics, and both imaging and spectroscopic instrumentation. To fully take advantage of the low background afforded by a cold telescope, spectroscopy with PRIMA requires detectors with a noise equivalent power (NEP) better than $1 \times 10^{-19}$ W Hz$^{-1/2}$. To meet this goal we are developing large format arrays of kinetic inductance detectors (KIDs) to work across the $25-250$ micron range. Here we present the design and characterization of a single pixel prototype detector optimized for $210$ micron. The KID consists of a lens-coupled aluminum inductor-absorber connected to a niobium interdigitated capacitor to form a 2 GHz resonator. We have fabricated a small array with 28 KIDs, and we measure the performance of one of these detectors with an optical loading in the $0.01 - 300$ aW range. At low loading the detector achieves an NEP of $9\times10^{-20}$ W Hz$^{-1/2}$ at a 10 Hz readout frequency, and the lens-absorber system achieves a good optical efficiency. An extrapolation of these measurements suggest this detector may remain photon noise limited at up to 20 fW of loading, offering a high dynamic range for PRIMA observations of bright astronomical sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.03586v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven Hailey-Dunsheath, Sven van Berkel, Andrew E. Beyer, Logan Foote, Reinier M. J. Janssen, Henry G. LeDuc, Pierre M. Echternach, Charles M. Bradford, Jochem J. A. Baselmans, Shahab Dabironezare, Peter K. Day, Nicholas F. Cothard, Jason Glenn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Basic Iterative Deconvolution: A fast instrumental point-spread function deconvolution method that corrects for light that is scattered out of the field of view of a detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.11784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.11784v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A point-spread function describes the optics of an imaging system and can be used to correct collected images for instrumental effects. The state of the art for deconvolving images with the point-spread function is the Richardson-Lucy algorithm; however, despite its high fidelity, it is slow and cannot account for light scattered out of the field of view of the detector. We reinstate the Basic Iterative Deconvolution (BID) algorithm, a deconvolution algorithm that considers photons scattered out of the field of view of the detector, and extend it for image subregion deconvolutions. Its runtime is 1.8 to 7.1 faster than the Richardson-Lucy algorithm for 4096 x 4096 pixels images and up to an additional factor of 150 for subregions of 250 x 250 pixels. We test the extended BID algorithm for solar images taken by the Atmospheric Imaging Assembly (AIA), and find that the deviations between the reconstructed intensities of BID and the Richardson-Lucy algorithm are smaller than 1%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.11784v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Johann Hofmeister</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CiaoCiao WFS: sensing phase discontinuities at the ELT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.12898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.12898v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The upcoming extremely large telescopes will have to deal with the so-called ''pupil fragmentation'' effect: for what concerns the Extremely Large Telescope (ELT), the presence of thick spider legs supporting the secondary mirror may induce unseen phase discontinuities across the pupil sectors that could limit the performance of the adaptive optics correction. In this context, we propose a wavefront sensor (WFS), the CiaoCiao WFS, consisting in a rotational shearing interferometer to sense phase differences between the pupil sectors. In this work, we present the CiaoCiao WFS concept and the first analyses carried out through numerical simulations. In particular, we analyze the performance of such a wavefront sensor in case the phase discontinuities are induced by low-wind effect during observations with the Multiconjugate adaptive Optics Relay For ELT Observations (MORFEO).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.12898v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Carl\`a, L. Busoni, S. Esposito, G. Agapito, R. Holzl\"ohner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fabrication and characterization of optical filters from polymeric aerogels loaded with diamond scattering particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.16364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.16364v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We have developed a suite of infrared-blocking filters made by embedding diamond scattering particles in a polyimide aerogel substrate. We demonstrate the ability to tune the spectral performance of the filters based on both the composition of the base aerogel material and the properties of the scattering particles. We summarize the fabrication, optical modeling, and characterization of these filters. We investigate two polyimide base aerogel formulations and the effects of loading them with diamond scattering particles of varying sizes and relative densities. We describe a model for the filters' behavior using a combination of Maxwell Garnett and Mie Scattering techniques. We present optical characterization results for diamond-loaded aerogel filters with cutoff frequencies (50% transmittance) ranging between 2.5 and 15 THz, and confirm that the measured spectral performance is in agreement with our optical models. We also measure the filters' refractive index in the microwave and report findings in agreement with Maxwell Garnett model predictions (typically n &lt; 1.08).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.16364v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alyssa Barlis, Haiquan Guo, Kyle Helson, Charles Bennett, Yan Yan Chan, Tobias Marriage, Manuel Quijada, Ariel Tokarz, Stephanie Vivod, Edward Wollack, Thomas Essinger-Hileman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limiting noise and outliers in the MICROSCOPE space test of the weak equivalence principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.06400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.06400v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The MICROSCOPE space mission has tested the weak equivalence principle finding no violation to about 1e-15, about two orders of magnitude better than on the ground. We review this result looking for lessons for the future. The acceleration difference of the falling bodies is limited by random thermal noise attributed to losses in the tiny gold wire which connects each of them to the enclosing cage. Our analysis reveals anomalies which are inexplicable within the current best knowledge of such noise. The anomalies may be due to a fluctuating sub-microVolt potential caused by electric charge patches on the surface of the test bodies and the electrodes coupled to large acceleration/voltage biases. Since the acceleration difference is derived from the individual measurements of each test body, it depends upon their arbitrarily defined zero, and this causes the bias. The measurement data show a large number of outliers, acceleration spikes (glitches) induced by thermal stress from the Earth and the Sun on the insulating blankets of the spacecraft. They occur at the synodic frequency relative to Earth (also the frequency of a violation signal) and the Sun, their harmonics and their difference. Outliers are removed and the ensuing gaps (up to 35%, 40% of the data) are filled with artificial data. However, gaps and artificial data retain memory of the outliers they have replaced and may therefore mimic a violation signal or cancel an effect (signal or systematic). An existing alternative approach relying solely on measured data would make the result of the experiment fully robust and unquestionable. A correct model of the stiffness of the wire, the presence of a fluctuating patch potential noise with the same frequency dependence as thermal noise from internal damping, as well as an insulation that does not give rise to glitches, were all anticipated by the GOCE gravity mission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.06400v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna M. Nobili, Alberto Anselmi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latent Stochastic Differential Equations for Modeling Quasar Variability and Inferring Black Hole Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.04277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.04277v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quasars are bright and unobscured active galactic nuclei (AGN) thought to be powered by the accretion of matter around supermassive black holes at the centers of galaxies. The temporal variability of a quasar's brightness contains valuable information about its physical properties. The UV/optical variability is thought to be a stochastic process, often represented as a damped random walk described by a stochastic differential equation (SDE). Upcoming wide-field telescopes such as the Rubin Observatory Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST) are expected to observe tens of millions of AGN in multiple filters over a ten year period, so there is a need for efficient and automated modeling techniques that can handle the large volume of data. Latent SDEs are machine learning models well suited for modeling quasar variability, as they can explicitly capture the underlying stochastic dynamics. In this work, we adapt latent SDEs to jointly reconstruct multivariate quasar light curves and infer their physical properties such as the black hole mass, inclination angle, and temperature slope. Our model is trained on realistic simulations of LSST ten year quasar light curves, and we demonstrate its ability to reconstruct quasar light curves even in the presence of long seasonal gaps and irregular sampling across different bands, outperforming a multioutput Gaussian process regression baseline. Our method has the potential to provide a deeper understanding of the physical properties of quasars and is applicable to a wide range of other multivariate time series with missing data and irregular sampling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.04277v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/ad2988</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>The Astrophysical Journal, Volume 965, Number 2, April 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Fagin, Ji Won Park, Henry Best, James Hung-Hsu Chan, K. E Saavik Ford, Matthew J. Graham, V. Ashley Villar, Shirley Ho, Matthew O'Dowd</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Methods for Incorporating Model Uncertainty into Exoplanet Atmospheric Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.03713v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A key goal of exoplanet spectroscopy is to measure atmospheric properties, such as abundances of chemical species, in order to connect them to our understanding of atmospheric physics and planet formation. In this new era of high-quality JWST data, it is paramount that these measurement methods are robust. When comparing atmospheric models to observations, multiple candidate models may produce reasonable fits to the data. Typically, conclusions are reached by selecting the best-performing model according to some metric. This ignores model uncertainty in favour of specific model assumptions, potentially leading to measured atmospheric properties that are overconfident and/or incorrect. In this paper, we compare three ensemble methods for addressing model uncertainty by combining posterior distributions from multiple analyses: Bayesian model averaging, a variant of Bayesian model averaging using leave-one-out predictive densities, and stacking of predictive distributions. We demonstrate these methods by fitting the HST+Spitzer transmission spectrum of the hot Jupiter HD 209458b using models with different cloud and haze prescriptions. All of our ensemble methods lead to uncertainties on retrieved parameters that are larger, but more realistic, and consistent with physical and chemical expectations. Since they have not typically accounted for model uncertainty, uncertainties of retrieved parameters from HST spectra have likely been underreported. We recommend stacking as the most robust model combination method. Our methods can be used to combine results from independent retrieval codes, and from different models within one code. They are also widely applicable to other exoplanet analysis processes, such as combining results from different data reductions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.03713v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew C. Nixon, Luis Welbanks, Peter McGill, Eliza M. -R. Kempton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital Polarimetric Tomography of a Flare Near the Sagittarius A* Supermassive Black Hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07687v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The interaction between the supermassive black hole at the center of the Milky Way, Sagittarius A*, and its accretion disk occasionally produces high-energy flares seen in X-ray, infrared, and radio. One proposed mechanism that produces flares is the formation of compact, bright regions that appear within the accretion disk and close to the event horizon. Understanding these flares provides a window into accretion processes. Although sophisticated simulations predict the formation of these flares, their structure has yet to be recovered by observations. Here we show the first three-dimensional (3D) reconstruction of an emission flare recovered from ALMA light curves observed on April 11, 2017. Our recovery shows compact, bright regions at a distance of roughly six times the event horizon. Moreover, it suggests a clockwise rotation in a low-inclination orbital plane, consistent with prior studies by GRAVITY and EHT. To recover this emission structure, we solve an ill-posed tomography problem by integrating a neural 3D representation with a gravitational model for black holes. Although the recovery is subject to, and sometimes sensitive to, the model assumptions, under physically motivated choices, our results are stable, and our approach is successful on simulated data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07687v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aviad Levis, Andrew A. Chael, Katherine L. Bouman, Maciek Wielgus, Pratul P. Srinivasan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precise Cosmological Constraints from BOSS Galaxy Clustering with a Simulation-Based Emulator of the Wavelet Scattering Transform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.16116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.16116v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We perform a reanalysis of the BOSS CMASS DR12 galaxy dataset using a simulation-based emulator for the Wavelet Scattering Transform (WST) coefficients. Moving beyond our previous works, which laid the foundation for the first galaxy clustering application of this estimator, we construct a neural net-based emulator for the cosmological dependence of the WST coefficients and the 2-point correlation function multipoles, trained from the state-of-the-art suite of \textsc{AbacusSummit} simulations combined with a flexible Halo Occupation Distribution (HOD) galaxy model. In order to confirm the accuracy of our pipeline, we subject it to a series of thorough internal and external mock parameter recovery tests, before applying it to reanalyze the CMASS observations in the redshift range $0.46&lt;z&lt;0.57$. We find that a joint WST + 2-point correlation function likelihood analysis allows us to obtain marginalized 1$\sigma$ errors on the $\Lambda$CDM parameters that are tighter by a factor of $2.5-6$, compared to the 2-point correlation function, and by a factor of $1.4-2.5$ compared to the WST-only results. This corresponds to a competitive $0.9\%$, $2.3\%$ and $1\%$ level of determination for parameters $\omega_c$, $\sigma_8$ $\&amp;$ $n_s$, respectively, and also to a $0.7\%$ $\&amp;$ $2.5 \%$ constraint on derived parameters h and $f(z)\sigma_8(z)$, in agreement with the \textit{Planck} 2018 results. Our results reaffirm the constraining power of the WST and highlight the exciting prospect of employing higher-order statistics in order to fully exploit the power of upcoming Stage-IV spectroscopic observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.16116v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georgios Valogiannis, Sihan Yuan, Cora Dvorkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Bayesian Approach to Strong Lens Finding in the Era of Wide-area Surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.07455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.07455v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The arrival of the Vera C. Rubin Observatory's Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST), Euclid-Wide and Roman wide area sensitive surveys will herald a new era in strong lens science in which the number of strong lenses known is expected to rise from $\mathcal{O}(10^3)$ to $\mathcal{O}(10^5)$. However, current lens-finding methods still require time-consuming follow-up visual inspection by strong-lens experts to remove false positives which is only set to increase with these surveys. In this work we demonstrate a range of methods to produce calibrated probabilities to help determine the veracity of any given lens candidate. To do this we use the classifications from citizen science and multiple neural networks for galaxies selected from the Hyper Suprime-Cam (HSC) survey. Our methodology is not restricted to particular classifier types and could be applied to any strong lens classifier which produces quantitative scores. Using these calibrated probabilities, we generate an ensemble classifier, combining citizen science and neural network lens finders. We find such an ensemble can provide improved classification over the individual classifiers. We find a false positive rate of $10^{-3}$ can be achieved with a completeness of $46\%$, compared to $34\%$ for the best individual classifier. Given the large number of galaxy-galaxy strong lenses anticipated in LSST, such improvement would still produce significant numbers of false positives, in which case using calibrated probabilities will be essential for population analysis of large populations of lenses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.07455v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae875</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Philip Holloway, Philip J. Marshall, Aprajita Verma, Anupreeta More, Raoul Ca\~nameras, Anton T. Jaelani, Yuichiro Ishida, Kenneth C. Wong</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
