<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 04:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 01 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Study of bound and resonant states of NS molecule in the R-matrix approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19298v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The bound and resonance states along with corresponding autoionization widths for nitrogen sulphide (NS) molecule are determined using electron NS$^+$ cation scattering calculations. The calculations are performed for $^2{\Sigma}^+$, $^2{\Pi}$ and $^2\Delta$ total symmetries using the ab initio R-matrix method for both bound and continuum states. Calculations are performed on a grid of 106 points for internuclear separations between 1.32 and 3 $\AA$. The resonance states yield dissociative potential curves which, when considered together with their widths, provide input for models of different electron-cation collision processes including dissociative recombination, and rotational and vibrational excitation. Curves and couplings which will lead directly to dissociative recombination are identified.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19298v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6455/ac9cae</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. B: At. Mol. Opt. Phys. 55 (2022) 235202 (9pp)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>F. Iacob, T. Meltzer, J. Zs. Mezei, I. F. Schneider, J. Tennyson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissociative recombination of the CH$^+$ molecular ion at low energy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19302v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The reactive collisions of the CH$^+$ molecular ion with electrons is studied in the framework of the multichannel quantum defect theory, taking into account the contribution of the core-excited Rydberg states. In addition to the $X^1\Sigma^+$ ground state of the ion, we also consider the contribution to the dynamics of the $a^3\Pi$ and $A^1\Pi$ excited states of CH$^+$. Our results - in the case of the dissociative recombination in good agreement with the storage ring measurements - rely on decisive improvements - complete account of the ionisation channels and accurate evaluation of the reaction matrix - of a previously used model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19302v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6455/aab937</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. B: At. Mol. Opt. Phys. 51 (2018) 104002 (8pp)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>K. Chakrabarti, J. Zs Mezei, O. Motapon, A. Faure, O. Dulieu, K. Hassouni, I. F. Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DARWIN/XLZD: a future xenon observatory for dark matter and other rare interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19524v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The DARWIN/XLZD experiment is a next-generation dark matter detector with a multi-ten-ton liquid xenon time projection chamber at its core. Its principal goal will be to explore the experimentally accessible parameter space for Weakly Interacting Massive Particles (WIMPs) in a wide mass-range, until interactions of astrophysical neutrinos will become an irreducible background. The prompt scintillation light and the charge signals induced by particle interactions in the liquid xenon target will be observed by VUV-sensitive, ultra-low background photosensors. Besides its excellent sensitivity to WIMPs with masses above $\sim$5\,GeV, such a detector with its large mass, low-energy threshold and ultra-low background level will also be sensitive to other rare interactions, and in particular also to bosonic dark matter candidates with masses at the keV-scale. We present the detector concept, discuss the main sources of backgrounds, the technological challenges and some of the ongoing detector design and R&amp;D efforts, as well as the large-scale demonstrators. We end by discussing the sensitivity to particle dark matter interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19524v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laura Baudis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acceptance Tests of more than 10 000 Photomultiplier Tubes for the multi-PMT Digital Optical Modules of the IceCube Upgrade</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19589v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: More than 10,000 photomultiplier tubes (PMTs) with a diameter of 80 mm will be installed in multi-PMT Digital Optical Modules (mDOMs) of the IceCube Upgrade. These have been tested and pre-calibrated at two sites. A throughput of more than 1000 PMTs per week with both sites was achieved with a modular design of the testing facilities and highly automated testing procedures. The testing facilities can easily be adapted to other PMTs, such that they can, e.g., be re-used for testing the PMTs for IceCube-Gen2. Single photoelectron response, high voltage dependence, time resolution, prepulse, late pulse, afterpulse probabilities, and dark rates were measured for each PMT. We describe the design of the testing facilities, the testing procedures, and the results of the acceptance tests.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19589v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Abbasi, M. Ackermann, J. Adams, S. K. Agarwalla, J. A. Aguilar, M. Ahlers, J. M. Alameddine, N. M. Amin, K. Andeen, C. Arg\"uelles, Y. Ashida, S. Athanasiadou, L. Ausborm, S. N. Axani, X. Bai, A. Balagopal V., M. Baricevic, S. W. Barwick, S. Bash, V. Basu, R. Bay, J. J. Beatty, J. Becker Tjus, J. Beise, C. Bellenghi, C. Benning, S. BenZvi, D. Berley, E. Bernardini, D. Z. Besson, E. Blaufuss, L. Bloom, S. Blot, F. Bontempo, J. Y. Book Motzkin, C. Boscolo Meneguolo, S. B\"oser, O. Botner, J. B\"ottcher, J. Braun, B. Brinson, J. Brostean-Kaiser, L. Brusa, R. T. Burley, D. Butterfield, M. A. Campana, I. Caracas, K. Carloni, J. Carpio, S. Chattopadhyay, N. Chau, Z. Chen, D. Chirkin, S. Choi, B. A. Clark, A. Coleman, G. H. Collin, A. Connolly, J. M. Conrad, P. Coppin, R. Corley, P. Correa, D. F. Cowen, P. Dave, C. De Clercq, J. J. DeLaunay, D. Delgado, S. Deng, A. Desai, P. Desiati, K. D. de Vries, G. de Wasseige, T. DeYoung, A. Diaz, J. C. D\'iaz-V\'elez, P. Dierichs, M. Dittmer, A. Domi, L. Draper, H. Dujmovic, K. Dutta, M. A. DuVernois, T. Ehrhardt, L. Eidenschink, A. Eimer, P. Eller, E. Ellinger, S. El Mentawi, D. Els\"asser, R. Engel, H. Erpenbeck, J. Evans, P. A. Evenson, K. L. Fan, K. Fang, K. Farrag, A. R. Fazely, A. Fedynitch, N. Feigl, S. Fiedlschuster, C. Finley, L. Fischer, D. Fox, A. Franckowiak, S. Fukami, P. F\"urst, J. Gallagher, E. Ganster, A. Garcia, M. Garcia, G. Garg, E. Genton, L. Gerhardt, A. Ghadimi, C. Girard-Carillo, C. Glaser, T. Gl\"usenkamp, J. G. Gonzalez, S. Goswami, A. Granados, D. Grant, S. J. Gray, O. Gries, S. Griffin, S. Griswold, K. M. Groth, C. G\"unther, P. Gutjahr, C. Ha, C. Haack, A. Hallgren, L. Halve, F. Halzen, H. Hamdaoui, M. Ha Minh, M. Handt, K. Hanson, J. Hardin, A. A. Harnisch, P. Hatch, A. Haungs, J. H\"au{\ss}ler, K. Helbing, J. Hellrung, J. Hermannsgabner, L. Heuermann, N. Heyer, S. Hickford, A. Hidvegi, C. Hill, G. C. Hill, K. D. Hoffman, S. Hori, K. Hoshina, M. Hostert, W. Hou, T. Huber, K. Hultqvist, M. H\"unnefeld, R. Hussain, K. Hymon, A. Ishihara, W. Iwakiri, M. Jacquart, O. Janik, M. Jansson, G. S. Japaridze, M. Jeong, M. Jin, B. J. P. Jones, N. Kamp, D. Kang, W. Kang, X. Kang, A. Kappes, D. Kappesser, L. Kardum, T. Karg, M. Karl, A. Karle, A. Katil, U. Katz, M. Kauer, J. L. Kelley, M. Khanal, A. Khatee Zathul, A. Kheirandish, J. Kiryluk, S. R. Klein, A. Kochocki, R. Koirala, H. Kolanoski, T. Kontrimas, L. K\"opke, C. Kopper, D. J. Koskinen, P. Koundal, M. Kovacevich, M. Kowalski, T. Kozynets, J. Krishnamoorthi, K. Kruiswijk, E. Krupczak, A. Kumar, E. Kun, N. Kurahashi, N. Lad, C. Lagunas Gualda, M. Lamoureux, M. J. Larson, S. Latseva, F. Lauber, J. P. Lazar, J. W. Lee, K. Leonard DeHolton, A. Leszczy\'nska, J. Liao, M. Lincetto, Y. T. Liu, M. Liubarska, E. Lohfink, C. Love, C. J. Lozano Mariscal, L. Lu, F. Lucarelli, W. Luszczak, Y. Lyu, J. Madsen, E. Magnus, K. B. M. Mahn, Y. Makino, E. Manao, S. Mancina, W. Marie Sainte, I. C. Mari\c{s}, S. Marka, Z. Marka, M. Marsee, I. Martinez-Soler, R. Maruyama, F. Mayhew, F. McNally, J. V. Mead, K. Meagher, S. Mechbal, A. Medina, M. Meier, Y. Merckx, L. Merten, J. Micallef, J. Mitchell, T. Montaruli, R. W. Moore, Y. Morii, R. Morse, M. Moulai, T. Mukherjee, R. Naab, R. Nagai, M. Nakos, U. Naumann, J. Necker, A. Negi, L. Neste, M. Neumann, H. Niederhausen, M. U. Nisa, K. Noda, A. Noell, A. Novikov, A. Obertacke Pollmann, V. O'Dell, B. Oeyen, A. Olivas, R. Orsoe, J. Osborn, E. O'Sullivan, H. Pandya, N. Park, G. K. Parker, E. N. Paudel, L. Paul, C. P\'erez de los Heros, T. Pernice, J. Peterson, S. Philippen, A. Pizzuto, M. Plum, A. Pont\'en, Y. Popovych, M. Prado Rodriguez, B. Pries, R. Procter-Murphy, G. T. Przybylski, C. Raab, J. Rack-Helleis, M. Ravn, K. Rawlins, Z. Rechav, A. Rehman, P. Reichherzer, E. Resconi, S. Reusch, W. Rhode, B. Riedel, A. Rifaie, E. J. Roberts, S. Robertson, S. Rodan, G. Roellinghoff, M. Rongen, A. Rosted, C. Rott, T. Ruhe, L. Ruohan, D. Ryckbosch, I. Safa, J. Saffer, D. Salazar-Gallegos, P. Sampathkumar, A. Sandrock, M. Santander, S. Sarkar, S. Sarkar, J. Savelberg, P. Savina, P. Schaile, M. Schaufel, H. Schieler, S. Schindler, B. Schl\"uter, F. Schl\"uter, N. Schmeisser, T. Schmidt, J. Schneider, F. G. Schr\"oder, L. Schumacher, S. Sclafani, D. Seckel, M. Seikh, M. Seo, S. Seunarine, P. Sevle Myhr, R. Shah, S. Shefali, N. Shimizu, M. Silva, B. Skrzypek, B. Smithers, R. Snihur, J. Soedingrekso, A. S{\o}gaard, D. Soldin, P. Soldin, G. Sommani, C. Spannfellner, G. M. Spiczak, C. Spiering, M. Stamatikos, T. Stanev, T. Stezelberger, T. St\"urwald, T. Stuttard, G. W. Sullivan, I. Taboada, S. Ter-Antonyan, A. Terliuk, M. Thiesmeyer, W. G. Thompson, J. Thwaites, S. Tilav, K. Tollefson, C. T\"onnis, S. Toscano, D. Tosi, A. Trettin, R. Turcotte, J. P. Twagirayezu, M. A. Unland Elorrieta, A. K. Upadhyay, K. Upshaw, A. Vaidyanathan, N. Valtonen-Mattila, J. Vandenbroucke, N. van Eijndhoven, D. Vannerom, J. van Santen, J. Vara, J. Veitch-Michaelis, M. Venugopal, M. Vereecken, S. Verpoest, D. Veske, A. Vijai, C. Walck, A. Wang, C. Weaver, P. Weigel, A. Weindl, J. Weldert, A. Y. Wen, C. Wendt, J. Werthebach, M. Weyrauch, N. Whitehorn, C. H. Wiebusch, D. R. Williams, L. Witthaus, A. Wolf, M. Wolf, G. Wrede, X. W. Xu, J. P. Yanez, E. Yildizci, S. Yoshida, R. Young, S. Yu, T. Yuan, Z. Zhang, P. Zhelnin, P. Zilberman, M. Zimmerman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical ray tracing of echelle spectrographs applied to the wavelength solution for precise radial velocities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19691v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present $\texttt{moes}$, a ray tracing software package that computes the path of rays through echelle spectrographs. Our algorithm is based on sequential direct tracing with Seidel aberration corrections applied at the detector plane. As a test case, we model the CARMENES VIS spectrograph. After subtracting the best model from the data, the residuals yield an rms of 0.024 pix, setting a new standard to the precision of the wavelength solution of state-of-the-art radial velocity instruments. By including the influence of the changes of the environment in the ray propagation, we are able to predict instrumental radial velocity systematics at the 1 m/s level.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19691v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1117/1.JATIS.10.2.028001</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Astron. Telesc. Instrum. Syst. 10(2), 028001 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marcelo Tala Pinto, Adrian Kaminski, Andreas Quirrenbach, Mathias Zechmeister</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Convolutional Neural Network-Based Star Detection and Centroiding Method for CubeSat Star Tracker</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19108</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19108v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Star trackers are one of the most accurate celestial sensors used for absolute attitude determination. The devices detect stars in captured images and accurately compute their projected centroids on an imaging focal plane with subpixel precision. Traditional algorithms for star detection and centroiding often rely on threshold adjustments for star pixel detection and pixel brightness weighting for centroid computation. However, challenges like high sensor noise and stray light can compromise algorithm performance. This article introduces a Convolutional Neural Network (CNN)-based approach for star detection and centroiding, tailored to address the issues posed by noisy star tracker images in the presence of stray light and other artifacts. Trained using simulated star images overlayed with real sensor noise and stray light, the CNN produces both a binary segmentation map distinguishing star pixels from the background and a distance map indicating each pixel's proximity to the nearest star centroid. Leveraging this distance information alongside pixel coordinates transforms centroid calculations into a set of trilateration problems solvable via the least squares method. Our method employs efficient UNet variants for the underlying CNN architectures, and the variants' performances are evaluated. Comprehensive testing has been undertaken with synthetic image evaluations, hardware-in-the-loop assessments, and night sky tests. The tests consistently demonstrated that our method outperforms several existing algorithms in centroiding accuracy and exhibits superior resilience to high sensor noise and stray light interference. An additional benefit of our algorithms is that they can be executed in real-time on low-power edge AI processors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19108v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongrui Zhao, Michael F. Lembeck, Adrian Zhuang, Riya Shah, Jesse Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPHERE RefPlanets: Search for epsilon Eridani b and warm dust</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19504v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We carried out very deep VLT/SPHERE imaging polarimetry of the nearby system Eps Eri based on 38.5 hours of integration time with a 600 - 900 nm broadband filter to search for polarized scattered light from a planet or from circumstellar dust using AO, coronagraphy, high precision differential polarimetry, and angular differential imaging. We have improved several data reduction and post-processing techniques and also developed new ones to further increase the sensitivity of SPHERE/ZIMPOL. The data provide unprecedented contrast limits, but no significant detection of a point source or an extended signal from circumstellar dust. For each observing epoch, we obtained a point source contrast for the polarized intensity between $2\cdot 10^{-8}$ and $4\cdot 10^{-8}$ at the expected separation of the planet Eps Eri b of 1'' near quadrature phase. The polarimetric contrast limits are about six to 50 times better than the intensity limits because polarimetric imaging is much more efficient in speckle suppression. Combining the entire 14-month data set to the search for a planet moving on a Keplerian orbit with the K-Stacker software further improves the contrast limits by a factor of about two, to about $8 \cdot 10^{-9}$ at 1''. This would allow the detection of a planet with a radius of about 2.5 Jupiter radii. The surface brightness contrast limits achieved for the polarized intensity from an extended scattering region are about 15 mag arcsec$^{-2}$ at 1'', or up to 3 mag arcsec$^{-2}$ deeper than previous limits. For Eps Eri, these limits exclude the presence of a narrow dust ring and they constrain the dust properties. This study shows that the polarimetric contrast limits for reflecting planets with SPHERE/ZIMPOL can be improved to a level $&lt;10^{-8}$ simply by collecting more data over many nights and using the K-Stacker software.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19504v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202449442</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>C. Tschudi, H. M. Schmid, M. Nowak, H. Le Coroller, S. Hunziker, R. G. van Holstein, C. Perrot, D. Mouillet, J. -C. Augereau, A. Bazzon, J. L. Beuzit, A. Boccaletti, M. J. Bonse, G. Chauvin, S. Desidera, K. Dohlen, C. Dominik, N. Engler, M. Feldt, J. H. Girard, R. Gratton, Th. Henning, M. Kasper, P. Kervella, A. -M. Lagrange, M. Langlois, P. Martinez, F. M\'enard, M. R. Meyer, J. Milli, J. Pragt, P. Puget, S. P. Quanz, R. Roelfsema, J. -F. Sauvage, J. Szulagyi, Ch. Thalmann, A. Zurlo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An evaluation of the BALROG and RoboBA algorithms for determining the position of Fermi/GBM GRBs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19732v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Fermi/GBM instrument is a vital source of detections of gamma-ray bursts and has an increasingly important role to play in understanding gravitational-wave transients. In both cases, its impact is increased by accurate positions with reliable uncertainties. We evaluate the RoboBA and BALROG algorithms for determining the position of gamma-ray bursts detected by the Fermi/GBM instrument. We construct a sample of 54 bursts with detections both by Swift/BAT and by Fermi/GBM. We then compare the positions predicted by RoboBA and BALROG with the positions measured by BAT, which we can assume to be the true position. We find that RoboBA and BALROG are similarly precise for bright bursts whose uncertainties are dominated by systematic errors, but RoboBA performs better for faint bursts whose uncertainties are dominated by statistical noise. We further find that the uncertainties in the positions predicted by RoboBA are consistent with the distribution of position errors, whereas BALROG seems to be underestimating the uncertainties by a factor of about two. Additionally, we consider the implications of these results for the follow-up of the optical afterglows of Fermi/GBM bursts. In particular, for the DDOTI wide-field imager we conclude that a single pointing is best. Our sample would allow a similar study to be carried out for other telescopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19732v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Oc\'elotl. C. L\'opez, Alan M. Watson, William H. Lee, Rosa L. Becerra, Margarita Pereyra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First upper limits on the 21 cm signal power spectrum from cosmic dawn from one night of observations with NenuFAR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.05364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.05364v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The redshifted 21 cm signal from neutral hydrogen is a direct probe of the physics of the early universe and has been an important science driver of many present and upcoming radio interferometers. In this study we use a single night of observations with the New Extension in Nan\c{c}ay Upgrading LOFAR (NenuFAR) to place upper limits on the 21 cm power spectrum from cosmic dawn at a redshift of $z$ = 20.3. NenuFAR is a new low-frequency radio interferometer, operating in the 10-85 MHz frequency range, currently under construction at the Nan\c{c}ay Radio Observatory in France. It is a phased array instrument with a very dense uv coverage at short baselines, making it one of the most sensitive instruments for 21 cm cosmology analyses at these frequencies. Our analysis adopts the foreground subtraction approach, in which sky sources are modeled and subtracted through calibration and residual foregrounds are subsequently removed using Gaussian process regression. The final power spectra are constructed from the gridded residual data cubes in the uv plane. Signal injection tests are performed at each step of the analysis pipeline, the relevant pipeline settings are optimized to ensure minimal signal loss, and any signal suppression is accounted for through a bias correction on our final upper limits. We obtain a best 2$\sigma$ upper limit of $2.4\times 10^7$ $\text{mK}^{2}$ at $z$ = 20.3 and $k$ = 0.041 $h\,\text{cMpc}^{-1}$. We see a strong excess power in the data, making our upper limits two orders of magnitude higher than the thermal noise limit. We investigate the origin and nature of this excess power and discuss further improvements to the analysis pipeline that can potentially mitigate it and consequently allow us to reach thermal noise sensitivity when multiple nights of observations are processed in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.05364v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202348329</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>A&amp;A 681, A62 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S. Munshi, F. G. Mertens, L. V. E. Koopmans, A. R. Offringa, B. Semelin, D. Aubert, R. Barkana, A. Bracco, S. A. Brackenhoff, B. Cecconi, E. Ceccotti, S. Corbel, A. Fialkov, B. K. Gehlot, R. Ghara, J. N. Girard, J. M. Grie{\ss}meier, C. H\"ofer, I. Hothi, R. M\'eriot, M. Mevius, P. Ocvirk, A. K. Shaw, G. Theureau, S. Yatawatta, P. Zarka, S. Zaroubi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The past and future 20-years endeavor for discovering origins of ultra-high energy cosmic rays -- Rapporteur's summary of cosmic ray indirect --</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.08952</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.08952v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article is the rapporteur's summary of the cosmic ray indirect sessions of the 38th International Cosmic Ray Conference in Nagoya, Japan. The rapporteur highlights cosmic ray indirect observatories around the world, and reviews a selection of the latest results regarding the cosmic ray energy spectrum, mass composition, anisotropy, hadronic interaction models, theory, geophysics, interdisciplinary research, and future projects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.08952v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.22323/1.444.0031</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PoS (ICRC2023) 031</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Toshihiro Fujii</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
