<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Jun 2024 02:47:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of reflection-based measurements of microwave kinetic inductance detectors in the optical bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09436v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the single photon response from the reflection of the Microwave Kinetic Inductance Detector (MKID) array. Reflection measurements are carried out using two configurations: one is measured simultaneously with the transmission, and the other is obtained with a single-ended MKID array terminated with an open load. Compared with the transmission, reflection measurements significantly reduce the readout noise of the single-ended MKID array. This is also reflected in the improvement of the median energy resolving power by around 20%-30% under pulsed photon illumination at $\lambda = 405$~nm, mainly due to an increase in the size of the resonance circle on the IQ plane. This method has the potential to be used to read out large MKID arrays.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09436v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0207817</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Appl. Phys. Lett. 124, 242602 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jie Hu, Faouzi Boussaha, Paul Nicaise, Christine Chaumont, Maria Appavou, Viet Dung Pham, Michel Piat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Japanese Vision for the Black Hole Explorer Mission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09516v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Black Hole Explorer (BHEX) is a next-generation space very long baseline interferometry (VLBI) mission concept that will extend the ground-based millimeter/submillimeter arrays into space. The mission, closely aligned with the science priorities of the Japanese VLBI community, involves an active engagement of this community in the development of the mission, resulting in the formation of the Black Hole Explorer Japan Consortium. Here we present the current Japanese vision for the mission, ranging from scientific objectives to instrumentation. The Consortium anticipates a wide range of scientific investigations, from diverse black hole physics and astrophysics studied through the primary VLBI mode, to the molecular universe explored via a potential single-dish observation mode in the previously unexplored 50-70\,GHz band that would make BHEX the highest-sensitivity explorer ever of molecular oxygen. A potential major contribution for the onboard instrument involves supplying essential elements for its high-sensitivity dual-band receiving system, which includes a broadband 300\,GHz SIS mixer and a space-certified multi-stage 4.5K cryocooler akin to those used in the Hitomi and XRISM satellites by the Japan Aerospace Exploration Agency. Additionally, the Consortium explores enhancing and supporting BHEX operations through the use of millimeter/submillimeter facilities developed by the National Astronomical Observatory of Japan, coupled with a network of laser communication stations operated by the National Institute of Information and Communication Technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09516v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazunori Akiyama, Kotaro Niinuma, Kazuhiro Hada, Akihiro Doi, Yoshiaki Hagiwara, Aya E. Higuchi, Mareki Honma, Tomohisa Kawashima, Dimitar Kolev, Shoko Koyama, Sho Masui, Ken Ohsuga, Hidetoshi Sano, Hideki Takami, Yuh Tsunetoe, Yoshinori Uzawa, Takuya Akahori, Yuto Akiyama, Peter Galison, Takayuki J. Hayashi, Tomoya Hirota, Makoto Inoue, Yuhei Iwata, Michael D. Johnson, Motoki Kino, Yutaro Kofuji, Yosuke Mizuno, Kotaro Moriyama, Hiroshi Nagai, Kenta Nakamura, Shota Notsu, Fumie Ono, Yoko Oya, Tomoaki Oyama, Hannah Rana, Hiromi Saida, Ryo Saito, Yoshihiko Saito, Mahito Sasada, Satoko Sawada-Satoh, Mikiya M. Takahashi, Mieko Takamura, Edward Tong, Hiroyuki Tsuji, Shogo Yoshioka, Yoshimasa Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Receivers for the Black Hole Explorer (BHEX) Mission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09558v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce the receiver architecture for the Black Hole Explorer (BHEX) Mission, designed to reveal the photon ring of black holes. The primary instrument is a dual-polarization receiver operating over the 240-320 GHz frequency range, utilizing a Superconductor-Insulator-Superconductor (SIS) mixer. This Double-Side-Band (DSB) receiver has an intermediate frequency (IF) range of 4-12 GHz and operates at a bath temperature of 4.5 K, for optimal performance, which necessitates the integration of a cryocooler. Complementing the primary receiver is a secondary unit covering the 80-106 GHz spectrum, featuring a cryogenic low noise amplifier. This secondary receiver, affixed to the 20 K stage of the cryocooler, serves to augment the SIS receiver performance by employing the Frequency Phase Transfer technique to boost the signal-to-noise ratio at the correlator output. Together, this sophisticated receiver duo is engineered to achieve the quantum-limited sensitivity required to detect the photon ring of black holes, marking a breakthrough in astrophysical observation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09558v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Edward Tong, Kazunori Akiyama, Paul Grimes, Mareki Honma, Janice Houston, Michael D. Johnson, Daniel P. Marrone, Hannah Rana, Yoshinori Uzawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High Data Rate Laser Communications for the Black Hole Explorer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09572v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Black Hole Explorer (BHEX) is a mission concept that can dramatically improve state-of-the-art astronomical very long baseline interferometry (VLBI) imaging resolution by extending baseline distances to space. To support these scientific goals, a high data rate downlink is required from space to ground. Laser communications is a promising option for realizing these high data rate, long-distance space-to-ground downlinks with smaller space/ground apertures. Here, we present a scalable laser communications downlink design and current lasercom mission results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09572v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jade Wang, Bryan Bilyeu, Don Boroson, Dave Caplan, Kat Riesing, Bryan Robinson, Curt Schieler, Michael D. Johnson, Lindy Blackburn, Kari Haworth, Janice Houston, Sara Issaoun, Daniel Palumbo, Elliot Richards, Ranjani Srinivasan, Jonathan Weintroub, Dan Marrone</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Black Hole Explorer: Operating a Hybrid Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09610</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09610v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a baseline science operations plan for the Black Hole Explorer (BHEX), a space mission concept aiming to confirm the existence of the predicted sharp ``photon ring" resulting from strongly lensed photon trajectories around black holes, as predicted by general relativity, and to measure its size and shape to determine the black hole's spin. BHEX will co-observe with a ground-based very long baseline interferometric (VLBI) array at high-frequency radio wavelengths, providing unprecedented high resolution with the extension to space that will enable photon ring detection and studies of active galactic nuclei. Science operations require a simultaneous coordination between BHEX and a ground array of large and small radio apertures to provide opportunities for surveys and imaging of radio sources, while coordination with a growing network of optical downlink terminals provides the data rates necessary to build sensitivity on long baselines to space. Here we outline the concept of operations for the hybrid observatory, the available observing modes, the observation planning process, and data delivery to achieve the mission goals and meet mission requirements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09610v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara Issaoun, Kim Alonso, Kazunori Akiyama, Lindy Blackburn, Don Boroson, Peter Galison, Kari Haworth, Janice Houston, Michael D. Johnson, Yuri Y. Kovalev, Peter Kurczynski, Robert Lafon, Daniel P. Marrone, Daniel Palumbo, Eliad Peretz, Dominic Pesce, Leonid Petrov, Alexander Plavin, Jade Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffuse X-ray Explorer: a high-resolution X-ray spectroscopic sky surveyor on the China Space Station</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09813</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09813v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: DIffuse X-ray Explorer (DIXE) is a proposed high-resolution X-ray spectroscopic sky surveyor on the China Space Station (CSS). DIXE will focus on studying hot baryons in the Milky Way. Galactic hot baryons like the X-ray emitting Milky Way halo and eROSITA bubbles are best observed in the sky survey mode with a large field of view. DIXE will take advantage of the orbital motion of the CSS to scan a large fraction of the sky. High-resolution X-ray spectroscopy, enabled by superconducting microcalorimeters based on the transition-edge sensor (TES) technology, will probe the physical properties (e.g., temperature, density, elemental abundances, kinematics) of the Galactic hot baryons. This will complement the high-resolution imaging data obtained with the eROSITA mission. Here we present the preliminary design of DIXE. The payload consists mainly of a detector assembly and a cryogenic cooling system. The key components of the detector assembly are a microcalorimeter array and frequency-domain multiplexing readout electronics. To provide a working temperature for the detector assembly, the cooling system consists of an adiabatic demagnetization refrigerator and a mechanical cryocooler system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09813v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hai Jin, Junjie Mao, Liubiao Chen, Naihui Chen, Wei Cui, Bo Gao, Jinjin Li, Xinfeng Li, Jiejia Liu, Jia Quan, Chunyang Jiang, Guole Wang, Le Wang, Qian Wang, Sifan Wang, Aimin Xiao, Shuo Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Black Hole Explorer Cryocooling Instrument</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09975v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Black Hole Explorer (BHEX) is a space-based very-long baseline interferometry (VLBI) mission aimed at precision black hole measurements, detecting the photon ring around black holes, exploring spacetime, spin, and mass properties, and validating predictions of General Relativity. These objectives are achieved using cryogenic receivers with quantum-limited sensitivities across a broad frequency range. Dual-band receivers at 80-106 GHz and 240-320 GHz require operating temperatures of 20 K and 4.5 K, respectively. A cryocooling system with two cold stages will be employed: a 20 K stage handling a 125 mW heat load and a 4.5 K stage handling a 10 mW heat load.
  To design the cryocooling system, the mission leverages existing space industry technology at high Technology Readiness Levels (TRLs), informed by missions such as Planck, JEM/SMILES, Hitomi, and XRISM, and advancements from the ACTDP/JWST program. Integrating the cryocooler with the receivers and broader instrument involves careful consideration of thermal challenges, including linking the cold ends of each cooling stage to minimize heat losses and ensuring adequate passive cooling for the cryocooler warm end heat rejection.
  Key challenges and trade-offs include sizing the mass and reducing power consumption while meeting the receiver cold temperature requirements, which impact the scientific objectives. This paper addresses efforts to balance the scientific requirements with the limitations of technical cryocooling capabilities within the framework of a small-class (SMEX) space mission, presenting an overview of cooling needs, initial design considerations, a survey of 4 K spaceflight cryocooler developments, and trade-offs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09975v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannah Rana, Kazunori Akiyama, Edgar Canavan, Michael DiPirro, Mark Freeman, Peter Galison, Paul Grimes, Mareki Honma, Janice Houston, Michael Johnson, Mark Kimball, Daniel Marrone, Edward Tong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Spectrometer Development of CosmoCube, Lunar Orbiting Satellite to Detect 21-cm Hydrogen Signal from Cosmic Dark Ages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10096v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The cosmic Dark Ages represent a pivotal epoch in the evolution of the Universe, marked by the emergence of the first cosmic structures under the influence of dark matter. The 21-cm hydrogen line, emanating from the hyperfine transition of neutral hydrogen, serves as a critical probe into this era. We describe the development and implementation of the spectrometer for CosmoCube, a novel lunar orbiting CubeSat designed to detect the redshifted 21-cm signal within the redshift range of 13 to 150. Our instrumentation utilizes a Xilinx RFSoC, which integrates both Analog-to-Digital Converters (ADCs) and Digital-to-Analog Converters (DACs), tailored for the spectrometer component of the radiometer. This system is characterized by a 4096 FFT length at 62.5 kHz steps using a Polyphase Filter Bank (PFB), achieving an average Effective Number of Bits (ENOB) of 11.5 bits throughout the frequency of interest, from 10 MHz to 100 MHz. The spectrometer design is further refined through loopback tests involving both DAC and ADC of the RFSoC, with DAC outputs varying between high (+1 dBm) and low (-3 dBm) power modes to characterize system performance. The power consumption was optimized to 5.45 W using three ADCs and one DAC for the radiometer. Additionally, the stability of the ADC noise floor was investigated in a thermal chamber with environmental temperatures ranging from 5{\deg}C to 40{\deg}C. A consistent noise floor of approximately -152.5 dBFS/Hz was measured, with a variation of $\pm$0.2 dB, ensuring robust performance under varying thermal conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10096v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaan Artuc, Eloy de Lera Acedo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Black Hole Explorer: Back End Electronics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10103v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper describes specification and early design of back end signal processing subsystems for the Black Hole Explorer (BHEX) Very Long Baseline Interferometry (VLBI) space telescope. The "back end" consists of two subsystems. First, the block downconverter (BDC) is a heterodyne system that performs a frequency translation of the analog signal from IF to baseband and amplifies and filters it for digitization. Second, the digital back end (DBE) samples the analog signal with an analog-to-digital converters (ADC) and digitally processes the data stream formatting them to the VLBI "VDIF" standard and converting to Ethernet packets for 100 gigabit-per-second (Gb/s) Ethernet transport to the optical downlink system. Both the BDC and the DBE for BHEX support eight channels of 4.096 GHz bandwidth each, for a total processed bandwidth of 32.768 GHz. The BHEX back end benefits from mature terrestrial back end heritage, described in some detail. The BHEX back end itself is in the early stages of design, with requirements, interface specifications, and component trade studies well advanced. The aim is to build a prototype using terrestrial grade parts which are available in functionally identical space grade equivalents, and to use this prototype to advance the back end Technology Readiness Level (TRL) preparing for a Small Explorer (SMEX) proposal in 2025.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10103v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ranjani Srinivasan, Jonathan Weintroub, Rick Raffanti, Bryan Bilyeu, Thomas Gauron, John Test, Elliot Richards, Manuel Fernandez, Mark Freeman, Peter Cheimets, Mauricio Gendelman, Kari Haworth, Janice Houston, Michael D. Johnson, Emilia Mamani, Daniel Marrone, Ariel L. Pola, Jade Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Black Hole Explorer: Instrument System Overview</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10143v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Black Hole Explorer (BHEX) is a space very-long-baseline interferometry (VLBI) mission concept that is currently under development. BHEX will study supermassive black holes at unprecedented resolution, isolating the signature of the "photon ring" - light that has orbited the black hole before escaping - to probe physics at the edge of the observable universe. It will also measure black hole spins, study the energy extraction and acceleration mechanisms for black hole jets, and characterize the black hole mass distribution. BHEX achieves high angular resolution by joining with ground-based millimeter-wavelength VLBI arrays, extending the size, and therefore improving the angular resolution of the earthbound telescopes. Here we discuss the science instrument concept for BHEX. The science instrument for BHEX is a dual-band, coherent receiver system for 80-320 GHz, coupled to a 3.5-meter antenna. BHEX receiver front end will observe simultaneously with dual polarizations in two bands, one sampling 80-106 GHz and one sampling 240-320 GHz. An ultra-stable quartz oscillator provides the master frequency reference and ensures coherence for tens of seconds. To achieve the required sensitivity, the front end will instantaneously receive 32 GHz of frequency bandwidth, which will be digitized to 64 Gbits/sec of incompressible raw data. These data will be buffered and transmitted to the ground via laser data link, for correlation with data recorded simultaneously at radio telescopes on the ground. We describe the challenges associated with the instrument concept and the solutions that have been incorporated into the baseline design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10143v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel P. Marrone (University of Arizona), Janice Houston (Center for Astrophysics | Harvard/Smithsonian), Kazunori Akiyama (MIT Haystack Observatory, Mizusawa VLBI Observatory, BHI), Bryan Bilyeu (MIT Lincoln Laboratory), Don Boroson (MIT Lincoln Laboratory), Paul Grimes (Center for Astrophysics | Harvard/Smithsonian), Kari Haworth (Center for Astrophysics | Harvard/Smithsonian), Robert Lehmensiek (National Radio Astronomy Observatory), Eliad Peretz (NASA Goddard Space Flight Center), Hannah Rana (Center for Astrophysics | Harvard/Smithsonian, BHI), Laura C. Sinclair (National Institute of Standards and Technology), Sridharan Tirupati Kumara (National Radio Astronomy Observatory), Ranjani Srinivasan (Center for Astrophysics | Harvard/Smithsonian), Edward Tong (Center for Astrophysics | Harvard/Smithsonian), Jade Wang (MIT Lincoln Laboratory), Jonathan Weintroub (Center for Astrophysics | Harvard/Smithsonian), Michael D. Johnson (Center for Astrophysics | Harvard/Smithsonian, BHI)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultra-low noise laser and optical frequency comb-based timing system for the Black Hole Explorer (BHEX) mission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10222v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this effort, we demonstrate the performance of a highly stable time reference for the proposed Black Hole Explorer (BHEX) mission, a space-based extension to the Event Horizon Telescope (EHT) Very Long Baseline Interferometry (VLBI) project. This precision timing system is based on the use of a space-qualified, ultra-low noise laser developed as part of the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA) mission as the timing reference, and an optical frequency comb to transfer the stability of this laser to the microwave regime for instrumentation use. We describe the implementation of this system and experimental setup to characterize the stability performance. We present the results of this experiment that demonstrate the performance of this system meets requirements for the BHEX mission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10222v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hannah Tomio, Guangning Yang, Holly F. Leopardi, Kenji Numata, Anthony W. Yu, Andrew Attar, Xiaozhen Xu, Wei Lu, Cheryl Gramling, T. K. Sridharan, Peter Kurczynski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computational generation of tailored radionuclide libraries for alpha-particle and gamma-ray spectrometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09560v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Radionuclide identification is a radioanalytical method employed in various scientific disciplines that utilize alpha-particle or gamma-ray spectrometric assays, ranging from astrophysics to nuclear medicine. Radionuclide libraries in conventional radionuclide identification systems are crafted in a manual fashion, accompanying labor-intensive and error-prone user tasks and hindering library customization. This research presents a computational algorithm and the architecture of its dedicated software that can automatically generate tailored radionuclide libraries. Progenitor-progeny recurrence relations were modeled to enable recursive computation of radionuclide subsets. This theoretical concept was incorporated into open-source software called RecurLib and validated against four actinide decay series and twelve radioactive substances, including a uranium-glazed legacy Fiestaware, natural uranium and thorium sources, a $^{226}$Ra sample, and the medical radionuclides $^{225}$Ac, $^{177}$Lu, and $^{99\text{m}}$Tc. The developed algorithm yielded radionuclide libraries for all the tested specimens within minutes, demonstrating its efficiency and applicability across diverse scenarios. The proposed approach introduces a framework for computerized radionuclide library generation, thereby trivializing library-driven radionuclide identification and facilitating the spectral recognition of unregistered radionuclides in radiation spectrometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09560v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jaewoong Jang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MKIDGen3: Energy-Resolving, Single-Photon-Counting MKID Readout on an RFSoC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09764v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Building large, cryogenic MKID arrays requires processing highly-multiplexed, wideband readout signals in real time; a task that has previously required large, heavy, and power-intensive custom electronics. In this work, we present the third-generation UVOIR MKID readout system (Gen3) which is capable of reading out twice as many detectors with a fifth the weight and power and an order of magnitude less volume and cost-per-pixel as compared to the previous system. Gen3 leverages the Xilinx RFSoC4x2 platform to read out 2048, 1 MHz MKID channels per board. The system takes a modern approach to FPGA design using Vitis High-Level Synthesis (HLS) to specify signal processing blocks in C/C++, Vivado ML Intelligent Design Runs (IDR) to inform implementation stragety and close timing, and Python Productivity for ZYNQ (PYNQ) to simplify interacting with and programming the FPGA using Python. This design suite and tool flow allows general users to contribute to and maintain the design and positions Gen3 to rapidly migrate to future platforms as they become available. In this work, we describe the system requirements, design, and implementation. We also provide performance characterization details and show that the system achieves detector-limited resolving power in the case of few readout tones and minimal degradation with all 2048 tones. Planned upgrades and future work are also discussed. The Gen3 MKID readout system is fully open-source and is expected to facilitate future array scaling to megapixel-sized formats and increase the feasibility of deploying UVOIR MKIDs in space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09764v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jennifer Pearl Smith, John I. Bailey,  III., Aled Cuda, Nicholas Zobrist, Benjamin A. Mazin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence for Morning-to-Evening Limb Asymmetry on the Cool Low-Density Exoplanet WASP-107b</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09863v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Transmission spectroscopy has enabled unprecedented insights into the makeup of exoplanet atmospheres. A transmission spectrum combines contributions from a planet's morning and evening limbs, but these limbs may have different temperatures, compositions, and aerosol properties due to atmospheric circulation. High-resolution ground-based observations have detected limb asymmetry on several ultra-hot (&gt;2000 K) exoplanets, but space-based investigation into limb asymmetry is in its infancy, and limb asymmetry's prevalence in the broader exoplanet population remains unexplored. We find evidence for limb asymmetry on the exoplanet WASP-107b via transmission spectroscopy from 2.5 to 4.0 micrometers with JWST/NIRCam. This is one of the first low-resolution space-based measurements of limb asymmetry and is unique because, at 770 K, WASP-107b is in a relatively cool regime where planetary terminators are expected to be homogeneous. These observations imply a difference in temperature and cloud properties between WASP-107b's limbs, challenging our models of limb asymmetry in this cooler regime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09863v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew M. Murphy, Thomas G. Beatty, Everett Schlawin, Taylor J. Bell, Michael R. Line, Thomas P. Greene, Vivien Parmentier, Emily Rauscher, Luis Welbanks, Jonathan J. Fortney, Marcia Rieke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GASTLI: An open-source coupled interior-atmosphere model to unveil gas giant composition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10032v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The metal mass fractions of gas giants are a powerful tool to constrain their formation mechanisms and evolution. The metal content is inferred by comparing mass and radius measurements with interior structure and evolution models. In the midst of the JWST, CHEOPS, TESS, and the forthcoming PLATO era, we are at the brink of obtaining unprecedented precision in radius, age and atmospheric metallicity measurements. To prepare for this wealth of data, we present the GAS gianT modeL for Interiors (GASTLI), an easy-to-use, publicly available Python package. The code is optimized to rapidly calculate mass-radius relations, and radius and luminosity thermal evolution curves for a variety of envelope compositions and core mass fractions. Its applicability spans planets with masses $17 \ M_{\oplus} &lt; M &lt; 6 \ M_{Jup}$, and equilibrium temperatures $T_{eq} &lt; 1000$ K. The interior model is stratified in a core composed of water and rock, and an envelope constituted by H/He and metals (water). The interior is coupled to a grid of self-consistent, cloud-free atmospheric models to determine the atmospheric and boundary interior temperature, as well as the contribution of the atmosphere to the total radius. We successfully validate GASTLI by comparing it to previous work and data of the Solar System's gas giants and Neptune. We also test GASTLI on the Neptune-mass exoplanet HAT-P-26 b, finding a bulk metal mass fraction between 0.60-0.78 and a core mass of 8.5-14.4 $M_{\oplus}$. Finally, we explore the impact of different equations of state and assumptions, such as C/O ratio and transit pressure, in the estimation of bulk metal mass fraction. These differences between interior models entail a change in radius of up to 2.5% for Jupiter-mass planets, but more than 10\% for Neptune-mass. These are equivalent to variations in core mass fraction of 0.07, or 0.10 in envelope metal mass fraction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10032v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorena Acu\~na, Laura Kreidberg, Meng Zhai, Paul Molli\`ere</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A SART-Based Iterative Inversion Methodology to Infer the Solar Rotation Rate from Global Helioseismic Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10183v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a new iterative rotation inversion technique based on the Simultaneous Algebraic Reconstruction Technique developed for image reconstruction. We describe in detail our algorithmic implementation and compare it to the classical inversion techniques like the Regularized Least Squares (RLS) and the Optimally Localized Averages (OLA) methods. In our implementation, we are able to estimate the formal uncertainty on the inferred solution using standard error propagation, and derive the averaging kernels without recourse to any Monte-Carlo simulation. We present the potential of this new technique using simulated rotational frequency splittings. We use noiseless sets that cover the range of observed modes and associate to these artificial splittings observational uncertainties. We also add random noise to present the noise magnification immunity of the method. Since the technique is iterative we also show its potential when using an apriori solution. With the right regularization this new method can outperform our RLS implementation in precision, scope and resolution. Since it results in very different averaging kernels where the solution is poorly constrained, this technique infers different values. Adding such a technique to our compendium of inversion methods will allow us to improve the robustness of our inferences when inverting real observations and better understand where they might be biased and/or unreliable, as we push our techniques to maximize the diagnostic potential of our observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10183v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sylvain G. Korzennik, Antonio Eff-Darwich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AstroCLIP: A Cross-Modal Foundation Model for Galaxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.03024v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present AstroCLIP, a single, versatile model that can embed both galaxy images and spectra into a shared, physically meaningful latent space. These embeddings can then be used - without any model fine-tuning - for a variety of downstream tasks including (1) accurate in-modality and cross-modality semantic similarity search, (2) photometric redshift estimation, (3) galaxy property estimation from both images and spectra, and (4) morphology classification. Our approach to implementing AstroCLIP consists of two parts. First, we embed galaxy images and spectra separately by pretraining separate transformer-based image and spectrum encoders in self-supervised settings. We then align the encoders using a contrastive loss. We apply our method to spectra from the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument and images from its corresponding Legacy Imaging Survey. Overall, we find remarkable performance on all downstream tasks, even relative to supervised baselines. For example, for a task like photometric redshift prediction, we find similar performance to a specifically-trained ResNet18, and for additional tasks like physical property estimation (stellar mass, age, metallicity, and sSFR), we beat this supervised baseline by 19\% in terms of $R^2$. We also compare our results to a state-of-the-art self-supervised single-modal model for galaxy images, and find that our approach outperforms this benchmark by roughly a factor of two on photometric redshift estimation and physical property prediction in terms of $R^2$, while remaining roughly in-line in terms of morphology classification. Ultimately, our approach represents the first cross-modal self-supervised model for galaxies, and the first self-supervised transformer-based architectures for galaxy images and spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.03024v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae1450</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Liam Parker, Francois Lanusse, Siavash Golkar, Leopoldo Sarra, Miles Cranmer, Alberto Bietti, Michael Eickenberg, Geraud Krawezik, Michael McCabe, Ruben Ohana, Mariel Pettee, Bruno Regaldo-Saint Blancard, Tiberiu Tesileanu, Kyunghyun Cho, Shirley Ho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbation-theory informed integrators for cosmological simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.09655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.09655v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large-scale cosmological simulations are an indispensable tool for modern cosmology. To enable model-space exploration, fast and accurate predictions are critical. In this paper, we show that the performance of such simulations can be further improved with time-stepping schemes that use input from cosmological perturbation theory. Specifically, we introduce a class of time-stepping schemes derived by matching the particle trajectories in a single leapfrog/Verlet drift-kick-drift step to those predicted by Lagrangian perturbation theory (LPT). As a corollary, these schemes exactly yield the analytic Zel'dovich solution in 1D in the pre-shell-crossing regime (i.e. before particle trajectories cross). One representative of this class is the popular FastPM scheme by Feng et al. 2016, which we take as our baseline. We then construct more powerful LPT-inspired integrators and show that they outperform FastPM and standard integrators in fast simulations in two and three dimensions with $\mathcal{O}(1 - 100)$ timesteps, requiring less steps to accurately reproduce the power spectrum and bispectrum of the density field. Furthermore, we demonstrate analytically and numerically that, for any integrator, convergence is limited in the post-shell-crossing regime (to order 3/2 for planar wave collapse), owing to the lacking regularity of the acceleration field, which makes the use of high-order integrators in this regime futile. Also, we study the impact of the timestep spacing and of a decaying mode present in the initial conditions. Importantly, we find that symplecticity of the integrator plays a minor role for fast approximate simulations with a small number of timesteps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.09655v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Florian List, Oliver Hahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the first test of the Weak Equivalence Principle in low Earth orbit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.06400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.06400v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Weak Equivalence Principle is the founding pillar of General Relativity and as such should be verified as precisely as possible. The Microscope experiment tested it in low Earth orbit, finding that Pt and Ti test masses fall toward Earth with the same acceleration to about 1e-15, an improvement of about two orders of magnitude over ground tests. Space missions, even if small, are expensive and hard to replicate; yet, the essence of physics is repeatability. This work is an assessment of the Microscope results based on the laws of physics and knowledge from previous experiments, focusing on the limiting thermal noise and the treatment of acceleration outliers. Thermal noise reveals anomalies that we explain by stray sub-microVolt potentials caused by patch charges, giving rise to an unstable zero. The measurements were affected by numerous acceleration spikes occurring at the synodic frequencies relative to the Earth (the signal frequency) and the Sun, which we interpret as evidence of a thermal origin. In Microscope authors' analysis, the spikes were removed and the resulting gaps replaced with artificial data (up to 35, 40 per cent of the sessions data), which retain memory of the gaps and may simulate or cancel an effect (signal or systematic). An alternative approach based exclusively on real measured data would avoid any ambiguity. The lessons of Microscope are crucial to any futures improved mission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.06400v4</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna M. Nobili, Alberto Anselmi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near Real-Time Gravitational Wave Data Analysis of the Massive Black Hole Binary with TianQin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.06910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.06910v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Space-borne gravitational wave (GW) detectors can detect the merger of massive black holes. The early warning and localization of GW events before merging can be used to inform electromagnetic telescopes and conduct multimessenger observations. However, this requires real-time data transmission and analysis capabilities. The geocentric orbit of the space-borne GW detector TianQin makes it possible to conduct real-time data transmission. In this study, we develop a search and localization pipeline for massive black hole binaries (MBHBs) with TianQin under both regular and real-time data transmission modes. We demonstrate that, with real-time data transmission, MBHBs can be accurately localized on the fly. With the approaching merger, each analysis can be finished in only 40 min. For an MBHB system at a distance of 1 Gpc, if we receive data every hour, then we can pinpoint its location to within less than 1 deg$^2$ on the final day before the merger.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.06910v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11433-023-2377-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci. China-Phys. Mech. Astron. 67, 279512 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hong-Yu Chen, Xiang-Yu Lyu, En-Kun Li, Yi-Ming Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lichen-Mediated Self-Growing Construction Materials for Habitat Outfitting on Mars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02522</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02522v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As its next step in space exploration, the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) revealed plans to establish a permanent human presence on Mars. Habitat outfitting, i.e., the technology to provide the crew with the necessary equipment to perform mission tasks as well as a comfortable, safe, and livable habitable volume, has not been fully explored yet. This study proposes that, rather than shipping prefabricated outfitting elements to Mars, habitat outfitting can be realized by in-situ construction using cyanobacteria and fungi as building agents. A synthetic lichen system, composed of diazotrophic cyanobacteria and filamentous fungi, can be created to produce abundant biominerals (CaCO3) and biopolymers, which will glue Martian regolith into consolidated building blocks. These self-growing building blocks can be assembled into various structures, such as floors, walls, partitions, and furniture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02522v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nisha Rokaya, Erin C. Carr, Richard A. Wilson, Congrui Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
