<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 04:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 26 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Costless correction of chain based nested sampling parameter estimation in gravitational wave data and beyond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16428v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nested sampling parameter estimation differs from evidence estimation, in that it incurs an additional source of error. This error affects estimates of parameter means and credible intervals in gravitational wave analyses and beyond, and yet, it is typically not accounted for in standard error estimation methods. In this paper, we present two novel methods to quantify this error more accurately for any chain based nested sampler, using the additional likelihood calls made at runtime in producing independent samples. Using injected signals of black hole binary coalescences as an example, we first show concretely that the usual error estimation method is insufficient to capture the true error bar on parameter estimates. We then demonstrate how the extra points in the chains of chain based samplers may be carefully utilised to estimate this error correctly, and provide a way to check the accuracy of the resulting error bars. Finally, we discuss how this error affects $p$-$p$ plots and coverage assessments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16428v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Metha Prathaban, Will Handley</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Validating Prior-informed Fisher-matrix Analyses against GWTC Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16103v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Next-generation gravitational-wave detectors, such as the Einstein Telescope (ET), are expected to observe a few 100,000 signals each year. This will require efficient analysis tools and computational resources well beyond the needs of current detectors. Such resources are not presently available to the science community. Therefore, to investigate ET observational capabilities and science cases, Fisher-matrix methods are used to predict how precisely parameters like mass, spin, source distance or sky location can be estimated from ET data. The approach is based on a Gaussian approximation of the likelihood function. However, the reliability of error estimates obtained from Fisher-matrix methods remains an open question. In this article, we present a Fisher-matrix analysis of signals of the Gravitational Wave Transient Catalog (GWTC). We compare parameter-estimation errors obtained using the Fisher matrix code GWFish with the errors from the marginal distributions of the Virgo/LIGO posterior analysis. In order to understand the impact of prior distributions on the results, we implemented a Gaussian likelihood sampling algorithm with priors in GWFish. To ensure a fair comparison of the methods, the GWFish analyses presented in this article use the same priors and the same instrument-noise spectra as the Virgo/LIGO posterior analyses. Our findings imply that Fisher-matrix methods, especially if augmented with the use of priors, are a valid tool for ET science-case studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16103v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulyana Dupletsa, Jan Harms, Ken K. Y. Ng, Jacopo Tissino, Filippo Santoliquido, Andrea Cozzumbo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of Interstellar Magnetization by Synchrotron Polarization Variance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16310</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16310v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Since synchrotron polarization fluctuations are related to the fundamental properties of the magnetic field, we propose the polarization intensity variance to measure the Galactic interstellar medium (ISM) magnetization. We confirm the method's applicability by comparing it with the polarization angle dispersion and its reliability by measuring the underlying Alfv\'enic Mach number of MHD turbulence. With the finding of the power-law relation of $\mathcal{A} \propto M_{\rm A}^{2}$ between polarization intensity variance $\mathcal{A}$ and Alfv\'enic Mach number $M_{\rm A}$, we apply the new technique to the Canadian Galactic Plane Survey (CGPS) data, achieving Alfv\'enic Mach number of the Galactic ISM. Our results show that the low-latitude Galactic ISM is dominated by sub-Alf\'enic turbulence, with $M_{\rm A}$ approximately between 0.5 and 1.0.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16310v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ning-Ning Guo (Xiangtan Univ.), Jian-Fu Zhang, Hua-Ping Xiao, Jungyeon Cho, Xue-Juan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TESS Free-floating Planet Candidate Is Likely a Stellar Flare</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16480v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The discovery of a terrestrial-mass free-floating planet candidate in the light curve of the star TIC 107150013 observed by the Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) has recently been announced. A short-duration (~0.5 day), low-amplitude (~0.06 mag) brightening in the TESS light curve was interpreted as a short-timescale gravitational microlensing event. However, the purported event occurred far from the Galactic center and the Galactic plane (l~ 239 deg, b ~ -5 deg), on a relatively nearby (~3.2 kpc) star, making the microlensing interpretation unlikely. Here, we report the archival photometric observations of TIC 107150013 collected by the Optical Gravitational Lensing Experiment (OGLE) from 2018 through 2020. The archival OGLE light curve reveals periodic variability indicative of starspots on the surface of the star. The presence of starspots indicates magnetic activity of the star, which may also manifest as stellar flares. We interpret the brightening of TIC 107150013 seen in the TESS data as the stellar flare. We present similar flaring stars detected in the archival OGLE data, mimicking short-timescale, low-amplitude microlensing events. Such stars may be a source of non-negligible false positive detections in the planned space-based microlensing surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16480v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Przemek Mroz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>J-PLUS: Bayesian object classification with a strum of BANNJOS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16567v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With its 12 optical filters, the Javalambre-Photometric Local Universe Survey (J-PLUS) provides an unprecedented multicolor view of the local Universe. The third data release (DR3) covers 3,192 deg$^2$ and contains 47.4 million objects. However, the classification algorithms currently implemented in its pipeline are deterministic and based solely on the sources morphology. Our goal is classify the sources identified in the J-PLUS DR3 images into stars, quasi-stellar objects (QSOs), and galaxies. For this task, we present BANNJOS, a machine learning pipeline that uses Bayesian neural networks to provide the probability distribution function (PDF) of the classification. BANNJOS is trained on photometric, astrometric, and morphological data from J-PLUS DR3, Gaia DR3, and CatWISE2020, using over 1.2 million objects with spectroscopic classification from SDSS DR18, LAMOST DR9, DESI EDR, and Gaia DR3. Results are validated using $1.4 10^5$ objects and cross-checked against theoretical model predictions. BANNJOS outperforms all previous classifiers in terms of accuracy, precision, and completeness across the entire magnitude range. It delivers over 95% accuracy for objects brighter than $r = 21.5$ mag, and ~90% accuracy for those up to $r = 22$ mag, where J-PLUS completeness is &lt; 25%. BANNJOS is also the first object classifier to provide the full probability distribution function (PDF) of the classification, enabling precise object selection for high purity or completeness, and for identifying objects with complex features, like active galactic nuclei with resolved host galaxies. BANNJOS has effectively classified J-PLUS sources into around 20 million galaxies, 1 million QSOs, and 26 million stars, with full PDFs for each, which allow for later refinement of the sample. The upcoming J-PAS survey, with its 56 color bands, will further enhance BANNJOS's ability to detail each source's nature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16567v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. del Pino, C. L\'opez-Sanjuan, A. Hern\'an-Caballero, H. Dom\'inguez-S\'anchez, R. von Marttens, J. A. Fern\'andez-Ontiveros, P. R. T. Coelho, A. Lumbreras-Calle, J. Vega-Ferrero, F. Jimenez-Esteban, P. Cruz, V. Marra, M. Quartin, C. A. Galarza, R. E. Angulo, A. J. Cenarro, D. Crist\'obal-Hornillos, R. A. Dupke, A. Ederoclite, C. Hern\'andez-Monteagudo, A. Mar\'in-Franch, M. Moles, L. Sodr\'e Jr., J. Varela, H. V\'azquez Rami\'o</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A general polarimetric model for transiting and non-transiting ringed exoplanets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16606</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16606v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the potential of polarimetry as a tool for detecting and characterizing exorings. For that purpose, we have improved the publicly available photometric code Pryngles by adding the results of radiative transfer calculations that fully include polarization and scattering by irregularly shaped particles. With this improved code, we compute the total and polarized fluxes and the degree of polarization of a ringed gas giant along its orbit. We vary key model parameters such as the orbit inclination, ring size and orientation, particle albedo and optical thickness, and demonstrate the versatility of our code by predicting the total and polarized fluxes of the "puffed-up" planet HIP41378f assuming this planet has an opaque dusty ring. We find that spatially unresolved dusty rings can significantly modify the flux and polarization signals of the light that is reflected. Rings are expected to have a low polarization signal and will generally decrease the degree of polarization as the ring casts a shadow on the planet and/or blocks part of the light the planet reflects. During ring-plane crossings, when the thin ring is illuminated edge-on, a ringed exoplanet's flux and degree of polarization are close to those of a ring-less planet and generally appear as sharp changes in the flux and polarization curves. Ringed planets in edge-on orbits tend to be difficult to distinguish from ring-less planets in reflected flux and degree of polarization. We show that if HIP41378f is surrounded by a ring, its reflected flux (compared to the star) will be of the order of $10^{-9}$, and the ring would decrease the degree of polarization in a detectable way. The improved version of the photometric code Pryngles that we present here shows that dusty rings may produce distinct polarimetric features in light curves across a wide range of orbital configurations, orientations and ring optical properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16606v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Allard K. Veenstra, Jorge I. Zuluaga, Jaime A. Alvarado-Montes, Mario Sucerquia, Daphne M. Stam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The azimuthal distribution of ejecta mass from oblique impacts into sand</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16677</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16677v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We measure ejecta mass as a function of azimuthal and impact angle for 104 m/s oblique impacts into sand. We find that the ejecta mass distribution is strongly sensitive to azimuthal angle with up to 8 times more mass in ejecta on the downrange side compared to the uprange side. Crater radii, measured from the site of impact, are measured at different impact and azimuthal angles. Crater ejecta scaling laws are modified to depend on azimuthal and impact angle. We find that crater radii are sensitive to both impact and azimuthal angle but the ejecta mass as a function of both angles can be estimated from the cube of the crater radius without an additional angular dependent function. The ejecta distributions are relevant for processes that depend upon the integrated properties of intermediate velocity impacts occurring in the outer solar system and possibly during planetesimal formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16677v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alice C. Quillen, Sean Doran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure-Preserving Oscillation-Eliminating Discontinuous Galerkin Schemes for Ideal MHD Equations: Locally Divergence-Free and Positivity-Preserving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16794v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper develops structure-preserving, oscillation-eliminating discontinuous Galerkin (OEDG) schemes for ideal magnetohydrodynamics (MHD), as a sequel to our recent work [Peng, Sun, and Wu, OEDG: Oscillation-eliminating discontinuous Galerkin method for hyperbolic conservation laws, 2023]. The schemes are based on a locally divergence-free (LDF) oscillation-eliminating (OE) procedure to suppress spurious oscillations while maintaining many of the good properties of original DG schemes, such as conservation, local compactness, and optimal convergence rates. The OE procedure is built on the solution operator of a novel damping equation -- a simple linear ordinary differential equation (ODE) whose exact solution can be exactly formulated. Because this OE procedure does not interfere with DG spatial discretization and RK stage update, it can be easily incorporated to existing DG codes as an independent module. These features make the proposed LDF OEDG schemes highly efficient and easy to implement.In addition, we present a positivity-preserving (PP) analysis of the LDF OEDG schemes on Cartesian meshes via the optimal convex decomposition technique and the geometric quasi-linearization (GQL) approach. Efficient PP LDF OEDG schemes are obtained with the HLL flux under a condition accessible by the simple local scaling PP limiter.Several one- and two-dimensional MHD tests confirm the accuracy, effectiveness, and robustness of the proposed structure-preserving OEDG schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16794v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengqing Liu, Kailiang Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curvature in the very-high energy gamma-ray spectrum of M87</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.13330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.13330v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The radio galaxy M87 is a variable very-high energy (VHE) gamma-ray source, exhibiting three major flares reported in 2005, 2008, and 2010. Despite extensive studies, the origin of the VHE gamma-ray emission is yet to be understood. In this study, we investigate the VHE gamma-ray spectrum of M87 during states of high gamma-ray activity, utilizing 20.2$\,$ hours the H.E.S.S. observations. Our findings indicate a preference for a curved spectrum, characterized by a log-parabola model with extra-galactic background light (EBL) model above 0.3$\,$TeV at the 4$\sigma$ level, compared to a power-law spectrum with EBL. We investigate the degeneracy between the absorption feature and the EBL normalization and derive upper limits on EBL models mainly sensitive in the wavelength range 12.4$\,$$\mu$m - 40$\,$$\mu$m.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.13330v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. E. S. S. Collaboration, F. Aharonian, F. Ait Benkhali, J. Aschersleben, H. Ashkar, M. Backes, V. Barbosa Martins, R. Batzofin, Y. Becherini, D. Berge, K. Bernl\"ohr, M. B\"ottcher, C. Boisson, J. Bolmont, M. de Bony de Lavergne, F. Bradascio, R. Brose, F. Brun, B. Bruno, T. Bulik C. Burger-Scheidlin, T. Bylund, S. Casanova, R. Cecil, J. Celic, M. Cerruti, T. Chand, S. Chandra, A. Chen, J. Chibueze, O. Chibueze, T. Collins, G. Cotter, J. Damascene Mbarubucyeye, A. Djannati-Ata\"i, J. Djuvsland, A. Dmytriiev, K. Egberts, S. Einecke, S. Fegan, G. Fontaine, S. Funk, S. Gabici, J. F. Glicenstein, J. Glombitza, G. Grolleron, L. Haerer, W. Hofmann, T. L. Holch, M. Holler, D. Horns, M. Jamrozy, F. Jankowsky, V. Joshi, I. Jung-Richardt, E. Kasai, K. Katarzy\'nski, R. Khatoon, B. Kh\'elifi, W. Klu\'zniak, Nu. Komin, K. Kosack, D. Kostunin, A. Kundu, R. G. Lang, S. Le Stum, F. Leitl, A. Lemi\`ere, M. Lemoine-Goumard, J. -P. Lenain, I. Lypova, A. Luashvili, J. Mackey, D. Malyshev, G. Mart\'i-Devesa, R. Marx, A. Mehta, M. Meyer, A. Mitchell, R. Moderski, M. O. Moghadam, L. Mohrmann, A. Montanari, E. Moulin, T. Murach, M. de Naurois, J. Niemiec, S. Ohm, L. Olivera-Nieto, E. de Ona Wilhelmi, S. Panny, M. Panter, R. D. Parsons, U. Pensec, S. Pita, G. P\"uhlhofer, M. Punch, A. Quirrenbach, M. Regeard, A. Reimer, O. Reimer, H. Ren, B. Reville, F. Rieger, B. Rudak, E. Ruiz-Velasco, V. Sahakian, H. Salzmann, A. Santangelo, M. Sasaki, F. Sch\"ussler, H. M. Schutte, J. N. S. Shapopi, H. Sol, S. Spencer, {\L}. Stawarz, R. Steenkamp, S. Steinmassl, C. Steppa, K. Streil, T. Takahashi, T. Tanaka, A. M. Taylor, R. Terrier, M. Tsirou, C. van Eldik, C. Venter, J. Vink, T. Wach, S. J. Wagner, A. Wierzcholska, M. Zacharias, A. A. Zdziarski, A. Zech, P. Zilberman, N. Zywucka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physical Properties of Type II Supernovae Inferred from ZTF and ATLAS Photometric Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12620</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12620v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report an analysis of a sample of 186 spectroscopically confirmed Type II supernova (SN) light curves (LCs) obtained from a combination of Zwicky Transient Facility (ZTF) and Asteroid Terrestrial-impact Last Alert System (ATLAS) observations. We implement a method to infer physical parameters from these LCs using hydrodynamic models that take into account the progenitor mass, the explosion energy, and the presence of circumstellar matter (CSM). The CSM is modelled via the mass loss rate, wind acceleration at the surface of the progenitor star with a $\beta$ velocity law, and the CSM radius. We also infer the time of explosion, attenuation (A$_V$), and the redshift for each SN. Our results favor low-mass progenitor stars (M$_{ZAMS}$\,$&lt;$14\,$M_\odot$) with a dense CSM ($\dot{M}$ $&gt;$ 10$^{-3}$ [M$_\odot$ yr$^{-1}$], a CSM radius of $\sim$ 10$^{15}$ cm, and $\beta$ $&gt;$ 2). Additionally, we find that the redshift inferred from the supernova LCs is significantly more accurate than that inferred using the host galaxy photometric redshift, suggesting that this method could be used to infer more accurate host galaxy redshifts from large samples of SNe II in the LSST era. Lastly, we compare our results with similar works from the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12620v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier Silva-Farf\'an, Francisco F\"orster, Takashi J. Moriya, L. Hern\'andez-Garc\'ia, A. M. Mu\~noz Arancibia, P. S\'anchez-S\'aez, Joseph P. Anderson, John L. Tonry, Alejandro Clocchiatti</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
