<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 May 2024 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 31 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Motivating Emissions from Positive Energy Warp Bubbles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19381v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent research has proposed that advanced propulsion mechanisms such as warp drives are more physically feasible than previously thought, using positive energy sources potentially sourced by known classical physics. Motivated by this, we hypothesize that an advanced inter-planetary or interstellar civilization using warp drives at sub-luminal or super-luminal speeds will broadcast detectable emissions of their travels. These technosignatures would be of significant astronomical, physical, and technological interest. This paper seeks to motivate signatures from warp drive emissions due to intrinsic and extrinsic processes across several messenger types (electromagnetic, particle, and gravitational) and propose a research program to simulate such emissions in sufficient detail to search for their signatures through coordinated analyses across multiple observatories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19381v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erik W. Lentz, Ryan C. Felton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Ingot-like class of WaveFront Sensors for Laser Guide Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19415v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Full sky coverage Adaptive Optics on Extremely Large Telescopes requires the adoption of several Laser Guide Stars as references.With such large apertures, the apparent elongation of the beacons is absolutely significant.With few exceptions,WaveFront Sensors designed for Natural Guide Stars are adapted and used in suboptimal mode in this context. We analyse and describe the geometrical properties of a class of WaveFront Sensors that are specifically designed to deal with Laser Guide Stars propagated from a location in the immediate vicinity of the telescope aperture. We describe in three dimensions the loci where the light of the Laser Guide Stars would focus in the focal volume located behind the focal plane (where astronomical objects are reimaged). We also describe the properties of several types of optomechanical devices that, through refraction and reflections, act as perturbers for this new class of pupil plane sensors, which we call ingot WaveFront Sensor. We give the recipes both for the most reasonable complex version of these WaveFront Sensors, with 6 pupils, and for the simplest one, with only 3 pupils. Both of them are referred to the ELT case. Elements to have a qualitative idea of how the sensitivity of such a new class of sensors compared to conventional ones are outlined. We present a new class of WaveFront Sensors, by carrying out the extension to the case of elongated sources at finite distance of the pyramid WaveFront Sensor and pointing out which advantages of the pyramid are retained and how it can be adopted to optimize the sensing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19415v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roberto Ragazzoni, Elisa Portaluri, Davide Greggio, Marco Dima, Carmelo Arcidiacono, Maria Bergomi, Simone Di Filippo, Tania Sofia Gomes Machado, Kalyan Kumar Radhakrishnan Santhakumari, Valentina Viotto, Federico Battaini, Elena Carolo, Simonetta Chinellato, Jacopo Farinato, Demetrio Magrin, Luca Marafatto, Gabriele Umbriaco, Daniele Vassallo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development of the Low Frequency Telescope focal plane detector arrays for LiteBIRD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19455</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19455v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: LiteBIRD, a forthcoming JAXA mission, aims to accurately study the microwave sky within the 40-400 GHz frequency range divided into 15 distinct nominal bands. The primary objective is to constrain the CMB inflationary signal, specifically the primordial B-modes. LiteBIRD targets the CMB B-mode signal on large angular scales, where the primordial inflationary signal is expected to dominate, with the goal of reaching a tensor-to-scalar ratio sensitivity of $\sigma_r\sim0.001$. LiteBIRD frequency bands will be split among three telescopes, with some overlap between telescopes for better control of systematic effects. Here we report on the development status of the detector arrays for the Low Frequency Telescope (LFT), which spans the 34-161 GHz range, with 12 bands subdivided between four types of trichroic pixels consisting of lenslet-coupled sinuous antennas. The signal from the antenna is bandpass filtered and sensed by AlMn Transition-Edge Sensors (TES). We provide an update on the status of the design and development of LiteBIRD's LFT LF1 (40-60-78 GHz), LF2 (50-68-89 GHz) pixels. We discuss design choices motivated by LiteBIRD scientific goals. In particular we focus on the details of the optimization of the design parameters of the sinuous antenna, on-chip bandpass filters, cross-under and impedance transformers and all the RF components that define the LF1 and LF2 pixel detection chain. We present this work in the context of the technical challenges and physical constraints imposed by the finite size of the instrument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19455v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Ghigna, Aritoki Suzuki, Benjamin Westbrook, Christopher Raum, Hiroki Akamatsu, Shawn Beckman, Nicole Farias, Tijmen de Haan, Nils Halverson, Masashi Hazumi, Johannes Hubmayr, Greg Jaehnig, Adrian T. Lee, Samantha L. Stever, Yu Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implications of in-ice volume scattering for radio-frequency neutrino experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19472v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the last three decades, several experimental initiatives have been launched with the goal of observing radio-frequency signals produced by ultra-high energy neutrinos (UHEN) interacting in solid media. Observed neutrino event signatures comprise impulsive signals with duration of order the inverse of the antenna+system bandwidth, superimposed upon an incoherent (typically white noise) thermal noise spectrum. Although bulk volume scattering (VS) of external radio-frequency signals is well-studied within the radar and glaciological communities, and can, in principle, contribute to that background. However, thus far, neutrino experiments have neglected to account for VS when projecting event rates. Herein, we present both model-dependent and model-independent constraints on both coherent, and also incoherent volume scattering, and assess their impact on UHEN experiments. We find that VS contributions are only weakly constrained by extant data; stronger limits may be obtained with dedicated calibration experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19472v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Nozdrina, D. Besson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Sixteen Multiple-Amplifier-Sensing CCD and Characterization Techniques Targeting The Next Generation of Astronomical Instruments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19505</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19505v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents a candidate sensor for future spectroscopic applications, such as a Stage-5 Spectroscopic Survey Experiment or the Habitable Worlds Observatory. This new type of CCD sensor features multiple in-line amplifiers at its output stage allowing multiple measurements of the same charge packet, either in each amplifier and/or in the different amplifiers. Recently, the operation of an 8-amplifier sensor has been experimentally demonstrated, and the operation of a 16-amplifier sensor is presented in this work. This new sensor enables a noise level of approximately $1^e_{\rm rms}$ with a single sample per amplifier. Additionally, it is shown that sub-electron noise can be achieved using multiple samples per amplifier. In addition to demonstrating the performance of the 16-amplifier sensor, this work aims to create a framework for future analysis and performance optimization of this type of detectors. New models and techniques are presented to characterize specific parameters, which are absent in conventional CCDs and Skipper-CCDs: charge transfer between amplifiers and independent and common noise in the amplifiers, and their processing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19505v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Agustin J. Lapi, Blas J. Irigoyen Gimenez, Miqueas E. Gamero, Claudio R. Chavez Blanco, Fernando Chierchie, Guillermo Fernandez Moroni, Stephen E. Holland, Juan Estrada, Javier Tiffenberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>14-m aperture deployable off-axis far-IR space telescope design for SALTUS observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Single Aperture Large Telescope for Universe Studies (SALTUS) is a deployable space telescope designed to provide the astrophysics community with an extremely large far-infrared (far-IR) space observatory to explore our cosmic origins. The SALTUS observatory can observe thousands of faint astrophysical targets, including the first galaxies, protoplanetary disks in various evolutionary states, and a wide variety of solar system objects. The SALTUS design architecture utilizes radiatively cooled, 14-m diameter unobscured aperture, and cryogenic instruments to enable both high spectral and spatial resolution at unprecedented sensitivity over a wavelength range largely unavailable to any existing ground or space observatories. The unique SALTUS optical design, utilizing a large inflatable off-axis primary mirror, provides superb sensitivity, angular resolution, and imaging performance at far-IR wavelengths over a wide +/-0.02 x 0.02 degree Field of View. SALTUS design, with its highly compact form factor, allows it to be readily stowed in available launch fairings and subsequently deployed in orbit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19584v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daewook Kim, Youngsik Kim, Heejoo Choi, Marcos Esparza, Oliver Wu, Yuzuru Takashima, Art Palisoc, Christopher Walker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IOP4, the Interactive Optical Photo-Polarimetric Python Pipeline</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20111</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20111v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: IOP4 is a pipeline to perform photometry and polarimetry analysis of optical data from Calar Alto (CAHA) and Sierra Nevada (OSN) observatories. IOP4 implements Object Relational Mapping (ORM) to seamlessly integrate all information about the reduction and results in a database which can be used to query and plot results, flag data and inspect the reduction process in an integrated fashion with the whole pipeline. It also ships with an already built-in web interface which can be used out of the box to browse the database and supervise all pipeline processes. It is built to ease debugging and inspection of data. Reduction from five different instruments are already implemented: RoperT90, AndorT90 and DIPOL (at OSN 0.9m telescope), AndorT150 (OSN 1.5m telescope) and CAFOS (CAHA 2.2m telescope). IOP4's modular design allows for easy integration of new observatories and instruments, and its results have already featured in several high-impact refereed publications. In this paper we describe the implementation and characteristics of IOP4.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20111v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Escudero Pedrosa, Ivan Agudo, Daniel Morcuende, Jorge Otero-Santos, Giacomo Bonnoli, Vilppu Piirola, C\'esar Husillos, Mabel Bernardos, Rub\'en L\'opez-Coto, Alfredo Sota, V\'ictor Casanova, Francisco Aceituno, Pablo Santos-Sanz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The key science drivers for the Atacama Large Aperture Submillimeter Telescope (AtLAST)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20140</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20140v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sub-mm and mm wavelengths provide a unique view of the Universe, from the gas and dust that fills and surrounds galaxies to the chromosphere of our own Sun. Current single-dish facilities have presented a tantalising view of the brightest (sub-)mm sources, and interferometers have provided the exquisite resolution necessary to analyse the details in small fields, but there are still many open questions that cannot be answered with current facilities: Where are all the baryons? How do structures interact with their environments? What does the time-varying (sub-)mm sky look like? In order to make major advances on these questions and others, what is needed now is a facility capable of rapidly mapping the sky spatially, spectrally, and temporally, which can only be done by a high throughput, single-dish observatory. An extensive design study for this new facility is currently being undertaken. In this paper, we focus on the key science drivers and the requirements they place on the observatory. As a 50m single dish telescope with a 1-2{\deg} field of view, the strength of the Atacama Large Aperture Submillimeter Telescope (AtLAST) is in science where a large field of view, highly multiplexed instrumentation and sensitivity to faint large-scale structure is important. AtLAST aims to be a sustainable, upgradeable, multipurpose facility that will deliver orders of magnitude increases in sensitivity and mapping speeds over current and planned telescopes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20140v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Booth, Pamela Klaassen, Claudia Cicone, Tony Mroczkowski, Sven Wedemeyer, Kazunori Akiyama, Geoffrey Bower, Martin A. Cordiner, Luca Di Mascolo, Doug Johnstone, Eelco van Kampen, Minju M. Lee, Daizhong Liu, John Orlowski-Scherer, Am\'elie Saintonge, Matthew Smith, Alexander E. Thelen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A theoretical study of the dissociative recombination of SH$^+$ with electrons through the $^2\Pi$ states of SH</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20147v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A quantitative theoretical study of the dissociative recombination of SH$^+$ with electrons has been carried out. Multireference, configuration interaction calculations were used to determine accurate potential energy curves for SH$^+$ and SH. The block diagonalization method was used to disentangle strongly interacting SH valence and Rydberg states and to construct a diabatic Hamiltonian whose diagonal matrix elements provide the diabatic potential energy curves. The off-diagonal elements are related to the electronic valence-Rydberg couplings. Cross sections and rate coefficients for the dissociative recombination reaction were calculated with a step-wise version of the multichannel quantum defect theory, using the molecular data provided by the block diagonalization method. The calculated rates are compared with the most recent measurements performed on the TSR ion storage ring in Heidelberg, Germany.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20147v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/1.4983690</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Chem. Phys. 146, 204109 (2017)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>D. O. Kashinski, D. Talbi, A. P. Hickman, O. E. Di Nallo, F. Colboc, K. Chakrabarti, I. F. Schneider, J. Zs Mezei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autonomous Disentangling for Spectroscopic Surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19391v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A suite of spectroscopic surveys is producing vast sets of stellar spectra with the goal of advancing stellar physics and Galactic evolution by determining their basic physical properties. A substantial fraction of these stars are in binary systems, but almost all large-survey modeling pipelines treat them as single stars. For sets of multi-epoch spectra, spectral disentangling is a powerful technique to recover or constrain the individual components' spectra of a multiple system. So far, this approach has focused on small samples or individual objects, usually with high resolution ($R \gtrsim 10.000$) spectra and many epochs ($\gtrsim 8$). Here, we present a disentangling implementation that accounts for several aspects of few-epoch spectra from large surveys: that vast sample sizes require automatic determination of starting guesses; that some of the most extensive spectroscopic surveys have a resolution of only $\approx 2,000$; that few epochs preclude unique orbit fitting; that one needs effective regularisation of the disentangled solution to ensure resulting spectra are smooth. We describe the implementation of this code and show with simulated spectra how well spectral recovery can work for hot and cool stars at $R \approx 2000$. Moreover, we verify the code on two established binary systems, the ``Unicorn'' and ``Giraffe''. This code can serve to explore new regimes in survey disentangling in search of massive stars with massive dark companions, e.g. the $\gtrsim 200,000$ hot stars of the SDSS-V survey.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19391v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/stae982</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Rhys Seeburger, Kareem El-Badry, Hans-Walter Rix, Maosheng Xiang, Morgan Fouesneau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tempered Multifidelity Importance Sampling for Gravitational Wave Parameter Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19407v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Estimating the parameters of compact binaries which coalesce and produce gravitational waves is a challenging Bayesian inverse problem. Gravitational-wave parameter estimation lies within the class of multifidelity problems, where a variety of models with differing assumptions, levels of fidelity, and computational cost are available for use in inference. In an effort to accelerate the solution of a Bayesian inverse problem, cheaper surrogates for the best models may be used to reduce the cost of likelihood evaluations when sampling the posterior. Importance sampling can then be used to reweight these samples to represent the true target posterior, incurring a reduction in the effective sample size. In cases when the problem is high dimensional, or when the surrogate model produces a poor approximation of the true posterior, this reduction in effective samples can be dramatic and render multifidelity importance sampling ineffective. We propose a novel method of tempered multifidelity importance sampling in order to remedy this issue. With this method the biasing distribution produced by the low-fidelity model is tempered, allowing for potentially better overlap with the target distribution. There is an optimal temperature which maximizes the efficiency in this setting, and we propose a low-cost strategy for approximating this optimal temperature using samples from the untempered distribution. In this paper, we motivate this method by applying it to Gaussian target and biasing distributions. Finally, we apply it to a series of problems in gravitational wave parameter estimation and demonstrate improved efficiencies when applying the method to real gravitational wave detections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19407v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bassel Saleh, Aaron Zimmerman, Peng Chen, Omar Ghattas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paths to Robust Exoplanet Science Yield Margin for the Habitable Worlds Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19418v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Habitable Worlds Observatory (HWO) will seek to detect and characterize potentially Earth-like planets around other stars. To ensure that the mission achieves the Astro2020 Decadal's recommended goal of 25 exoEarth candidates (EECs), we must take into account the probabilistic nature of exoplanet detections and provide "science margin" to budget for astrophysical uncertainties with a reasonable level of confidence. In this study, we explore the probabilistic distributions of yields to be expected from a blind exoEarth survey conducted by such a mission. We identify and estimate the impact of all major known sources of astrophysical uncertainty on the exoEarth candidate yield. As expected, eta_Earth uncertainties dominate the uncertainty in EEC yield, but we show that sampling uncertainties inherent to a blind survey are another important source of uncertainty that should be budgeted for during mission design. We adopt the Large UV/Optical/IR Surveyor Design B (LUVOIR-B) as a baseline and modify the telescope diameter to estimate the science margin provided by a larger telescope. We then depart from the LUVOIR-B baseline design and identify six possible design changes that, when compiled, provide large gains in exoEarth candidate yield and more than an order of magnitude reduction in exposure times for the highest priority targets. We conclude that a combination of telescope diameter increase and design improvements could provide robust exoplanet science margins for HWO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19418v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher C. Stark, Bertrand Mennesson, Steve Bryson, Eric B. Ford, Tyler D. Robinson, Ruslan Belikov, Matthew R. Bolcar, Lee D. Feinberg, Olivier Guyon, Natasha Latouf, Avi M. Mandell, Bernard J. Rauscher, Dan Sirbu, Noah W. Tuchow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Exoplanet Ephemerides by Leveraging Professional and Citizen Science Data: A Test Case with WASP-77A b</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19615v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present an updated ephemeris and physical parameters for the exoplanet WASP-77 A b. In this effort, we combine 64 ground- and space-based transit observations, 6 space-based eclipse observations, and 32 radial velocity observations to produce the most precise orbital solution to date for this target, aiding in the planning of James Webb Space Telescope (JWST) and Ariel observations and atmospheric studies. We report a new orbital period of 1.360029395 +- 5.7e-8 days, a new mid-transit time of 2459957.337860 +- 4.3e-5 BJDTDB (Barycentric Julian Date in the Barycentric Dynamical Time scale; arXiv:1005.4415) and a new mid-eclipse time of 2459956.658192 +- 6.7e-5 BJDTDB. Furthermore, the methods presented in this study reduce the uncertainties in the planet mass to 1.6654 +- 4.5e-3 Mjup and orbital period to 1.360029395 +- 5.7e-8 days by factors of 15.1 and 10.9, respectively. Through a joint fit analysis comparison of transit data taken by space-based and citizen science-led initiatives, our study demonstrates the power of including data collected by citizen scientists compared to a fit of the space-based data alone. Additionally, by including a vast array of citizen science data from ExoClock, Exoplanet Transit Database (ETD), and Exoplanet Watch, we can increase our observational baseline and thus acquire better constraints on the forward propagation of our ephemeris than what is achievable with TESS data alone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19615v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico R. Noguer, Suber Corley, Kyle A. Pearson, Robert T. Zellem, Molly N. Simon, Jennifer A. Burt, Isabela Huckabee, Prune C. August, Megan Weiner-Mansfield, Paul A. Dalba, Timothy Banks, Ira Bell, Dominique Daniel, Lindsay Dawson, Jes\'us De Mula, Marc Deldem, Dimitrios Deligeorgopoulos, Romina P. Di Sisto, Roger Dymock, Phil Evans, Giulio Follero, Martin J. F. Fowler, Eduardo Fern\'andez-Laj\'us, Alex Hamrick, Nicoletta Iannascoli, Andre O. Kovacs, Denis Henrique Kulh, Claudio Lopresti, Antonio Marino, Bryan E. Martin, Paolo Arcangelo Matassa, Tasso Augusto Napole\~ao, Alessandro Nastasi, Anthony Norris, Alessandro Odasso, Nikolaos I. Paschalis, Pavel Pintr, Jake Postiglione, Justus Randolph, Fran\c{c}ois Regembal, Lionel Rousselot, Sergio Jos\'e Gon\c{c}alves da Silva, Andrew Smith, Andrea Tomacelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Feasibility of meteor surveying from a Venus orbiter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20063v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Meteor and bolide phenomena caused by the atmospheric ablation of incoming meteoroids are predicted to occur at the planet Venus. Their systematic observation would allow to measure and compare the sub-mm to m meteoroid flux at different locations in the solar system. Using a physical model of atmospheric ablation, we demonstrate that Venus meteors would be brighter, shorter-lived, and appear higher in the atmosphere than Earth meteors. To investigate the feasibility of meteor detection at Venus from an orbiter, we apply the SWARMS survey simulator tool to sets of plausible meteoroid population parameters, atmospheric models and instrument designs suited to the task, such as the Mini-EUSO camera operational on the ISS since 2019. We find that such instrumentation would detect meteors at Venus with a 1.5x to 2.5x higher rate than at Earth. The estimated Venus-Earth detection ratio remains insensitive to variations in the chosen observation orbit and detector characteristics, implying that a meteor survey from Venus orbit is feasible, though contingent on the availability of suitable algorithms and methods for efficient on-board processing and downlinking of the meteor data to Earth. We further show that a hypothetical camera onboard the upcoming EnVision mission to Venus similar to the ISS instrument should detect many times more meteors than needed for an initial characterisation of the large meteoroid population at 0.7 au from the Sun.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20063v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Apostolos A. Christou, Maria Gritsevich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Solar System Notification Alert Processing System (SNAPS): Asteroid Population Outlier Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20176v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Solar System Notification Alert Processing System (SNAPS) is a ZTF and Rubin Observatory alert broker that will send alerts to the community regarding interesting events in the Solar System. SNAPS is actively monitoring Solar System objects and one of its functions is to compare objects (primarily main belt asteroids) to one another to find those that are outliers relative to the population. In this paper, we use the SNAPShot1 dataset which contains 31,693 objects from ZTF and derive outlier scores for each of these objects. SNAPS employs an unsupervised approach; consequently, to derive outlier rankings for each object, we propose four different outlier metrics such that we can explore variants of outlier scores and add confidence to outlier rankings. We also provide outlier scores for each object in each permutation of 15 feature spaces, between 2 and 15 features, which yields 32,752 total feature spaces. We show that we can derive population outlier rankings each month at Rubin Observatory scale using four Nvidia A100 GPUs, and present several avenues of scientific investigation that can be explored using population outlier detection.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20176v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-3881/ad4da5</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Michael Gowanlock, David E. Trilling, Daniel Kramer, Maria Chernyavskaya, Andrew McNeill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-delay interferometry with onboard optical delays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20196v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Time-delay interferometry (TDI) is a data processing technique for space-based gravitational-wave detectors to create laser-noise-free equal-optical-path-length interferometers virtually on the ground. It relies on the interspacecraft signal propagation delays, which are delivered by intersatellite ranging monitors. Also delays due to onboard signal propagation and processing have a nonnegligible impact on the TDI combinations. However, these onboard delays were only partially considered in previous TDI-related research; onboard optical path lengths have been neglected so far. In this paper, we study onboard optical path lengths in TDI. We derive analytical models for their coupling to the second-generation TDI Michelson combinations and verify these models numerically. Furthermore, we derive a compensation scheme for onboard optical path lengths in TDI and validate its performance via numerical simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20196v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Niklas Reinhardt, Philipp Euringer, Olaf Hartwig, Gerald Hechenblaikner, Gerhard Heinzel, Kohei Yamamoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Filter Design for Estimation of Stellar Metallicity: Insights from Experiments with Gaia XP Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20212v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We search for an optimal filter design for the estimation of stellar metallicity, based on synthetic photometry from Gaia XP spectra convolved with a series of filter-transmission curves defined by different central wavelengths and bandwidths. Unlike previous designs based solely on maximizing metallicity sensitivity, we find that the optimal solution provides a balance between the sensitivity and uncertainty of the spectra. With this optimal filter design, the best precision of metallicity estimates for relatively bright ($G \sim 11.5$) stars is excellent, $\sigma_{\rm [Fe/H]} = 0.034$\,dex for FGK dwarf stars, superior to that obtained utilizing custom sensitivity-optimized filters (e.g., SkyMapper\,$v$). By selecting hundreds of high-probabability member stars of the open cluster M67, our analysis reveals that the intrinsic photometric-metallicity scatter of these cluster members is only 0.036\,dex, consistent with this level of precision. Our results clearly demonstrate that the internal precision of photometric-metallicity estimates can be extremely high, even providing the opportunity to perform chemical tagging for very large numbers of field stars in the Milky Way. This experiment shows that it is crucial to take into account uncertainty alongside the sensitivity when designing filters for measuring the stellar metallicity and other parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20212v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Xiao, Bowen Huang, Yang Huang, Haibo Yuan, Timothy C. Beers, Jifeng Liu, Maosheng Xiang, Xue Lu, Shuai Xu, Lin Yang, Chuanjie Zheng, Zhirui Li, Bowen Zhang, Ruifeng Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-sensitivity Kinetic Inductance Detector Arrays for the Probe Far-Infrared Mission for Astrophysics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.02175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.02175v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Far-infrared (far-IR) astrophysics missions featuring actively cooled telescopes will offer orders of magnitude observing speed improvement at wavelengths where galaxies and forming planetary systems emit most of their light. The PRobe far-Infrared Mission for Astrophysics (PRIMA), which is currently under study, emphasizes low and moderate resolution spectroscopy throughout the far-IR. Full utilization of PRIMA's cold telescope requires far-IR detector arrays with per-pixel noise equivalent powers (NEPs) at or below 1 x 10-19 W/rtHz. We are developing low-volume Aluminum kinetic inductance detector (KID) arrays to reach these sensitivities. We will present on the development of our long-wavelength (210 um) array approach, with a focus on multitone measurements of our 1,008-pixel arrays. We measure an NEP below 1 x 10-19 W/rtHz for 73 percent of our pixels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.02175v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Logan Foote (Matt), Chris Albert (Matt), Jochem Baselmans (Matt), Andrew Beyer (Matt), Nicholas Cothard (Matt), Peter Day (Matt), Steven Hailey-Dunsheath (Matt), Pierre Echternach (Matt), Reinier Janssen (Matt), Elijah Kane (Matt), Henry Leduc (Matt), Lun-Jun Liu (Matt), Hien Nguyen (Matt), Joanna Perido (Matt), Jason Glenn (Matt), Jonas Zmuidzinas (Matt),  Charles (Matt),  Bradford</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The BlackGEM telescope array I: Overview</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18923v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The main science aim of the BlackGEM array is to detect optical counterparts to gravitational wave mergers. Additionally, the array will perform a set of synoptic surveys to detect Local Universe transients and short time-scale variability in stars and binaries, as well as a six-filter all-sky survey down to ~22nd mag. The BlackGEM Phase-I array consists of three optical wide-field unit telescopes. Each unit uses an f/5.5 modified Dall-Kirkham (Harmer-Wynne) design with a triplet corrector lens, and a 65cm primary mirror, coupled with a 110Mpix CCD detector, that provides an instantaneous field-of-view of 2.7~square degrees, sampled at 0.564\arcsec/pixel. The total field-of-view for the array is 8.2 square degrees. Each telescope is equipped with a six-slot filter wheel containing an optimised Sloan set (BG-u, BG-g, BG-r, BG-i, BG-z) and a wider-band 440-720 nm (BG-q) filter. Each unit telescope is independent from the others. Cloud-based data processing is done in real time, and includes a transient-detection routine as well as a full-source optimal-photometry module. BlackGEM has been installed at the ESO La Silla observatory as of October 2019. After a prolonged COVID-19 hiatus, science operations started on April 1, 2023 and will run for five years. Aside from its core scientific program, BlackGEM will give rise to a multitude of additional science cases in multi-colour time-domain astronomy, to the benefit of a variety of topics in astrophysics, such as infant supernovae, luminous red novae, asteroseismology of post-main-sequence objects, (ultracompact) binary stars, and the relation between gravitational wave counterparts and other classes of transients</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18923v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul J. Groot (Radboud, UCT, SAAO), S. Bloemen (Radboud), P. Vreeswijk (Radboud), J. van Roestel (UvA), P. G. Jonker (Radboud), G. Nelemans (Radboud, SRON), M. Klein-Wolt (Radboud), R. Le Poole (Leiden), D. Pieterse (Radboud), M. Rodenhuis (NOVA), W. Boland (NOVA), M. Haverkorn (Radboud), C. Aerts (KU Leuven), R. Bakker (Radboud), H. Balster (Radboud), M. Bekema (NOVA), E. Dijkstra (NOVA), P. Dolron (Radboud), E. Elswijk (NOVA), A. van Elteren (Leiden), A. Engels (Radboud), M. Fokker (Radboud), M. de Haan (NOVA), F. Hahn (Radboud), R. ter Horst (NOVA), D. Lesman (NOVA), J. Kragt (NOVA), J. Morren (KU Leuven), H. Nillissen (Radboud), W. Pessemier (KU Leuven), A de Rijke (CWI), G. Raskin (KU Leuven), L. H. A. Scheers (CWI), M. Schuil (NOVA), S. T. Timmer (Radboud), I. Arcavi (Tel Aviv), N. Blagorodnova (U Barcelona), S. Biswas (Radboud), R. Breton (Manchester), H. Dawson (Potsdam), P. Dayal (Groningen), S. De Wet (UCT, SAAO), C. Duffy (Armagh), S. Faris (Tel Aviv), M. Fausnaugh (TTU), A. Gal-Yam (Weizmann), S. Geier (Potsdam), A. Horesh (HUJI), C. Johnston (Radboud, MPA, KU Leuven), R. A. D. Wijnands (UvA), D. Modiano (UvA), G. Katusiime (U Barcelona), C. Kelley (Radboud), A. Kosakowski (TTU), T. Kupfer (Hamburg), G. Leloudas (DTU Space), O. Mogawana (UCT, SAAO), J. Munday (Warwick), J. A. Paice (Durham), F. Patat (ESO), I. Pelisoli (Warwick), G. Ramsay (Armagh), P. T. Ranaivomanana (Radboud, KU Leuven), R. Ruiz-Carmona (NOIRLabs, HUJI), V. Schaffenroth (Potsdam, Tautenburg), S. Scaringi (Durham), F. Stoppa (Radboud), H. Tranin (U Barcelona), M. Uzundag (KU Leuven), S. Valenti (UC Davis), M. Veresvarska (Durham), H. C. I. Wichern (DTU Space), R. A. M. J. Wijers (UvA), E. Zimmerman (Weizmann)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gaia22dkvLb: A Microlensing Planet Potentially Accessible to Radial-Velocity Characterization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.03944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.03944v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report discovering an exoplanet from following up a microlensing event alerted by Gaia. The event Gaia22dkv is toward a disk source rather than the traditional bulge microlensing fields. Our primary analysis yields a Jovian planet with M_p = 0.59^{+0.15}_{-0.05} M_J at a projected orbital separation r_perp = 1.4^{+0.8}_{-0.3} AU, and the host is a ~1.1 M_sun turnoff star at ~1.3 kpc. At r'~14, the host is far brighter than any previously discovered microlensing planet host, opening up the opportunity of testing the microlensing model with radial velocity (RV) observations. RV data can be used to measure the planet's orbital period and eccentricity, and they also enable searching for inner planets of the microlensing cold Jupiter, as expected from the ''inner-outer correlation'' inferred from Kepler and RV discoveries. Furthermore, we show that Gaia astrometric microlensing will not only allow precise measurements of its angular Einstein radius theta_E, but also directly measure the microlens parallax vector and unambiguously break a geometric light-curve degeneracy, leading to definitive characterization of the lens system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.03944v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zexuan Wu, Subo Dong, Tuan Yi, Zhuokai Liu, Kareem El-Badry, Andrew Gould, L. Wyrzykowski, K. A. Rybicki, Etienne Bachelet, Grant W. Christie, L. de Almeida, L. A. G. Monard, J. McCormick, Tim Natusch, P. Zielinski, Huiling Chen, Yang Huang, Chang Liu, A. Merand, Przemek Mroz, Jinyi Shangguan, Andrzej Udalski, J. Woillez, Huawei Zhang, Franz-Josef Hambsch, P. J. Mikolajczyk, M. Gromadzki, M. Ratajczak, Katarzyna Kruszynska, N. Ihanec, Uliana Pylypenko, M. Sitek, K. Howil, Staszek Zola, Olga Michniewicz, Michal Zejmo, Fraser Lewis, Mateusz Bronikowski, Stephen Potter, Jan Andrzejewski, Jaroslav Merc, Rachel Street, Akihiko Fukui, R. Figuera Jaimes, V. Bozza, P. Rota, A. Cassan, M. Dominik, Y. Tsapras, M. Hundertmark, J. Wambsganss, K. Bakowska, A. Slowikowska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Hera Radio Science Experiment at Didymos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.11883</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.11883v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hera represents the European Space Agency's inaugural planetary defense space mission and plays a pivotal role in the Asteroid Impact and Deflection Assessment international collaboration with NASA DART mission that performed the first asteroid deflection experiment using the kinetic impactor techniques. With the primary objective of conducting a detailed post-impact survey of the Didymos binary asteroid following the DART impact on its small moon called Dimorphos, Hera aims to comprehensively assess and characterize the feasibility of the kinetic impactor technique in asteroid deflection while conducting an in-depth investigation of the asteroid binary, including its physical and compositional properties as well as the effect of the impact on the surface and shape of Dimorphos. In this work, we describe the Hera radio science experiment, which will allow us to precisely estimate critical parameters, including the mass, which is required to determine the momentum enhancement resulting from the DART impact, mass distribution, rotational states, relative orbits, and dynamics of the asteroids Didymos and Dimorphos. Through a multi-arc covariance analysis, we present the achievable accuracy for these parameters, which consider the full expected asteroid phase and are based on ground radiometric, Hera optical images, and Hera to CubeSats InterSatellite Link radiometric measurements. The expected formal uncertainties for Didymos and Dimorphos GM are better than 0.01% and 0.1%, respectively, while their J2 formal uncertainties are better than 0.1% and 10%, respectively. [...]</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.11883v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.pss.2024.105906</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Planetary and Space Science, 2024, 105906</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Edoardo Gramigna, Riccardo Lasagni Manghi, Marco Zannoni, Paolo Tortora, Ryan S. Park, Giacomo Tommei, S\'ebastien Le Maistre, Patrick Michel, Francesco Castellini, Michael Kueppers</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
