<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 05:00:40 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Decisively Demonstrating Roman CGI's TTR5 Requirement by Reimaging a Newly-Discovered Brown Dwarf Orbiting a Bright Accelerating Star</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09977v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose Roman Coronagraph project HLC/575 nm observations of a newly-discovered brown dwarf (HIP 71618 B) from the Subaru/OASIS survey of young accelerating stars, which is supported by NASA headquarters with the directive to identify targets for the Roman Coronagraph that could fulfill TTR5 requirements and be observed during the technology demonstration phase. The target and multiple bright PSF references are within/close to the Roman Continuous Viewing Zone. A high SNR detection of this companion would singlehandedly fulfill TTR5 and would be the first optical detection of a companion at $&lt;$10$^{-6}$ contrast.
  Roman CPP reference star vetting prioritizing stars that can be paired with HIP 71618 would aid the execution of a successful technology demonstration. Additional similar targets may be discovered from OASIS over the next few years that could increase CGI scheduling flexibility and enhance its scientific and technical return. A close collaborative partnership with the CPP team could ensure that they are schedulable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09977v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thayne Currie, Brianna Lacy, Mona El Morsy, Masayuki Kuzuhara, Naoshi Murakami, Danielle Bovie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The SPace-based InterFerometer Feasibility (SPIFF) Project: Enabling Future High-Resolution Astronomy Across the EM Spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10009v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A plethora of astronomical science cases can only be achieved with high angular resolution observations, and we can expect the number of these to grow as astronomers are constrained by the size limitations of single-aperture space telescopes, making space-based interferometry inevitable. However, the enabling technologies do not have flight heritage at the system level, and the concept remains immature to much of the community, meaning no direct-detection synthetic-aperture space-based interferometer has yet flown and an opportunity exists for the UK to take a world leading role. Here we propose the SPace-based InterFerometry Feasibility (SPIFF) Project as a program to address both issues simultaneously by: 1) completing a thorough survey of the science cases across the EM spectrum that would directly benefit from, or be impossible without, space-based interferometry; 2) down selecting key requirements via a Science Traceability Matrix mapping exercise; 3) host a workshop for the UK astronomical community to consolidate these findings; 4) build a technology demonstration mission to raise TRL and achieve flight heritage of critical technologies. Such a program positions the UK as the partner of choice for any future NASA or ESA space-based interferometry mission, allowing the UK to lead groundbreaking scientific discoveries, while also directly benefiting the UK industrial base by advancing domestic exportable technologies and building direct synergy with other UK space priorities. Indeed, the UK is uniquely positioned to lead in space-based interferometry, possessing a rare trifecta of domestic strengths: world-class expertise in ground-based interferometry and space-based instrumentation; commercial entities developing mission-critical technologies; and scientists whose research spans the full range of science cases that would benefit directly from space-based interferometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10009v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Berke Vow Ricketti, Victoria Yankelevich, Chris Benson, Renske Smit, Sebastian Kamann, Ettore Pedretti, Sebastian Marino, Gerard van Belle, Stephen Eales, Chris Bee, Mark Wyatt, Matthew Smith, Tim D. Pearce, Emily Williams, Rebecca Harwin, David Pearson, Andy Vick, Giorgio Savini, Taro Matsuo, Hiroshi Matsuo, Locke Spencer, David T. Leisawitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MorphZ: Enhancing evidence estimation through the Morph approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10283v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the Morph approximation, a class of product approximations of probability densities that selects low-order disjoint parameter blocks by maximizing the sum of their total correlations. We use the posterior approximation via Morph as the importance distribution in optimal bridge sampling. We denote this procedure by MorphZ, which serves as a post-processing estimator of the marginal likelihood. The MorphZ estimator requires only posterior samples together with the prior and likelihood, and is fully agnostic to the choice of sampler. We evaluate MorphZ's performance across statistical benchmarks, pulsar timing array (PTA) models, compact binary coalescence (CBC) gravitational-wave (GW) simulations and the GW150914 event. Across these applications, spanning low to high dimensionalities, MorphZ yields accurate evidence at substantially reduced computational cost relative to standard approaches, and can improve these estimates even when posterior coverage is incomplete. Its bridge sampling relative error diagnostic provides conservative uncertainty estimates. Because MorphZ operates directly on posterior draws, it complements exploration-oriented samplers by enabling fast and reliable evidence estimation, while it can be seamlessly integrated into existing inference workflows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10283v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>El Mehdi Zahraoui, Patricio Maturana-Russel, Avi Vajpeyi, Willem van Straten, Renate Meyer, Sergei Gulyaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating stellar atmospheric parameters and elemental abundances using fully connected residual network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10345</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10345v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stellar atmospheric parameters and elemental abundances are traditionally determined using template matching techniques based on high-resolution spectra. However, these methods are sensitive to noise and unsuitable for ultra-low-resolution data. Given that the Chinese Space Station Telescope (CSST) will acquire large volumes of ultra-low-resolution spectra, developing effective methods for ultra-low-resolution spectral analysis is crucial. In this work, we investigated the Fully Connected Residual Network (FCResNet) for simultaneously estimating atmospheric parameters ($T_\text{eff}$, $\log g$, [Fe/H]) and elemental abundances ([C/Fe], [N/Fe], [Mg/Fe]). We trained and evaluated FCResNet using CSST-like spectra (\textit{R} $\sim$ 200) generated by degrading LAMOST spectra (\textit{R} $\sim$ 1,800), with reference labels from APOGEE. FCResNet significantly outperforms traditional machine learning methods (KNN, XGBoost, SVR) and CNN in prediction precision. For spectra with g-band signal-to-noise ratio greater than 20, FCResNet achieves precisions of 78 K, 0.15 dex, 0.08 dex, 0.05 dex, 0.10 dex, and 0.05 dex for $T_\text{eff}$, $\log g$, [Fe/H], [C/Fe], [N/Fe] and [Mg/Fe], respectively, on the test set. FCResNet processes one million spectra in only 42 seconds while maintaining a simple architecture with just 348 KB model size. These results suggest that FCResNet is a practical and promising tool for processing the large volume of ultra-low-resolution spectra that will be obtained by CSST in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10345v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1674-4527/ae06ff</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Shuo Li et al 2025 Res. Astron. Astrophys. 25 125009</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shuo Li, Yin-Bi Li, A-Li Luo, Jun-Chao Liang, Hai-Ling Lu, Hugh R. A. Jones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Near Ultraviolet Transient Explorer (NUTEx): A CubeSat-Based NUV Imaging Payload for Transient Sky Surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10538v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Near Ultraviolet Transient Explorer (NUTEx) is a CubeSat-based near-ultraviolet (NUV) imaging payload designed for transient sky surveys and is currently under development. CubeSats are compact and cost-effective satellite platforms that have emerged as versatile tools for scientific exploration and technology demonstrations in space. NUTEx is an imaging telescope operating in the 200-300 nm wavelength range, intended for deployment on a micro-satellite bus. The optical system is based on a Ritchey Chretien (RC) telescope configuration, featuring a 146 mm primary mirror. The detector is a photon-counting microchannel plate (MCP) device with a solar-blind photocathode, paired with an in-house developed readout unit. The instrument has a wide field of view (FoV) of 4 deg, a peak effective area of approximately 18 sq cm at 260 nm, and can reach a sensitivity of 21 AB magnitude (SNR = 5) in a 200 second exposure. The primary scientific objective of NUTEx is to monitor the night sky for transient phenomena, such as supernova remnants, flaring M-dwarf stars, and other short-timescale events. The payload is currently scheduled for launch in Q2 2026. This paper presents the NUTEx instrument design, outlines its scientific goals and capabilities, and provides an overview of the electronics and mechanical subsystems, including structural analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10538v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3389/fspas.2025.1670437</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shubham Ghatul, Rekhesh Mohan, Jayant Murthy, Margarita Safonova, Praveen Kumar, Maheswar Gopinathan, Shubhangi Jain, Mahesh Babu S</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FAST-MEPSA: an optimised and faster version of peak detection algorithm MEPSA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10579v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present FAST-MEPSA, an optimised version of the MEPSA algorithm developed to detect peaks in uniformly sampled time series affected by uncorrelated Gaussian noise. Although originally conceived for the analysis of gamma-ray burst (GRB) light curves (LCs), MEPSA can be readily applied to other transient phenomena. The algorithm scans the input data by applying a set of 39 predefined patterns across multiple timescales. While robust and effective, its computational cost becomes significant at large re-binning factors. To address this, FAST-MEPSA introduces a sparser offset-scanning strategy. In parallel, building on MEPSA's flexibility, we introduce a 40th pattern specifically designed to recover a class of elusive peaks that are typically sub-threshold and lie on the rising edge of broader structures - often missed by the original pattern set. Both versions of FAST-MEPSA - with 39 and 40 patterns - were validated on simulated GRB LCs. Compared to MEPSA, the new implementation achieves a speed-up of nearly a factor 400 at high re-binning factors, with only a minor (~4%) reduction in the number of detected peaks. It retains the same detection efficiency while significantly lowering the false positive rate of low significance. The inclusion of the new pattern increases the recovery of previously undetected and sub-threshold peaks. These improvements make FAST-MEPSA an effective tool for large-scale analyses where a robust trade-off between speed, efficiency, and reliability is essential. The adoption of 40 patterns instead of the classical 39 is advisable when an enhanced efficiency in detecting faint events is desired. The code is made publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10579v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ascom.2025.101040</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Volume 55, April 2026, 101040</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Manuele Maistrello, Romain Maccary, Cristiano Guidorzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reaching diffraction-limited localization with coherent PTAs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Current pulsar timing array (PTA) analyses do not take full advantage of pulsar distance information, thereby missing out on improved angular resolution and on a potential factor-of-two gain in detection sensitivity for individual gravitational-wave (GW) sources. In this work, we investigate the impact of precise pulsar distance measurements on angular resolution as an extension to previous work measuring the angular resolution of a dense, isotropic PTA [Jow et al., 2025]. We present a coherent map-making technique that utilizes precise pulsar distance measurements to reach the diffraction-limited resolution of an individual source: $\delta \theta_{\mathrm{diff}} \sim (1/\mathrm{SNR})(\lambda_{\mathrm{GW}}/r) \approx 2~\mathrm{arcmin}$, where the SNR refers to the detection strength of the source. With this level of angular resolution, identifying an EM counterpart may become feasible, enabling multi-messenger follow-up. We show that for $\rm SNR=10$, which may be the current sensitivity level using a coherent analysis, the diffraction limit is reached with roughly 9 pulsars. Moreover, angular resolution scales sharply with the number of known pulsar distances as $\sim (1/\mathrm{SNR})^{N_{\mathrm{dist}}/2}$. Thus, each additional pulsar with high signal-to-noise timing and precise distance measurement can improve PTA resolution by an order of magnitude. The distance to the best-timed millisecond pulsar (PSR J0437$-$4715) is already constrained to sub-parsec levels. We argue, therefore, that a coherent analysis of PTA data, fully incorporating pulsar distance information, is timely.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10795v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna C. Tsai, Dylan L. Jow, Ue-Li Pen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A vision for ground-based astronomy beyond the 2030s: How to build ESO's next big telescope sustainably</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10902</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10902v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Astronomy is the study of the Universe and all the objects that it comprises. Our attention is therefore usually focused beyond Earth, home to the only form of life known today. However, how can we continue to explore the secrets of the Universe, if we stand by and watch our only home burn? We know that there is no Planet B. It is therefore urgent that, as astronomers, we collectively work to protect the Earth, allowing future generations the opportunity to continue to uncover the secrets of the cosmos. As astronomical facilities account for the majority of our community's carbon footprint, we propose guidelines that we hold crucial for the European Southern Observatory (ESO) to consider in the context of the Expanding Horizons programme as it plans a next-generation, transformational facility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10902v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laurane Fr\'eour, Mathilde Bouvier, Tony Mroczkowski, Callie Clontz, Fatemeh Zahra Majidi, Vasundhara Shaw, Olivier Absil, Anna Cabr\'e, Olivier Lai, Dylan Magill, Jake D. Turner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Eschatian Hypothesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09970v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The history of astronomical discovery shows that many of the most detectable phenomena, especially detection firsts, are not typical members of their broader class, but rather rare, extreme cases with disproportionately large observational signatures. Motivated by this, we propose the Eschatian Hypothesis: that the first confirmed detection of an extraterrestrial technological civilization is most likely to be an atypical example, one that is unusually "loud" (i.e., producing an anomalously strong technosignature), and plausibly in a transitory, unstable, or even terminal phase. Using a toy model, we derive conditions under which such loud civilizations dominate detections, finding for example that if a society is loud for only $10^{-6}$ of its lifetime, it must emit ${\gtrsim}1$% of its total observable energy budget during that phase to outrun quieter populations. The hypothesis naturally motivates agnostic anomaly searches in wide-field, multi-channel, continuous surveys as a practical strategy for a first detection of extraterrestrial technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09970v1</guid>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Kipping</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clues from $\mathcal{Q}$--A null test designed for line intensity mapping cross-correlation studies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.09984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.09984v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Estimating the auto power spectrum of cosmological tracers from line-intensity mapping (LIM) data is often limited by instrumental noise, residual foregrounds, and systematics. Cross-power spectra between multiple lines offer a robust alternative, mitigating noise bias and systematics. However, inferring the auto spectrum from cross-correlations relies on two key assumptions: that all tracers are linearly biased with respect to the matter density field, and that they are strongly mutually correlated. In this work, we introduce a new diagnostic statistic, \(\mathcal{Q}\), which serves as a data-driven null test of these assumptions. Constructed from combinations of cross-spectra between four distinct spectral lines, \(\mathcal{Q}\) identifies regimes where cross-spectrum-based auto-spectrum reconstruction is unbiased. We validate its behavior using both analytic toy models and simulations of LIM observables, including star formation lines ([CII], [NII], [CI],[OIII]) and the 21-cm signal. We explore a range of redshifts and instrumental configurations, incorporating noise from representative surveys. Our results demonstrate that the criterion \( \mathcal{Q} \approx 1 \) reliably selects the modes where cross-spectrum estimators are valid, while significant deviations are an indicator that the key assumptions have been violated. The \( \mathcal{Q} \) diagnostic thus provides a simple yet powerful data-driven consistency check for multi-tracer LIM analyses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.09984v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debanjan Sarkar, Ella Iles, Adrian Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Space-Based Time-Domain Revolution in Astrophysics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10002v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Space-based time-domain telescopes such as CoRoT, Kepler/K2 and TESS have profoundly impacted astrophysics over the past two decades. Continuous light curves with high cadence and high photometric precision are now available for millions of sources within our galaxy and beyond. In addition to revolutionizing exoplanet science, the data have enabled breakthroughs ranging from the solar system to stellar interiors, the transient universe, and active galaxies. The key summary points of this review are: (1) Stellar astrophysics has been transformed by the ability to probe the internal structures of stars, test the physics of stellar convection, connect stellar rotation and magnetic activity, and reveal complex variability in young stars. (2) Ages of stellar populations probe the formation history of our Milky Way, and binary star variability enables the detection of "dark" galactic populations such as solar-mass black holes and neutron stars. (3) Early-time observations of explosive transients provide new insights into the progenitors of supernovae, while the quasi-periodic variability of galaxies probes the physics of accretion processes onto supermassive black holes and the tidal disruption of stars. (4) Observations of solar system objects reveal asteroid compositions through their rotation periods and amplitudes, constrain the cloud structure of ice giants, and allow the discovery of new objects in the outer solar system. (5) Open data policies and software have contributed to remarkable scientific productivity and enabled discoveries by citizen scientists, including new exoplanets and exotic variability in mature Sun-like stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10002v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Huber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beyond prewhitening: detection of gravity modes and their period spacings in slowly pulsating B stars using the multitaper F-test</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10019v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gravity modes in main-sequence stars have traditionally been studied using a prewhitening approach, which iteratively identifies modes in the Fourier domain and subsequently tunes their frequencies, amplitudes, and phases through time-domain regression. While effective, this method becomes inefficient when analysing large volumes of long time-series data and often relies on subjective stopping criteria to determine the number of iterations. We aim to perform frequency extraction of gravity modes in slowly pulsating B (SPB) stars using a statistically robust, data-driven approach based on advanced power spectrum and harmonic analysis techniques. Our approach employs the multitaper non-uniform fast Fourier transform, mtNUFFT, a power spectrum estimator that addresses several statistical limitations of traditional methods such as the Lomb-Scargle periodogram. We apply its extension, the multitaper F-test, to extract coherent gravity modes from 4-year Kepler light curves of SPB stars and to search for period spacing patterns among the extracted modes. The multitaper F-test enables fast and accurate extraction of the properties of gravity modes with quasi-infinite lifetimes, preferentially selecting modes that exhibit purely periodic behaviour. Although the method typically extracts fewer frequencies than conventional prewhitening, it recovers most known modes and, in some cases, reveals new ones. We also find evidence for gravity modes with long but finite lifetimes, and detect more than one period spacing pattern in some of the studied SPB stars. Overall, the multitaper F-test offers a more objective and statistically sound alternative to prewhitening. It scales efficiently to large datasets containing thousands of pulsators, and has the potential to facilitate mode identification and to distinguish between the different excitation mechanisms operating in SPB stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10019v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aarya A. Patil, Conny Aerts, Nikki Y. N. Wang, Jordan Van Beeck, May G. Pedersen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refined M-type Star Catalog from LAMOST DR10: Measurements of Radial Velocities, $T_\text{eff}$, log $g$, [M/H] and [$\alpha$/M]</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10337</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10337v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Precise stellar parameters for M-type stars, the Galaxy's most common stellar type, are crucial for numerous studies. In this work, we refined the LAMOST DR10 M-type star catalog through a two-stage process. First, we purified the catalog using techniques including deep learning and color-magnitude diagrams to remove 22,496 non-M spectra, correct 2,078 dwarf/giant classifications, and update 12,900 radial velocities. This resulted in a cleaner catalog containing 870,518 M-type spectra (820,493 dwarfs, 50,025 giants). Second, applying a label transfer strategy using values from APOGEE DR16 for parameter prediction with a ten-fold cross-validated CNN ensemble architecture, we predicted $T_\text{eff}$, $\log g$, [M/H], and [$\alpha$/M] separately for M dwarfs and giants. The average internal errors for M dwarfs/giants are respectively: $T_\text{eff}$ 30/17 K, log $g$ 0.07/0.07 dex, [M/H] 0.07/0.05 dex, and [$\alpha$/M] 0.02/0.02 dex. Comparison with APOGEE demonstrates external precisions of 34/14 K, 0.12/0.07 dex, 0.09/0.04 dex, and 0.03/0.02 dex for M dwarfs/giants, which represents precision improvements of over 20\% for M dwarfs and over 50\% for M giants compared to previous literature results. The catalog is available at https://nadc.china-vo.org/res/r101668/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10337v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4365/ae1586</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Shuo Li et al 2025 ApJS 281 58</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shuo Li, Yin-Bi Li, A-Li Luo, Jun-Chao Liang, You-Fen Wang, Jing Chen, Shuo Zhang, Mao-Sheng Xiang, Hugh R. A. Jones, Zhong-Rui Bai, Xiao-Xiao Ma, Yun-Jin Zhang, Hai-Ling Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Does the Babcock-Leighton dynamo operate in rapidly rotating solar-type stars? Exploration using a 3D dynamo model at different rotation rates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10508v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Babcock-Leighton dynamo, which relies on the generation of a poloidal field through the decay and dispersal of tilted bipolar magnetic regions (BMRs), is a promising paradigm for explaining the features of the solar magnetic cycle. In rapidly rotating stars, BMRs are expected to emerge at high latitudes, which are less efficient in generating the poloidal field due to poor cross-equatorial cancellation. The operation of the Babcock-Leighton dynamo in rapidly rotating stars is therefore questionable. We, for the first time, using a 3D kinematic dynamo model, STABLE, explore this question. By taking large-scale flows from mean-field hydrodynamics models for stars rotating at different speeds, We conduct a series of dynamo simulations in rapidly rotating stars, exploring the following four cases of spot deposition, each based on a different assumption about toroidal flux tube rise: (i) radial rise, (ii) parallel rise to the rotation axis, (iii) parallel rise combined with an increase in Joy's law slope with the stellar rotation rate, and (iv) increasing time delay and spot size. We find cyclic magnetic fields in all cases except case IV of the 1-day rotating star, for which the magnetic field is irregular. For the parallel-rise cases, the magnetic field becomes quadrupolar, and for all other cases, it is dipolar. Our work demonstrates that the Babcock-Leighton dynamo may operate even in rapidly rotating stars with starspots appearing at higher latitudes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10508v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vindya Vashishth, Bidya Binay Karak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BinaryGFH-v2: Improved method to search for gravitational waves from sub-solar-mass, ultra-compact binaries using the Generalized Frequency-Hough Transform</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10539v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Observing gravitational waves from sub-solar-mass, inspiraling compact binaries would provide almost smoking-gun evidence for primordial black holes. Here, we develop a method to search for ultra-compact binaries with chirp masses ranging from $[10^{-2},10^{-1}]M_\odot$. This mass range represents a previously unexplored gap in gravitational-wave searches for compact binaries: it was thought that the signals would too long for matched-filtering analyses but too short for time-frequency pattern-recognition techniques. Despite this, we show that a pattern-recognition technique, the Generalized frequency-Hough (GFH), can be employed with particular modifications that allow us to handle rapidly spinning-up binaries and to increase the statistical robustness of our method, and call this improved method BinaryGFH-v2. We then design a hypothetical search for binaries in this mass regime, compare the empirical and theoretical sensitivities of this method, and project constraints on formation rate densities and the fraction of dark matter that primordial black holes could compose in both current- and future-generation gravitational-wave detectors. Our results show that our method can be used to search for sub-solar-mass, ultra-compact objects in a mass regime that remains to-date unconstrained with gravitational waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10539v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew L. Miller, Lorenzo Pierini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>nDspec: a new Python library for modelling multi-dimensional datasets in X-ray astronomy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10615v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The current fleet of X-ray telescopes produces a wealth of multi-dimensional data, allowing us to study sources in time, photon energy and polarization. At the same time, it has become increasingly clear that progress in our physical understanding will only come from studying these sources in multiple dimensions simultaneously. Enabling multi-dimensional studies of X-ray sources requires new theoretical models predicting these data sets, new methods to analyse them and a software framework to combine data, models and methods efficiently. In this paper, we introduce the alpha release of nDspec, a new python-based library designed to allow users to model one- and multi-dimensional datasets common to X-ray astronomy. In the alpha release, we focus on modelling time-averaged data as well as Fourier spectral-timing mode, but highlight how additional dimensions can be added. We discuss design philosophy and current features, and showcase an example use case by characterizing a NICER observation of a black hole X-ray binary. We also highlight current plans for extensions to other dimensions and new features.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10615v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Lucchini, Benjamin Ricketts, Phil Uttley, Daniela Huppenkothen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Applying the BF method on the DESI evidence for dynamical dark energy models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10763v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent baryon acoustic oscillation measurements from the DESI, when combined with CMB data and Type Ia supernovae observations, indicate a preference for dynamical dark energy when considering the Chevallier-Polarski-Linder (CPL) model, over the standard {\Lambda}CDM or the wCDM model. However, the Bayes factor, a key metric for model comparison, remains inconclusive on which model is preferred. This paper applies the BF method, that integrates both Bayesian and frequentist approaches to DESI data to address the limitations of purely frequentist or Bayesian methods. It consists in considering the Bayes factor as a random variable and calculates its distribution, that results from values computed in a frequentist approach after perturbing the data following the model considered. We apply this hybrid method to DESI data, comparing the CPL and w models under various prior conditions, including weak and strong priors, and theory-informed priors. We find that, when the traditional bayes factor is considered, that weak priors favor the w model over CPL, while strong priors favor CPL. Additionally, theory-informed priors further enhance the preference for the w model. While when we apply the BF method, the preference for CPL over w is seen in all cases albeit with similar but reduced impact on the p-value from the different prior considerations. We also tried to generalize further, by perturbing as well the covariance matrix following the model considered, and found that, in general, the current data in that case is not stringent enough to disentangle between the two models. Our results demonstrate that varying the Bayes factor as a random variable, providing that the covariance matrix is kept as model independent, provides a robust model comparison, reducing the impact of prior dependence as well as offering quantitative assessment of the preferences of the competing models.(abridged)</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10763v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziad Sakr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shedding Light on Large Space-Based Telescopes: Modeling Stray Light due to Primary Mirror Damage from Micrometeoroid Impacts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10915</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10915v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A large space-based telescope aimed at detecting and characterizing the atmospheres of Earth-like planets orbiting Sun-like stars will require unprecedented contrast and stability. However, damage to the primary mirror due to micrometeoroid impacts will provide a stochastic, time-dependent source of stray light in the coronagraph's field of view that could significantly lengthen exposure times and reduce the expected science yield. To better quantify the impact of stray light and inform the Habitable Worlds Observatory mission design process, we present estimates of stray light in different micrometeoroid damage scenarios for a broad range of targets, and use that to find the expected decrease in science yield (i.e., the expected number of detected exoEarth candidates). We find that stray light due to micrometeoroid damage may significantly reduce yield, by 30% -- 60% in some cases, but significant uncertainties remain due to the unknown maximum expected impactor energy, and the relationship between impact energy and expected crater size. Micrometeoroid damage therefore needs further exploration, as it has the potential to reduce scientific yield, and in turn drive the development of mitigation strategies, selection of telescope designs, and selection of observing priorities in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10915v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Megan T. Gialluca, Jonathan W. Arenberg, Chris Stark, Blake Shepherd, Victoria S. Meadows, Aki Roberge, Tyler D. Robinson, Robert Podgurski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Signatures of star formation inside galactic outflows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10924v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Observations have suggested that galactic outflows contain substantial amounts of dense and clumpy molecular gas, creating favourable conditions for igniting star formation. Indeed, theoretical models and hydrodynamical simulations have suggested that stars could form within galactic outflows, representing a new mode of star-formation that differs significantly from the typical star formation in star forming discs. In this paper, we examine 12 local galaxies with powerful Active Galactic Nuclei and high star-formation rate using spectroscopic data from the X-shooter spectrograph at the Very Large Telescope. We investigate the excitation mechanism and physical properties of these outflows via spatially resolved diagnostic diagrams (along with tests to rule out contribution by shocks and external photoionisation). Out of the seven galaxies with clearly detected outflows, we find robust evidence for star formation within the outflow of one galaxy (IRAS 20551-4250), with two additional galaxies showing tentative signs (IRAS 13120-5453 and F13229-2934). Therefore, our findings support previous results that star formation inside outflows can be a relatively common phenomenon among these active galaxies and may have played an important role in the formation and evolution of the spheroidal component of galaxies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10924v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dily Duan Yi Ong, Francesco D'Eugenio, Roberto Maiolino, Santiago Arribas, Francesco Belfiore, Enrica Bellocchi, Stefano Carniani, Sara Cazzoli, Giovanni Cresci, Andrew Fabian, Wako Ishibashi, Filippo Mannucci, Alessandro Marconi, Helen Russell, Eckhard Sturm, Giacomo Venturi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bringing together African &amp; European research communities with an inclusive astronomy conference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12834</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12834v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report on an international scientific conference, where we brought together African and European academic astronomers. This aimed to bridge the gap between those in position of privilege, with ease of access to international events (i.e., the typical experience of academics in Western institutions), with those historically excluded (affecting the majority of African scientists/institutions). We describe how we designed the conference around cutting-edge research problems, but with a parallel focus on building networking and professional relationships. Significant effort went into: (1) ensuring a diversity of participants; (2) practically and financially supporting those who may never have attended an international conference and; (3) creating an inclusive and supportive environment through a careful programme of activities, both before and during the event. Maintaining scientific integrity was a core commitment throughout. We summarise successes, challenges and lessons learnt from organising this conference. We also present feedback obtained from participants immediately after the conference, and a discussion of some longer-term impacts, which we identified around 1 year later. We found an overall achievement of our objectives, and multiple longer-term benefits. With this report we provide some key recommendations for groups, from any research field, who may wish to lead similar initiatives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12834v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chris M. Harrison (Newcastle University), Leah Morabito (Durham University), Ann Njeri (Newcastle University, on behalf of the Organising Committees)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euclid Quick Data Release (Q1): VIS processing and data products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15303</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15303v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper describes the VIS Processing Function (VIS PF) of the Euclid ground segment pipeline, which processes and calibrates raw data from the VIS camera. We present the algorithms used in each processing element, along with a description of the on-orbit performance of VIS PF, based on Performance Verification (PV) and Q1 data. We demonstrate that the principal performance metrics (image quality, astrometric accuracy, photometric calibration) are within pre-launch specifications. The image-to-image photometric scatter is less than $0.8\%$, and absolute astrometric accuracy compared to Gaia is $5$ mas Image quality is stable over all Q1 images with a full width at half maximum (FWHM) of $0.\!^{\prime\prime}16$. The stacked images (combining four nominal and two short exposures) reach $I_\mathrm{E} = 25.6$ ($10\sigma$, measured as the variance of $1.\!^{\prime\prime}3$ diameter apertures). We also describe quality control metrics provided with each image, and an appendix provides a detailed description of the provided data products. The excellent quality of these images demonstrates the immense potential of Euclid VIS data for weak lensing. VIS data, covering most of the extragalactic sky, will provide a lasting high-resolution atlas of the Universe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15303v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Euclid Collaboration, H. J. McCracken, K. Benson, C. Dolding, T. Flanet, C. Grenet, O. Herent, P. Hudelot, C. Laigle, G. Leroy, P. Liebing, R. Massey, S. Mottet, R. Nakajima, H. N. Nguyen-Kim, J. W. Nightingale, J. Skottfelt, L. C. Smith, F. Soldano, E. Vilenius, M. Wander, M. von Wietersheim-Kramsta, M. Akhlaghi, H. Aussel, S. Awan, R. Azzollini, A. Basset, G. P. Candini, P. Casenove, M. Cropper, H. Hoekstra, H. Israel, A. Khalil, K. Kuijken, Y. Mellier, L. Miller, S. -M. Niemi, M. J. Page, K. Paterson, M. Schirmer, N. A. Walton, A. Zacchei, J. P. L. G. Barrios, T. Erben, R. Hayes, J. A. Kegerreis, D. J. Lagattuta, A. Lan\c{c}on, N. Aghanim, B. Altieri, A. Amara, S. Andreon, P. N. Appleton, N. Auricchio, C. Baccigalupi, M. Baldi, A. Balestra, S. Bardelli, P. Battaglia, A. N. Belikov, R. Bender, F. Bernardeau, A. Biviano, A. Bonchi, E. Branchini, M. Brescia, J. Brinchmann, S. Camera, G. Ca\~nas-Herrera, V. Capobianco, C. Carbone, J. Carretero, S. Casas, F. J. Castander, M. Castellano, G. Castignani, S. Cavuoti, K. C. Chambers, A. Cimatti, C. Colodro-Conde, G. Congedo, C. J. Conselice, L. Conversi, Y. Copin, F. Courbin, H. M. Courtois, A. Da Silva, R. da Silva, H. Degaudenzi, G. De Lucia, A. M. Di Giorgio, J. Dinis, H. Dole, F. Dubath, X. Dupac, S. Dusini, A. Ealet, S. Escoffier, M. Fabricius, M. Farina, R. Farinelli, S. Ferriol, F. Finelli, P. Fosalba, S. Fotopoulou, N. Fourmanoit, M. Frailis, E. Franceschi, S. Galeotta, K. George, W. Gillard, B. Gillis, C. Giocoli, P. G\'omez-Alvarez, J. Gracia-Carpio, B. R. Granett, A. Grazian, F. Grupp, L. Guzzo, M. Hailey, S. V. H. Haugan, J. Hoar, W. Holmes, F. Hormuth, A. Hornstrup, K. Jahnke, M. Jhabvala, B. Joachimi, E. Keih\"anen, S. Kermiche, A. Kiessling, M. Kilbinger, B. Kubik, M. K\"ummel, M. Kunz, H. Kurki-Suonio, Q. Le Boulc'h, A. M. C. Le Brun, D. Le Mignant, S. Ligori, P. B. Lilje, V. Lindholm, I. Lloro, G. Mainetti, D. Maino, E. Maiorano, O. Mansutti, S. Marcin, O. Marggraf, M. Martinelli, N. Martinet, F. Marulli, D. C. Masters, S. Maurogordato, E. Medinaceli, S. Mei, M. Melchior, M. Meneghetti, E. Merlin, G. Meylan, A. Mora, M. Moresco, L. Moscardini, C. Neissner, R. C. Nichol, C. Padilla, S. Paltani, F. Pasian, K. Pedersen, W. J. Percival, V. Pettorino, S. Pires, G. Polenta, M. Poncet, L. A. Popa, L. Pozzetti, G. D. Racca, F. Raison, R. Rebolo, A. Renzi, J. Rhodes, G. Riccio, E. Romelli, M. Roncarelli, E. Rossetti, B. Rusholme, R. Saglia, Z. Sakr, A. G. S\'anchez, D. Sapone, B. Sartoris, J. A. Schewtschenko, P. Schneider, T. Schrabback, A. Secroun, G. Seidel, M. Seiffert, S. Serrano, P. Simon, C. Sirignano, G. Sirri, A. Spurio Mancini, L. Stanco, J. Steinwagner, P. Tallada-Cresp\'i, D. Tavagnacco, A. N. Taylor, H. I. Teplitz, I. Tereno, N. Tessore, S. Toft, R. Toledo-Moreo, F. Torradeflot, I. Tutusaus, E. A. Valentijn, L. Valenziano, J. Valiviita, T. Vassallo, G. Verdoes Kleijn, A. Veropalumbo, Y. Wang, J. Weller, G. Zamorani, F. M. Zerbi, I. A. Zinchenko, E. Zucca, V. Allevato, M. Ballardini, M. Bolzonella, E. Bozzo, C. Burigana, R. Cabanac, M. Calabrese, A. Cappi, D. Di Ferdinando, J. A. Escartin Vigo, G. Fabbian, L. Gabarra, M. Huertas-Company, J. Mart\'in-Fleitas, S. Matthew, N. Mauri, R. B. Metcalf, A. Pezzotta, M. P\"ontinen, C. Porciani, I. Risso, V. Scottez, M. Sereno, M. Tenti, M. Viel, M. Wiesmann, Y. Akrami, I. T. Andika, S. Anselmi, M. Archidiacono, F. Atrio-Barandela, C. Benoist, P. Bergamini, D. Bertacca, M. Bethermin, L. Bisigello, A. Blanchard, L. Blot, S. Borgani, A. S. Borlaff, M. L. Brown, S. Bruton, A. Calabro, B. Camacho Quevedo, F. Caro, C. S. Carvalho, T. Castro, F. Cogato, S. Conseil, A. R. Cooray, O. Cucciati, S. Davini, F. De Paolis, G. Desprez, A. D\'iaz-S\'anchez, J. J. Diaz, S. Di Domizio, J. M. Diego, P. -A. Duc, A. Enia, Y. Fang, A. M. N. Ferguson, A. G. Ferrari, A. Finoguenov, A. Fontana, A. Franco, K. Ganga, J. Garc\'ia-Bellido, T. Gasparetto, V. Gautard, E. Gaztanaga, F. Giacomini, F. Gianotti, A. H. Gonzalez, G. Gozaliasl, A. Gregorio, M. Guidi, C. M. Gutierrez, A. Hall, W. G. Hartley, C. Hern\'andez-Monteagudo, H. Hildebrandt, J. Hjorth, J. J. E. Kajava, Y. Kang, V. Kansal, D. Karagiannis, K. Kiiveri, C. C. Kirkpatrick, S. Kruk, J. Le Graet, L. Legrand, M. Lembo, F. Lepori, G. F. Lesci, J. Lesgourgues, L. Leuzzi, T. I. Liaudat, S. J. Liu, A. Loureiro, J. Macias-Perez, G. Maggio, M. Magliocchetti, F. Mannucci, R. Maoli, C. J. A. P. Martins, L. Maurin, C. J. R. McPartland, M. Miluzio, P. Monaco, A. Montoro, C. Moretti, G. Morgante, C. Murray, S. Nadathur, K. Naidoo, A. Navarro-Alsina, S. Nesseris, F. Passalacqua, L. Patrizii, A. Pisani, D. Potter, S. Quai, M. Radovich, P. Reimberg, P. -F. Rocci, G. Rodighiero, R. P. Rollins, S. Sacquegna, M. Sahl\'en, D. B. Sanders, E. Sarpa, C. Scarlata, A. Schneider, M. Schultheis, D. Sciotti, E. Sellentin, F. Shankar, A. Silvestri, K. Tanidis, C. Tao, G. Testera, M. Tewes, R. Teyssier, S. Tosi, A. Troja, M. Tucci, C. Valieri, A. Venhola, D. Vergani, G. Verza, P. Vielzeuf, J. R. Weaver, D. Scott</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Validating Angular Power Spectral Models for the Stochastic Gravitational-Wave Background Without Distributional Assumptions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16959v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It is demonstrated that estimators of the angular power spectrum commonly used for the stochastic gravitational-wave background (SGWB) lack a closed-form analytical expression for the likelihood function and, typically, cannot be accurately approximated by a Gaussian likelihood. Nevertheless, a robust statistical analysis can be performed to enable the estimation and testing of angular power spectral models for the SGWB without specifying distributional assumptions. Here, the technical aspects of the method are discussed in detail. Moreover, a new, consistent estimator for the covariance of the angular power spectrum is derived. The proposed approach is applied to data from the third observing run (O3) of Advanced LIGO and Advanced Virgo.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16959v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangyu Zhang, Erik Floden, Hongru Zhao, Sara Algeri, Galin Jones, Vuk Mandic, Jesse Miller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>fftvis: A Non-Uniform Fast Fourier Transform Based Interferometric Visibility Simulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02130v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The detection and characterization of the 21cm signal from the Epoch of Reionization (EoR) demands extraordinary precision in radio interferometric observations and analysis. For modern low-frequency arrays, achieving the dynamic range necessary to detect this signal requires simulation frameworks to validate analysis techniques and characterize systematic effects. However, the computational expense of direct visibility calculations grows rapidly with sky model complexity and array size, posing a potential bottleneck for scalable forward modeling. In this paper, we present fftvis, a high-performance visibility simulator built on the Flatiron Non-Uniform Fast-Fourier Transform (finufft) algorithm. We show that fftvis matches the well-validated matvis simulator to near numerical precision while delivering substantial runtime reductions, up to two orders of magnitude for dense, many-element arrays. We provide a detailed description of the fftvis algorithm and benchmark its computational performance, memory footprint, and numerical accuracy against matvis, including a validation study against analytic solutions for diffuse sky models. We further assess the utility of fftvis in validating 21cm analysis pipelines through a study of the dynamic range in simulated delay and fringe-rate spectra. Our results establish fftvis as a fast, precise, and scalable simulation tool for 21cm cosmology experiments, enabling end-to-end validation of analysis pipelines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02130v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tyler A. Cox, Steven G. Murray, Aaron R. Parsons, Joshua S. Dillon, Kartik Mandar, Zachary E. Martinot, Robert Pascua, Piyanat Kittiwisit, James E. Aguirre</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Light for the GRAVITY+ Adaptive Optics: Extreme Adaptive Optics for the Very Large Telescope Interferometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21431v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: GRAVITY+ improves by orders of magnitude the sensitivity, sky-coverage and contrast of the Very Large Telescope Interferometer (VLTI). A central part of this project is the development of Gravity Plus Adaptive Optics (GPAO), a dedicated high-order and laser-guide star Adaptive Optics (AO) system for VLTI. GPAO consists of four state-of-the-art AO systems equipping all 8m-class Unit Telescopes (UTs) for the wavefront correction of the VLTI instruments. It offers both visible and infrared Natural Guide Star (NGS) and Laser Guide Star (LGS) operations. The paper presents the design, operations and performances of GPAO. We illustrate the improvement brought by GPAO with interferometric observations obtained during the commissioning of the NGS mode end-2024. These science results include the first optical interferometry observations of a redshift $z\sim4$ quasar, the spectroscopy of a cool brown-dwarf with magnitude $K\sim 21.0$, the first observations of a Class I young star with GRAVITY, and the first sub-micro arcsecond differential astrometry in the optical. Together with the entire GRAVITY+ project, the implementation of GPAO is a true paradigm shift for observing the optical Universe at very high angular resolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21431v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>GRAVITY+ Collaboration,  :, F. Allouche, C. Bailet, M. Benisty, A. Berdeu, J. -P. Berger, P. Berio, A. Bigioli, C. Blanchard, O. Boebion, H. Bonnet, G. Bourdarot, P. Bourget, W. Brandner, J. Brul\'e, P. Burgos, M. Carbillet, C. Correia, B. Courtney Barrer, S. Curaba, R. Davies, D. Defr\`ere, A. Delboulb\'e, F. Delplancke, R. Dembet, A. Drescher, N. Dubost, A. Eckart, C. \'Edouard, F. Eisenhauer, L. Esteras Otal, M. Fabricius, H. Feuchtgruber, P. F\'edou, G. Finger, N. M. F\"orster Schreiber, R. Frahm, E. Garcia, P. Garcia, R. Garcia Lopez, R. Genzel, J. P. Gil, S. Gillessen, T. Gomes, F. Gont\'e, V. Gopinath, C. Gouvret, J. Graf, P. Guajardo, S. Guieu, W. Hackenberg, M. Hartl, X. Haubois, F. Hau{\ss}mann, T. Henning, P. Hibon, S. H\"onig, M. Horrobin, M. Houll\'e, N. Hubin, I. Ibn Taieb, L. Jochum, L. Jocou, A. Jost, J. Kammerer, L. Karl, A. Kaufer, P. Kern, P. Kervella, J. Kolb, H. Korhonen, L. Kreidberg, P. Krempl, S. Lacour, S. Lagarde, O. Lai, V. Lapeyr\`ere, R. Laugier, V. Leal, J. -B. Le Bouquin, J. Leftley, P. L\'ena, B. Lopez, D. Lutz, Y. Magnard, F. Mang, A. Marcotto, D. Maurel, A. M\'erand, F. Millour, M. Montarges, N. More, N. Moruj\~ao, T. Moulin, H. Nowacki, M. Nowak, S. Oberti, T. Ott, L. Pallanca, F. Patru, T. Paumard, K. Perraut, G. Perrin, P. O. Petrucci, R. Petrov, O. Pfuhl, N. Pourr\'e, S. Rabien, C. Rau, M. Riquelme, S. Robbe-Dubois, S. Rochat, M. Salman, J. S\'anchez-Berm\'udez, J. Schubert, J. Scigliuto, P. Shchekaturov, N. Schuhler, J. Shangguan, T. Shimizu, S. Scheithauer, C. Soenke, F. Soulez, E. Stadler, J. Stadler, C. Straubmeier, E. Sturm, M. Subroweit, C. Sykes, L. J. Tacconi, K. R. W. Tristram, S. Uysal, S. von Fellenberg, F. Widmann, E. Wieprecht, E. Wiezorrek, J. Woillez, S. Yazici, G. Zins</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pre-flight Background Estimates for COSI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25304v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Compton Spectrometer and Imager (COSI) is a Compton telescope designed to survey the 0.2 - 5 MeV sky, consisting of a compact array of cross-strip germanium detectors. It is planned to be launched in 2027 into an equatorial low-Earth (530 km) orbit with a prime mission duration of 2 years. The observation of MeV gamma rays is dominated by background, mostly from extragalactic and atmospheric photon but also from the activation of the detector materials induced by cosmic-ray interactions. Thus, background simulation and identification are crucial for the data analysis. In this work we perform Monte Carlo simulations of the background for the first 3 months in orbit, and we extrapolate the results to 2 years in orbit, in order to determine the build-up of the activation due to long-lived isotopes. We determine the rates of events induced by the background that are reconstructed as Compton events in the simulated COSI data. We find that the extragalactic background photons dominate at low energies (&lt;660 keV), while delayed activation from cosmic-ray primaries (proton/alpha) and albedo photons dominate at higher energies. As part of this work, a comparison at low latitude (&lt;1 deg) between recent measurement of the SAA by the High-Energy Particle Detector (HEPD-01) on board the China Seismo-Electromagnetic Satellite (CSES-01) and the AP9/AE9 model has been made, showing an overestimation of the flux by a factor 9 by the model. The systematic uncertainties associated with these components are quantified. This work marks a major step forward in estimating and understanding the expected background rates for the COSI satellite mission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25304v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Savitri Gallego, Uwe Oberlack, Jan Lommler, M. Christopher Karwin, Francesco Fenu, Valentina Fioretti, Andreas Zoglauer, F. M. Follega, A. Perinelli, Roberto Battiston, Roberto Iuppa, E. Steven Boggs, Saurabh Mittal, Pierre Jean, Carolyn Kierans, H. Dieter Hartmann, A. John Tomsick</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-impact Scientific Software in Astronomy and its creators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.12195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.12195v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the last decades, scientific software has graduated from a hidden side-product to a first-class member of the astrophysics literature. We aim to quantify the activity and impact of software development for astronomy, using a systematic survey. Starting from the Astrophysics Source Code Library and the Journal of Open Source Software, we analyse 3432 public git-based scientific software packages. Paper abstract text analysis suggests seven dominant themes: cosmology, data reduction pipelines, exoplanets, hydrodynamic simulations, radiative transfer spectra simulation, statistical inference and galaxies. We present key individual software contributors, their affiliated institutes and countries of high-impact software in astronomy &amp; astrophysics. We consider the number of citations to papers using the software and the number of person-days from their git repositories, as proxies for impact and complexity, respectively. We find that half of the mapped development is through US-affiliated institutes, and a large number of high-impact projects are led by a single person. Our results indicate that there are currently over 200 people active on any given day to improve software in astronomy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.12195v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/25c2cfeb.fe9c1f84</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Bulletin of the AAS, 2025, Dec 11, Volume 57</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Johannes Buchner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing models for angular power spectra: A distribution-free approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16079v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A novel goodness-of-fit strategy is introduced for testing models of angular power spectra with unknown parameters. Using this strategy, it is possible to assess the validity of such models without specifying the distribution of the angular power spectrum estimators. This holds under general conditions, ensuring the method's applicability in diverse applications. Moreover, the proposed solution overcomes the need for case-by-case simulations when testing different models, leading to notable computational advantages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16079v5</guid>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara Algeri, Xiangyu Zhang, Erik Floden, Hongru Zhao, Galin L. Jones, Vuk Mandic, Jesse Miller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trustworthy scientific inference with generative models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02602v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Generative artificial intelligence (AI) excels at producing complex data structures (text, images, videos) by learning patterns from training examples. Across scientific disciplines, researchers are now applying generative models to "inverse problems" to directly predict hidden parameters from observed data along with measures of uncertainty. While these predictive or posterior-based methods can handle intractable likelihoods and large-scale studies, they can also produce biased or overconfident conclusions even without model misspecifications. We present a solution with Frequentist-Bayes (FreB), a mathematically rigorous protocol that reshapes AI-generated posterior probability distributions into (locally valid) confidence regions that consistently include true parameters with the expected probability, while achieving minimum size when training and target data align. We demonstrate FreB's effectiveness by tackling diverse case studies in the physical sciences: identifying unknown sources under dataset shift, reconciling competing theoretical models, and mitigating selection bias and systematics in observational studies. By providing validity guarantees with interpretable diagnostics, FreB enables trustworthy scientific inference across fields where direct likelihood evaluation remains impossible or prohibitively expensive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02602v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Carzon, Luca Masserano, Joshua D. Ingram, Alex Shen, Antonio Carlos Herling Ribeiro Junior, Tommaso Dorigo, Michele Doro, Joshua S. Speagle, Rafael Izbicki, Ann B. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Markov Decision Process Framework for Early Maneuver Decisions in Satellite Collision Avoidance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05876v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a Markov decision process (MDP) framework to autonomously make guidance decisions for satellite collision avoidance maneuver (CAM) and a reinforcement learning policy gradient (RL-PG) algorithm to enable direct optimization of guidance policy using historic CAM data. In addition to maintaining acceptable collision risks, this approach seeks to minimize the average propellant consumption of CAMs by making early maneuver decisions. We model CAM as a continuous state, discrete action and finite horizon MDP, where the critical decision is determining when to initiate the maneuver. The MDP models decision rewards using analytical models of collision risk, propellant consumption, and transit orbit geometry. By deciding to maneuver earlier than conventional methods, the Markov policy effectively favors CAMs that achieve comparable rates of collision risk reduction while consuming less propellant. Using historical data of tracked conjunction events, we verify this framework and conduct an extensive parameter-sensitivity study. When evaluated on synthetic conjunction events, the trained policy consumes significantly less propellant overall and per maneuver in comparison to a conventional cut-off policy that initiates maneuvers 24 hours before the time of closest approach (TCA). On historical conjunction events, the trained policy consumes more propellant overall but consumes less propellant per maneuver. For both historical and synthetic conjunction events, the trained policy is slightly more conservative in identifying conjunctions events that warrant CAMs in comparison to cutoff policies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05876v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Ferrara, Lander W. Schillinger Arana, Florian D\"orfler, Sarah H. Q. Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Exoplanet Yield of Gaia Astrometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.04673v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We re-examine the expected yield of Gaia astrometric planet detections using updated models for giant-planet occurrence, the local stellar population, and Gaia's demonstrated astrometric precision. Our analysis combines a semi-analytic model that clarifies key scaling relations with more realistic Monte Carlo simulations. We predict $7{,}500 \pm 2{,}100$ planet discoveries in the 5-year dataset (DR4) and $120{,}000 \pm 22{,}000$ over the full 10-year mission (DR5), with the dominant error arising from uncertainties in giant-planet occurrence. We evaluate the sensitivity of these forecasts to the detection threshold and the desired precision for measurements of planet masses and orbital parameters. Roughly $1{,}900 \pm 540$ planets in DR4 and $38{,}000 \pm 7{,}300$ planets in DR5 should have masses and orbital periods determined to better than $20$%. Most detections will be super-Jupiters ($3$ - $13 M_{\rm J}$) on $2$ - $5$AU orbits around GKM-type stars ($0.4$ - $1.3 M_\odot$) within $500$ pc. Unresolved binary stars will lead to spurious planet detections, but we estimate that genuine planets will outnumber them by a factor of $5$ or more. An exception is planets around M-dwarfs with $a &lt; 1$AU, for which the false-positive rate is expected to be about $50$%. To support community preparation for upcoming data releases, we provide mock catalogs of Gaia exoplanets and planet-impostor binaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.04673v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caleb Lammers, Joshua N. Winn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Progress on the ALETHEIA project and a new approach to mitigate events overlap</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08954v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The ALETHEIA project aims to search for low-mass dark matter using liquid helium (LHe)-filled time projection chambers (TPCs). While liquid argon and liquid xenon TPCs have been extensively employed in the field of direct dark matter detection, successful development of LHe TPCs has not yet been achieved. Launched in 2020, our project has made significant progress since then. These advancements have convinced us that a single-phase LHe TPC is technologically feasible. Compared to liquid xenon and liquid argon TPCs, one of the unique challenges for LHe TPCs is event overlap caused by the 13-second lifetime scintillation. We will demonstrate that this overlap can be entirely mitigated when the LHe temperature is maintained near 1.0 K. At this temperature, electron mobility is three orders of magnitude higher than at approximately 4.0 K, which is the temperature we initially proposed for the LHe TPC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08954v2</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junhui Liao (on behalf of the ALETHEIA collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
