<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Local Galactic Transient Survey Applied to an Optical Search for Directed Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18903v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss our transient search for directed energy systems in local galaxies, with calculations indicating the ability of modest searches to detect optical Search for Extraterrestrial Intelligence (SETI) sources in the closest galaxies. Our analysis follows Lubin (2016) where a messenger civilization follows a beacon strategy we call "intelligent targeting." We plot the required laser time to achieve an SNR of 10 and find the time for a blind transmission to target all stars in the Milky Way to be achievable for local galactic civilizations. As high cadence and sky coverage is the pathway to enable such a detection, we operate the Local Galactic Transient Survey (LGTS) targeting M31 (the Andromeda Galaxy), the Large Magellanic Cloud (LMC), and the Small Magellanic Cloud (SMC) via Las Cumbres Observatory's (LCO) network of 0.4 m telescopes. We explore the ability of modest searches like the LGTS to detect directed pulses in optical and near-infrared wavelengths from Extraterrestrial Intelligence (ETI) at these distances and conclude a civilization utilizing less powerful laser technology than we can construct in this century is readily detectable with the LGTS's observational capabilities. Data processing of 30,000 LGTS images spanning 5 years is in progress with the TRansient Image Processing Pipeline (TRIPP; Thomas et al. (2025)).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18903v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Thomas, Natalie LeBaron, Luca Angeleri, Phillip Morgan, Varun Iyer, Prerana Kottapalli, Enda Mao, Samuel Whitebook, Jasper Webb, Dharv Patel, Rachel Darlinger, Kyle Lam, Kelvin Yip, Michael McDonald, Robby Odum, Cole Slenkovich, Yael Brynjegard-Bialik, Nicole Efstathiu, Joshua Perkins, Ryan Kuo, Audrey O'Malley, Alec Wang, Ben Fogiel, Sam Salters, Marlon Munoz, Natalie Kim, Lee Fowler, Ruiyang Wang, Philip Lubin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning in Gamma Astronomy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.19064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.19064v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The purpose of this paper is to review the most popular deep learning methods used to analyze astroparticle data obtained with Imaging Atmospheric Cherenkov Telescopes and provide references to the original papers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.19064v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3103/S002713492470214X</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>A. P. Kryukov, A. P. Demichev, V. A. Ilyin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematic Uncertainties in the Measurement of Neutron lifetime Using Lunar Prospector Neutron Spectrometer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18831v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The lifetime of free neutrons measured in the lab has a long standing disparity of $\sim$9~s. A space-based technique has recently been proposed to independently measure the neutron lifetime using interactions between the galactic cosmic rays and a low atmosphere planetary body. This technique has not produced competitive results yet due to constraints of non-optimized data that contain large systematic errors. We use data from the neutron spectrometer on-board NASA's Lunar Prospector, and quantify the effects of lunar sub-surface temperature and the composition on the measurement of neutron lifetime. We use the HeCd and HeSn neutron spectrometer data when the spacecraft was in a highly elliptical orbit during the orbit insertion period. We report the neutron lifetime using lunar composition maps at different resolutions: 5$^{\circ}$ Prettyman+2006 and 2$^{\circ}$ re-binned Wilson+2021 maps to be 777.59$\pm$11.71~s and 739.64$\pm$10.83~s respectively. Further, for the 20$^{\circ}$ map, we apply both a constant equatorial and a latitude-dependent temperature model and report 738.63$\pm$10.75~s and 767.33$\pm$11.17~s respectively. We report the weighted average of the four measurements to be $\tau_n = 754.72 ^{+34.58}_{-25.91}$~s.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18831v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akshatha Vydula, Daniel Coupland, Katherine Mesick, Craig Hardgrove</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A general method to reconstruct strong gravitational lenses based on the singular perturbative approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.15134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.15134v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The number of gravitational arcs systems detected is increasing quickly and should even increase at a faster rate in the near future. This wealth of new gravitational arcs requires the development of a purely automated method to reconstruct the lens and source. A general reconstruction method based on the singular perturbative approach is proposed in this paper. This method generates a lens and source reconstruction directly from the gravitational arc image. The method is fully automated and works in two steps. The first step is to generate a guess solution based on the circular solution in the singular perturbative approach. The second step is to break the sign degeneracy and to refine the solution by using a general source model. The refinement of the solution is conducted step by step to avoid the source-lens degeneracy issue. One important asset of this automated method is that the lens solution is written in universal terms which allows the computation of statistics. Considering the large number of lenses which should be available in the near future this ability to compute un-biased statistics is an important asset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.15134v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christophe Alard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>State-space algorithm for detecting the nanohertz gravitational wave background</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.06990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.06990v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The stochastic gravitational wave background (SGWB) can be observed in the nanohertz band using a pulsar timing array (PTA). Here a computationally efficient state-space framework is developed for analysing SGWB data, in which the stochastic gravitational wave strain at Earth is tracked with a non-linear Kalman filter and separated simultaneously from intrinsic, achromatic pulsar spin wandering. The filter is combined with a nested sampler to estimate the parameters of the model, and to calculate a Bayes factor for selecting between models with and without a SGWB. The procedure extends previous state-space formulations of PTA data analysis applied to individually resolvable binary black hole sources. The performance of the new algorithm is tested on synthetic data from the first International PTA Mock Data Challenge. It is shown that the algorithm distinguishes a SGWB from pure noise for $A_{\rm gw} \geq 3 \times 10^{-14}$, where $A_{\rm gw}$ denotes the standard normalization factor for a power spectral density with power-law exponent $-13/3$. Additional, systematic validation tests are also performed with synthetic data generated independently by adjusting the injected parameters to cover astrophysically plausible ranges. Full posterior distributions are recovered and tested for accuracy. The state-space procedure is memory-light and evaluates the likelihood for a standard-sized PTA dataset in $\lesssim 10^{-1}$ s without optimization on a standard central processing unit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.06990v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Kimpson, Andrew Melatos, Joseph O'Leary, Julian B. Carlin, Robin J. Evans, William Moran, Tong Cheunchitra, Wenhao Dong, Liam Dunn, Julian Greentree, Nicholas J. O'Neill, Sofia Suvorova, Kok Hong Thong, Andr\'es F. Vargas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning inference of the neutron star equation of state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17908v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a pipeline to infer the equation of state of neutron stars from observations based on deep neural networks. In particular, using the standard (deterministic), as well as Bayesian (probabilistic) deep networks, we explore how one can infer the interior speed of sound of the star given a set of mock observations of total stellar mass, stellar radius and tidal deformability. We discuss in detail the construction of our simulated dataset of stellar observables starting from the solution of the gravitational equations, as well as the relevant architectures for the deep networks, along with their performance and accuracy. We further explain how our pipeline is capable to detect a possible QCD phase transition in the stellar core. Our results show that deep networks offer a promising tool towards solving the inverse problem of neutron stars, and the accurate inference of their interior from future stellar observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17908v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/01/073</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Giulia Ventagli, Ippocratis D. Saltas</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
