<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 16 Sep 2025 02:41:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Commissioning and Testing of IceAct Telescopes at the IceCube Neutrino Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09778v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: IceAct is an array of imaging air Cherenkov telescopes located at the ice surface above the IceCube Neutrino Observatory. Each telescope features a silicon photomultiplier based 61 pixel camera and a Fresnel-lens as imaging optic, resulting in a 12-degree field of view. The design is optimized to be operated in harsh environments, particularly at the South Pole. The setup will consist of seven telescopes in a so-called fly's eye configuration, increasing the field of view to 36^\circ, and an additional telescope 200m apart for stereoscopic observations. Rigorous testing procedures have been performed before deployment to ensure that operation under these conditions is possible, e.g. night sky observations and cold temperature tests. Furthermore, on-site calibrations are used to verify the accuracy and reliability of the installation. We derive the geometric alignment of each IceAct telescope by comparing the directional reconstruction of muons measured with IceCube to the corresponding primary particle direction reconstruction from IceAct. This contribution presents these testing procedures. Additionally, we present the on-site alignment calibration, including a Graph Neural Network reconstruction for the primary particle direction in IceAct, verification on Monte Carlo simulation, and the application to a commissioning dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09778v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arun Vaidyanathan, Lars Heuermann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Progress toward a demonstration of high contrast imaging at ultraviolet wavelengths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09780v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: NASA's Habitable Worlds Observatory (HWO) aims to achieve starlight suppression to the $10^{-10}$ level for the detection and spectral characterization of Earth-like exoplanets. Broadband ozone absorption features are key biosignatures that appear in the 200-400nm near-ultraviolet (UV) regime. Extending coronagraphy from visible wavelengths to the UV, however, brings with it a number of challenges, including tighter requirements on wavefront sensing and control, optical surface quality, scattered light, and polarization aberrations, among other things. We aim to partially quantify and address these challenges with a combination of modeling, high-resolution metrology to the scales required for UV coronagraphy, and ultimately a demonstration of UV coronagraphy on the Space Coronagraph Optical Bench (SCoOB) vacuum testbed. In these proceedings, we provide a status update on our modeling and contrast budgeting efforts, characterization efforts to understand performance limitations set by key optical components, and our plans to move toward a demonstration of UV coronagraphy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09780v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kyle Van Gorkom, Ramya M. Anche, Christopher B. Mendillo, Jessica Gersh-Range, G. C. Hathaway, Saraswathi Kalyani Subramanian, Justin Hom, Tyler D. Robinson, Mamadou N'Diaye, Nikole K. Lewis, Bruce Macintosh, Ewan S. Douglas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stellar halo subtraction alternative for accreting companions' characterization with integral field spectroscopy: Analytical and on-sky demonstration on the PDS70, HTLup, and YSES1 systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09878v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Context. Medium-resolution IFS, such as MUSE at the VLT, are equipped to detect the emission lines of faint accreting companions when associated with dedicated stellar halo subtraction methods. We recently proposed a new approach based on polynomial modulations of a stellar spectrum estimate across the field of view, with orthogonal polynomials and lines masking. Aims. We seek to highlight and quantify analytically and on real data the benefits of this new approach over the one classically used, particularly with regard to distortions of the extracted spectra. Methods. We carried out analytical calculations based on simple toy models. Simulations of the most extreme situations identified were used to highlight these problems and corrections. Archival VLT/MUSE data of the young PDS70 and HTLup systems were used to vet the detection and characterization capabilities using on-sky observations. New images of the YSES1 planetary system were used to further illustrate the gains. Results. We show that the state-of-the-art method, based on low-pass filtering, can lead to the self-subtraction of the emission lines and modify the neighboring continua. We show that the proposed technique corrects these characterization problems, while maintaining the same detection capabilities. The two protoplanets PDS70 b and c were detected with 5sigma significance. The Halpha line estimate of the HTLup B stellar companion was improved by ~30% for the integrated flux and by ~8% for the 10%-width. As for YSES1 b, we found it uniquely displays a combination of Halpha, Hbeta, CaII H&amp;K triplet, and HeI lines in emission. Conclusions. The proposed method better preserves the spectral information, notably the emission line fluxes and profiles, while achieving similar detection performance. Based on a linear and parametric approach, it can be extended and/or combined with additional faint signal search algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09878v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Julo, M. Bonnefoy, F. Chatelain, O. Flasseur, O. J. J. Michel, S. Jorquera, P. Delorme, G. Chauvin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Differentiable Surrogate Model for the Generation of Radio Pulses from In-Ice Neutrino Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10274</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10274v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The planned IceCube-Gen2 radio neutrino detector at the South Pole will enhance the detection of cosmic ultra-high-energy neutrinos. It is crucial to utilize the available time until construction to optimize the detector design. A fully differentiable pipeline, from signal generation to detector response, would allow for the application of gradient descent techniques to explore the parameter space of the detector. In our work, we focus on the aspect of signal generation, and propose a modularized deep learning architecture to generate radio signals from in-ice neutrino interactions conditioned on the shower energy and viewing angle. The model is capable of generating differentiable signals with amplitudes spanning multiple orders of magnitude, as well as consistently producing signals corresponding to the same underlying event for different viewing angles. The modularized approach ensures physical consistency of the samples and leads to advantageous computational properties when using the model as part of a bigger optimization pipeline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10274v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philipp Pilar, Martin Ravn, Christian Glaser, Niklas Wahlstr\"om</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The CHARA Array Polarization Model and Prospects for Spectropolarimetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10451v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Polarimetric data provide key insights into infrared emission mechanisms in the inner disks of YSOs and the details of dust formation around AGB stars. While polarization measurements are well-established in radio interferometry, they remain challenging at visible and near-infrared due to the significant time-variable birefringence introduced by the complex optical beamtrain. In this study, we characterize instrumental polarization effects within the optical path of the CHARA Array, focusing on the H-band MIRC-X and K-band MYSTIC beam combiners. Using Jones matrix formalism, we developed a comprehensive model describing diattenuation and retardance across the array. By applying this model to an unpolarized calibrator, we derived the instrumental parameters for both MIRC-X and MYSTIC. Our results show differential diattenuation consistent with &gt;= 97% reflectivity per aluminum-coated surface at 45 deg incidence. The differential retardance exhibits small wavelength-dependent variations, in some cases larger than we expected. Notably, telescope W2 exhibits a significantly larger phase shift in the Coude path, attributable to a fixed aluminum mirror (M4) used in place of deformable mirrors present on the other telescopes during the observing run. We also identify misalignments in the LiNbO_3 birefringent compensator plates on S1 (MIRC-X) and W2 (MYSTIC). After correcting for night-to-night offsets, we achieve calibration accuracies of $\pm$ 3.4% in visibility ratio and $\pm$ 1.4 deg in differential phase for MIRC-X, and $\pm$ 5.9% and $\pm$ 2.4 deg, respectively, for MYSTIC. Given that the differential intrinsic polarization of spatially resolved sources, such as AGB stars and YSOs, typically greater than these instrumental uncertainties, our results demonstrate that CHARA is now capable of achieving high-accuracy measurements of intrinsic polarization in astrophysical targets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10451v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linling Shuai, John D. Monnier, Benjamin R. Setterholm, Stefan Kraus, Narsireddy Anugu, Tyler Gardner, Jean-Baptiste Le Bouquin, Gail H. Schaefer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Witnessing downsizing in the making: quiescent and breathing galaxies at the dawn of the Universe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09764v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: [Shortened for arXiv] We conduct a systematic search for $\log(M_\ast/M_\odot) \geq 9.5$ quiescent galaxies at $z &gt; 3$ in six extragalactic deep fields observed with NIRCam, with the goal of extracting their physical and statistical features in a uniform and self-consistent manner. We exploit the ASTRODEEP-JWST photometric catalogs to single out robust candidates, including sources quenched only a few tens of Myr before the observation. We apply a SED-fitting procedure which explores three functional forms of star formation history and the $\chi^2$ probabilities of the solutions, with additional checks to minimise the contamination from interlopers, tuning our selection criteria against available spectroscopic data from the DAWN archive and simulated catalogs. We select 633 candidates, which we rank by a reliability parameter based on the probabilities of the quiescent and alternative star-forming solutions, with 291 candidates tagged as "gold". According to the best-fit models, 79\% of the massive ($\log(M_\ast/M_\odot) \geq 10.5$) quiescent galaxies at $3 &lt; z &lt; 5$ stopped forming stars at least 150 Myr before the time of observation, while 89\% of low-mass sources have been quenched for less than 150 Myr. The abundance of low-mass old quiescent systems does not increase significantly with time from $z = 5$ to 3: low-mass objects seem to be experiencing a short episode of quenching followed by rejuvenation (``breathing''), consistent with a downsizing scenario of galaxy formation. We also find an abrupt drop in the density of massive quiescent candidates at $z &gt; 5$. We derive estimates for the number density of early passive galaxies up to $z = 10$ and compare them against various models: tensions with data remain in the modeling of the observed bimodality of time passed since quenching as a function of mass.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09764v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emiliano Merlin, Flaminia Fortuni, Antonello Calabr\'o, Marco Castellano, Paola Santini, Adriano Fontana, Lucas C. Kimmig, Francesco Shankar, Lorenzo Napolitano, Anton M. Koekemoer, Ray A. Lucas, Fabio Pacucci, Michael C. Cooper, Michaela Hirschmann, Pablo G. P\'erez-Gonz\'alez, Guillermo Barro, Mark Dickinson, Giovanni Gandolfi, Norman A. Grogin, Xin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Next generation direct RF sampling LLRF control and monitoring system for linear accelerators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09905v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The low-level RF (LLRF) systems for linear accelerating structures are typically based on heterodyne architectures. The linear accelerators normally have many RF stations and multiple RF inputs and outputs for each station, so the complexity and size of the LLRF system grows rapidly when scaling up. To meet the design goals of being compact and affordable for future accelerators, or upgrading existing ones, we have developed and characterized the next generation LLRF (NG-LLRF) platform based on the RF system-on-chip (RFSoC) for S-band and C-band accelerating structures. The integrated RF data converters in RFSoC sample and generate the RF signals directly without any analogue mixing circuits, which significantly simplified the architecture compared with the conventional LLRF systems. We have performed high-power tests for the NG-LLRF with the S-band accelerating structure in the Next Linear Collider Test Accelerator (NLCTA) test facility at SLAC National Accelerator Laboratory and a C-band structure prototyped for Cool Cooper Collider (CCC). The NG-LLRF platform demonstrated pulse-to-pulse fluctuation levels considerably better than the requirements of the targeted applications and high precision and flexibility in generating and measuring the RF pulses. In this paper, the characterization results of the platform with different system architectures will be summarized and a selection of high-power test results of the NG-LLRF will be presented and analyzed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09905v1</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. Liu, E. Snively, R. Herbst, K. Kim, E. A. Nanni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Doppler boosted LISA response to gravitational waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10038v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The future space-based gravitational wave observatory LISA is expected to detect massive black hole binaries (MBHBs) with high signal-to-noise ratios (SNRs), ranging up to thousands. Such high-precision observations require accurate modeling of the detector response. However, current derivations of the response function neglect the motion of the spacecraft during light travel time, omitting velocity-dependent terms of order $\beta = v/c \sim 10^{-4}$. In this work, we derive the velocity-dependent corrections to the gravitational wave response. We analyze the contribution of the velocity-terms for MBHBs in the mass range $[10^6,10^8]\:\mathrm{M}_{\odot}$ using a modified version of the state-of-the-art response simulator lisagwresponse. We find that corrections introduce residual SNRs up to $\sim 2$ for the loudest events and fractional differences up to $0.04\%$, compared to lisagwresponse. While small, these effects are comparable to current waveform modeling uncertainties and imprint distinctive sky-localization signatures, making them potentially relevant for parameter estimation of high-mass MBHBs and simulation of mock datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10038v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom van der Steen, Henri Inchausp\'e, Thomas Hertog, Aur\'elien Hees</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bertrand's Representation of the Optimal Detector</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10198</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10198v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is shown how the optimal detector of Gaussian signals can be represented in terms of Bertrand's class of time-frequency distributions. In this representation, the detector is a correlation between the corresponding time-frequency distributions. Since Bertrand's class is related to the power-law chirp signals, the new representation can be useful for their detection. The new approach is shown to be more effective then other time-frequency methods for the case of phase-insensitive detection. The finding provides a complementary representation to Cohen's class representation in the time-frequency domain already known in the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10198v1</guid>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Lenok</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astroclimes -- measuring the abundance of CO$_2$ and CH$_4$ in the Earth's atmosphere using astronomical observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.10258</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.10258v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Monitoring the abundance of greenhouse gases (GHGs) such as carbon dioxide (CO$_2$) and methane (CH$_4$) is necessary to quantify their impact on global warming and climate change. Although a number of satellites and ground-based networks measure the total column volume mixing ratio (VMR) of these gases, they rely on sunlight, and column measurements at night are comparatively scarce. We present a new algorithm, Astroclimes, that hopes to complement and extend nighttime CO$_2$ and CH4 column measurements. Astroclimes can measure the abundance of GHGs on Earth by generating a model telluric transmission spectra and fitting it to the spectra of telluric standard stars in the near-infrared taken by ground-based telescopes. A Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) analysis on an extensive dataset from the CARMENES spectrograph showed that Astroclimes was able to recover the long term trend known to be present in the molecular abundances of both CO$_2$ and CH$_4$, but not their seasonal cycles. Using the Copernicus Atmosphere Monitoring Service (CAMS) global greenhouse gas reanalysis model (EGG4) as a benchmark, we identified an overall vertical shift in our data and quantified the long term scatter in our retrievals. The scatter on a 1 hour timescale, however, is much lower, and is on par with the uncertainties on individual measurements. Although currently the precision of the method is not in line with state of the art techniques using dedicated instrumentation, it shows promise for further development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.10258v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcelo Aron Fetzner Keniger, David Armstrong, Matteo Brogi, Siddharth Gandhi, Marina Lafarga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development of a Compton Imager Setup</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.08822</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.08822v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Hard X-ray photons with energies in the range of hundreds of keV typically undergo Compton scattering when they are incident on a detector. In this process, an incident photon deposits a fraction of its energy at the point of incidence and continues onwards with a change in direction that depends on the amount of energy deposited. By using a pair of detectors to detect the point of incidence and the direction of the scattered photon, we can calculate the scattering direction and angle. The position of a source in the sky can be reconstructed using many Compton photon pairs from a source. We demonstrate this principle in the laboratory by using a pair of Cadmium Zinc Telluride (CZT) detectors sensitive in the energy range of 20-200 keV, similar to those used in $\textit{AstroSat}$/CZT Imager (CZTI). The laboratory setup consists of the two detectors placed perpendicular to each other in a lead-lined box. The detectors are read out by a custom-programmed Xilinx PYNQ-Z2 FPGA board, and data are then transferred to a personal computer (PC)}. There are two key updates from CZTI: the detectors are read concurrently rather than serially, and the time resolution has been improved from $20~\mu$s to $7.5~\mu$s. We irradiated the detectors with a collimated $^{133}\mathrm{Ba}$ source and identified Compton scattering events for the 356 keV line. We run a Compton reconstruction algorithm to correctly infer the location of the source in the detector frame, with a location-dependent angular response measure of $16\deg-30\deg$. This comprises a successful technology demonstration for a Compton imaging camera in the hard X-ray regime. We present the details of our setup, the data acquisition process, and software algorithms, and showcase our results. We also quantify the limitations of this setup and discuss ways of improving the performance in future experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.08822v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anuraag Arya, Harmanjeet Singh Bilkhu, Sandeep Vishwakarma, Hrishikesh Belatikar, Varun Bhalerao, Abhijeet Ghodgaonkar, Jayprakash G. Koyande, Aditi Marathe, N. P. S. Mithun, Sanjoli Narang, Sudhanshu Nimbalkar, Pranav Page, Sourav Palit, Arpit Patel, Amit Shetye, Siddharth Tallur, Shriharsh Tendulkar, Santosh Vadawale, Gaurav Waratkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ImageMM: Joint multi-frame image restoration and super-resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03002</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03002v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A key processing step in ground-based astronomy involves combining multiple noisy and blurry exposures to produce an image of the night sky with an improved signal-to-noise ratio. Typically, this is achieved via image coaddition, and can be undertaken such that the resulting night sky image has enhanced spatial resolution. Yet, this task remains a formidable challenge despite decades of advancements. In this paper, we introduce ImageMM: a new framework based on the majorization-minimization (MM) algorithm for joint multi-frame astronomical image restoration and super-resolution. ImageMM uses multiple registered astronomical exposures to produce a nonparametric latent image of the night sky, prior to the atmosphere's impact on the observed exposures. Our framework also features a novel variational approach to compute refined point-spread functions of arbitrary resolution for the restoration and super-resolution procedure. Our algorithms, implemented in TensorFlow, leverage graphics processing unit acceleration to produce latent images in near real time, even when processing high-resolution exposures. We tested ImageMM on Hyper Suprime-Cam (HSC) exposures, which are a precursor of the upcoming imaging data from the Rubin Observatory. The results are encouraging: ImageMM produces sharp latent images, in which spatial features of bright sources are revealed in unprecedented detail (e.g., showing the structure of spiral galaxies), and where faint sources that are usually indistinguishable from the noisy sky background also become discernible, thus pushing the detection limits. Moreover, aperture photometry performed on the HSC pipeline coadd and ImageMM's latent images yielded consistent source detection and flux measurements, thereby demonstrating ImageMM's suitability for cutting-edge photometric studies with state-of-the-art astronomical imaging data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03002v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-3881/adfb72</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yashil Sukurdeep, Tam\'as Budav\'ari, Andrew J. Connolly, Fausto Navarro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mitigation of the Flexing-Filtering Effect in Time-Delay Interferometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04316v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In early 2024, ESA formally adopted the Laser Interferometer Space Antenna (LISA) space mission with the aim of measuring gravitational waves emitted in the millihertz range. The constellation employs three spacecraft that exchange laser beams to form interferometric measurements over a distance of 2.5 million kilometers. The measurements will then be telemetered down to Earth at a lower sampling frequency. Anti-aliasing filters will be used on board to limit spectral folding of out-of-band laser noise. The dominant noise in these measurements is laser frequency noise which does not cancel naturally in LISA's unequal-arm heterodyne interferometers. Suppression of this noise requires time-shifting of the data using delay operators to build virtual beam paths that simulate equal-arm interferometers. The non-commutativity of these delay operators and on-board filters manifests as a noise (flexing-filtering) that significantly contributes to the noise budget. This non-commutativity is a consequence of the non-flatness of the filter in-band. Attenuation of this noise requires high-order and computationally expensive filters, putting additional demands on the spacecraft. The following work studies an alternative method to reduce this flexing filtering noise via the introduction of a modified delay operator that accounts for the non-commutativity with the filter in the delay operation itself. Our approach allows us to reduce the flexing-filtering noise by over six orders of magnitude whilst reducing the dependency on the flatness of the filter. The work is supplemented by numerical simulations of the data processing chain that compare the results with those of the standard approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04316v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivani Harer, Martin Staab, Hubert Halloin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstruction of the depth of the shower maximum of air showers with the SD-750 surface detector of the Pierre Auger Observatory using neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.09328</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.09328v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The origin of ultra-high-energy cosmic rays (UHECRs) is one of the intriguing mysteries in astroparticle physics. In order to identify their sources, we need precise knowledge of the mass composition of UHECRs. The direct detection of UHECRs is not feasible at energies above 0.1 PeV, necessitating the use of mass-sensitive observables of extended air showers induced by UHECRs interacting with the atmosphere. One way to achieve high statistics for these mass-sensitive observables is to use ground-based detector arrays, such as the Surface Detector (SD) of the Pierre Auger Observatory. The SD consists of three sub-arrays of independent detector stations arranged in triangular grids with different spacings. Recently, it has been shown that neural networks (NNs) can extract mass-sensitive observables from data taken by the SD-1500, the largest sub-detector of the SD. In this contribution, we demonstrate the feasibility of using NNs to reconstruct a high-level shower observable, the depth of the shower maximum, from data simulated for and observed by the SD-750, the second-largest detector array nested within the SD-1500. A simulation study shows that the SD-750 NN exhibits behavior similar to that of an SD-1500 NN and outperforms the latter in the energy range [1, 10) EeV. Moreover, we show that, after performing a correction and calibration procedure, the predictions of the SD-750 NN are consistent with the measurement of the depth of the shower maximum obtained by the Fluorescence Detector of the Pierre Auger Observatory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.09328v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steffen Hahn (for the Pierre Auger Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid Construction of Joint Pulsar Timing Array Datasets: The Lite Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20949</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20949v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The International Pulsar Timing Array (IPTA)'s second data release (IPTA DR2) combines decades of observations of 65 millisecond pulsars from 7 radio telescopes. IPTA datasets should be the most sensitive datasets to nanohertz gravitational waves (GWs), but take years to assemble, often excluding valuable recent data. To address this, we introduce the IPTA "Lite" analysis, where a Figure of Merit is used to select an optimal PTA dataset to analyze for each pulsar, enabling immediate access to new data and preliminary results prior to full combination. We test the capabilities of the Lite analysis using IPTA DR2, finding that "DR2 Lite" can be used to detect the common red noise process with an amplitude of $A = 4.8^{+1.8}_{-1.8} \times 10^{-15}$ at $\gamma = 13/3$. This amplitude is slightly large in comparison to the combined analysis, and likely biased high as DR2 Lite is more sensitive to systematic errors from individual pulsars than the full dataset. Furthermore, although there is no strong evidence for Hellings-Downs correlations in IPTA DR2, we still find the full dataset is better at resolving Hellings-Downs correlations than DR2 Lite. Alongside the Lite analysis, we also find that analyzing a subset of pulsars from IPTA DR2, available at a hypothetical "early" stage of combination (EDR2), yields equally competitive results as the full dataset. Looking ahead, the Lite method will enable rapid synthesis of the latest PTA data, offering preliminary GW constraints before the superior full dataset combinations are available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20949v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/mnras/staf1420</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society, Volume 542, Issue 4, October 2025, Pages 3028-3048</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bjorn Larsen, Chiara M. F. Mingarelli, Paul T. Baker, Jeffrey S. Hazboun, Siyuan Chen, Levi Schult, Stephen R. Taylor, Joseph Simon, John Antoniadis, Jeremy Baier, R. Nicolaos Caballero, Aur\'elien Chalumeau, Zu-Cheng Chen, Ismael Cognard, Debabrata Deb, Valentina Di Marco, Timothy Dolch, Innocent O. Eya, Elizabeth C. Ferrara, Kyle A. Gersbach, Deborah C. Good, Huanchen Hu, Agastya Kapur, Shubham Kala, Michael Kramer, Michael T. Lam, William G. Lamb, T. Joseph W. Lazio, Kuo Liu, Yang Liu, Maura McLaughlin, David J. Nice, Benetge B. P. Perera, Antoine Petiteau, Scott M. Ransom, Daniel J. Reardon, Christopher J. Russell, Golam M. Shaifullah, Lorenzo Speri, Aman Srivastava, Gilles Theureau, Jingbo Wang, Jun Wang, Lei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Distribution-Free Approach to Testing Models for Angular Power Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16079v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A novel goodness-of-fit strategy is introduced for testing models of angular power spectra with unknown parameters. Using this strategy, it is possible to assess the validity of such models without specifying the distribution of the angular power spectrum estimators. This holds under general conditions, ensuring the method's applicability in diverse applications. Moreover, the proposed solution overcomes the need for case-by-case simulations when testing different models, leading to notable computational advantages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16079v4</guid>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara Algeri, Xiangyu Zhang, Erik Floden, Hongru Zhao, Galin L. Jones, Vuk Mandic, Jesse Miller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantifying the intrinsic variability due to randomness of the Auriga galaxy formation model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13440v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Numerical simulations have become an indispensable tool in astrophysics. To interpret their results, it is critical to understand their intrinsic variability, that is, how much the results change with numerical noise or inherent stochasticity of the physics model. We present a set of seven realisations of high-resolution cosmological zoom-in simulations of a Milky Way-like galaxy with the Auriga galaxy formation model. All realisations share the same initial conditions and code parameters, but draw different random numbers for the inherently stochastic parts of the model. We show that global galaxy properties at $z=0$, including stellar mass, star formation history, masses of stellar bulge and stellar disc, the radius and height of the stellar disk change by less than $10\%$ between the different realisations, and that magnetic field structures in the disc and the halo are very similar. In contrast, the star formation rate today can vary by a factor of two and the internal morphological structure of the stellar disc can change. The time and orbit of satellite galaxies and their galaxy properties when falling into the main halo are again very similar, but their orbits start to deviate after first pericenter passage. Finally, we show that changing the mass resolution of all matter components by a factor of $8$ in the Auriga model changes galaxy properties significantly more than the intrinsic variability of the model, and that these changes are systematic. This limits detailed comparisons between simulations at different numerical resolutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13440v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruediger Pakmor, Rebekka Bieri, Francesca Fragkoudi, Facundo A. Gomez, Robert J. J. Grand, Christine M. Simpson, Rosie Y. Talbot, Freeke van de Voort, Maria Werhahn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for GEMS: The Occurrence of Giant Planets orbiting M-dwarfs within 100 pc</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08773v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present results from a systematic search for transiting short-period Giant Exoplanets around M-dwarf Stars (GEMS; $P &lt; 10$ days, $R_p \gtrsim 8~R_\oplus$) within a distance-limited 100\,pc sample of 149,316 M-dwarfs using TESS-Gaia Light Curve (TGLC) data. This search led to the discovery of one new candidate GEM, following spectroscopic vetting of 12 additional candidates to eliminate astrophysical false positives and refine our occurrence rate estimates. We describe the development and application of the \texttt{TESS-miner} package and associated vetting procedures used in this analysis. To assess detection completeness, we conducted $\sim$ 72 million injection-recovery tests across $\sim$ 26,000 stars with an average of $\sim$3 sectors of data per star, subdivided into early-type (M0--M2.5), mid-type (M2.5--M4), and late-type (M4 or later) M-dwarfs. Our pipeline demonstrates high sensitivity across all M-dwarf subtypes within the injection bounds.
  We estimate the occurrence rates of short-period GEMS as a function of stellar mass, and combine our measured occurrence rates with those derived for FGK stars and fit an exponential trend with stellar mass, consistent with core-accretion theory predictions. We find GEMS occurrence rates of $0.067\% \pm 0.047\%$ for early-type M-dwarfs, $0.139\% \pm 0.069\%$ for mid-type, and $0.032\% \pm 0.032\%$ for late-type M-dwarfs, with a mean rate of $0.065^{+0.025}_{-0.027}\%$ across the full M-dwarf sample. We note that while our search spanned $1.0~\mathrm{days} &lt; P &lt; 10.0$ days, these occurrence rates were calculated using planets orbiting with $1.0~\mathrm{days} &lt; P &lt; 5.0$ days. This work lays the foundation for future occurrence rate investigations for GEMS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08773v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rowen I. Glusman, Caleb I. Ca\~nas, Shubham Kanodia, Te Han, Rachel B. Fernandes, Gu{\dh}mundur Stef\'ansson, Marissa Maney, Andrew Monson, Andrew Hotnisky, Suvrath Mahadevan, Michael Rodruck, Kristo Ment, Andrew McWilliam, William D. Cochran, Knicole D. Col\'on, Mark R. Giovinazzi, Jaime A. Alvarado-Montes, Chad F. Bender, Cullun H. Blake, Alexandra Boone, Scott A. Diddams, Arvind F. Gupta, Samuel Halverson, Daniel Krolikowski, Andrew S. J. Lin, Joe P. Ninan, Paul Robertson, Arpita Roy, Christian Schwab, Ryan Terrien, Johanna Teske, Jason T. Wright</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
