<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 04:00:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A Multi-Scale Attention-Enhanced Architecture for Gravity Wave Localization in Satellite Imagery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02704</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02704v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Satellite images present unique challenges due to their high object variability and lower spatial resolution, particularly for detecting atmospheric gravity waves which exhibit significant variability in scale, shape, and pattern extent, making accurate localization highly challenging. This variability is further compounded by dominant unwanted objects such as clouds and city lights, as well as instrumental noise, all within a single image channel, while conventional detection methods struggle to capture the diverse and often subtle features of gravity waves across varying conditions. To address these issues, we introduce YOLO-DCAT incorporating Multi Dilated Residual Convolution (MDRC) and Simplified Spatial and Channel Attention (SSCA), an enhanced version of YOLOv5 specifically designed to improve gravity wave localization by effectively handling their complex and variable characteristics. MDRC captures multi-scale features through parallel dilated convolutions with varying dilation rates, while SSCA focuses on the most relevant spatial regions and channel features to enhance detection accuracy and suppress interference from background noise. In our experiments, the improved model outperformed state-of-the-art alternatives, improving mean Average Precision (mAP) by over 14% and Intersection over Union (IoU) by approximately 17%, demonstrating significantly improved localization accuracy for gravity waves in challenging satellite imagery and contributing to more precise climate research and modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02704v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seraj Al Mahmud Mostafa, Jianwu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design and performance of "R-FLEX", a flexure-based fiber positioning robot for spectroscopic cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02730</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02730v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the design, fabrication, and testing of R-FLEX, a novel flexure mechanism for next-generation fiber-fed astronomical instruments. As the current Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) revolutionizes cosmology with over 56 million collected spectra using 5,000 robotic fiber positioners at 10.4 mm pitch, we project that future instruments will require 2.5-3x smaller fiber robots by area. R-FLEX enables precision radial motion for fiber robots mountable at 6.2 mm pitch, delivering repeatable positioning accuracy $\leq$ 5 $\mu$m over a 4 mm travel range. The travel range extends outside the robot's mechanical envelope, providing complete patrol coverage of the focal surface. The R-FLEX design must meet challenging requirements for parasitic motion &lt; 30 $\mu$m, angular misalignment &lt; 0.3{\deg}, 1 million cycle lifetime, operating in a mountaintop telescope environment, and is suitable for mass production of $\sim$30,000 units.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02730v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas R. Wenner, Joseph H. Silber, David J. Schlegel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>21st-Century Astrobiology Missions Should Seek These High-Confidence Biosignatures in Mid-Latitude Martian Ice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02746v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This white paper was submitted to NASA's Search For Life Science Analysis Group (SFL-SAG): To ensure that the first mission designed to seek signs of extant life since 1976 is able to produce an unambiguous biological interpretation, the SFL-SAG is tasked with identifying the most high-confidence, agnostic biosignatures which are targetable, detectable, and measurable in Martian subsurface mid-latitude ice. To aid in this effort, this white paper highlights three examples of target materials or phenomena, along with associated instrument concepts, which the SFL-SAG shall prioritize in its efforts to define the appropriate astrobiological strategy. These include 1) polyelectrolyte informational biopolymers, 2) macromolecular biological homochirality, and 3) chiral-specific metabolic reactions. The Agnostic Life Finding Association (ALFA) and University of Florida (UF) support the development of instrumentation that seeks these high-confidence biosignatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02746v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher Temby, Jan Spacek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NASIM: Revealing the low surface brightness Universe from legacy VISTA data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02780v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Near-infrared imaging is a powerful technique in observational astronomy, but the bright background, primarily from the Earth\'s atmosphere, makes the detection of faint features particularly challenging. To recover low surface brightness (LSB) structures in such data, we present NASIM (Near-infrared Automated low Surface brightness reduction In Maneage), a fully automated and reproducible data reduction pipeline optimised for VISTA/VIRCAM observations. NASIM builds on GNU Astronomy Utilities (Gnuastro) to effectively remove large-scale instrumental artefacts while preserving faint, diffuse emission. As a key science application, we focus on deep Ks-band observations of the Euclid Deep Field South (KEDFS), one of the deepest VISTA/VIRCAM datasets and a high-priority field for synergy with current and future facilities, including Euclid, JWST, LSST, Roman, Spitzer, and ALMA. With VIRCAM no longer operational, KEDFS now stands as a unique legacy dataset. We release selected tiles from the KEDFS survey and highlight science cases, including galaxy outskirts, LSB galaxies, and intracluster light, that demonstrate NASIM\'s ability to recover diffuse structures. A direct comparison with conventional VISTA data reduction pipelines demonstrates the advantages of NASIM in preserving diffuse emission without compromising compact source detection. All quantitative results presented in this paper are fully reproducible with Maneage (commit 4d32667).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02780v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202555929</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Elham Saremi, Ignacio Trujillo, Mohammad Akhlaghi, Zohreh Ghaffari, Johan H. Knapen, Manda Banerji, Helmut Dannerbauer, S\'ebastien Comer\'on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature and wind characteristics of Lenghu site for ventilation and structural design of large telescope enclosure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03122</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03122v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In recent years, a significant number of observatories and universities have been planning to construct optical and infrared telescopes at the Lenghu site in Qinghai Province due to the site's excellent seeing and clear night sky fraction. Although astronomical performances of the Lenghu site have been reported in detail by numerous papers, there were few reports showing statistics of temperature and wind characteristics in the traditional way required for the design of steel structures of large astronomical telescopes and enclosures, as well as the ventilation and air conditioning systems of these enclosures. This paper aims to present such new statistical data on temperature and wind conditions at the site, which could be helpful to inform and aid in such design decisions at the Lenghu site</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03122v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taoran Li, Lu Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation on deep learning-based galaxy image translation models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03291</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03291v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Galaxy image translation is an important application in galaxy physics and cosmology. With deep learning-based generative models, image translation has been performed for image generation, data quality enhancement, information extraction, and generalized for other tasks such as deblending and anomaly detection. However, most endeavors on image translation primarily focus on the pixel-level and morphology-level statistics of galaxy images. There is a lack of discussion on the preservation of complex high-order galaxy physical information, which would be more challenging but crucial for studies that rely on high-fidelity image translation. Therefore, we investigated the effectiveness of generative models in preserving high-order physical information (represented by spectroscopic redshift) along with pixel-level and morphology-level information. We tested four representative models, i.e. a Swin Transformer, an SRGAN, a capsule network, and a diffusion model, using the SDSS and CFHTLS galaxy images. We found that these models show different levels of incapabilities in retaining redshift information, even if the global structures of galaxies and morphology-level statistics can be roughly reproduced. In particular, the cross-band peak fluxes of galaxies were found to contain meaningful redshift information, whereas they are subject to noticeable uncertainties in the translation of images, which may substantially be due to the nature of many-to-many mapping. Nonetheless, imperfect translated images may still contain a considerable amount of information and thus hold promise for downstream applications for which high image fidelity is not strongly required. Our work can facilitate further research on how complex physical information is manifested on galaxy images, and it provides implications on the development of image translation models for scientific use.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03291v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hengxin Ruan, Qiufan Lin, Shupei Chen, Yang Wang, Wei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative AI for image reconstruction in Intensity Interferometry: a first attempt</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03398v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the last few years Intensity Interferometry (II) has made significant strides in achieving high-precision resolution of stellar objects at optical wavelengths. Despite these advancements, phase retrieval remains a major challenge due to the nature of photon correlation. This paper explores the application of a conditional Generative Adversarial Network (cGAN) to tackle the problem of image reconstruction in Intensity Interferometry. This approach successfully reconstructs the shape, size, and brightness distribution of a fast-rotating star from sparsely sampled, spatial power spectrum of the source, corresponding to II with four telescopes. Although this particular example could also be addressed using parameter fitting, the results suggest that with larger arrays much more complicated systems could be reconstructed by applying machine-learning techniques to II.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03398v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Km Nitu Rai, Yuri van der Burg, Soumen Basak, Prasenjit Saha, Subrata Sarangi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepAP: Deep Learning-based Aperture Photometry Feasibility Assessment and Aperture Size Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03400v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Aperture photometry is a fundamental technique widely used to obtain high-precision light curves in optical survey projects like Tianyu. However, its effectiveness is limited in crowded fields, and the choice of aperture size critically impacts photometric precision. To address these challenges, we propose DeepAP, an efficient and accurate two-stage deep learning framework for aperture photometry. Specifically, for a given source, we first train a Vision Transformer (ViT) model to assess its feasibility of aperture photometry. We then train the Residual Neural Network (ResNet) to predict its optimal aperture size. For aperture photometry feasibility assessment, the ViT model yields an ROC AUC value of 0.96, and achieves a precision of 0.974, a recall of 0.930, and an F1 score of 0.952 on the test set. For aperture size prediction, the ResNet model effectively mitigates biases inherent in classical growth curve methods by adaptively selecting apertures appropriate for sources of varying brightness, thereby enhancing the signal-to-noise ratio (SNR) across a wide range of targets. Meanwhile, some samples in the test set have a higher SNR than those obtained by exhaustive aperture size enumeration because of the finer granularity of aperture size estimation. By integrating ResNet with the ViT network, the DeepAP framework achieves a median total processing time of 18 milliseconds for a batch of 10 images, representing a speed-up of approximately 59000 times compared to exhaustive aperture size enumeration. This work paves the way for the automatic application of aperture photometry in future high-precision surveys such as Tianyu and LSST. The source code and model are available at https://github.com/ruiyicheng/DeepAP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03400v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng-Jun Du, Qing-Quan Li, Yi-Cheng Rui, Yu-Li Liu, Yu-Ting Wu, Dong Li, Bing-Feng Seng, Yi-Fan Xuan, Fa-Bo Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Connect the dots ... finding all possible orbits between two points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02695</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02695v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: You have a satellite spacecraft or asteroid that moves under the gravitational influence of a massive central body and follows a Keplerian orbit around it ellipse parabola or hyperbola Given measurements of two positions in its orbit what is the family of possible orbital paths that connects them I use the conic section orbits semilatus rectum directly related to orbital angular momentum to parameterise these orbits The solutions have applications to orbit determination ballistic missiles interplanetary interception and targeted reentry I also show how they can be applied to solve the Lambert problem of finding the unique transfer orbit that connects two points in a specified time interval These results are accessible to advanced undergraduate students in physics or aerospace engineering. Supplementary materials are provided online</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02695v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ed-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6404/ade37d</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Philip R. Blanco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of Density Distribution on Synchrotron Polarization Dispersion in Magnetized Interstellar Medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02938v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Faraday rotation measure synthesis is a well-known approach originated in Burn (1966) and later developed by Sokoloff et al. (1998) and Brentjens \&amp; de Bruyn (2005) for studying magnetic fields. This work presents a complementary approach--the polarization frequency analysis (PFA)--allowing the properties of the turbulent magnetic field, which are difficult for Burn's original approach. Based on synthetic polarization observation of MHD turbulence simulation data, we study the influence of the coupling effect between density and magnetic field on synchrotron polarization dispersion. By applying the PFA to different simulated interstellar turbulence environments, we find that the PFA technique can reveal the scaling slope of the turbulent magnetic field in the case of a weak coupling effect and can also reflect the scaling slope of the rotation measure in the case of a strong coupling effect. Since avoiding the influence of Faraday depolarization, the PFA technique is a promising way to uncover turbulence properties using observational data from the Low-Frequency Array for Radio Astronomy and the Square Kilometer Array.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02938v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yawen Xiao, Jianfu Zhang, Alex Lazarian, Dmitri Pogosyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decadal upgrade strategy for KAGRA toward post-O5 gravitational-wave astronomy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03392v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The KAGRA Collaboration has investigated a ten-year upgrade strategy for the KAGRA gravitational wave detector, considering a total of 14 upgrade options that vary in mirror mass, quantum noise reduction techniques, and the quality of cryogenic suspensions. We evaluated the scientific potential of these configurations with a focus on key targets such as parameter estimation of compact binary coalescences, binary neutron star post-merger signals, and continuous gravitational waves. Rather than aiming to improve all science cases uniformly, we prioritized those most sensitive to the detector configuration. Technical feasibility was assessed based on required hardware developments, associated R\&amp;D efforts, cost, and risk. Our study finds that a high-frequency upgrade plan that enhances sensitivity over a broad frequency range above ~200 Hz offers the best balance between scientific return and technical feasibility. Such an upgrade would enable sky localization of binary neutron star mergers at 100 Mpc to better than 0.5 deg$^2$ in a LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA network, and improve the measurement precision of tidal deformability parameter by approximately 10% at median, compared to a network without KAGRA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03392v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> KAGRA Collaboration, T. Akutsu, M. Ando, M. Aoumi, A. Araya, Y. Aso, L. Baiotti, R. Bajpai, K. Cannon, A. H. -Y. Chen, D. Chen, H. Chen, A. Chiba, C. Chou, M. Eisenmann, K. Endo, T. Fujimori, S. Garg, D. Haba, S. Haino, R. Harada, H. Hayakawa, K. Hayama, S. Fujii, Y. Himemoto, N. Hirata, C. Hirose, H. -F. Hsieh, H. -Y. Hsieh, C. Hsiung, S. -H. Hsu, K. Ide, R. Iden, S. Ikeda, H. Imafuku, R. Ishikawa, Y. Itoh, M. Iwaya, H-B. Jin, K. Jung, T. Kajita, I. Kaku, M. Kamiizumi, N. Kanda, H. Kato, T. Kato, R. Kawamoto, S. Kim, C. Kim, K. Kobayashi, K. Kohri, K. Kokeyama, K. Komori, A. K. H. Kong, T. Koyama, J. Kume, S. Kuroyanagi, S. Kuwahara, K. Kwak, S. Kwon, H. W. Lee, R. Lee, S. Lee, K. L. Li, L. C. -C. Lin, E. -T. -Lin, Y. -C. Lin, G. C. Liu, K. Maeda, M. Meyer-Conde, Y. Michimura, K. Mitsuhashi, O. Miyakawa, S. Miyoki, S. Morisaki, Y. Moriwaki, M. Murakoshi, K. Nakagaki, K. Nakamura, H. Nakano, T. Narikawa, L. Naticchioni, L. Nguyen Quynh, Y. Nishino, A. Nishizawa, K. Obayashi, M. Ohashi, M. Onishi, K. Oohara, S. Oshino, R. Ozaki, M. A. Page, K. -C. Pan, B. -J. Park, J. Park, F. E. Pena Arellano, N. Ruhama, S. Saha, K. Sakai, Y. Sakai, R. Sato, S. Sato, Y. Sato, Y. Sato, T. Sawada, Y. Sekiguchi, N. Sembo, L. Shao, Z. -H. Shi, R. Shimomura, H. Shinkai, S. Singh, K. Somiya, I. Song, H. Sotani, Y. Sudo, K. Suzuki, M. Suzuki, H. Tagoshi, K. Takada, H. Takahashi, R. Takahashi, A. Takamori, S. Takano, H. Takeda, K. Takeshita, M. Tamaki, K. Tanaka, S. J. Tanaka, A. Taruya, T. Tomaru, T. Tomura, S. Tsuchida, N. Uchikata, T. Uchiyama, T. Uehara, K. Ueno, T. Ushiba, H. Wang, T. Washimi, C. Wu, H. Wu, K. Yamamoto, T. Yamamoto, T. S. Yamamoto, R. Yamazaki, Y. Yang, S. -W. Yeh, J. Yokoyama, T. Yokozawa, H. Yuzurihara, Z. -C. Zhao, X. Zhu, Z. -H. Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Genetic Algorithm Framework for Optimizing Three-Impulse Orbital Transfers with Poliastro Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03466v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Orbital maneuver planning is a critical aspect of mission design, aimed at minimizing propellant consumption, which is directly correlated with the total velocity change ($\Delta V$). While analytical solutions like the Hohmann and Bi-elliptic transfers offer optimal strategies for specific cases, they lack the flexibility for more general optimization problems. This paper presents a computational framework that couples a Genetic Algorithm (GA) with the Poliastro orbital mechanics library to autonomously discover fuel-optimal, three-impulse transfer trajectories between coplanar circular orbits. We validate this framework across two distinct scenarios: a low-energy transfer from Low Earth Orbit (LEO) to a Geostationary Orbit (GEO), and a high-energy transfer to a distant orbit with a radius 20 times that of LEO. Our results demonstrate the framework's remarkable adaptability. For the LEO-to-GEO transfer, the GA precisely converges to the classical Hohmann transfer, achieving an identical $\Delta V$ of 3853.96 m/s and validating the method's accuracy. Conversely, for the high-energy transfer, the GA identifies a superior Bi-elliptic trajectory that yields a significant $\Delta V$ saving of 213.47 m/s compared to the Hohmann transfer. This fuel efficiency, however, necessitates a trade-off, extending the mission duration from approximately 1 day to over 140 years. This work demonstrates an accessible and powerful toolchain for the rapid prototyping of optimal trajectories, showcasing how combining evolutionary algorithms with open-source libraries provides a robust method for solving complex astrodynamics problems and quantifying their critical design trade-offs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03466v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Phuc Hao Do, Tran Duc Le</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AION-10: Technical Design Report for a 10m Atom Interferometer in Oxford</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03491v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This Technical Design Report presents AION-10, a 10-meter atom interferometer to be located at Oxford University using ultracold strontium atoms to make precision measurements of fundamental physics. AION-10 serves as both a prototype for future larger-scale experiments and a versatile scientific instrument capable of conducting its own diverse physics programme.
  The design features a 10-meter vertical tower housing two atom interferometer sources in an ultra-high vacuum environment. Key engineering challenges include achieving nanometer-level vibrational stability and precise magnetic field control. Solutions include active vibration isolation, specialized magnetic shielding, and a modular assembly approach using professional lifting equipment.
  Detailed analysis confirms the design meets all performance requirements, with critical optical components remaining within our specifications 97% of the time under realistic operating conditions. Vacuum and vibration measurements in the host building validate that the instrument will achieve the precision needed for quantum sensing applications.
  This work establishes the technical foundation for scaling atom interferometry to longer baselines while creating a cutting-edge facility for precision measurements that could advance our understanding of fundamental physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03491v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Bongs, A. Brzakalik, U. Chauhan, S. Dey, O. Ennis, S. Hedges, T. Hird, M. Holynski, S. Lellouch, M. Langlois, B. Stray, B. Bostwick, J. Chen, Z. Eyler, V. Gibson, T. L. Harte, C. C. Hsu, M. Karzazi, C. Lu, B. Millward, J. Mitchell, N. Mouelle, B. Panchumarthi, J. Scheper, U. Schneider, X. Su, Y. Tang, K. Tkal\v{c}ec, M. Zeuner, S. Zhang, Y. Zhi, K. Clarke, A. Vick, C. F. A. Baynham, O. Buchm\"uller, D. Evans, L. Hawkins, R. Hobson, L. Iannizzotto-Venezze, A. Josset, D. Lee, E. Pasatembou, B. E. Sauer, M. R. Tarbutt, T. Walker, L. Badurina, A. Beniwal, D. Blas, J. Carlton, J. Ellis, C. McCabe, G. Parish, D. Pathak Govardhan, V. Vaskonen, T. Bowcock, K. Bridges, A. Carroll, J. Coleman, G. Elertas, S. Hindley, C. Metelko, H. Throssell, J. N. Tinsley, E. Bentine, M. Booth, D. Bortoletto, C. Foot, N. Callaghan, C. Gomez-Monedero, K. Hughes, A. James, T. Leese, A. Lowe, J. March-Russell, J. Sander, J. Schelfhout, I. Shipsey, D. Weatherill, D. Wood, S. N. Balashov, M. G. Bason, K. Hussain, H. Labiad, P. Majewski, A. L. Marchant, D. Newbold, Z. Pan, Z. Tam, T. C. Thornton, T. Valenzuela, M. G. D. van der Grinten, I. Wilmut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated Algorithmic Discovery for Gravitational-Wave Detection Guided by LLM-Informed Evolutionary Monte Carlo Tree Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03661v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Computational scientific discovery increasingly relies on algorithms to process complex data and identify meaningful patterns - yet faces persistent challenges in gravitational-wave signal identification. While existing algorithmic approaches like matched filtering (MF) and deep neural networks (DNNs) have achieved partial success, their limitations directly stem from fundamental limitations: MF's excessive computational demands arise from its reliance on predefined theoretical waveform templates, while DNNs' black-box architectures obscure decision logic and introduce hidden biases. We propose Evolutionary Monte Carlo Tree Search (Evo-MCTS), a framework that addresses these limitations through systematic algorithm space exploration guided by domain-aware physical constraints. Our approach combines tree-structured search with evolutionary optimization and large language model heuristics to create interpretable algorithmic solutions. Our Evo-MCTS framework demonstrates substantial improvements, achieving a 20.2\% improvement over state-of-the-art gravitational wave detection algorithms on the MLGWSC-1 benchmark dataset. High-performing algorithm variants consistently exceed thresholds. The framework generates human-interpretable algorithmic pathways that reveal distinct performance patterns. Beyond performance improvements, our framework discovers novel algorithmic combinations, thereby establishing a transferable methodology for automated algorithmic discovery across computational science domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03661v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>He Wang, Liang Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prospects of a New $L_5$ Trojan Flyby Target for the Lucy Mission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03687v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: NASA's Lucy spacecraft is en route to conduct the first close encounter with Jupiter's Trojans. While most scheduled flybys lie in the $L_4$ cloud, the only $L_5$ target is the Patroclus-Menoetius binary. Since each flyby offers unique insights into target and population properties unattainable from Earth, we examine the feasibility of including an additional, yet unknown, $L_5$ target while minimizing the impact on Lucy's primary mission. We use the background $L_5$ Trojans brighter than the completeness limit to model their absolute magnitude, spatial, and orbital distributions. A semi-analytical approach estimates the number of Trojans accessible to Lucy for a given $\Delta v$ budget in both pre- and post-Patroclus scenarios. Our results indicate that, while it is unlikely that any suitable Trojan lies on Lucy's nominal path, a moderate $\Delta v$ investment ($35-50\,\mathrm{m/s}$) could enable a sub-kilometer ($500-700\,\mathrm{m}$) flyby prior to the Patroclus encounter. Post-Patroclus, the likelihood of a similar flyby is $\sim60\%$ for $\Delta v\sim$ 50 m/s. Simulations with synthetic Trojans reveal that potential targets cluster near the node opposite to the encounter window, producing an optimal search period in late 2026 for both scenarios. Surveying the densest $10\%$ of this region would require under 5 nights with Subaru/HSC or under 2 nights with Rubin, using shift-and-stack techniques. A successful sub-kilometric flyby would expand Lucy's Trojan target size range and provide new constraints on collisional evolution and the long-standing asymmetry in the $L_4/L_5$ clouds. This nodal-clustering strategy could guide target searches in future Lucy extensions or other planetary flyby missions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03687v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis E. Salazar Manzano, David W. Gerdes, Kevin J. Napier, Hsing Wen Lin, Fred C. Adams, Tessa Frincke, Simone Marchi, Keith S. Noll, John Spencer</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
