<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 13:15:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Additive Manufacturing of PEEK/Lunar Regolith Composites for Sustainable Lunar Manufacturing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00894v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As humanity advances toward long-term lunar presence under NASA's Artemis program, the development of lunar-based manufacturing and construction (LBMC) capabilities has become increasingly critical. The high cost of transporting materials from Earth makes in-situ resource utilization (ISRU) essential, with lunar regolith serving as a promising local feedstock. Additive manufacturing (AM) offers a compelling platform for LBMC due to its geometric flexibility, material efficiency, and capacity for on-demand, site-specific production. This study investigates material extrusion (MEX) AM of polyether-ether-ketone (PEEK) composites containing 10 to 50 wt% lunar regolith simulant (LRS). PEEK and LMS-1D powders were melt-compounded via twin-screw extrusion, printed using a high-temperature chamber, and annealed at 300 degrees C. The samples were characterized through density measurements, thermal analysis, tensile testing, and microstructural and elemental mapping. All filaments exhibited densities above 96%, though as-printed porosity increased from less than 1% in neat PEEK to 7.5% at 50 wt% LRS due to elevated melt viscosity. Regolith incorporation enhanced crystallinity (17.4 to 20.5%) and elastic modulus (by 6-41%), while reducing delamination and warping, which improved dimensional accuracy and print success rates. Tensile strength declined gradually from 107 MPa to 90 MPa up to 40 wt% LRS, then dropped sharply to approximately 70 MPa at 50 wt%. Annealing improved density and stiffness for composites containing up to 30 wt% LRS, with marginal benefit at higher contents. Microstructural and elemental analyses confirmed a continuous PEEK matrix with uniformly dispersed regolith particles. This work establishes processing windows and trade-offs for regolith-rich PEEK composites, supporting ISRU-enabled AM of future lunar infrastructure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00894v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Azami, Pierre-Lucas Aubin-Fournier, Mehdi Hojjati, Krzysztof Skonieczny</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predictive calibration for digital sun sensors using sparse submanifold convolutional neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00918v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent developments in AI techniques for space applications mirror the success achieved in terrestrial applications. Machine learning, which excels in data rich environments, is particularly well suited to space-based computer vision applications, such as space optical attitude sensing. Of these sensors, digital sun sensors (DSS) are one of the most common and important sensors for spacecraft attitude determination. The main challenge in using the DSS for attitude estimation are sensor errors, which limit the overall achievable estimation accuracy. However, the traditional sun sensor calibration process is costly, slow, labor-intensive and inefficient. These limitations motivate the use of AI techniques to enable more accurate and efficient DSS calibration.
  The objective of this work is to develop an end-to-end predictive calibration methodology for digital sun sensors to solve 2-axis state estimates utilizing a sparse submanifold convolutional neural network (SSCNN). We find that the proposed framework can achieve state-of-the-art performance on synthetic data with a mean accuracy of 0.005{\deg} for the two sun angle estimates. Furthermore, the model is highly capable of implicitly learning complex noise patterns and handling mixed noise types, thereby greatly improving the model robustness and accuracy to real-world applications. The main contributions of this work are: (1) the first application (to our knowledge) of a CNN regression model to the problem of DSS predictive calibration, (2) the introduction of a fused end-to-end training approach for DSS calibration, (3) the creation of a publicly available physics-informed synthetic dataset and simulation for DSS training images, and (4) the evaluation of the performance of the deep learning approach for various mask configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00918v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Herman, Olivia J. Pinon Fischer, Dimitri N. Mavris</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of the Primary Beam of the Tianlai Cylindrical Antenna Using an Unmanned Aerial Vehicle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01413v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Tianlai Cylinder Pathfinder Array consists of three adjacent cylindrical reflectors fixed on the ground, each 40 meters long and 15 meters wide, with the cylinder axis oriented along the North-South (N-S)direction. Dual linear polarisation feeds are distributed along the focus line, parallel to the cylinder axis. Measurement of the primary beam profile of these cylindrical reflectors is difficult, as they are too large to be placed in an anechoic chamber. While the beam profile along the East-West (E-W) direction can be measured with the transit observations of bright astronomical radio sources, the beam profile along the N-S direction remains very uncertain. We present a preliminary measurement of the beam profile of the Tianlai cylindrical antenna along both the N-S direction and E-W direction in the frequency range of 700-800 MHz, using a calibrator source carried by an unmanned aerial vehicle (UAV) flying in the far field. The beam profile of the Tianlai cylindrical antenna is determined from the analysis of the auto-correlation signals from the the cylinder array correlator, taking into account the emitter antenna beam profile, itself measured with a dipole antenna on the ground. The accuracy of the UAV-based determination of the cylinder beam profiles is validated by comparing the results with the one derived from bright astronomical source transits, and with simulated beams.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01413v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jixia Li, Nanben Suo, Shenzhe Xu, Shijie Sun, Shifan Zuo, Yougang Wang, Fengquan Wu, Juyong Zhang, Peter Timbie, Reza Ansari, Albert Stebbins, Xuelei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SPAN: A cross-platform Python GUI software for optical and near-infrared spectral analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01923v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The increasing availability of high-quality optical and near-infrared spectroscopic data, as well as advances in modelling techniques, have greatly expanded the scientific potential of spectroscopic studies. However, the software tools needed to fully exploit this potential often remain fragmented across multiple specialised packages, requiring scripting skills and manual integration to handle complex workflows. In this paper we present SPAN (SPectral ANalysis), a cross-platform, Python-based Graphical User Interface (GUI) software that unifies the essential tools for modern spectral analysis within a single, user-friendly environment. While SPAN can be used with a variety of spectroscopic targets, its primary focus is the analysis of unresolved galaxy spectra. SPAN allows users to extract 1D spectra from FITS images and datacubes, perform spectral processing (e.g. Doppler correction, continuum modelling, denoising), and carry out detailed analyses, including line-strength measurements, stellar and gas kinematics, and stellar population studies, using both built-in routines and the widely adopted pPXF algorithm for full spectral fitting. It runs natively on Windows, Linux, macOS, and Android, and is fully task-driven, requiring no prior coding experience. We validate SPAN by comparing its output with existing pipelines and literature studies. By offering a flexible, accessible, and well integrated environment, SPAN simplifies and accelerates the spectral analysis workflow, while maintaining scientific accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01923v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniele Gasparri, Lorenzo Morelli, Umberto Battino, Jairo M\'endez Abreu, Adriana de Lorenzo-C\'aceres</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EDGES-3: Instrument Design and Commissioning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02577v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: EDGES-3 is the third iteration of the EDGES experiment, designed to measure the predicted global absorption feature in the radio spectrum produced by neutral hydrogen gas at cosmic dawn, a critical observation determining when and how the first stars populated the universe. The EDGES-3 instrument has been redesigned to include both the analog and digital electronics within the antenna, allowing for in-situ calibration and removal of the lossy balun found in EDGES-2. EDGES-3 has been on multiple deployments in the past 4 years; to Oregon, Devon Island, Adak Island, and is currently installed and taking data in the outback of Western Australia. This paper provides an accounting of the challenges inherent in the detection of the global, cosmological 21-cm signal, the strategies EDGES employs to mitigate each of these challenges, a description of the instrument, and a report on the Western Australia deployment along with observational data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02577v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rigel C. Cappallo, Alan E. E. Rogers, Colin J. Lonsdale, Judd D. Bowman, John P. Barrett, Steven G. Murray, Nivedita Mahesh, Peter Sims, Akshatha K. Vydula, Raul A. Monsalve, Christopher J. Eckert, Parker Steen, Kenneth M. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The multi-physics analysis, design and testing of CUSP, a CubeSat mission for space weather and solar flares x-ray polarimetry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02594v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The space-based CUbesat Solar Polarimeter (CUSP) mission aims to measure the linear polarization of solar flares in the hard X-ray band by means of a Compton scattering polarimeter. CUSP is a project in the framework of the Alcor Program of the Italian Space Agency aimed at developing new CubeSat missions. As part of CUSP's Phase B study, which began in December 2024 and will last one year, we present the current development status of the design solutions adopted for the mission's most critical multi-physics design drivers. These solutions have been formulated and applied to demonstrate compliance with system requirements at both the spacecraft and platform levels. In particular, we describe the mechanical design of each structural component, the results of static, dynamic finite element analyses, and a proposal for topological optimization of the interface between the platform and payload and some fixture for test, and the preliminary environmental testing campaign (e.g., vibration, shock) that will be carried out on a mechanical demonstrator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02594v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Lombardi, Sergio Fabiani, Ettore Del Monte, Andrea Alimenti, Riccardo Campana, Mauro Centrone, Enrico Costa, Nicolas De Angelis, Giovanni De Cesare, Sergio Di Cosimo, Giuseppe Di Persio, Abhay Kumar, Alessandro Lacerenza, Pasqualino Loffredo, Gabriele Minervini, Fabio Muleri, Paolo Romano, Alda Rubini, Emanuele Scalise, Enrico Silva, Paolo Soffitta, Davide Albanesi, Ilaria Baffo, Daniele Brienza, Valerio Campamaggiore, Giovanni Cucinella, Andrea Curatolo, Giulia de Iulis, Andrea Del Re, Vito Di Bari, Simone Di Filippo, Immacolata Donnarumma, Pierluigi Fanelli, Nicolas Gagliardi, Paolo Leonetti, Matteo Merge, Dario Modenini, Andrea Negri, Daniele Pecorella, Massimo Perelli, Alice Ponti, Francesca Sbop, Paolo Tortora, Alessandro Turchi, Valerio Vagelli, Emanuele Zaccagnino, Alessandro Zambardi, Costantino Zazza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting symbiotic binaries with interferometry: II. New PIONIER data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01304v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Symbiotic stars, which generally comprise a red giant and an accreting white dwarf, are excellent laboratories to understand mass transfer in wide binaries, with application to a wide family of systems. One of the fundamental questions is how mass is transferred from the red giant to the white dwarf. We use interferometric measurements made with the VLTI/PIONIER instrument, combined with Gaia data, to measure the radius of the giant in seven symbiotic systems. We further place the giants in the H-R diagramme, which allows us to estimate their mass and to show that they are all very evolved and likely on the asymptotic giant branch. We compare our measured giant radii to their Roche-lobe radius and show that, except for ZZ CMi, all giants are well within their Roche lobe and that mass transfer likely takes place via stellar wind. Our interferometric data provide further evidence that the giant in ZZ CMi (nearly) fills its Roche lobe. Our conclusions are still hampered by the poor characterisation of some of the giants or their binary orbit, and we encourage the community to make an effort to provide these.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01304v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Henri M. J. Boffin, Jaroslav Merc</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Gamma/Hadron Separation for Ultra-High-Energy Cherenkov Astronomy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01354</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01354v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Dark100 is a planned array of six telescopes, using the Panoramic Search for Extraterrestrial Intelligence (PANOSETI) telescope system. It will operate as an imaging atmospheric Cherenkov telescope array, with a telescope design and array layout optimized for accessing gamma rays with tens of TeV to PeV energies. The science goals of Dark100 include the search for ultra-heavy dark matter, observations of Galactic Pevatrons, and the search for ultra-fast optical transients. Rejection of background cosmic rays is key to the sensitivity of the array. We present a first study of gamma/hadron separation based on simulated gamma rays and protons, focusing on the impact of the hadronic background models used in CORSIKA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01354v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sruthiranjani Ravikularaman (for the PANOSETI Collaboration), Felix Riehn, Dominik Elsaesser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error dependencies in the space-based CNEOS fireball database</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01454v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We evaluate the reliability of CNEOS-derived ephemerides of fireball events given the absence of the underlying data. We analyzed 18 events that have both (i) sufficient satellite information to derive orbits and (ii) ground-based observational counterparts. We quantify the uncertainties on these calibrated events using the orbital similarity criterion D_D. We also examine the velocity components imbalance and identify discriminants that can indicate the accuracy of an event. We identify two groups in the CNEOS database. CNEOS data produces ephemeris determinations with D_D&lt;0.1 for fireballs reported either (i) after late 2017 or (ii) with impact energies above 0.45 kt with 74-78% of events having D_D=0.03$\pm$0.02, while ~11% show D_D&lt;0.008. Our statistical test confirms these two parameters as the only reliable discriminants that, when combined, explain the two accuracy groups. Daylight, z-velocity component, low altitude, long duration, and latitude might also indicate errors, although the limited dataset may obscure correlations. No clear discriminants are identified for more restrictive D_D cut-offs. We provide estimates of orbital uncertainties for calibrated events. The hyperbolic fireball subset in the CNEOS database appears as an outlier in the velocity imbalance test. Our results confirm that the fidelity of CNEOS fireball data improved significantly from 2018, likely due to the deployment of next-generation space sensors, and show a growing number of high-velocity events. Hyperbolic candidates should be interpreted with caution, as their velocities and inclinations likely reflect measurement errors. Accuracy constraints remain limited by the dataset size, as evidenced by the lack of statistically significant dependence on duration, preventing strong conclusions from being drawn.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01454v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eloy Pe\~na-Asensio, Hector Socas-Navarro, Darryl Z. Seligman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Attitude Determination and Control of GPS Satellites: Stabilization, Orbital Insertion, and Operational Control Mechanisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01660v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Global Positioning System (GPS) satellites are essential for providing accurate navigation and timing information worldwide. Operating in medium Earth orbit (MEO), these satellites must maintain precise Earth-pointing attitudes to transmit signals effectively. This paper presents a comprehensive review of the operational dynamics, attitude determination and control systems (ADCS), and orbital insertion techniques for GPS satellites. We explore the integration of sensors and actuators, control algorithms, stabilization strategies, and the launch procedures required to deploy these satellites. Key equations related to orbital mechanics and attitude control are discussed, and references to recent technical literature are included.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01660v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oliullah Samir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-Energy Calibration of SuperCDMS HVeV Cryogenic Silicon Calorimeters Using Compton Steps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02402v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cryogenic calorimeters for low-mass dark matter searches have achieved sub-eV energy resolutions, driving advances in both low-energy calibration techniques and our understanding of detector physics. The energy deposition spectrum of gamma rays scattering off target materials exhibits step-like features, known as Compton steps, near the binding energies of atomic electrons. We demonstrate a successful use of Compton steps for sub-keV calibration of cryogenic silicon calorimeters, utilizing four SuperCDMS High-Voltage eV-resolution (HVeV) detectors operated with 0 V bias across the crystal. This new calibration at 0 V is compared with the established high-voltage calibration using optical photons. The comparison indicates that the detector response at 0 V is about 30% weaker than expected, highlighting challenges in detector response modeling for low-mass dark matter searches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02402v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> SuperCDMS Collaboration, M. F. Albakry, I. Alkhatib, D. Alonso-Gon\'zalez, D. W. P. Amaral, J. Anczarski, T. Aralis, T. Aramaki, I. Ataee Langroudy, C. Bathurst, R. Bhattacharyya, A. J. Biffl, P. L. Brink, M. Buchanan, R. Bunker, B. Cabrera, R. Calkins, R. A. Cameron, C. Cartaro, D. G. Cerde\~no, Y. -Y. Chang, M. Chaudhuri, J. -H. Chen, R. Chen, N. Chott, J. Cooley, H. Coombes, P. Cushman, R. Cyna, S. Das, S. Dharani, M. L. di Vacri, M. D. Diamond, M. Elwan, S. Fallows, E. Fascione, E. Figueroa-Feliciano, S. L. Franzen, A. Gevorgian, M. Ghaith, G. Godden, J. Golatkar, S. R. Golwala, R. Gualtieri, J. Hall, S. A. S. Harms, C. Hays, B. A. Hines, Z. Hong, L. Hsu, M. E. Huber, V. Iyer, V. K. S. Kashyap, S. T. D. Keller, M. H. Kelsey, K. T. Kennard, Z. Kromer, A. Kubik, N. A. Kurinsky, M. Lee, J. Leyva, B. Lichtenberg, J. Liu, Y. Liu, E. Lopez Asamar, P. Lukens, R. L\'opez No\'e, D. B. MacFarlane, R. Mahapatra, J. S. Mammo, N. Mast, A. J. Mayer, P. C. McNamara, H. Meyer zu Theenhausen, \'E. Michaud, E. Michielin, K. Mickelson, N. Mirabolfathi, M. Mirzakhani, B. Mohanty, D. Mondal, D. Monteiro, J. Nelson, H. Neog, V. Novati, J. L. Orrell, M. D. Osborne, S. M. Oser, L. Pandey, S. Pandey, R. Partridge, P. K. Patel, D. S. Pedreros, W. Peng, W. L. Perry, R. Podviianiuk, M. Potts, S. S. Poudel, A. Pradeep, M. Pyle, W. Rau, E. Reid, R. Ren, T. Reynolds, M. Rios, A. Roberts, A. E. Robinson, L. Rosado Del Rio, J. L. Ryan, T. Saab, D. Sadek, B. Sadoulet, S. P. Sahoo, I. Saikia, S. Salehi, J. Sander, B. Sandoval, A. Sattari, B. Schmidt, R. W. Schnee, B. Serfass, A. E. Sharbaugh, R. S. Shenoy, A. Simchony, P. Sinervo, Z. J. Smith, R. Soni, K. Stifter, J. Street, M. Stukel, H. Sun, E. Tanner, N. Tenpas, D. Toback, A. N. Villano, J. Viol, B. von Krosigk, Y. Wang, O. Wen, Z. Williams, M. J. Wilson, J. Winchell, S. Yellin, B. A. Young, B. Zatschler, S. Zatschler, A. Zaytsev, E. Zhang, L. Zheng, A. Zuniga, M. J. Zurowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trustworthy scientific inference for inverse problems with generative models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02602</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02602v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Generative artificial intelligence (AI) excels at producing complex data structures (text, images, videos) by learning patterns from training examples. Across scientific disciplines, researchers are now applying generative models to ``inverse problems'' to infer hidden parameters from observed data. While these methods can handle intractable models and large-scale studies, they can also produce biased or overconfident conclusions. We present a solution with Frequentist-Bayes (FreB), a mathematically rigorous protocol that reshapes AI-generated probability distributions into confidence regions that consistently include true parameters with the expected probability, while achieving minimum size when training and target data align. We demonstrate FreB's effectiveness by tackling diverse case studies in the physical sciences: identifying unknown sources under dataset shift, reconciling competing theoretical models, and mitigating selection bias and systematics in observational studies. By providing validity guarantees with interpretable diagnostics, FreB enables trustworthy scientific inference across fields where direct likelihood evaluation remains impossible or prohibitively expensive.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02602v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Carzon, Luca Masserano, Joshua D. Ingram, Alex Shen, Antonio Carlos Herling Ribeiro Junior, Tommaso Dorigo, Michele Doro, Joshua S. Speagle, Rafael Izbicki, Ann B. Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpreting Multi-band Galaxy Observations with Large Language Model-Based Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.14807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.14807v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Astronomical research traditionally relies on extensive domain knowledge to interpret observations and narrow down hypotheses. We demonstrate that this process can be emulated using large language model-based agents to accelerate research workflows. We propose mephisto, a multi-agent collaboration framework that mimics human reasoning to interpret multi-band galaxy observations. mephisto interacts with the CIGALE codebase, which includes spectral energy distribution (SED) models to explain observations. In this open-world setting, mephisto learns from its self-play experience, performs tree search, and accumulates knowledge in a dynamically updated base. As a proof of concept, we apply mephisto to the latest data from the James Webb Space Telescope. mephisto attains near-human proficiency in reasoning about galaxies' physical scenarios, even when dealing with a recently discovered population of "Little Red Dot" galaxies. This represents the first demonstration of agentic research in astronomy, advancing towards end-to-end research via LLM agents and potentially expediting astronomical discoveries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.14807v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zechang Sun, Yuan-Sen Ting, Yaobo Liang, Nan Duan, Song Huang, Zheng Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Dark Energy Implies a Coupled Dark Sector: Insights from DESI DR2 via a Data-Driven Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00985v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent observations from the Dark Energy Spectroscopic Instrument (DESI) Data Release 2 (DR2) have revealed compelling evidence for dynamical dark energy, challenging the $\Lambda$CDM paradigm. In this work, we adopt a data-driven, model-independent approach to reconstruct the dark energy equation of state (EoS) and its potential interaction with dark matter using combined background cosmological datasets, including DESI DR2, cosmic chronometers, observational Hubble data, and Type Ia supernovae. Using Gaussian Process regression and a non-parametric formalism, we first confirm a $\sim 2\sigma$ indication of dynamical dark energy, featuring a phantom crossing around redshift $z \sim 0.4$, consistent with DESI results. We then explore the implications of dynamical EoS from DESI DR2 for dark sector coupling. Incorporating priors on the EoS from DESI DR2, we find a $\sim 2\sigma$ signal for non-zero interactions between dark energy and dark matter at low redshift. Our results suggest that if DESI's evidence for time-varying dark energy is confirmed, a coupled dark sector may be a necessary extension beyond $\Lambda$CDM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00985v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/f6v7-n9fr</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 112 (2025) 043503</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Changyu You, Dan Wang, Tao Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model-Independent Machine Learning Approach for Nanometric Axial Localization and Tracking</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14754v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Accurately tracking particles and determining their coordinate along the optical axis is a major challenge in optical microscopy, especially when extremely high precision is needed. In this study, we introduce a deep learning approach using convolutional neural networks (CNNs) that can determine axial coordinates from dual-focal-plane images without relying on predefined models. Our method achieves an axial localization precision of 40 nanometers-six times better than traditional single-focal-plane techniques. The model's simple design and strong performance make it suitable for a wide range of uses, including dark matter detection, proton therapy for cancer, and radiation protection in space. It also shows promise in fields like biological imaging, materials science, and environmental monitoring. This work highlights how machine learning can turn complex image data into reliable, precise information, offering a flexible and powerful tool for many scientific applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14754v2</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrey Alexandrov, Giovanni Acampora, Giovanni De Lellis, Antonia Di Crescenzo, Chiara Errico, Daria Morozova, Valeri Tioukov, Autilia Vittiello</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid stellar and binary population synthesis with COMPAS: methods paper II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02316v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The COMPAS public rapid binary population synthesis code has undergone a number of key improvements since the original COMPAS methods paper (Team COMPAS: Riley et al., 2022) was published. These include more sophisticated and robust treatments of binary interactions: mass transfer physics, common-envelope events, tides and gravitational-wave radiation reaction; and updated prescriptions for stellar evolution, winds and supernovae. The code structure and outputs have also been updated, with a focus on improving resolution without sacrificing computational speed. This paper describes the substantive changes in the code between the previous methods paper and COMPAS v03.22.01.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02316v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ilya Mandel, Jeff Riley, Adam Boesky, Adam Brcek, Ryosuke Hirai, Veome Kapil, Mike Y. M. Lau, JD Merritt, Nicol\'as Rodr\'iguez-Segovia, Isobel Romero-Shaw, Yuzhe Song, Simon Stevenson, Avi Vajpeyi, L. A. C. van Son, Alejandro Vigna-G\'omez, Reinhold Willcox</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First Robust Detection of Linear Polarization from Metric Solar Emissions: Challenging Established Paradigms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05196v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Polarimetric radio observations of the Sun can provide rich information about emission mechanisms and the propagation medium. For the past five decades, solar polarimetric studies at low radio frequencies have almost always assumed the absence of linear polarization. This has been based on the expectations from coronal propagation effects. Here we present the first robust evidence of linear polarization from solar emissions at meter wavelengths using simultaneous measurements with two telescopes of very different designs separated by thousands of kilometers - the Murchison Widefield Array and the upgraded Giant Metrewave Radio Telescope. Both datasets show consistent linear polarization fractions, confirming this detection. Rapid changes in morphology, as well as the fractional linear polarization at small time and frequency spans, further rule out any possibilities of an instrumental origin. Assuming the absence of linear polarization in solar radio emissions can result in incorrect interpretation of solar observations as well as those of other flare stars, which are often guided by learnings from solar studies. This discovery highlights the need for relaxing this assumption, and is essential for precise estimation of polarization signatures, ultimately leading to a better understanding of the plasma conditions in the Sun and other stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05196v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/2041-8213/adef0e</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ApJL 988 L73 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Soham Dey, Devojyoti Kansabanik, Divya Oberoi, Surajit Mondal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlation and Redundancy of Time-Delay Interferometry Configurations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.18397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.18397v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Time-Delay Interferometry (TDI) is essential for space-based gravitational wave (GW) missions, as it suppresses laser frequency noise and achieve the required sensitivity. Beyond the standard Michelson configuration, a variety of second-generation TDI schemes have been proposed, each utilizing different combinations of inter-spacecraft laser links. In this work, we conduct a comparative study of several representative TDI configurations with varying time spans and demonstrate that their (quasi-)orthogonal channels are highly correlated, indicating substantial redundancy among these schemes. In the low-frequency regime, the performance of different TDI configurations are nearly identical. Their distinctions emerge primarily at high frequencies, where the GW wavelength becomes comparable to the arm length. In this regime, shorter TDI time spans with minimal null frequencies facilitate more accurate waveform modeling and parameter recovery in frequency domain. In contrast, configurations with longer time spans and more null frequencies, such as the Michelson, are more susceptible to frequency aliasing and waveform modulation effects, which degrade inference accuracy. However, if signal modeling and analysis are performed in the time domain, all TDI configurations become effectively equivalent. Considering the usability in both frequency and time domain, the short-span PD4L scheme, which exhibits minimal nulls and superior performance in high frequencies, emerges as a promising candidate for future space-based GW mission designs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.18397v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intercepting 3I/ATLAS at Closest Approach to Jupiter with the Juno spacecraft</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.21402v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The interstellar object 3I/ATLAS is expected to arrive at a distance of $53.56(\pm 0.45)$ million ${\rm km}$ ($0.358\pm 0.003$~au) from Jupiter on March 16, 2026. We show that applying a total thrust $\Delta$V of $2.6755 {{\rm km~s^{-1}}}$ to lower perijove on September 9, 2025 and then execute a Jupiter Oberth Maneuver, can bring the Juno spacecraft from its orbit around Jupiter to intercept the path of 3I/ATLAS on March 14, 2026. We further show that it is possible for Juno to come much closer to 3I/ATLAS ($\sim{27}$ million km) with 110 kg of remaining propellant, merely 5.4% of the initial fuel reservoir. We find that for low available $\Delta$V there is no particular benefit in application of a double impulse (for example to reach $\sim{27}$ million km from 3I/ATLAS), however if Juno has a higher $\Delta$V capability there is significant advantage to a second impulse with typically a saving of propellant by a factor of a half. A close fly-by might be able to probe the nature of 3I/ATLAS far better than telescopes on Earth.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.21402v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abraham Loeb, Adam Hibberd, Adam Crowl</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
