<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 01:55:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An Edge AI Solution for Space Object Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13468v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Effective Edge AI for space object detection (SOD) tasks that can facilitate real-time collision assessment and avoidance is essential with the increasing space assets in near-Earth orbits. In SOD, low Earth orbit (LEO) satellites must detect other objects with high precision and minimal delay. We explore an Edge AI solution based on deep-learning-based vision sensing for SOD tasks and propose a deep learning model based on Squeeze-and-Excitation (SE) layers, Vision Transformers (ViT), and YOLOv9 framework. We evaluate the performance of these models across various realistic SOD scenarios, demonstrating their ability to detect multiple satellites with high accuracy and very low latency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13468v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenxuan Zhang, Peng Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Galaxy Surveys with Hybrid SBI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13591v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Simulation-based inference (SBI) has emerged as a powerful tool for extracting cosmological information from galaxy surveys deep into the non-linear regime. Despite its great promise, its application is limited by the computational cost of running simulations that can describe the increasingly-large cosmological datasets. Recent work proposed a hybrid SBI framework (HySBI), which combines SBI on small-scales with perturbation theory (PT) on large-scales, allowing information to be extracted from high-resolution observations without large-volume simulations. In this work, we lay out the HySBI framework for galaxy clustering, a key step towards its application to next-generation datasets. We study the choice of priors on the parameters for modeling galaxies in PT analysis and in simulation-based analyses, as well as investigate their cosmology dependence. By jointly modeling large- and small-scale statistics and their associated nuisance parameters, we show that HySBI can obtain 20\% and 60\% tighter constraints on $\Omega_m$ and $\sigma_8$, respectively, compared to traditional PT analyses, thus demonstrating the efficacy of this approach to maximally extract information from upcoming spectroscopic datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13591v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gemma Zhang, Chirag Modi, Oliver H. E. Philcox</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multipole Analysis and Application to Supernova Remnant X-ray Images</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13671v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a multipole analysis method for images with a circular boundary, then apply it to supernova remnant (SNR) images. The morphology of SNR images is related to several factors, including the inhomogeneities of the supernova ejecta and of the circumstellar medium in which the ejecta and shock wave travel. The current multipole method corrects some errors in a previously presented method, and applies the new analysis to test for differences in X-ray image morphology between Type Ia and core-collapse type SNRs. We find there is no clear difference between the two SNR types in morphology as measured by multipole moments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13671v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Denis A. Leahy, S. Ranasinghe, J. Hansen, M. D. Filipovi\'c, Z. Smeaton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Ultraviolet Radiation on Sub-Neptune Exoplanet Hazes Through Laboratory Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13692v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Temperate sub-Neptune exoplanets could contain large inventories of water in various phases, such as water-worlds with water-rich atmospheres or even oceans. Both space-based and ground-based observations have shown that many exoplanets likely also contain photochemically-generated hazes. Haze particles are a key source of organic matter and may impact the evolution or origin of life. In addition, haze layers could provide a mechanism for lower-atmospheric shielding and ultimately atmospheric retention. Often orbiting close to M-dwarf stars, these planets receive large amounts of radiation, especially during flaring events, which may strip away their atmospheres. M-dwarf stars are known to have higher stellar activity than other types of stars, and stellar flares have the potential to accelerate atmospheric escape. In this work, we present results on laboratory investigations of UV radiation effects simulating two different stellar flare energies on laboratory-produced exoplanet hazes made under conditions analogous to water-world atmospheres. We find that both simulated flares altered the overall transmittance and reflectance of the hazes, and higher energy "flares" make those alterations more pronounced. On a larger scale, these laboratory-made hazes show potential signs of degradation over the simulated flaring period. Our results provide insight into the effects that stellar flaring events have on potential exoplanet haze composition and the ability for water-world-like exoplanets to retain their atmospheres.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13692v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lori Huseby, Sarah E. Moran, Neil Pearson, Tiffany Kataria, Chao He, Cara Pesciotta, Sarah M. H\"orst, Pierre Haenecour, Travis Barman, Vishnu Reddy, Nikole K. Lewis, V\'eronique Vuitton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Practice Makes Perfect: A Study of Digital Twin Technology for Assembly and Problem-solving using Lunar Surface Telerobotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13722v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Robotic systems that can traverse planetary or lunar surfaces to collect environmental data and perform physical manipulation tasks, such as assembling equipment or conducting mining operations, are envisioned to form the backbone of future human activities in space. However, the environmental conditions in which these robots, or "rovers," operate present challenges toward achieving fully autonomous solutions, meaning that rover missions will require some degree of human teleoperation or supervision for the foreseeable future. As a result, human operators require training to successfully direct rovers and avoid costly errors or mission failures, as well as the ability to recover from any issues that arise on the fly during mission activities. While analog environments, such as JPL's Mars Yard, can help with such training by simulating surface environments in the real world, access to such resources may be rare and expensive. As an alternative or supplement to such physical analogs, we explore the design and evaluation of a virtual reality digital twin system to train human teleoperation of robotic rovers with mechanical arms for space mission activities. We conducted an experiment with 24 human operators to investigate how our digital twin system can support human teleoperation of rovers in both pre-mission training and in real-time problem solving in a mock lunar mission in which users directed a physical rover in the context of deploying dipole radio antennas. We found that operators who first trained with the digital twin showed a 28% decrease in mission completion time, an 85% decrease in unrecoverable errors, as well as improved mental markers, including decreased cognitive load and increased situation awareness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13722v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xavier O'Keefe, Katy McCutchan, Alexis Muniz, Jack Burns, Daniel Szafir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracking Reentries of Starlink Satellites During the Rising Phase of Solar Cycle 25</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13752</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13752v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The exponential increase of low-Earth orbit (LEO) satellites in the past 5 years has brought into intense focus the need for reliable monitoring and reentry prediction to safeguard from space collisions and ground debris impacts. However, LEO satellites fly within the upper atmosphere region that exerts significant drag forces to their orbits, reducing their lifetimes, and increasing collision risks during dynamic events, like geomagnetic storms. Such conditions can become more severe during geomagnetic storms, particularly during extreme events. In this work, we use two-line element (TLE) satellite tracking data to investigate geomagnetic activity effects on the reentries of 523 Starlink satellites from 2020 to 2024. This period coincides with the rising phase of solar cycle 25, which has shown itself to be more intense than the previous solar cycle. We derive satellite altitudes and velocities from TLE files and perform a superposed epoch analysis, the first with hundreds of similar satellites. Even with limitedly accurate TLE data, our results indisputably show that satellites reenter faster with higher geomagnetic activity. This is explained by the fastest orbital decay rates (in km/day) of the satellites caused by increased drag forces. We also find that prediction errors, defined as the difference between the epochs of actual reentries and predicted reentries at reference altitudes, increase with geomagnetic activity. As a result, we clearly show that the intense solar activity of the current solar cycle has already had significant impacts on Starlink reentries. This is a very exciting time in satellite orbital drag research, since the number of satellites in LEO and solar activity are the highest ever observed in human history.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13752v1</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3389/fspas.2025.1572313</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Frontiers in Astronomy and Space Science, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Denny M. Oliveira, Eftyhia Zesta, Katherine Garcia-Sage</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical Properties of Predicted Blended Eclipsing Binary False Positives in PLATO LOPS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13793v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With the planned launch of the PLAnetary Transit and Oscillation of stars (PLATO) satellite mission in 2026, an understanding of the stellar properties and spatial distribution of astrophysical false positives (FPs) is essential to ensure the limited ground-based spectroscopy resources are used efficiently to target the most likely genuine planetary transit (PT) candidates. In our previous paper, Bray et al. (2023), we presented the expected blended eclipsing binary false positive (BEB) percentage in the proposed Southern PLATO field, which we referred to as SPF0. This was obtained from a detailed statistical analysis of a complete synthetic rendering of SPF0. In this follow-up paper, we present a more detailed analysis of the synthetic binary population creating these BEBs including the apparent radii of the planets mimicked, distances from Earth, orbital periods and binary component masses and evolutionary state.We examine the properties of the BEBs from 400 new independent simulations where random orbital inclinations were assigned to all synthetic binaries in the entire SPF0 region. We consider BEBs created by all eclipses of non-compact remnant binaries. Finally we examine the BEBs most likely to be mistaken for planets in the habitable zone which we define as fully or partially eclipsing binaries with periods between 180 and 1,000 days satisfying our critical inclination angle check.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13793v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J C Bray, U Kolb, S A Mills</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TransFit: An Efficient Framework for Transient Light-Curve Fitting with Time-Dependent Radiative Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13825v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Modeling the light curves (LCs) of luminous astronomical transients, such as supernovae, is crucial for understanding their progenitor physics, particularly with the exponential growth of survey data. However, existing methods face limitations: efficient semi-analytical models (e.g., Arnett-like) employ significant physical simplifications (like time-invariant temperature profiles and simplified heating distributions), often compromising accuracy, especially for early-time LCs. Conversely, detailed numerical radiative transfer simulations, while accurate, are computationally prohibitive for large datasets. This paper introduces TransFit, a novel framework that numerically solves a generalized energy conservation equation, explicitly incorporating time-dependent radiative diffusion, continuous radioactive or central engine heating, and ejecta expansion dynamics. The model accurately captures the influence of key ejecta properties and diverse heating source characteristics on light curve morphology, including peak luminosity, rise time, and overall shape. Furthermore, TransFit provides self-consistent modeling of the transition from shock-cooling to $^{56}$Ni}-powered light curves. By combining physical realism with computational speed, TransFit provides a powerful tool for efficiently inverting LCs and extracting detailed physical insights from the vast datasets of current and future transient surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13825v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang-Duan Liu, Yu-Hao Zhang, Yun-Wei Yu, Ze-Xin Du, Jing-Yao Li, Guang-Lei Wu, Zi-Gao Dai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ThermoONet -- a deep learning-based small body thermophysical network: applications to modelling water activity of comets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14016v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cometary activity is a compelling subject of study, with thermophysical models playing a pivotal role in its understanding. However, traditional numerical solutions for small body thermophysical models are computationally intensive, posing challenges for investigations requiring high-resolution or repetitive modeling. To address this limitation, we employed a machine learning approach to develop ThermoONet - a neural network designed to predict the temperature and water ice sublimation flux of comets. Performance evaluations indicate that ThermoONet achieves a low average error in subsurface temperature of approximately 2% relative to the numerical simulation, while reducing computational time by nearly six orders of magnitude. We applied ThermoONet to model the water activity of comets 67P/Churyumov-Gerasimenko and 21P/Giacobini-Zinner. By successfully fitting the water production rate curves of these comets, as obtained by the Rosetta mission and the SOHO telescope, respectively, we demonstrate the network's effectiveness and efficiency. Furthermore, when combined with a global optimization algorithm, ThermoONet proves capable of retrieving the physical properties of target bodies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14016v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunjing Zhao, Xian Shi, Hanlun Lei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No Evidence for Second-Scale Periodicity in FRB 20201124A from FAST Observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14219</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14219v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fast Radio Bursts (FRBs) are bright and short radio flashes of cosmological origin. Although a great number of FRBs were detected in the last two decades, their progenitors and the physical processes that create them are unknown. In recent years, magnetars have been proposed as one of the leading progenitor candidates. A striking feature that can hint at such a magnetar origin is second-scale periodicity. In this paper, we define a robust procedure to search for such periodicity and estimate the significance of its results. We search for such periodicity in the bursts of FRB 20201124A, observed by the Five-hundred-meter Aperture Spherical Telescope (FAST) between April and June 2021. Our analysis does not find any significant periodicity. We discuss the differences between our non-detection and the ~1.7s periodicity claim by C. Du et al. (2025).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14219v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dotan Gazith, Barak Zackay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving the {\Gamma}-functions Method for Vortex Identification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14384</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14384v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Vortices have been observed at various heights within the solar atmosphere and are suggested to potentially play great roles in heating the solar upper atmosphere. Multiple automated vortex detection methods have been developed and applied to detect vortices. We aim to improve the $\Gamma$-functions method for vortex identification by optimizing the value of $\Gamma_{1min}$ and the approach to calculate $\Gamma_1$ and $\Gamma_2$ used to determine vortex center and edge. In this way, we can detect vortices more accurately and enable more statistical studies that can improve our knowledge of the generation and evolution of vortices in the solar atmosphere. We apply the automated swirl detection algorithm (ASDA, one representative of $\Gamma$-functions method) with different parameters to various synthetic data, with each containing 1000 Lamb-Oseen vortices, and search for the optimal $\Gamma_{1min}$ and kernel size when calculating $\Gamma_1$ and $\Gamma_2$. We also compare another detection method using simulation and observational data to validate the results obtained from the synthetic data. The best performance is found with the Optimized ASDA, which combines different kernel sizes (5, 7, 9, and 11) to calculate $\Gamma_1$ and $\Gamma_2$ with a fixed $\Gamma_{1min}$ = 0.63 to detect vortex center. We find that more vortices can be detected by the Optimized ASDA with higher location, radius, and rotation speed accuracies. The above results are further confirmed by comparing vortices detected by the Optimized ASDA and the SWIRL method on CO5BOLD numerical simulation data and SST observational data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14384v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Quan Xie, Jiajia Liu, Robert Erd\'elyi, Yuming Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Task-parallelism in SWIFT for heterogeneous compute architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14538v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper highlights the first steps towards enabling graphics processing unit (GPU) acceleration of the smoothed particle hydrodynamics (SPH) solver for cosmology SWIFT and creating a hydrodynamics solver capable of fully leveraging the hardware available on heterogeneous exascale machines composed of central and graphics processing units (CPUs and GPUs). Exploiting the existing task-based parallelism in SWIFT, novel combinations of algorithms are presented which enable SWIFT to function as a truly heterogeneous software leveraging CPUs for memory-bound computations concurrently with GPUs for compute-bound computations in a manner which minimises the effects of CPU-GPU communication latency. These algorithms are validated in extensive testing which shows that the GPU acceleration methodology is capable of delivering up to 3.5x speedups for SWIFTs SPH hydrodynamics computation kernels when including the time required to prepare the computations on the CPU and unpack the results on the CPU. Speedups of 7.5x are demonstrated when not including the CPU data preparation and unpacking times. Whilst these measured speedups are substantial, it is shown that the overall performance of the hydrodynamic solver for a full simulation when accelerated on the GPU of state-of-the-art superchips, is only marginally faster than the code performance when using the Grace Hopper superchips fully parallelised CPU capabilities. This is shown to be mostly due to excessive fine-graining of the tasks prior to offloading on the GPU. Fine-graining introduces significant over-heads associated with task management on the CPU hosting the simulation and also introduces un-necessary duplication of CPU-GPU communications of the same data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14538v1</guid>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abouzied M. A. Nasar, Benedict D. Rogers, Georgios Fourtakas, Scott T. Kay, Matthieu Schaller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OSIRIS-REx Operational Key Decision Points: A Retrospective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14632</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14632v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: OSIRIS-REx, NASA's first asteroid sample return mission, rendezvoused with the near-Earth asteroid Bennu in 2018 and delivered a 121.6-gram sample to Earth in 2023, the largest amount of material ever recovered from a planetary body beyond the Moon. The operations phase of OSIRIS-REx was considered the most challenging robotic mission that NASA had undertaken, owing to the tight constraints on spacecraft performance and the microgravity environment. In preparation for the sample collection and return campaign, the mission leadership defined four operational key decision points (OKDPs) at critical junctures: sample site selection, rehearsal and execution of the sample collection maneuver, sample stow, and Earth return. This publication examines these OKDPs in depth, inclusive of rationale, implementation, decision processes, and efficacy. We also review other decisions that enabled mission success despite the unexpectedly rugged nature of Bennu's surface. This information should be beneficial for future challenging operational concepts where science-in-the-loop, time-critical decision making is integral to success.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14632v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rich Burns, Dante S. Lauretta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commissioning and Performance of the Trinity Demonstrator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11864v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Trinity Demonstrator is a proof of concept prototype for the Trinity Neutrino Observatory, which is sensitive to astrophysical neutrinos above PeV energies. The Demonstrator is a one-square meter class imaging atmospheric Cherenkov telescope deployed on Frisco Peak, Utah, and remotely operated. The light-collection surface is equipped with 77 mirror facets with 15 cm diameter, and its $3.87^\circ\times3.87^\circ$ field of view is instrumented with a 256-pixel camera yielding a $0.24^\circ$ angular resolution. The camera signals are digitized with a 100 MS/s, and 12-bit resolution switched capacitor array readout. We discuss the Demonstrator's design, the telescope's deployment on Frisco Peak, and its commissioning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11864v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahdi Bagheri, Adam Barletta, Jordan Bogdan, Anthony M. Brown, Luigi Cedeno, Mariia Fedkevych, Srikar Gadamsetty, Eliza Gazda, Jamie Holder, Eleanor Judd, Dave Kieda, Evgeny Kuznetsov, Nolan Lew, Oscar Romero Matamala, Arnav Menon, Nepomuk A. Otte, Mathew Potts, Wayne Springer, Sofia Stepanoff, Ace Wilcox, Angelina Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for activity in the centimeter band of Solar-type dwarfs with Earth-like planets on the RATAN-600 radio telescope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.01791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.01791v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The paper presents the results of multi-wave radio observations of sixteen red dwarfs with Earth-like planets in the habitable zones on RATAN-600. In the passage mode, radiometers of four frequency ranges of 22, 11, 4.7 and 2.3 GHz (1.38, 2.68, 6.38, 13.3 cm) were used with a sampling step of quasi-simultaneous registration of about $\sim 18$ Hz and an exposure duration (the time of passage of the instrument's directivity pattern) of 1.5 -- 15 s. Observations were carried out from 3 to 27 times in April-May 2018, while radio emission was not detected. Upper limits were established for its intensity in flares with a duration of 0.05 -- 10 s at the level of 80 -- 800 mJy (corresponding to a luminosity of $10^{23} - 10^{29}$ erg/s) and in a steady state with a luminosity of $10^{22} - 10^{27}$ erg/s. During the observations, 11 anomalous flux outlier at the level of 100 mJy were registered, which apparently have an atmospheric (thunderstorms, airplanes) origin. Assuming an artificial origin of the sought radio emission (transmission from inhabited planets), the upper limits of the power of hypothetical transmitters were $2\times 10^9 - 10^{15}$ W, interestingly that the lower boundary of this interval close to the power of terrestrial planetary radars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.01791v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grigory M. Beskin, Vladimir N. Chernenkov, Nikolai N. Bursov, Alexey A. Shlyapnikov, Alexander D. Panov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstructing parametric gravitational-wave population fits from non-parametric results without refitting the data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17233v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Combining multiple events into population analyses is a cornerstone of gravitational-wave astronomy. A critical component of such studies is the assumed population model, which can range from astrophysically motivated functional forms to non-parametric treatments that are flexible but difficult to interpret. In practice, the current approach is to fit the data multiple times with different population models to identify robust features. We propose an alternative strategy: assuming the data have already been fit with a flexible model, we present a practical recipe to reconstruct the population distribution of a different model. As our procedure postprocesses existing results, it avoids the need to access the underlying gravitational-wave data again and handle selection effects. Additionally, our reconstruction metric provides a goodness-of-fit measure to compare multiple models. We apply this method to the mass distribution of black-hole binaries detected by LIGO/Virgo/KAGRA. Our work paves the way for streamlined gravitational-wave population analyses by fitting the data once and for all with advanced non-parametric methods and careful handling of selection effects, while the astrophysical interpretation is then made accessible using our reconstruction procedure on targeted models. The key principle is that of conceptually separating data description from data interpretation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17233v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.104053</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111 (2025) 104053</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cecilia Maria Fabbri, Davide Gerosa, Alessandro Santini, Matthew Mould, Alexandre Toubiana, Jonathan Gair</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ExoMiner++: Enhanced Transit Classification and a New Vetting Catalog for 2-Minute TESS Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09790v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present ExoMiner++, an enhanced deep learning model that builds on the success of ExoMiner to improve transit signal classification in 2-minute TESS data. ExoMiner++ incorporates additional diagnostic inputs, including periodogram, flux trend, difference image, unfolded flux, and spacecraft attitude control data, all of which are crucial for effectively distinguishing transit signals from more challenging sources of false positives. To further enhance performance, we leverage multi-source training by combining high-quality labeled data from the Kepler space telescope with TESS data. This approach mitigates the impact of TESS's noisier and more ambiguous labels. ExoMiner++ achieves high accuracy across various classification and ranking metrics, significantly narrowing the search space for follow-up investigations to confirm new planets. To serve the exoplanet community, we introduce new TESS catalog containing ExoMiner++ classifications and confidence scores for each transit signal. Among the 147,568 unlabeled TCEs, ExoMiner++ identifies 7,330 as planet candidates, with the remainder classified as false positives. These 7,330 planet candidates correspond to 1,868 existing TESS Objects of Interest (TOIs), 69 Community TESS Objects of Interest (CTOIs), and 50 newly introduced CTOIs. 1,797 out of the 2,506 TOIs previously labeled as planet candidates in ExoFOP are classified as planet candidates by ExoMiner++. This reduction in plausible candidates combined with the excellent ranking quality of ExoMiner++ allows the follow-up efforts to be focused on the most likely candidates, increasing the overall planet yield.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09790v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hamed Valizadegan, Miguel J. S. Martinho, Jon M. Jenkins, Joseph D. Twicken, Douglas A. Caldwell, Patrick Maynard, Hongbo Wei, William Zhong, Charles Yates, Sam Donald, Karen A. Collins, David Latham, Khalid Barkaoui, Michael L. Calkins, Kylee Carden, Nikita Chazov, Gilbert A. Esquerdo, Tristan Guillot, Vadim Krushinsky, Grzegorz Nowak, Benjamin V. Rackham, Amaury Triaud, Richard P. Schwarz, Denise Stephens, Chris Stockdale, Cristilyn N. Watkins, Francis P. Wilkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
