<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 05:00:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Real-Time Active Learning for optimised spectroscopic follow-up: Enhancing early SN Ia classification with the Fink broker</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19555v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Current and future surveys rely on machine learning classification to obtain large and complete samples of transients. Many of these algorithms are restricted by training samples that contain a limited number of spectroscopically confirmed events. Here, we present the first real-time application of Active Learning to optimise spectroscopic follow-up with the goal of improving training sets of early type Ia supernovae (SNe Ia) classifiers. Using a photometric classifier for early SN Ia, we apply an Active Learning strategy for follow-up optimisation using the real-time FINK broker processing of the ZTF public stream. We perform follow-up observations at the ANU 2.3m telescope in Australia and obtain 92 spectroscopic classified events that are incorporated in our training set. We show that our follow-up strategy yields a training set that, with 25% less spectra, improves classification metrics when compared to publicly reported spectra. Our strategy selects in average fainter events and, not only supernovae types, but also microlensing events and flaring stars which are usually not incorporated on training sets. Our results confirm the effectiveness of active learning strategies to construct optimal training samples for astronomical classifiers. With the Rubin Observatory LSST soon online, we propose improvements to obtain earlier candidates and optimise follow-up. This work paves the way to the deployment of real-time AL follow-up strategies in the era of large surveys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19555v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. M\"oller, E. E. O. Ishida, J. Peloton, O. Vidal Vel\'azquez, J. Soon, B. Martin, M. Cluver, M. Leoni, E. Taylor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of Machine Learning to Identify Radio Pulses of Air Showers at the South Pole (ARENA 2024)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19931v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Machine learning is a useful tool for identifying radio pulses from cosmic-ray air showers and for cleaning such pulses from radio background. This can lower the detection threshold and increase the accuracy for the pulse time and amplitude. We have trained Convolutional Neural Networks (CNNs) using CoREAS simulations and background recorded by a prototype station at the IceTop surface array at the South Pole and have applied them to air-shower measurements by this station. The station consists of 3 SKALA antennas and 8 scintillators, which are used to trigger the readout of the antennas upon a sixfold coincidence. Afterwards, the radio signal is filtered to the band of 70-350 MHz. By applying neural networks to search for radio signals in about four months of data, we find about five times more events than by a traditional method based on a signal-to-noise ratio cut after filtering for radio frequency interferences. Despite the lower threshold, the purity of the selected events seems to improve, and the angular resolution of the radio measurements does not deteriorate, which we have confirmed by a comparison of the reconstructed shower direction with IceTop. This analysis thus provides experimental confirmation that neural networks can indeed be used to clean air-shower radio signals from background and to lower the radio detection threshold of hybrid arrays combining particle and radio detectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19931v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.22323/1.470.0034</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PoS(ARENA2024)034</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Frank G. Schroeder (for the IceCube Collaboration), Abdul Rehman (for the IceCube Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linnik point spread functions, time-reversed logarithmic diffusion equations, and blind deconvolution of electron microscope imagery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19420</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19420v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A non iterative direct blind deconvolution procedure, previously used successfully to sharpen Hubble Space Telescope imagery, is now found useful in sharpening nanoscale scanning electron microscope (SEM) and helium ion microscope (HIM) images. The method is restricted to images $g(x,y)$, whose Fourier transforms $\hat{g}(\xi,\eta)$ are such that $log~|\hat{g}(\xi,0)|$ is globally monotone decreasing and convex. The method is not applicable to defocus blurs. A point spread function in the form of a Linnik probability density function is postulated, with parameters obtained by least squares fitting the Fourier transform of the preconditioned microscopy image. Deconvolution is implemented in slow motion by marching backward in time, in Fourier space, from $t = 1$ to $t = 0$, in an associated logarithmic diffusion equation. Best results are usually found in a partial deconvolution at time $\bar{t}$, with $0 &lt; \bar{t} &lt; 1$, rather than in total deconvolution at $t=0$. The method requires familarity with microscopy images, as well as interactive search for optimal parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19420v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.6028/NIST.TN.2324</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>2024 NIST Technical Note 2324</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alfred S. Carasso, Andras E. Vladar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recommended Actions for the American Astronomical Society: CSWA's Perspective on Steps for a more Inclusive Astronomy -- I. Background and Methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19432v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In a series of two papers, we provide a comprehensive agenda of actions the American Astronomical Society (AAS) can take to create a more diverse and inclusive professional system for astronomers, with a focus on women astronomers. This first paper of the series outlines the background and methods, while the recommendations are treated in the second companion paper (Paper II). We take the stance that since the 2020 Decadal Survey (Astro2020) was delivered in 2021, with its first-ever set of recommendations on the State of the Profession, now is the time for the AAS to take decisive action to transform astronomy into a diverse and inclusive profession. In the spring of 2019, the CSWA surveyed the astronomical community to assess the popularity and feasibility of actions that the AAS can take to reduce harassment and advance career development for women in astronomy. Here we present the quantitative results of that survey and a synopsis of the free response sections, which are publicly accessible. By combining the results of our survey, peer-reviewed academic literature, and findings from many of the white papers submitted to Astro2020, the CSWA has developed 26 specific actions that the AAS can take to help end harassment in astronomy, to advance career development for astronomers who are women and who are other members of historically marginalized groups, and intersections of these populations, and to improve the climate and culture of AAS and AAS-sponsored meetings. This paper presents the data we used to make these recommendations, and the recommendations themselves will be presented in Paper II.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19432v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/25c2cfeb.cdff43a1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Bulletin of the AAS, 57(1)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rachel Wexler, Patricia Knezek, Gregory Rudnick, Nicolle Zellner, Kathleen Eckert, JoEllen McBride, Maria Patterson, Christina Richey, the Committee on the Status of Women in Astronomy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recommended Actions for the American Astronomical Society: CSWA's Perspective on Steps for a more Inclusive Astronomy -- II. Recommendations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19433</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19433v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper, the second in a series of two, provides a set of recommendations that the American Astronomical Society (AAS) can take to create a more diverse and inclusive professional society for astronomers, with a focus on women astronomers. As noted in Paper I, now is the time for the AAS to take decisive action to transform astronomy into a diverse and inclusive profession. By combining the results of our 2019 survey, which is described in Paper I, peer-reviewed academic literature, and findings from many of the white papers submitted to Astro2020, the CSWA has developed 26 specific actions the AAS can take to help end harassment and bullying in astronomy; advance career development for astronomers who are women, members of other underrepresented groups, and intersections of these populations; and improve the climate and culture of AAS meetings. Actions to reduce rates of harassment and bullying include improvements to the AAS's anti-harassment policies and procedures and the development of astronomy-specific anti-harassment training resources. Actions to advance career development include creating a compensation database, improving how jobs are posted in the AAS Job Register, and supporting/enhancing a distance mentorship program. Finally, we call on the AAS to continue improving the accessibility of AAS meetings and to continue to support meeting sessions whose focus is to discuss issues of equity, diversity, and inclusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19433v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/25c2cfeb.144eafda</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Bulletin of the AAS, 57(1)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rachel Wexler, Patricia Knezek, Gregory Rudnick, Nicolle Zellner, Kathleen Eckert, JoEllen McBride, Maria Patterson, Christina Richey, the Committee on the Status of Women in Astronomy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stellar Models Also Limit Exoplanet Atmosphere Studies in Emission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19585</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19585v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Stellar contamination has long been recognized as a major bottleneck in transmission spectroscopy, limiting our ability to accurately characterize exoplanet atmospheres, particularly for terrestrial worlds. In response, significant observational efforts have shifted toward emission spectroscopy as a potentially more robust alternative, exemplified by initiatives such as the 50 hour JWST "Rocky Worlds" Director's Discretionary Time (DDT) program. However, the extent to which emission spectroscopy may be affected by stellar effects remain mostly unexplored, in stark contrast with exploration and mitigation work for transmission spectroscopy. In this study, we assess the impact of imperfect knowledge of stellar spectra on exoplanet atmospheric retrievals from emission spectroscopy. For TRAPPIST-1, a 29 ppm precision on the 15 um eclipse depth is required to differentiate surface albedo with precision of 0.1 at 3 sigma confidence. Yet, we find that current 15 um eclipse depth estimations using different stellar models introduce a 40 to 80 ppm uncertainty. Moreover, such model precision should not be mistaken for a model accuracy, as we also find that JWST MIRI photometric observations of the star in-eclipse at 12.8 and 15 um, acquired with a 90 ppm 1 sigma precision, fall outside the range defined by existing models by 7 to 21 %. This lack of precision and accuracy leads to a degeneracy in retrievals of planetary albedo and impacts the search for atmospheres, effects that could be solved by acquiring the true mid-IR spectrum of the star. We therefore recommend a revised observation design for JWST secondary eclipse measurements in which mid-IR stellar spectra should be systematically acquired alongside eclipse data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19585v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas J. Fauchez, Benjamin V. Rackham, Elsa Ducrot, Kevin B. Stevenson, Julien de Wit</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Science Potential and Technical Design of the IceCube-Gen2 Surface Array (UHECR 2024)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19950v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: IceCube-Gen2, the next generation extension of the IceCube Neutrino Observatory at the South Pole, offers a unique scientific potential for cosmic-ray physics at PeV to EeV energies complementing the main science case of neutrino astronomy. The cosmic-ray science case will be enabled by a surface array on top of an extended optical array deep in the polar ice. The optical array measures TeV muons of air showers, and the surface array primarily measures the electromagnetic shower component and low-energy muons. The design of the surface array foresees scintillation panels providing a full-efficiency threshold for near-vertical proton showers of 0.5 PeV and radio antennas increasing the measurement accuracy for the electromagnetic shower component in the energy range of the Galactic-to-extragalactic transition. Compared to IceCube, the aperture for air showers measured in coincidence with the surface and optical arrays will increase by a factor of 30, due to the larger area and angular acceptance in zenith angle. The science potential includes both, the particle physics of air showers, such as prompt muons, and the astrophysics of the highest energy Galactic cosmic-rays, enabled by the higher sensitivity for the mass composition and anisotropy of cosmic rays, and by the search for PeV photons. This proceeding summarizes the science case and design of the surface array as presented in the recently released IceCube-Gen2 Technical Design Report: https://icecube-gen2.wisc.edu/science/publications/tdr/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19950v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.22323/1.484.0055</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PoS(UHECR2024)055</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Frank G. Schroeder (for the IceCube-Gen2 Collaboration)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-contrast spectroscopy with the new VLT/ERIS instrument: Molecular maps and radial velocity of the gas giant AF Lep b</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19961v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Enhanced Resolution Imager and Spectrograph (ERIS) is the new Adaptive-Optics (AO) assisted Infrared instrument at the Very Large Telescope (VLT). Its refurbished Integral Field Spectrograph (IFS) SPIFFIER leverages a new AO module, enabling high-contrast imaging applications and giving access to the orbital and atmospheric characterisation of super-Jovian exoplanets. We test the detection limits of ERIS and demonstrate its scientific potential by exploring the atmospheric composition of the young super-Jovian AF Lep b and improving its orbital solution by measuring its radial velocity relative to its host star. We present new spectroscopic observations of AF Lep b in $K$-band at $R\sim 11000$ obtained with ERIS/SPIFFIER at the VLT. We reduce the data using the standard pipeline together with a custom wavelength calibration routine, and remove the stellar PSF using principal component analysis along the spectral axis. We compute molecular maps by cross-correlating the residuals with molecular spectral templates and measure the radial velocity of the planet relative to the star. Furthermore, we compute contrast grids for molecular mapping by injecting fake planets. We detect a strong signal from H$_{2}$O and CO but not from CH$_{4}$ or CO$_{2}$. This result corroborates the hypothesis of chemical disequilibrium in the atmosphere of AF Lep b. Our measurement of the RV of the planet yields $\Delta v_{\mathrm{R,P\star}} = 7.8 \pm 1.7$ km s$^{-1}$. This enables us to disentangle the degeneracy of the orbital solution, namely the correct longitude of the ascending node is $\Omega=248^{+0.4}_{-0.7}$ deg and the argument of periapsis is $\omega=109^{+13}_{-21}$ deg. Our results demonstrate the competitiveness of the new ERIS/SPIFFIER instrument for the orbital and atmospheric characterisation of exoplanets at high contrast and small angular separation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19961v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean Hayoz, Markus Johannes Bonse, Felix Dannert, Emily Omaya Garvin, Gabriele Cugno, Polychronis Patapis, Timothy D. Gebhard, William O. Balmer, Robert J. De Rosa, Alexander Agudo Berbel, Yixian Cao, Gilles Orban de Xivry, Tomas Stolker, Richard Davies, Olivier Absil, Hans Martin Schmid, Sascha Patrick Quanz, Guido Agapito, Andrea Baruffolo, Martin Black, Marco Bonaglia, Runa Briguglio, Luca Carbonaro, Giovanni Cresci, Yigit Dallilar, Matthias Deysenroth, Ivan Di Antonio, Amico Di Cianno, Gianluca Di Rico, David Doelman, Mauro Dolci, Frank Eisenhauer, Simone Esposito, Daniela Fantinel, Debora Ferruzzi, Helmut Feuchtgruber, Natascha F\"orster-Schreiber, Xiaofeng Gao, Reinhard Genzel, Stefan Gillessen, Adrian Glauser, Paolo Grani, Michael Hartl, David Henry, Heinrich Huber, Christoph Keller, Matthew Kenworthy, Kateryna Kravchenko, John Lightfoot, David Lunney, Dieter Lutz, Mike Macintosh, Filippo Manucci, Thomas Ott, David Pearson, Alfio Puglisi, Sebastian Rabien, Christian Rau, Armando Riccardi, Bernardo Salasnich, Taro Shimizu, Frans Snik, Eckhard Sturm, Linda Tacconi, William Taylor, Angelo Valentini, Christopher Waring, Erich Wiezorrek, Marco Xompero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Radio Detection of ultra-high-energy Cosmic-Ray Air Showers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.19969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.19969v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Radio antennas have become a standard tool for the detection of cosmic-ray air showers in the energy range above $10^{16}\,$eV. The radio signal of these air showers is generated mostly due to the deflection of electrons and positrons in the geomagnetic field, and contains information about the energy and the depth of the maximum of the air showers. Unlike the traditional air-Cherenkov and air-fluorescence techniques for the electromagnetic shower component, radio detection is not restricted to clear nights, and recent experiments have demonstrated that the measurement accuracy can compete with these traditional techniques. Numerous particle detector arrays for air showers have thus been or will be complemented by radio antennas. In particular when combined with muon detectors, the complementary information provided by the radio antennas can enhance the total accuracy for the arrival direction, energy and mass of the primary cosmic rays. Digitization and computational techniques have been crucial for this recent progress, and radio detection will play an important role in next-generation experiments for ultra-high-energy cosmic rays. Moreover, stand-alone radio experiments are under development and will search for ultra-high-energy photons and neutrinos in addition to cosmic rays. This article provides a brief introduction to the physics of the radio emission of air showers, an overview of air-shower observatories using radio antennas, and highlights some of their recent results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.19969v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjs/s11734-025-01503-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Frank G. Schr\"oder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fundamental Physics and Cosmology with TianQin</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20138v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The exploration of the surrounding world and the universe is an important theme in the legacy of humankind. The detection of gravitational waves is adding a new dimension to this grand effort. What are the fundamental physical laws governing the dynamics of the universe? What is the fundamental composition of the universe? How has the universe evolved in the past and how will it evolve in the future? These are the basic questions that press for answers. The space-based gravitational wave detector TianQin will tune in to gravitational waves in the millihertz frequency range ($10^{-4} \sim 1$ Hz, to be specific), opening a new gravitational wave spectrum window to explore many of the previously hidden sectors of the universe. TianQin will discover many astrophysical systems, populating the universe at different redshifts: some will be of new types that have never been detected before, some will have very high signal-to-noise ratios, and some will have very high parameter estimation precision. The plethora of information collected will bring us to new fronts on which to search for the breaking points of general relativity, the possible violation of established physical laws, the signature of possible new gravitational physics and new fundamental fields, and to improve our knowledge on the expansion history of the universe. In this white paper, we highlight the advances that TianQin can bring to fundamental physics and cosmology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20138v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Luo, Haipeng An, Ligong Bian, Rong-Gen Cai, Zhoujian Cao, Wenbiao Han, Jianhua He, Martin A. Hendry, Bin Hu, Yi-Ming Hu, Fa Peng Huang, Shun-Jia Huang, Sang Pyo Kim, En-Kun Li, Yu-Xiao Liu, Vadim Milyukov, Shi Pi, Konstantin Postnov, Misao Sasaki, Cheng-Gang Shao, Lijing Shao, Changfu Shi, Shuo Sun, Anzhong Wang, Pan-Pan Wang, Sai Wang, Shao-Jiang Wang, Zhong-Zhi Xianyu, Huan Yang, Tao Yang, Jian-dong Zhang, Xin Zhang, Wen Zhao, Liang-Gui Zhu, Jianwei Mei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Paths to Robust Exoplanet Science Yield Margin for the Habitable Worlds Observatory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19418v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Habitable Worlds Observatory (HWO) will seek to detect and characterize potentially Earth-like planets around other stars. To ensure that the mission achieves the Astro2020 Decadal's recommended goal of 25 exoEarth candidates (EECs), we must take into account the probabilistic nature of exoplanet detections and provide "science margin" to budget for astrophysical uncertainties with a reasonable level of confidence. In this study, we explore the probabilistic distributions of yields to be expected from a blind exoEarth survey conducted by such a mission. We identify and estimate the impact of all major known sources of astrophysical uncertainty on the exoEarth candidate yield. As expected, eta_Earth uncertainties dominate the uncertainty in EEC yield, but we show that sampling uncertainties inherent to a blind survey are another important source of uncertainty that should be budgeted for during mission design. We adopt the Large UV/Optical/IR Surveyor Design B (LUVOIR-B) as a baseline and modify the telescope diameter to estimate the science margin provided by a larger telescope. We then depart from the LUVOIR-B baseline design and identify six possible design changes that, when compiled, provide large gains in exoEarth candidate yield and more than an order of magnitude reduction in exposure times for the highest priority targets. We conclude that a combination of telescope diameter increase and design improvements could provide robust exoplanet science margins for HWO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19418v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christopher C. Stark, Bertrand Mennesson, Steve Bryson, Eric B. Ford, Tyler D. Robinson, Ruslan Belikov, Matthew R. Bolcar, Lee D. Feinberg, Olivier Guyon, Natasha Latouf, Avi M. Mandell, Bernard J. Rauscher, Dan Sirbu, Noah W. Tuchow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calculating Bayesian evidence for inflationary models using CONNECT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.03968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.03968v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Bayesian evidence is a standard tool used for comparing the ability of different models to fit available data and is used extensively in cosmology. However, since the evidence calculation involves performing an integral of the likelihood function over the entire space of model parameters this can be prohibitively expensive in terms of both CPU and time consumption. For example, in the simplest $\Lambda$CDM model and using CMB data from the Planck satellite, the dimensionality of the model space is over 30 (typically 6 cosmological parameters and 28 nuisance parameters). Even the simplest possible model requires $\mathcal{O}(10^6)$ calls to an Einstein--Boltzmann solver such as CLASS or CAMB and takes several days.
  Here we present calculations of Bayesian evidence using the CONNECT framework to calculate cosmological observables. We demonstrate that we can achieve results comparable to those obtained using Einstein--Boltzmann solvers, but at a minute fraction of the computational cost. As a test case, we then go on to compute Bayesian evidence ratios for a selection of slow-roll inflationary models.
  In the setup presented here, the total computation time is completely dominated by the likelihood function calculation which now becomes the main bottleneck for increasing computation speed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.03968v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Camilla T. G. S{\o}rensen, Steen Hannestad, Andreas Nygaard, Thomas Tram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ionospheric effect on the synthetic Epoch of Reionization observations with the SKA1-Low</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17573v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The redshifted $21$\,cm signal of neutral hydrogen can be used as a direct probe of the intergalactic medium during Cosmic Dawn\,(CD) and Epoch of Reionization\,(EoR). However, detecting this inherently weak signal has numerous challenges. The major ones include accurate foreground removal from low-frequency radio observations and systematics arising from instrumental effects. The Earth's ionosphere poses a major obstacle at these low radio frequencies. Thus, a systematic study of ionospheric effects on these sensitive low-frequency observations is critical, given that the construction of the Square Kilometre Array (SKA1-Low) is in full progress. We use the end-to-end pipeline, called {\sc 21cme2e}, to study the effect of time-varying ionospheric corruption on the $21$\,cm power spectrum recovery. We use two models: a) a catalogue-based model focused on source position shift due to the refractive effect of the ionosphere and b) a realistic ionospheric condition generated using Kolmogorov's turbulence model. We assess the effect of the imperfections thus generated on the extraction of \HI\ $21$\,cm signal power spectrum. Our study shows that beyond ``median ionospheric offset" ($\theta_{\text{MIO}} \lesssim 0.1''$), the $21$\,cm signal from the EoR is unaffected by residual ionospheric effects. Our study emphasizes the need for the development of efficient ionospheric calibration algorithms for the upcoming SKA1-Low observations to extract the \HI\ $21$\,cm power spectra from the CD/EoR.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17573v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/02/058</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP, Volume 2025, February 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Samit Kumar Pal, Abhirup Datta, Aishrila Mazumder</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
