<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-harmonic and special shape/pattern/template approximations of discrete signals with generally irregular arguments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11518v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The invited review of own algorithms and software (MAVKA and MCV) for the data analysis of astronomical signals - irregularly spaced, multi-periodic multi-harmonic, periodogram analysis and approximations with taking into account a polynomial trend simultaneously, instead of commonle used detrending and prewhitening. The references to original papers are listed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11518v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ivan L. Andronov, Hanna M. Akopian, Vitalii V. Breus, Lidiia L. Chinarova, Larysa S. Kudashkina, Nina V. Savchuk, Serhii I. Iovchev, Vladyslava I. Marsakova, Serhii V. Kolesnikov, Maksym Yu. Pyatnytskyy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Machine Learning Framework for Stellar Collision Transient Identification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11529v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modern astronomical surveys, such as the Zwicky Transient Facility (ZTF), are capable of detecting thousands of transient events per year, necessitating the use of automated and scalable data analysis techniques. Recent advances in machine learning have enabled the efficient classification and characterization of these transient phenomena. We aim to develop a fully systematic pipeline to identify candidate stellar collision events in galactic nuclei, which may otherwise be identified as tidal disruption events or other transients. We also seek to validate our simulations by comparing key physical parameters derived from observations and used in modeling these events. We generate a comprehensive bank of simulated light curves spanning a range of physical parameters and employ an approximate nearest neighbor algorithm (via the annoy library) to match these with observed ZTF light curves. Our pipeline is successfully able to associate observed ZTF light curves with simulated events. The resulting estimated parameters, including supermassive black hole masses and ejecta mass, are presented and compared to known values when applicable. We demonstrate that a systematic, machine learning-based approach can effectively identify and characterize stellar collision candidate events from large-scale transient surveys. This methodology is especially promising for future surveys which will provide us with significantly high volumes of data, such as LSST, where automated, data-intensive analysis will be critical for advancing our understanding of transient astrophysical phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11529v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Betty X. Hu, Avi Loeb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the impact of satellites on radio astronomy observations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11561v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Radio telescopes observe extremely faint emission from astronomical objects, ranging from compact sources to large scale structures that can be seen across the whole sky. Satellites actively transmit at radio frequencies (particularly at 10--20\,GHz, but usage of increasing broader frequency ranges are already planned for the future by satellite operators), and can appear as bright as the Sun in radio astronomy observations. Remote locations have historically enabled telescopes to avoid most interference, however this is no longer the case with dramatically increasing numbers of satellites that transmit everywhere on Earth. Even more remote locations such as the far side of the Moon may provide new radio astronomy observation opportunities, but only if they are protected from satellite transmissions. Improving our understanding of satellite transmissions on radio telescopes across the whole spectrum and beyond is urgently needed to overcome this new observational challenge, as part of ensuring the future access to dark and quiet skies.
  In this contribution we summarise the current status of observations of active satellites at radio frequencies, the implications for future astronomical observations, and the longer-term consequences of an increasing number of active satellites. This will include frequencies where satellites actively transmit, where they unintentionally also transmit, and considerations about thermal emission and other unintended emissions. This work is ongoing through the IAU CPS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11561v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Peel, S. Eggl, M. L. Rawls, H. Qiu, D. L. Clements</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning to improve the discovery of near-Earth asteroids in the Zwicky Transient Facility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11918</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11918v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a novel pipeline that uses a convolutional neural network (CNN) to improve the detection capability of near-Earth asteroids (NEAs) in the context of planetary defense. Our work aims to minimize the dependency on human intervention of the current approach adopted by the Zwicky Transient Facility (ZTF). The target NEAs have a high proper motion of up to tens of degrees per day and thus appear as streaks of light in the images. We trained our CNNs to detect these streaks using three datasets: a set with real asteroid streaks, a set with synthetic (i.e., simulated) streaks and a mixed set, and tested the resultant models on real survey images. The results achieved were almost identical across the three models: $0.843\pm0.005$ in completeness and $0.820\pm0.025$ in precision. The bias on streak measurements reported by the CNNs was $1.84\pm0.03$ pixels in streak position, $0.817\pm0.026$ degrees in streak angle and $-0.048\pm0.003$ in fractional bias in streak length (computed as the absolute length bias over the streak length, with the negative sign indicating an underestimation). We compared the performance of our CNN trained with a mix of synthetic and real streaks to that of the ZTF human scanners by analyzing a set of 317 streaks flagged as valid by the scanners. Our pipeline detected $80~\%$ of the streaks found by the scanners and 697 additional streaks that were subsequently verified by the scanners to be valid streaks. These results suggest that our automated pipeline can complement the work of the human scanners at no cost for the precision and find more objects than the current approach. They also prove that the synthetic streaks were realistic enough to be used for augmenting training sets when insufficient real streaks are available or exploring the simulation of streaks with unusual characteristics that have not yet been detected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11918v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bel\'en Yu Irureta-Goyena, George Helou, Jean-Paul Kneib, Frank Masci, Thomas Prince, Kumar Venkataramani, Quanzhi Ye, Joseph Masiero, Fr\'ed\'eric Dux, Mathieu Salzmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to use Gaia parallaxes for stars with poor astrometric fits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11528</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11528v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Gaia parallax measurements for stars with poor astrometric fits -- as evidenced by high renormalized unit weight error (RUWE) -- are often assumed to be unreliable, but the extent and nature of their biases remain poorly quantified. High RUWE is usually a consequence of binarity or higher-order multiplicity, so the parallaxes of sources with high RUWE are often of greatest astrophysical interest. Using realistic simulations of Gaia epoch astrometry, we show that the parallax uncertainties of sources with elevated RUWE are underestimated by a factor that ranges from 1 to 4 and can be robustly predicted from observables. We derive an empirical prescription to inflate reported uncertainties based on a simple analytic function of RUWE, apparent magnitude, and parallax. We validate the correction using (a) single-star solutions for Gaia sources with known orbital solutions and (b) wide binaries containing one component with elevated RUWE. The same uncertainty corrections are expected to perform well in DR4 and DR5. Our results demonstrate that Gaia parallaxes for high-RUWE sources can still yield robust distance estimates if uncertainties are appropriately inflated, enabling distance constraints for triples, binaries with periods too long or too short to be fit astrometrically, and sources blended with neighboring sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11528v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kareem El-Badry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarisation-Inclusive Spiking Neural Networks for Real-Time RFI Detection in Modern Radio Telescopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11720v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Radio Frequency Interference (RFI) is a known growing challenge for radio astronomy, intensified by increasing observatory sensitivity and prevalence of orbital RFI sources. Spiking Neural Networks (SNNs) offer a promising solution for real-time RFI detection by exploiting the time-varying nature of radio observation and neuron dynamics together. This work explores the inclusion of polarisation information in SNN-based RFI detection, using simulated data from the Hydrogen Epoch of Reionisation Array (HERA) instrument and provides power usage estimates for deploying SNN-based RFI detection on existing neuromorphic hardware. Preliminary results demonstrate state-of-the-art detection accuracy and highlight possible extensive energy-efficiency gains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11720v1</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas J. Pritchard, Andreas Wicenec, Richard Dodson, Mohammed Bennamoun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recovering the CMB signal with neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11869v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Component separation is the process of extracting one or more emission sources in astrophysical maps. It is therefore crucial to develop models that can accurately clean the cosmic microwave background (CMB) in current and future experiments. In this work, we present a new methodology based on neural networks which operates on realistic temperature and polarization simulations. We assess its performance by comparing the power spectra of the output maps with those of the input maps and other emissions. For temperature, we obtain residuals of $20 \pm \mu K^{2}$. For polarization, we analyze the $E$ and $B$ modes, which are related to density (scalar) and primordial gravitational waves (tensorial) perturbations occurring in the first second of the Universe, obtaining residuals of $10^{-2} \mu K^{2}$ at $l&gt;200$ and $10^{-2}$ and $10^{-3} \mu K^{2}$ for $E$ and $B$, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11869v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. M. Casas, L. Bonavera, J. Gonz\'alez-Nuevo, G. Puglisi, C. Baccigalupi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QSHS: An Axion Dark Matter Resonant Search Apparatus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12257v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We describe a resonant cavity search apparatus for axion dark matter constructed by the Quantum Sensors for the Hidden Sector (QSHS) collaboration. The apparatus is configured to search for QCD axion dark matter, though also has the capability to detect axion-like particles (ALPs), dark photons, and some other forms of wave-like dark matter. Initially, a tuneable cylindrical oxygen-free copper cavity is read out using a low noise microwave amplifier feeding a heterodyne receiver. The cavity is housed in a dilution refrigerator and threaded by a solenoidal magnetic field, nominally 8T. The apparatus also houses a magnetic field shield for housing superconducting electronics, and several other fixed-frequency resonators for use in testing and commissioning various prototype quantum electronic devices sensitive at a range of axion masses in the range $\rm 2.0$ to $\rm 40\,eV/c^2$. We present performance data for the resonator, dilution refrigerator, and magnet, and plans for the first science run.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12257v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Alsulami, I. Bailey, G. Carosi, G. Chapman, B. Chakraborty, E. J. Daw, N. Duc, S. Durham, J. Esmenda, J. Gallop, T. Gamble, T. Godfrey, G. Gregori, J. Halliday, L. Hao, E. Hardy, E. A. Laird, P. Leek, J. March-Russell, P. J. Meeson, C. F. Mostyn, Yu. A. Pashkin, S. O. Peatain, M. Perry, M. Piscitelli, M. Reig, E. J. Romans, S. Sarkar, P. J. Smith, A. Sokolov, N. Song, A. Sundararajan, B. -K Tan, S. M. West, S. Withington</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cataclysmic Variable Candidates Identified in eROSITA-DE DR1,XMM-Newton, Swift, and ROSAT Catalogs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10794</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10794v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cataclysmic variables (CVs) are binary systems with a white dwarf accreting matter from a low-mass star, making them significant sources of X-ray emission in the Galaxy. We present a systematic search for X-ray emitting CV candidates by cross-matching four X-ray catalogs (eROSITA, XMM-Newton, Swift, and ROSAT) with Gaia sources located in the bridge region between the main sequence and white dwarf cooling sequence in the Hertzsprung-Russell diagram. From 444 candidates (267 confirmed CVs and 177 new candidates), we detect orbital modulation in 56 sources using ZTF/TESS light curves. The eROSITA catalog contributes 51% of candidates, outperforming other surveys due to its wider sky coverage and higher sensitivity (~10^{-14} erg cm^{-2} s^{-1}). Our method demonstrates the efficiency of combining X-ray data with time-domain analysis for CV identification, with future eROSITA observations expected to expand the population of X-ray emitting CVs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10794v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangxiang Wang, Jumpei Takata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Design and Fabrication of a lightweight three-lens corrector system for the 2.34-m Vainu Bappu Telescope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10872v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Vainu Bappu Telescope (VBT) is a 2.34-m reflector, primarily supported on-axis field of view, offering high-resolution and low-to-medium resolution spectroscopic observations in its prime and Cassegrain configurations. This study presents the design and fabrication of a compact, lightweight, three-element wide-field corrector (WFC) utilizing three spherical lenses to cover a polychromatic wavelength range over a 30$'$ FoV at prime focus. The WFC design was optimized using ZEMAX, ensuring precision in aberrations, tolerances, and atmospheric dispersion. The fabricated lenses met stringent tolerances, with a $\pm$1 mm deviation in radius of curvature and $\pm$2 mm deviation in center thickness. A mechanical mount was developed to integrate all the WFC lenses, and wavefront error testing for the WFC system was performed using ZYGO interferometry, yielding a Wavefront Error of 0.05 $\lambda$. Laboratory performance tests were designed and conducted using a dedicated setup with achromatic lenses and 100 $\mu m$ fiber-coupled polychromatic light source showed a deviation of 0.1 pixel on-axis and 0.5 pixel at the extreme off-axis field compared to the ZEMAX design, demonstrating that the optical performance of WFC is with minimal aberrations across the entire FoV. The successful integration of the WFC at the VBT prime focus will increase the FoV, enabling the multi-fiber, multi-spectrograph setup in 30$'$ field that will facilitate both OMR and Echelle spectrograph to be used on the same night along with the addition of new multi-object spectrograph and an integral field unit instrument. This will mark a significant upgrade for the VBT, broadening its research potential, and expanding its observational versatility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10872v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nitish Singh, S. Sriram, Ramya Sethuram, Bharat Kumar Yerra, Rahuldeb Burman, G. Nataraj, C Chethan, P. Madan Mohan Kemkar, K Sagayanathan, Saikat Das, Francis Xavier Rozario J</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Additional Planets in TESS Multi-Planet Systems: Testing Empirical Models Based on Kepler Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.03852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.03852v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multi-planet system architectures are frequently used to constrain possible formation and evolutionary pathways of observed exoplanets. Therefore, understanding the predictive and descriptive power of empirical models of these systems is critical to understanding their formation histories. Additionally, if empirical models can reproduce architectures over a range of scales, transit and radial velocity observations can be more easily and effectively used to inform future microlensing, astrometric, and direct imaging surveys. We analyze 52 TESS multi-planet systems previously studied using Dynamite (Dietrich &amp; Apai 2020), who used TESS data alongside empirical models based on Kepler planets to predict additional planets in each system. We analyze additional TESS data to search for these predicted planets. We thereby evaluate the degree to which these models can be used to predict planets in TESS multi-planet systems. Specifically, we study whether a period ratio method or clustered period model is more predictive. We find that the period ratio model predictions are most consistent with the planets discovered since 2020, accounting for detection sensitivity. However, neither model is highly predictive, highlighting the need for additional data and nuanced models to describe the full population. Improved eccentricity and dynamical stability prescriptions incorporated into Dynamite provide a modest improvement in the prediction accuracy. We also find that the current sample of 183 TESS multi-planet systems are are highly dynamically packed, and appear truncated relative to detection biases. These attributes are consistent with the Kepler sample, and suggest a highly efficient formation process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.03852v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emma V. Turtelboom, Jamie Dietrich, Courtney D. Dressing, Caleb K. Harada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to detect periodic radio emissions from an exoplanet, star, or their interaction?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18733</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18733v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The search for radio signals from exoplanets or star-planet interactions is a major challenge, as it is likely the best way to detect and measure a planetary magnetic field and thus prob exoplanets' interior structure. The aim of this article is to demonstrate the relevance of using statistical tools to detect periodic radio signals in unevenly spaced observations, and identify the implications of eas measured period. Identification of periodic radio signal is achieved here by a Lomb-Scargle (LS) analysis. We first apply the technique on simulated astrophysical observations with controlled simulated noise. This allows to characterize the origin of spurious detection peaks in the resulting periodograms, as well as identifying peaks due to real periods in the studied system, as well as resonance or beat periods. We then validate this method on a real signal, using ~1400 hours of data from observations of Jupiter's radio emissions by the NenuFAR radio telescope over more than six years to detect jovian radio emissions periodicities (auroral and induced by the Galilean moons). We demonstrate with the simulation that the LS periodogram allows to correctly identify periodic radio signal, even in a diluted signal. On real measurements, it correctly detects the rotation period of the strong signal produced by Jupiter and the synodic period of the emission triggered by the interaction between Jupiter and its Galilean moon Io, but also possibly weaker signal such as the one produced by the interaction between Jupiter and Europa or between Jupiter and Ganymede. It is important to note that secondary peaks in the LS periodogram will be observed at the synodic and resonance periods between all the detected signal periodicities (i.e. real signals, but also periodicities in the observation). These secondary peaks can then be used to strengthen the detections of weak signals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18733v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. K. Louis, A. Loh, P. Zarka, L. Lamy, E. Mauduit, J. N. Girard, J. -M. Griessmeier, B. Cecconi, Q. N\'enon, S. Corbel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Prototype Atom Interferometer to Detect Dark Matter and Gravitational Waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09158</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09158v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The AION project has built a tabletop prototype of a single-photon long-baseline atom interferometer using the 87Sr clock transition - a type of quantum sensor designed to search for dark matter and gravitational waves. Our prototype detector operates at the Standard Quantum Limit (SQL), producing a signal with no unexpected noise beyond atom shot noise. Importantly, the detector remains at the SQL even when additional laser phase noise is introduced, emulating conditions in a long-baseline detector such as AION or AEDGE where significant laser phase deviations will accumulate during long atom interrogation times. Our results mark a key milestone in extending atom interferometers to long baselines. Such interferometers can complement laser-interferometer gravitational wave detectors by accessing the mid-frequency gravitational wave band around 1 Hz, and can search for physics beyond the Standard Model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09158v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. F. A. Baynham, R. Hobson, O. Buchmueller, D. Evans, L. Hawkins, L. Iannizzotto-Venezze, A. Josset, D. Lee, E. Pasatembou, B. E. Sauer, M. R. Tarbutt, T. Walker, O. Ennis, U. Chauhan, A. Brzakalik, S. Dey, S. Hedges, B. Stray, M. Langlois, K. Bongs, T. Hird, S. Lellouch, M. Holynski, B. Bostwick, J. Chen, Z. Eyler, V. Gibson, T. L. Harte, C. C. Hsu, M. Karzazi, C. Lu, B. Millward, J. Mitchell, N. Mouelle, B. Panchumarthi, J. Scheper, U. Schneider, X. Su, Y. Tang, K. Tkalcec, M. Zeuner, S. Zhang, Y. Zhi, L. Badurina, A. Beniwal, D. Blas, J. Carlton, J. Ellis, C. McCabe, G. Parish, D. Pathak Govardhan, V. Vaskonen, T. Bowcock, K. Bridges, A. Carroll, J. Coleman, G. Elertas, S. Hindley, C. Metelko, H. Throssell, J. N. Tinsley, E. Bentine, M. Booth, D. Bortoletto, N. Callaghan, C. Foot, C. Gomez-Monedero, K. Hughes, A. James, T. Leese, A. Lowe, J. March-Russell, J. Sander, J. Schelfhout, I. Shipsey, D. Weatherill, D. Wood, M. G. Bason, K. Hussain, H. Labiad, A. L. Marchant, T. C. Thornton, T. Valenzuela, S. N. Balashov, P. Majewski, D. Newbold, M. G. D. van der Grinten, Z. Pan, Z. Tam, I. Wilmut, K. Clarke, A. Vick</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
