<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 05:00:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A New Plotly-Dash-based Query Infrastructure for the Keck Observatory Archive</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15057v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Keck Observatory Archive (KOA) curates all observational data acquired at the W. M. Keck Observatory. The archive is expected to grow rapidly as complex new instruments are commissioned and as the expectations of archive users have expanded. In response, KOA has implemented a new Python-based, VO-compliant query infrastructure. This work is a continuation of the architectural design and technology selection identified at ADASS 2024. We have deployed real-time ingestion of newly acquired data and a dedicated interface for observers to manage these data. Our ADASS 2024 poster identified the new technologies chosen: Plotly-Dash, a low-code framework that exploits event-driven callbacks to simplify the handling of user interactions; R-tree spatial indexing to speed up spatial searches by x20; a VO-compliant TAP middleware, already in use at the NASA Exoplanet Archive and NEID archive; and mViewer, a visualization engine in the Montage Image Mosaic toolkit that is optimized for astronomy images.
  These technologies will underpin new services that can be hosted on web pages or in Jupyter notebooks, and when completed, will replace the current query infrastructure. We have completed two new services now in beta release. The first is the Data Discovery Service, a web-based dashboard that returns spatial and temporal queries of the entire archive in seconds. It supports filtering observations by keywords, previewing results in an interactive data grid, and visualizing images, and it offers data downloads. The second is a Jupyter notebook that performs interactive visualization of Keck observations of protostars in the Rho Oph Dark Cloud and uses data from CDS and IRSA, as well as KOA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15057v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Moseley, G. Bruce Berriman, Christopher R. Gelino, John C. Good, Meca Lynn, Melanie Swain, Toba Oluyide</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GW-FALCON: A Novel Feature-Driven Deep Learning Approach for Early Warning Alerts of BNS and NSBH Inspirals in Next-Generation GW Observatories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15073v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Next-generation GW observatories such as the ET and CE will detect BNS and NSBH inspirals with high SNRs and long in-band durations, making systematic early-warning alerts both feasible and scientifically valuable. Such triggers are essential for coordinating rapid electromagnetic follow-up. In this work, we introduce GW-FALCON, a novel feature-driven DL framework for early-time detection between GW signal+noise and noise-only data in next-generation detectors. Instead of feeding raw time series to CNN or more complex neural network architectures, we first extract a large set of statistical, temporal, and spectral quantities from short observational time windows using the TSFEL library. The resulting fixed-length feature vectors are then used as input to feed-forward ANNs suitable for low-latency operation. We demonstrate the method using simulated BNS and NSBH inspiral waveforms injected into colored Gaussian noise generated from the ET and CE design PSDs. We train separate ANNs on feature sets extracted from partial-inspiral windows characterized by different maximum instantaneous frequencies, enabling early-warning triggers from tens to hundreds of seconds before merger. Across all detector configurations and datasets, the resulting classifiers achieve high accuracy and detection efficiency, with ET-like networks typically reaching test accuracies of order 90% and CE-like ones exceeding 97% at low false-alarm probability. To the best of our knowledge, this work presents the first comprehensive feature-based DL detection framework for Next-generation GW observatories, connecting feature extraction from strain time series data to robust signal-noise classification within a setup that can be extended to real data and to more advanced neural network architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15073v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grigorios Papigkiotis, Georgios Vardakas, Nikolaos Stergioulas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Well-being and career instability across genders in the Spanish Astronomical Society</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15085v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the results of a comprehensive survey conducted among members of the Spanish Astronomical Society (Sociedad Espanola de Astronomia, SEA) to assess well-being, professional satisfaction, and family-work balance of researchers in astronomy. The survey addressed multiple aspects of professional life, including happiness, career stability, publication pressure, and access to childcare services during scientific meetings. Responses were examined across gender and career stages to identify trends and sources of dissatisfaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15085v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41550-026-02784-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Maritza A. Lara-Lopez, I. Rebollido, A. Vidal-Garcia, A. Rouco Escorial, S. Berlanas, I. Garcia-Bernete, B. Agis-Gonzalez, M. Rodriguez-Baras, N. Barrado-Izagirre, I. Pintos Castro, N. Ospina, S. Bonoli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Response to paper Critical Evaluation of Studies Alleging Evidence for Technosignatures in the POSS1-E Photographic Plates by Watters et al. (2026)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15171v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We respond to the critique by Watters et al. (2026) of the statistical analyses in Villarroel et al. (2025) and Bruehl &amp; Villarroel (2025). We argue that the critique conflates object-level validation with ensemble-level statistical inference and relies on a reduced, heterogeneously filtered subset originally constructed for a different scientific purpose. We further question whether the aggressively filtered subset used in Watters et al. (2026) demonstrates a meaningful improvement in sample purity, given the twenty-fold reduction in sample size. Our simple, visual check does not suggest that it does. The subset further lacks complete temporal information and is seriously statistically underpowered for testing the reported Earth-shadow deficit. We emphasise that the horizontal separation metric used for plate assignment and time reconstruction as in Watters et al. (2026) depends on the inclusion of the cos(Dec) factor to ensure geometric consistency. Any omission would alter plate assignment and inferred observation times. Moreover, the analyses presented in Watters et al. (2026) do not include uncertainty estimates or error propagation, limiting the interpretability of the claimed null results. We conclude that the principal findings reported in Villarroel et al. (2025) and Bruehl &amp; Villarroel (2025) are not invalidated by the analyses presented in Watters et al. (2026).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15171v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beatriz Villarroel, Alina Streblyanska, Stephen Bruehl, Stefan Geier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GPS constellation search for exotic physics messengers coincident with the binary neutron star merger GW170817</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Global Positioning System (GPS) includes a continuously operating, planet-scale network of atomic clocks that, beyond navigation and time dissemination, enables precision tests of fundamental physics. Here we use GPS carrier phase archival data to perform a retrospective search for exotic low-mass fields (ELFs) that might be emitted by the binary neutron-star merger GW170817, complementing gravitational wave and electromagnetic modalitiesnin multi-messenger astronomy. Such ultra-relativistic fields would imprint a dispersive, anti-chirp signature in clock-frequency time series, delayed with respect to the LIGO-Virgo gravitational wave detection. We construct network-median pseudo-frequency data from eighteen Rb satellite clocks referenced to a terrestrial hydrogen maser and conduct a template-bank search spanning ELF pulse duration, arrival delay, and characteristic frequency. No statistically significant signal is observed after accounting for noise statistics and template-bank trials. We derive 95\% confidence-level lower bounds on the interaction energy scale $\Lambda_\alpha$ of quadratic couplings driving variations in electromagnetic fine-structure constant. These limits improve upon existing astrophysical and gravity-test constraints across the ELF-energy range $\approx10^{-18}$--$10^{-14}\,\mathrm{eV}$. This demonstrates that mature global satellite-clock networks provide an observational capability for retrospective, multi-messenger searches for new physics using decades of archival timing data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15296v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arko P. Sen, Geoffrey Blewitt, Andrey Sarantsev, Paul Ries, Andrei Derevianko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Slow focus sensor for the Keck I laser guide star adaptive optics system using focal plane wavefront sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15746v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Laser guide stars (LGSs) have been deployed for the last 20-30 years in ground-based astronomical telescopes to overcome the limited sky coverage of classical adaptive optics (AO) systems. Unfortunately, slow altitude drifts of the sodium layer compromise focus measurements, generating the so-called slow focus error, and, consequently, a natural guide star (NGS) is needed to compensate for that error. Our goal is to develop and operationalize a focal plane wavefront sensing (FPWFS) technique for slow focus tracking for the Keck I telescope, which can significantly increase sky coverage and allow slow focus tracking at higher frequencies, reducing the lag error. We develop, characterize, and compare three different FPWFS algorithms, namely Gerchberg-Saxton (GS), linearized focal plane technique (LiFT), and Gaussian fit (Gf). These algorithms were studied for the specific purpose of slow focus sensing in the NIR (H and K bands) using numerical simulations and data collected at Keck in 2025 (bench and on-sky). The three algorithms were studied and characterized against different criteria such as linearity, computational costs, and resistance to low signal-to-noise ratio and/or residuals. From the results obtained, the main candidate for an on-sky deployment was GS. On-sky tests showed promising results, with GS successfully compensating for purposely introduced focus errors, even under the presence of high turbulence conditions. This work can also be extrapolated to other existing 8-10 m class telescopes, or even future 30-40 m class telescopes, where the use of FPWFS can significantly improve sky coverage and reduce the lag error.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15746v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael M. Salgueiro, Carlos M. Correia, Benoit Neichel, Antonin Bouchez, Peter Wizinowich, Avinash Surendran, Max Service, Thierry Fusco, C\'edric Ta\"issir, Pierre Jouve</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep Learning for Point Spread Function Modeling in Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15780v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the development of a data-driven, AI-based model of the Point Spread Function (PSF) that achieves higher accuracy than the current state-of-the-art approach, "PSF in the Full Field-of-View'' (PIFF). PIFF is widely used in leading weak-lensing surveys, including the Dark Energy Survey (DES), the Hyper Suprime-Cam (HSC) Survey, and the Vera C. Rubin Observatory Legacy Survey of Space and Time (LSST). The PSF characterizes how a point source, such as a star, is imaged after its light traverses the atmosphere and telescope optics, effectively representing the "blurred fingerprint'' of the entire imaging system. Accurate PSF modeling is essential for weak gravitational lensing analyses, as biases in its estimation propagate directly into cosmic shear measurements -- one of the primary cosmological probes of the expansion history of the Universe and the growth of large-scale structure for dark energy studies. To address the limitations of PIFF, which constructs PSF models independently for each CCD and therefore loses spatial coherence across the focal plane, we introduce a deep-learning-based framework for PSF reconstruction. In this approach, an autoencoder is trained on stellar images obtained with the Hyper Suprime-Cam (HSC) of the Subaru Telescope and combined with a Gaussian process to interpolate the PSF across the telescope's full field of view. This hybrid model captures systematic variations across the focal plane and achieves a reconstruction error of $3.4 \times 10^{-6}$ compared to PIFF's $3.7 \times 10^{-6}$, laying the foundation for integration into the LSST Science Pipelines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15780v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Revista eSpectra, Vol. 4, Num. 1, 2026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dayana Andrea Henao Arbel\'aez, Pierre-Fran\c{c}ois L\'eget, Andr\'es Alejandro Plazas Malag\'on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Venting and Outgassing Simulations of Pressurized Lunar Modules: Contamination of the Lunar Environment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15046</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15046v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: One objective of Artemis science is to determine the impact human activities have on the lunar environment, which might compromise science objectives and measurements. We perform a preliminary analysis of the contamination associated with airlock venting and outgassing from a prototype lunar-module geometry intended to host astronauts on the lunar surface. The air flow generated by the depressurization of the airlock, expanding in the lunar exosphere, is studied using the Direct Simulation Monte Carlo (DSMC) method for two different venting configurations and the particle flux on the surface is computed as a function of the distance from the the module. Outgassing from the main body of the module -- assumed to be covered with a Multi-Layer Insulation (MLI) blanketing -- and from the solar panels is then analyzed using a view-factor method, employing outgassing rates from the literature.Our results give preliminary indications of the distance at which contamination levels fall below the values characteristic of native species in the lunar atmosphere. Scientific measurements targeting 40Ar should be carried farther than 30--100 meters from the module, while the detection of lower-abundance species such as polar-crater water might require to travel up to and beyond 3 km from the module.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15046v1</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefano Boccelli, William M. Farrell, Prabal Saxena, Orenthal J. Tucker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coupled Map Lattice for Astronomical Object Formation: A Scenario for Evolution from Star to Disk, Arms, and Companions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15083</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15083v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a new dynamic formation model of a star, a disk, arms, and companions using a coupled map lattice (CML), a complex systems approach. This CML simulates the viscoelastic and chaotic dynamics and evolution of gas clumps containing a little dust with a minimal set of one Eulerian procedure for the flow formation of gas clumps due to gravitational interaction, and one Lagrangian procedure for the collision and mixture of gas clumps due to viscoelastic advection. Despite its simplicity, this CML successfully obtains four typical astronomical objects consistent with protoplanetary disk observations: a central star, Keplerian disk, spiral arms, and even stellar, substellar, and planetary companions. All these formation processes are truly dynamic, with the central star "starring" in them, and they are not based on the conventional disk gravitational instability but on the central star gravitational instability with high-dimensional chaotic gas ejection, namely the chaotic itinerancy. Of particular note is the process in which diverse companions are formed due to the rapid density increase caused by the intersection of spiral arms. This suggests a novel companion formation scenario that should be called "arm-crossing companion formation" with a view to planet formation, which may overcome the radial drift barrier and angular momentum problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15083v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erika Nozawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IT-DPC-SRI: A Cloud-Optimized Archive of Italian Radar Precipitation (2010-2025)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15088v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present IT-DPC-SRI, the first publicly available long-term archive of Italian weather radar precipitation estimates, spanning 16 years (2010--2025). The dataset contains Surface Rainfall Intensity (SRI) observations from the Italian Civil Protection Department's national radar mosaic, harmonized into a coherent Analysis-Ready Cloud-Optimized (ARCO) Zarr datacube. The archive comprises over one million timesteps at temporal resolutions from 15 to 5 minutes, covering a $1200\times1400$ kilometer domain at 1 kilometer spatial resolution, compressed from 7TB to 51GB on disk. We address the historical fragmentation of Italian radar data - previously scattered across heterogeneous formats (OPERA BUFR, HDF5, GeoTIFF) with varying spatial domains and projections - by reprocessing the entire record into a unified store. The dataset is accessible as a static versioned snapshot on Zenodo, via cloud-native access on the ECMWF European Weather Cloud, and as a continuously updated live version on the ArcoDataHub platform. This release fills a significant gap in European radar data availability, as Italy does not participate in the EUMETNET OPERA pan-European radar composite. The dataset is released under a CC BY-SA 4.0 license.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15088v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ao-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriele Franch, Elena Tomasi, Uladzislau Azhel, Giacomo Tomezzoli, Alessandro Camilletti, Virginia Poli, Renata Pelosini, Gianfranco Vulpiani, Gabriella Scipione, Giuseppe Trotta, Matteo Angelinelli, Leif Denby, Irene Livia Kruse, Marco Cristoforetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Searching for Extragalactic Exoplanets: A Survey of the Sagittarius Dwarf Galaxy Stream with TESS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15105v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To date no exoplanets have been detected outside the Milky Way, and their extragalactic occurrence rates are poorly constrained. Using available data from TESS we perform the first transit survey of the Sagittarius dwarf galaxy stream using 15,176 main sequence stars identified as likely members. We calculate an upper limit of $&lt;$1.01% for hot Jupiters with radii of 1-2 R$_{Jup}$ and periods of 0.6-10 days after detecting zero planets. We compare our calculated occurrence rate upper limits to the upper limits found in the Milky Way globular clusters M4 and 47 Tuc. Our 1-$\sigma$ occurrence rate upper limit of $&lt;$0.37% for the Sagittarius dwarf galaxy stream, for planets with radii of 1.5-2 R$_{Jup}$ and periods $&lt;$10 days, is lower than the $&lt;$0.57% upper limit measured in 47 Tuc. Similarly, our 2 sigma upper limit of $&lt;$0.78% for planets with radii of 1.4-2 $_{Jup}$ and periods $&lt;$8 days is below the $&lt;$0.81% upper limit measured in M4. We predict that a future analysis of TESS data with a high detection efficiency for hot Jupiter transit depths would require $\eta_{extragalactic}$ $\geq$ 11,467 target stars to detect a planet of extragalactic origin. Therefore, we predict that a future investigation of TESS data which includes additional extragalactic stellar streams will be able to either detect the first extragalactic origin planet or provide evidence that older, lower metallicity extragalactic environments may experience a lower hot Jupiter occurrence rate than is observed for the Milky Way.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15105v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-3881/ae4345</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>William Schap, Jason Dittmann, Elizabeth Lada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The First Instrumentally Documented Fall of an Iron Meteorite: atmospheric trajectory and ground impact</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15440v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Iron meteorite falls are rare compared to stony meteorites, and until recently no iron meteorite had a reliably determined pre-atmospheric orbit. This changed on 2020 November 7, when a bright fireball was observed across Sweden and neighboring regions, with optical, acoustic, and seismic detections extending up to 665 km from the trajectory. After a month-long recovery effort, a 13.8 kg iron meteorite was discovered near {\AA}dalen, representing the first instrumentally recorded and recovered fall of its type and the first iron meteorite with a derivable heliocentric orbit; the event also exhibited the lowest terminal height measured for a well-documented fireball. We combine optical, infrasound, and seismic data to reconstruct the luminous trajectory and employ a Monte Carlo model to simulate the dark flight phase and predicted strewn field, while also investigating the plausibility of a ricochet prior to final deposition. Our analysis identifies distinct aerodynamic properties of iron meteoroids compared to stony bodies, including the influence of streamlined shapes and deep regmaglypts on drag and flight stability, underscoring the need to incorporate iron-specific parameters into entry models to constrain atmospheric dynamics and improve recovery predictions for future events.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15440v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jarmo Moilanen, Maria Gritsevich, Jaakko Visuri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dust measurements with the Mars Dust Counter on board Nozomi (PLANET-B)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.15576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.15576v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Nozomi was Japan's first space mission to Mars, launched on 3 July 1998 UT. It was equipped with the Mars Dust Counter (MDC) which was an impact ionisation dust detector. MDC detected 96 dust particle impacts when the spacecraft was in Earth orbit and later in interplanetary space, before its operation ended in April 2002 due to a technical failure on board. We compare the Nozomi dust measurements with the dust measurements obtained with the dust detector on board the Ulysses spacecraft. Impact speeds and masses of dust particles measured by Nozomi MDC are overall consistent with the measurements obtained by Ulysses in the same region of interplanetary space. Based on the impact speeds measured while Nozomi was in Earth orbit, MDC detected neither dust particles of natural origin that were bound to the Earth nor space debris. The dust impact rate measured in interplanetary space varied by approximately a factor of 2, consistent with theoretical predictions by the Interplanetary Meteoroid Engineering Model. The particle impact direction was concentrated towards the ecliptic plane, in agreement with an interplanetary origin of the majority of the measured dust particles. No impacts of cometary trail particles could positively be identified during known cometary trail crossings of Nozomi. The Nozomi dust data may become a valuable reference for the dust measurements to be obtained in the same region of interplanetary space with future space missions like, for example, MMX and DESTINY$^+$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.15576v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harald Kr\"uger, Masanori Kobayashi, Hiroshi Kimura, Tomoko Arai, Hakan Svedhem, Sho Sasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ephemeris and Almanac Design for Lunar Navigation Satellites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25161</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25161v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents almanac and ephemeris message representation for lunar navigation satellites supporting the Lunar Augmented Navigation System (LANS). The proposed method combines osculating orbital elements, Chebyshev polynomials, and Fourier series to efficiently represent lunar satellite trajectories subject to complex perturbations from lunar gravity and third-body effects. For the ephemeris, a hybrid Chebyshev--Fourier formulation improves fitting accuracy over long arcs while maintaining message compactness under the data-size constraint of the LunaNet Interoperability Specification. For the almanac, a compact low-order polynomial and Fourier model is introduced to capture mid-term orbital variations over a 15-day fitting arc. The approach is validated for multiple orbit regimes, including 30-hour, 24-hour, and 12-hour elliptical lunar frozen orbits (ELFOs) and a 6-hour polar orbit. Results show that the proposed framework achieves sub-meter position and sub-millimeter-per-second velocity fitting errors within the 900-bit limit for 6-hour ephemeris arcs, and almanac fitting accuracy sufficient for reliable satellite-visibility identification in warm-start operations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25161v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keidai Iiyama, Grace Gao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Numerics of VMEC++</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04374v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: VMEC++ is a Python-friendly, from-scratch reimplementation in C++ of the Variational Moments Equilibrium Code (VMEC), a fixed- and free-boundary ideal-MHD equilibrium solver for stellarators and tokamaks. The first VMEC implementation was written by Steven P. Hirshman and colleagues in the 1980s and 1990s and its latest Fortran incarnation (PARVMEC, https://github.com/ORNL-Fusion/PARVMEC) is widely used in stellarator optimization systems. Our work improves on previous implementations with regard to various critical aspects: special care has been put in providing an idiomatic Python experience, from installation to actual usage; VMEC++ has a zero-crash policy; it supports inputs in the classic INDATA format as well as friendlier JSON files. VMEC++ execution times are typically less than or equal to previous implementations, and time to convergence can be decreased dramatically by leveraging its hot-restart feature: by providing the output of a VMEC++ run as initial state for a subsequent one, VMEC++ is initialized using the previously converged equilibrium. This can dramatically decrease runtimes when running on many similar magnetic configurations as it typically happens in stellarator optimization pipelines. On the flip side, some features of the original Fortran VMEC implementation are not yet available in VMEC++, such as support for non-stellarator-symmetric configurations. This contribution presents the internal numerics of the open-source VMEC++ package publicly for the first time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04374v2</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Schilling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coordinate Systems and Transforms in Space Physics: Terms, Definitions, Implementations, and Recommendations for Reproducibility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.07605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.07605v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In space physics, acronyms for coordinate systems (e.g., \texttt{GEI}, \texttt{GSM}) are commonly used; however, differences in their definitions and implementations can prevent reproducibility. In this work, we compare definitions in online resources, software packages, and frequently cited journal articles and show that implementation differences can lead to transformations between same-named coordinate systems and position values from different data providers to differ significantly. Based on these comparisons and results, and to enable reproducibility, we recommend that (a) a standard for acronyms and definitions for coordinate systems is developed; (b) a standards body develops a citable database of reference data needed for these transforms; (c) a central authority maintains the SPICE (Spacecraft, Planet, Instrument, C-matrix, Events) kernels used by space physics spacecraft missions to generate data products in different coordinate systems; and (d) software developers provide explicit comparisons of their implementations with the results of (b) and documentation on implementation choices. Additionally, we provide recommendations for scientists and metadata developers to ensure that sufficient information is provided to enable reproducibility.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.07605v3</guid>
      <category>physics.space-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. S. Weigel, A. Y. Shih, R. Ringuette, I. Christopher, S. M. Petrinec, S. Turner, R. M. Candey, G. K. Stephens, B. Cecconi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seasonal Variation of Polar Ice: Implications for Ultrahigh Energy Neutrino Detectors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.08921</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.08921v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The upper $100 \, \mathrm{m}$ to $150 \, \mathrm{m}$ of the polar ice sheet, called the firn, has a time-dependent density due to seasonal variations in the surface temperature and snow accumulation. We present RF simulations of an in-ice neutrino-induced radio source that show that these density anomalies create variations in the amplitude and propagation times of radio signals propagating through polar firn at an altitude of ${\sim}3000 \, \mathrm{m}$ above sea level. The received power from signals generated in the ice that refract within the upper ${\sim} 15 \, \mathrm{m}$ firn are subject to a seasonal variation on the order of 10\%. These variations result in an irreducible background uncertainty on the reconstructed neutrino energy and arrival direction for detectors using ice as a detection medium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.08921v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Kyriacou, Steven Prohira, Dave Besson</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
