<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>astro-ph.IM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM</link>
    <description>astro-ph.IM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/astro-ph.IM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 23 Jan 2026 02:38:39 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Sample-efficient non-Gaussian noise reduction in gravitational wave data via learnable wavelets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14326v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce $\texttt{WaveletNet}$, a wavelet-based neural network architecture to identify and reduce non-Gaussian noise in gravitational wave data. Traditionally, convolutional neural networks (CNNs) have been widely used as a flexible machine learning method to mitigate non-Gaussian noise. However, training CNNs requires many data samples, especially when the input data segments are long. Glitches that mimic high-mass black hole signals are empirically known to have a wavelet-like structure. We exploit this property in $\texttt{WaveletNet}$ by using simple neural networks to learn the best family of wavelets to model glitches in the LIGO-Virgo-KAGRA O3 data. Due to its simplicity, our framework is significantly more sample-efficient than CNNs. As a use case, we build upon the $\texttt{TIER}$ method and show how $\texttt{WaveletNet}$ can improve the performance of any search pipeline. We take potential GW candidates from the pipeline, and then downweight the candidates having noisy strain regions in their vicinity. We use our framework in a modular way: we provide an output score which can be added to the pipeline's existing detection statistic score for the candidates. We test our method using candidates from the $\texttt{IAS-HM}$ search pipeline and show that it improves the search sensitive volume by up to 15% for high-mass, asymmetric binaries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14326v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arush Pimpalkar, Digvijay Wadekar, Mark Ho-Yeuk Cheung, Emanuele Berti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>One Attempt at Building an Inclusive &amp; Accessible Hybrid Astronomy Conference: FRB 2025</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14357v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The rapid expansion of the Fast Radio Burst (FRB) field has been accompanied by a simultaneous growth of FRB conferences. While these meetings are essential for interacting with other researchers and establishing collaborations, many remain only accessible to those with substantial travel funding, flexible schedules, or geographical proximity. This introduces barriers that predominantly affect early career researchers (ECRs) and people from under-resourced regions, limiting the growth, diversity, and sustainability of the community. To address these issues, the FRB 2025 conference, held in Montr\'eal in July 2025 with over 200 participants, was designed to prioritize inclusivity and accessibility alongside scientific excellence. In this work, we describe how we implemented these goals, including: organizing committees spearheaded by ECRs, a fully hybrid format including YouTube livestreams, low registration fees, a pedagogical day at the beginning of the conference, local vegetarian catering, and the implementation of flash-talks instead of posters. From a post-conference survey of participants, we were able to assess the effectiveness of our initiatives. Notably, we received very positive feedback from the online participants, which amounted to roughly half of the attendees, especially regarding the livestreams and talk recordings. The pedagogical day was also greatly appreciated. The low registration fees naturally led to challenges, in particular with the audio-visual management, and although areas for improvement were noted, such as poster sessions and support for attendees requiring visas, the conference was generally viewed as a success. Our experience demonstrates that highly accessible, hybrid conferences are possible within modest budgets ($\$20$k CAD), and we outline recommendations for future conferences, both in the FRB field and in other domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14357v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alice P. Curtin, Reshma Anna-Thomas, Amanda M. Cook, Carolina Cruz-Vinaccia, Jason Hessels, Robert Main, In\'es Pastor Marazuela, Lauren Rhodes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PyISH: Python Integral Field Spectroscopy Simulation for HWO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14432v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Habitable Worlds Observatory (HWO) will be a large ultraviolet/optical/near-infrared space telescope operating at the Sun-Earth Lagrange point L2. HWO was highly recommended by the National Academies` 2020 decadal survey and will be the first telescope designed specifically to search for life on planets orbiting other stars. HWO will also be able to perform a host of other transformational astrophysics, including cosmology, galaxy evolution, solar system science, and beyond. The development of the telescope and instrument suite is an iterative process. Example observatory architectures, called exploratory analytic cases (EACs) by the HWO Technology Maturation Project Office (TMPO), are modeled end-to-end to explore the engineering and science trade space. Recently, an ultraviolet Integral Field Spectrograph (UV IFS) was added to HWO's instrument suite for the EACs 4 and 5. To explore the science and engineering trade space for this specific instrument, we developed a high-fidelity UV IFS simulation tool, PyISH. The UV IFS simulation tool is designed to be used by scientists to model specific science cases as seen by a UV IFS on HWO, as well as engineers to explore the trade space when developing potential instrument architectures. The modular components, deliverables, and an example of the tool simulating a specific science case proposed for HWO are described in this paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14432v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grace Sweetak, Breann Sitarski, Kevin France, Randall McEntaffer, Richard Cartwright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Control algorithms for dual-wavefront sensor single-conjugate adaptive optics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14531</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14531v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-contrast imaging systems using active control with adaptive optics (AO) are often limited by non-common path (NCP) aberrations that are seen only at the final science image. AO systems employing focal-plane wavefront sensors (FP-WFSs) are able to simultaneously correct NCP aberrations and measure science images, but they typically require a second stage of control that adds system cost and complexity. We present control algorithms to augment AO systems with FP-WFSs within their existing control setup. We demonstrate inter-arm NCP aberration transfer can be mitigated through temporal filtering, present frequency- and time-domain validation of controller stability and performance, and discuss the optimality of the chosen controllers. This work will enable the development, testing, and installation of FP-WFS technologies for direct imaging of exoplanets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14531v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aditya R. Sengupta, Lisa A. Poyneer, Benjamin L. Gerard, Rebecca Jensen-Clem, Aaron J. Lemmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comment on "Application of the three-dimensional telegraph equation to cosmic-ray transport" (arXiv:1606.08272)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.15125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.15125v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In a recent publication [R. C. Tautz and I. Lerche, Res. Astron. Astrophys. 16, 162 (2016); arXiv:1606.08272], the authors present a derivation of the Green's function for the three-dimensional telegraph equation (also known as the heat wave equation, or relativistic heat conduction equation). We demonstrate that the closed-form expression derived in their Appendix A is incorrect. Specifically, the published solution lacks a Dirac delta term representing the ballistic wavefront and contains an algebraic error in the prefactor of the wake term. These omissions arise from the neglect of distributional derivatives when differentiating a Heaviside step function. We provide a rigorous derivation of the Green's function using the Fourier transform method, verify the correct limiting behavior as the damping vanishes, and pinpoint the exact mathematical step where the original derivation failed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.15125v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrei Galiautdinov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CO$_2$ collision-induced line parameters for the $\nu_3$ band of $^{12}$CH$_4$ measured using a hard-collision speed-dependent line shape and the relaxation matrix formalism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14294v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ten high resolution Fourier transform spectra of the pentad region near 3.3 {\mu}m of methane diluted in carbon dioxide at total pressures up to 800 hPa have been recorded at 296.5(5) K. Including a high resolution spectrum of pure methane at low pressure, these spectra have been analyzed using multi-spectrum fitting techniques. The methane lines were modeled using hard-collision speed-dependent line profiles and line mixing was included in the strongest absorption regions, considering the first order Rosenkranz approximation and the relaxation matrix formalism. CO$_2$ broadening and shift coefficients have been measured, together with the speed dependence of broadening. Results obtained using the two line mixing models are intercompared and compared with previous work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14294v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jqsrt.2024.109069</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Quantitative Spectroscopy and Radiative Transfer, Volume 324, September 2024, p. 109069</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thibault Bertin, Jean Vander Auwera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmo-FOLD: Fast generation and upscaling of field-level cosmological maps with overlap latent diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14377v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We demonstrate the capabilities of probabilistic diffusion models to reduce dramatically the computational cost of expensive hydrodynamical simulations to study the relationship between observable baryonic cosmological probes and dark matter at field level and well into the non-linear regime. We introduce a novel technique, Cosmo-FOLD (Cosmological Fields via Overlap Latent Diffusion) to rapidly generate accurate and arbitrarily large cosmological and astrophysical 3-dimensional fields, conditioned on a given input field. We are able to generate TNG300-2 dark matter density and gas temperature fields from a model trained only on ~1% of the volume (a process we refer to as `upscaling'), reproducing both large scale coherent dark matter filaments and power spectra to within 10% for wavenumbers k &lt;= 5 h Mpc^-1. These results are obtained within a small fraction of the original simulation cost and produced on a single GPU. Beyond one and two points statistics, the bispectrum is also faithfully reproduced through the inclusion of positional encodings. Finally, we demonstrate Cosmo-FOLD's generalisation capabilities by upscaling a CAMELS volume of 25 (Mpc h^-1)^3 to a full TNG300-2 volume of 205 (Mpc h^-1)^3$ with no fine-tuning. Cosmo-FOLD opens the door to full field-level simulation-based inference on cosmological scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14377v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Satvik Mishra, Roberto Trotta, Matteo Viel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inferring Meteoroid Properties with Dynamic Nested Sampling: A Case Study of Orionid and Capricornid Shower Meteors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14426v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate estimation of meteoroid bulk density is crucial for assessing spacecraft impact hazards from sub-millimeter to millimeter-sized meteoroids. Previous studies often used manual tuning or optimization methods to fit ablation and fragmentation models to optical meteor data, but subjective choices made physical properties and uncertainties difficult to compare. We develop a global, statistically robust method that uses Dynamic Nested Sampling to fit an erosion-fragmentation model to meteor light curves and deceleration measured by the Canadian Automated Meteor Observatory (CAMO) mirror tracking system and Electron-Multiplied CCD (EMCCD) cameras. Applied to 15 shower meteors, the method returns posterior distributions and Bayesian evidences for single- and double-fragmentation scenarios. Tests on four synthetic cases recover the known inputs, with best-guess solutions matching the true parameters. For 9 Orionids and 6 Alpha Capricornids with masses 1e-6 to 1e-5 kg, the median bulk density is 159 (+558/-57) kg/m3 for Orionids and 333 (+1089/-114) kg/m3 for Alpha Capricornids. Orionids are consistent with low-density cometary material, while Alpha Capricornids are systematically denser and show a second density cluster near 1300 kg/m3, consistent with higher-density asteroidal material. This framework enables automated, statistically rigorous characterization of meteoroid properties and will be extended to larger samples of shower and sporadic meteors across orbital classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14426v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maximilian Vovk, Peter G. Brown, Denis Vida, Daeyoung Lee, Emma G. Harmos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astrometric Radial Velocities from the Hipparcos-Gaia Catalog of Accelerations and Implications for Astrometric Acceleration Measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14459v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Astrometry from the Gaia satellite and from the long-term combination of Hipparcos and Gaia are now sensitive to sky-plane accelerations as low as $\approx$1 m/s/yr. This paper quantifies and explores an important caveat: apparent nonlinear motion due to a star's nonzero radial velocity can be indistinguishable from real astrometric acceleration. This nonlinear motion is parallel to the proper motion, so it can be both quantified and avoided by projecting apparent astrometric accelerations into components parallel and perpendicular to the proper motion. We illustrate this distinction for a sample of very nearby, fast-moving stars from the Hipparcos-Gaia Catalog of Accelerations (HGCA). We then generalize the effect of stellar radial velocity and projections of the astrometric acceleration to binary stars in which we observe the acceleration of both components. Finally, we demonstrate that the proper motion differences in the HGCA are statistically well-behaved even for the nearest and fastest-moving stars, at least in the component perpendicular to the proper motion. This distinction -- between astrometric acceleration parallel and perpendicular to proper motion -- could have important consequences for future missions reaching extreme astrometric sensitivities around nearby stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14459v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothy D Brandt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Closed-Form Statistical Relations Between Projected Separation, Semimajor Axis, Companion Mass, and Host Acceleration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14688v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: I derive the statistical relationship between a radial velocity or astrometric acceleration (a trend), a companion's mass, and the projected separation of the companion. These relationships, expressed as probability density functions, are analytic and independent of all Keplerian orbital elements so long as orbits are randomly oriented in space. I also derive a closed-form expression for the probability distribution of the ratio of the projected separation to the semimajor axis at fixed eccentricity. This expression can be numerically integrated over eccentricity for an arbitrary distribution of eccentricities. I verify my results with empirical comparisons to equivalent but more complex expressions in the literature based on the equations of Keplerian orbits. The closed-formed expressions derived here would be especially useful for any calculation that requires derivatives, e.g., Hamiltonian Monte Carlo. I also provide a Jupyter notebook including all figures and calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14688v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothy D Brandt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A SiPM-Based RICH Detector with Timing Capabilities for Isotope Identification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14767v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we present a novel compact particle identification (PID) detector concept based on Silicon Photomultipliers (SiPMs) optimized to perform combined Ring-Imaging Cherenkov (RICH) and Time-of-Flight (TOF) measurements using a common photodetector layer. The system consists of a Cherenkov radiator layer separated from a photosensitive surface equipped with SiPMs by an expansion gap. A thin glass slab, acting as a second Cherenkov radiator, is coupled to the SiPMs to perform Cherenkov-based charged particle timing measurements. We assembled a small-scale prototype instrumented with various Hamamatsu SiPM array sensors with pixel pitches ranging from 2 to 3 mm and coupled with 1 mm thick fused silica window. The RICH radiator consisted of a 2 cm thick aerogel tile with a refractive index of 1.03 at 400 nm. The prototype was successfully tested in beam test campaigns at the CERN PS T10 beam line with pions and protons. We measured a single-hit angular resolution of about 4 mrad at the Cherenkov angle saturation value and a time resolution better than 50 ps RMS for charged particles with Z = 1. The present technology makes the proposed SiPM-based PID system particularly attractive for space applications due to the limited detector volumes available. In this work, we present beam test results obtained with the detector prototype and we discuss possible configurations optimized for the identification of ions in space applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14767v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/particles8040094</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Particles 2025, 8(4), 94</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. N. Mazziotta, L. Congedo, G. De Robertis, M. Giliberti, F. Licciulli, A. Liguori, L. Lorusso, N. Nicassio, G. Panzarini, R. Pillera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ExoMiner++ 2.0: Vetting TESS Full-Frame Image Transit Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.14877v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Transiting Exoplanet Survey Satellite (TESS) Full-Frame Images (FFIs) provide photometric time series for millions of stars, enabling transit searches beyond the limited set of pre-selected 2-minute targets. However, FFIs present additional challenges for transit identification and vetting. In this work, we apply ExoMiner++ 2.0, an adaptation of the ExoMiner++ framework originally developed for TESS 2-minute data, to FFI light curves. The model is used to perform large-scale planet versus non-planet classification of Threshold Crossing Events across the sectors analyzed in this study. We construct a uniform vetting catalog of all evaluated signals and assess model performance under different observing conditions. We find that ExoMiner++ 2.0 generalizes effectively to the FFI domain, providing robust discrimination between planetary signals, astrophysical false positives, and instrumental artifacts despite the limitations inherent to longer cadence data. This work extends the applicability of ExoMiner++ to the full TESS dataset and supports future population studies and follow-up prioritization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.14877v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel J. S. Martinho, Hamed Valizadegan, Jon M. Jenkins, Douglas A. Caldwell, Joseph D. Twicken, Ben Tofflemire, Marziye Jafariyazani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient prior sensitivity analysis for Bayesian model comparison</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.15132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.15132v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Bayesian model comparison implements Occam's razor through its sensitivity to the prior. However, prior-dependence makes it important to assess the influence of plausible alternative priors. Such prior sensitivity analyses for the Bayesian evidence are expensive, either requiring repeated, costly model re-fits or specialised sampling schemes. By exploiting the learned harmonic mean estimator (LHME) for evidence calculation we decouple sampling and evidence calculation, allowing resampled posterior draws to be used directly to calculate the evidence without further likelihood evaluations. This provides an alternative approach to prior sensitivity analysis for Bayesian model comparison that dramatically alleviates the computational cost and is agnostic to the method used to generate posterior samples. We validate our method on toy problems and a cosmological case study, reproducing estimates obtained by full Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) sampling and nested sampling re-fits. For the cosmological example considered our approach achieves up to $6000\times$ lower computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.15132v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zixiao Hu, Jason D. McEwen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A nomenclature for individual exocomets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.15176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.15176v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With recent observational advancements, exocomet studies have entered a new era: we have moved from an epoch where exocomets' signatures were analysed to identify their true nature to a new epoch where individual exocomets' detections are studied in detail to characterise the observed bodies. In this context, as with other astronomical objects such as exoplanets and minor bodies in the solar system, a nomenclature system is needed to uniquely identify any observed exocometary body. Here, after outlining the purpose of a nomenclature and its required characteristics, we review the information on exocomets that can be included in the nomenclature. Finally, we propose an exocomet nomenclature scheme to identify the individual exocomets that have been discovered or yet to be discovered. Examples of nomenclature names of a few archetypal exocomets are provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.15176v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11214-025-01261-8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Space Sci Rev 222, 12 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alain Lecavelier des Etangs, Paul A. Str{\o}m, Darryl Z. Seligman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced detection limits in the SHINE F150 survey through the Regime Switching Model. Optimizing thresholds and investigating environmental noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.01511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.01511v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In high-contrast imaging, a novel detection algorithm for angular differential imaging (ADI) sequences has recently been introduced: the Regime Switching Model (RSM). In this study, we apply the RSM algorithm to analyze the F150 sample from the SHINE high-contrast imaging survey carried out with VLT/SPHERE, aiming to enhance detection limits and identify new exoplanet candidates. Additionally, we investigate how environmental conditions influence post-processed noise distributions and detection thresholds. We generate detection maps and contrast curves for 213 observations in the F150 SHINE sample using the RSM algorithm. A clustering approach based on environmental parameters is used to group observations with similar noise characteristics. We propose two methods for defining radial detection thresholds in the RSM maps: fitting a log-normal distribution to the post-processed noise and maximizing the F1 score. We also assess the performance of various combinations of post-processing techniques within the RSM framework to identify optimal configurations. This study demonstrates the utility of clustering based on observational parameters, effectively distinguishing features like wind-driven halos and low-wind effects. Detection thresholds vary significantly across clusters, differing by up to a factor of 10, highlighting the importance of considering observational environments. Log-normal thresholds provide conservative, noise-aware limits, while F1 score-based thresholds offer observation-specific results, both showing compatibility overall. RSM improves detection limits by an average factor of two at 1arcsec and five at inner working angles compared to standard PCA processing. This study reports more than 30 newly detected signals, including one promising candidate awaiting second-epoch confirmation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.01511v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1051/0004-6361/202555206</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mariam Sabalbal, Olivier Absil, Carl-Henrik Dahlqvist, Philippe Delorme</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Habitable Worlds Observatory's Concept and Technology Maturation: Initial Feasibility and Trade Space Exploration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.11803</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.11803v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Habitable Worlds Observatory is the first telescope ever designed to search for life and will be a powerhouse of discovery across topics in astrophysics. The observatory was the top recommendation of the Astro2020 Decadal Survey for large missions and a new HWO Technology Maturation Project Office was formed in August 2024 to mature the architecture, science and technology. In this paper we review the overall approach taken to mature the mission concept. We show progress on architecture development, integrated modeling, science cases, and technology roadmaps consistent with pre-formulation studies. We discuss plans for instrument studies and international engagement and science engagement including a Community Science and Instrument Team. Finally, we describe the plan forward to the Mission Concept Review.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.11803v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lee D. Feinberg, Breann N. Sitarski, Michael W. McElwain, Giada Arney, Caleb Baker, Matthew R. Bolcar, Marie Levine, Alice Liu, Bertrand Mennesson, Aki Roberge, J. Scott Smith, Feng Zhao, John Ziemer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Comparative biosignatures with systemic retrievals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.01512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.01512v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The discovery of inhabited exoplanets hinges on identifying biosignature gases. JWST can reveal biosignature gases, though current discoveries have yet to evidence life. The central challenge is attribution: how can we confidently identify biogenic sources while ruling out, or deeming unlikely, abiotic explanations? Attribution is particularly difficult for individual planets, especially given the stochastic abiotic processes that can set atmospheric conditions. To address this, we propose a comparative multi-planet approach centred on systemic retrievals: the analysis of multiple planets within a system to empirically define the `abiotic baseline'. This baseline, constructed from obligate uninhabited planets, serves as a local reference point. Systemic retrievals enable marginalisation over inaccessible, latent, shared abiotic parameters within planet evolution models. This is possible because planets within a system are linked by their birth in the same natal disk, have been irradiated by the same evolving star, and have a linked dynamical history. Observations aligning with the abiotic baseline, where the locally-informed abiotic planet evolution models demonstrate high out-of-sample predictive accuracy, are likely non-biological. Potentially biological anomalies are identified as statistical outliers from the abiotic baseline using Bayesian leave-one-out cross-validation. A comparative biosignature is thus defined: an anomaly where a biotic planetary evolution model provides a superior fit than its abiotic counterpart. Where both abiotic and biotic models yield poor predictive accuracy, the anomaly is flagged as an ``unknown unknown"; a signature of either unconstrained abiotic processes, or life as we don't yet know it.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.01512v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tereza Constantinou, Oliver Shorttle, Miles Cranmer, Paul B. Rimmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Task-parallelism in SWIFT for heterogeneous compute architectures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14538v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper highlights first steps towards enabling graphics processing unit (GPU) acceleration of the task-parallel smoothed particle hydrodynamics (SPH) solver SWIFT. Novel combinations of algorithms are presented, enabling SWIFT to function as a truly heterogeneous software leveraging task-parallelism on CPUs for memory-bound computations concurrently with GPUs for compute-bound computations while minimising the effects of CPU-GPU communication latency. The proposed algorithms are validated in extensive testing. The GPU acceleration methodology is shown to deliver up to 3.5 and 7.5 speedups for the offloaded computations when including and excluding the time required to prepare and post-process data transfers on the CPU side, respectively. The overall performance of the GPU-accelerated hydrodynamic solver for a full simulation on a single Grace-Hopper superchip is 1.8 times faster compared to the superchips fully parallelised CPU capabilities. This constitutes an improvement from 8 million particle updates/s for the full CPU-only baseline (115,000 updates per CPU core) to 15 million updates/s for the GPU-accelerated SPH solver. Moreover, it displays near-perfect strong scaling on 4 Grace-Hopper nodes. The GPU-acceleration is also demonstrated to give a 29 percent improvement in energy efficiency in comparison to CPU-only baselines. Finally, inter-influential bottlenecks in the prototype solver presented in this work are identified: A significant amount of time (up to 80 percent) of a GPU-offloading cycle is spent on preparing and post-processing particle data on the CPU for the transfer to and from the GPU, respectively. Approaches are suggested to minimise their effects and maximise the solver's performance in our future work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14538v2</guid>
      <category>cs.PF</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/rasti/rzag008</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>RAS Techniques and Instruments, 2026, rzag008</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Abouzied M. A. Nasar, Benedict D. Rogers, Georgios Fourtakas, Mladen Ivkovic, Tobias Weinzierl, Scott T. Kay, Matthieu Schaller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Practical Framework for Estimating the Repetition Likelihood of Fast Radio Bursts from Spectral Morphology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16338</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16338v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The repeating behavior of fast radio bursts (FRBs) is regarded as a key clue to understanding their physical origin, yet reliably distinguishing repeaters from apparent non-repeaters with current observations remains challenging. Here we propose a physically interpretable and practically quantifiable classification framework based on spectral morphology. Using dimensionality reduction, clustering, and feature-importance analysis, we identify the spectral running $r$ and spectral index $\gamma$ as the most critical parameters for distinguishing repeaters from apparent non-repeaters in the CHIME/FRB sample. In the $\gamma$-$r$ space, repeaters preferentially occupy regions with steeper, narrower-band spectra, whereas non-repeaters cluster in flatter, broader-band regions, resulting in a clear density separation. We further construct an empirical probability map in the $\gamma$-$r$ space, showing a clear gradient of repetition likelihood, from $\sim 65\%$ in the high-repetition region to $\sim 5\%$ in the low-repetition region. Combining this with Gaussian Mixture Model posterior analysis, we identify several apparent non-repeaters with high inferred repetition probability, recommending them as priority targets for future monitoring. This framework provides a simple and generalizable tool for assessing repeatability in the CHIME/FRB sample and highlights the diagnostic power of spectral morphology in unveiling FRB origins.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16338v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wan-Peng Sun, Yong-Kun Zhang, Ji-Guo Zhang, Xiaohui Liu, Yichao Li, Fu-Wen Zhang, Wan-Ting Hou, Jing-Fei Zhang, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-bandpass Photometry for Exoplanet Atmosphere Reconnaissance (MPEAR) with the Habitable Worlds Observatory (HWO) -- I. Differentiating Earth from Neptunes During Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.05279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.05279v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As the architecture for the Habitable Worlds Observatory (HWO) is being developed, it is crucial to optimize the observing strategies for a survey to detect and characterize Earth-like planets around Sun-like stars. Efficient target identification and characterization will help drive mission requirements that can be matched to the planned observations. Current HWO concepts allow simultaneous multi-bandpass observations with the coronagraph instrument, critical for performing a qualitative planetary reconnaissance to optimize observing time for deriving orbital constraints and prioritize characterization of promising targets.
  We describe a new algorithm designed to determine the best combination of broadband photometric observations for extracting maximum information from the first visit. It identifies degeneracies in the orbital configurations, fluxes, and noise, and determines optimal secondary photometry bands to reduce these. We demonstrate its application by comparing an Earth seen at quadrature with a cold and a warm Neptune at inclined orbits and varying phases, with comparable flux in the discovery bandpass centered at 500 nm (20\% bandwidth). Using the noise and exposure time calculator that we developed for the HWO coronagraph instrument, we find that the baseline $S/N=7$ (corresponding to 3.2 hours observing time for a planet at 10pc) is only sufficient to marginally differentiate the Earth from a cold Neptune-like planet assuming two parallel bandpasses (550 nm + 850 nm). However, increasing to $S/N=15$ (7 hours observing time) and using three parallel bandpasses (360 nm + 500 nm + 1.11 micron) would differentiate the Earth from either a warm or cold Neptune.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.05279v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eleonora Alei, Avi M. Mandell, Miles H. Currie, Aki Roberge, Christopher C. Stark, Allison Payne, Vincent Kofman, Geronimo L. Villanueva, Renyu Hu, Amber V. Young</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Catching 3I/ATLAS Using a Solar Oberth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02533v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The third interstellar object to be discovered, 3I/ATLAS, has a unique and continually unfolding story to tell about its nature and origin as it is monitored by telescopes on Earth, orbiting Earth and around the Solar System. Previous research into missions using chemical propulsion have only really addressed the direct case, where the opportunity to launch already expired before 3I/ATLAS's discovery. In contrast, investigations herein exploit 'Optimum Interplanetary Trajectory Software' to simulate an alternative indirect option for chemical propulsion, namely the Solar Oberth Manoeuvre (SOM). For a SOM, a low perihelion burn provides maximum benefit from the Oberth Effect, and accelerates the spacecraft rapidly towards the receding 3I/ATLAS. Though in principle feasible, results indicate this option presents significant challenges. For possible launch years between 2031 and 2037 inclusive, a 2035 launch permits the most efficient transfer to 3I/ATLAS. The reference mission requires a SOM at 3.2 Solar Radii from the Sun's centre, with an intercept after 35-50 years. It is found the SOM can leverage spacecraft masses up to $\sim{500}$ kg. Two or three solid propellant boosters could deliver the required SOM $\Delta$V, and furthermore a refuelled Starship Block 3 in LEO has sufficient performance for such a mission. As inevitable with a SOM, some of the payload mass would be needed for a heat shield to protect against the high solar flux at low perihelion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02533v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Hibberd, T. Marshall Eubanks, Andreas Hein</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
