<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.HC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.HC</link>
    <description>cs.HC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.HC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2024 04:00:38 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 22 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>BlendScape: Enabling Unified and Personalized Video-Conferencing Environments through Generative AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13947v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Today's video-conferencing tools support a rich range of professional and social activities, but their generic, grid-based environments cannot be easily adapted to meet the varying needs of distributed collaborators. To enable end-user customization, we developed BlendScape, a system for meeting participants to compose video-conferencing environments tailored to their collaboration context by leveraging AI image generation techniques. BlendScape supports flexible representations of task spaces by blending users' physical or virtual backgrounds into unified environments and implements multimodal interaction techniques to steer the generation. Through an evaluation with 15 end-users, we investigated their customization preferences for work and social scenarios. Participants could rapidly express their design intentions with BlendScape and envisioned using the system to structure collaboration in future meetings, but experienced challenges with preventing distracting elements. We implement scenarios to demonstrate BlendScape's expressiveness in supporting distributed collaboration techniques from prior work and propose composition techniques to improve the quality of environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13947v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shwetha Rajaram, Nels Numan, Balasaravanan Thoravi Kumaravel, Nicolai Marquardt, Andrew D. Wilson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>"This is not a data problem": Algorithms and Power in Public Higher Education in Canada</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13969v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Algorithmic decision-making is increasingly being adopted across public higher education. The expansion of data-driven practices by post-secondary institutions has occurred in parallel with the adoption of New Public Management approaches by neoliberal administrations. In this study, we conduct a qualitative analysis of an in-depth ethnographic case study of data and algorithms in use at a public college in Ontario, Canada. We identify the data, algorithms, and outcomes in use at the college. We assess how the college's processes and relationships support those outcomes and the different stakeholders' perceptions of the college's data-driven systems. In addition, we find that the growing reliance on algorithmic decisions leads to increased student surveillance, exacerbation of existing inequities, and the automation of the faculty-student relationship. Finally, we identify a cycle of increased institutional power perpetuated by algorithmic decision-making, and driven by a push towards financial sustainability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13969v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3613904.3642451</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Kelly McConvey, Shion Guha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crowdsourcing Task Traces for Service Robotics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14014v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Demonstration is an effective end-user development paradigm for teaching robots how to perform new tasks. In this paper, we posit that demonstration is useful not only as a teaching tool, but also as a way to understand and assist end-user developers in thinking about a task at hand. As a first step toward gaining this understanding, we constructed a lightweight web interface to crowdsource step-by-step instructions of common household tasks, leveraging the imaginations and past experiences of potential end-user developers. As evidence of the utility of our interface, we deployed the interface on Amazon Mechanical Turk and collected 207 task traces that span 18 different task categories. We describe our vision for how these task traces can be operationalized as task models within end-user development tools and provide a roadmap for future work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14014v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3568294.3580112</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>David Porfirio, Allison Saupp\'e, Maya Cakmak, Aws Albarghouthi, Bilge Mutlu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>"It's Not a Replacement:" Enabling Parent-Robot Collaboration to Support In-Home Learning Experiences of Young Children</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14041v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Learning companion robots for young children are increasingly adopted in informal learning environments. Although parents play a pivotal role in their children's learning, very little is known about how parents prefer to incorporate robots into their children's learning activities. We developed prototype capabilities for a learning companion robot to deliver educational prompts and responses to parent-child pairs during reading sessions and conducted in-home user studies involving 10 families with children aged 3-5. Our data indicates that parents want to work with robots as collaborators to augment parental activities to foster children's learning, introducing the notion of parent-robot collaboration. Our findings offer an empirical understanding of the needs and challenges of parent-child interaction in informal learning scenarios and design opportunities for integrating a companion robot into these interactions. We offer insights into how robots might be designed to facilitate parent-robot collaboration, including parenting policies, collaboration patterns, and interaction paradigms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14041v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3613904.3642806</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Hui-Ru Ho, Edward Hubbard, Bilge Mutlu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Empowering Personalized Learning through a Conversation-based Tutoring System with Student Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14071v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As the recent Large Language Models(LLM's) become increasingly competent in zero-shot and few-shot reasoning across various domains, educators are showing a growing interest in leveraging these LLM's in conversation-based tutoring systems. However, building a conversation-based personalized tutoring system poses considerable challenges in accurately assessing the student and strategically incorporating the assessment into teaching within the conversation. In this paper, we discuss design considerations for a personalized tutoring system that involves the following two key components: (1) a student modeling with diagnostic components, and (2) a conversation-based tutor utilizing LLM with prompt engineering that incorporates student assessment outcomes and various instructional strategies. Based on these design considerations, we created a proof-of-concept tutoring system focused on personalization and tested it with 20 participants. The results substantiate that our system's framework facilitates personalization, with particular emphasis on the elements constituting student modeling. A web demo of our system is available at http://rlearning-its.com.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14071v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3613905.3651122</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Minju Park, Sojung Kim, Seunghyun Lee, Soonwoo Kwon, Kyuseok Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Design Space for Intelligent and Interactive Writing Assistants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14117v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In our era of rapid technological advancement, the research landscape for writing assistants has become increasingly fragmented across various research communities. We seek to address this challenge by proposing a design space as a structured way to examine and explore the multidimensional space of intelligent and interactive writing assistants. Through a large community collaboration, we explore five aspects of writing assistants: task, user, technology, interaction, and ecosystem. Within each aspect, we define dimensions (i.e., fundamental components of an aspect) and codes (i.e., potential options for each dimension) by systematically reviewing 115 papers. Our design space aims to offer researchers and designers a practical tool to navigate, comprehend, and compare the various possibilities of writing assistants, and aid in the envisioning and design of new writing assistants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14117v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3613904.3642697</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mina Lee, Katy Ilonka Gero, John Joon Young Chung, Simon Buckingham Shum, Vipul Raheja, Hua Shen, Subhashini Venugopalan, Thiemo Wambsganss, David Zhou, Emad A. Alghamdi, Tal August, Avinash Bhat, Madiha Zahrah Choksi, Senjuti Dutta, Jin L. C. Guo, Md Naimul Hoque, Yewon Kim, Seyed Parsa Neshaei, Agnia Sergeyuk, Antonette Shibani, Disha Shrivastava, Lila Shroff, Jessi Stark, Sarah Sterman, Sitong Wang, Antoine Bosselut, Daniel Buschek, Joseph Chee Chang, Sherol Chen, Max Kreminski, Joonsuk Park, Roy Pea, Eugenia H. Rho, Shannon Zejiang Shen, Pao Siangliulue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PeerGPT: Probing the Roles of LLM-based Peer Agents as Team Moderators and Participants in Children's Collaborative Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14227v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In children's collaborative learning, effective peer conversations can significantly enhance the quality of children's collaborative interactions. The integration of Large Language Model (LLM) agents into this setting explores their novel role as peers, assessing impacts as team moderators and participants. We invited two groups of participants to engage in a collaborative learning workshop, where they discussed and proposed conceptual solutions to a design problem. The peer conversation transcripts were analyzed using thematic analysis. We discovered that peer agents, while managing discussions effectively as team moderators, sometimes have their instructions disregarded. As participants, they foster children's creative thinking but may not consistently provide timely feedback. These findings highlight potential design improvements and considerations for peer agents in both roles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14227v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3613905.3651008</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jiawen Liu, Yuanyuan Yao, Pengcheng An, Qi Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recourse for reclamation: Chatting with generative language models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14467</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14467v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Researchers and developers increasingly rely on toxicity scoring to moderate generative language model outputs, in settings such as customer service, information retrieval, and content generation. However, toxicity scoring may render pertinent information inaccessible, rigidify or "value-lock" cultural norms, and prevent language reclamation processes, particularly for marginalized people. In this work, we extend the concept of algorithmic recourse to generative language models: we provide users a novel mechanism to achieve their desired prediction by dynamically setting thresholds for toxicity filtering. Users thereby exercise increased agency relative to interactions with the baseline system. A pilot study ($n = 30$) supports the potential of our proposed recourse mechanism, indicating improvements in usability compared to fixed-threshold toxicity-filtering of model outputs. Future work should explore the intersection of toxicity scoring, model controllability, user agency, and language reclamation processes -- particularly with regard to the bias that many communities encounter when interacting with generative language models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14467v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3613905.3650999</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jennifer Chien, Kevin R. McKee, Jackie Kay, William Isaac</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Human-Centered Explainable AI Interface Are Designed and Evaluated: A Systematic Survey</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14496v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite its technological breakthroughs, eXplainable Artificial Intelligence (XAI) research has limited success in producing the {\em effective explanations} needed by users. In order to improve XAI systems' usability, practical interpretability, and efficacy for real users, the emerging area of {\em Explainable Interfaces} (EIs) focuses on the user interface and user experience design aspects of XAI. This paper presents a systematic survey of 53 publications to identify current trends in human-XAI interaction and promising directions for EI design and development. This is among the first systematic survey of EI research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14496v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thu Nguyen, Alessandro Canossa, Jichen Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Explanation Emphasis in Human-XAI Interaction with Communication Robot</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14550v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Communication robots have the potential to contribute to effective human-XAI interaction as an interface that goes beyond textual or graphical explanations. One of their strengths is that they can use physical and vocal expressions to add detailed nuances to explanations. However, it is not clear how a robot can apply such expressions, or in particular, how we can develop a strategy to adaptively use such expressions depending on the task and user in dynamic interactions. To address this question, this paper proposes DynEmph, a method for a communication robot to decide where to emphasize XAI-generated explanations with physical expressions. It predicts the effect of emphasizing certain points on a user and aims to minimize the expected difference between predicted user decisions and AI-suggested ones. DynEmph features a strategy for deciding where to emphasize in a data-driven manner, relieving engineers from the need to manually design a strategy. We further conducted experiments to investigate how emphasis selection strategies affect the performance of user decisions. The results suggest that, while a naive strategy (emphasizing explanations for an AI's most probable class) does not necessarily work better, DynEmph effectively guides users to better decisions under the condition that the performance of the AI suggestion is high.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14550v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yosuke Fukuchi, Seiji Yamada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Changing human's impression of empathy from agent by verbalizing agent's position</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14557v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As anthropomorphic agents (AI and robots) are increasingly used in society, empathy and trust between people and agents are becoming increasingly important. A better understanding of agents by people will help to improve the problems caused by the future use of agents in society. In the past, there has been a focus on the importance of self-disclosure and the relationship between agents and humans in their interactions. In this study, we focused on the attributes of self-disclosure and the relationship between agents and people. An experiment was conducted to investigate hypotheses on trust and empathy with agents through six attributes of self-disclosure (opinions and attitudes, hobbies, work, money, personality, and body) and through competitive and cooperative relationships before a robotic agent performs a joint task. The experiment consisted of two between-participant factors: six levels of self-disclosure attributes and two levels of relationship with the agent. The results showed that the two factors had no effect on trust in the agent, but there was statistical significance for the attribute of self-disclosure regarding a person's empathy toward the agent. In addition, statistical significance was found regarding the agent's ability to empathize with a person as perceived by the person only in the case where the type of relationship, competitive or cooperative, was presented. The results of this study could lead to an effective method for building relationships with agents, which are increasingly used in society.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14557v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takahiro Tsumura, Seiji Yamada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Looking Together $\neq$ Seeing the Same Thing: Understanding Surgeons' Visual Needs During Intra-operative Coordination and Instruction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14561</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14561v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Shared gaze visualizations have been found to enhance collaboration and communication outcomes in diverse HCI scenarios including computer supported collaborative work and learning contexts. Given the importance of gaze in surgery operations, especially when a surgeon trainer and trainee need to coordinate their actions, research on the use of gaze to facilitate intra-operative coordination and instruction has been limited and shows mixed implications. We performed a field observation of 8 surgeries and an interview study with 14 surgeons to understand their visual needs during operations, informing ways to leverage and augment gaze to enhance intra-operative coordination and instruction. We found that trainees have varying needs in receiving visual guidance which are often unfulfilled by the trainers' instructions. It is critical for surgeons to control the timing of the gaze-based visualizations and effectively interpret gaze data. We suggest overlay technologies, e.g., gaze-based summaries and depth sensing, to augment raw gaze in support of surgical coordination and instruction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14561v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3613904.3641929</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>CHI'2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Vitaliy Popov, Xinyue Chen, Jingying Wang, Michael Kemp, Gurjit Sandhu, Taylor Kantor, Natalie Mateju, Xu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual-sided transparent display</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13831v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the past decade, display technology has been reimagined to meet the needs of the virtual world. By mapping information onto a scene through a transparent display, users can simultaneously visualize both the real world and layers of virtual elements. However, advances in augmented reality (AR) technology have primarily focused on wearable gear or personal devices. Here we present a single display capable of delivering visual information to observers positioned on either side of the transparent device. This dual-sided display system employs a polymer stabilized liquid crystal waveguide technology to achieve a transparency window of 65% while offering active-matrix control. An early-stage prototype exhibits full-color information via time-sequential processing of a red-green-blue (RGB) light-emitting diode (LED) strip. The dual-sided display provides a perspective on transparent mediums as display devices for human-centric and service-related experiences that can support both enhanced bi-directional user interactions and new media platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13831v1</guid>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suman Halder, Yunho Shin, Yidan Peng, Long Wang, Liye Duan, Paul Schmalenberg, Guangkui Qin, Yuxi Gao, Ercan M. Dede, Deng-Ke Yang, Sean P. Rodrigues</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shortchanged: Uncovering and Analyzing Intimate Partner Financial Abuse in Consumer Complaints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.13944v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Digital financial services can introduce new digital-safety risks for users, particularly survivors of intimate partner financial abuse (IPFA). To offer improved support for such users, a comprehensive understanding of their support needs and the barriers they face to redress by financial institutions is essential. Drawing from a dataset of 2.7 million customer complaints, we implement a bespoke workflow that utilizes language-modeling techniques and expert human review to identify complaints describing IPFA. Our mixed-method analysis provides insight into the most common digital financial products involved in these attacks, and the barriers consumers report encountering when doing so. Our contributions are twofold; we offer the first human-labeled dataset for this overlooked harm and provide practical implications for technical practice, research, and design for better supporting and protecting survivors of IPFA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.13944v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arkaprabha Bhattacharya, Kevin Lee, Vineeth Ravi, Jessica Staddon, Rosanna Bellini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>HRI Curriculum for a Liberal Arts Education</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14025v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we discuss the opportunities and challenges of teaching a human-robot interaction course at an undergraduate liberal arts college. We provide a sample syllabus adapted from a previous version of a course.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14025v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason R. Wilson, Emily Jensen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PureConnect: A Localized Social Media System to Increase Awareness and Connectedness in Environmental Justice Communities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14038</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14038v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Frequent disruptions like highway constructions are common now-a-days, often impacting environmental justice communities (communities with low socio-economic status with disproportionately high and adverse human health and environmental effects) that live nearby. Based on our interactions via focus groups with the members of four environmental justice communities impacted by a major highway construction, a common concern is a sense of uncertainty about project activities and loss of social connectedness, leading to increased stress, depression, anxiety and diminished well-being. This paper addresses this concern by developing a localized social media system called PureConnect with a goal to raise the level of awareness about the project and increase social connectedness among the community members. PureConnect has been designed using active engagement with four environmental justice communities affected by a major highway construction. It has been deployed in the real world among the members of the four environmental justice communities, and a detailed analysis of the data collected from this deployment as well as surveys show that PureConnect is potentially useful in improving community members' well-being and the members appreciate the functionalities it provides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14038v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omar Hammad, Md Rezwanur Rahman, Gopala Krishna Vasanth Kanugo, Nicholas Clements, Shelly Miller, Shivakant Mishra, Esther Sullivan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Roadmap Towards Automated and Regulated Robotic Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14049v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rapid development of generative technology opens up possibility for higher level of automation, and artificial intelligence (AI) embodiment in robotic systems is imminent. However, due to the blackbox nature of the generative technology, the generation of the knowledge and workflow scheme is uncontrolled, especially in a dynamic environment and a complex scene. This poses challenges to regulations in safety-demanding applications such as medical scenes. We argue that the unregulated generative processes from AI is fitted for low level end tasks, but intervention in the form of manual or automated regulation should happen post-workflow-generation and pre-robotic-execution. To address this, we propose a roadmap that can lead to fully automated and regulated robotic systems. In this paradigm, the high level policies are generated as structured graph data, enabling regulatory oversight and reusability, while the code base for lower level tasks is generated by generative models. Our approach aims the transitioning from expert knowledge to regulated action, akin to the iterative processes of study, practice, scrutiny, and execution in human tasks. We identify the generative and deterministic processes in a design cycle, where generative processes serve as a text-based world simulator and the deterministic processes generate the executable system. We propose State Machine Seralization Language (SMSL) to be the conversion point between text simulator and executable workflow control. From there, we analyze the modules involved based on the current literature, and discuss human in the loop. As a roadmap, this work identifies the current possible implementation and future work. This work does not provide an implemented system but envisions to inspire the researchers working on the direction in the roadmap. We implement the SMSL and D-SFO paradigm that serve as the starting point of the roadmap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14049v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yihao Liu, Mehran Armand</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Perils to Possibilities: Understanding how Human (and AI) Biases affect Online Fora</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14298v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Social media platforms are online fora where users engage in discussions, share content, and build connections. This review explores the dynamics of social interactions, user-generated contents, and biases within the context of social media analysis (analyzing works that use the tools offered by complex network analysis and natural language processing) through the lens of three key points of view: online debates, online support, and human-AI interactions. On the one hand, we delineate the phenomenon of online debates, where polarization, misinformation, and echo chamber formation often proliferate, driven by algorithmic biases and extreme mechanisms of homophily. On the other hand, we explore the emergence of online support groups through users' self-disclosure and social support mechanisms. Online debates and support mechanisms present a duality of both perils and possibilities within social media; perils of segregated communities and polarized debates, and possibilities of empathy narratives and self-help groups. This dichotomy also extends to a third perspective: users' reliance on AI-generated content, such as the ones produced by Large Language Models, which can manifest both human biases hidden in training sets and non-human biases that emerge from their artificial neural architectures. Analyzing interdisciplinary approaches, we aim to deepen the understanding of the complex interplay between social interactions, user-generated content, and biases within the realm of social media ecosystems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14298v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Virginia Morini, Valentina Pansanella, Katherine Abramski, Erica Cau, Andrea Failla, Salvatore Citraro, Giulio Rossetti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tell Me What You Want (What You Really, Really Want): Addressing the Expectation Gap for Goal Conveyance from Humans to Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14344</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14344v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Conveying human goals to autonomous systems (AS) occurs both when the system is being designed and when it is being operated. The design-step conveyance is typically mediated by robotics and AI engineers, who must appropriately capture end-user requirements and concepts of operations, while the operation-step conveyance is mediated by the design, interfaces, and behavior of the AI. However, communication can be difficult during both these periods because of mismatches in the expectations and expertise of the end-user and the roboticist, necessitating more design cycles to resolve. We examine some of the barriers in communicating system design requirements, and develop an augmentation for applied cognitive task analysis (ACTA) methods, that we call robot task analysis (RTA), pertaining specifically to the development of autonomous systems. Further, we introduce a top-down view of an underexplored area of friction between requirements communication -- implied human expectations -- utilizing a collection of work primarily from experimental psychology and social sciences. We show how such expectations can be used in conjunction with task-specific expectations and the system design process for AS to improve design team communication, alleviate barriers to user rejection, and reduce the number of design cycles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14344v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Leahy, Ho Chit Siu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detoxifying Large Language Models via Knowledge Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14472v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates using knowledge editing techniques to detoxify Large Language Models (LLMs). We construct a benchmark, SafeEdit, which covers nine unsafe categories with various powerful attack prompts and equips comprehensive metrics for systematic evaluation. We conduct experiments to compare knowledge editing approaches with previous baselines, indicating that knowledge editing has the potential to efficiently detoxify LLMs with limited impact on general performance. Then, we propose a simple yet effective baseline, dubbed Detoxifying with Intraoperative Neural Monitoring (DINM), to diminish the toxicity of LLMs within a few tuning steps via only one instance. We further provide an in-depth analysis of the internal mechanism for various detoxify approaches, demonstrating that previous methods like SFT and DPO may merely suppress the activations of toxic parameters, while DINM mitigates the toxicity of the toxic parameters to a certain extent, making permanent adjustments. We hope that these insights could shed light on future work of developing detoxifying approaches and the underlying knowledge mechanisms of LLMs. Code and benchmark are available at https://github.com/zjunlp/EasyEdit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14472v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengru Wang, Ningyu Zhang, Ziwen Xu, Zekun Xi, Shumin Deng, Yunzhi Yao, Qishen Zhang, Linyi Yang, Jindong Wang, Huajun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Era of Semantic Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14562v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent work demonstrated great promise in the idea of orchestrating collaborations between LLMs, human input, and various tools to address the inherent limitations of LLMs. We propose a novel perspective called semantic decoding, which frames these collaborative processes as optimization procedures in semantic space. Specifically, we conceptualize LLMs as semantic processors that manipulate meaningful pieces of information that we call semantic tokens (known thoughts). LLMs are among a large pool of other semantic processors, including humans and tools, such as search engines or code executors. Collectively, semantic processors engage in dynamic exchanges of semantic tokens to progressively construct high-utility outputs. We refer to these orchestrated interactions among semantic processors, optimizing and searching in semantic space, as semantic decoding algorithms. This concept draws a direct parallel to the well-studied problem of syntactic decoding, which involves crafting algorithms to best exploit auto-regressive language models for extracting high-utility sequences of syntactic tokens. By focusing on the semantic level and disregarding syntactic details, we gain a fresh perspective on the engineering of AI systems, enabling us to imagine systems with much greater complexity and capabilities. In this position paper, we formalize the transition from syntactic to semantic tokens as well as the analogy between syntactic and semantic decoding. Subsequently, we explore the possibilities of optimizing within the space of semantic tokens via semantic decoding algorithms. We conclude with a list of research opportunities and questions arising from this fresh perspective. The semantic decoding perspective offers a powerful abstraction for search and optimization directly in the space of meaningful concepts, with semantic tokens as the fundamental units of a new type of computation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14562v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxime Peyrard, Martin Josifoski, Robert West</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Envisioning the Next-Generation AI Coding Assistants: Insights &amp; Proposals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14592v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As a research-product hybrid group in AI for Software Engineering (AI4SE), we present four key takeaways from our experience developing in-IDE AI coding assistants. AI coding assistants should set clear expectations for usage, integrate with advanced IDE capabilities and existing extensions, use extendable backend designs, and collect app data responsibly for downstream analyses. We propose open questions and challenges that academia and industry should address to realize the vision of next-generation AI coding assistants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14592v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khanh Nghiem, Anh Minh Nguyen, Nghi D. Q. Bui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended Reality for Enhanced Human-Robot Collaboration: a Human-in-the-Loop Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14597</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14597v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rise of automation has provided an opportunity to achieve higher efficiency in manufacturing processes, yet it often compromises the flexibility required to promptly respond to evolving market needs and meet the demand for customization. Human-robot collaboration attempts to tackle these challenges by combining the strength and precision of machines with human ingenuity and perceptual understanding. In this paper, we conceptualize and propose an implementation framework for an autonomous, machine learning-based manipulator that incorporates human-in-the-loop principles and leverages Extended Reality (XR) to facilitate intuitive communication and programming between humans and robots. Furthermore, the conceptual framework foresees human involvement directly in the robot learning process, resulting in higher adaptability and task generalization. The paper highlights key technologies enabling the proposed framework, emphasizing the importance of developing the digital ecosystem as a whole. Additionally, we review the existent implementation approaches of XR in human-robot collaboration, showcasing diverse perspectives and methodologies. The challenges and future outlooks are discussed, delving into the major obstacles and potential research avenues of XR for more natural human-robot interaction and integration in the industrial landscape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14597v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yehor Karpichev, Todd Charter, Homayoun Najjaran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Empathy-Based Sandbox Approach to Bridge the Privacy Gap among Attitudes, Goals, Knowledge, and Behaviors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.14510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.14510v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Managing privacy to reach privacy goals is challenging, as evidenced by the privacy attitude-behavior gap. Mitigating this discrepancy requires solutions that account for both system opaqueness and users' hesitations in testing different privacy settings due to fears of unintended data exposure. We introduce an empathy-based approach that allows users to experience how privacy attributes may alter system outcomes in a risk-free sandbox environment from the perspective of artificially generated personas. To generate realistic personas, we introduce a novel pipeline that augments the outputs of large language models (e.g., GPT-4) using few-shot learning, contextualization, and chain of thoughts. Our empirical studies demonstrated the adequate quality of generated personas and highlighted the changes in privacy-related applications (e.g., online advertising) caused by different personas. Furthermore, users demonstrated cognitive and emotional empathy towards the personas when interacting with our sandbox. We offered design implications for downstream applications in improving user privacy literacy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.14510v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3613904.3642363</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Chaoran Chen, Weijun Li, Wenxin Song, Yanfang Ye, Yaxing Yao, Toby Jia-jun Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Designing Digital Voting Systems for Citizens: Achieving Fairness and Legitimacy in Participatory Budgeting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.03501v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Participatory Budgeting (PB) has evolved into a key democratic instrument for resource allocation in cities. Enabled by digital platforms, cities now have the opportunity to let citizens directly propose and vote on urban projects, using different voting input and aggregation rules. However, the choices cities make in terms of the rules of their PB have often not been informed by academic studies on voter behaviour and preferences. Therefore, this work presents the results of behavioural experiments where participants were asked to vote in a fictional PB setting. We identified approaches to designing PB voting that minimise cognitive load and enhance the perceived fairness and legitimacy of the digital process from the citizens' perspective. In our study, participants preferred voting input formats that are more expressive (like rankings and distributing points) over simpler formats (like approval voting). Participants also indicated a desire for the budget to be fairly distributed across city districts and project categories. Participants found the Method of Equal Shares voting rule to be fairer than the conventional Greedy voting rule. These findings offer actionable insights for digital governance, contributing to the development of fairer and more transparent digital systems and collective decision-making processes for citizens.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.03501v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua C. Yang, Carina I. Hausladen, Dominik Peters, Evangelos Pournaras, Regula H\"anggli Fricker, Dirk Helbing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoQuest: Exploring Research Question Co-Creation with an LLM-based Agent</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.06155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.06155v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Developing novel research questions (RQs) often requires extensive literature reviews, especially in interdisciplinary fields. To support RQ development through human-AI co-creation, we leveraged Large Language Models (LLMs) to build an LLM-based agent system named CoQuest. We conducted an experiment with 20 HCI researchers to examine the impact of two interaction designs: breadth-first and depth-first RQ generation. The findings revealed that participants perceived the breadth-first approach as more creative and trustworthy upon task completion. Conversely, during the task, participants considered the depth-first generated RQs as more creative. Additionally, we discovered that AI processing delays allowed users to reflect on multiple RQs simultaneously, leading to a higher quantity of generated RQs and an enhanced sense of control. Our work makes both theoretical and practical contributions by proposing and evaluating a mental model for human-AI co-creation of RQs. We also address potential ethical issues, such as biases and over-reliance on AI, advocating for using the system to improve human research creativity rather than automating scientific inquiry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.06155v3</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiren Liu, Si Chen, Haocong Cheng, Mengxia Yu, Xiao Ran, Andrew Mo, Yiliu Tang, Yun Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Large Language Models to Facilitate Variable Autonomy for Human-Robot Teaming</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.07214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.07214v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In a rapidly evolving digital landscape autonomous tools and robots are becoming commonplace. Recognizing the significance of this development, this paper explores the integration of Large Language Models (LLMs) like Generative pre-trained transformer (GPT) into human-robot teaming environments to facilitate variable autonomy through the means of verbal human-robot communication. In this paper, we introduce a novel framework for such a GPT-powered multi-robot testbed environment, based on a Unity Virtual Reality (VR) setting. This system allows users to interact with robot agents through natural language, each powered by individual GPT cores. By means of OpenAI's function calling, we bridge the gap between unstructured natural language input and structure robot actions. A user study with 12 participants explores the effectiveness of GPT-4 and, more importantly, user strategies when being given the opportunity to converse in natural language within a multi-robot environment. Our findings suggest that users may have preconceived expectations on how to converse with robots and seldom try to explore the actual language and cognitive capabilities of their robot collaborators. Still, those users who did explore where able to benefit from a much more natural flow of communication and human-like back-and-forth. We provide a set of lessons learned for future research and technical implementations of similar systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.07214v3</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3389/frobt.2024.1347538</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Front. Robot. AI 11:1347538 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Younes Lakhnati, Max Pascher, Jens Gerken</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intelligent Canvas: Enabling Design-Like Exploratory Visual Data Analysis with Generative AI through Rapid Prototyping, Iteration and Curation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.08812v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Complex data analysis inherently seeks unexpected insights through exploratory visual analysis methods, transcending logical, step-by-step processing. However, existing interfaces such as notebooks and dashboards have limitations in exploration and comparison for visual data analysis. Addressing these limitations, we introduce a "design-like" intelligent canvas environment integrating generative AI into data analysis, offering rapid prototyping, iteration, and comparative visualization management. Our dual contributions include the integration of generative AI components into a canvas interface, and empirical findings from a user study (N=10) evaluating the effectiveness of the canvas interface.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.08812v3</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zijian Ding, Joel Chan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Image-based Typology for Visualization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05594v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present and discuss the results of a qualitative analysis of visual representations from images. We labeled each image's essential stimuli, the removal of which would render a visualization uninterpretable. As a result, we derive a typology of 10 visualization types of defined groups. We describe the typology derivation process in which we engaged. The resulting typology and image analysis can serve a number of purposes: enabling researchers to study the evolution of the community and its research output over time, facilitating the categorization of visualization images for the purpose of research and teaching, allowing researchers and practitioners to identify visual design styles to further align the quantification of any visual information processor, be that a person or an algorithm observer, and it facilitates a discussion of standardization in visualization. In addition to the visualization typology from images, we provide a dataset of 6,833 tagged images and an online tool that can be used to explore and analyze the large set of labeled images. The tool and data set enable scholars to closely examine the diverse visual designs used and how they are published and communicated in our community. A pre-registration, a free copy of this paper, and all supplemental materials are available via osf.io/dxjwt.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05594v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Chen, Petra Isenberg, Robert S. Laramee, Tobias Isenberg, Michael Sedlmair, Torsten Moeller, Rui Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding the Factors Influencing Self-Managed Enterprises of Crowdworkers: A Comprehensive Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12769</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12769v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the shift in crowdsourcing towards self-managed enterprises of crowdworkers (SMECs), diverging from traditional platform-controlled models. It reviews the literature to understand the foundational aspects of this shift, focusing on identifying key factors that may explain the rise of SMECs, particularly concerning power dynamics and tensions between Online Labor Platforms (OLPs) and crowdworkers. The study aims to guide future research and inform policy and platform development, emphasizing the importance of fair labor practices in this evolving landscape.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12769v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Prestes Uchoa, Daniel Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Human's Gender Perception and Bias toward Non-Humanoid Robots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.12001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.12001v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As non-humanoid robots increasingly permeate various sectors, understanding their design implications for human acceptance becomes paramount. Despite their ubiquity, studies on how to improve human interaction are sparse. Our investigation, conducted through two surveys, addresses this gap. The first survey emphasizes non-humanoid robots and human perceptions about gender attributions, suggesting that both design and perceived gender influence acceptance. Survey 2 investigates the effects of varying gender cues on robot designs and their consequent impacts on human-robot interactions. Our findings highlighted that distinct gender cues can bolster or impede interaction comfort.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.12001v3</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahya Ramezani, Jose Luis Sanchez-Lopez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Language Models for Multi-Modal Human-Robot Interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15174</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15174v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper presents an innovative large language model (LLM)-based robotic system for enhancing multi-modal human-robot interaction (HRI). Traditional HRI systems relied on complex designs for intent estimation, reasoning, and behavior generation, which were resource-intensive. In contrast, our system empowers researchers and practitioners to regulate robot behavior through three key aspects: providing high-level linguistic guidance, creating "atomics" for actions and expressions the robot can use, and offering a set of examples. Implemented on a physical robot, it demonstrates proficiency in adapting to multi-modal inputs and determining the appropriate manner of action to assist humans with its arms, following researchers' defined guidelines. Simultaneously, it coordinates the robot's lid, neck, and ear movements with speech output to produce dynamic, multi-modal expressions. This showcases the system's potential to revolutionize HRI by shifting from conventional, manual state-and-flow design methods to an intuitive, guidance-based, and example-driven approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15174v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3613905.3651029</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Chao Wang, Stephan Hasler, Daniel Tanneberg, Felix Ocker, Frank Joublin, Antonello Ceravola, Joerg Deigmoeller, Michael Gienger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EasyInstruct: An Easy-to-use Instruction Processing Framework for Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.03049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.03049v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In recent years, instruction tuning has gained increasing attention and emerged as a crucial technique to enhance the capabilities of Large Language Models (LLMs). To construct high-quality instruction datasets, many instruction processing approaches have been proposed, aiming to achieve a delicate balance between data quantity and data quality. Nevertheless, due to inconsistencies that persist among various instruction processing methods, there is no standard open-source instruction processing implementation framework available for the community, which hinders practitioners from further developing and advancing. To facilitate instruction processing research and development, we present EasyInstruct, an easy-to-use instruction processing framework for LLMs, which modularizes instruction generation, selection, and prompting, while also considering their combination and interaction. EasyInstruct is publicly released and actively maintained at https://github.com/zjunlp/EasyInstruct, along with an online demo app and a demo video for quick-start, calling for broader research centered on instruction data and synthetic data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.03049v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yixin Ou, Ningyu Zhang, Honghao Gui, Ziwen Xu, Shuofei Qiao, Yida Xue, Runnan Fang, Kangwei Liu, Lei Li, Zhen Bi, Guozhou Zheng, Huajun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Social Robots for Sleep Health: A Scoping Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.04169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.04169v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Poor sleep health is an increasingly concerning public healthcare crisis, especially when coupled with a dwindling number of health professionals qualified to combat it. However, there is a growing body of scientific literature on the use of digital technologies in supporting and sustaining individuals' healthy sleep habits. Social robots are a relatively recent technology that has been used to facilitate health care interventions and may have potential in improving sleep health outcomes, as well. Social robots' unique characteristics -- such as anthropomorphic physical embodiment or effective communication methods -- help to engage users and motivate them to comply with specific interventions, thus improving the interventions' outcomes. This scoping review aims to evaluate current scientific evidence for employing social robots in sleep health interventions, identify critical research gaps, and suggest future directions for developing and using social robots to improve people's sleep health. Our analysis of the reviewed studies found them limited due to a singular focus on the older adult population, use of small sample sizes, limited intervention durations, and other compounding factors. Nevertheless, the reviewed studies reported several positive outcomes, highlighting the potential social robots hold in this field. Although our review found limited clinical evidence for the efficacy of social robots as purveyors of sleep health interventions, it did elucidate the potential for a successful future in this domain if current limitations are addressed and more research is conducted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.04169v2</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Nikhil Antony, Mengchi Li, Shu-Han Lin, Junxin Li, Chien-Ming Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
