<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.HC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.HC</link>
    <description>cs.HC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.HC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 02:32:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Can ChatGPT assist visually impaired people with micro-navigation?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08321</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08321v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Objective: Micro-navigation poses challenges for blind and visually impaired individuals. They often need to ask for sighted assistance. We explored the feasibility of utilizing ChatGPT as a virtual assistant to provide navigation directions. Methods: We created a test set of outdoor and indoor micro-navigation scenarios consisting of 113 scene images and their human-generated text descriptions. A total of 412 way-finding queries and their expected responses were compiled based on the scenarios. Not all queries are answerable based on the information available in the scene image. "I do not know"response was expected for unanswerable queries, which served as negative cases. High level orientation responses were expected, and step-by-step guidance was not required. ChatGPT 4o was evaluated based on sensitivity (SEN) and specificity (SPE) under different conditions. Results: The default ChatGPT 4o, with scene images as inputs, resulted in SEN and SPE values of 64.8% and 75.9%, respectively. Instruction on how to respond to unanswerable questions did not improve SEN substantially but SPE increased by around 14 percentage points. SEN and SPE both improved substantially, by about 17 and 16 percentage points on average respectively, when human written descriptions of the scenes were provided as input instead of images. Providing further prompt instructions to the assistants when the input was text description did not substantially change the SEN and SPE values. Conclusion: Current native ChatGPT 4o is still unable to provide correct micro-navigation guidance in some cases, probably because its scene understanding is not optimized for navigation purposes. If multi-modal chatbots could interpret scenes with a level of clarity comparable to humans, and also guided by appropriate prompts, they may have the potential to provide assistance to visually impaired for micro-navigation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08321v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junxian He, Shrinivas Pundlik, Gang Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Urban Comfort through Novel Wearables and Environmental Surveys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08323</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08323v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study presents a comprehensive dataset capturing indoor environmental parameters, physiological responses, and subjective perceptions across three global cities. Utilizing wearable sensors, including smart eyeglasses, and a modified Cozie app, environmental and physiological data were collected, along with pre-screening, onboarding, and recurring surveys. Peripheral cues facilitated participant engagement with micro-EMA surveys, minimizing disruption over a 5-day collection period. The dataset offers insights into urban comfort dynamics, highlighting the interplay between environmental conditions, physiological responses, and subjective perceptions. Researchers can utilize this dataset to deepen their understanding of indoor environmental quality and inform the design of healthier built environments. Access to this dataset can advance indoor environmental research and contribute to the creation of more comfortable and sustainable indoor spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08323v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Chwalek, Sailin Zhong, Nathan Perry, Tianqi Liu, Clayton Miller, Hamed Seiied Alavi, Denis Lalanne, Joseph A. Paradiso</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Help-Seeking Behavior of Students Using LLMs vs. Web Search for Writing SQL Queries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08401v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Growth in the use of large language models (LLMs) in programming education is altering how students write SQL queries. Traditionally, students relied heavily on web search for coding assistance, but this has shifted with the adoption of LLMs like ChatGPT. However, the comparative process and outcomes of using web search versus LLMs for coding help remain underexplored. To address this, we conducted a randomized interview study in a database classroom to compare web search and LLMs, including a publicly available LLM (ChatGPT) and an instructor-tuned LLM, for writing SQL queries. Our findings indicate that using an instructor-tuned LLM required significantly more interactions than both ChatGPT and web search, but resulted in a similar number of edits to the final SQL query. No significant differences were found in the quality of the final SQL queries between conditions, although the LLM conditions directionally showed higher query quality. Furthermore, students using instructor-tuned LLM reported a lower mental demand. These results have implications for learning and productivity in programming education.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08401v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harsh Kumar, Mohi Reza, Jeb Mitchell, Ilya Musabirov, Lisa Zhang, Michael Liut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Voicing Uncertainty: How Speech, Text, and Visualizations Influence Decisions with Data Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08438v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding and communicating data uncertainty is crucial for informed decision-making across various domains, including finance, healthcare, and public policy. This study investigates the impact of gender and acoustic variables on decision-making, confidence, and trust through a crowdsourced experiment. We compared visualization-only representations of uncertainty to text-forward and speech-forward bimodal representations, including multiple synthetic voices across gender. Speech-forward representations led to an increase in risky decisions, and text-forward representations led to lower confidence. Contrary to prior work, speech-forward forecasts did not receive higher ratings of trust. Higher normalized pitch led to a slight increase in decision confidence, but other voice characteristics had minimal impact on decisions and trust. An exploratory analysis of accented speech showed consistent results with the main experiment and additionally indicated lower trust ratings for information presented in Indian and Kenyan accents. The results underscore the importance of considering acoustic and contextual factors in presentation of data uncertainty.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08438v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chase Stokes, Chelsea Sanker, Bridget Cogley, Vidya Setlur</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Transparency Paradox? Investigating the Impact of Explanation Specificity and Autonomous Vehicle Perceptual Inaccuracies on Passengers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08785v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transparency in automated systems could be afforded through the provision of intelligible explanations. While transparency is desirable, might it lead to catastrophic outcomes (such as anxiety), that could outweigh its benefits? It's quite unclear how the specificity of explanations (level of transparency) influences recipients, especially in autonomous driving (AD). In this work, we examined the effects of transparency mediated through varying levels of explanation specificity in AD. We first extended a data-driven explainer model by adding a rule-based option for explanation generation in AD, and then conducted a within-subject lab study with 39 participants in an immersive driving simulator to study the effect of the resulting explanations. Specifically, our investigation focused on: (1) how different types of explanations (specific vs. abstract) affect passengers' perceived safety, anxiety, and willingness to take control of the vehicle when the vehicle perception system makes erroneous predictions; and (2) the relationship between passengers' behavioural cues and their feelings during the autonomous drives. Our findings showed that passengers felt safer with specific explanations when the vehicle's perception system had minimal errors, while abstract explanations that hid perception errors led to lower feelings of safety. Anxiety levels increased when specific explanations revealed perception system errors (high transparency). We found no significant link between passengers' visual patterns and their anxiety levels. Our study suggests that passengers prefer clear and specific explanations (high transparency) when they originate from autonomous vehicles (AVs) with optimal perceptual accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08785v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Omeiza, Raunak Bhattacharyya, Marina Jirotka, Nick Hawes, Lars Kunze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CPS-TaskForge: Generating Collaborative Problem Solving Environments for Diverse Communication Tasks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08853v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Teams can outperform individuals; could adding AI teammates further bolster performance of teams solving problems collaboratively? Collaborative problem solving (CPS) research commonly studies teams with two agents (human-human or human-AI), but team research literature finds that, for complex tasks, larger teams are more effective. Progress in studying collaboration with more than two agents, through textual records of team interactions, is hindered by a major data challenge: available CPS corpora are predominantly dyadic, and adapting pre-existing CPS tasks to more agents is non-trivial. We address this data challenge by developing a CPS task generator, CPS-TaskForge, that can produce environments for studying CPS under a wide array of conditions, and releasing a CPS task design checklist grounded in the theoretical PISA 2015 CPS framework to help facilitate the development of CPS corpora with more agents. CPS-TaskForge takes the form of a resource management (tower defense) game, and different CPS tasks can be studied by manipulating game design parameters. We conduct a case study with groups of 3-4 humans to validate production of diverse natural language CPS communication in a game instance produced by CPS-TaskForge. We discuss opportunities for advancing research in CPS (both with human-only and human-AI teams) using different task configurations. We will release data and code.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08853v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikita Haduong (Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science &amp; Engineering, University of Washington), Irene Wang (Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science &amp; Engineering, University of Washington), Bo-Ru Lu (Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science &amp; Engineering, University of Washington), Prithviraj Ammanabrolu (University of California, San Diego), Noah A. Smith (Paul G. Allen School of Computer Science &amp; Engineering, University of Washington, Allen Institute for AI)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Models Matter: Setting Accurate Privacy Expectations for Local and Central Differential Privacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08475</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08475v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Differential privacy is a popular privacy-enhancing technology that has been deployed both in industry and government agencies. Unfortunately, existing explanations of differential privacy fail to set accurate privacy expectations for data subjects, which depend on the choice of deployment model. We design and evaluate new explanations of differential privacy for the local and central models, drawing inspiration from prior work explaining other privacy-enhancing technologies. We find that consequences-focused explanations in the style of privacy nutrition labels that lay out the implications of differential privacy are a promising approach for setting accurate privacy expectations. Further, we find that while process-focused explanations are not enough to set accurate privacy expectations, combining consequences-focused explanations with a brief description of how differential privacy works leads to greater trust.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08475v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mary Anne Smart, Priyanka Nanayakkara, Rachel Cummings, Gabriel Kaptchuk, Elissa Redmiles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TextCAVs: Debugging vision models using text</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08652</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08652v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Concept-based interpretability methods are a popular form of explanation for deep learning models which provide explanations in the form of high-level human interpretable concepts. These methods typically find concept activation vectors (CAVs) using a probe dataset of concept examples. This requires labelled data for these concepts -- an expensive task in the medical domain. We introduce TextCAVs: a novel method which creates CAVs using vision-language models such as CLIP, allowing for explanations to be created solely using text descriptions of the concept, as opposed to image exemplars. This reduced cost in testing concepts allows for many concepts to be tested and for users to interact with the model, testing new ideas as they are thought of, rather than a delay caused by image collection and annotation. In early experimental results, we demonstrate that TextCAVs produces reasonable explanations for a chest x-ray dataset (MIMIC-CXR) and natural images (ImageNet), and that these explanations can be used to debug deep learning-based models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08652v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angus Nicolson, Yarin Gal, J. Alison Noble</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>As Generative Models Improve, People Adapt Their Prompts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14333v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In an online experiment with N = 1893 participants, we collected and analyzed over 18,000 prompts and over 300,000 images to explore how the importance of prompting will change as the capabilities of generative AI models continue to improve. Each participant in our experiment was randomly and blindly assigned to use one of three text-to-image diffusion models: DALL-E 2, its more advanced successor DALL-E 3, or a version of DALL-E 3 with automatic prompt revision. Participants were then asked to write prompts to reproduce a target image as closely as possible in 10 consecutive tries. We find that task performance was higher for participants using DALL-E 3 than for those using DALL-E 2. This performance gap corresponds to a noticeable difference in the similarity of participants' images to their target images, and was caused in equal measure by: (1) the increased technical capabilities of DALL-E 3, and (2) endogenous changes in participants' prompting in response to these increased capabilities. More specifically, despite being blind to the model they were assigned, participants assigned to DALL-E 3 wrote longer prompts that were more semantically similar to each other and contained a greater number of descriptive words. Furthermore, while participants assigned to DALL-E 3 with prompt revision still outperformed those assigned to DALL-E 2, automatic prompt revision reduced the benefits of using DALL-E 3 by 58\%. Taken together, our results suggest that as models continue to progress, people will continue to adapt their prompts to take advantage of new models' capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14333v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eaman Jahani, Benjamin S. Manning, Joe Zhang, Hong-Yi TuYe, Mohammed Alsobay, Christos Nicolaides, Siddharth Suri, David Holtz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brain Tumor Segmentation (BraTS) Challenge 2024: Meningioma Radiotherapy Planning Automated Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18383v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The 2024 Brain Tumor Segmentation Meningioma Radiotherapy (BraTS-MEN-RT) challenge aims to advance automated segmentation algorithms using the largest known multi-institutional dataset of radiotherapy planning brain MRIs with expert-annotated target labels for patients with intact or postoperative meningioma that underwent either conventional external beam radiotherapy or stereotactic radiosurgery. Each case includes a defaced 3D post-contrast T1-weighted radiotherapy planning MRI in its native acquisition space, accompanied by a single-label "target volume" representing the gross tumor volume (GTV) and any at-risk postoperative site. Target volume annotations adhere to established radiotherapy planning protocols, ensuring consistency across cases and institutions. For preoperative meningiomas, the target volume encompasses the entire GTV and associated nodular dural tail, while for postoperative cases, it includes at-risk resection cavity margins as determined by the treating institution. Case annotations were reviewed and approved by expert neuroradiologists and radiation oncologists. Participating teams will develop, containerize, and evaluate automated segmentation models using this comprehensive dataset. Model performance will be assessed using an adapted lesion-wise Dice Similarity Coefficient and the 95% Hausdorff distance. The top-performing teams will be recognized at the Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention Conference in October 2024. BraTS-MEN-RT is expected to significantly advance automated radiotherapy planning by enabling precise tumor segmentation and facilitating tailored treatment, ultimately improving patient outcomes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18383v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominic LaBella, Katherine Schumacher, Michael Mix, Kevin Leu, Shan McBurney-Lin, Pierre Nedelec, Javier Villanueva-Meyer, Jonathan Shapey, Tom Vercauteren, Kazumi Chia, Omar Al-Salihi, Justin Leu, Lia Halasz, Yury Velichko, Chunhao Wang, John Kirkpatrick, Scott Floyd, Zachary J. Reitman, Trey Mullikin, Ulas Bagci, Sean Sachdev, Jona A. Hattangadi-Gluth, Tyler Seibert, Nikdokht Farid, Connor Puett, Matthew W. Pease, Kevin Shiue, Syed Muhammad Anwar, Shahriar Faghani, Muhammad Ammar Haider, Pranav Warman, Jake Albrecht, Andr\'as Jakab, Mana Moassefi, Verena Chung, Alejandro Aristizabal, Alexandros Karargyris, Hasan Kassem, Sarthak Pati, Micah Sheller, Christina Huang, Aaron Coley, Siddharth Ghanta, Alex Schneider, Conrad Sharp, Rachit Saluja, Florian Kofler, Philipp Lohmann, Phillipp Vollmuth, Louis Gagnon, Maruf Adewole, Hongwei Bran Li, Anahita Fathi Kazerooni, Nourel Hoda Tahon, Udunna Anazodo, Ahmed W. Moawad, Bjoern Menze, Marius George Linguraru, Mariam Aboian, Benedikt Wiestler, Ujjwal Baid, Gian-Marco Conte, Andreas M. Rauschecker, Ayman Nada, Aly H. Abayazeed, Raymond Huang, Maria Correia de Verdier, Jeffrey D. Rudie, Spyridon Bakas, Evan Calabrese</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
