<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.HC updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.HC</link>
    <description>cs.HC updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.HC" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 May 2024 04:01:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Data Makes Better Data Scientists</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17690v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: With the goal of identifying common practices in data science projects, this paper proposes a framework for logging and understanding incremental code executions in Jupyter notebooks. This framework aims to allow reasoning about how insights are generated in data science and extract key observations into best data science practices in the wild. In this paper, we show an early prototype of this framework and ran an experiment to log a machine learning project for 25 undergraduate students.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17690v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinjin Zhao, Avidgor Gal, Sanjay Krishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RealityEffects: Augmenting 3D Volumetric Videos with Object-Centric Annotation and Dynamic Visual Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17711</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17711v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces RealityEffects, a desktop authoring interface designed for editing and augmenting 3D volumetric videos with object-centric annotations and visual effects. RealityEffects enhances volumetric capture by introducing a novel method for augmenting captured physical motion with embedded, responsive visual effects, referred to as object-centric augmentation. In RealityEffects, users can interactively attach various visual effects to physical objects within the captured 3D scene, enabling these effects to dynamically move and animate in sync with the corresponding physical motion and body movements. The primary contribution of this paper is the development of a taxonomy for such object-centric augmentations, which includes annotated labels, highlighted objects, ghost effects, and trajectory visualization. This taxonomy is informed by an analysis of 120 edited videos featuring object-centric visual effects. The findings from our user study confirm that our direct manipulation techniques lower the barriers to editing and annotating volumetric captures, thereby enhancing interactive and engaging viewing experiences of 3D volumetric videos.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17711v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3643834.3661631</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jian Liao, Kevin Van, Zhijie Xia, Ryo Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DanceGen: Supporting Choreography Ideation and Prototyping with Generative AI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17827v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Choreography creation requires high proficiency in artistic and technical skills. Choreographers typically go through four stages to create a dance piece: preparation, studio, performance, and reflection. This process is often individualized, complicated, and challenging due to multiple constraints at each stage. To assist choreographers, most prior work has focused on designing digital tools to support the last three stages of the choreography process, with the preparation stage being the least explored. To address this research gap, we introduce an AI-based approach to assist the preparation stage by supporting ideation, creating choreographic prototypes, and documenting creative attempts and outcomes. We address the limitations of existing AI-based motion generation methods for ideation by allowing generated sequences to be edited and modified in an interactive web interface. This capability is motivated by insights from a formative study we conducted with seven choreographers. We evaluated our system's functionality, benefits, and limitations with six expert choreographers. Results highlight the usability of our system, with users reporting increased efficiency, expanded creative possibilities, and an enhanced iterative process. We also identified areas for improvement, such as the relationship between user intent and AI outcome, intuitive and flexible user interaction design, and integration with existing physical choreography prototyping workflows. By reflecting on the evaluation results, we present three insights that aim to inform the development of future AI systems that can empower choreographers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17827v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3643834.3661594</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yimeng Liu, Misha Sra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enabling Generative Design Tools with LLM Agents for Building Novel Devices: A Case Study on Fluidic Computation Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17837</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17837v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the field of Human-Computer Interaction (HCI), the development of interactive devices represents a significant area of focus. The advent of novel hardware and advanced fabrication techniques has underscored the demand for specialized design tools that democratize the prototyping process for such cutting-edge devices. While these tools simplify the process through parametric design and simulation, they typically require a certain learning curve and often fall short in facilitating creative ideation. In this study, we employ fluidic computation interface as a case study to investigate the potential of augmenting design tools of physical devices with Large Language Model (LLM) agents. Enhanced by LLM agents, the Generative Design Tool (GDT) can comprehend the capabilities and limitations of newly developed devices; it can propose varied, insightful, and practical application scenarios, and recommend device designs that are technically and contextually appropriate. Furthermore, it generates the necessary design parameters for the traditional part of the design tool to visualize results and produce support files for fabrication. This paper outlines the GDT's framework, implementation, and performance, while also contemplating its prospects and the obstacles encountered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17837v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiuyu Lu, Jiawei Fang, Zhihao Yao, Yue Yang, Shiqing Lyu, Haipeng Mi, Lining Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ai.llude: Encouraging Rewriting AI-Generated Text to Support Creative Expression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17843v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In each step of the creative writing process, writers must grapple with their creative goals and individual perspectives. This process affects the writer's sense of authenticity and their engagement with the written output. Fluent text generation by AIs risks undermining the reflective loop of rewriting. We hypothesize that deliberately generating imperfect intermediate text can encourage rewriting and prompt higher level decision making. Using logs from 27 writing sessions using a text generation AI, we characterize how writers adapt and rewrite AI suggestions, and show that intermediate suggestions significantly motivate and increase rewriting. We discuss the implications of this finding, and future steps for investigating how to leverage intermediate text in AI writing support tools to support ownership over creative expression.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17843v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3635636.3656187</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>David Zhou, Sarah Sterman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A System for Quantifying Data Science Workflows with Fine-Grained Procedural Logging and a Pilot Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is important for researchers to understand precisely how data scientists turn raw data into insights, including typical programming patterns, workflow, and methodology. This paper contributes a novel system, called DataInquirer, that tracks incremental code executions in Jupyter notebooks (a type of computational notebook). The system allows us to quantitatively measure timing, workflow, and operation frequency in data science tasks without resorting to human annotation or interview. In a series of pilot studies, we collect 97 traces, logging data scientist activities across four studies. While this paper presents a general system and data analysis approach, we focus on a foundational sub-question in our pilot studies: How consistent are different data scientists in analyzing the same data? We taxonomize variation between data scientists on the same dataset according to three categories: semantic, syntactic, and methodological. Our results suggest that there are statistically significant differences in the conclusions reached by different data scientists on the same task and present quantitative evidence for this phenomenon. Furthermore, our results suggest that AI-powered code tools subtly influence these results, allowing student participants to generate workflows that more resemble expert data practitioners.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17845v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinjin Zhao, Avidgor Gal, Sanjay Krishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative AI Enhances Team Performance and Reduces Need for Traditional Teams</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advancements in generative artificial intelligence (AI) have transformed collaborative work processes, yet the impact on team performance remains underexplored. Here we examine the role of generative AI in enhancing or replacing traditional team dynamics using a randomized controlled experiment with 435 participants across 122 teams. We show that teams augmented with generative AI significantly outperformed those relying solely on human collaboration across various performance measures. Interestingly, teams with multiple AIs did not exhibit further gains, indicating diminishing returns with increased AI integration. Our analysis suggests that centralized AI usage by a few team members is more effective than distributed engagement. Additionally, individual-AI pairs matched the performance of conventional teams, suggesting a reduced need for traditional team structures in some contexts. However, despite this capability, individual-AI pairs still fell short of the performance levels achieved by AI-assisted teams. These findings underscore that while generative AI can replace some traditional team functions, more comprehensively integrating AI within team structures provides superior benefits, enhancing overall effectiveness beyond individual efforts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17924v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ning Li, Huaikang Zhou, Kris Mikel-Hong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Manipulating Drivers' Mental Workload: Neuroergonomic Evaluation of the Speed Regulation N-Back Task Using NASA-TLX and Auditory P3a</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18099v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Manipulating MW in driving simulator studies without the need to introduce a non-driving-related task remains challenging. This study aims to empirically evaluate the modified speed regulation n-back task, a tool to manipulate drivers' MW. Our experiment involved 23 participants who experienced a 0-back and 2-back driving condition, with task-irrelevant novel environmental sounds used to elicit P3a event-related potentials. Results indicate that the 2-back condition was perceived as more demanding, evidenced by higher NASA-TLX scores (overall score, mental and temporal demand, effort, frustration). The mean P3a amplitude was diminished during the 2-back condition compared to the 0-back condition, suggesting that drivers experienced higher MW and had fewer resources available to process the novel environmental sounds. This study provides empirical evidence indicating that the speed regulation n-back task could be a valid, effective, and reproducible method to manipulate MW in driving research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18099v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3581961.3609887</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>AutomotiveUI '23 Adjunct: Adjunct Proceedings of the 15th International Conference on Automotive User Interfaces and Interactive Vehicular Applications, September 2023, 145-149</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nikol Figalov\'a, J\"urgen Pichen, Vanchha Chandrayan, Olga Pollatos, Lewis Chuang, Martin Baumann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fatigue and mental underload further pronounced in L3 conditionally automated driving: Results from an EEG experiment on a test track</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18114v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Drivers' role changes with increasing automation from the primary driver to a system supervisor. This study investigates how supervising an SAE L2 and L3 automated vehicle (AV) affects drivers' mental workload and sleepiness compared to manual driving. Using an AV prototype on a test track, the oscillatory brain activity of 23 adult participants was recorded during L2, L3, and manual driving. Results showed decreased mental workload and increased sleepiness in L3 drives compared to L2 and manual drives, indicated by self-report scales and changes in the frontal alpha and theta power spectral density. These findings suggest that fatigue and mental underload are significant issues in L3 driving and should be considered when designing future AV interfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18114v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3581754.3584133</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Companion Proceedings of the 28th International Conference on Intelligent User Interfaces, March 2023</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nikol Figalov\'a, Hans Joachim Bieg, Michael Schulz, J\"urgen Pichen, Martin Baumann, Lewis Chuang, Olga Pollatos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The CoExplorer Technology Probe: A Generative AI-Powered Adaptive Interface to Support Intentionality in Planning and Running Video Meetings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18239v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Effective meetings are effortful, but traditional videoconferencing systems offer little support for reducing this effort across the meeting lifecycle. Generative AI (GenAI) has the potential to radically redefine meetings by augmenting intentional meeting behaviors. CoExplorer, our novel adaptive meeting prototype, preemptively generates likely phases that meetings would undergo, tools that allow capturing attendees' thoughts before the meeting, and for each phase, window layouts, and appropriate applications and files. Using CoExplorer as a technology probe in a guided walkthrough, we studied its potential in a sample of participants from a global technology company. Our findings suggest that GenAI has the potential to help meetings stay on track and reduce workload, although concerns were raised about users' agency, trust, and possible disruption to traditional meeting norms. We discuss these concerns and their design implications for the development of GenAI meeting technology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18239v1</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gun Woo (Warren),  Park, Payod Panda, Lev Tankelevitch, Sean Rintel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Human-AI Complementarity with Predictions Sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17544</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17544v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Decision support systems based on prediction sets have proven to be effective at helping human experts solve classification tasks. Rather than providing single-label predictions, these systems provide sets of label predictions constructed using conformal prediction, namely prediction sets, and ask human experts to predict label values from these sets. In this paper, we first show that the prediction sets constructed using conformal prediction are, in general, suboptimal in terms of average accuracy. Then, we show that the problem of finding the optimal prediction sets under which the human experts achieve the highest average accuracy is NP-hard. More strongly, unless P = NP, we show that the problem is hard to approximate to any factor less than the size of the label set. However, we introduce a simple and efficient greedy algorithm that, for a large class of expert models and non-conformity scores, is guaranteed to find prediction sets that provably offer equal or greater performance than those constructed using conformal prediction. Further, using a simulation study with both synthetic and real expert predictions, we demonstrate that, in practice, our greedy algorithm finds near-optimal prediction sets offering greater performance than conformal prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17544v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni De Toni, Nastaran Okati, Suhas Thejaswi, Eleni Straitouri, Manuel Gomez-Rodriguez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Facilitating Holistic Evaluations with LLMs: Insights from Scenario-Based Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17728v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Workshop courses designed to foster creativity are gaining popularity. However, achieving a holistic evaluation that accommodates diverse perspectives is challenging, even for experienced faculty teams. Adequate discussion is essential to integrate varied assessments, but faculty often lack the time for such deliberations. Deriving an average score without discussion undermines the purpose of a holistic evaluation. This paper explores the use of a Large Language Model (LLM) as a facilitator to integrate diverse faculty assessments. Scenario-based experiments were conducted to determine if the LLM could synthesize diverse evaluations and explain the underlying theories to faculty. The results were noteworthy, showing that the LLM effectively facilitated faculty discussions. Additionally, the LLM demonstrated the capability to generalize and create evaluation criteria from a single scenario based on its learned domain knowledge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17728v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Toru Ishida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Widening Gap: The Benefits and Harms of Generative AI for Novice Programmers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17739v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Novice programmers often struggle through programming problem solving due to a lack of metacognitive awareness and strategies. Previous research has shown that novices can encounter multiple metacognitive difficulties while programming. Novices are typically unaware of how these difficulties are hindering their progress. Meanwhile, many novices are now programming with generative AI (GenAI), which can provide complete solutions to most introductory programming problems, code suggestions, hints for next steps when stuck, and explain cryptic error messages. Its impact on novice metacognition has only started to be explored. Here we replicate a previous study that examined novice programming problem solving behavior and extend it by incorporating GenAI tools. Through 21 lab sessions consisting of participant observation, interview, and eye tracking, we explore how novices are coding with GenAI tools. Although 20 of 21 students completed the assigned programming problem, our findings show an unfortunate divide in the use of GenAI tools between students who accelerated and students who struggled. Students who accelerated were able to use GenAI to create code they already intended to make and were able to ignore unhelpful or incorrect inline code suggestions. But for students who struggled, our findings indicate that previously known metacognitive difficulties persist, and that GenAI unfortunately can compound them and even introduce new metacognitive difficulties. Furthermore, struggling students often expressed cognitive dissonance about their problem solving ability, thought they performed better than they did, and finished with an illusion of competence. Based on our observations from both groups, we propose ways to scaffold the novice GenAI experience and make suggestions for future work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17739v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Prather, Brent Reeves, Juho Leinonen, Stephen MacNeil, Arisoa S. Randrianasolo, Brett Becker, Bailey Kimmel, Jared Wright, Ben Briggs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Human-Cobot collaboration's impact on success, time completion, errors, workload, gestures and acceptability during an assembly task</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17910v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The 5.0 industry promotes collaborative robots (cobots). This research studies the impacts of cobot collaboration using an experimental setup. 120 participants realized a simple and a complex assembly task. 50% collaborated with another human (H/H) and 50% with a cobot (H/C). The workload and the acceptability of the cobotic collaboration were measured. Working with a cobot decreases the effect of the task complexity on the human workload and on the output quality. However, it increases the time completion and the number of gestures (while decreasing their frequency). The H/C couples have a higher chance of success but they take more time and more gestures to realize the task. The results of this research could help developers and stakeholders to understand the impacts of implementing a cobot in production chains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17910v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.apergo.2024.104306</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Applied Ergonomics, Volume 119, September 2024, 104306</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>\'Etienne Fournier, Christine Jeoffrion, Belal Hmedan, Damien Pellier, Humbert Fiorino, Aur\'elie Landry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Open-Source Reproducible Chess Robot for Human-Robot Interaction Research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18170v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent advancements in AI have sped up the evolution of versatile robot designs. Chess provides a standardized environment that allows for the evaluation of the influence of robot behaviors on human behavior. This article presents an open-source chess robot for human-robot interaction (HRI) research, specifically focusing on verbal and non-verbal interactions. OpenChessRobot recognizes chess pieces using computer vision, executes moves, and interacts with the human player using voice and robotic gestures. We detail the software design, provide quantitative evaluations of the robot's efficacy and offer a guide for its reproducibility. The code and are accessible on GitHub: https://github.com/renchizhhhh/OpenChessRobot</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18170v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renchi Zhang, Joost de Winter, Dimitra Dodou, Harleigh Seyffert, Yke Bauke Eisma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hostile Counterspeech Drives Users From Hate Subreddits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18374v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Counterspeech -- speech that opposes hate speech -- has gained significant attention recently as a strategy to reduce hate on social media. While previous studies suggest that counterspeech can somewhat reduce hate speech, little is known about its effects on participation in online hate communities, nor which counterspeech tactics reduce harmful behavior. We begin to address these gaps by identifying 25 large hate communities ("subreddits") within Reddit and analyzing the effect of counterspeech on newcomers within these communities. We first construct a new public dataset of carefully annotated counterspeech and non-counterspeech comments within these subreddits. We use this dataset to train a state-of-the-art counterspeech detection model. Next, we use matching to evaluate the causal effects of hostile and non-hostile counterspeech on the engagement of newcomers in hate subreddits. We find that, while non-hostile counterspeech is ineffective at keeping users from fully disengaging from these hate subreddits, a single hostile counterspeech comment substantially reduces both future likelihood of engagement. While offering nuance to the understanding of counterspeech efficacy, these results a) leave unanswered the question of whether hostile counterspeech dissuades newcomers from participation in online hate writ large, or merely drives them into less-moderated and more extreme hate communities, and b) raises ethical considerations about hostile counterspeech, which is both comparatively common and might exacerbate rather than mitigate the net level of antagonism in society. These findings underscore the importance of future work to improve counterspeech tactics and minimize unintended harm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18374v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Hickey, Matheus Schmitz, Daniel M. T. Fessler, Paul E. Smaldino, Kristina Lerman, Goran Muri\'c, Keith Burghardt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brain Tumor Segmentation (BraTS) Challenge 2024: Meningioma Radiotherapy Planning Automated Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18383v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The 2024 Brain Tumor Segmentation Meningioma Radiotherapy (BraTS-MEN-RT) challenge aims to advance automated segmentation algorithms using the largest known multi-institutional dataset of radiotherapy planning brain MRIs with expert-annotated target labels for patients with intact or post-operative meningioma that underwent either conventional external beam radiotherapy or stereotactic radiosurgery. Each case includes a defaced 3D post-contrast T1-weighted radiotherapy planning MRI in its native acquisition space, accompanied by a single-label "target volume" representing the gross tumor volume (GTV) and any at-risk post-operative site. Target volume annotations adhere to established radiotherapy planning protocols, ensuring consistency across cases and institutions. For pre-operative meningiomas, the target volume encompasses the entire GTV and associated nodular dural tail, while for post-operative cases, it includes at-risk resection cavity margins as determined by the treating institution. Case annotations were reviewed and approved by expert neuroradiologists and radiation oncologists. Participating teams will develop, containerize, and evaluate automated segmentation models using this comprehensive dataset. Model performance will be assessed using the lesion-wise Dice Similarity Coefficient and the 95% Hausdorff distance. The top-performing teams will be recognized at the Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention Conference in October 2024. BraTS-MEN-RT is expected to significantly advance automated radiotherapy planning by enabling precise tumor segmentation and facilitating tailored treatment, ultimately improving patient outcomes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18383v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominic LaBella, Katherine Schumacher, Michael Mix, Kevin Leu, Shan McBurney-Lin, Pierre Nedelec, Javier Villanueva-Meyer, Jonathan Shapey, Tom Vercauteren, Kazumi Chia, Omar Al-Salihi, Justin Leu, Lia Halasz, Yury Velichko, Chunhao Wang, John Kirkpatrick, Scott Floyd, Zachary J. Reitman, Trey Mullikin, Ulas Bagci, Sean Sachdev, Jona A. Hattangadi-Gluth, Tyler Seibert, Nikdokht Farid, Connor Puett, Matthew W. Pease, Kevin Shiue, Syed Muhammad Anwar, Shahriar Faghani, Muhammad Ammar Haider, Pranav Warman, Jake Albrecht, Andr\'as Jakab, Mana Moassefi, Verena Chung, Alejandro Aristizabal, Alexandros Karargyris, Hasan Kassem, Sarthak Pati, Micah Sheller, Christina Huang, Aaron Coley, Siddharth Ghanta, Alex Schneider, Conrad Sharp, Rachit Saluja, Florian Kofler, Philipp Lohmann, Phillipp Vollmuth, Louis Gagnon, Maruf Adewole, Hongwei Bran Li, Anahita Fathi Kazerooni, Nourel Hoda Tahon, Udunna Anazodo, Ahmed W. Moawad, Bjoern Menze, Marius George Linguraru, Mariam Aboian, Benedikt Wiestler, Ujjwal Baid, Gian-Marco Conte, Andreas M. T. Rauschecker, Ayman Nada, Aly H. Abayazeed, Raymond Huang, Maria Correia de Verdier, Jeffrey D. Rudie, Spyridon Bakas, Evan Calabrese</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating and Designing for Trust in AI-powered Code Generation Tools</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.11248</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.11248v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: As AI-powered code generation tools such as GitHub Copilot become popular, it is crucial to understand software developers' trust in AI tools -- a key factor for tool adoption and responsible usage. However, we know little about how developers build trust with AI, nor do we understand how to design the interface of generative AI systems to facilitate their appropriate levels of trust. In this paper, we describe findings from a two-stage qualitative investigation. We first interviewed 17 developers to contextualize their notions of trust and understand their challenges in building appropriate trust in AI code generation tools. We surfaced three main challenges -- including building appropriate expectations, configuring AI tools, and validating AI suggestions. To address these challenges, we conducted a design probe study in the second stage to explore design concepts that support developers' trust-building process by 1) communicating AI performance to help users set proper expectations, 2) allowing users to configure AI by setting and adjusting preferences, and 3) offering indicators of model mechanism to support evaluation of AI suggestions. We gathered developers' feedback on how these design concepts can help them build appropriate trust in AI-powered code generation tools, as well as potential risks in design. These findings inform our proposed design recommendations on how to design for trust in AI-powered code generation tools.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.11248v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3630106.3658984</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ruotong Wang, Ruijia Cheng, Denae Ford, Thomas Zimmermann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Redefining Qualitative Analysis in the AI Era: Utilizing ChatGPT for Efficient Thematic Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.10771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.10771v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: AI tools, particularly large-scale language model (LLM) based applications such as ChatGPT, have the potential to simplify qualitative research. Through semi-structured interviews with seventeen participants, we identified challenges and concerns in integrating ChatGPT into the qualitative analysis process. Collaborating with thirteen qualitative researchers, we developed a framework for designing prompts to enhance the effectiveness of ChatGPT in thematic analysis. Our findings indicate that improving transparency, providing guidance on prompts, and strengthening users' understanding of LLMs' capabilities significantly enhance the users' ability to interact with ChatGPT. We also discovered and revealed the reasons behind researchers' shift in attitude towards ChatGPT from negative to positive. This research not only highlights the importance of well-designed prompts in LLM applications but also offers reflections for qualitative researchers on the perception of AI's role. Finally, we emphasize the potential ethical risks and the impact of constructing AI ethical expectations by researchers, particularly those who are novices, on future research and AI development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.10771v3</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>He Zhang, Chuhao Wu, Jingyi Xie, Yao Lyu, Jie Cai, John M. Carroll</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Future You: A Conversation with an AI-Generated Future Self Reduces Anxiety, Negative Emotions, and Increases Future Self-Continuity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12514</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12514v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce "Future You," an interactive, brief, single-session, digital chat intervention designed to improve future self-continuity--the degree of connection an individual feels with a temporally distant future self--a characteristic that is positively related to mental health and wellbeing. Our system allows users to chat with a relatable yet AI-powered virtual version of their future selves that is tuned to their future goals and personal qualities. To make the conversation realistic, the system generates a "synthetic memory"--a unique backstory for each user--that creates a throughline between the user's present age (between 18-30) and their life at age 60. The "Future You" character also adopts the persona of an age-progressed image of the user's present self. After a brief interaction with the "Future You" character, users reported decreased anxiety, and increased future self-continuity. This is the first study successfully demonstrating the use of personalized AI-generated characters to improve users' future self-continuity and wellbeing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12514v2</guid>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pat Pataranutaporn, Kavin Winson, Peggy Yin, Auttasak Lapapirojn, Pichayoot Ouppaphan, Monchai Lertsutthiwong, Pattie Maes, Hal Hershfield</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GesGPT: Speech Gesture Synthesis With Text Parsing from ChatGPT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.13013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.13013v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Gesture synthesis has gained significant attention as a critical research field, aiming to produce contextually appropriate and natural gestures corresponding to speech or textual input. Although deep learning-based approaches have achieved remarkable progress, they often overlook the rich semantic information present in the text, leading to less expressive and meaningful gestures. In this letter, we propose GesGPT, a novel approach to gesture generation that leverages the semantic analysis capabilities of large language models , such as ChatGPT. By capitalizing on the strengths of LLMs for text analysis, we adopt a controlled approach to generate and integrate professional gestures and base gestures through a text parsing script, resulting in diverse and meaningful gestures. Firstly, our approach involves the development of prompt principles that transform gesture generation into an intention classification problem using ChatGPT. We also conduct further analysis on emphasis words and semantic words to aid in gesture generation. Subsequently, we construct a specialized gesture lexicon with multiple semantic annotations, decoupling the synthesis of gestures into professional gestures and base gestures. Finally, we merge the professional gestures with base gestures. Experimental results demonstrate that GesGPT effectively generates contextually appropriate and expressive gestures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.13013v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/LRA.2024.3359544</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Robotics and Automation Letters 9 (2024) 3</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nan Gao, Zeyu Zhao, Zhi Zeng, Shuwu Zhang, Dongdong Weng, Yihua Bao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The future of human-centric eXplainable Artificial Intelligence (XAI) is not post-hoc explanations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.00364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.00364v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Explainable Artificial Intelligence (XAI) plays a crucial role in enabling human understanding and trust in deep learning systems. As models get larger, more ubiquitous, and pervasive in aspects of daily life, explainability is necessary to minimize adverse effects of model mistakes. Unfortunately, current approaches in human-centric XAI (e.g. predictive tasks in healthcare, education, or personalized ads) tend to rely on a single post-hoc explainer, whereas recent work has identified systematic disagreement between post-hoc explainers when applied to the same instances of underlying black-box models. In this paper, we therefore present a call for action to address the limitations of current state-of-the-art explainers. We propose a shift from post-hoc explainability to designing interpretable neural network architectures. We identify five needs of human-centric XAI (real-time, accurate, actionable, human-interpretable, and consistent) and propose two schemes for interpretable-by-design neural network workflows (adaptive routing with InterpretCC and temporal diagnostics with I2MD). We postulate that the future of human-centric XAI is neither in explaining black-boxes nor in reverting to traditional, interpretable models, but in neural networks that are intrinsically interpretable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.00364v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vinitra Swamy, Jibril Frej, Tanja K\"aser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>InterpretCC: Intrinsic User-Centric Interpretability through Global Mixture of Experts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.02933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.02933v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Interpretability for neural networks is a trade-off between three key requirements: 1) faithfulness of the explanation (i.e., how perfectly it explains the prediction), 2) understandability of the explanation by humans, and 3) model performance. Most existing methods compromise one or more of these requirements; e.g., post-hoc approaches provide limited faithfulness, automatically identified feature masks compromise understandability, and intrinsically interpretable methods such as decision trees limit model performance. These shortcomings are unacceptable for sensitive applications such as education and healthcare, which require trustworthy explanations, actionable interpretations, and accurate predictions. In this work, we present InterpretCC (interpretable conditional computation), a family of interpretable-by-design neural networks that guarantee human-centric interpretability, while maintaining comparable performance to state-of-the-art models by adaptively and sparsely activating features before prediction. We extend this idea into an interpretable, global mixture-of-experts (MoE) model that allows humans to specify topics of interest, discretely separates the feature space for each data point into topical subnetworks, and adaptively and sparsely activates these topical subnetworks for prediction. We apply variations of the InterpretCC architecture for text, time series and tabular data across several real-world benchmarks, demonstrating comparable performance with non-interpretable baselines, outperforming interpretable-by-design baselines, and showing higher actionability and usefulness according to a user study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.02933v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vinitra Swamy, Syrielle Montariol, Julian Blackwell, Jibril Frej, Martin Jaggi, Tanja K\"aser</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Detoxifying Large Language Models via Knowledge Editing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14472v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates using knowledge editing techniques to detoxify Large Language Models (LLMs). We construct a benchmark, SafeEdit, which covers nine unsafe categories with various powerful attack prompts and equips comprehensive metrics for systematic evaluation. We conduct experiments with several knowledge editing approaches, indicating that knowledge editing has the potential to detoxify LLMs with a limited impact on general performance efficiently. Then, we propose a simple yet effective baseline, dubbed Detoxifying with Intraoperative Neural Monitoring (DINM), to diminish the toxicity of LLMs within a few tuning steps via only one instance. We further provide an in-depth analysis of the internal mechanism for various detoxifying approaches, demonstrating that previous methods like SFT and DPO may merely suppress the activations of toxic parameters, while DINM mitigates the toxicity of the toxic parameters to a certain extent, making permanent adjustments. We hope that these insights could shed light on future work of developing detoxifying approaches and the underlying knowledge mechanisms of LLMs. Code and benchmark are available at https://github.com/zjunlp/EasyEdit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14472v5</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengru Wang, Ningyu Zhang, Ziwen Xu, Zekun Xi, Shumin Deng, Yunzhi Yao, Qishen Zhang, Linyi Yang, Jindong Wang, Huajun Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
