<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP</link>
    <description>math.MP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 05:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo-potentials and local isometric immersion for a generalized Camassa-Holm equation describing pseudospherical surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18128</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18128v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A generalized Camassa-Holm equation, which describes pseudospherical surfaces, is considered. Using geometric methods, it is demonstrated that the equation is geometrically integrable. Additionally, an infinite hierarchy of conservation laws is derived. Furthermore, the paper delves into the investigation of the problem of locally isometric immersion into three-dimensional Euclidean space based on the equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18128v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingyue Guo, Zhenhua Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soliton Shielding of the focusing modified KdV equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18175v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider soliton gas solutions of the modified Korteweg-de Vries (mKdV) equation, where the point spectrum of the condensate is located within a bounded domain in the upper half-plane. We first demonstrate that when the domain is a quadrature and the soliton density is an analytic function, the corresponding deterministic soliton gas coincides with a finite number of solitons, which we call this effect soliton shielding. When the domain is an ellipse and the soliton density is analytic, the corresponding deterministic soliton gas reduces the spectral data to the segment joining the foci. The initial datum of this Cauchy problem is asymptotically step-like oscillatory, described by a periodic elliptic function as \( x \to +\infty \), and it vanishes exponentially fast as \( x \to -\infty \).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18175v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruihong Ma, Engui Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cyclic $BV_\infty$ algebra and Frobenius manifold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18325v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We describe the construction of Frobenius manifold out of a cyclic (commutative) $BV_\infty$ algebra $(A,\Delta)$ under the assumption of a Hodge-to-de Rham degeneration property and the existence of a compatible homotopy retract of $A$ onto its cohomology. We then apply it to Jacobi manifolds and Hermitian manifolds, generalizing known results in literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18325v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen Hao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Maximum Entropy Principle in Nonequilibrium Thermodynamics: A Brief History and the Contributions of Wolfgang Dreyer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18340v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a brief history of how the famous Maximum Entropy Principle was used as closure of moments of the Boltzmann equation. In particular, we want to remark on the important role of two fundamental papers by Wolfgang Dreyer, one in the classical framework and one in a relativistic context, to use this principle and to compare the result with the macroscopic theory of Rational Extended Thermodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18340v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takashi Arima, Tommaso Ruggeri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A geometric description of some thermodynamical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18478v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper we show how almost cosymplectic structures are a natural framework to study thermodynamical systems. Indeed, we are able to obtain the same evolution equations obtained previously by Gay-Balmaz and Yoshimura (see Entropy, 21(8):39, 2019) using variational arguments. The proposed geometric description allows us to apply geometrical tools to discuss reduction by symmetries, the Hamilton-Jacobi equation or discretization of these systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18478v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manuel de Le\'on, Jaime Bajo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KP integrability of non-perturbative differentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18592</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18592v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the KP integrability of non-perturbative topological recursion, which can be considered as a formal $\hbar$-deformation of the Krichever construction. This property goes back to a 2011 conjecture of Borot and Eynard.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18592v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Alexandrov, Boris Bychkov, Petr Dunin-Barkowski, Maxim Kazarian, Sergey Shadrin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C-R-T Fractionalization in the First Quantized Hamiltonian Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11958</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11958v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent research has revealed that the CRT symmetry for fermions exhibits a fractionalization distinct from the $\mathbb{Z}_2^{\mathcal{C}}\times\mathbb{Z}_2^{\mathcal{R}}\times\mathbb{Z}_2^{\mathcal{T}}$ for scalar bosons. In fact, the CRT symmetry for fermions can be extended by internal symmetries such as fermion parity, thereby forming a group extension of the $\mathbb{Z}_2$ direct product. Conventionally, a Majorana fermion is defined by one Dirac fermion with trivial charge conjugation. However, when the spacetime dimension $d+1=5,6,7\bmod8$, the real dimension of Majorana fermion (dim$_{\mathbb{R}}\chi_{\mathcal{C}\ell(d,0)}$) aligns with the real dimension of Dirac fermion (dim$_{\mathbb{R}}\psi_{\mathcal{C}\ell(d)}$), rather than being half, which necessitates the introduction of a symplectic Majorana fermion, defined by two Dirac fermions with trivial charge conjugation. To include these two types of Majorana fermions, we embed the theory in $n_{\mathbb{R}}$ and define the Majorana fermion field as a representation of the real Clifford algebra with 8-fold periodicity. Within the Hamiltonian formalism, we identify the 8-fold CRT-internal symmetry groups across general dimensions. Similarly, Dirac fermion field is defined as a representation of the complex Clifford algebra with 2-fold periodicity. Interestingly, we discover that the CRT-internal symmetry groups exhibit an 8-fold periodicity that is distinct from that of the complex Clifford algebra. In certain dimensions where distinct mass terms can span a mass manifold, the CRT-internal symmetries can act non-trivially upon this mass manifold. Employing domain wall reduction method, we are able to elucidate the relationships between symmetries across different dimensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11958v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang-Yang Li, Zheyan Wan, Juven Wang, Shing-Tung Yau, Yi-Zhuang You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Utilizing Causal Network Markers to Identify Tipping Points ahead of Critical Transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16235v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Early-warning signals of delicate design are always used to predict critical transitions in complex systems, which makes it possible to render the systems far away from the catastrophic state by introducing timely interventions. Traditional signals including the dynamical network biomarker (DNB), based on statistical properties such as variance and autocorrelation of nodal dynamics, overlook directional interactions and thus have limitations in capturing underlying mechanisms and simultaneously sustaining robustness against noise perturbations. This paper therefore introduces a framework of causal network markers (CNMs) by incorporating causality indicators, which reflect the directional influence between variables. Actually, to detect and identify the tipping points ahead of critical transition, two markers are designed: CNM-GC for linear causality and CNM-TE for non-linear causality, as well as a functional representation of different causality indicators and a clustering technique to verify the system's dominant group. Through demonstrations using benchmark models and real-world datasets of epileptic seizure, the framework of CNMs shows higher predictive power and accuracy than the traditional DNB indicator. It is believed that, due to the versatility and scalability, the CNMs are suitable for comprehensively evaluating the systems. The most possible direction for application includes the identification of tipping points in clinical disease.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16235v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shirui Bian, Zezhou Wang, Siyang Leng, Wei Lin, Jifan Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A landscape of 4d N=1 SCFTs with a=c</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17895v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a landscape of four-dimensional $\mathcal{N}=1$ superconformal field theories (SCFTs) with identical central charges. These theories are obtained by renormalization group flows triggered by supersymmetry-preserving superpotential deformations of the $\mathcal{N}=1$ gauging of the flavor symmetry of a collection of $\mathcal{N}=2$ $\mathcal{D}_p(G)$ Argyres--Douglas SCFTs. In this work, we focus on the fixed points in the landscape of the $SU(3)$ gauging of three copies of the $\mathcal{D}_2(SU(3)) = H_2$ theory together with an adjoint-valued chiral multiplet. We catalogue the network of $a = c$ fixed points, and, along the way, we find a variety of dualities and instances of supersymmetry enhancement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17895v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Monica Jinwoo Kang, Craig Lawrie, Ki-Hong Lee, Jaewon Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinitely Stable Disordered Systems on Emergent Fractal Structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17905v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In quenched disordered systems, the existence of ordering is generally believed to be only possible in the weak disorder regime (disregarding models of spin-glass type). In particular, sufficiently large random field is expected to prohibit any finite temperature ordering. Here, we show that this is not necessarily true. We provide physically motivated examples of systems in which disorder induces an ordering that is *infinitely stable* in the sense that: (1) there exists ordering at arbitrarily large disorder strength and (2) the transition temperature remains, asymptotically, nonzero in the limit of infinite disorder. The ordering is spatially localized on the boundary of a disorder-induced, emergent percolating fractal structure. The examples we give are most naturally described when the spatial dimension $d \ge 3$, but can also be formulated when $d=2$, provided that the underlying graph is non-planar.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17905v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew C. Yuan, Nick Crawford</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonabelian shift operators and shifted Yangians</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17906v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce nonabelian analogs of shift operators in the enumerative theory of quasimaps. We apply them on the one hand to strengthen the emerging analogy between enumerative geometry and the geometric theory of automorphic forms, and on the other hand to obtain results about quantized Coulomb branch algebras. In particular, we find a short and direct proof that the equivariant convolution homology of the affine Grassmannian of $GL_n$ is a quotient of a shifted Yangian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17906v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Spencer Tamagni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A dynamical algebra of protocol-induced transformations on Dicke states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17917v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum $n$-qubit states that are totally symmetric under the permutation of qubits are essential ingredients of important algorithms and applications in quantum information. Consequently, there is significant interest in developing methods to prepare and manipulate Dicke states, which form a basis for the subspace of fully symmetric states. Two simple protocols for transforming Dicke states are considered. An algebraic characterization of the operations that these protocols induce is obtained in terms of the Weyl algebra $W(2)$ and $\mathfrak{su}(2)$. Fixed points under the application of the combination of both protocols are explicitly determined. Connections with the binary Hamming scheme, the Hadamard transform, and Krawtchouk polynomials are highlighted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17917v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierre-Antoine Bernard, Luc Vinet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An analytic study on the properties of solitary waves traveling on tensegrity-like lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18026v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper develops an analytic study on the existence and properties of solitary waves on 1D chains of lumped masses and nonlinear springs, which exhibit a mechanical response similar to that of tensegrity prisms with locking-type response under axial loading. Making use of the Weierstrass' theory of 1D Lagrangian conservative systems, we show that such waves exist and that their shapes depend on the wave speed. A progressive localization of the traveling pulses in narrow regions of space is observed as the wave speed increases up to a limit value. A comparative analysis illustrates that the presented study is able to capture the wave dynamics observed in previous numerical studies on tensegrity mass-spring chains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18026v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ijnonlinmec.2022.104264</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Non-Linear Mechanics 148 (2023): 104264</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ada Amendola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rational symmetric functions from the Izergin-Korepin 19-vertex model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18085</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18085v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Starting from the Izergin-Korepin 19-vertex model in the quadrant, we introduce two families of rational multivariate functions $F_S$ and $G_S$; these are in direct analogy with functions introduced by Borodin in the context of the higher-spin 6-vertex model in the quadrant.
  We prove that $F_S(x_1,\dots,x_N;z)$ and $G_S(y_1,\dots,y_M;z)$ are symmetric functions in their alphabets $(x_1,\dots,x_N)$ and $(y_1,\dots,y_M)$, and pair together to yield a Cauchy identity. Both properties are consequences of the Yang-Baxter equation of the model.
  We show that, in an appropriate limit of the spectral parameters $z$, $F_S$ tends to a stable symmetric function denoted $H_S$. This leads to a simplified version of the Cauchy identity with a fully factorized kernel, and suggests self-duality of the functions $H_S$.
  We obtain a symmetrization formula for the function $F_S(x_1,\dots,x_N;z)$, which exhibits its symmetry in $(x_1,\dots,x_N)$. In contrast to the 6-vertex model, where $F^{6{\rm V}}_S(x_1,\dots,x_N;z)$ is cast as a sum over the symmetric group $\mathfrak{S}_N$, the symmetrization formula in the 19-vertex model is over a larger set of objects that we define; we call these objects 2-permutations.
  As a byproduct of the proof of our symmetrization formula, we obtain explicit formulas for the monodromy matrix elements of the 19-vertex model in a basis that renders them totally spatially symmetric.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18085v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandr Garbali, Weiying Guo, Michael Wheeler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>KPZ fixed point convergence of the ASEP and stochastic six-vertex models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18117</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18117v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the stochastic six-vertex (S6V) model and asymmetric simple exclusion process (ASEP) under general initial conditions which are bounded below lines of arbitrary slope at $\pm\infty$. We show under Kardar-Parisi-Zhang (KPZ) scaling of time, space, and fluctuations that the height functions of these models converge to the KPZ fixed point. Previously, our results were known in the case of ASEP (for a particular direction in the rarefaction fan) via a comparison approach arXiv:2008.06584.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18117v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amol Aggarwal, Ivan Corwin, Milind Hegde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$N=1$ super Virasoro tensor categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18127v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the category of $C_1$-cofinite modules for the universal $N=1$ super Virasoro vertex operator superalgebra $\mathcal{S}(c,0)$ at any central charge $c$ is locally finite and admits the vertex algebraic braided tensor category structure of Huang-Lepowsky-Zhang. For central charges $c^{\mathfrak{ns}}(t)=\frac{15}{2}-3(t+t^{-1})$ with $t\notin\mathbb{Q}$, we show that this tensor category is semisimple, rigid, and slightly degenerate, and we determine its fusion rules. For central charge $c^{\mathfrak{ns}}(1)=\frac{3}{2}$, we show that this tensor category is rigid and that its simple modules have the same fusion rules as $\mathrm{Rep}\,\mathfrak{osp}(1\vert 2)$, in agreement with earlier fusion rule calculations of Milas. Finally, for the remaining central charges $c^{\mathfrak{ns}}(t)$ with $t\in\mathbb{Q}^\times$, we show that the simple $\mathcal{S}(c^{\mathfrak{ns}}(t),0)$-module $\mathcal{S}_{2,2}$ of lowest conformal weight $h^{\mathfrak{ns}}_{2,2}(t)=\frac{3(t-1)^2}{8t}$ is rigid and self-dual, except possibly when $t^{\pm 1}$ is a negative integer or when $c^{\mathfrak{ns}}(t)$ is the central charge of a rational $N=1$ superconformal minimal model.
  As $\mathcal{S}_{2,2}$ is expected to generate the category of $C_1$-cofinite $\mathcal{S}(c^{\mathfrak{ns}}(t),0)$-modules under fusion, rigidity of $\mathcal{S}_{2,2}$ is the first key step to proving rigidity of this category for general $t\in\mathbb{Q}^\times$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18127v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Creutzig, Robert McRae, Florencia Orosz Hunziker, Jinwei Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a class of exact solutions of the Ishimori equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18195v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, a class of particular solutions of the Ishimori equation is found. This equation is known as the spatially two-dimensional version of the Heisenberg equation, which has important applications in the theory of ferromagnets. It is shown that the two-dimensional Toda-type lattice found earlier by Ferapontov, Shabat and Yamilov is a dressing chain for this equation. Using the integrable reductions of the dressing chain, the authors found an essentially new class of solutions to the Ishimori equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18195v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rustem N. Garifullin, Ismagil T. Habibullin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free the Design Space of Equivariant Graph Neural Networks: High-Rank Irreducible Cartesian Tensor Decomposition and Bases of Equivariant Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18263</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18263v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Irreducible Cartesian tensors (ICTs) play a crucial role in the design of equivariant graph neural networks, as well as in theoretical chemistry and chemical physics. Meanwhile, the design space of available linear operations on tensors that preserve symmetry presents a significant challenge. The ICT decomposition and a basis of this equivariant space are difficult to obtain for high-order tensors. After decades of research, we recently achieve an explicit ICT decomposition for $n=5$ \citep{bonvicini2024irreducible} with factorial time/space complexity. This work, for the first time, obtains decomposition matrices for ICTs up to rank $n=9$ with reduced and affordable complexity, by constructing what we call path matrices. The path matrices are obtained via performing chain-like contraction with Clebsch-Gordan matrices following the parentage scheme. We prove and leverage that the concatenation of path matrices is an orthonormal change-of-basis matrix between the Cartesian tensor product space and the spherical direct sum spaces. Furthermore, we identify a complete orthogonal basis for the equivariant space, rather than a spanning set \citep{pearce2023brauer}, through this path matrices technique. We further extend our result to the arbitrary tensor product and direct sum spaces, enabling free design between different spaces while keeping symmetry. The Python code is available in the appendix where the $n=6,\dots,9$ ICT decomposition matrices are obtained in &lt;0.1s, 0.5s, 1s, 3s, 11s, and 4m32s, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18263v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shihao Shao, Yikang Li, Zhouchen Lin, Qinghua Cui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mechanics of curved crease origami: 1DoF mechanisms, distributed actuation by spontaneous curvature, and cross-talk between multiple folds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18265v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Origami morphing, obtained with patches of piecewise smooth isometries separated by straight fold lines, is an exquisite art that has already received considerable attention in the mathematics and mechanics literature. Curved fold lines, leading to curved creases and curved pleated structures, introduce the additional complexity of mechanical coupling between the folds. This coupling can be exploited to obtain morphing structures with more robust folding pathways. We discuss one-degree-of-freedom mechanisms and folds actuated by spontaneous curvature (as in the case of hygromorphic multilayered composites), comparing the purely geometric approach to two approaches based on the mechanics of active shells and of active three-dimensional solids. Moreover, we discuss the cooperativity of multiple folds and demonstrate the energetic advantage of synchronous folding over sequential folding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18265v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio DeSimone, Luciano Teresi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noether Symmetry Analysis for Generalized Brans-Dicke Cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18311</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18311v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the complete solution to the classification problem regarding the variational symmetries of the generalized Brans-Dicke cosmological model in the presence of a second scalar field minimally coupled to gravity and the generalized Brans-Dicke scalar field theory. Through the symmetry analysis, we were able to specify the functional form of the field equations such that they become integrable. Additionally, new families of integrable cosmological models are presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18311v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andronikos Paliathanasis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Quasinormal Modes of charged de Sitter Blackholes from Quiver Gauge Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18359v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We give the connection formulae for ordinary differential equations with 5 and 6 (and in principle can be generalized to more) regular singularities from the data of instanton partition functions of quiver gauge theories. We check the consistency of these connection formulae by numerically computing the quasinormal modes (QNMs) of Reissner-Nordstr\"om de Sitter (RN-dS) blackhole. Analytic expressions are obtained for all the families of QNMs, including the photon-sphere modes, dS modes, and near-extremal modes. We also argue that a similar method can be applied to the dS-Kerr-Newman blackhole.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18359v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pujun Liu, Rui-Dong Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wehrl inequalities for matrix coefficients of holomorphic discrete series</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18382v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove Wehrl-type $L^2(G)-L^{p}(G)$ inequalities for matrix coefficients of vector-valued holomorphic discrete series of $G$, for even integers $p=2n$. The optimal constant is expressed in terms of Harish-Chandra formal degrees for the discrete series. We prove the maximizers are precisely the reproducing kernels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18382v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robin van Haastrecht, Genkai Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral Property of Magnetic Quantum Walk on Hypercube</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce and investigate a model of magnetic quantum walk on a general hypercube. We first construct a set of unitary involutions associated with a magnetic potential $\nu$ by using quantum Bernoulli noises. And then, with these unitary involutions as the magnetic shift operators, we define the evolution operator $\mathsf{W}^{(\nu)}$ for the model, where $\nu$ is the magnetic potential. We examine the point-spectrum and approximate-spectrum of the evolution operator $\mathsf{W}^{(\nu)}$ and obtain their representations in terms of the coin operator system of the model. We show that the point-spectrum and approximate-spectrum of $\mathsf{W}^{(\nu)}$ are completely independent of the magnetic potential $\nu$ although $\mathsf{W}^{(\nu)}$ itself is dependent of the magnetic potential $\nu$. Our work might suggest that a quantum walk perturbed by a magnetic field can have spectral stability with respect to the magnetic potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18401v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ce Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Global Bifurcation Curve for Fourth-Order MEMS/NEMS Models with Clamped Boundary Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18427v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Global solution curve and exact multiplicity of positive solutions for a class of fourth-order equations with doubly clamped boundary conditions are established. The results extend a theorem of P. Korman (2004) by allowing the presence of a singularity in the nonlinearity. The paper also provides a global a priori bound for $C^3$-norm of positive solutions, which is optimal in terms of regularity. Examples arising in MEMS/NEMS models are presented to illustrate applications of the main results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18427v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manting Lin, Hongjing Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $S=\frac{1}{2}$ XY and XYZ models on the two or higher dimensional hypercubic lattice do not possess nontrivial local conserved quantities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18504</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18504v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the $S=\frac{1}{2}$ quantum spin system on the $d$-dimensional hypercubic lattice with $d\ge2$ with uniform nearest-neighbor interaction of the XY or XYZ type and arbitrary uniform magnetic field. By extending the method recently developed for quantum spin chains, we prove that the model possesses no local conserved quantities except for the trivial ones, such as the Hamiltonian. This result strongly suggests that the model is non-integrable. We note that our result applies to the XX model without a magnetic field, which is one of the easiest solvable models in one dimension.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18504v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoto Shiraishi, Hal Tasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weyl-Heisenberg covariant quantization for the discrete torus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18521v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Covariant integral quantization is implemented for systems whose phase space is $Z_{d} \times Z_{d}$, i.e., for systems moving on the discrete periodic set $Z_d= \{0,1,\dotsc d-1$ mod$ d\}$. The symmetry group of this phase space is the periodic discrete version of the Weyl-Heisenberg group, namely the central extension of the abelian group $Z_d \times Z_d$. In this regard, the phase space is viewed as the left coset of the group with its center. The non-trivial unitary irreducible representation of this group, as acting on $L^2(Z_{N})$, is square integrable on the phase phase. We derive the corresponding covariant integral quantizations from (weight) functions on the phase space, and display their phase space portrait.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18521v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Romain Murenzi, Aidan Zlotak, Jean Pierre Gazeau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fiber decomposition of non-commutative harmonic oscillators by two-photon quantum Rabi models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04239v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The non-commutative harmonic oscillators (NcHO) and 2p-quantum Rabi models (2pQRM) are extensions of harmonic oscillators. The purpose of this paper is to give a relationship between NcHO and 2pQRM, and the fiber decomposition of NcHO by 2pQRM is shown. We also construct Feynman-Kac formulas of NcHO and 2pQRM. Then asymptotic behaviors of the spectral zeta function of 2pQRM is considered.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04239v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fumio Hiroshima, Tomoyuki Shirai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probability Bracket Notation, Wick-Matsubara Relation, Density Operators, and Microscopic Probability Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/0909.1295</link>
      <description>arXiv:0909.1295v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Following the Dirac vector bracket notation (VBN), we proposed the probability bracket notation (PBN) in our previous paper. We mentioned that under the special Wick rotation (imaginary time), a stationary Schrodinger equation in the Hilbert space transforms into the master equation of a microscopic probabilistic process (MPP) in the probability space. In this article, we first study the MPP of the system of a single particle, we show that the energy expectation of the MPP eventually approaches the lowest energy level in its initial condition and its von Neumann entropy finally vanishes. Then we explore the MPP for the quantum system of identical particles in the Fock space, we recover the expected occupation number of particles and the grand partition function in quantum statistics by connecting time with temperature (the Wick-Matsubara relation). We also reproduce the internal energy of an ideal gas in thermodynamics by using the relation. To address the entropy issue and relate the PBN with research topics of statistics in the literature, we express the density operators and the von Neumann entropy in the probability space by using the PBN. The Wick-Matsubara relation plus the PBN might provide a new way of microscopic probability modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:0909.1295v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xing M. Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Riesz basisness of the eigenfunctions and eigenvectors connected to the stability problem of a fluid-conveying tube with boundary control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2204.01432</link>
      <description>arXiv:2204.01432v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the present paper we study the stability problem for a stretched tube conveying fluid with boundary control. The abstract spectral problem concerns operator pencils of the forms \begin{equation*} \mathcal{M}\left(\lambda\right)=\lambda^2G+\lambda D+C\quad\text{and}\quad\mathcal{P}\left(\lambda\right)=\lambda I-T \end{equation*} taking values in different Hilbert product spaces. Thorough analysis is made of the location and asymptotics of eigenvalues in the complex plane and Riesz basisness of the corresponding eigenfunctions and eigenvectors. Well-posedness of the closed-loop system represented by the initial-value problem for the abstract equation \begin{equation*} \dot{{x}}\left(t\right)=Tx\left(t\right) \end{equation*} is established in the framework of semigroups as well as expansions of the solutions in terms of eigenvectors and stability of the closed-loop system operator $T$. For the parameters of the problem we give regions, larger than those in the literature, in which a stretched tube with flow, simply supported at one end, with a boundary controller applied at the other end, can be made exponentially stable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2204.01432v4</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/zamm.202300455</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Mahyar Mahinzaeim, Gen Qi Xu, Xiao Xuan Feng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short- and long-time path tightness of the continuum directed random polymer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.05670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.05670v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider the point-to-point continuum directed random polymer ($\mathsf{CDRP}$) model that arises as a scaling limit from $1+1$ dimensional directed polymers in the intermediate disorder regime. We show that the annealed law of a point-to-point $\mathsf{CDRP}$ of length $t$ converges to the Brownian bridge under diffusive scaling when $t \downarrow 0$. In case that $t$ is large, we show that the transversal fluctuations of point-to-point $\mathsf{CDRP}$ are governed by the $2/3$ exponent. More precisely, as $t$ tends to infinity, we prove tightness of the annealed path measures of point-to-point $\mathsf{CDRP}$ of length $t$ upon scaling the length by $t$ and fluctuations of paths by $t^{2/3}$. The $2/3$ exponent is tight such that the one-point distribution of the rescaled paths converges to the geodesics of the directed landscape. This point-wise convergence can be enhanced to process-level modulo a conjecture. Our short and long-time tightness results also extend to point-to-line $\mathsf{CDRP}$. In the course of proving our main results, we establish quantitative versions of quenched modulus of continuity estimates for long-time $\mathsf{CDRP}$ which are of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.05670v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1214/22-AIHP1334</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Ann. Inst. H. Poincar\'e Probab. Statist. 60(1): 343-372 (February 2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sayan Das, Weitao Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Massive wave propagation near null infinity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.01119</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.01119v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study, fully microlocally, the propagation of massive waves on the octagonal compactification \[\mathbb{O}=[\overline{\mathbb{R}^{1,d}};\mathscr{I};1/2]\] of asymptotically Minkowski spacetime, which allows a detailed analysis both at timelike and spacelike infinity (as previously investigated using Parenti-Shubin-Melrose's sc-calculus) and, more novelly, at null infinity, denoted $\mathscr{I}$. The analysis is closely related to Hintz-Vasy's recent analysis of massless wave propagation at null infinity using the ``e,b-calculus'' on $\mathbb{O}$. We prove several elementary corollaries regarding the Klein-Gordon IVP. Our main technical tool is a fully symbolic pseudodifferential calculus, $\Psi_{\mathrm{de,sc}}(\mathbb{O})$, the ``de,sc-calculus'' on $\mathbb{O}$. The `de' refers to the structure (``double edge'') of the calculus at null infinity, and the `sc' refers to the structure (``scattering'') at the other boundary faces. We relate this structure to the hyperbolic coordinates used in other studies of the Klein-Gordon equation. Unlike hyperbolic coordinates, the de,sc-boundary fibration structure is Poincar\'e invariant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.01119v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ethan Sussman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random ordinate method for mitigating the ray effect in radiative transport equation simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12527v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Discrete Ordinates Method (DOM) is the most widely used velocity discretiza-tion method for simulating the radiative transport equation. However, the ray effect is a long-standing drawback of DOM. In benchmark tests that exhibit the ray effect, we observe low regularity in the velocity variable of the solution. To address this issue, we propose a Random Ordinate Method (ROM) to mitigate the ray effect. Compared to other strategies proposed in the literature for mitigating the ray effect, ROM offers several advantages: 1) the computational cost is comparable to that of DOM; 2) it is simple and requires minimal changes to existing DOM-based code; 3) it is easily parallelizable and independent of the problem setup. A formal analysis is presented for the convergence orders of the error and bias. Numerical tests demonstrate the reduction in computational cost compared toDOM, as well as its effectiveness in mitigating the ray effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12527v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lei Li, Min Tang, Yuqi Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A purely geometrical Aharonov-Bohm effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13919v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we apply covariant affine integral quantization to study motion in the 2D punctured plane. The associated four-dimensional phase space is identified with the similitude group SIM(2), representing transformations of the plane composed of translations, rotations, and dilations. Near the punctured point, we observe that the topology influencing quantum fluctuations gives rise to an affine vector potential, which can be interpreted as the Aharonov-Bohm (AB) gauge potential generated by an infinite coil. This finding suggests that the AB effect originates from the topology enforced by the impenetrable coil, rather than from a classical gauge potential. Our results offer a novel perspective on the AB effect, emphasizing the fundamental role of topology in quantum mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13919v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean-Pierre Gazeau, Tomoi Koide, Romain Murenzi, Aidan Zlotak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum chaos on the separatrix of the periodically perturbed Harper model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14926</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14926v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore the relation between a classical periodic Hamiltonian system and an associated discrete quantum system on a torus in phase space. The model is a sinusoidally perturbed Harper model and is similar to the sinusoidally perturbed pendulum. Separatrices connecting hyperbolic fixed points in the unperturbed classical system become chaotic under sinusoidal perturbation. We numerically compute eigenstates of the Floquet propagator for the associated quantum system. For each Floquet eigenstate we compute a Husimi distribution in phase space and an energy and energy dispersion from the expectation value of the unperturbed Hamiltonian operator. The Husimi distribution of each Floquet eigenstate resembles a classical orbit with a similar energy and similar energy dispersion. Chaotic orbits in the classical system are related to Floquet eigenstates that appear ergodic. For a hybrid regular and chaotic system, we use the energy dispersion to separate the Floquet eigenstates into ergodic and integrable subspaces. The distribution of quasi-energies in the ergodic subspace resembles that of a random matrix model. The width of a chaotic region in the classical system is estimated by integrating the perturbation along a separatrix orbit. We derive a related expression for the associated quantum system from the averaged perturbation in the interaction representation evaluated at states with energy close to the separatrix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14926v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alice C. Quillen, Abobakar Sediq Miakhel</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
