<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP</link>
    <description>math.MP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 03:02:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Odd and even derivations, transposed Poisson superalgebra and 3-Lie superalgebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16900v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One important example of a transposed Poisson algebra can be constructed by means of a commutative algebra and its derivation. This approach can be extended to superalgebras, that is, one can construct a transposed Poisson superalgebra given a commutative superalgebra and its even derivation. In this paper we show that including odd derivations in the framework of this approach requires introducing a new notion. It is a super vector space with two operations that satisfy the compatibility condition of transposed Poisson superalgebra. The first operation is determined by a left supermodule over commutative superalgebra and the second is a Jordan bracket. Then it is proved that the super vector space generated by an odd derivation of a commutative superalgebra satisfies all the requirements of introduced notion. We also show how to construct a 3-Lie superalgebra if we are given a transposed Poisson superalgebra and its even derivation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16900v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AC</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Viktor Abramov, Nikolai Sovetnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum geometric tensors from sub-bundle geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17163</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17163v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The geometric properties of quantum states are crucial for understanding many physical phenomena in quantum mechanics, condensed matter physics, and optics. The central object describing these properties is the quantum geometric tensor, which unifies the Berry curvature and the quantum metric. In this work, we use the differential-geometric framework of vector bundles to analyze the properties of parameter-dependent quantum states and generalize the quantum geometric tensor to this setting. This construction is based on an arbitrary connection on a Hermitian vector bundle, which defines a notion of quantum state transport in parameter space, and a sub-bundle projector, which constrains the set of accessible quantum states. We show that the sub-bundle geometry is similar to that of submanifolds in Riemannian geometry and is described by a generalization of the Gauss-Codazzi-Mainardi equations. This leads to a novel definition of the quantum geometric tensor, which contains an additional curvature contribution. To illustrate our results, we describe the sub-bundle geometry arising in the semiclassical treatment of Dirac fields propagating in curved spacetime and show how the quantum geometric tensor, with its additional curvature contributions, is obtained in this case. As a concrete example, we consider Dirac fermions confined to a hyperbolic plane and demonstrate how spatial curvature influences the quantum geometry. This work sets the stage for further exploration of quantum systems in curved geometries, with applications in both high-energy physics and condensed matter systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17163v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marius A. Oancea, Thomas B. Mieling, Giandomenico Palumbo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperboloidal initial data without logarithmic singularities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11804v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Andersson and Chru\'sciel showed that generic asymptotically hyperboloidal initial data sets admit polyhomogeneous expansions, and that only a non-generic subclass of solutions of the conformal constraint equations is free of logarithmic singularities. The purpose of this work is twofold. First, within the evolutionary framework of the constraint equations, we show that the existence of a well-defined Bondi mass brings the asymptotically hyperboloidal initial data sets into a subclass whose Cauchy development guaranteed to admit a smooth boundary, by virtue of the results of Andersson and Chru\'sciel. Second, by generalizing a recent result of Beyer and Ritchie, we show that the existence of well-defined Bondi mass and angular momentum, together with some mild restrictions on the free data, implies that the generic solutions of the parabolic-hyperbolic form of the constraint equations are completely free of logarithmic singularities. We also provide numerical evidence to show that in the vicinity of Kerr, asymptotically hyperboloidal initial data without logarithmic singularities can indeed be constructed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11804v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K\'aroly Csuk\'as, Istv\'an R\'acz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Isoperimetric Inequalities in Quantum Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16604v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We reveal strong and weak inequalities relating two fundamental macroscopic quantum geometric quantities, the quantum distance and Berry phase, for closed paths in the Hilbert space of wavefunctions. We recount the role of quantum geometry in various quantum problems and show that our findings place new bounds on important physical quantities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16604v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Praveen Pai, Fan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotics for resolutions and smoothings of Calabi-Yau conifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16702</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16702v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that the Calabi--Yau metrics with isolated conical singularities of Hein--Sun admit polyhomogeneous expansions near their singularities. Moreover, we show that, under certain generic assumptions, natural families of smooth Calabi--Yau metrics on crepant resolutions and on polarized smoothings of conical Calabi--Yau manifolds degenerating to the initial conical Calabi--Yau metric admit polyhomogeneous expansions where the singularities are forming. The construction proceeds by performing weighted Melrose--type blow--ups and then gluing conical and scaled asymptotically conical Calabi--Yau metrics on the fibers, close to the blow--up's front face without compromising polyhomogeneity. This yields a polyhomogeneous family of K\"ahler metrics that are approximately Calabi--Yau. Solving formally a complex Monge--Amp\`ere equation, we obtain a polyhomogeneous family of K\"ahler metrics with Ricci potential converging rapidly to zero as the family is degenerating. We can then conclude that the corresponding family of degenerating Calabi--Yau metrics is polyhomogeneous by using a fixed point argument.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16702v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdou Oussama Benabida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Partition function for position-dependent mass systems from superestatistics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16748v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we show a connection between superstatistics and position-dependent mass (PDM) systems in the context of the canonical ensemble. The key point is to set the fluctuation distribution of the inverse temperature in terms od the system PDM. For PDMs associated to Tsallis and Kaniadakis nonextensive statistics, the pressure and entropy of the ideal gas result lower than the standard case but maintaining monotonic behavior. Gas of non-interacting harmonic oscillators provided with quadratic and exponential PDMs exhibit a behavior of standard ED harmonic oscillator gas and a linear specific heat respectively, the latter being consistent with Nernst's third law of thermodynamics. Thus, a combined PDM-superstatistics scenario offers an alternative way to study the effects of the inhomogeneities of PDM systems in their thermodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16748v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ignacio S. Gomez, Matheus Gabriel Alves Santos, Daniela de Almeida dos Santos, Ronaldo Thibes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An asymptotic systems approach for the good-bad-ugly model with application to general relativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17036</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17036v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We employ an adapted version of H\"ormander's asymptotic systems method to show heuristically that the standard good-bad-ugly model admits formal polyhomogeneous asymptotic solutions near null infinity. In a related earlier approach, our heuristics were unable to capture potential leading order logarithmic terms appearing in the asymptotic solution of the good equation (the standard wave equation). Presently, we work with an improved method which overcomes this shortcoming, allowing the faithful treatment of a larger class of initial data in which such logarithmic terms are manifest. We then generalize this method to encompass models that include stratified null forms as sources and whose wave operators are built from an asymptotically flat metric. We then apply this result to the Einstein field equations in generalized harmonic gauge and compute the leading decay in~$R^{-1}$ of the Weyl scalars, where~$R$ is a suitably defined radial coordinate. We detect an obstruction to peeling, a decay statement on the Weyl scalars~$\Psi_n$ that is ensured by smoothness of null infinity. The leading order obstruction appears in~$\Psi_2$ and, in agreement with the literature, can only be suppressed by a careful choice of initial</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17036v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Duarte, Justin C. Feng, Edgar Gasper\'in, David Hilditch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multifractal formalism of Lyapunov exponents for fiber-bunched linear cocycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17045v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a higher-dimensional extension of multifractal analysis for typical fiber-bunched linear cocycles. Our main result is a relative variational principle, which shows that the topological entropy of the level sets of Lyapunov exponents can be approximated by the metric entropy of ergodic measures fully concentrated on those level sets, addressing a question posed by Breuillard and Sert. We also establish a variational principle for the generalized singular value function. As an application to dynamically defined linear cocycles, we obtain a multifractal formalism for open sets of $C^{1+\alpha}$ repellers and Anosov diffeomorphisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17045v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Reza Mohammadpour, Paulo Varandas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ubiquitous order known as chaos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17157</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17157v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A close relation has recently emerged between two of the most fundamental concepts in physics and mathematics: chaos and supersymmetry. In striking contrast to the semantics of the word 'chaos,' the true physical essence of this phenomenon now appears to be a spontaneous order associated with the breakdown of the topological supersymmetry (TS) hidden in all stochastic (partial) differential equations, i.e., in all systems from a broad domain ranging from cosmology to nanoscience. Among the low-hanging fruits of this new perspective, which can be called the supersymmetric theory of stochastic dynamics (STS), are theoretical explanations of 1/f noise and self-organized criticality. Central to STS is the physical meaning of TS breaking order parameter (OP). In this paper, we discuss that the OP is a field-theoretic embodiment of the 'butterfly effect' (BE) -- the infinitely long dynamical memory that is definitive of chaos. We stress that the formulation of the corresponding effective theory for the OP would mark the inception of the first consistent physical theory of the BE. Such a theory, potentially a valuable tool in solving chaos-related problems, would parallel the well-established and successful field theoretic descriptions of superconductivity, ferromagentism and other known orders arising from the spontaneous breakdown of various symmetries of nature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17157v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.chaos.2024.114611</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chaos, Solitons and Fractals 181 (2024) 114611</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Igor V. Ovchinnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite-dimensional genetic and evolution algebras generated by Gibbs measures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.06450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.06450v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Genetic and evolution algebras arise naturally from applied probability and stochastic processes. Gibbs measures describe interacting systems commonly studied in thermodynamics and statistical mechanics with applications in several fields. Here, we consider that the algebras are determined by configurations of finite spins on a countable set with their associated Gibbs distributions. The model preserves properties of the finite-dimensional Gibbs algebras found in the literature and extend their results. We introduce infertility in the genetic dynamics when the configurations differ macroscopically. It induces a decomposition of the algebra into a direct sum of fertile ideals with genetic realization.
  The proposed infinite-dimensional algebras are commutative, non-associative, with uncountable basis and zero divisors. The properties of Gibbs measures allow us to deal with the difficulties arising from the algebraic structure and obtain the results presented in this article.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.06450v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristian F. Coletti, Lucas R. de Lima, Denis A. Luiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An algebraic correspondence between stochastic differential equations and the Martin-Siggia-Rose formalism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.10579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.10579v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the realm of complex systems, dynamics is often modeled in terms of a non-linear, stochastic, ordinary differential equation (SDE) with either an additive or a multiplicative Gaussian white noise. In addition to a well-established collection of results proving existence and uniqueness of the solutions, it is of particular relevance the explicit computation of expectation values and correlation functions, since they encode the key physical information of the system under investigation. A pragmatically efficient way to dig out these quantities consists of the Martin-Siggia-Rose (MSR) formalism which establishes a correspondence between a large class of SDEs and suitably constructed field theories formulated by means of a path integral approach. Despite the effectiveness of this duality, there is no corresponding, mathematically rigorous proof of such correspondence. We address this issue using techniques proper of the algebraic approach to quantum field theories which is known to provide a valuable framework to discuss rigorously the path integral formulation of field theories as well as the solution theory both of ordinary and of partial, stochastic differential equations. In particular, working in this framework, we establish rigorously, albeit at the level of perturbation theory, a correspondence between correlation functions and expectation values computed either in the SDE or in the MSR formalism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.10579v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto Bonicelli, Claudio Dappiaggi, Nicol\`o Drago</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algebraic structures and Hamiltonians from the equivalence classes of 2D conformal algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.11030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.11030v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The construction of superintegrable systems based on Lie algebras and their universal enveloping algebras has been widely studied over the past decades. However, most constructions rely on explicit differential operator realisations and Marsden-Weinstein reductions. In this paper, we develop an algebraic approach based on the subalgebras of the 2D conformal algebra $\mathfrak{c}(2)$. This allows us to classify the centralisers of the enveloping algebra of the conformal algebra and construct the corresponding Hamiltonians with integrals in algebraic form. It is found that the symmetry algebras underlying these algebraic Hamiltonians are six-dimensional quadratic algebras. The Berezin brackets and commutation relations of the quadratic algebraic structures are closed without relying on explicit realisations or representations. We also give the Casimir invariants of the symmetry algebras. Our approach provides algebraic perspectives for the recent work by Fordy and Huang on the construction of superintegrable systems in the Darboux spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.11030v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Marquette, Junze Zhang, Yao-Zhong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polar form of Dirac fields: implementing symmetries via Lie derivative</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.10678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.10678v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the Lie derivative along Killing vector fields of the Dirac relativistic spinors: by using the polar decomposition we acquire the mean to study the implementation of symmetries on Dirac fields. Specifically, we will become able to examine under what conditions it is equivalent to impose a symmetry upon a spinor or only upon its observables. For one physical application, we discuss the role of the above analysis for the specific spherical symmetry, obtaining some no-go theorem regarding spinors and discussing the generality of our approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.10678v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11005-024-01770-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Lett. Math. Phys. 114, 21 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Luca Fabbri, Stefano Vignolo, Roberto Cianci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A von Neumann algebraic approach to Quantum Theory on curved spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14107</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14107v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: By extending the method developed in our recent paper \cite{LM} we present the AQFT framework in terms of von Neumann algebras. In particular, this approach allows for a categorical description of AQFT as well as providing a natural and intrinsic framework for a description of entanglement. Turning to dynamical aspects of QFT we show that Killing local flows may be lifted to the algebraic setting in curved space-time. Furthermore, conditions under which quantum Lie derivatives of such local flows exist are provided. The central question that then emerges is how such quantum local flows might be described in interesting representations. We show that quasi-free representations of Weyl algebra fit the presented framework perfectly. Finally, the problem of enlarging the set of observables is discussed. We point out the usefulness of Orlicz space techniques to encompass unbounded field operators. In particular, a well-defined framework within which one can manipulate such operators is necessary for the correct presentation of (semiclassical) Einstein's equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14107v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis E Labuschagne, W Adam Majewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low energy resolvent expansions in dimension two</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.13446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.13446v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The behavior of the resolvent at low energies has implications for many kinds of asymptotics, including for the scattering matrix and phase, for the Dirichlet-to-Neumann map, and for wave evolution. In this paper we present a robust method, based in part on resolvent identity arguments following Vodev and boundary pairing arguments following Melrose, for deriving such expansions, and implement it in detail for compactly supported perturbations of the Laplacian on $\mathbb R^2$. We obtain precise results for general self-adjoint black box perturbations, in the sense of Sj\"ostrand--Zworski, and also for some non-self-adjoint ones. The most important terms are the most singular ones, and we compute them in detail, relating them to spaces of zero eigenvalues and resonances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.13446v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. J. Christiansen, K. Datchev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A multiscale cavity method for sublinear-rank symmetric matrix factorization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07189v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a statistical model for symmetric matrix factorization with additive Gaussian noise in the high-dimensional regime where the rank $M$ of the signal matrix to infer scales with its size $N$ as $M={\rm o}(\sqrt{\ln N})$. Allowing for an $N$-dependent rank offers new challenges and requires new methods. Working in the Bayes-optimal setting, we show that whenever the signal has i.i.d.~entries, the limiting mutual information between signal and data is given by a variational formula involving a rank-one replica symmetric potential. In other words, from the information-theoretic perspective, the case of a (slowly) growing rank is the same as when $M=1$ (namely, the standard spiked Wigner model). The proof is primarily based on a novel multiscale cavity method allowing for growing rank along with some information-theoretic identities on worst noise for the vector Gaussian channel. We believe that the cavity method developed here will play a role in the analysis of a broader class of inference and spin models where the degrees of freedom are large arrays instead of vectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07189v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean Barbier, Justin Ko, Anas A. Rahman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear steepest descent on a torus: A case study of the Landau-Lifshitz equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.17662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.17662v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We obtain rigorous large time asymptotics for the Landau-Lifshitz equation in the soliton free case by extending the nonlinear steepest descent method to genus 1 surfaces. The methods presented in this paper pave the way to a rigorous analysis of other integrable equations on the torus and enable asymptotic analysis on different regimes of the Landau-Lifshitz equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.17662v4</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harini Desiraju, Alexander R. Its, Andrei Prokhorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poincare gauge gravity from nonmetric gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13867v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider general linear gauge theory, with independent solder form and connection. These spaces have both torsion and nonmetricity. We show that the Cartan structure equations together with the defining equation for nonmetricity allow the mixed symmetry components of nonmetricity to be absorbed into an altered torsion tensor. Field redefinitions reduce the structure equations to those of Poincare gauge theory, with local Lorentz symmetry and metric compatibility. In order to allow recovery the original torsion and nonmetric fields, we replace the definition of nonmetricity by an additional structure equation and demand integrability of the extended system. We show that the maximal Lie algebra compatible with the enlarged set is isomorphic to the conformal Lie algebra. From this Lorentzian conformal geometry, we establish that the difference between the field strength of special conformal transformations and the torsion and is given by the mixed symmetry nonmetricity of an equivalent asymmetric system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13867v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2025.116860.</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nuclear Physics B, Volume 1014, 2025, 116860, ISSN 0550-3213</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>James T. Wheeler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T-duality on Almost Hermitian Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.19931v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate T-duality transformation on an almost bi-hermitian space with torsion. By virtue of the Buscher rule, we completely describe not only the covariant derivative of geometrical objects but also the Nijenhuis tensor. We apply this description to an almost bi-hermitian space with isometry and investigate integrability on its T-dualized one. We find that hermiticity is not a sufficient condition to preserve integrability under T-duality transformations. However, in the presence of the K\"{a}hler condition, the T-dualized space still admits integrability of the almost complex structures. We also observe that the form of H-flux is suitable for string compactification scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.19931v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysb.2025.116870</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nucl.Phys.B 1014 (2025) 116870</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tetsuji Kimura, Shin Sasaki, Kenta Shiozawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poincare field theory for massless particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12969v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Our main proposition is that field equations for all spins can be obtained from Casimir eigenvalue equations for Poincare group. We have already confirm that statement for massive scalar, spinor and vector fields in Ref.[1]. In the present article we are going to confirm this statement for massless vector, second and fourth rang tensor fields. In particular we will obtain Maxwell equations and Einstein equation in weak field approximation.
  As is well known, Wigner define a particles as irreducible representation of Poincare group [2,3]. But, as Weinberg noted in [4] irreducible representations for massless vector field with helicities $\pm 1$ do not exist. In the present article we will conform this statement for a wide class of massless fields. They are not Lorentz invariant since their Lorentz transformations have additional term in the form of gauge transformations. Such fields can appear in the theory only in the form which do not depend on corresponding gauge parameters. These forms are our equations of motion and they are by definition gauge invariant. So, the massless case is significantly different from massive one. In the end we will show that our approach can reproduce main contributions from well known articles with highest helicity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12969v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Sazdovi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Counting Equilibria of the Electrostatic Potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05315v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In 1873, James C. Maxwell conjectured that the electric field generated by $n$ point charges in generic position has at most $(n-1)^2$ isolated zeroes. The first (non-optimal) upper bound was only obtained in 2007 by Gabrielov, Novikov and Shapiro, who also posed two additional interesting conjectures.
  In this article, we give the best upper bound known to date on the number of zeroes of the electric field, and construct a counterexample to a conjecture of Gabrielov, Novikov and Shapiro that the number of equilibria cannot exceed those of the distance function defined by the unit point charges.
  Finally, we note that it is quite possible that Maxwell's quadratic upper bound is not tight, so it is prudent to find smaller bounds. Hence, we also explore examples and construct configurations of charges achieving the highest ratios of the number of electric field zeroes by point charges found to this day.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05315v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Herbert Edelsbrunner, Christopher Fillmore, Gon\c{c}alo Oliveira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-Local Black Hole Horizons: Recent Advances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.11825</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.11825v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: While the early literature on black holes focused on event horizons, subsequently it was realized that their teleological nature makes them unsuitable for many physical applications both in classical and quantum gravity. Therefore, over the past two decades, event horizons have been steadily replaced by quasi-local horizons which do not suffer from teleology. In numerical simulations event horizons can be located as an `after thought' only after the entire space-time has been constructed. By contrast, quasi-local horizons naturally emerge in the course of these simulations, providing powerful gauge-invariant tools to extract physics from the numerical outputs. They also lead to interesting results in mathematical GR, providing unforeseen insights. For example, for event horizons we only have a qualitative result that their area cannot decrease, while for quasi-local horizons the increase in the area during a dynamical phase is quantitatively related to local physical processes at the horizon. In binary black hole mergers, there are interesting correlations between observables associated with quasi-local horizons and those defined at future null infinity. Finally, the quantum Hawking process is naturally described as formation and evaporation of a quasi-local horizon. This review focuses on the dynamical aspects of quasi-local horizons in classical general relativity, emphasizing recent results and ongoing research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.11825v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhay Ashtekar, Badri Krishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
