<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP</link>
    <description>math.MP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 01:48:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Moser Regularization of a Stochastically Perturbed Kepler Problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14442v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a stochastic Kepler problem perturbed by a Hamiltonian noise affecting the angular momentum vector. We show that the angular momentum and the Laplace-Runge-Lenz vectors are conserved in magnitude and as a consequence, the distance and speed of the particle follow deterministic dynamics. Further, in a procedure similar to Moser's regularization, we transform the stochastic Kepler problem to obtain its dynamics as a stochastic geodesic flow on a 3-sphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14442v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Archishman Saha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lie modules analysis of hydrodynamic-type systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14756v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The objective of this paper is to study nonlinear superpositions of Riemann wave solutions admitted by quasilinear hyperbolic first-order systems of partial differential equations. Particular attention is devoted to the analysis of non-elastic wave superpositions that cannot be decomposed into pairwise independent interactions of waves (quasi-rectifiability). In the case of the compressible Euler system, we describe the structure of the infinite-dimensional Lie algebra of vector fields associated with waves. We prove that a certain class of Lie modules associated with a hydrodynamic-type systems can be uniquely transformed into a real Lie algebra in an angle-preserving manner. For the Euler system, we then demonstrate the connection between the transformed finite-dimensional Lie algebra and the infinite-dimensional algebra associated with waves. This enables a detailed investigation of the geometry of wave superpositions using tools from differential geometry and Lie group theory. In particular, we study the geometry of the manifold of wave superpositions in terms of deformations of submanifolds corresponding to Lie subalgebras associated with waves. Additionally, we present new methods and criteria for determining the quasi-rectifiability of Riemann k-waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14756v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>{\L}ukasz Chomienia, Alfred Michel Grundland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Categorifying Clifford QCA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14811</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14811v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide a complete classification of Clifford quantum cellular automata (QCAs) on arbitrary metric spaces and any qudits (of prime or composite dimensions) in terms of algebraic L-theory. Building on the delooping formalism of Pedersen and Weibel, we reinterpret Clifford QCAs as symmetric formations in a filtered additive category constructed from the geometry of the underlying space. This perspective allows us to identify the group of stabilized Clifford QCAs, modulo circuits and separated automorphisms, with the Witt group of the corresponding Pedersen--Weibel category. For Euclidean lattices, the classification reproduces and expands upon known results, while for more general spaces -- including open cones over finite simplicial complexes -- we relate nontrivial QCAs to generalized homology theories with coefficients in the L-theory spectrum. We also outline extensions to QCAs with symmetry and mixed qudit dimensions, and discuss how these fit naturally into the L-theoretic framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14811v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bowen Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Curves in the Context of Symplectic Duality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14924v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss how to use the recent progress in understanding of the $x$-$y$ duality and symplectic duality in the theory of topological recursion and its generalizations in order to efficiently compute the quantum spectral curve operators for the wave functions with arbitrary base points. The paper also contains an overview of recent generalizations of the setup of topological recursion prompted by the progress in understanding the $x$-$y$ duality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14924v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Hock, Sergey Shadrin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Walker and para-Hermite Einstein spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15221v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A special class of (complex) para-Hermite Einstein spaces is analyzed. For this class of spaces the self-dual Weyl tensor is type-[D] in the Petrov-Penrose classification. The anti-self-dual Weyl tensor is algebraically degenerate, equivalently, there exists an anti-self-dual congruence of null strings. It is assumed that this congruence is parallely propagated. Thus, the spaces are not only para-Hermite but also Walker. A classification of the spaces according to three criteria is given. Finally, explicit metrics of all admitted Petrov-Penrose types are found.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15221v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Chudecki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ising Models with Hidden Markov Structure: Applications to Probabilistic Inference in Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13927</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13927v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate a Hamiltonian that incorporates Ising interactions between hidden $\pm 1$ spins, alongside a data-dependent term that couples the hidden and observed variables. Specifically, we explore translation-invariant Gibbs measures (TIGM) of this Hamiltonian on Cayley trees. 
  Under certain explicit conditions on the model's parameters, we demonstrate that there can be up to three distinct TIGMs. Each of these measures represents an equilibrium state of the spin system. These measures provide a structured approach to inference on hierarchical data in machine learning. They have practical applications in tasks such as denoising, weakly supervised learning, and anomaly detection. The Cayley tree structure is particularly advantageous for exact inference due to its tractability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13927v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Herrera, U. A. Rozikov, M. V. Velasco</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transport alpha divergences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14084v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We derive a class of divergences measuring the difference between probability density functions on a one-dimensional sample space. This divergence is a one-parameter variation of the Ito-Sauda divergence between quantile density functions. We prove that the proposed divergence is one-parameter variation of transport Kullback-Leibler divergence and Hessian distance of negative Boltzmann entropy with respect to Wasserstein-2 metric. From Taylor expansions, we also formulate the 3-symmetric tensor in Wasserstein space, which is given by an iterative Gamma three operators. The alpha-geodesic on Wasserstein space is also derived. From these properties, we name the proposed information measures transport alpha divergences. We provide several examples of transport alpha divergences for generative models in machine learning applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14084v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wuchen Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demonstration of the rotational viscosity transfer across scales in Navier-Stokes turbulence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14114v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Mechanical effects that span multiple physical scales -- such as the influence of vanishing molecular viscosity on large-scale flow structures under specific conditions -- play a critical role in real fluid systems. The spin angular momentum-conserving Navier--Stokes equations offer a theoretical framework for describing such multiscale fluid dynamics by decomposing total angular momentum into bulk and intrinsic spin components. However, this framework still assumes locally non-solid rotational flows, a condition that remains empirically unverified. This study addresses such unvalidated assumptions intrinsic to the model and extends it within the framework of turbulence hierarchy theory. The theory suggests that under certain conditions, small-scale structures may transfer to larger scales through the rotational viscosity. To verify this, we conducted spectral analyses of freely decaying two-dimensional turbulence initialized with a vortex-concentrated distribution. The results indicate that rotational viscosity exhibits interscale transfer behavior, revealing a new mechanism by which order can propagate from small to large scales in Navier--Stokes turbulence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14114v1</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Satori Tsuzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elliptic Virtual Structure Constants and Gromov-Witten Invariants for Complete Intersections in Weighted Projective Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14273v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we generalize our formalism of the elliptic virtual structure constants to hypersurfaces and complete intersections within certain weighted projective spaces possessing a single K\"{a}hler class.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14273v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masao Jinzenji (Okayama University), Ken Kuwata (National Institute of Technology, Kagawa College)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the wave turbulence theory of 2D gravity waves, II: propagation of randomness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14304</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14304v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This is the second part of our work initiating the rigorous study of wave turbulence for water waves equations. We combine energy estimates, normal forms, and probabilistic and combinatorial arguments to complete the construction of long-time solutions with random initial data for the 2d (1d interface) gravity water waves system on large tori.
  This is the first long-time regularity result for solutions of water waves systems with large energy (but small local energy), which is the correct setup for applications to wave turbulence. Such a result is only possible in the presence of randomness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14304v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Deng, Alexandru Ionescu, Fabio Pusateri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dichotomy theorem distinguishing non-integrability and the lowest-order Yang-Baxter equation for isotropic spin chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14315v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the integrability and non-integrability of isotropic spin chains with nearest-neighbor interaction with general spin $S$. We prove a dichotomy theorem that a single relation sharply separates two scenarios: (i) this system is non-integrable, or (ii) the lowest-order Yang-Baxter equation is satisfied. This result solves in the affirmative the Grabowski-Mathieu conjecture stating that a model is integrable only if this model has a 3-local conserved quantity. This theorem also serves as a complete classification of integrability and non-integrability for $S\leq 13.5$, suggesting that all the integrable models are in the scope of the Yang-Baxter equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14315v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoto Shiraishi, Mizuki Yamaguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolution Of Multiplicative Anomaly Of Zeta Regularization For Polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14563v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, the problem of multiplicative anomaly of zeta regularization is solved for polynomials. For a regularizable sequence $\Lambda$, we explicitly calculate the zeta regularized product of $(\Lambda-z_1)\dots(\Lambda-z_n)$ for $z_1,\dots,z_n\in\mathbb{C}$. We give an explicit formula for the discrepancies between polynomials. Our results imply Mizuno's theorem as a special case. We furthermore give novel regularized product formulas for multi-dimensional products in terms of Barnes multiple gamma functions, zeros of the Riemann zeta function and zeros of the Bessel function of the first kind.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14563v1</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Efe G\"urel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The ladder of Finsler-type objects and their variational problems on spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14710v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The space of anisotropic $r$-contravariant $s$-covariant $\alpha$-homogeneous tensors on a manifold admits a functorial structure where vertical derivatives $\dot{\partial}$ and contractions $\imath_{\mathbb{C}}$ by the Liouville vector field $\mathbb{C}$ are operators which maintain $s+\alpha$ constant. In (semi-)Finsler geometry, this structure is transmitted faithfully to connection-type elements yielding the following ladder: geodesic sprays / nonlinear connections / anisotropic connections / linear (Finslerian) connections. However, it is more loosely transmitted to metric-type ones: Finslerian Lagrangians / Legendre transformations / anisotropic metrics. We will study this structure in depth and apply it to discuss the recent variational proposals (Einstein-Hilbert, Einstein-Palatini, Einstein-Cartan) for generalizing Einstein equations to the Finsler setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14710v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel S\'anchez, Fidel F. Villase\~nor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Measurement Without Collapse or Many Worlds: The Branched Hilbert Subspace Interpretation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14791</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14791v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The interpretation of quantum measurements presents a fundamental challenge in quantum mechanics, with concepts such as the Copenhagen Interpretation (CI), Many-Worlds Interpretation (MWI), and Bohmian Mechanics (BM) offering distinct perspectives. We propose the Branched Hilbert Subspace Interpretation (BHSI), which describes measurement as branching the local Hilbert space of a system into parallel subspaces. We formalize the mathematical framework of BHSI using branching and the engaging and disengaging unitary operators to relationally and causally update the states of observers. Unlike the MWI, BHSI avoids the ontological proliferation of worlds and copies of observers, realizing the Born rule based on branch weights. Unlike the CI, BHSI retains the essential features of the MWI: unitary evolution and no wavefunction collapse. Unlike the BM, BHSI does not depend on a nonlocal structure, which may conflict with relativity. We apply BHSI to examples such as the double-slit experiment, the Bell test, Wagner and his friend, and the black hole information paradox. In addition, we explore whether recohering branches can be achieved in BHSI. Compared to the CI and MWI, BHSI provides a minimalist, unitarity-preserving, collapse-free, and probabilistically inherent alternative interpretation of quantum measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14791v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xing M. Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On tensor invariants of the Clebsch system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14867v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present some new Poisson bivectors that are invariants by the Clebsch system flow. Symplectic integrators on their symplectic leaves exactly preserve the corresponding Casimir functions, which have different physical meanings. The Kahan discretization of the Clebsch system is discussed briefly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14867v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Tsiganov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of pulsating swarmalators on a ring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14912v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a simple one-dimensional model of swarmalators, a generalization of phase oscillators that swarm around in space as well as synchronize internal oscillations in time. Previous studies of the model focused on Kuramoto-type couplings, where the phase interactions are governed by phase differences. Here we consider Winfree-type coupling, where the interactions are multiplicative, determined by the product of a phase response function $R(\theta)$ and phase pulse function $P(\theta)$. This more general interaction (from which the Kuramoto phase differences emerge after averaging) produces rich physics: six long-term modes of organization are found, which we characterize numerically and analytically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14912v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samali Ghosh, Kevin O'Keeffe, Gourab Kumar Sar, Dibakar Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On negative eigenvalues of 1D Schr\"{o}dinger operators with $\delta'$-like potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14934</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14934v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the asymptotic behavior of the discrete spectrum of one-dimensional Schr\"odinger operators with $\delta'$-like potentials, which are used to construct exactly solvable models for localized dipoles in quantum mechanics. Although these operators converge in the norm resolvent topology to a limiting operator that is bounded from below, we prove that they can possess a finite but arbitrarily large number of discrete eigenvalues that diverge to negative infinity as the regularization parameter tends to zero. This phenomenon illustrates a spectral instability of Schr\"odinger operators with these singular potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14934v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuriy Golovaty, Rostyslav Hryniv</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Hermitian Hopf insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.15154</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.15154v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hopf insulators represent a unique class of topological insulators that exist exclusively in two-band systems and are inherently unstable upon the inclusion of additional bands. Meanwhile, recent studies have shown that non-Hermiticity gives rise to distinctive complex-energy gap structures, known as point gaps, and associated topological phases with no analogs in Hermitian systems. However, non-Hermitian counterparts of Hopf insulators have remained largely elusive. Here, we generally classify topological phases of two-band non-Hermitian systems based on the homotopy theory and uncover Hopf-type point-gap topology present only for two bands. Specifically, we reveal such Hopf-type point-gap topology for three-dimensional systems with chiral symmetry (class AIII) and four-dimensional systems with no symmetry (class A). Explicitly constructing prototypical models from the Hermitian Hopf insulator, we further demonstrate that these non-Hermitian topological phases lead to anomalous point-gapless boundary states spectrally detachable from the bulk bands.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.15154v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daichi Nakamura, Kohei Kawabata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A network based approach for unbalanced optimal transport on surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21346v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we present a neural network approach to address the dynamic unbalanced optimal transport problem on surfaces with point cloud representation. For surfaces with point cloud representation, traditional method is difficult to apply due to the difficulty of mesh generating. Neural network is easy to implement even for complicate geometry. Moreover, instead of solving the original dynamic formulation, we consider the Hamiltonian flow approach, i.e. Karush-Kuhn-Tucker system. Based on this approach, we can exploit mathematical structure of the optimal transport to construct the neural network and the loss function can be simplified. Extensive numerical experiments are conducted for surfaces with different geometry. We also test the method for point cloud with noise, which shows stability of this method. This method is also easy to generalize to diverse range of problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21346v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiangong Pan, Wei Wan, Yuejin Zhang, Chenlong Bao, Zuoqiang Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The multiplicative constant in asymptotics of higher-order analogues of the Tracy-Widom distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12679v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we are concerned with higher-order analogues of the Tracy-Widom distribution, which describe the eigenvalue distributions in unitary random matrix models near critical edge points. The associated kernels are constructed by functions related to the even members of the Painlev\'{e} I hierarchy $\mathrm{P_{I}^{2k}}, k\in\mathbb{N}^{+}$, and are regarded as higher-order analogues of the Airy kernel. We present a novel approach to establish the multiplicative constant in the large gap asymptotics of the distribution, resolving an open problem in the work of Clayes, Its and Krasovsky. An important new feature of the expression is the involvement of an integral of the Hamiltonian associated with a special, real, pole-free solution for $\mathrm{P_{I}^{2k}}$. In addition, we show that the total integral of the Hamiltonian vanishes for all $k$, and establish a transition from the higher-order Tracy-Widom distribution to the classical one in the asymptotic regime. Our approach can also be adapted to calculate similar critical constants in other problems arising from mathematical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12679v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Dai, Wen-Gao Long, Shuai-Xia Xu, Lu-Ming Yao, Lun Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic Scattering Relation for the Toda Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.08018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.08018v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we consider the Toda lattice $(\boldsymbol{p}(t); \boldsymbol{q}(t))$ at thermal equilibrium, meaning that its variables $(p_i)$ and $(e^{q_i-q_{i+1}})$ are independent Gaussian and Gamma random variables, respectively. We justify the notion from the physics literature that this model can be thought of as a dense collection of ``quasiparticles'' that act as solitons by, (i) precisely defining the locations of these quasiparticles; (ii) showing that local charges and currents for the Toda lattice are well-approximated by simple functions of the quasiparticle data; and (iii) proving an asymptotic scattering relation that governs the dynamics of the quasiparticle locations. Our arguments are based on analyzing properties about eigenvector entries of the Toda lattice's (random) Lax matrix, particularly, their rates of exponential decay and their evolutions under inverse scattering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.08018v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amol Aggarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effective Velocities in the Toda Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.11407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.11407v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we consider the Toda lattice $(\boldsymbol{p}(t); \boldsymbol{q}(t))$ at thermal equilibrium, meaning that its variables $(p_i)$ and $(e^{q_i-q_{i+1}})$ are independent Gaussian and Gamma random variables, respectively. This model can be thought of a dense collection of many ``quasiparticles'' that act as solitons. We establish a law of large numbers for the trajectory of these quasiparticles, showing that they travel with approximately constant velocities, which are explicit. Our proof is based on a direct analysis of the asymptotic scattering relation, an equation (proven in previous work of the author) that approximately governs the dynamics of quasiparticles locations. This makes use of a regularization argument that essentially linearizes this relation, together with concentration estimates for the Toda lattice's (random) Lax matrix.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.11407v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amol Aggarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Beta function without UV divergences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.12483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.12483v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we construct the beta function in the functorial formulation of two-dimensional quantum field theories (FQFT). A key feature of this approach is the absence of ultraviolet divergences. We show that, nevertheless, in the FQFT perturbation theory, the local observables of deformed theories acquire logarithmic dimension, leading to a conformal anomaly. The beta function arises in the functorial approach as an infinitesimal transformation of the partition function under the variation of the metric's conformal factor, without ultraviolet divergences, UV cutoff, or the traditional renormalization procedure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.12483v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxim Gritskov, Andrey Losev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular modules for affine Lie algebras, and applications to irregular WZNW conformal blocks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.14793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2012.14793v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We give a mathematical definition of spaces of irregular vacua/covacua in genus zero, for any simple Lie algebra, working at generic noncritical level. This uses coinvariants of affine-Lie-algebra modules whose parameters match up with those of moduli spaces of irregular-singular meromorphic connections: the de Rham spaces. The Segal--Sugawara representation of the Virasoro algebra is used to show that the spaces of irregular conformal blocks assemble into a flat vector bundle over the space of somonodromy times \`a la Klar\`es, and we provide a universal version of the resulting flat connection generalising the irregular KZ connection of Reshetikhin and the dynamical KZ connection of Felder--Markov--Tarasov--Varchenko.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2012.14793v3</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00029-022-00821-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Selecta Mathematica (2023) 29:15</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Felder, Gabriele Rembado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smooth imploding solutions for 3D compressible fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.09445</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.09445v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Building upon the pioneering work [Merle, Rapha\"el, Rodnianski, and Szeftel, Ann. of Math., 196(2):567-778, 2022, Ann. of Math., 196(2):779-889, 2022, Invent. Math., 227(1):247-413, 2022] we construct exact, smooth self-similar imploding solutions to the 3D isentropic compressible Euler equations for ideal gases for all adiabatic exponents $\gamma&gt;1$. For the particular case $\gamma=\frac75$ (corresponding to a diatomic gas, e.g. oxygen, hydrogen, nitrogen), akin to the previous result, we show the existence of a sequence of smooth, self-similar imploding solutions. In addition, we provide simplified proofs of linear stability and non-linear stability, which allow us to construct asymptotically self-similar imploding solutions to the compressible Navier-Stokes equations with density independent viscosity for the case $\gamma=\frac75$. Moreover, the solutions constructed have density bounded away from zero and converge to a constant at infinity, representing the first example of singularity formation in such a setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.09445v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1017/fmp.2024.12</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Forum of Mathematics, Pi 13 (2025) e6</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tristan Buckmaster, Gonzalo Cao-Labora, Javier G\'omez-Serrano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuation Bounds for the Restricted Solid-on-Solid Model of Surface Growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.07160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.07160v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The restricted solid-on-solid (RSOS) model is a model of continuous-time surface growth characterized by the constraint that adjacent height differences are bounded by a fixed constant. Though the model is conjectured to belong to the KPZ universality class, mathematical progress on the model is very sparse. We study basic properties of the model and establish bounds on surface height fluctuations as a function of time. A linear fluctuation bound is proven for all dimensions, and a logarithmic fluctuation lower bound is given for dimension one. The proofs rely on a new characterization of RSOS as a type of first passage percolation on a disordered lattice, which is of independent interest. The logarithmic lower bound is established by showing equality in distribution to the minimum of a certain dual RSOS process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.07160v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Timothy Sudijono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics and Geometry of Entanglement in Many-Body Quantum Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.09784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.09784v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A new framework is formulated to study entanglement dynamics in many-body quantum systems along with an associated geometric description. In this formulation, called the Quantum Correlation Transfer Function (QCTF), the system's wave function or density matrix is transformed into a new space of complex functions with isolated singularities. Accordingly, entanglement dynamics is encoded in specific residues of the QCTF, and importantly, the explicit evaluation of the system's time dependence is avoided. Notably, the QCTF formulation allows for various algebraic simplifications and approximations to address the normally encountered complications due to the exponential growth of the many-body Hilbert space with the number of bodies. These simplifications are facilitated through considering the \textit{patterns}, in lieu of the elements, lying within the system's state. Consequently, a main finding of this paper is the exterior (Grassmannian) algebraic expression of many-body entanglement as the collective areas of regions in the Hilbert space spanned by pairs of projections of the wave function onto an arbitrary basis. This latter geometric measure is shown to be equivalent to the second-order R\'enyi entropy. Additionally, the geometric description of the QCTF shows that characterizing features of the reduced density matrix can be related to experimentally observable quantities. The QCTF-based geometric description offers the prospect of theoretically revealing aspects of many-body entanglement, by drawing on the vast scope of methods from geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.09784v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S0219887825501105</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Peyman Azodi, Herschel A Rabitz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-radial implosion for compressible Euler and Navier-Stokes in $\mathbb{T}^3$ and $\mathbb{R}^3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.05325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.05325v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we construct smooth, non-radial solutions of the compressible Euler and Navier-Stokes equation that develop an imploding finite time singularity. Our construction is motivated by the works [Merle, Rapha\"{e}l, Rodnianski, and Szeftel, Ann. of Math., 196(2):567-778, 2022, Ann. of Math., 196(2):779-889, 2022], [Buckmaster, Cao-Labora, and G\'{o}mez-Serrano, arXiv:2208.09445, 2022], but is flexible enough to handle both periodic and non-radial initial data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.05325v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gonzalo Cao-Labora, Javier G\'omez-Serrano, Jia Shi, Gigliola Staffilani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A comprehensive exploration of quasisymmetric stellarators and their coil sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.04826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.04826v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We augment the `QUAsi-symmetric Stellarator Repository' (QUASR) to include vacuum field stellarators with quasihelical symmetry using a globalized optimization workflow. The database now has almost 370,000 quasisaxisymmetry and quasihelically symmetric devices along with coil sets, optimized for a variety of aspect ratios, rotational transforms, and discrete rotational symmetries. This paper outlines a couple of ways to explore and characterize the data set. We plot devices on a near-axis quasisymmetry landscape, revealing close correspondence to this predicted landscape. We also use principal component analysis to reduce the dimensionality of the data so that it can easily be visualized in two or three dimensions. Principal component analysis also gives a mechanism to compare the new devices here to previously published ones in the literature. We are able to characterize the structure of the data, observe clusters, and visualize the progression of devices in these clusters. The topology of the data is governed by the interplay of the design constraints and valleys of the quasisymmetry objective. These techniques reveal that the data has structure, and that typically one, two or three principal components are sufficient to characterize it. The latest version of QUASR is archived at https://zenodo.org/doi/10.5281/zenodo.10050655 and can be explored online at quasr.flatironinstitute.org.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.04826v3</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Giuliani, Eduardo Rodr\'iguez, Marina Spivak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact WKB in all sectors I: Potentials with degenerate saddles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09511v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore the exact-WKB (EWKB) method through the analysis of Airy and Weber types, with an emphasis on the exact quantization of locally harmonic potentials in multiple sectors. The core innovation of our work lies in introducing a novel complexification approach to the energy parameter $u$, distinct from the common complexification of the (semi-classical) expansion parameter used in Borel summability. This new technique allows for continuous analytical continuation across different sectors of a potential while maintaining the exact quantization condition, even before median summation. By redefining the $A$-cycle above the potential barrier top, we ensure the quantization condition remains real and, by use of the Stokes automorphism and the median resummation, show that the resurgence structure is preserved across transitions between sectors. Furthermore, we discuss the Weber-type exact-WKB method, offering exact estimates for quantum actions around all types of saddle points, generalizing previous results. Through the analysis of these quantum actions, we reveal the presence of $S$-duality, facilitating the exchange between perturbative and non-perturbative behaviors, and we conjecture the mapping of the P-NP relations between dual theories. Our study encompasses periodic and symmetric double-well potentials, demonstrating that the exact-WKB method captures intricate structures in quantum systems in all sectors, including multi-instanton contributions and the resurgence of quantum actions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09511v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tatsuhiro Misumi, Cihan Pazarba\c{s}{\i}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tessellation codes: encoded quantum gates by geometric rotation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.18713</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.18713v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We utilize the symmetry groups of regular tessellations on two-dimensional surfaces of different constant curvatures, including spheres, Euclidean planes and hyperbolic planes, to encode a qubit or qudit into the physical degrees of freedom on these surfaces, which we call tessellation codes. We show that tessellation codes exhibit decent error correction properties by analysis via geometric considerations and the representation theory of the isometry groups on the corresponding surfaces. Interestingly, we demonstrate how this formalism enables the implementation of certain logical operations through geometric rotations of surfaces in real space, opening a new approach to logical quantum computation. We provide a variety of concrete constructions of such codes associated with different tessellations, which give rise to different logical groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.18713v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yixu Wang, Yijia Xu, Zi-Wen Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement witnesses and separability criteria based on generalized equiangular tight frames</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07065v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We use operators from generalized equiangular measurements to construct positive maps. Their positivity follows from the inequality for indices of coincidence corresponding to few equiangular tight frames. These maps give rise to entanglement witnesses, which include as special cases many important classes considered in the literature. Additionally, we introduce separability criteria based on the correlation matrix and analyze them for various types of measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07065v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katarzyna Siudzi\'nska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fisher Information in Kinetic Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00925v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: These notes review the theory of Fisher information, especially its use in kinetic theory of gases and plasmas. The recent monotonicity theorem by Guillen--Silvestre for the Landau--Coulomb equation is put in perspective and generalised. Following my joint work with Imbert and Silvestre, it is proven that Fisher information is decaying along the spatially homogeneous Boltzmann equation, for all relevant interactions, and from this the once longstanding problem of regularity estimates for very singular collision kernels (very soft potentials) is solved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00925v4</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C\'edric Villani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lusztig sheaves, characteristic cycles and the Borel-Moore homology of Nakajima's quiver varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12047v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By using characteristic cycles, we build a morphism from the canonical bases of integrable highest weight modules of quantum groups to the top Borel-Moore homology groups of Nakajima's quiver and tensor product varieties, and compare the canonical bases and the fundamental classes. As an application, we show that Nakajima's realization of irreducible highest weight modules and their tensor products can be defined over integers. We also give a new proof of Nakajima's conjecture on the canonical isomorphism of tensor product varieties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12047v3</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiepeng Fang, Yixin Lan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Riccati-type pseudo-potential approach to quasi-integrability of deformed soliton theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05890v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This review paper explores the Riccati-type pseudo-potential formulation applied to the quasi-integrable sine-Gordon, KdV, and NLS models. The proposed framework provides a unified methodology for analyzing quasi-integrability properties across various integrable systems, including deformations of the sine-Gordon, Bullough-Dodd, Toda, KdV, pKdV, NLS and SUSY sine-Gordon models. Key findings include the emergence of infinite towers of anomalous conservation laws within the Riccati-type approach and the identification of exact non-local conservation laws in the linear formulations of deformed models. As modified integrable models play a crucial role in diverse fields of nonlinear physics-such as Bose-Einstein condensation, superconductivity, gravity models, optics and soliton turbulence-these results may have far-reaching applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05890v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harold Blas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Schr\"odinger-Liouville and projective dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05532v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum dynamics provides the arguably most fundamental example of hybrid dynamics: As long as no measurement takes place, the system state is governed by the Schr\"odinger-Liouville differential equation, which is however interrupted and replaced by projective dynamics at times when measurements take place. We show how this alternatingly continuous and projective evolution can be cast in form of one single differential equation for a refined state space manifold and thus be made amenable to standard port-theoretic analysis and control techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05532v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kaja Krhac, Frederic P. Schuller, Stefano Stramigioli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Refined Vogel's universality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.13831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.13831v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In accordance with P. Vogel, a set of algebra structures in Chern-Simons theory can be made universal, independent of a particular family of simple Lie algebras. In particular, this means that various quantities in the adjoint representations of these simple Lie algebras such as dimensions and quantum dimensions, Racah coefficients, etc. are simple rational functions of two parameters on Vogel's plane, giving three lines associated with $sl$, $so/sp$ and exceptional algebras correspondingly. By analyzing the partition function of refined of Chern-Simons theory, it was suggested earlier that the refinement may preserve the universality for simply laced algebras. Here we support this conjecture by analysing the Macdonald dimensions, i.e. values of Macdonald polynomials at $q^\rho$, where $\rho$ is the Weyl vector: there is a universality formula that describes these dimensions for the simply laced algebras as a function on the Vogel's plane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.13831v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liudmila Bishler, Andrei Mironov</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
