<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP</link>
    <description>math.MP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 03:29:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The Vicsek-Kuramoto model in collective dynamics: macroscopic equations and pattern formation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we investigate an individual-based model (IBM) for self-propelled agents interacting locally on a plane. Agents are characterized by their position, the angle determining their direction of motion, and their angular velocity. The dynamics combine features of the well-known Vicsek and Kuramoto models, which describe collective dynamics and synchronization, respectively. The evolution of the directions of motion follows a Vicsek model, where agents align their orientations with the mean orientation of their neighbors, subject to some noise. Similarly, the angular velocities relax towards the average angular velocity of the neighboring agents, also subject to noise. From the IBM we derive the corresponding kinetic equation in the limit of a large number of agents and formally obtain the macroscopic equations through a macroscopic (hydrodynamic) limit. Numerical simulations of the IBM reveal a variety of patterns, including rotating clusters, traveling orientation waves, and globally synchronized rotational motion. A qualitative comparison with simulations of the macroscopic system show the ability of the macroscopic model to reproduce some emergent behavior of the IBM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17035v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara Merino-Aceituno, Carmela Moschella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the convergence of the Born series for Coulomb potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17104</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17104v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide a short proof of the convergence of the Born series on asymptotically conic manifolds, at sufficiently high energy. The potential is allowed to have multiple Coulomb singularities. This is handled using powerful semiclassical estimates recently proven by Hintz for the case of a single dipole (or better) singularity. The potential is also allowed to be long-range, like the actual Coulomb potential $1/r$; long-range potentials are handled using anisotropic semiclassical (sc-) Sobolev spaces. As a consequence of the above estimates, we show the existence of a resonance-free region for Hamiltonians with multiple screened Coulomb singularities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17104v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ethan Sussman, Jared Wunsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Asymptotic Approach for Modeling Multiscale Complex Fluids at the Fast Relaxation Limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17134v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a new asymptotic strategy for general micro-macro models which analyze complex viscoelastic fluids governed by coupled multiscale dynamics. In such models, the elastic stress appearing in the macroscopic continuum equation is derived from the microscopic kinetic theory, which makes direct numerical simulations computationally expensive. To address this challenge, we introduce a formal asymptotic scheme that expands the density function around an equilibrium distribution, thereby reducing the high computational cost associated with the fully coupled microscopic processes while still maintaining the dynamic microscopic feedback in explicit expressions. The proposed asymptotic expansion is based on a detailed physical scaling law which characterizes the multiscale balance at the fast relaxation limit of the microscopic state. An asymptotic closure model for the macroscopic fluid equation is then derived according to the explicit asymptotic density expansion. Furthermore, the resulting closure model preserves the energy-dissipation law inherited from the original fully coupled multiscale system. Numerical experiments are performed to validate the asymptotic density formula and the corresponding flow velocity equations in several micro-macro models. This new asymptotic strategy offers a promising approach for efficient computations of a wide range of multiscale complex fluids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17134v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuenan Li, Chun Liu, Di Qi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harmonic band theory: rigidity of non-zero degree harmonic maps from 2-torus to complex projective space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17150v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove the rigidity of isotropic harmonic maps from a 2-torus to a complex projective space, when they are constructed from holomorphic embeddings associated to complete linear systems. We also prove that this rigidity holds for any holomorphic embeddings without special hyperosculation points, with an extra assumption on the pullbacks of Fubini--Study symplectic forms. These results ensure the rigidity of towers of harmonic bands in condensed matter physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17150v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshinori Hashimoto, Bruno Mera, Tomoki Ozawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimates, asymptotics and trace formulas for periodic vector NLS equations, II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17272</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17272v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider a first order operator with a smooth periodic 3x3 matrix potential on the real line. It is the Lax operator for the periodic vector NLS equation. Its spectrum covers the real line and it is union of the spectral bands of multiplicity 3, separated by intervals (gaps) of multiplicity 1. We prove and describe the following:
  \\ $\cdot$ The geometry of the Riemann surface and its branch points. \\ $\cdot$ The asymptotics of branch points are determined and they are real at high energy. \\ $\cdot$ Trace formulas for integral of motions, including the Hamiltonian of the NLS equation. \\ $\cdot$ Estimates of the Hamiltonian in terms of gap lengths.
  The proof is based on the analysis of averaged quasi-momentum as a conformal mapping of the upper half plane on the domain on the upper half plane and on the asymptotics of the monodromy matrix and multipliers at high energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17272v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evgeny Korotyaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational Dissipative Mechanics on Lie Algebroids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We formulate a Herglotz-type variational principle on a Lie algebroid and derive the corresponding Euler--Lagrange--Herglotz equations for a Lagrangian depending on an additional scalar variable $z$. This provides a geometric framework for dissipative systems on Lie algebroids and recovers, as special cases, the classical Euler--Lagrange--Herglotz equations on tangent bundles, the Euler--Poincar\'e--Herglotz equations on a Lie algebra, and the Lagrange--Poincar\'e--Herglotz equations on Atiyah algebroids of principal bundles. Starting from the local formulation, we then use Lie algebroid connections to obtain a coordinate-free Euler--Lagrange--Poincar\'e--Herglotz and Hamilton--Pontryagin--Herglotz theory. Finally, we establish energy balance laws and Noether--Herglotz-type results, in which classical conserved quantities are replaced by dissipated invariants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17424v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandre Anahory Simoes, Leonardo Colombo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrable $\mathbb{Z}_2^2$-graded super-Liouville Equation and Induced $\mathbb{Z}_2^2$-graded super-Virasoro Algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17449v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a framework for enlarging the construction of $\mathbb{Z}_2^2$-graded classical Toda theory from the class of $\mathbb{Z}_2^2$-graded Lie algebras to the class of $\mathbb{Z}_2^2$-graded Lie superalgebras. This scheme is applied to derive a $\mathbb{Z}_2^2$-graded extension of the super-Liouville equation based on a $\mathbb{Z}_2^2$-graded extension of $\mathfrak{osp}(1|2).$ The mathematical tools employed in this work are a $\mathbb{Z}_2^2$-graded version of the zero-curvature formalism and of the Polyakov's soldering procedure. It is demonstrated that both methods yield the same $\mathbb{Z}_2^2$-graded super-Liouville equation. An algebraic construction of solutions to the resulting equations is also presented, together with their B\"acklund transformations. Furthermore, three distinct new $\mathbb{Z}_2^2$-graded extensions of the super-Virasoro algebra are obtained via Hamiltonian reduction of the WZNW currents defined for $\mathbb{Z}_2^2$-$\mathfrak{osp}(1|2).$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17449v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naruhiko Aizawa, Ichi Fujii, Ren Ito, Toshiya Tanaka, Francesco Toppan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On surface polariton resonance and its curvature concentration effects from 3D elastic nanorods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17513v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper investigates surface polariton resonance (SPR) in three-dimensional elastic metamaterials with nanorod geometry. The primary motivation is to surpass the physical limitations imposed by the quasi-static approximation for SPRs through anisotropic geometric design. The analysis boils down to analyzing the spectral properties of the matrix-valued elastic Neumann-Poincar\'e (NP) operator defined on the nanorod boundary. We develop novel analytical techniques and conduct a rigorous asymptotic analysis of elastic layer potential operators, specifically adapted for highly anisotropic structures. Within this framework, we derive precise asymptotic formulas for the scattered field in the quasi-static regime. A thorough examination of these expressions yields explicit resonance conditions that intricately link three fundamental parameters: elastic material parameters, wave frequency, and nanorod geometry. Furthermore, we characterize the intrinsic relationship between these parameters and the associated energy blow-up rate of the resonant field. This analysis explicitly establishes a sharp curvature concentration effect at the nanorod extremities, where field enhancement is locally maximized. Our work provides a rigorous theoretical foundation for harnessing elastic SPRs through anisotropic geometric engineering, with implications for sensing, wave focusing, and metamaterial applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17513v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Youjun Deng, Hongyu Liu, Wanjing Tang, Guang-Hui Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Les Houches Lectures on Exact WKB Analysis and Painlev\'e Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17599v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The first part of these lecture notes is devoted to an introduction to the theory of exact WKB analysis for second-order Schr\"odinger-type ordinary differential equations. It reviews the construction of the WKB solution, Borel summability, connection formulas, and their application to direct monodromy problems.
  In the second part, we discuss recent developments in applying exact WKB analysis to the study of Painlev\'e equations. By combining exact WKB analysis with topological recursion, it becomes possible to explicitly compute the monodromy of linear differential equations associated with Painlev\'e equations, assuming Borel summability and other conditions. Furthermore, by using isomonodromy deformations (integrability of the Painlev\'e equations), the resurgent structure of the $\tau$-function and partition function is analyzed.
  These lecture notes accompanied a series of lectures at the Les Houches school, ``Quantum Geometry (Mathematical Methods for Gravity, Gauge Theories and Non-Perturbative Physics)'' in Summer 2024.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17599v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kohei Iwaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbative Chern-Simons invariants from non-acyclic flat connections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17638v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give a short review of our construction of a higher-loop perturbative invariant of framed 3-manifolds, generalizing the perturbative Chern-Simons invariant of Witten-Axelrod-Singer, associated to an acyclic flat connection, to an invariant given by the integral of a certain "Chern-Simons volume form" over a smooth closed component of the moduli space of flat connections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17638v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavel Mnev, Konstantin Wernli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bundling of bipartite entanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16979v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate bipartite entanglement and prove that in constrained energy subspaces, the entanglement spectra of multiple bipartitions are the same across the whole subspace. We show that in quantum many-body systems the bipartite entanglement entropy is affected in such a way that it forms "bundles" under unitary time evolution. Leveraging the structure of the subspace, we present methods to verify whether the entanglement spectrum of two bipartitions is identical throughout the entire subspace. For the subspace defined by the parity embedding, we further provide an algorithm that can determine this in polynomial time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16979v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maike Drieb-Schoen, Florian Dreier, Wolfgang Lechner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double Yangian, Factorization, and qKZ-equation for Cotangent Lie Algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.16996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.16996v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we construct the dual $Y^*_\hbar(\mathfrak d)$ and double $DY_\hbar (\mathfrak d)$ of the Yangian $Y_\hbar (\mathfrak d)$ associated with a cotangent Lie algebra $\mathfrak d=T^*\mathfrak g$. We define a coherent factorization algebra version of the dual Yangian $Y_\hbar^*(\mathfrak d)^{\mathrm{co-op}}$ with opposite coproduct. Furthermore, we define a quantum vertex algebra structure on the quantum vacuum module $V_{\hbar,k}(\mathfrak d)$ of central extensions $\widehat{DY}_{\hbar,\ell} (\mathfrak d)$ of this double Yangian and show that its conformal blocks satisfy quantum KZ equations. We discuss examples of $\mathfrak d$ that arise from 3d $N=4$ gauge theories via the work of Costello-Gaiotto. These examples include Takiff Lie algebras $T^*\mathfrak g$, whose affine VOA is a large subalgebra of the chiral differential operator algebra of $G$, as well as the smallest type-A Lie superalgebra $\mathfrak{gl} (1|1)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.16996v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raschid Abedin, Wenjun Niu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Explicit Sixth Order Runge-Kutta Method for Simple Lawson Integration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17006v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Explicit Runge-Kutta schemes become impractical when a stiff linear operator is present in the dynamics. This failure mode is quite common in numerical simulations of fluids and plasmas. Lawson proposed Generalized Runge-Kutta Processes for stiff problems in 1967, in which the stiff linear operator is treated fully implicitly via matrix exponentiation. Any Runge-Kutta scheme induces valid Lawson integration, but a scheme is exceptionally simple to implement if the abscissa $c_i$ are ordered and equally spaced. Classical RK4 satisfies this requirement, but it is difficult to derive efficient higher order schemes with this constraint. Here I present an explicit sixth order method identified with Newton-Raphson iteration that provides simple Lawson integration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17006v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew Golden</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Continuum canonical purifications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17014v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct and characterize canonical purifications for general algebraic states, extending prior constructions by Woronowicz and by Dutta/Faulkner to general quantum field theories. Given a quantum state on a *-algebra, the canonical purification is a state on a "doubled" algebra that admits an interpretation in terms of CRT reflection. We study the conditions under which these enlarged states are "pure" in the technical sense, compute their modular conjugations, and relate them to GNS and natural-cone purifications in certain settings. In a forthcoming paper with Caminiti and Capeccia, we provide an application of this general theory to the problem of excitability in quantum field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17014v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Sorce</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subsystems (in)dependence in GIE proposals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17024</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17024v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent proposals suggest that detecting entanglement between two spatially superposed masses would establish the quantum nature of gravity. However, these gravitationally induced entanglement (GIE) experiments rely on assumptions about subsystem independence. We sharpen the theoretical underpinnings of such proposals by examining them through the lens of algebraic quantum field theory (AQFT), distinguishing distinct operational and algebraic notions of independence. We argue that state and measurement independence of subsystems, essential to the experimental logic, is nontrivial in the presence of gauge constraints and gravitational dressing. Using gravitationally dressed fields, we recall that commutation relations between spacelike separated observables are nontrivial, undermining strict Hilbert space factorization. We further explore the implications for entanglement witnesses, investigating the Tsirelson bound when subsystem algebras fail to commute, and showing that the Tsirelson bound persists for a suitably symmetrized CHSH observable even though the operational status of such "joint" observables becomes delicate when commensurability fails. Our analysis highlights how even within linearized covariant quantum gravity, violations of microcausality may affect both the interpretation, modelling, and design of proposed laboratory tests of quantum gravity, despite remaining negligible for current experimental regimes. Although we consider GIE-style protocols as a concrete case study, the subsystem-independence issues we highlight are generic to low-energy (perturbative) quantum gravity. Finally, we derive estimates for dressing-induced microcausality violations, which suggest a complementary avenue to current proposals: in principle, bounding dressing-induced microcausality violations themselves as a probe of the quantum nature of gravity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17024v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Boulle, Guilherme Franzmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absence of twisting for non-trivial discrete torsion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17068v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study discrete torsion for the $n$--torus with finite symmetry group $G$ from the Dijkgraaf--Witten viewpoint. A class in $H^n(G,U(1))$ assigns a phase to each flat $G$--bundle, equivalently to each commuting $n$--tuple in $G$ up to conjugation. We introduce the subgroup $\Br^n(G)\subseteq H^n(G,U(1))$ of \emph{untwisted} classes, those whose Dijkgraaf--Witten phases are trivial on all commuting tuples, and derive a universal coefficient exact sequence involving this invariant. In degree $2$ this recovers the Bogomolov multiplier / unramified Brauer group. We implement algorithms for computing $\Br^n(G)$ and corresponding torus partition functions, and report on computations for families of finite subgroups of $\SU(4)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17068v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Primoz Moravec</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the existence of solutions to the multi-species Landau equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17082v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider the spatially homogeneous Landau equation for multiple species with different masses. As in the single-species case, the singularity of the collision operator is determined by a parameter $\gamma \in [-3,1]$, where $\gamma = -3$ corresponds to Coulomb interactions. We prove that if $\gamma\geq -\sqrt{8}$ in the cross-interaction operators, then there exists a natural multi-species generalization of the Fisher information which is a Lyapunov functional for the multi-species Landau system. On the other hand, we give a counterexample showing that the Fisher information is in general no longer a Lyapunov functional below the threshold $(\gamma &lt; - \sqrt{8})$ for the two-species system if one species has infinite mass. However, we are able to provide a new method to show global well-posedness, by constructing a different Lyapunov functional based on the spherical Fisher information.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17082v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Junn\'e, Raphael Winter, Havva Yolda\c{s}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>fractional-time deformation of quantum coherence in open systems: a non-markovian framework beyond lindblad dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17144v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a fractional time extension of the Quan tum Master Equation. We introduce a Caputo-type fractional derivative in time as an extension of the exponential decay of the Lindblad framework through the incorporation of fractional derivatives into the Lindblad framework. We show that the analytical and numerical results of our analytical and numerical models, demonstrate that fractional dynamics produces long-memory coherence decay naturally and provides an interpretable and flexible model of non-Markovianity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17144v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taylan Demir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Voltage Ionized Gas with Spherical Cathode Emission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17159v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider a plasma that is created by a high voltage difference, which is known as a Townsend gas discharge. The plasma is confined to the region between two concentric spheres, one of which is a cathode and the other an anode. Ion-electron pairs are created by collisions inside the plasma. Additional electrons enter the plasma by collisions of ions with the cathode. We prove under certain conditions that there are many steady states exhibiting gas discharge, beginning with a `sparking' voltage. In fact, there is an analytic one-parameter family of them that connects the non-ionized gas to a plasma with arbitrarily high ionization or arbitrarily high potential, or else the family ends at an `anti-sparking' voltage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17159v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Walter A. Strauss, Masahiro Suzuki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MINPO: Memory-Informed Neural Pseudo-Operator to Resolve Nonlocal Spatiotemporal Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17273v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Many physical systems exhibit nonlocal spatiotemporal behaviors described by integro-differential equations (IDEs). Classical methods for solving IDEs require repeatedly evaluating convolution integrals, whose cost increases quickly with kernel complexity and dimensionality. Existing neural solvers can accelerate selected instances of these computations, yet they do not generalize across diverse nonlocal structures. In this work, we introduce the Memory-Informed Neural Pseudo-Operator (MINPO), a unified framework for modeling nonlocal dynamics arising from long-range spatial interactions and/or long-term temporal memory. MINPO, employing either Kolmogorov-Arnold Networks (KANs) or multilayer perceptron networks (MLPs) as encoders, learns the nonlocal operator and its inverse directly through neural representations, and then explicitly reconstruct the unknown solution fields. The learning is guarded by a lightweight nonlocal consistency loss term to enforce coherence between the learned operator and reconstructed solution. The MINPO formulation allows to naturally capture and efficiently resolve nonlocal spatiotemporal dependencies governed by a wide spectrum of IDEs and their subsets, including fractional PDEs. We evaluate the efficacy of MINPO in comparison with classical techniques and state-of-the-art neural-based strategies based on MLPs, such as A-PINN and fPINN, along with their newly-developed KAN variants, A-PIKAN and fPIKAN, designed to facilitate a fair comparison. Our study offers compelling evidence of the accuracy of MINPO and demonstrates its robustness in handling (i) diverse kernel types, (ii) different kernel dimensionalities, and (iii) the substantial computational demands arising from repeated evaluations of kernel integrals. MINPO, thus, generalizes beyond problem-specific formulations, providing a unified framework for systems governed by nonlocal operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17273v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Farinaz Mostajeran, Aruzhan Tleubek, Salah A Faroughi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin minimum uncertainty states for refined uncertainty relations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17307v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Minimum uncertainty states of the conventional Heisenberg uncertainty relation have been extensively studied and are often regarded as the most classical quantum states from the perspective of uncertainty, providing valuable insight into the nature of quantumness and its potential applications. In this work, we investigate the minimum uncertainty states associated with an information-theoretic refinement of the Heisenberg uncertainty relation in general spin systems. Using two different approaches, the matrix formulation and the Wick symbol representation, we derive explicit expressions for the states that saturate the uncertainty bound. We show that spin coherent states indeed achieve minimum uncertainty, consistent with their conventional identification as the classical states of spin systems. Moreover, we also identify additional classes of minimum uncertainty states beyond the coherent family. Finally, we compare the spin-system results with the previously studied bosonic case and elucidate the origin of the differences between the two settings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17307v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Dai, Yue Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Equality of the critical inverse temperatures for the one- and two-sided Dyson models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17451v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that the critical inverse temperatures $\beta_c^{\mathbb N}(\alpha)$ and $\beta_c^{\mathbb Z}(\alpha)$ for the one- and two-sided Dyson models are the same when the power of the interaction strength $\alpha$ satisfies $1&lt;\alpha&lt;2$. We conjecture that this is true also in the remaining case of $\alpha=2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17451v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Noam Berger, Anders Johansson, Anders \"Oberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Group-theoretical analysis of quantum complexity: the oscillator group case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17552</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17552v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by the recent rapid development of complexity theory applied to quantum mechanical processes we present the complete derivation of Nielsen's complexity of unitaries belonging to the representations of oscillator group. Our approach is based on the observation that the whole problem refers to the structure of the underlying group. The questions concerning the complexity of particular unitaries are solved by lifting the abstract structure to the operator level by considering the relevant unitary representation. For the class of right-invariant metrics obeying natural invariance condition we solve the geodesic equations on oscillator group. The solution is given explicitly in terms of elementary functions. Imposing the boundary conditions yield a transcendental equation and the length of the geodesic is given in terms of the solutions to the latter. Since the unitary irreducible representations of oscillator group are classified this allows us to compute, at least in principle, the complexity of any unitary operator belonging to the representation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17552v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Andrzejewski, K. Bolonek-Laso\'n, P. Kosi\'nski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>St\"ackel problem for non-diagonal Killing tensors: Yano-Patterson lifts, algebra of strong symmetries and quadratic in momenta integrals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17609v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct integrable Hamiltonian systems such that functionally independent Poisson commuting integrals are quadratic in the momenta. Unlike the classical St\"ackel setting, we allow the associated self-adjoint $(1,1)$-tensors $K_\alpha$ to be non-diagonalisable and have Jordan blocks and points where the Segre characteristic changes. Our construction is covariant and is based on Nijenhuis geometry: starting from a gl-regular Nijenhuis operator $L$ and its symmetry algebra, we obtain a large class of such integrable systems in a coordinate-free and signature-independent way; it is explicit once we have chosen a gl-regular Nijnhuis operator. In the diagonalisable case, our construction reproduces the St\"ackel construction, and in dimension $n=2$ it recovers all known systems of this type; for $n\ge 3$ most of our systems are new. Finally, we establish applications to infinite-dimensional integrable systems of hydrodynamic type: namely, we show that for Killing $(1,1)$-tensors $ K_\alpha$ corresponding to our example the evolutionarly PDE system of hydrodynamic type $u_t = K_\alpha(u)u_x$ is integrable. We describe its symmetries, and use generalised reciprocal transformations to reduce it to a system with constant coefficient matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17609v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexey V. Bolsinov, Andrey Yu. Konyaev, Vladimir S. Matveev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The threshold for quantum-classical correspondence is $D \sim \hbar^{\frac43}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17623</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17623v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In chaotic quantum systems, an initially localized quantum state can deviate strongly from the corresponding classical phase-space distribution after the Ehrenfest time $t_{\mathrm{E}} \sim \log(\hbar^{-1})$, even in the limit $\hbar \to 0$. Decoherence by the environment is often invoked to explain the persistence of the quantum-classical correspondence at longer timescales. Recent rigorous results for Lindblad dynamics with phase-space diffusion strength $D$ show that quantum and classical evolutions remain close for times that are exponentially longer than the Ehrenfest time whenever $D \gg \hbar^{\frac43}$, in units set by the classical Hamiltonian. At the same time, some heuristic arguments have suggested the weaker condition $D \gg \hbar^{2}$ always suffices. Here we construct an explicit Lindbladian that demonstrates that the scaling $D \sim \hbar^{\frac43}$ is indeed the threshold for quantum-classical correspondence beyond the Ehrenfest time. Our example uses a smooth time-dependent Hamiltonian and linear Lindblad operators generating homogeneous isotropic diffusion. It exhibits an $\hbar$-independent quantum-classical discrepancy at the Ehrenfest time whenever $D \ll \hbar^{\frac43}$, even for $\hbar$-independent "macroscopic" smooth observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17623v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felipe Hern\'andez, Daniel Ranard, C. Jess Riedel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of atmospheric traveling waves at cloud level</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17627v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We classify within the quasi-geostrophic framework all types of traveling waves in zonal bands of the planetary atmosphere at cloud level according to their wave speeds. This classification pertains to waves of all amplitudes, going beyond the small-amplitude perturbative regime. It provides a structurally robust criterion for determining which traveling-wave profiles are dynamically possible and we show that each wave classification type was observed on Jupiter or Saturn. Building on this classification, we also investigate the related rigidity issue for large-amplitude traveling waves and waves propagating near shear flows. Our study offers a unified quantitative characterization of the intrinsic constraints for traveling waves in the quasi-geostrophic regime of planetary atmospheric flow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17627v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Constantin, Zhiwu Lin, Hao Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prescribing the mean curvature of an achronal hypersurface as a measure: the case of 3D spacetimes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17670v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the existence problem for achronal hypersurfaces $M \hookrightarrow \overline{M}$ in a globally hyperbolic spacetime, whose mean curvature is a prescribed -- possibly singular -- source, and whose boundary is a given smooth spacelike submanifold. Since $M$ is allowed to go null somewhere, the mean curvature prescription is to be understood in the distributional sense. We prove a general existence and regularity theorem for surfaces in ambient dimension $3$. Although most of our estimates hold in any dimension, recent counterexamples show that some of our conclusions fail in ambient dimension at least $5$. The case of $4$D-spacetimes is an open problem. Our theorems have application to Born-Infeld electrostatics in general static spacetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17670v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Maniscalco, Luciano Mari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inclusion constants for free spectrahedra with applications to quantum incompatibility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17706v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Building on the matrix cube problem, inclusions of free spectrahedra have been used successfully to obtain relaxations of hard spectrahedral inclusion problems. The quality of such a relaxation is quantified by the inclusion constant associated with each free spectrahedron. While optimal values of inclusion constants were known in certain highly symmetric cases, no general method for computing them was available. In this work, we show that inclusion constants for Cartesian products of free simplices can be computed using methods from non-commutative polynomial optimization, together with a detailed analysis of the extreme points of the associated free spectrahedra. This analysis also yields new closed-form analytic expressions for these constants. As an application to quantum information theory, we prove new bounds on the amount of white noise that incompatible measurements can tolerate before they become compatible. In particular, we study the case of one dichotomic and one $k$-outcome measurement, as well as the case of four dichotomic qubit measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17706v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreas Bluhm, Eric Evert, Igor Klep, Victor Magron, Ion Nechita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Wasserstein distance for Gaussian states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17809v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Optimal transport between classical probability distributions has been proven useful in areas such as machine learning and random combinatorial optimization. Quantum optimal transport, and the quantum Wasserstein distance as the minimal cost associated with transforming one quantum state to another, is expected to have implications in quantum state discrimination and quantum metrology. In this work, following the formalism introduced in [De Palma, G. and Trevisan, D. Ann. Henri Poincar\'e, {\bf 22} (2021), 3199-3234] to compute the optimal transport plan between two quantum states, we give a general formula for the Wasserstein distance of order 2 between any two one-mode Gaussian states. We discuss how the Wasserstein distance between classical Gaussian distributions and the quantum Wasserstein distance by De Palma and Trevisan for thermal states can be recovered from our general formula for Gaussian states. This opens the path to directly compare various known distance measures with the Wasserstein distance through their closed-form solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17809v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anaelle Hertz, Mohammad Ahmadpoor, Oleksandr Dzhenzherov, Augusto Gerolin, Khabat Heshami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>van den Berg-Kesten--type correlation inequalities for disjoint polymers in the KPZ universality class</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17823v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In classical percolation theory, the van den Berg-Kesten (BK) inequality is a fundamental tool that shows that disjoint events induce negative conditionings on each other. The inequality also holds in the context of last passage percolation (LPP), which is the zero temperature limit of polymer models and an important subclass in the Kardar-Parisi-Zhang (KPZ) universality class. Recently, an analog of the BK inequality was discovered in the context of zero temperature line ensembles and the scaling limit of LPP, where it was used to study upper tail probabilities of the weight and the scaling limit of geodesics under such upper tail conditionings. However, while it has become apparent that such an inequality in the positive temperature setting would have a number of applications, it seems likely that a direct generalization of the zero temperature inequality would not hold. In this work we prove a version of the BK inequality for the KPZ line ensemble and the continuum directed random polymer. We do so by working with the log gamma polymer, making use of its integrability and the geometric RSK correspondence. Our inequality serves as a key input in analyzing the KPZ line ensemble and proving sharp upper tail estimates of the KPZ equation in arXiv:2208.08922, and proving convergence of the continuum directed random polymer to Brownian bridge under the upper tail event in arXiv:2311.12009. The crucial role of integrability in the validity of such an inequality is highlighted via a counter-example for a non-integrable model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17823v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shirshendu Ganguly, Milind Hegde, Lingfu Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Semi-Classical Limit from the Dirac Equation with Time-Dependent External Electromagnetic Field to Relativistic Vlasov Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17849v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove the mathematically rigorous (semi-)classical limit $\hbar \to 0$ of the Dirac equation with time-dependent external electromagnetic field to relativistic Vlasov equations with Lorentz force for electrons and positrons. In this limit antimatter and spin remain as intrinsically relativistic effects on a classical level. Our global-in-time results use Wigner transforms and a Lagrange multiplier viewpoint of the matrix-valued Wigner equation. In particular, we pass to the limit in the ''full" Wigner matrix equation without projecting on the eigenspaces of the matrix-valued symbol of the Dirac operator. In the limit, the Lagrange multiplier maintains the constraint that the Wigner measure and the symbol of the Dirac operator commute and vanishes when projected on the electron or positron eigenspace. This is a different approach to the problem as discussed in [P. G\'erard, P. Markowich, N.J. Mauser, F. Poupaud: Comm. Pure Appl. Math. 50(4):323--379, 1997], where the limit is taken in the projected Wigner equation. By explicit calculation of the remainder term in the expansion of the Moyal product we are able to generalize to time-dependent potentials with much less regularity. We use uniform $L^2$ bounds for the Wigner transform, which are only possible for a special class of mixed states as initial data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17849v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fran\c{c}ois Golse, Nikolai Leopold, Norbert J. Mauser, Jakob M\"oller, Chiara Saffirio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Conformal invariants for the zero mode equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17854v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For non-trivial solutions to the zero mode equation on a closed spin manifold \[D \varphi=iA\cdot \varphi,\] we first provide a simple proof for the sharp inequality \eq{ \norm{A}_{L^n}^2 \ge \frac {n}{4(n-1)} Y(M,[g]), } where $Y(M,[g])$ is the Yamabe constant of $(M,g)$, which was obtained by Frank-Loss and Reuss. Then we classify completely the equality case by proving that equality holds if and only if $\varphi$ is a Killing spinor, and if and only if $(M,g)$ is a Sasaki-Einstein manifold with $A$ (up to scaling) as its Reeb field and $\varphi$ a vacuum up to a conformal transformation. More generalizations have been also studied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17854v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guofang Wang, Mingwei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Matrix representation of Picard--Lefschetz--Pham theory near the real plane in $\mathbb{C}^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02481v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A matrix formalism is proposed for computations based on Picard--Lefschetz theory in a 2D case. The formalism is essentially equivalent to the computation of the intersection indices necessary for the Picard--Lefschetz formula and enables one to prove non-trivial topological identities for integrals depending on parameters.
  We introduce the universal Riemann domain $\tilde U$, i.e. a sort of ``compactification'' of the universal covering space $\tilde U_2$ over a small tubular neighborhood $N\mathbb{R}^2$ of $\mathbb{R}^2\backslash\sigma$ in $\mathbb{B}\subset\mathbb{C}^2$, where $\mathbb{B}\subset\mathbb{C}^2$ is a big ball, and $\sigma$ is a one-dimensional complex analytic set (the set of singularities). We compute the Picard-Lefschetz monodromy of the relative homology group of the space $\tilde U$ modulo the singularities and the boundary for the standard local degenerations of type $P_1 ,P_2,P_3$ in Pham's [1] notations and for more complicated configurations in $\mathbb{C}^2$. We consider this homology group as a module over the group ring of the $\pi_1((N\mathbb{R}^2 \cap \mathbb{B})\backslash\sigma)$ over $\mathbb{Z}$. The results of the computations are presented in the form of a matrix of the monodromy operator calculated in a certain natural basis. We prove an ``inflation'' theorem, which states that the integration surfaces of interest (i.e.\ the elements of the homology group $H_2(\tilde U_2,\tilde{\partial \mathbb{B}})$) (the surfaces in the branched space possibly passing through singularities) are injectively mapped to the group $H_2(\tilde U,\tilde U'\cup\tilde{\partial \mathbb{B}})$ (the surfaces avoiding the singularities). The matrix formalism obtained describes the behaviour of integrals depending on parameters and can be applied to the study of Wiener-Hopf method in two complex variables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02481v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Shanin, A. I. Korolkov, N. M. Artemov, R. C. Assier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multispecies inhomogeneous $t$-PushTASEP from antisymmetric fusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.00829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.00829v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate the recently introduced inhomogeneous $n$-species $t$-PushTASEP, a long-range stochastic process on a periodic lattice. A Baxter-type formula is established, expressing the Markov matrix as an alternating sum of commuting transfer matrices over all the fundamental representations of $U_t(\widehat{sl}_{n+1})$. This superposition acts as an inclusion-exclusion principle, selectively extracting the sequential particle transitions characteristic of the PushTASEP, while canceling forbidden channels. The homogeneous specialization connects the PushTASEP to ASEP, showing that the two models share eigenstates and a common integrability structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.00829v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1214/25-EJP1448</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Electron. J. Probab. 30: 1-28 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Arvind Ayyer, Atsuo Kuniba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lieb-Robinson bounds, automorphic equivalence and LPPL for long-range interacting fermions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.03319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.03319v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove a Lieb-Robinson bound for lattice fermion models with polynomially decaying interactions, which can be used to show the locality of the quasi-local inverse Liouvillian. This allows us to prove automorphic equivalence and the local perturbations perturb locally (LPPL) principle for these systems. The proof of the Lieb-Robinson bound is based on the work of Else et al. (2020), and our results also apply to spin systems. We explain why some newer Lieb-Robinson bounds for long-range spin systems cannot be used to prove the locality of the quasi-local inverse Liouvillian, and in some cases may not even hold for fermionic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.03319v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Teufel, Tom Wessel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new upper bound on the specific free energy of dilute Bose gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.20877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.20877v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove an upper bound for the free energy (per unit volume) of the dilute Bose gas in the thermodynamic limit, showing that the free energy at density $\rho$ and inverse temperature $\beta$ differs from that of the non-interacting system by the correction term $4 \pi \frak{a} (2 \rho^2 - [\rho - \rho_{\textsf{c}}(\beta)]^2_+ )$. Here, $\frak{a}$ denotes the scattering length of the interaction potential, $\rho_{\textsf{c}}(\beta)$ the critical density for Bose-Einstein condensation of the non-interacting gas and $[\cdot]_+=\max\{0,\cdot\}$. This result was previously established by Yin in [37]. Our proof applies to a broader class of interaction potentials, yields a better rate, and we believe it has potential for further extensions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.20877v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giulia Basti, Chiara Boccato, Serena Cenatiempo, Andreas Deuchert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Finsler geometry in anisotropic superconductivity: a Ginzburg-Landau approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19720v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a rigorous generalization of the classical Ginzburg--Landau model to smooth, compact Finsler manifolds without boundary. This framework provides a natural analytic setting for describing anisotropic superconductivity within Finsler geometry. The model is constructed via the Finsler--Laplacian, defined through the Legendre transform associated with the fundamental function F, and by employing canonical Finsler measures such as the Busemann--Hausdorff and Holmes--Thompson volume forms. We introduce an anisotropic Ginzburg--Landau functional for complex scalar fields coupled to gauge potentials and establish the existence of minimizers in the appropriate Finsler--Sobolev spaces by the direct method in the calculus of variations. Furthermore, we analyze the asymptotic regime as the Ginzburg--Landau parameter epsilon to 0 and prove a precise Gamma--convergence result: the rescaled energies converge to the Finslerian length functional associated with the limiting vortex filaments. In particular, the limiting vortex energy is shown to equal $\pi$ times the Finslerian length of the corresponding current, thereby extending the classical Bethuel--Brezis--He'lein result to anisotropic settings. These findings demonstrate that Finsler geometry unifies metric anisotropy and variational principles in gauge-field models, broadening the geometric scope of the Ginzburg--Landau theory beyond the Riemannian framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19720v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.46298/ocnmp.16773</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Open Communications in Nonlinear Mathematical Physics, Volume 5 (November 4, 2025) ocnmp:16773</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Y. Alipour Fakhri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Self Propelled Vortex Dipole Model on Surfaces of Variable Negative Curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.00923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.00923v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We investigate vortex dipoles on surfaces of variable negative curvature, focusing on a catenoid of arbitrary throat radius as a concrete example. We construct the effective dynamical system including mutual and geometric self-interaction terms and show that the resulting Hamiltonian dynamics makes dipoles follow catenoid geodesics, in agreement with recent works, Gustafsson (J. Nonlinear Sci. 32, 62, 2022) and by Drivas, Glukhovskiy and Khesin (Int. Math. Res. Not. 2024, 14, 10880-10894). We utilize the symplectic structure to find a conserved momentum map J related to the U(1) symmetry along the azimuthal direction. We verify the conservation of both the Hamiltonian and this momentum for arbitrary throat radius. We then demonstrate direct and exchange scattering of classical vortices on the catenoid, and we contrast this with the collective rotational motion (with azimuthal drift) that arises for chiral pairs. Finally, we build a finite-dipole dynamical system on the catenoid and show that the self-propulsion terms emerge to leading order in the dipole size. This provides a concrete realization, on a curved minimal surface, of the intuitive statement that a finite dipole propels orthogonal to the dipole axis, with a speed modulated by curvature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.00923v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khushi Banthia, Rickmoy Samanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>U(1) Gauge Potentials on de Sitter Spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1304.0568</link>
      <description>arXiv:1304.0568v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The smooth 1-form Verma module of $\mathfrak{so}(1,4)$ is acquired, which can be regarded as the U(1) gauge potential on de Sitter spacetime. It is shown that electromagnetic fields could not be source free on de Sitter background.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1304.0568v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bin Zhou, Shi-Bei Kong, Peng Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of quantum dynamics from chaos: The case of prequantum cat maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.02027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.02027v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Faure and Tsujii recently proposed a new quantization theory for symplectic Anosov diffeomorphisms. It combines prequantization with the study of the Pollicott--Ruelle resonances of an associated transfer operator. We apply this framework to the hyperbolic symplectic automorphisms of the $2n$-dimensional torus, the so-called cat maps. Our main result gives an explicit relation between the resonances of the prequantum transfer operator and the eigenvalues of the standard quantum cat maps, generalizing the case $n=1$ previously treated by Faure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.02027v3</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3934/dcds.2026016</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Javier Echevarr\'ia Cuesta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Langevin dynamics of lattice Yang-Mills-Higgs and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13299</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13299v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the Langevin dynamics of various lattice formulations of the Yang--Mills--Higgs model, with an inverse Yang--Mills coupling $\beta$ and a Higgs parameter $\kappa$. The Higgs component is either a bounded field taking values in a compact target space, or an unbounded field taking values in a vector space in which case the model also has a Higgs mass parameter $m$. We study the regime where $(\beta,\kappa)$ are small in the first case or $(\beta,\kappa/m)$ are small in the second case. We prove the exponential ergodicity of the dynamics on the whole lattice via functional inequalities. We establish exponential decay of correlations for a broad class of observables, namely, the infinite volume measure exhibits a strictly positive mass gap. Moreover, when the target space of the Higgs field is compact, appropriately rescaled observables exhibit factorized correlations in the large $N$ limit. These extend the earlier results \cite{SZZ22} on pure lattice Yang--Mills to the case with a coupled Higgs field.
  Unlike pure lattice Yang--Mills where the field is always bounded, in the case where the coupled Higgs component is unbounded, the control of its behavior is much harder and requires new techniques. Our approach involves a disintegration argument and a delicate analysis of correlations to effectively control the unbounded Higgs component.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13299v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Shen, Rongchan Zhu, Xiangchan Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fluctuation exponents of the half-space KPZ at stationarity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01653</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01653v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the half-space KPZ equation with a Neumann boundary condition, starting from stationary Brownian initial data. We derive a variance identity that links the fluctuations of the height function to the transversal fluctuations of a half-space polymer model. Utilizing this identity, we obtain estimates for the polymer endpoints, leading to optimal fluctuation exponents for the height function in both the subcritical and critical regimes, as well as an optimal upper bound for the fluctuation exponents in the extended critical regime. We also compute the average growth rate as a function of the boundary parameter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01653v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Gu, Ran Tao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A consistent treatment of dynamic contact angles in the sharp-interface framework with the generalized Navier boundary condition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10762v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we revisit the Generalized Navier Boundary condition (GNBC) introduced by Qian et al.\ in the sharp interface Volume-of-Fluid context. We replace the singular uncompensated Young stress by a smooth function with a characteristic width $\varepsilon &gt; 0$ that is understood as a physical parameter of the model. Therefore, we call the model the ``Contact Region GNBC'' (CR-GNBC). We show that the model is consistent with the fundamental kinematics of the contact angle transport described by Fricke, K\"ohne and Bothe. We implement the model in the geometrical Volume-of-Fluid solver Basilisk using a ``free angle'' approach. This means that the dynamic contact angle is not prescribed but reconstructed from the interface geometry and subsequently applied as an input parameter to compute the uncompensated Young stress. We couple this approach to the two-phase Navier Stokes solver and study the withdrawing tape problem with a receding contact line. It is shown that the model allows for grid-independent solutions and leads to a full regularization of the singularity at the moving contact line, which is in accordance with the thin-film equation subject to this boundary condition. In particular, it is shown that the curvature at the moving contact line is finite and mesh converging. As predicted by the fundamental kinematics, the parallel shear stress component vanishes at the moving contact line for quasi-stationary states (i.e. for $\dot{\theta}_d=0$) and the dynamic contact angle is determined by a balance between the uncompensated Young stress and an effective contact line friction. Furthermore, a non-linear generalization of the model is proposed, which aims at reproducing the Molecular Kinetic Theory of Blake and Haynes for quasi-stationary states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10762v3</guid>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomas Fullana, Yash Kulkarni, Mathis Fricke, St\'ephane Popinet, Shahriar Afkhami, Dieter Bothe, St\'ephane Zaleski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic robustness of entanglement in noisy quantum networks and graph connectivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12548v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum networks are promising venues for quantum information processing. This motivates the study of the entanglement properties of the particular multipartite quantum states that underpin these structures. In particular, it has been recently shown that when the links are noisy two drastically different behaviors can occur regarding the global entanglement properties of the network. While in certain configurations the network displays genuine multipartite entanglement (GME) for any system size provided the noise level is below a certain threshold, in others GME is washed out if the system size is big enough for any fixed non-zero level of noise. However, this difference has only been established considering the two extreme cases of maximally and minimally connected networks (i.e. complete graphs versus trees, respectively). In this article we investigate this question much more in depth and relate this behavior to the growth of several graph theoretic parameters that measure the connectivity of the graph sequence that codifies the structure of the network as the number of parties increases. The strongest conditions are obtained when considering the degree growth. Our main results are that a sufficiently fast degree growth (i.e. $\Omega(N)$, where $N$ is the size of the network) is sufficient for asymptotic robustness of GME, while if it is sufficiently slow (i.e. $o(\log N)$) then the network becomes asymptotically biseparable. We also present several explicit constructions related to the optimality of these results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12548v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Lled\'o, Carlos Palazuelos, Julio I. de Vicente</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scattering, Polyhomogeneity and Asymptotics for Quasilinear Wave Equations From Past to Future Null Infinity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09814v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a general construction of semiglobal scattering solutions to quasilinear wave equations in a neighbourhood of spacelike infinity including past and future null infinity, where the scattering data are posed on an ingoing null cone and along past null infinity. More precisely, we prove weighted, optimal-in-decay energy estimates and propagation of polyhomogeneity statements from past to future null infinity for these solutions, we provide an algorithmic procedure how to compute the precise coefficients in the arising polyhomogeneous expansions, and we apply this procedure to various examples. As a corollary, our results directly imply the summability in the spherical harmonic number $\ell$ of the estimates proved for fixed spherical harmonic modes in the papers [Keh22b,KM24] from the series "The Case Against Smooth Null Infinity".
  Our (physical space) methods are based on weighted energy estimates near spacelike infinity similar to those of [HV23], commutations with (modified) scaling vector fields to remove leading order terms in the relevant expansions, time inversions, as well as the Minkowskian conservation laws: $$
  \partial_u(r^{-2\ell}\partial_v(r^2\partial_v)^{\ell}(r\phi_{\ell}))=0, $$ which are satisfied if $\Box_\eta\phi=0$.
  Our scattering constructions apply to systems of equations as well and go beyond the usual class of finite energy solutions. We use this to also derive a scattering theory and prove propagation of polyhomogeneity for the Einstein vacuum equations in a harmonic gauge. In the process, we also need to introduce a novel ansatz accounting for the stronger-than-Schwarzschildean divergence of the light cones, which, in particular, extends existing exterior stability of Minkowski statements in harmonic gauge to allow for slowly decaying data as considered in [Bie10].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09814v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Istvan Kadar, Lionor Kehrberger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heat semigroups on quantum automorphism groups of finite dimensional C*-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.03448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.03448v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate heat semigroups on a quantum automorphism group ${\rm Aut}^+(B)$ of a finite dimensional C*-algebra $B$ and its Plancherel trace. We show ultracontractivity, hypercontractivity, and the spectral gap inequality of the heat semigroups on ${\rm Aut}^+(B)$. Furthermore, we obtain the sharpness of the Sobolev embedding property and the Hausdorff-Young inequality of ${\rm Aut}^+(B)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.03448v4</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Futaba Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bulk metric reconstruction from entanglement data via minimal surface area variations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.07016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.07016v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the reconstruction of asymptotically anti-de Sitter (AdS) bulk geometries from boundary entanglement entropy data for ball-shaped entangling regions. By deriving an explicit inversion formula, we relate variations in entanglement entropy to deviations of the bulk metric about a fixed background. Applying this formula, we recover the Schwarzschild-AdS spacetime in the low-temperature regime to first order. We further extend our analysis to include deformations of the bulk geometry with nontrivial dependence on boundary directions, and propose an iterative reconstruction scheme aimed at recovering the full spacetime starting close to a conformal fixed point. We do this by building on recent advances in the mathematics of inverse problems by introducing the higher-order linearization method as a new tool in the context of holographic bulk reconstruction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.07016v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 10 (2025) 079</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Niko Jokela, Tony Liimatainen, Miika Sarkkinen, Leo Tzou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cosmological dynamical systems of non-minimally coupled fluids and scalar fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14440v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the cosmological dynamics of non-minimally coupled matter models using the Brown's variational approach to relativistic fluids in General Relativity. After decomposing the Ricci scalar into a bulk and a boundary term, we construct new models by coupling the bulk term to the fluid variables and an external scalar field. Using dynamical systems techniques, we study models of this type and find that they can give rise to both early-time inflationary behaviour and late-time accelerated expansion. Moreover, these models also contain very interesting features that are rarely seen in this context. For example, we find dark energy models which exhibit phantom crossing in the recent past. Other possibilities include models that give a viable past evolution but terminate in a matter-dominated universe. The dynamical systems themselves display an array of mathematically interesting phenomena, including spirals, centres, and non-trivial bifurcations depending on the chosen parameter values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14440v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10714-025-03502-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>General Relativity and Gravitation 57 (2025) 167</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hala A. Ashi, Christian G. Boehmer, Antonio d'Alfonso del Sordo, Erik Jensko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Consistent energy-momentum trace couplings of fluids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24843v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Gravitational models with non-minimal couplings involving the trace of the energy-momentum tensor have become increasingly popular. The idea of coupling the trace of the matter tensor to the geometry can be applied to various matter models, including relativistic perfect fluids. However, it is well-known that the variational formulation of perfect fluids involves some technicalities. We carefully derive the field equations including the trace coupling of a perfect fluid using two different approaches, namely, that given by Brown using Lagrange multipliers, and that given by Schutz using velocity potentials. We show that previous results involving such trace couplings do not match the results presented here. We demonstrate that our fluid's equations of motion are consistent with the gravitational field equations. Moreover, we present a simple on-shell argument which further supports the correctness of our results.
  Our work implies that a vast amount of the $f(R,T)$ literature using perfect fluids needs to be revisited.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24843v2</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian G. Boehmer, Eissa Al-Nasrallah</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Limits on Quantum Correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24950v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum correlations are the singular, defining resource of quantum information science and metrology, forming the basis of every operational advantage that quantum systems hold over classical ones. Yet exact bounds on these correlations-such as the Lieb-Robinson bound on entanglement propagation and the Heisenberg limit on metrological precision-are known only in special cases and have long appeared to arise from unrelated mechanisms. Here we show that these limits share a common geometric origin. We identify a positivity invariant of the block correlation matrix, denoted $\chi$, that quantifies how far a bipartite state lies from the positivity boundary of quantum state space. For any system with a specified observable algebra and parameter-encoding map, every correlation measure determined solely by the positive correlation matrix obeys a $\chi$-dependent inequality. For systems with simple symmetry structures these inequalities take closed analytic form, reproducing the structure of the Heisenberg and Cram\'er-Rao limits and producing new results, including an exact entanglement floor and a universal Fisher-information ceiling even in all-to-all connected quantum networks. We thus demonstrate that positive geometry provides a unified framework for the attainable strength of quantum correlations, linking entanglement, metrological sensitivity, and dynamical causal structure through a single invariant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24950v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Alperin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral torsion of the internal noncommutative geometry of the Standard Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.08159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.08159v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We compute the nonvanishing spectral torsion functional of the internal part of the noncommutative geometry behind the Standard Model. We show that with a suitable modification of the usual differential graded calculus it matches an analogous functional constructed in terms of the connection. We study also the impact of the torsion on the other spectral fuctionals, which correspond to geometric invariants such as volume integral, metric and Einstein tensors, and scalar curvature. We discuss the impact of the SM Yukawa couplings and the Majorana mass matrix on our results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.08159v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ludwik D\k{a}browski, Sugato Mukhopadhyay, Filip Po\v{z}ar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variations of the Hardy Z-Function and the Montgomery Pair Correlation Conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.18275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.18275v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In 1973 Montgomery formulated the pair correlation conjecture, predicting that the local spacing statistics of the nontrivial zeros of the Riemann zeta function coincide with those of eigenvalues of large Hermitian matrices from the Gaussian Unitary Ensemble (GUE). The zeta function, however, is a fixed deterministic object, and the mechanism by which its zeros reproduce random matrix statistics has remained unclear. In this paper, assuming the Riemann Hypothesis, we prove Montgomery's pair correlation conjecture for the zeros of Hardy's $Z$-function. Building on earlier works, we use a finite-dimensional variational space of sections $Z_N(t;a)$ that approximate $Z(t)$ on each window $[2N,2N+2]$. Inside this space we define the real hall $\mathcal{RH}_N(\mathbb{R})$, consisting of those sections whose zeros in the corresponding critical rectangle are real, simple, and remain so along any homotopy from the core section. This real hall plays the role of a random matrix ensemble. Equipping it with an admissible probability measure with smooth, positive density on the coefficient space, we construct a Skorokhod-type stochastic differential equation with reflection at the discriminant boundary. We show that the induced dynamics of the unfolded zeros are, in the bulk, equivalent in law to Dyson Brownian motion with $\beta=2$, and by invoking modern universality results for Dyson Brownian motion and log-gases we obtain that, for any such measure, the ensemble-averaged local pair-correlation converges to the GUE sine-kernel law. Finally, using Selberg's probabilistic theory of the argument $S(t)$, we prove that the pair-correlation observables of the canonical approximants $Z_N(t;1)$ over disjoint windows behave asymptotically like decorrelated samples drawn from this GUE-distributed ensemble, and we upgrade the averaged GUE law to a deterministic pair-correlation law for the zeros of $Z(t)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.18275v2</guid>
      <category>math.NT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yochay Jerby</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intensity doubling for Brownian loop-soups in high dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21670v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We derive an intensity doubling feature of critical Brownian loop-soups on the cable-graphs of ${\mathbb Z}^d$ for $d \ge 7$ that can be described as follows: In the box $[-N, N]^d$ (and with a probability that goes to $1$ as $N$ goes to infinity), the set of all clusters of Brownian loops that do contain proper self-avoiding cycles of diameter comparable to $N$ can be decomposed into two identically distributed families: (a) The collection of clusters that do contain a large Brownian loop from the loop-soup (and therefore do automatically contain such a large cycle) (b) The collection of clusters that contain no macroscopic loop from the loop-soup (more specifically, no loop of diameter greater than $N^{\beta}$ when $\beta &gt; 4/ (d-2)$ is fixed) but nevertheless contain a large cycle. In particular, due to the fact that these two families are asymptotically identically distributed, large cycles formed in case (b) by chains of small Brownian loops (i.e., all of diameter much smaller than $N$) will look like large Brownian loops themselves, and form a second independent "ghost" critical loop-soup in the scaling limit. Reformulated in terms of the Gaussian free field on such cable-graphs, this shows that large cycles in the collection of its sign clusters will converge in the scaling limit to a Brownian loop-soup with twice the usual critical intensity. This result had been conjectured by the first author in arXiv:2209.07901 [math.PR] ; our proof builds heavily on the second author's switching property for such loop-soups from arXiv:2502.06754 [math.PR] .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21670v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Titus Lupu, Wendelin Werner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Mathematical Theory of Adaptive Memory: From Time-Varying to Responsive Fractional Brownian Motion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.10057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.10057v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work develops a comprehensive mathematical theory for a class of stochastic processes whose local regularity adapts dynamically in response to their own state. We first introduce and rigorously analyze a time-varying fractional Brownian motion (TV-fBm) with a deterministic, H\"older-continuous Hurst exponent function. Key properties are established, including its exact variance scaling law, precise local increment asymptotics, local non-determinism, large deviation asymptotics for its increments, and a covariance structure that admits a closed-form hypergeometric representation. We then define a novel class of processes termed Responsive Fractional Brownian Motion (RfBm). Here,the Hurst exponent is governed by a Lipschitz-H\"older response function depending on the process state itself, creating an intrinsic feedback mechanism between state and memory. We establish the well-posedness of this definition, prove pathwise H\"older regularity of the induced instantaneous scaling exponent, and analyze associated cumulative memory processes along with their asymptotic convergence. The mathematical structure of RfBm naturally gives rise to a continuous-time, pathwise attention mechanism. We show that its kernel induces a well-defined attention weight distribution, derive fundamental bounds for these weights, and quantify the stability of attentional allocation through residence measures and volatility functionals. This work develops a stochastic-process-theoretic framework for concepts central to adaptive memory and content-sensitive information processing, offering a mathematically grounded perspective that may complement existing empirical approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.10057v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiahao Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
