<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP</link>
    <description>math.MP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 04:01:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Oscillator Algebra in Complex Position-Dependent Mass Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09260</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09260v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work introduces non-Hermitian position-dependent mass Hamiltonians characterized by complex ladder operators and real, equidistant spectra. By imposing the Heisenberg-Weyl algebraic structure as a constraint, we derive the corresponding potentials, ladder operators, and eigenfunctions. The method provides a systematic procedure for constructing exactly solvable models for arbitrary mass profiles. Specific cases are illustrated for quadratic, cosenoidal, and exponential mass functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09260v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. I. Estrada-Delgado, Z. Blanco-Garcia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge states in square lattice media and their deformations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09352v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Edge states are time-harmonic solutions of conservative wave systems which are plane wave-like parallel to and localized transverse to an interface between two bulk media. We study a class of 2D edge Hamiltonians modeling a medium which slowly interpolates between periodic bulk media via a domain wall across a "rational" line defect. We consider the cases of (1) periodic bulk media having the symmetries of a square lattice, and (2) linear deformations of such media. Our bulk Hamiltonians break time-reversal symmetry due to perturbation by a magnetic term, which opens a band gap about the band structure degeneracies of the unperturbed bulk Hamiltonian. In case (1), these are quadratic band degeneracies; in case (2), they are pairs of conical degeneracies. We demonstrate that this band gap is traversed by two distinct edge state curves, consistent with the bulk-edge correspondence principle of topological physics. Blow-ups of these curves near the bulk band degeneracies are described by effective (homogenized) edge Hamiltonians derived via multiple-scale analysis which control the bifurcation of edge states. In case (1), the bifurcation is governed by a matrix Schr\"{o}dinger operator; in case (2), it is governed by a pair of Dirac operators. We present analytical results and numerical simulations for both the full 2D edge Hamiltonian spectral problem and the spectra of effective edge Hamiltonians.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09352v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonah Chaban, Jeremy L. Marzuola, Michael I. Weinstein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Complex Dimensions and Heat Content of Self-Similar Fractals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09512</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09512v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Complex fractal dimensions, defined as poles of appropriate fractal zeta functions, describe the geometric oscillations in fractal sets. In this work, we show that the same possible complex dimensions in the geometric setting also govern the asymptotics of the heat content on self-similar fractals.
  We consider the Dirichlet problem for the heat equation on bounded open regions whose boundaries are self-similar fractals. The class of self-similar domains we consider allow for non-disjoint overlap of the self-similar copies, provided some control over the separation. The possible complex dimensions, determined strictly by the similitudes that define the self-similar domain, control the scaling exponents of the asymptotic expansion for the heat content.
  We illustrate our method in the case of generalized von Koch snowflakes and in particular extend known results for these fractals with arithmetic scaling ratios to the generic (in the topological sense), non-arithmetic setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09512v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William E. Hoffer, Michel L. Lapidus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Joint Moments of Characteristic Polynomials from the Orthogonal and Unitary Symplectic Groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09910v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We establish asymptotic formulae for general joint moments of characteristic polynomials and their higher-order derivatives associated with matrices drawn randomly from the groups $\mathrm{USp}(2N)$ and $\mathrm{SO}(2N)$ in the limit as $N\to\infty$. This relates the leading-order asymptotic contribution in each case to averages over the Laguerre ensemble of random matrices. We uncover an exact connection between these joint moments and a solution of the $\sigma$-Painlev\'{e} V equation, valid for finite matrix size, as well as a connection between the leading-order asymptotic term and a solution of the $\sigma$-Painlev\'{e} III$'$ equation in the limit as $N \rightarrow \infty$. These connections enable us to derive exact formulae for joint moments for finite matrix size and for the joint moments of certain random variables arising from the Bessel point process in a recursive way. As an application, we provide a positive answer to a question proposed by Altu\u{g} et al.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09910v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Theodoros Assiotis, Mustafa Alper Gunes, Jonathan P. Keating, Fei Wei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solutions And Gradient Of The Conformal Ricci Bourguignon Soliton On Vaidya Spacetime</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09985v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we derive the complete and explicit solution for the conformal Ricci-Bourguignon soliton on Vaidya spacetime. We provide the closed-form expression for the vector field and establish the necessary conditions for the existence of the scalar potential, for which we also derive an explicit form. Our solution to the underlying system of linear partial differential equations proves that such solitons exist if and only if the mass function vanishes, forcing the metric to reduce to flat Minkowski spacetime (Schwarzschild, $m=0$). Synthesizing prior works, we show that the established classification of the soliton as shrinking, steady, or expanding is justified by the principles of linear stability. These findings refine the set of possible solitons within the non-linear theory of geometric flows by proving they are only admissible in the non-radiating vacuum limit, thereby enhancing the reliability of such models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09985v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayaan Abdur Rehman, Narayan S Iyer, Naeem Ahmed Pundeer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of 10,059 new three-dimensional periodic orbits of general three-body problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08568</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08568v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A very few three-dimensional (3D) periodic orbits of general three-body problem (with three finite masses) have been discovered since Newton mentioned it in 1680s. Using a high-accuracy numerical strategy we discovered 10,059 three-dimensional periodic orbits of the three-body problem in the cases of $m_{1}=m_{2}=1$ and $m_{3}=0.1n$ where $1\leq n\leq 20$ is an integer, among which 1,996 (about 20\%) are linearly stable. Note that our approach is valid for arbitrary mass $m_{3}$ so that in theory we can gain an arbitrarily large amount of 3D periodic orbits of the three-body problem. In the case of three equal masses, we discovered twenty-one 3D ``choerographical'' periodic orbits whose three bodies move periodically in a single closed orbit. It is very interesting that, in the case of two equal masses, we discovered 273 three-dimensional periodic orbits with the two bodies ($m_{1}=m_{2}=1$) moving along a single closed orbit and the third ($m_{3}\neq 1$) along a different one: we name them ``piano-trio'' orbits, like a trio for two violins and one piano. To the best of our knowledge, all of these 3D periodic orbits have never been reported, indicating the novelty of this work. The large amount of these new 3D periodic orbits are helpful for us to have better understandings about chaotic properties of the famous three-body problem, which ``are, so to say, the only opening through which we can try to penetrate in a place which, up to now, was supposed to be inaccessible'', as pointed out by Poincar\'e, the founder of chaos theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08568v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>astro-ph.GA</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoming Li, Shijun Liao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some geometrical aspects of gravitational waves using continuum mechanics analogy: State of the art and potential consequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09279v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this study, the authors employ the analogy between continuum mechanics and general relativity to investigate, from the perspective of elasticity and crystal plasticity, the deformations of space measured by LIGO/VIRGO interferometers during the passage of gravitational waves over Earth. The results of different innovative or existing mechanical models are compared with each other and compared with the observations in the framework of general relativity and Einstein-Cartan theory. Despite limitations, there is a convergence of results: the polarizations of gravitational waves can be viewed as expressions of an equivalent elastic media deformation tensor. Additionally, an anisotropy of space properties is unavoidable at the measurement point of the gravitational wave if we rely on the current first-order general relativity, which predict that gravitational waves generate deformations only in transverse planes. It is demonstrated that the classical polarizations of general relativity can be associated with a state of pure torsion in the analogous elastic medium and acted upon by the rotation of massive bodies such as black holes. This approach involves a transverse isotropic medium composed of independent sheets that deform perpendicularly to the direction of propagation of these waves. Considering geometric torsion in general relativity, associated with plastic crystallography, allows for the examination of complementary polarizations in the direction of wave propagation. This makes it possible to connect these sheets and reconstruct a complete, coherent 3D environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09279v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.2140/memocs.2025.13.103</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Vol. 13, No. 2, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David Izabel, Yves Remond, Matteo Luca Ruggiero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(BAA)-branes from higher Teichm\"uller theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09562v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Interpreting certain holomorphic Lagrangians that arise from the relative Langlands program, we construct moduli stacks underlying the generalized Slodowy categories of Collier--Sanders and $G^\mathbf{R}$-Higgs bundles over a Riemann surface. Furthermore, we extend the Cayley correspondence of Bradlow--Collier--Garc\'ia-Prada--Gothen--Oliveira to a morphism of Lagrangians over the Hitchin moduli stack, and initiate the study of its hyperholomorphic mirror partner under $S$-duality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09562v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Y. Chen, Enya Hsiao, Mengxue Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quivers and BPS states in 3d and 4d</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09729</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09729v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a symmetrization relation between BPS quivers encoding 4d $\mathcal{N}=2$ theories and symmetric quivers associated to 3d $\mathcal{N}=2$ theories. We analyse in detail the symmetrization of BPS quivers for a series of $A_m$ Argyres-Douglas theories by engineering 3d-4d systems in geometric backgrounds involving appropriate 3-manifolds and Riemann surfaces. We discuss properties of these geometric backgrounds and derive the corresponding quiver partition functions from the perspective of skein modules, which forms the foundation of the symmetrization map for the minimal chamber. We also prove that the structure of wall-crossing in 4d $A_m$ Argyres-Douglas theories is isomorphic to the structure of unlinking of symmetric quivers encoding their partner 3d theories, which allows for a proper definition of the symmetrization map outside the minimal chamber. Finally, we show that the Schur indices of 4d theories are captured by symmetric quivers that include symmetrization of 4d BPS quivers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09729v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Piotr Kucharski, Pietro Longhi, Dmitry Noshchenko, Sunghyuk Park, Piotr Su{\l}kowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metric-Induced Principal Symbols in Nonlinear Electrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09859v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a geometrical formulation of nonlinear electrodynamics by expressing its principal symbol as an optical metric-induced object. Under the assumption of no birefringence, we show that the evolution of linear perturbations can be recast as a covariant divergence on a curved, field-dependent background, enabling the application of quantum field theory techniques as in Maxwell's theory in curved backgrounds. This geometric reformulation opens a new route for analogue models potentially implementable in laboratory via tailored nonlinear metamaterials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09859v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Erico Goulart, Eduardo Bittencourt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Hydrodynamics in an Exclusion Process with Long-Range Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09879v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the symmetric Dyson exclusion process (SDEP) - a lattice gas with exclusion and long-range, Coulomb-type interactions that emerge both as the maximal-activity limit of the symmetric exclusion process and as a discrete version of Dyson's Brownian motion on the unitary group. Exploiting an exact ground-state (Doob) transform, we map the stochastic generator of the SDEP onto the spin-$1/2$ XX quantum chain, which in turn admits a free-fermion representation. At macroscopic scales we conjecture that the SDEP displays ballistic (Eulerian) scaling and non-local hydrodynamics governed by the equation $\partial_t \rho+\partial_x j[\rho]=0$ with $j[\rho]=(1/\pi)\sin(\pi\rho(x,t))\sinh(\pi\mathcal{H}\rho(x,t))$, where $\mathcal{H}$ is the Hilbert transform, making the current a genuinely non-local functional of the density. This non-local one-field description is equivalent to a local two-field "complex Hopf" system for finite particle density. Closed evolution formulas allow us to solve the melting of single and double block initial states, producing limit shapes and arctic curves that agree with large-scale Monte Carlo simulations. The model thus offers a tractable example of emergent non-local hydrodynamics driven by long-range interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09879v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Zahra, Jerome Dubail, Gunter M. Sch\"utz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collision-Free Bearing-Driven Formation Tracking for Euler-Lagrange Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09908</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09908v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the problem of tracking formations driven by bearings for heterogeneous Euler-Lagrange systems with parametric uncertainty in the presence of multiple moving leaders. To estimate the leaders' velocities and accelerations, we first design a distributed observer for the leader system, utilizing a bearing-based localization condition in place of the conventional connectivity assumption. This observer, coupled with an adaptive mechanism, enables the synthesis of a novel distributed control law that guides the formation towards the target formation, without requiring prior knowledge of the system parameters. Furthermore, we establish a sufficient condition, dependent on the initial formation configuration, that ensures collision avoidance throughout the formation evolution. The effectiveness of the proposed approach is demonstrated through a numerical example.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09908v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haoshu Cheng, Martin Guay, Shimin Wang, Yunhong Che</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum recurrences and the arithmetic of Floquet dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09933v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Poincar\'e recurrence theorem shows that conservative systems in a bounded region of phase space eventually return arbitrarily close to their initial state after a finite amount of time. An analogous behavior occurs in certain quantum systems where quantum states can recur after sufficiently long unitary evolution, a phenomenon known as quantum recurrence. Periodically driven (i.e. Floquet) quantum systems in particular exhibit complex dynamics even in small dimensions, motivating the study of how interactions and Hamiltonian structure affect recurrence behavior. While most existing studies treat recurrence in an approximate, distance-based sense, here we address the problem of exact, state-independent recurrences in a broad class of finite-dimensional Floquet systems, spanning both integrable and non-integrable models. Leveraging techniques from algebraic field theory, we construct an arithmetic framework that identifies all possible recurrence times by analyzing the cyclotomic structure of the Floquet unitary's spectrum. This computationally efficient approach yields both positive results, enumerating all candidate recurrence times and definitive negative results, rigorously ruling out exact recurrences for given Hamiltonian parameters. We further prove that rational Hamiltonian parameters do not, in general, guarantee exact recurrence, revealing a subtle interplay between system parameters and long-time dynamics. Our findings sharpen the theoretical understanding of quantum recurrences, clarify their relationship to quantum chaos, and highlight parameter regimes of special interest for quantum metrology and control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09933v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amit Anand, Dinesh Valluri, Jack Davis, Shohini Ghose</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving quantum communication rates with permutation-invariant codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09978</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09978v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work we improve the quantum communication rates of various quantum channels of interest using permutation-invariant quantum codes. We focus in particular on parametrized families of quantum channels and aim to improve bounds on their quantum capacity threshold, defined as the lowest noise level at which the quantum capacity of the channel family vanishes. These thresholds are important quantities as they mark the noise level up to which faithful quantum communication is theoretically possible. Our method exploits the fact that independent and identically distributed quantum channels preserve any permutation symmetry present at the input. The resulting symmetric output states can be described succinctly using the representation theory of the symmetric and general linear groups, which we use to derive an efficient algorithm for computing the channel coherent information of a permutation-invariant code. Our approach allows us to evaluate coherent information values for a large number of channel copies, e.g., at least 100 channel copies for qubit channels. We apply this method to various physically relevant channel models, including general Pauli channels, the dephrasure channel, the generalized amplitude damping channel, and the damping-dephasing channel. For each channel family we obtain improved lower bounds on their quantum capacities. For example, for the 2-Pauli and BB84 channel families we significantly improve the best known quantum capacity thresholds derived in [Fern, Whaley 2008]. These threshold improvements are achieved using a repetition code-like input state with non-orthogonal code states, which we further analyze in our representation-theoretic framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09978v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sujeet Bhalerao, Felix Leditzky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic behaviour of determinants through the expansion of the Moyal star product</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12781v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We work out a generalization of the Szeg\"o limit theorems on the determinant of large matrices. We focus on matrices with nonzero leading principal minors and elements that decay to zero exponentially fast with the distance from the main diagonal, but we relax the constraint of the Toeplitz structure. We obtain an expression for the asymptotic behaviour of the determinant written in terms of the factors of a left and right Wiener-Hopf type factorization of an appropriately defined symbol. For matrices with elements varying slowly along the diagonals (e.g., in locally Toeplitz sequences), we propose to apply the analogue of the semiclassical expansion of the Moyal star product in phase-space quantum mechanics. This is a systematic method that provides approximations up to any order in the typical scale of the inhomogeneity and allows us to obtain explicit asymptotic formulas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12781v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maurizio Fagotti, Vanja Mari\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Irreversibility and Stochastic Systems; Part Two</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01516</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01516v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We attempt to characterize irreversibility of a dynamical system from the existence of different forward and backward mathematical representations depending on the direction of the time arrow. Such different representations have been studied intensively and are shown to exist for stochastic diffusion models. In this setting one has however to face the preliminary justification of the existence of a stochastic description for physical systems which are traditionally described by classical mechanics as inherently deterministic and conservative.
  In part one of this paper we have addressed this modeling problem from a deterministic viewpoint for linear systems. We have shown that there are forward-backward representations which can describe conservative finite dimensional deterministic systems when they are coupled to an infinite-dimensional conservative heat bath. A key observation is that the heat bath acts on the finite-dimensional system by {\em state-feedback} which can shift its eigenvalues to make the system dissipative, but also may generate a totally unstable system which naturally evolves backward in time.
  In this second part, we address the stochastic description of these two representations. Under a natural family of invariant measures it is shown that the heat bath induces a white noise input acting on both the forward-backward representations making them true dissipative diffusions. We also consider how to relate the Stochastics to the Hamiltonian deterministic picture discussed in Part one. In our current context, we show that a continuous stationary process with a rational spectrum can always be thought of, or represented as, the output of a lossless deterministic system coupled to an infinite dimensional heat bath.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01516v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giorgio Picci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauge symmetry and partially Lagrangian systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19447v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a classical field theory whose equations of motion follow from the least action principle, but the class of admissible trajectories is restricted by differential equations. The key element of the proposed construction is the complete gauge symmetry of these additional equations. The unfree variation of the trajectories reduces to the infinitesimal gauge symmetry transformation of the equations, restricting the trajectories. We explicitly derive the equations that follow from the requirement that this gauge variation of the action vanishes. The system of equations for conditional extrema is not a Lagrangian system as such, but it admits an equivalent Hamiltonian formulation with a non-canonical Poisson bracket. The bracket is degenerate, in general. Alternatively, the equations restricting the dynamics could be added to the action with Lagrange multipliers with unrestricted variation of the original variables. In this case, we would arrive at the Lagrangian equations for the original variables involving Lagrange multipliers and for Lagrange multipliers themselves. In general, these two methods are not equivalent because the multipliers can bring extra degrees of freedom compared to the case of equations derived by unfree variation of the action. We illustrate the general method with two examples. The first example is a particle in a central field with varying trajectories restricted by the equation of conservation of angular momentum. The phase space acquires one more dimension, and there is an extra conserved quantity $K$ which is responsible for the precession of trajectories. The second example is linearized gravity with the Einstein-Hilbert action, and the class of varying fields is restricted by the linearized Nordstr\"om equation. This conditional extrema problem is shown to lead to the linearized Cotton gravity equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19447v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Lyakhovich, Nikita Sinelnikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A dynamical systems approach to WKB-methods: The eigenvalue problem for a single well potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10707v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we revisit the eigenvalue problem of the one-dimensional Schr{\"o}dinger equation for smooth single well potentials. In particular, we provide a new interpretation of the Bohr-Sommerfeld quantization formula. A novel aspect of our results, which are based on recent work of the authors on the turning point problem based upon dynamical systems methods, is that we cover all eigenvalues $E\in [0,\mathcal O(1)]$ and show that the Bohr-Sommerfeld quantitization formula approximates all of these eigenvalues (in a sense that is made precise). At the same time, we provide rigorous smoothness statements of the eigenvalues as functions of $\epsilon$. We find that whereas the small eigenvalues $E=\mathcal O(\epsilon)$ are smooth functions of $\epsilon$, the large ones $E=\mathcal O(1)$ are smooth functions of $n\epsilon \in[c_1,c_2],\,0&lt;c_1&lt;c_2&lt;\infty$, and $0\le \epsilon^{1/3}\ll 1$; here $n\in \mathbb N_0$ is the index of the eigenvalues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10707v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kristian Uldall Kristiansen, Peter Szmolyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SUSY hierarchies of Jaynes-Cummings Hamiltonians with different detuning parameters</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19943v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The aim of this work is to show how supersymmetric (SUSY) quantum mechanics can be applied to the Jaynes-Cummings (JC) Hamiltonian of quantum optics. These SUSY transformations connect pairs of Jaynes-Cummings Hamiltonians characterized by different detuning parameters as well as Jaynes-Cummings to anti-Jaynes-Cummings Hamiltonians. Therefore, JC Hamiltonians can be classified in hierarchies or sequences which are connected through SUSY transformations. As a byproduct, the symmetries of JC Hamiltonians are found as well as the special case of a sequence of resonant-like interacting systems having the form of a simple shape invariant JC Hamiltonian hierarchy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19943v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1402-4896/adf5fd</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Scr. 100 (2025) 085233</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>\.Ismail Burak Ate\c{s}, \c{S}eng\"ul Kuru, Javier Negro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hamiltonian formulation of the quasineutral Vlasov-Poisson system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21415v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Slow manifold reduction and the theory of Poisson-Dirac submanifolds are used to deduce a Hamiltonian formulation for a quasineutral limit of the planar, collisionless, magnetized Vlasov-Poisson system. Motion on the slow manifold models plasma dynamics free of fast Langmuir oscillations. Preservation of quasineutrality requires the bulk plasma flow is incompressible. The electric field is determined by counterbalancing plasma stresses that would otherwise produce compression. The Hamiltonian structure for the quasineutral model synthesizes well-known Poisson brackets for incompressible fluids and collisionless kinetic equations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21415v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. W. Burby, D. A. Kaltsas, P. J. Morrison, E. Tassi, G. N. Throumoulopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-adjoint realizations of higher-order squeezing operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.09044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.09044v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Higher-order squeezing captures non-Gaussian features of quantum light by probing moments of the field beyond the variance, and is associated with operators involving nonlinear combinations of creation and annihilation operators. Here we study a class of operators of the form $\xi (a^\dag)^ka^l+\xi^\ast (a^\dag)^la^k+f(a^\dag a)$, which arise naturally in the analysis of higher-order quantum fluctuations. The operators are defined on the linear span of Fock states. We show that the essential self-adjointness of these operators depends on the asymptotics of the real-valued function $f(n)$ at infinity. In particular, pure higher-order squeezing operators ($k\geq3$, $l=0$, and $f(n)=0$) are not essentially self-adjoint, but adding a properly chosen term $f(a^\dag a)$, like a Kerr term, can have a regularizing effect and restore essential self-adjointness. In the non-self-adjoint regime, we compute the deficiency indices and classify all self-adjoint extensions. Our results provide a rigorous operator-theoretic foundation for modeling and interpreting higher-order squeezing in quantum optics, and reveal interesting connections with the Birkhoff-Trjitzinsky theory of asymptotic expansions for recurrence relations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.09044v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felix Fischer, Daniel Burgarth, Davide Lonigro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integrated Local Energy Decay for Damped Magnetic Wave Equations on Stationary Space-Times</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.08628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.08628v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We establish local energy decay for damped magnetic wave equations on stationary, asymptotically flat space-times subject to the geometric control condition. More specifically, we allow for the addition of time-independent magnetic and scalar potentials, which negatively affect energy coercivity and may add in unwieldy spectral effects. By asserting the non-existence of eigenvalues in the lower half-plane and resonances on the real line, we are able to apply spectral theory from the work of Metcalfe, Sterbenz, and Tataru and combine with a generalization of prior work by the present author to extend the latter work and establish local energy decay, under one additional symmetry hypothesis. Namely, we assume that the damping term is the dominant principal term in the skew-adjoint part of the damped wave operator within the region where the metric perturbation from that of Minkowski space is permitted to be large. We also obtain an energy dichotomy if we do not prohibit non-zero real resonances. In order to make the structure of the argument more cohesive, we contextualize the present work within the requisite existing theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.08628v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s13324-025-01115-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Collin Kofroth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semi-definite optimization of the measured relative entropies of quantum states and channels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.19060</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.19060v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The measured relative entropies of quantum states and channels find operational significance in quantum information theory as achievable error rates in hypothesis testing tasks. They are of interest in the near term, as they correspond to hybrid quantum-classical strategies with technological requirements far less challenging to implement than required by the most general strategies allowed by quantum mechanics. In this paper, we prove that these measured relative entropies can be calculated efficiently by means of semi-definite programming, by making use of variational formulas for the measured relative entropies of states and semi-definite representations of the weighted geometric mean and the operator connection of the logarithm. Not only do the semi-definite programs output the optimal values of the measured relative entropies of states and channels, but they also provide numerical characterizations of optimal strategies for achieving them, which is of significant practical interest for designing hypothesis testing protocols.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.19060v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zixin Huang, Mark M. Wilde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adiabatic Dynamics of Entanglement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.18301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.18301v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that, during adiabatic evolution, any changes in entanglement can be attributed to a succession of avoided energy level crossings at which eigenvalues swap their eigenvectors. These swaps mediate the generation and redistribution of entanglement in multipartite systems. The efficiency of this redistribution depends on the narrowness of the avoided level crossings and thus constrains the speed of adiabatic evolution. Moreover, we relate the amount of entanglement involved to the ruggedness of the energy landscape, which directly affects the hardness of a computational problem. This enables an analysis of computational complexity and quantum advantage from the point of view of entanglement requirements. Applied to adiabatic quantum computation, our findings directly relate the computation's speed to its utilization of entanglement as a resource. The same principles extend to gate-based discretized adiabatic quantum algorithms, including those for Hamiltonian simulation and combinatorial optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.18301v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Einar Gabbassov, Achim Kempf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauging or extending bulk and boundary conformal field theories: Application to bulk and domain wall problem in topological matter and their descriptions by (mock) modular covariant</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19577</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19577v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study gauging operations (or group extensions) in (smeared) boundary conformal field theories (BCFTs) and bulk conformal field theories, and their applications to various phenomena in topologically ordered systems. We apply the resultant theories to the correspondence between the renormalization group (RG) flow of CFTs and the classification of topological quantum field theories in the testable information of general classes of partition functions. One can obtain the bulk topological properties of $2+1$ dimensional topological ordered phase corresponding to the massive RG flow of $1+1$ dimensional systems, or smeared BCFT. We present an obstruction of mass condensation for smeared BCFT analogous to the Lieb-Shultz-Mattis theorem for noninvertible symmetry. Related to the bulk topological degeneracies in $2+1$ dimensions and quantum phases in $1+1$ dimensions, we construct a new series of BCFT. We also investigate the implications of the massless RG flow of $1+1$ dimensional CFT to $2+1$ dimensional topological order, which corresponds to the earlier proposal by L. Kong and H. Zheng in [Nucl. Phys. B 966 (2021), 115384], arXiv:1912.01760, closely related to the integer-spin simple current by Schellekens and Gato-Rivera. We study the properties of the product of two CFTs connected by the two kinds of massless flows. The (mock) modular covariants appearing in the analysis seem to contain new ones. By applying the folding trick to the coupled model, we provide a general method to solve the gapped and charged domain wall. One can obtain the general phenomenology of the transportation of anyons through the domain wall. Our work gives a unified direction for the future theoretical and numerical studies of the topological phase based on the established data of classifications of conformal field theories or modular invariants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19577v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshiki Fukusumi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytic bulk-edge connection in circular-symmetric models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11186</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11186v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a systematic analysis of the eigenfunctions of two-band systems in two dimensions with a circular edge. Our approach is based on an analytic continuation of the wavenumber, which yields a mapping from the bulk modes to the edge modes. Phase relations of the eigenfunctions are described by their mapping onto a three-dimensional field of unit vectors. This mapping is studied in detail for a two-band Laplacian model and a Dirac model. The direction of the unit vector identifies the phase relation of the eigenfunctions and enables us to distinguish between the upper band, the lower band and the edge spectrum. Bulk and edge modes are spectrally separated, which results in two transitions from delocalized bulk modes to localized edge modes. These transitions are accompanied by transitions of the phase relations. Our analytic approach is compared with the topological bulk-edge correspondence, which is based on the Chern number of the bulk.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11186v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1751-8121/adfac2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. A: Math. Theor. (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Klaus Ziegler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adaptation of Moreau-Yosida regularization to the modulus of convexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.01772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.01772v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study a generalization of Moreau-Yosida regularization that is adapted to the geometry of Banach spaces where the dual space is uniformly convex with modulus of convexity of power type. Important properties for regularized convex functions are given, in particular strong monotonicity of the subdifferential of their convex conjugate and H\"older-continuity of their gradient.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.01772v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jmaa.2025.129956</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Math. Anal. Appl. 554, 129956 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Markus Penz, Andre Laestadius</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measures of Systems of Oscillators and Properties of Trajectories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18093v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the properties of trajectories in harmonic oscillator systems equipped with a point, absolutely continuous, or singular measure. As demonstrated in [30], infinite-dimensional linear flows of countable oscillator systems exhibit a new class of trajectory behavior. Specifically, these trajectories are non-periodic, and their projections onto any four-dimensional symplectic subspace fail to be dense in the corresponding projection of the invariant torus. Such trajectories do not arise in finite-dimensional systems, are non-generic for countable oscillator systems, but become generic in the continual case. We prove that for a countable harmonic oscillator system, every point on a non-degenerate invariant torus is a non-wandering point of the flow. In contrast, for a continual system with an absolutely continuous measure, all points on such a torus are wandering. Furthermore, for continual systems with a singular measure, we establish sufficient conditions on the measure and torus that rule out the existence of both transitive trajectories and non-wandering points. As an application, we exhibit a class of singular Bernoulli measures satisfying these conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18093v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vsevolod Sakbaev (Steklov Mathematical Institute of Russian Academy of Sciences), Igor Volovich (Steklov Mathematical Institute of Russian Academy of Sciences)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homomorphism, substructure and ideal: Elementary but rigorous aspects of renormalization group or hierarchical structure of topological orders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23155v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a general quantum Hamiltonian formalism of a renormalization group (RG) flow with an emphasis on generalized symmetry by interpreting the elementary relationship between homomorphism, quotient ring, and projection. In our formalism, the noninvertible nature of the ideal of a fusion ring realizing the generalized symmetry of an ultraviolet (UV) theory plays a fundamental role in determining condensation rules between anyons, resulting in the infrared (IR) theories. Our algebraic method applies to the domain wall problem in $2+1$ dimensional topologically ordered systems and the corresponding classification of $1+1$ dimensional gapped phase, for example. An ideal decomposition of a fusion ring provides a straightforward but strong constraint on the gapped phase with noninvertible symmetry and its symmetry-breaking (or emergent symmetry) patterns. Moreover, even in several specific homomorphisms connected under massless RG flows, less familiar homomorphisms appear, and we conjecture that they correspond to partially solvable models in recent literature. Our work demonstrates the fundamental significance of the abstract algebraic structure, ideal, for the RG in physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23155v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshiki Fukusumi, Yuma Furuta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergence of a Boundary-Sensitive Phase in Hyperbolic Ising Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.21044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.21044v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Physical systems defined on hyperbolic lattices may exhibit phases of matter that only emerge due to negative curvature. We focus on the case of the Ising model under open boundary conditions and show that an ``intermediate'' phase emerges in addition to standard (high-temperature) paramagnetic and (low-temperature) ferromagnetic phases. When performing the Kramers-Wannier duality the fact that it alters boundary conditions becomes crucial, since a finite fraction of lattice sites lie on the boundary. We propose to characterize this ``intermediate'' phase by its sensitivity to boundary conditions, wherein bulk ordering is not spontaneous but rather induced by boundary effects, setting it apart from the Landau paradigm of spontaneous symmetry breaking. By developing a $\mathbb{Z}_2$ symmetry restricted extension of the Corner Transfer Matrix Renormalization Group method, we provide numerical evidence for the existence of all three distinct phases and their corresponding two-stage phase transitions, thereby establishing the complete phase diagram. We also establish how the (spontaneous) intermediate-to-ferromagnetic and the (induced) paramagnetic-to-intermediate transition points are related by the Kramers-Wannier duality relation. We discuss a holographic correspondence between boundary and bulk behaviors and derive exact expressions for boundary correlation functions on Cayley trees.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.21044v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xingzhi Wang, Zohar Nussinov, Gerardo Ortiz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Embedding Signature-Changing Manifolds: A Braneworld and Kaluza-Klein Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08662v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate a class of semi-Riemannian manifolds characterized by smooth metric signature changes with a transverse radical, This class includes spacetimes relevant to cosmological models such as the Hartle-Hawking "no boundary" proposal, where a Riemannian manifold transitions smoothly into a Lorentzian spacetime without boundaries or singularities. For this class, we prove the existence of global isometric embeddings into higher-dimensional pseudo-Euclidean spaces. We then strengthen this result by demonstrating that a specific type of global isometric embedding, which we term an $\mathcal{H}$-global embedding, also exists into both Minkowski space and Misner space. For the canonical $n$-dimensional signature-changing model, we explicitly construct a full global isometric embedding into $(n+1)$-dimensional Minkowski and Misner spaces, a significantly stronger result than an $\mathcal{H}$-global embedding for this specific case. This embedding framework provides new geometric tools for studying signature change and braneworlds through the geometry of submanifolds embedded in a bulk, thus presenting a mathematically well-defined approach to these phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08662v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N. E. Rieger</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
