<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP</link>
    <description>math.MP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Oct 2025 02:53:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Exact solutions for the relativistic dynamics of a self-consistent system with electromagnetic and gravitational interaction within the Wigner-Vlasov formalism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15090v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work derives exact solutions to the problem of interacting particle density evolution in relativistic and quasi-relativistic approximations for electromagnetic and gravitational interactions. Two types of radial symmetry for the initial density distribution are considered: spherical and cylindrical. It is shown that the relativistic effect delays the onset of the shock wave moment, and in some cases removes it entirely or, conversely, can facilitate it. The analysis of the system's dynamics is carried out within the Wigner-Vlasov formalism, which makes it possible to extend the obtained solutions to quantum systems, including those with gravitational interaction. The derived exact solutions can be directly used as a cross-check for modeling and optimizing nonlinear problems of beam dynamics with account for space charge, astrophysics, plasma physics, and quantum systems with a shock wave.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15090v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. E. Perepelkin, B. I. Sadovnikov, N. G. Inozemtseva, I. Yu. Baibara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Numerical computation of the density of states of aperiodic multiscale Schr\"odinger operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15369v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Computing the electronic structure of incommensurate materials is a central challenge in condensed matter physics, requiring efficient ways to approximate spectral quantities such as the density of states (DoS). In this paper, we numerically investigate two distinct approaches for approximating the DoS of incommensurate Hamiltonians for small values of the incommensurability parameters $\epsilon$ (e.g., small twist angle, or small lattice mismatch): the first employs a momentum-space decomposition, and the second exploits a semiclassical expansion with respect to $\epsilon$. In particular, we compare these two methods using a 1D toy model. We check their consistency by comparing the asymptotic expansion terms of the DoS, and it is shown that, for full DoS, the two methods exhibit good agreement in the small $\epsilon$ limit, while discrepancies arise for less small $\epsilon$, which indicates the importance of higher-order corrections in the semiclassical method for such regimes. We find these discrepancies to be caused by oscillations in the DoS at the semiclassical analogues of Van Hove singularities, which can be explained qualitatively, and quantitatively for $\epsilon$ small enough, by a semiclassical approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15369v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Canc\`es, Daniel Massatt, Long Meng, \'Etienne Polack, Xue Quan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discretization of Variable-Coefficient Dynamical Systems via Rota Algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15489v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a novel integrability-preserving discretization for a broad class of differential equations with variable coefficients, encompassing both linear and nonlinear cases. The construction is achieved via a categorical approach that enables a unified treatment of continuous and discrete dynamical systems.
  Within our theoretical framework, based on the finite operator calculus proposed by G. C. Rota, all difference operators act as derivations in an algebra of power series with respect to a suitable functional product.
  The core of our theory relies on the existence of covariant functors between the newly proposed Rota category of Galois differential algebras and suitable categories of abstract dynamical systems.
  In this setting, under certain regularity assumptions, a differential equation and its discrete analogues are naturally interpreted as objects of the same category. This perspective enables the construction of a vast class of integrable maps that share with their continuous analogues a wide set of exact solutions and, in the linear case, the Picard-Vessiot group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15489v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel A. Rodriguez, Piergiulio Tempesta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semiclassical limit of entropies and free energies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15777v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Entropy and free energy are central concepts in both statistical physics and information theory, with quantum and classical facets. In mathematics these concepts appear quite often in different contexts (dynamical systems, probability theory, von Neumann algebras, etc.). In this work, we study the von Neumann and Wehrl entropies from the point of view of semiclassical analysis. We first prove the semiclassical convergence of the von Neumann to the Wehrl entropy for quantum Gibbs states (thermal equilibrium), after a suitable renormalization has been taken into account. Then, we show that, in the same limit, the free energy functional defined with the Wehrl entropy $ \Gamma-$converges to its classical counterpart, so implying convergence of the minima and the associated minimizers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15777v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zied Ammari, Michele Correggi, Marco Falconi, Rapha\"el Gautier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vortex lines interaction in the three-dimensional magnetic Ginzburg--Landau model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.14910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.14910v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We complete our study of the three dimensional Ginzburg--Landau functional with magnetic field, in the asymptotic regime of a small inverse Ginzburg--Landau parameter $\varepsilon$, and near the first critical field $H_{c_1}$ for which the first vortex filaments appear in energy minimizers. Under a nondegeneracy condition, we show a next order asymptotic expansion of $H_{c_1}$ as $\varepsilon \to 0$, and exhibit a sequence of transitions, with vortex lines appearing one by one as the intensity of the applied magnetic field is increased: passing $H_{c_1}$ there is one vortex, then increasing $H_{c_1}$ by an increment of order $\log |\log\varepsilon|$ a second vortex line appears, etc. These vortex lines accumulate near a special curve $\Gamma_0$, solution to an isoflux problem. We derive a next order energy that the vortex lines must minimize in the asymptotic limit, after a suitable horizontal blow-up around $\Gamma_0$. This energy is the sum of terms where penalizations of the length of the lines, logarithmic repulsion between the lines and magnetic confinement near $\Gamma_0$ compete. This elucidates the shape of vortex lines in superconductors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.14910v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carlos Rom\'an, Etienne Sandier, Sylvia Serfaty</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Preparation of Non-Stabilizer States and Clifford Evolution in $SU(2)_1$ Chern-Simons Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15067v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a topological framework for preparing families of non-stabilizer states, and computing their entanglement entropies, in $SU(2)_1$ Chern-Simons theory. Using the Kac-Moody algebra, we construct Pauli and Clifford operators as path integrals over 3-manifolds with Wilson loop insertions, enabling an explicit topological realization of $W_n$ and Dicke states, as well as their entanglement properties. We further establish a correspondence between Clifford group action and modular transformations generated by Dehn twists on genus-$g$ surfaces, linking the mapping class group to quantum operations. Our results extend existing topological constructions for stabilizer states to include families of non-stabilizer states, improving the geometric interpretation of entanglement and quantum resources in topological quantum field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15067v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Munizzi, Howard J. Schnitzer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limiting absorption principle for a hybrid resonance in a two-dimensional cold plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15153</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15153v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study a limiting absorption principle for the boundary-value problem describing a hybrid plasma resonance, with a regular coefficient in the principal part of the operator that vanishes on a curve inside the domain and changes its sign across this curve. We prove the limiting absorption principle by establishing a priori bounds on the solution in certain weighted Sobolev spaces. Next, we show that the solution can be decomposed into regular and singular parts. A peculiar property of this decomposition enables us to introduce a radiation-like condition in a bounded domain and to state a well-posed problem satisfied by the limiting absorption solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15153v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maryna Kachanovska, \'Etienne Peillon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rogue waves and large deviations for 2D pure gravity deep water waves</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15159</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15159v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Rogue waves are extreme ocean events characterized by the sudden formation of anomalously large crests, and remain an important subject of investigation in oceanography and mathematics. A central problem is to quantify the probability of their formation under random Gaussian sea initial data. In this work, we rigorously characterize the tail probability for the formation of rogue waves of the pure gravity water wave equations in deep water, the most accurate quasilinear PDE modeling waves in open ocean. This large deviation result confirms various conjectures from the oceanography literature in the weakly nonlinear regime. Moreover, the result holds up to the optimal timescales allowed by deterministic well-posedness theory. The proof shows that rogue waves most likely arise through "dispersive focusing", where phase quasi-synchronization produces constructive amplification of the water crest. The main difficulty in justifying this mechanism is propagating statistical information over such long timescales, which we overcome by combining normal forms and probabilistic methods. Unlike prior work, this novel approach does not require approximate solutions to be Gaussian. Our general method tracks the tail probability of solutions to Hamiltonian PDEs with an integrable normal form and random Gaussian initial data, even in the absence of (quasi-)invariant measures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15159v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Massimiliano Berti, Ricardo Grande, Alberto Maspero, Gigliola Staffilani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Central limit theorem for the sine-$\beta$ point process at $\beta \le 2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15172</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15172v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The purpose of this paper is to establish the analogue of the Soshnikov Central Limit Theorem for the sine-$\beta$ process at $\beta \le 2$. We consider regularized additive functionals, which correspond to 1-Sobolev regular functions $f(x/R)$, in the limit $R\to\infty$. Their convergence to the Gaussian distribution with respect to the Kolmogorov-Smirnov metric at the rate $(\ln R)^{-1/2}$ is established.
  The proof is based on the convergence of the circular $\beta$-ensemble to the sine-$\beta$ process, which was shown by Killip and Stoiciu. We find a convenient bound for the Laplace transforms of additive functionals under the circular $\beta$-ensemble, which holds under the scaling limit, suggested by Killip and Stoiciu. Further, we show that the additive functionals under the circular $\beta$-ensemble with $n$ particles converge to the gaussian distribution as $n\to\infty$ for all $1/2$-Sobolev regular functions for $\beta\le 2$, as was conjectured by Lambert.
  Finally, in order to prove the limit theorem for the circular $\beta$-ensemble we derive the connection between expectations of multiplicative functionals and the Jack measures, which generalizes the connection between the circular unitary ensemble and the Schur measures given by Gessel's theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15172v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergei M. Gorbunov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dyadic microlocal partition for anisotropic metrics and uniform Weyl quantization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15183v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a dyadic microlocal partition adapted to position-dependent anisotropic metrics in phase space and prove uniform bounds for localized Weyl quantization and for Moyal truncation with explicit control of remainders. A semiclassical, per-band renormalization recovers the exact scaling on each frequency band, while a Cotlar-Stein almost-orthogonality scheme ensures global convergence and operator-norm estimates with transparent dependence on finitely many symbol seminorms. The approach is robust in non-homogeneous settings where anisotropy varies with position. As applications, we construct a microlocal parametrix via truncated Moyal expansion and develop a local-global analysis of the Radon transform viewed as a model Fourier integral operator. The results provide a constructive toolset for uniform localization, composition, and recombination of pseudodifferential and Fourier integral operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15183v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vicente Vergara</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>H\"older damping for fractional wave equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15213v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For fractional wave equations with low H\"older regularity damping, we establish quantitative energy decay rates for their solutions when the geometric control condition holds. The energy decay rates depend explicitly on the H\"older regularity of the damping. In particular, we show damping functions with lower H\"older regularities that below a certain threshold give slower energy decay.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15213v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Wang, Ruoyu P. T. Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Boundary Conditions for the qBounce Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15341v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Discrepancies between theory and recent qBounce data have prompted renewed scrutiny of how boundary conditions are implemented for ultracold neutrons bouncing above a mirror in Earth's gravity. We apply the theory of self-adjoint extensions to the linear gravitational potential on the half-line and derive the most general boundary condition that renders the Hamiltonian self-adjoint. This introduces a single real self-adjoint parameter $\lambda$ that continuously interpolates between the Dirichlet case and more general (Robin-type) reflecting surfaces.
  Building on this framework, we provide analytical expressions for the energy spectrum, eigenfunctions, relevant matrix elements, and a set of sum rules valid for arbitrary $\lambda$. We show how nontrivial boundary conditions can bias measurements of $g$ and can mimic or mask putative short-range ''fifth-force''. Our results emphasize that enforcing self-adjointness-and modeling the correct boundary physics-is essential for quantitative predictions in gravitational quantum states. Beyond neutron quantum bounces, the approach is broadly applicable to systems where boundaries and self-adjointness govern the observable spectra and dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15341v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric J. Sung, Benjamin Koch, Tobias Jenke, Hartmut Abele, Denys I. Bondar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hodge Laplacians on Weighted Simplicial Complexes: Forms, Closures, and Essential Self-Adjointness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15546v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We establish explicit operator norm bounds and essential self-adjointness criteria for discrete Hodge Laplacians on weighted graphs and simplicial complexes. For unweighted $d$-regular graphs we prove the universal estimate $\|\widetilde{\Delta}_{1,*}\|\le 4(d-1)$, and we provide weighted extensions with a sharp comparability constant. These bounds apply without geometric completeness or curvature assumptions and ensure essential self-adjointness on natural cores. The approach extends to higher degrees via dual up/down degrees, and we show a unitary equivalence between skew and symmetric models on colorable complexes. For periodic lattices we complement the universal bounds with exact Floquet--Bloch constants, typically of order $2d$, illustrating both the sharpness in growth and the generality of our method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15546v1</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marwa Ennaceur, Amel Jadlaoui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nijenhuis operators and twisted $\mathcal{O}$-operators on Nambu-Poisson algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15640v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A ternary Nambu-Poisson algebra (which we call a Nambu-Poisson algebra in the paper) is the underlying algebraic structure of Nambu-Poisson manifolds of order $3$ that appeared in the generalized Hamiltonian mechanics. First, we consider the 2nd cohomology group of a Nambu-Poisson algebra with coefficients in a given representation. Next, we discuss suitable linear deformations of a Nambu-Poisson algebra and show that any such trivial deformation yields a Nijenhuis operator on it. To understand the deformed Nambu-Poisson algebra obtained from a Nijenhuis operator, we introduce a new algebraic structure, which we name NS-Nambu-Poisson algebras. Finally, we consider $\mathcal{O}$-operators twisted by $2$-cocycles and find their close relationships with NS-Nambu-Poisson algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15640v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Apurba Das, Fattoum Harrathi, Sami Mabrouk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compactifying the Parameter Space for the Quantum Multiplication for Hypertoric Varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15687v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we will be studying the parameter space for the quantum multiplication for hypertoric varieties. The operation of quantum multiplication for hypertoric varieties has an explicit formulation which is given by McBreen and Shenfeld. In particular, this multiplication depends on a parameter which lives in the complement of a toric arrangement. Following a paper of deConcini and Gaiffi, I will define a compactification of this parameter space and show how the quantum multiplication can be extended to this compactification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15687v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeremy Peters</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalar fields with power-law potentials in quantum cosmology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15735</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15735v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A homogeneous and isotropic quantum cosmological system (universe) initially filled with a uniform scalar field that has a potential in the power law representation is considered. Depending on the epoch, this scalar field yields barotropic matter in the form of stiff matter, perfect gas, radiation, dust, cosmic strings, domain walls, de Sitter vacuum, or phantom matter. The proposed approach is based on quantum geometrodynamics for the maximally symmetric space. The relevant differential equations for the separate power-law summands of the scalar field potential and the corresponding quantum Hamiltonian constraint equations, which describe the universe that can be viewed as dominated by one form or another of barotropic matter, were obtained. The solutions to these equations have been found in analytical form.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15735v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>V. E. Kuzmichev (Bogolyubov Institute for Theoretical Physics), V. V. Kuzmichev (Bogolyubov Institute for Theoretical Physics)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin glass analysis of the invariant distribution of a Lotka-Volterra SDE with a large random interaction matrix</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15754</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15754v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The generalized Lotka-Volterra stochastic differential equation with a symmetric food interaction matrix is frequently used to model the dynamics of the abundances of the species living within an ecosystem when these interactions are mutualistic or competitive. In the relevant cases of interest, the Markov process described by this equation has an unique invariant distribution which has a Hamiltonian structure. Following an important trend in theoretical ecology, the interaction matrix is considered in this paper as a large random matrix. In this situation, the (conditional) invariant distribution takes the form of a random Gibbs measure that can be studied rigorously with the help of spin glass techniques issued from the field of physics of disordered systems. Considering that the interaction matrix is an additively deformed GOE matrix, which is a well-known model for this matrix in theoretical ecology, the free energy of the model is derived in the limit of the large number $n$ of species, making rigorous some recent results from the literature. The free energy analysis made in this paper could be adapted to other situations where the Gibbs measure is non compactly supported.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15754v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Younes Gueddari, Walid Hachem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Macroscopic suppression of supersonic quantum transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19788v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a broad class of strongly interacting quantum lattice gases, including the Fermi-Hubbard and Bose-Hubbard models. We focus on macroscopic particle clusters of size $\theta N$, with $\theta\in(0,1)$ and $N$ the total particle number, and we study the quantum probability that such a cluster is transported across a distance $r$ within time $t$. Conventional effective light cone arguments yield a bound of the form $\exp(v t-r)$. We report a substantially stronger bound $\exp(\theta N(vt-r))$, which provides exponential suppression that scales with system size. Our result establishes a universal dynamical large deviation principle: macroscopic suppression of supersonic macroscopic transport (MASSMAT).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19788v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\'er\'emy Faupin, Marius Lemm, Israel Michael Sigal, Jingxuan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On elastic and non-elastic wave superpositions for the Euler system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09576v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The paper contains an analysis of the conditions for the existence of elastic versus non-elastic wave superpositions governed by the Euler system in (1+1)-dimensions. This system admits entropic solutions and two types of sound wave solutions. It is shown that the smallest real Lie algebra containing vector fields (associated with these waves) is isomorphic to a semidirect sum of the infinite-dimensional Abelian real Lie algebra and the non-Abelian finite-dimensional real Lie algebra. Based on this fact, we are able to find a parametrization of the region of non-elastic wave superpositions which allows for the construction of the reduced form of the Euler system. It is proven that, in this case, the manifold spanned by the vector fields associated with waves possesses the structure of a local Lie group. It is also shown that this manifold has a torsion-free affine connection and the one-parameter subgroups of the Lie group are geodesics. Based on this fact, a description of the non-elastic wave superposition is given in terms of motion of the quasi-rectifiable surfaces spanned by the pair of vector fields associated with sound waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09576v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>{\L}ukasz Chomienia, Alfred Michel Grundland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Convergence Rate of Lie-Trotter Approximation for Quantum Thermal Averages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.05188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.05188v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Lie--Trotter product formula is a foundational approximation for the quantum partition function, yet obtaining rigorous error bounds for the unbounded Hamiltonians common in physics remains a significant challenge. This paper provides a quantitative error analysis for this approximation across two key systems. For a particle in a smooth, periodic potential, we establish an optimal convergence rate of $\mathcal O(1/N^2)$ for both the partition function and thermal averages, where $N$ is the number of imaginary time steps. We then extend this analysis to the more challenging case of a confining potential on $\mathbb R$, proving a nearly optimal rate of $\mathcal O((\log N+1)^{\frac32}/N^2)$. The derived error bounds provide a firm mathematical foundation for the high-order accuracy of path integral simulations in quantum statistical mechanics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.05188v5</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuda Ye, Zhennan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectrum of random centrosymmetric matrices; CLT and Circular law</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03513v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyze the asymptotic fluctuations of linear eigenvalue statistics of random centrosymmetric matrices with i.i.d. entries. We prove that for a complex analytic test function, the centered and normalized linear eigenvalue statistics of random centrosymmetric matrices converge to a normal distribution. We find the exact expression of the variance of the limiting normal distribution via combinatorial arguments. Moreover, we also argue that the limiting spectral distribution of properly scaled centrosymmetric matrices follows the circular law.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03513v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S2010326324500266</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Random Matrices: Theory and Applications, Vol. 14, No. 01 (2025) 2450026</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Indrajit Jana, Sunita Rani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loewner traces driven by Levy processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06144v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Loewner chains with Levy drivers have been proposed as models for random dendritic growth in two dimensions, and as candidates for finding extremal multifractal spectra in problems in classical function theory. These processes are not scale-invariant in general, but they do enjoy a natural domain Markov property thanks to the stationary independent increments of Levy processes. The associated Loewner hulls feature remarkably intricate topological properties, of which very little is known rigorously.
  We prove that a chordal Loewner chain driven by a Levy process $W$ satisfying mild regularity conditions (including stable processes) is a.s. generated by a cadlag curve. Specifically, if the diffusivity parameter of the driving process $W$ is $\kappa \in [0,8)$, then the jump measure of $W$ is required to be locally (upper) Ahlfors regular near the origin, while if $\kappa &gt; 8$, no constraints are imposed. In particular, we show that the associated Loewner hulls are a.s. locally connected and path-connected. We also show that, the complements of the hulls are a.s. Holder domains when $\kappa \neq 4$ (which is not expected to hold when $\kappa=4$), without any regularity assumptions. The proofs of these results mainly rely on careful derivative estimates for both the forward and backward Loewner maps obtained using delicate but robust enough supermartingale domination arguments. As one cannot control the jump accumulation of general Levy processes, we must circumvent all reasoning that would use continuity. To prove the local connectedness, we use an extension of part of the Hahn-Mazurkiewicz theorem: hulls generated by cadlag curves are locally connected even when jumps would occur at infinite intensity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06144v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eveliina Peltola, Anne Schreuder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adding the algebraic Ryu-Takayanagi formula to the algebraic reconstruction theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06361v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A huge progress in studying holographic theories is that holography can be interpreted via the quantum error correction, which makes equal the entanglement wedge reconstruction, the Jafferis-Lewkowycz-Maldacena-Suh formula, the radial commutativity and the Ryu-Takayanagi formula. We call the equivalence the reconstruction theorem, whose infinite-dimensional generalization via algebraic language was believed to exclude the algebraic version of the Ryu-Takayanagi formula. However, recent developments regarding gravitational algebras have shown that the inclusion of the algebraic Ryu-Takayanagi formula is plausible. In this letter, we prove that such inclusion holds for the cases of type I/II factors, which are expected to describe holographic theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06361v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingshuai Xu, Haocheng Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deterministic Underlying States are incompatible with a Counterfactual account of L\"uders' rule</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00546v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we show that a counterfactual account of L"uders' rule -- which we argue is naturally implied by the mathematical structure of the rule itself -- rules out underlying-state models of quantum mechanics (a type of hidden-variable model, typically used in the contextuality and nonlocality literature, where quantum states are treated as probability measures over ``better-defined states''). This incompatibility arises because the counterfactual update requires ontological models to update their states according to conditional probability, which in turn establishes an equivalence between compatibility and the existence of such models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00546v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/mrqr-sdyf</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Alisson Tezzin, B\'arbara Amaral, Jonte R. Hance</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Out-of-distribution generalisation for learning quantum channels with low-energy coherent states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.04454</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.04454v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: When experimentally learning the action of a continuous variable quantum process by probing it with inputs, there will often be some restriction on the input states used. One experimentally simple way to probe a quantum channel is using low energy coherent states. Learning a quantum channel in this way presents difficulties, due to the fact that two channels may act similarly on low energy inputs but very differently for high energy inputs. They may also act similarly on coherent state inputs but differently on non-classical inputs. Extrapolating the behaviour of a channel for more general input states from its action on the far more limited set of low energy coherent states is a case of out-of-distribution generalisation. To be sure that such generalisation gives meaningful results, one needs to relate error bounds for the training set to bounds that are valid for all inputs. We show that for any pair of channels that act sufficiently similarly on low energy coherent state inputs, one can bound how different the input-output relations are for any (high energy or highly non-classical) input. This proves out-of-distribution generalisation is always possible for learning quantum channels using low energy coherent states, as long as enough samples are used.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.04454v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/5m7p-kbf3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Quantum 6, 040306 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jason L. Pereira, Quntao Zhuang, Leonardo Banchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Minimal Factorization of Chern-Simons Theory -- Gravitational Anyonic Edge Modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00501</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00501v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: One approach to analyzing entanglement in a gauge theory is embedding it into a factorized theory with edge modes on the entangling boundary. For topological quantum field theories (TQFT), this naturally leads to factorizing a TQFT by adding local edge modes associated with the corresponding CFT. In this work, we instead construct a minimal set of edge modes compatible with the topological invariance of Chern-Simons theory. This leads us to propose a minimal factorization map. These minimal edge modes can be interpreted as the degrees of freedom of a particle on a quantum group. Of particular interest is three-dimensional gravity as a Chern-Simons theory with gauge group SL$(2,\mathbb{R}) \times$ SL$(2,\mathbb{R})$. Our minimal factorization proposal uniquely gives rise to quantum group edge modes factorizing the bulk state space of 3d gravity. This agrees with earlier proposals that relate the Bekenstein-Hawking entropy in 3d gravity to topological entanglement entropy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00501v3</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas G. Mertens, Qi-Feng Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct Sum Structure of the Super Virasoro Algebra and a Fermion Algebra Arising from the Quantum Toroidal $\mathfrak{gl}_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02926</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02926v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is known that the $q$-deformed Virasoro algebra can be constructed from a certain representation of the quantum toroidal $\mathfrak{gl}_1$ algebra. In this paper, we apply the same construction to the quantum toroidal algebra of type $\mathfrak{gl}_2$ and study the properties of resulting generators $W_i(z)$ ($i=1,2$). The algebra generated by $W_i(z)$ can be regarded as a $q$-deformation of the direct sum $\mathsf{F} \oplus \mathsf{SVir}$, where $\mathsf{F}$ denotes the free fermion algebra and $\mathsf{SVir}$ stands for the $N=1$ super Virasoro algebra, also referred to as the $N=1$ superconformal algebra or the Neveu-Schwarz-Ramond algebra. Moreover, the generators $W_i(z)$ admit two screening currents, and we show that their degeneration limits coincide with the screening currents of $\mathsf{SVir}$. We also establish quadratic relations satisfied by $W_i(z)$ and show that they generate a pair of commuting $q$-deformed Virasoro algebras, which degenerate into two nontrivial commuting Virasoro algebras included in $\mathsf{F} \oplus \mathsf{SVir}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02926v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11005-025-01997-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Lett. Math. Phys. 115, 107 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yusuke Ohkubo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Elias' Encoding from Lagrangians and Renormalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.23447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.23447v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the present paper we give a derivation of Elias' Omega code from physics principles by combining a constrained variational formulation of prefix coding with a renormalization flow on codeword distributions.
  Starting from a Lagrangian that minimizes average codelength under the Kraft-McMillan constraint, we show that the implied distribution is a fixed point of a coarse-graining map, yielding the canonical iterated log-sum length, asymptotically up to an additive constant.
  This establishes completeness and asymptotic optimality, and connects universal integer coding with coarse-grained entropy, uncertainty-type bounds, and entropy relations familiar from statistical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.23447v5</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Kolpakov, Aidan Rocke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Loss-Complexity Landscape and Model Structure Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.13543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.13543v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a framework for dualizing the Kolmogorov structure function $h_x(\alpha)$, which then allows using computable complexity proxies. We establish a mathematical analogy between information-theoretic constructs and statistical mechanics, introducing a suitable partition function and free energy functional. We explicitly prove the Legendre-Fenchel duality between the structure function and free energy, showing detailed balance of the Metropolis kernel, and interpret acceptance probabilities as information-theoretic scattering amplitudes. A susceptibility-like variance of model complexity is shown to peak precisely at loss-complexity trade-offs interpreted as phase transitions. Practical experiments with linear and tree-based regression models verify these theoretical predictions, explicitly demonstrating the interplay between the model complexity, generalization, and overfitting threshold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.13543v4</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Kolpakov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A further remark on the density estimate for degenerate Allen-Cahn equations: $\Delta_{p}$-type equations for $1&lt;p&lt;\frac{n}{n-1}$ with rough coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.19820</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.19820v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this short remark on a previous paper \cite{SZ25}, we continue the study of Allen-Cahn equations associated with Ginzburg-Landau energies \begin{equation*}
  J(v,\Omega)=\int_{\Omega}\Big\{F(\nabla v,v,x)+W(v,x)\Big\}dx, \end{equation*} involving a Dirichlet energy $F(\vec{\xi},\tau,x)\sim|\vec{\xi}|^{p}$ and a degenerate double-well potential $W(\tau,x)\sim(1-\tau^{2})^{m}$. In contrast to \cite{SZ25}, we remove all regularity assumptions on the Ginzburg-Landau energy. Then, with further assumptions that $1&lt;p&lt;\frac{n}{n-1}$ and that $W(\tau,x)$ is monotone in $\tau$ on both sides of $0$, we establish a density estimate for the level sets of nontrivial minimizers $|u|\leq1$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.19820v2</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chilin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplicative Turing Ensembles, Pareto's Law, and Creativity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.04167</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.04167v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study integer-valued multiplicative dynamics driven by i.i.d. prime multipliers and connect their macroscopic statistics to universal codelengths. We introduce the Multiplicative Turing Ensemble (MTE) and show how it arises naturally - though not uniquely - from ensembles of probabilistic Turing machines. Our modeling principle is variational: taking Elias' Omega codelength as an energy and imposing maximum entropy constraints yields a canonical Gibbs prior on integers and, by restriction, on primes. Under mild tail assumptions, this prior induces exponential tails for log-multipliers (up to slowly varying corrections), which in turn generate Pareto tails for additive gaps. We also prove time-average laws for the Omega codelength along MTE trajectories. Empirically, on Debian and PyPI package size datasets, a scaled Omega prior achieves the lowest KL divergence against codelength histograms. Taken together, the theory-data comparison suggests a qualitative split: machine-adapted regimes (Gibbs-aligned, finite first moment) exhibit clean averaging behavior, whereas human-generated complexity appears to sit beyond this regime, with tails heavy enough to produce an unbounded first moment, and therefore no averaging of the same kind.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.04167v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Kolpakov, Aidan Rocke</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
