<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP</link>
    <description>math.MP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 04:00:07 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Topological description of pure invariant states of the Weyl $C^*$-algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04938v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work we study the topology of certain families of states of the Weyl $C^*$-algebra with finite degrees of freedom. We focus on families of pure states characterized by symmetries and a (semi-)regularity condition, and obtain precise topological descriptions through homeomorphisms with other explicit spaces. Of special importance are the families of pure, semi-regular states invariant under either continuous (plane-wave states) or discrete (Bloch-wave states) spatial translations, and the family of states invariant under discrete, mutually commuting spatial and momentum translations (Zak-wave states), all of which we completely characterize.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04938v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe De Nittis, Santiago Rendel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poisson homogeneous spaces of Poisson 2-groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05080v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Drinfeld classified Poisson homogeneous spaces of a Poisson Lie group in terms of Dirac structures of the Lie bialgebra. In this paper, we study homogeneous spaces of a 2-group and develop Drinfeld theorem in the Poisson 2-group context.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05080v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Honglei Lang, Zhangju Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterization of the spectra of rotating truncated gas planets and inertia-gravity modes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05428v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the essential spectrum, which corresponds to inertia-gravity modes, of the system of equations governing a rotating and self-gravitating gas planet. With certain boundary conditions, we rigorously and precisely characterize the essential spectrum and show how it splits from the portion of the spectrum corresponding to the acoustic modes. The fundamental mathematical tools in our analysis are a generalization of the Helmholtz decomposition and the Lopantinskii conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05428v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maarten V. de Hoop, Sean Holman, Alexei Iantchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Epstein curves and holography of the Schwarzian action</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05690v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by the duality between Jackiw-Teitelboim gravity and Schwarzian field theory, we show identities between the Schwarzian action of a circle diffeomorphism with (1) the hyperbolic area enclosed by the Epstein curve in the hyperbolic disk $\mathbb{D}$, (2) the asymptotic excess in the isoperimetric inequality for the equidistant Epstein foliation, (3) the variation of the Loewner energy along its equipotential foliation, and (4) the asymptotic change in hyperbolic area under a conformal distortion near the circle. From these geometric interpretations, we obtain two new proofs of the non-negativity of the Schwarzian action for circle diffeomorphisms, one from the isoperimetric inequality and the other from the monotonicity of the Loewner energy. Moreover, we show that the horocycle truncation used in Epstein's construction of the Epstein curve also defines a renormalized length of hyperbolic geodesics in $\mathbb{D}$, which coincides with the log of the bi-local observable. From this, we show that the bi-local observables on the edges of any ideal triangulation of $\mathbb{D}$ determine the circle diffeomorphism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05690v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Franco Vargas Pallete, Yilin Wang, Catherine Wolfram</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anyon Theory and Topological Frustration of High-Efficiency Quantum LDPC Codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04699v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum low-density parity-check (QLDPC) codes present a promising route to low-overhead fault-tolerant quantum computation, yet systematic strategies for their exploration remain underdeveloped. In this work, we establish a topological framework for studying the bivariate-bicycle codes, a prominent class of QLDPC codes tailored for real-world quantum hardware. Our framework enables the investigation of these codes through universal properties of topological orders. Besides providing efficient characterizations for demonstrations using Gr\"obner bases, we also introduce a novel algebraic-geometric approach based on the Bernstein--Khovanskii--Kushnirenko theorem, allowing us to analytically determine how the topological order varies with the generic choice of bivariate-bicycle codes under toric layouts. Novel phenomena are unveiled, including topological frustration, where ground-state degeneracy on a torus deviates from the total anyon number, and quasi-fractonic mobility, where anyon movement violates energy conservation. We demonstrate their inherent link to symmetry-enriched topological orders and offer an efficient method for searching for finite-size codes. Furthermore, we extend the connection between anyons and logical operators using Koszul complex theory. Our work provides a rigorous theoretical basis for exploring the fault tolerance of QLDPC codes and deepens the interplay among topological order, quantum error correction, and advanced mathematical structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04699v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keyang Chen, Yuanting Liu, Yiming Zhang, Zijian Liang, Yu-An Chen, Ke Liu, Hao Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accumulation of Charge on an Extremal Black Hole's Event Horizon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04881v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We numerically analyze the behavior of a charged scalar field on a fixed extremal Reissner-Nordstr\"om background. We find an extension of the Aretakis instability characterized by an accumulation of charge on the extremal event horizon. In particular, when the charge coupling to the scalar field is sufficiently large, the charge density on the horizon asymptotes to a nonzero constant at late times. By constructing monochromatic initial data at the onset of charged superradiance, we give evidence supporting the claim that this instability is connected to the presence of a nearly zero-damped mode. Throughout this work, we employ a numerical integration scheme in compactified double-null coordinates, which allows us to capture the asymptotic behavior of the matter at the boundaries of the spacetime.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04881v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zachary Gelles, Frans Pretorius</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exceptional Topology on Nonorientable Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04889v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We classify gapped and gapless phases of non-Hermitian band structures on two-dimensional nonorientable parameter spaces. Such spaces arise in a wide range of physical systems in the presence of non-symmorphic parameter space symmetries. For gapped phases, we find that nonorientable spaces provide a natural setting for exploring fundamental structural problems in braid group theory, such as torsion and conjugacy. Gapless phases, which host exceptional points (EPs), explicitly violate the fermion doubling theorem, even in two-band models. We demonstrate that EPs traversing the nonorientable parameter space exhibit non-Abelian charge inversion. These braided phases and their transitions leave distinct signatures in the form of bulk Fermi arc degeneracies, offering a concrete route toward experimental realization and verification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04889v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Lukas K. K\"onig, Kang Yang, Andr\'e Grossi Fonseca, Sachin Vaidya, Marin Solja\v{c}i\'c, Emil J. Bergholtz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classical Simulation of Non-Classical Systems: A Large Deviation Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.04920</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.04920v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Any quasi-probability representation of a no-signaling system -- including quantum systems -- can be simulated via a purely classical scheme by allowing signed events and a cancellation procedure. This raises a fundamental question: What properties of the non-classical system does such a classical simulation fail to replicate? We answer by using large deviation theory to show that the probability of a large fluctuation under the classical simulation can be strictly greater than under the actual non-classical system. The key finding driving our result is that negativity in probability relaxes the data processing inequality of information theory. We propose this potential large deviation stability of quantum (and no-signaling) systems as a novel form of quantum advantage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.04920v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Brandenburger, Pierfrancesco La Mura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Butcher series for Hamiltonian Poisson integrators through symplectic groupoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05000v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a pre-Lie formalism of Butcher trees for the approximation of Hamilton-Jacobi solutions on any symplectic groupoid $\mathcal{G} \rightrightarrows M.$ The impact of this new algebraic approach is twofold. On the geometric side, it yields algebraic operations to approximate Lagrangian bisections of $\mathcal{G}$ using the Butcher-Connes-Kreimer Hopf algebra and, in turn, aims at a better understanding of the group of Poisson diffeomorphisms of $M.$ On the computational side, we define a new class of Poisson integrators for Hamiltonian dynamics on Poisson manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05000v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrien Busnot Laurent, Oscar Cosserat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homotopy Wave Function in Algebraic Geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose the homotopy shape of the Segal topos of derived stacks over simplicial k-algebras as the higher homotopical generalization of the concept of wave function in Quantum Mechanics</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05099v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renaud Gauthier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Dual Extended Hamming Code Immune to Collective Coherent Errors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05249v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum error correction (QEC) is crucial for protecting quantum information from various error sources, including collective coherent errors and depolarizing noise. In this work, we propose a novel family of constant excitation (CE) stabilizer codes with parameters $[[2^{r+1}, 2^r-(r+1), 4]]$. These codes are constructed by concatenating an inner complemented dual-rail (CDR) code with a classical outer $[2^r, 2^r-(r+1), 4]$ extended Hamming code. Our smallest instance, the CE $[[8,1,4]]$ code, improves upon the previously known CE $[[8,1,3]]$ code by increasing the code distance from 3 to 4, thereby enhancing its error-correcting capability. The combination of the extended Hamming code with the CDR structure allows for robust differentiation between bit-flip ($X$) and phase-flip ($Z$) errors. Our results contribute to the ongoing development of high-rate, fault-tolerant QEC schemes suitable for practical quantum computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05249v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>En-Jui Chang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a certain inequality for the sum of norms and reverse uncertainty relations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05669</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05669v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove a simple inequality for a sum of squares of norms of two vectors in an inner product space. Next, using this inequality we derive the so--called "reverse uncertainty relation" and analyze its properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05669v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Urbanowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum State Designs from Minimally Random Quantum Circuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.05698</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.05698v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Random many-body states are both a useful tool to model certain physical systems and an important asset for quantum computation. Realising them, however, generally requires an exponential (in system size) amount of resources. Recent research has presented a way out by showing that one can generate random states, or more precisely a controlled approximation of them, by applying a quantum circuit built in terms of few-body unitary gates. Most of this research, however, has been focussed on the case of quantum circuits composed by completely random unitary gates. Here we consider what happens for circuits that, instead, involve a minimal degree of randomness. Specifically, we concentrate on two different settings: (a) brickwork quantum circuits with a single one-qudit random matrix at a boundary; (b) brickwork quantum circuits with fixed interactions but random one-qudit gates everywhere. We show that, for any given initial state, (a) and (b) produce a distribution of states approaching the Haar distribution in the limit of large circuit depth. More precisely, we show that the moments of the distribution produced by our circuits can approximate the ones of the Haar distribution in a depth proportional to the system size. Interestingly we find that in both Cases (a) and (b) the relaxation to the Haar distribution occurs in two steps - this is in contrast with what happens in fully random circuits. Moreover, we show that choosing appropriately the fixed interactions, for example taking the local gate to be a dual-unitary gate with high enough entangling power, minimally random circuits produce a Haar random distribution more rapidly than fully random circuits. In particular, dual-unitary circuits with maximal entangling power - i.e. perfect tensors - appear to provide the optimal quantum state design preparation for any design number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.05698v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathon Riddell, Katja Klobas, Bruno Bertini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning the local density of states of a bilayer moir\'e material in one dimension</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.06688</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.06688v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent work of three of the authors showed that the operator which maps the local density of states of a one-dimensional untwisted bilayer material to the local density of states of the same bilayer material at non-zero twist, known as the twist operator, can be learned by a neural network. In this work, we first provide a mathematical formulation of that work, making the relevant models and operator learning problem precise. We then prove that the operator learning problem is well-posed for a family of one-dimensional models. To do this, we first prove existence and regularity of the twist operator by solving an inverse problem. We then invoke the universal approximation theorem for operators to prove existence of a neural network capable of approximating the twist operator.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.06688v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Diyi Liu, Alexander B. Watson, Michael Hott, Stephen Carr, Mitchell Luskin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>RG analysis of spontaneous stochasticity on a fractal lattice: stability and bifurcations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14903</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14903v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the stability and bifurcations of spontaneous stochasticity using an approach reminiscent of the Feigenbaum renormalization group (RG). We consider dynamical models on a self-similar space-time lattice as toy models for multiscale motion in hydrodynamic turbulence. Here an ill-posed ideal system is regularized at small scales and the vanishing regularization (inviscid) limit is considered. By relating the inviscid limit to the dynamics of the RG operator acting on the flow maps, we explain the existence and universality (regularization independence) of the limiting solutions as a consequence of the fixed-point RG attractor. Considering the local linearized dynamics, we show that the convergence to the inviscid limit is governed by the universal RG eigenmode. We also demonstrate that the RG attractor undergoes a period-doubling bifurcation with parameter variation, thereby changing the nature of the inviscid limit. In the case of chaotic RG dynamics, we introduce the stochastic RG operator acting on Markov kernels. Then the RG attractor becomes stochastic, which explains the existence and universality of spontaneously stochastic solutions in the limit of vanishing noise. We study a linearized structure (RG eigenmode) of the stochastic RG attractor and its period-doubling bifurcation. Viewed as prototypes of Eulerian spontaneous stochasticity, our models explain its mechanism, universality and potential diversity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14903v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10955-025-03425-w</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Statistical Physics (2025) 192:37</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alexei A. Mailybaev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pairs of Subspaces, Split Quaternions and the Modular Operator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04010v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit the work of Rieffel and van Daele on pairs of subspaces of a real Hilbert space, while relaxing as much as possible the assumption that all the relevant subspaces are in general positions with respect to each other. We work out, in detail, how two real projection operators lead to the construction of a complex Hilbert space where the theory of the modular operator is applicable, with emphasis on the relevance of a central extension of the group of split quaternions. Two examples are given for which the subspaces have unequal dimension and therefore are not in generic position.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04010v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Naudts, Jun Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noise-driven Synchronization of Vicsek Model in Mean</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13993v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Vicsek model has long stood as a pivotal framework in exploring collective behavior and self-organization, captivating the scientific community with its compelling dynamics. However, understanding how noise influences synchronization within this model and its associated phase transition characteristics has presented significant challenges. While numerous studies have focused on simulations due to the model's mathematical complexity, comprehensive theoretical analyses remain sparse. In this paper, we deliver a rigorous mathematical proof demonstrating that for any initial configuration of the Vicsek model, there exists a bound on noise amplitude such that if the noise amplitude is maintained within this bound, the system will achieve synchronization in mean. This finding not only lays a solid mathematical groundwork for the Vicsek model's phase transition theory but also underscores the critical role of noise in collective dynamics, enhancing our understanding of self-organizing systems in stochastic environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13993v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Su, Yongguang Yu, Ge Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable soap bubble clusters with multiple torus bubbles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02736</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02736v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the last two centuries and more particularly in the last decades, the geometry of foams has become an important research domain, in mathematics, physics, material sciences and biology. Most of the simplest geometrical observations of bubble clusters have long resisted rigorous mathematical proofs. Geometries can even get more complicated if immiscible fluids are considered. Although they have to fulfill Plateau's laws like soap bubble clusters if the surface tensions are close to unity, this is not the case in general. Whether we consider immiscible fluids clusters or soap type bubble clusters, an interesting question is the existence of stable clusters with topological torus bubbles. We propose to answer the latter numerically with simple numerical examples of stable clusters with bubbles having the topology of a torus, a triple torus, a fivefold torus or an elevenfold torus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02736v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrice Delbary</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dual-unitary shadow tomography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01068</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01068v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a classical shadow tomography protocol based on dual-unitary brick-wall circuits termed ``dual-unitary shadow tomography'' (DUST). To quantify the performance of DUST, we study operator spreading and Pauli weight dynamics in one-dimensional qubit systems, evolved by random two-local dual-unitary gates arranged in a brick-wall structure, ending with a final measurement layer. We do this by deriving general constraints on the Pauli weight transfer matrix and specializing to the case of dual-unitarity. Remarkably, we find that operator spreading in these circuits have a rich structure resembling that of relativistic quantum field theories, with massless chiral excitations that can decay or fuse into each other, which we call left- or right-movers. We develop a mean-field description of the Pauli weight in terms of $\rho(x,t)$, which represents the probability of having nontrivial support at site $x$ and depth $t$ starting from a fixed weight distribution. We develop an equation of state for $\rho(x,t)$ and simulate it numerically using Monte Carlo simulations. For the task of predicting operators with (nearly) full support, we show that DUST outperforms brick-wall Clifford shadows of equivalent depth. This advantage is further pronounced for small system sizes and more generally, our results are robust to finite-size effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01068v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmed A. Akhtar, Namit Anand, Jeffrey Marshall, Yi-Zhuang You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the $q$-generalised multinomial/divergence correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12712v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The asymptotic correspondence between the probability mass function of the $q$-deformed multinomial distribution and the $q$-generalised Kullback-Leibler divergence, also known as Tsallis relative entropy, is established. The probability mass function is generalised using the $q$-deformed algebra developed within the framework of nonextensive statistics, leading to the emergence of a family of divergence measures in the asymptotic limit as the system size increases. The coefficients in the asymptotic expansion yield Tsallis relative entropy as the leading-order term when $q$ is interpreted as an entropic parameter. Furthermore, higher-order expansion coefficients naturally introduce new divergence measures, extending Tsallis relative entropy through a one-parameter generalisation. Some fundamental properties of these extended divergences are also explored.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12712v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0236462</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Math. Phys. 66 (2025) 033302</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Keisuke Okamura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-dimensional magnetic Skyrmions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12190v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a generalization of the theory of magnetic Skyrmions in chiral magnets in two dimensions to a higher-dimensional theory with magnetic Skyrmions in three dimensions and an $S^3$ target space, requiring a 4-dimensional magnetization vector. A physical realization of our theory could be made using a synthetic dimension, recently promoted and realized in condensed matter physics. In the simplest incarnation of the theory, we find a Skyrmion and a sphaleron - the latter being an unstable soliton. Including also the Skyrme term in the theory enriches the spectrum to a small metastable Skyrmion, an unstable sphaleron and a large stable Skyrmion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12190v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP03(2025)016</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 2503:016, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sven Bjarke Gudnason, Stefano Bolognesi, Roberto Menta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gapped Phases in (2+1)d with Non-Invertible Symmetries: Part II</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20440v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We use the Symmetry Topological Field Theory (SymTFT) to systematically characterize gapped phases in 2+1 dimensions with categorical symmetries. The SymTFTs that we consider are (3+1)d Dijkgraaf-Witten (DW) theories for finite groups $G$, whose gapped boundaries realize all so-called ``All Bosonic type" fusion 2-category symmetries. In arXiv:2408.05266 we provided the general framework and studied the case where $G$ is an abelian group. In this work we focus on the case of non-Abelian $G$. Gapped boundary conditions play a central role in the SymTFT construction of symmetric gapped phases. These fall into two broad families: minimal and non-minimal boundary conditions, respectively. The first kind corresponds to boundaries on which all line operators are obtainable as boundary projections of bulk line operators. The symmetries on such boundaries include (anomalous) 2-groups and 2-representation categories of 2-groups. Conversely non-minimal boundaries contain line operators that are intrinsic to the boundaries. The symmetries on such boundaries correspond to fusion 2-categories where modular tensor categories intertwine non-trivially with the above symmetry types. We discuss in detail the generalized charges of these symmetries and their condensation patterns that give rise to a zoo of rich beyond-Landau gapped phases. Among these are phases that exhibit novel patterns of symmetry breaking wherein the symmetry broken vacua carry distinct kinds of topological order. We exemplify this framework for the case where $G$ is a dihedral group.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20440v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lakshya Bhardwaj, Sakura Schafer-Nameki, Apoorv Tiwari, Alison Warman</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
