<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MP updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP</link>
    <description>math.MP updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MP" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 05:00:53 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Link in $\mathbb{R}\mathbb{P}^3$ and the Topological Vertex</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12566v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide the first computations of colored unknots and Hopf link in $\mathbb{R}\mathbb{P}^3$ using both the topological vertex and its refinement. Our approach utilizes the toric Calabi-Yau threefold arising from the geometric transition of the cotangent bundle of $\mathbb{R}\mathbb{P}^3$ under the large $N$ duality. We find that the link invariants are series in the Kahler parameters of the toric Calabi-Yau manifold and the $q$-expansions of the rational functions of the series have positivity property. We conjecture that they are Poincare series of an infinite dimensional link homology theory for links in $\mathbb{R}\mathbb{P}^3$. We compare our results with that of the $S^3$ and speculate the consequences of the series nature of the invariants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12566v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Chae</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The BCS-Bogoliubov gap equation with external magnetic field and the first-order phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12609v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We deal with a type I superconductor in a constant external magnetic field. We obtain the BCS-Bogoliubov gap equation with external magnetic field and apply the implicit function theorem to it. We show that there is a unique magnetic field (the critical magnetic field) given by a smooth function of the temperature and that there is also a unique nonnegative solution (the gap function) given by a smooth function of both the temperature and the external magnetic field. Using the grand potential, we show that the transition from the normal state to the superconducting state in a type I superconductor is of the first order. Moreover we obtain the explicit expression for the entropy gap.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12609v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1751-8121/ada743</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Physics A: Mathematical and Theoretical 58 (2025) 045203</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shuji Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The multiplicative constant in asymptotics of higher-order analogues of the Tracy-Widom distribution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12679v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we are concerned with higher-order analogues of the Tracy-Widom distribution, which describe the eigenvalue distributions in unitary random matrix models near critical edge points. The associated kernels are constructed by functions related to the even members of the Painlev\'{e} I hierarchy $\mathrm{P_{I}^{2k}}, k\in\mathbb{N}^{+}$, and are regarded as higher-order analogues of the Airy kernel. We present a novel approach to establish the multiplicative constant in the large gap asymptotics of the distribution, resolving an open problem in the work of Clayes, Its and Krasovsky. An important new feature of the expression is the involvement of an integral of the Hamiltonian associated with a special, real, pole-free solution for $\mathrm{P_{I}^{2k}}$. In addition, we show that the total integral of the Hamiltonian vanishes for all $k$, and establish a transition from the higher-order Tracy-Widom distribution to the classical one in the asymptotic regime. Our approach can also be adapted to calculate similar critical constants in other problems arising from mathematical physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12679v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Dai, Wen-Gao Long, Shuai-Xia Xu, Lu-Ming Yao, Lun Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Achronal localization and representation of the causal logic from conserved current, application to massive scalar boson</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12699v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Covariant achronal localizations are gained out of covariant conserved currents computing their flux passing through achronal surfaces. This general method applies to the probability density currents with causal kernel regarding the massive scalar boson. Due to the one-to-one correspondence between (covariant) achronal localizations and (covariant) representations of the causal logic thus, apparently for the first time, a covariant representation of the causal logic for an elementary relativistic quantum mechanical system has been achieved. Similarly one derives the covariant family of representations of the causal logic related to the stress energy tensor of the massive scalar boson. While reaching this result the divergence theorem is proven for open sets with almost Lipschitz boundary.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12699v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Domenico P. L. Castrigiano, Carmine De Rosa, Valter Moretti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Euler--Poincar\'e reduction and the Kelvin--Noether theorem for discrete mechanical systems with advected parameters and additional dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12940v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Euler--Poincar\'e equations, firstly introduced by Henri Poincar\'e in 1901, arise from the application of Lagrangian mechanics to systems on Lie groups that exhibit symmetries, particularly in the contexts of classical mechanics and fluid dynamics. These equations have been extended to various settings, such as semidirect products, advected parameters, and field theory, and have been widely applied to mechanics and physics. In this paper, we introduce the discrete Euler--Poincar\'e reduction for discrete Lagrangian systems on Lie groups with advected parameters and additional dynamics, utilizing the group difference map technique. Specifically, the group difference map is defined using either the Cayley transform or the matrix exponential. The continuous and discrete Kelvin--Noether theorems are extended accordingly, that account for Kelvin--Noether quantities of the corresponding continuous and discrete Euler--Poincar\'e equations. As an application, we show both continuous and discrete Euler--Poincar\'e formulations about the dynamics of underwater vehicles, followed by numerical simulations. Numerical results illustrate the scheme's ability to preserve geometric properties over extended time intervals, highlighting its potential for practical applications in the control and navigation of underwater vehicles, as well as in other domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12940v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yusuke Ono, Simone Fiori, Linyu Peng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Edge spectrum for truncated $\mathbb{Z}_2$-insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13096v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fermionic time-reversal-invariant insulators in two dimensions -- class AII in the Kitaev table -- come in two different topological phases. These are characterized by a $\mathbb{Z}_2$-index: the Fu-Kane-Mele index. We prove that if two such insulators with different indices occupy regions containing arbitrarily large balls, then the spectrum of the resulting operator fills the bulk spectral gap. Our argument follows a proof by contradiction developed in an earlier work by two of the authors for quantum Hall systems. It boils down to showing that the $\mathbb{Z}_2$-index can be computed only from bulk information in sufficiently large balls. This is achieved via a result of independent interest: a local trace formula for the $\mathbb{Z}_2$-index.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13096v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexis Drouot, Jacob Shapiro, Xiaowen Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncommutative Boussinesq and NLS type 2- and 3-simplex maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12462v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We construct noncommutative maps related to the Boussinesq and Nonlinear Schr\"odinger (NLS) equations with their variables belonging to a noncommutative division ring. We show that the noncommutative Boussinesq type map satisfies the Yang--Baxter equation, and it can be squeezed down to a noncommutative version of the Boussinesq lattice equation. Moreover, we show that the noncommutative NLS type map is a Zamolodchikov tetrahedron map.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12462v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Konstantinou-Rizos, A. A. Kutuzova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limit shape of the leaky Abelian sandpile model with multiple layers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12664</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12664v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we study a triple generalization of the Leaky Abelian Sandpile Model (LASM) of Alevy and Mkrtchyan, originally analyzed in the case of the square lattice in dimension two. First, we work in any dimension. Second, each site can hold several different stacks of sand, one for each of a certain given number of different layers or colors. Third, when a stack of one color at a site topples, it can send sand not only to its nearest neighbors in equal amounts, but to all possible locations and colors, according to a fixed but arbitrary mass distribution. Stacks of different colors can topple according to different distributions and different leakiness parameters, however the toppling rule should be site-independent. We obtain three main results. First, in this generality, when the LASM is started with $N$ grains of sand in one color at the origin, the final stable configuration, after scaling down by $\log N$, converges to a limit shape as $N$ goes to infinity. Second, when the leakiness parameter converges to infinity and the toppling distribution has finite range, the limit shape converges to a polytope. Third, when the leakiness parameters converge to one, which means the leakiness disappears, the limit shape of the sandpile converges to an ellipsoid. From a technical point of view, we rely on a strong relation between the Green function for random walk and the shape of the sandpile. Finally, the limit shape exhibits interesting duality properties, which we also investigate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12664v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Th\'eo Ballu, C\'edric Boutillier, Sevak Mkrtchyan, Kilian Raschel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kink dynamics for the Yang-Mills field in an extremal Reissner-Nordstr\"om black hole</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12790v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Considered in this work is the Yang-Mills field in an extremal Reissner-Nordstr\"om black hole, a physically motivated mathematical model introduced by Bizo\'n and Kahl. The kink is a fundamental, strongly unstable stationary solution in this non-perturbative, variable coefficients model, with a polynomial tail and no explicit form. In this paper, we introduce and extend several virial techniques, adapt them to the inhomogeneous medium setting, and construct a finite codimensional manifold of the energy space where the kink is asymptotically stable. In particular, we handle, using virial techniques, the emergence of a weak threshold resonance in the description of the stable manifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12790v1</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ignacio Acevedo, Claudio Mu\~noz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability of fluids in spacetimes with decelerated expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12798v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove the nonlinear stability of homogeneous barotropic perfect fluid solutions in fixed cosmological spacetimes undergoing decelerated expansion. The results hold provided a specific inequality between the speed of sound of the fluid and the expansion rate of spacetime is valid. Numerical studies in our earlier complementary paper provide strong evidence that the aforementioned condition is sharp, i.e. that instabilities occur when the inequality is violated. In this regard, our present result covers the regime of slowest possible expansion which allows for fluids to stabilize, depending on their speed of sound. Our proof relies on an energy functional which is universal in the sense that it also applies to the case of linear expansion and enables a significantly simplified proof of bounds for fluids on linearly expanding spacetimes. Finally, we consider the special cases of dust and radiation fluids in the decelerated regime and prove shock formation for arbitrarily small perturbations of homogeneous solutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12798v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Fajman, Maximilian Ofner, Todd Oliynyk, Zoe Wyatt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bispectrality of the sieved Jacobi polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12806</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12806v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: It is shown that the CMV Laurent polynomials associated to the sieved Jacobi polynomials on the unit circle satisfy an eigenvalue equation with respect to a first order differential operator of Dunkl type. Using this result, the sieved Jacobi polynomials on the real line are found to be eigenfunctions of a Dunkl differential operator of second order. Eigenvalue equations for the sieved ultraspherical polynomials of the first and second kind are obtained as special cases. These results mean that the sieved Jacobi polynomials (either on the unit circle or on the real line) are bispectral.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12806v1</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luc Vinet, Alexei Zhedanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perturbations of embedded eigenvalues of asymptotically periodic magnetic Schr\"odinger operators on a cylinder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12817v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the persistence of embedded eigenvalues for a class of magnetic Laplacians on an infinite cylindrical domain. The magnetic potential is assumed to be $C^2$ and asymptotically periodic along the unbounded direction, with an algebraic decay rate towards a periodic background potential. Under the condition that the embedded eigenvalue of the unperturbed operator lies away from the thresholds of the continuous spectrum, we show that the set of nearby potentials for which the embedded eigenvalue persists forms a smooth manifold of finite and even codimension. The proof employs tools from Floquet theory, exponential dichotomies, and Lyapunov--Schmidt reduction. Additionally, we give an example of a potential which satisfies the assumptions of our main theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12817v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas Jansen, Sara Maad Sasane, Wilhelm Treschow</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differential and other reductions of the self-dual conformal structure equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12858</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12858v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The dispersionless integrable system we consider here was introduced to the literature rather recently, it is connected with the general local form of self-dual conformal structure (SDCS) for the signature (2,2). In integrability framework this system possesses a rich structure of reductions, including differential reductions. We will discuss several characteristic reductions for this system, using the Lax pair, hierarchy structure and the dressing scheme. We use reductions to construct solutions for the SDCS equations. One of our goals is to present type B SDCS system and consider its relations with the SDCS system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12858v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. V. Bogdanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Complex hidden symmetries in real spacetime and their algebraic structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12960v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Considering real spacetime as a Lorentzian fiber in a complex manifold, there is a mismatch of the elementary linear representations of their symmetry groups, the real and complex Poincar\'{e} groups. No spinors are allowed as linear irreducible representations for the complex case, but when a spin$^{h}$ structure is implemented on the associated principal bundles, one is naturally led to an algebraic structure similar to the one of the standard model. This last (dynamical) structure might therefore be inherited from the kinematical symmetries of a larger space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12960v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>R. Vilela Mendes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete Lagrangian multiforms for ABS equations I: quad equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13012v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Discrete Lagrangian multiform theory is a variational perspective on lattice equations that are integrable in the sense of multidimensional consistency. The Lagrangian multiforms for the equations of the ABS classification formed the start of this theory, but the Lagrangian multiforms that are usually considered in this context produce equations that are slightly weaker than the ABS equations. In this work, we present alternative Lagrangian multiforms that have Euler-Lagrange equations equivalent to the ABS equations.
  In addition, the treatment of the ABS Lagrangian multiforms in the existing literature fails to acknowledge that the complex functions in their definitions have branch cuts. The choice of branch affects both the existence of an additive three-leg form for the ABS equations and the closure property of the Lagrangian multiforms. We give counterexamples for both these properties, but we recover them by including integer-valued fields, related to possible the branch choices, in the action sums.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13012v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacob J. Richardson, Mats Vermeeren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient simulation of parametrized quantum circuits under non-unital noise through Pauli backpropagation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13050v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: As quantum devices continue to grow in size but remain affected by noise, it is crucial to determine when and how they can outperform classical computers on practical tasks. A central piece in this effort is to develop the most efficient classical simulation algorithms possible. Among the most promising approaches are Pauli backpropagation algorithms, which have already demonstrated their ability to efficiently simulate certain classes of parameterized quantum circuits-a leading contender for near-term quantum advantage-under random circuit assumptions and depolarizing noise. However, their efficiency was not previously established for more realistic non-unital noise models, such as amplitude damping, that better capture noise on existing hardware. Here, we close this gap by adapting Pauli backpropagation to non-unital noise, proving that it remains efficient even under these more challenging conditions. Our proof leverages a refined combinatorial analysis to handle the complexities introduced by non-unital channels, thus strengthening Pauli backpropagation as a powerful tool for simulating near-term quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13050v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Victor Martinez, Armando Angrisani, Ekaterina Pankovets, Omar Fawzi, Daniel Stilck Fran\c{c}a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Irreducible matrix representations for the walled Brauer algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13067v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper investigates the representation theory of the algebra of partially transposed permutation operators, $\mathcal{A}^d_{p,p}$, which provides a matrix representation for the abstract walled Brauer algebra. This algebra has recently gained significant attention due to its relevance in quantum information theory, particularly in the efficient quantum circuit implementation of the mixed Schur-Weyl transform. In contrast to previous Gelfand-Tsetlin type approaches, our main technical contribution is the explicit construction of irreducible matrix units in the second-highest ideal that are group-adapted to the action of $\mathbb{C}[\mathcal{S}_p]\times \mathbb{C}[\mathcal{S}_p]$ subalgebra, where $\mathcal{S}_p$ is the symmetric group. This approach suggests a recursive method for constructing irreducible matrix units in the remaining ideals of the algebra. The framework is general and applies to systems with arbitrary numbers of components and local dimensions. The obtained results are applied to a special class of operators motivated by the mathematical formalism appearing in all variants of the port-based teleportation protocols through the mixed Schur-Weyl duality. We demonstrate that the given irreducible matrix units are, in fact, eigenoperators for the considered class.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13067v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Micha{\l} Studzi\'nski, Tomasz M{\l}ynik, Marek Mozrzymas, Micha{\l} Horodecki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multicomplex Ideals, Modules and Hilbert Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.04683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.04683v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article we study some algebraic aspects of multicomplex numbers $\mathbb M_n$. For $n\geq 2$ a canonical representation is defined in terms of the multiplication of $n-1$ idempotent elements. This representation facilitates computations in this algebra and makes it possible to introduce a generalized conjugacy $\Lambda_n$, i.e. a composition of the $n$ multicomplex conjugates $\Lambda_n:=\dagger_1\cdots \dagger_n$, as well as a multicomplex norm. The ideals of the ring of multicomplex numbers are then studied in details, free $\mathbb M_n$-modules and their linear operators are considered and, finally, we develop Hilbert spaces on the multicomplex algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.04683v4</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00006-025-01373-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advances in Applied Clifford Algebras, Volume 35, Article 9 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Derek Courchesne, S\'ebastien Tremblay</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Linear Criterion for an Upper Bound on the Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer Critical Temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.00796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.00796v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Since Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer theory of superconductivity is non-linear, it is difficult to study superconducting properties analytically. There is a more tractable linear criterion which determines a temperature $T_l$ below which the system is superconducting. Here, we observe that there is a similar linear criterion which gives a temperature $T_u$ above which no superconductivity occurs. We provide examples of translation invariant systems where $T_u&gt;T_l$ as well as systems where $T_u=T_l$. Furthermore, we estimate $T_u$ for half-spaces and show that it is exponentially small in the weak coupling limit, exhibiting the same asymptotics as the critical temperature for full space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.00796v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0230179</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Math. Phys. 1 January 2025; 66 (1): 011901</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Barbara Roos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of metastable states in many-body quantum systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.05261</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.05261v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a mathematical theory of metastable pure states in closed many-body quantum systems with finite-dimensional Hilbert space. Given a Hamiltonian, a pure state is defined to be metastable when all sufficiently local operators either stabilize the state, or raise its average energy. We prove that short-range entangled metastable states are necessarily eigenstates (scars) of a perturbatively close Hamiltonian. Given any metastable eigenstate of a Hamiltonian, in the presence of perturbations, we prove the presence of prethermal behavior: local correlation functions decay at a rate bounded by a time scale nonperturbatively long in the inverse metastability radius, rather than Fermi's Golden Rule. Inspired by this general theory, we prove that the lifetime of the false vacuum in certain $d$-dimensional quantum models grows at least as fast as $\exp(\epsilon^{-d} )$, where $\epsilon\rightarrow 0$ is the relative energy density of the false vacuum; this lower bound matches, for the first time, explicit calculations using quantum field theory. We identify metastable states at finite energy density in the PXP model, along with exponentially many metastable states in "helical" spin chains and the two-dimensional Ising model. Our inherently quantum formalism reveals precise connections between many problems, including prethermalization, robust quantum scars, and quantum nucleation theory, and applies to systems without known semiclassical and/or field theoretic limits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.05261v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao Yin, Federica M. Surace, Andrew Lucas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Achronal Localization, Representations of the Causal Logic for massive systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.08082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.08082v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: On plain physical grounds localization of relativistic quantum particles is extended to the achronal regions of Minkowski spacetime. Achronal localization fulfills automatically the requirements of causality. It constitutes the frame which complies most completely with the principle of causality for quantum mechanical systems. Achronal localization is equivalent to the localization in the regions of the causal logic. Representations of the causal logic are constructed for the systems with mass spectrum of positive Lebesgue measure and every definite spin. Apparently no representation of the causal logic for a real mass system has been achieved in the past.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.08082v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Domenico P. L. Castrigiano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational closures for composite homogenised fluid flows</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10408v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Homogenisation theory has seen recent application in the derivation of stochastic transport models for fluids dynamics. In this work, we first construct the Lagrange-to-Euler map of an ideal fluid flow, modelled by a stochastic flow of diffeomorphism, as the deterministic homogenized limit of a parameterized flow map that decomposes into rapidly fluctuating and slow components. Specifically, we prove the convergence of this parameterized map to a scale-separated limit under the assumptions of a weak-invariance principle for the rapidly fluctuating component and path continuity for the slow component. In this limit, the rapidly fluctuating component becomes a stochastic flow of diffeomorphism that can introduce stochastic transport into the dynamics of the slow component, which remains to be closed.
  The second contribution of this work formulates two distinct types of variational closures for the slow component of the homogenized flow whilst utilising the composite structure of the full stochastic flow. In one case, the critical points of the new principle satisfy a system of random partial differential equations equivalent to a system of stochastic partial differential equations (SPDEs) under stochastic transport via a transformation by the stochastic flow. Additionally, we show these equations are stochastic Euler-Poincar\'e equations previously derived in Holm, Proc. Royal Soc. (2015). In the other case, we modify the assumptions on the slow component of composite flow and the associated variational principle to derive averaged models inspired by previous work such as Generalised Lagrangian Mean (GLM) and Lagrangian Average Euler Poincar\'e (LAEP).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10408v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Theo Diamantakis, Ruiao Hu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The HOMFLY-PT polynomial and HZ factorisation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04933</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04933v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Harer-Zagier (HZ) transform maps the HOMFLY-PT polynomial into a rational function. For some special knots and links, the latter admits a simple factorised form, which is referred to as HZ factorisation. This property is preserved under full twists and concatenation with the Jucys-Murphy braid, which are hence used to generate infinite HZ-factorisable families. For such families, the HOMFLY-PT polynomial can be fully encoded in two sets of integers, corresponding to the numerator and denominator exponents, which turn out to be related to the Khovanov homology and its Euler characteristics. Moreover, a relation between the HOMFLY-PT and Kauffman polynomials, which was originally found for torus knots, is now proven for several such families. Interestingly, this relation is equivalent to the vanishing of the two-crosscap BPS invariants in topological string theory. It is conjectured that the HOMFLY-PT-Kauffman relation provides a criterion for HZ factorisability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04933v3</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andreani Petrou, Shinobu Hikami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-inhomogeneous KPZ equation from non-equilibrium Ginzburg-Landau SDEs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.01499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.01499v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a framework, which is a mesoscopic-fluctuation-scale analog of Yau's method [46] for hydrodynamic limits, for deriving KPZ equations with time-dependent coefficients from time-inhomogeneous interacting particle systems. To our knowledge, this is the first derivation of a time-inhomogeneous KPZ equation whose solution theory has an additional nonlinearity that is absent in the time-homogeneous case. So, we also show global well-posedness for the SPDE. To be concrete, we restrict to time-inhomogeneous Ginzburg-Landau SDEs. The method for deriving KPZ is based on a Cole-Hopf transform, whose analysis is the bulk of this paper. The key ingredient for said analysis is a ``local" second-order Boltzmann-Gibbs principle, shown by stochastic calculus of the Ginzburg-Landau SDEs and regularity estimates for their Kolmogorov equations, all of which likely generalizes to many other particle systems. This addresses a ``Big Picture Question" in [47] on deriving KPZ equations. It is also, to our knowledge, a first result on KPZ-type limits in a non-equilibrium like that in [6].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.01499v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Eigenvalues and resonances of dissipative acoustic operator for strictly convex obstacles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.01192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.01192v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We examine the wave equation in the exterior of a strictly convex bounded domain $K$ with dissipative boundary condition $\partial_{\nu} u - \gamma(x) \partial_t u = 0$ on the boundary $\Gamma$ and $0 &lt; \gamma(x) &lt;1, \:\forall x \in \Gamma.$ The solutions are described by a contraction semigroup $V(t) = e^{tG}, \: t \geq 0.$ The poles $\lambda$ of the meromorphic incoming resolvent $(G - \lambda)^{-1}: \:{ \mathcal H}_{comp} \rightarrow {\mathcal D}_{loc}$ are eigenvalues of G if ${\rm Re}\: \lambda &lt; 0$ and incoming resonances if ${\rm Re}\: \lambda &gt; 0$. We obtain sharper results for the location of the eigenvalues of $G$ and incoming resonances in $\Lambda = \{\lambda \in \mathbb C:\: |{\rm Re}\: \lambda| \leq C_2(1 + |{\rm Im}\: \lambda|)^{-2},\: |{\rm Im}\: \lambda| \geq A_2 &gt; 1\}$ and we prove a Weyl formula for their asymptotic. For $K = \{x \in {\mathbb R}^3:\:|x| \leq 1\}$ and $\gamma$ constant we show that $G$ has no eigenvalues so the Weyl formula concerns only the incoming resonances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.01192v3</guid>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vesselin Petkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nicolai maps with four-fermion interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.19946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.19946v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Nicolai maps offer an alternative description of supersymmetric theories via nonlinear and nonlocal transformations characterized by the so-called `free-action' and `determinant-matching' conditions. The latter expresses the equality of the Jacobian determinant of the transformation with the one obtained by integrating out the fermions, which so far have been considered only to quadratic terms. We argue that such a restriction is not substantial, as Nicolai maps can be constructed for arbitrary nonlinear sigma models, which feature four-fermion interactions. The fermionic effective one-loop action then gets generalized to higher loops and the perturbative tree expansion of such Nicolai maps receives quantum corrections in the form of fermion loop decorations. The `free-action condition' continues to hold for the classical map, but the `determinant-matching condition' is extended to an infinite hierarchy in fermion loop order. After general considerations for sigma models in four dimensions, we specialize to the case of $\mathbb{C}\mathrm{P}^N$ symmetric spaces and construct the associated Nicolai map. These sigma models admit a formulation with only quadratic fermions via an auxiliary vector field, which does not simplify our analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.19946v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. High Energ. Phys. 2023, 132 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Casarin, Olaf Lechtenfeld, Maximilian Rupprecht</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Wigdersons' approach to the uncertainty principle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.17438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.17438v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We revisit the uncertainty principle from the point of view suggested by A. Wigderson and Y. Wigderson. This approach is based on a primary uncertainty principle from which one can derive several inequalities expressing the impossibility of a simultaneous sharp localization in time and frequency. Moreover, it requires no specific properties of the Fourier transform and can therefore be easily applied to all operators satisfying the primary uncertainty principle. A. Wigderson and Y. Wigderson also suggested many generalizations to higher dimensions and stated several conjectures which we address in the present paper. We argue that we have to consider a more general primary uncertainty principle to prove the results suggested by the authors. As a by-product we obtain some new inequalities akin to the Cowling-Price uncertainty principle, a generalization of the Heisenberg uncertainty principle, and derive the entropic uncertainty principle from the primary uncertainty principles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.17438v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nuno Costa Dias, Franz Luef, Jo\~ao Nuno Prata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rational Homotopy Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.00939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.00939v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This is a survey of Rational Homotopy Theory, intended for a Mathematical Physics readership.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.00939v2</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/B978-0-323-95703-8.00207-X</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Encyclopedia of Mathematical Physics (Second Edition), volume 4, Elsevier, 2025, 24-38</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alexander A. Voronov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some properties of a non-hydrostatic stochastic oceanic primitive equations model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02289</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02289v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study how relaxing the classical hydrostatic balance hypothesis affects theoretical aspects of the LU primitive equations well-posedness. We focus on models that sit between incompressible 3D LU Navier-Stokes equations and standard LU primitive equations, aiming for numerical manageability while capturing non-hydrostatic phenomena. Our main result concerns the well-posedness of a specific stochastic interpretation of the LU primitive equations. This holds with rigid-lid type boundary conditions, and when the horizontal component of noise is independent of z. In fact these conditions can be related to the dynamical regime in which the primitive equations remain valid. Moreover, under these conditions, we show that the LU primitive equations solution tends toward the one of the deterministic primitive equations for a vanishing noise, thus providing a physical coherence to the LU stochastic model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02289v3</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnaud Debussche, \'Etienne M\'emin, Antoine Moneyron</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>5d-4d Correspondence in Twisted M-theory on a Conifold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.04849</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.04849v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study twisted M-theory in a general conifold background, and describe it in terms of a 5d non-commutative Chern-Simons-matter theory, which is equivalent to 5d non-commutative Chern-Simons theory for a supergroup. In an equivalent description as twisted type IIA string theory, the matter degrees of freedom arise from topological strings stretched between stacks of D6-branes. In order to study 5d Chern-Simons-matter theories with a boundary, we first construct and investigate the properties of a 4d non-commutative gauged chiral WZW model. We prove the gauge invariant coupling of this 4d theory to the bulk 5d Chern-Simons theory defined on $\mathbb{R}_+ \times \mathbb{C}^2 $, and further generalize our results to the 5d Chern-Simons-matter theory. We also investigate the toroidal current algebra of the 4d chiral WZW model that arises from radial quantization along one of the complex planes. Finally, we show that a gauged non-commutative chiral 4d WZW model arises from the partition function for quantum 5d non-commutative Chern-Simons theory with boundaries in the BV-BFV formalism, and further generalize this 5d-4d correspondence to the 5d non-commutative Chern-Simons-matter theory for the case of adjoint matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.04849v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Meer Ashwinkumar, Mir Faizal, Arshid Shabir, Douglas J. Smith, Yehao Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Construction of Lie algebra weight system kernel via Vogel algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14417</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14417v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a method of constructing a kernel of Lie algebra weight system. A main tool we use in the analysis is Vogel's $\Lambda$ algebra and the surrounding framework. As an example of a developed technique we explicitly provide all Jacobi diagrams lying in the kernel of $\mathfrak{sl}_N$ weight system at low orders. We also discuss consequences of the presence of the kernel in Lie algebra weight systems for detection of correlators in the 3D Chern-Simons topological field theory and for distinguishing of knots by the corresponding quantum knot invariants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14417v2</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmitry Khudoteplov, Elena Lanina, Alexey Sleptsov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-Dual Gauge Theory from the Top Down</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02680v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a family of dualities between certain non-supersymmetric self-dual gauge theories on a large class of $4d$ self-dual asymptotically flat backgrounds, and the large $N$ limit of an independently defined $2d$ chiral defect CFT. Our construction goes via twisted holography for the type I topological string on a Calabi-Yau five-fold which fibres over twistor space. In particular, we show that single-trace operators of the $2d$ defect CFT are in bijection with states of the celestial chiral algebra. We match the operator products of these states with the collinear splitting amplitudes of the self-dual gauge theory up to one-loop. Assigning vacuum expectations to central operators in the boundary theory computes bulk amplitudes on self-dual backgrounds. We are able to extract form factors from these amplitudes, which we use to give a simple closed formula for certain $n$-point two-loop all $+$ amplitudes in $\mathrm{SU}(K) \times \mathrm{SU}(R)$ gauge theory coupled to bifundamental massless fermions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02680v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roland Bittleston, Kevin Costello, Keyou Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct and inverse spectral problems for the Schrodinger operator with double generalized Regge boundary conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20642</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20642v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we study the direct and inverse spectral problems for the Schrodinger operator with two generalized Regge boundary conditions. For the direct problem, we give the properties of the spectrum, including the asymptotic distribution of the eigenvalues. For the inverse problems, we prove several uniqueness theorems, including the cases: even potential, two-spectra, as well as the general partial inverse problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20642v2</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Chuan Xu, Yu-Ting Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The density conjecture for Juddian points for the quantum Rabi model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12105v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study doubly degenerate (Juddian) eigenvalues for the Quantum Rabi Hamiltonian, a simple model of the interaction between a two-level atom and a single quantized mode of light. We prove a strong form of the density conjecture of Kimoto, Reyes-Bustos, and Wakayama, showing that any fixed value of the splitting between the two atomic levels, there is a dense set of coupling strengths for which the corresponding Rabi Hamiltonian admits Juddian eigenvalues. We also construct infinitely many sets of parameters for which the Rabi Hamiltonian admits two distinct Juddian eigenvalues. The fine structure of the zeros of classical Laguerre polynomials plays a key role in our methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12105v2</guid>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rishi Kumar, Ze\'ev Rudnick</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
