<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.AO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.AO</link>
    <description>nlin.AO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.AO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 04:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Finite-size effect in Kuramoto phase oscillators with higher-order interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.16049</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.16049v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Finite-size systems of Kuramoto model display intricate dynamics, especially in the presence of multi-stability where both coherent and incoherent states coexist. We investigate such scenario in globally coupled populations of Kuramoto phase oscillators with higher-order interactions, and observe that fluctuations inherent to finite-size systems drives the transition to the synchronized state occurring before the critical point in the thermodynamic limit. Using numerical methods, we plot the first exit time distribution of the magnitude of complex order parameter and obtain numerical transition probabilities across various system sizes. Further, we extend this study to a two-population oscillator system, and using velocity field of the associated order parameters, show the emergence of a new fixed point corresponding to a partially synchronized state arising due to the finite-size effect which is absent in the thermodynamics limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.16049v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayushi Suman, Sarika Jalan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A least-squares Galerkin approach to gradient recovery for Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman equation with Cordes coefficients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.07583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.07583v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a conforming finite element method to approximate the strong solution of the second order Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman equation with Dirichlet boundary and coefficients satisfying Cordes condition. We show the convergence of the continuum semismooth Newton method for the fully nonlinear Hamilton-Jacobi-Bellman equation. Applying this linearization for the equation yields a recursive sequence of linear elliptic boundary value problems in nondivergence form. We deal numerically with such BVPs via the least-squares gradient recovery of Lakkis &amp; Mousavi [2021, arxiv:1909.00491]. We provide an optimal-rate apriori and aposteriori error bounds for the approximation. The aposteriori error are used to drive an adaptive refinement procedure. We close with computer experiments on uniform and adaptive meshes to reconcile the theoretical findings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.07583v2</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Omar Lakkis, Amireh Mousavi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical Theory for Adaptive Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.01403</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.01403v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The investigation of adaptive dynamics, involving many degrees of freedom on two separated timescales, one for fast changes of state variables and another for the slow adaptation of parameters controlling the former's dynamics is crucial for understanding feedback mechanisms underlying evolutionary and learning processes. We present an extension of the Martin-Siggia-Rose-DeDominicis-Janssen (MSRDJ) path-integral approach to the study of nonequilibrium phase transitions in such dynamical systems. As an illustration, we apply our framework to biological adaptation under the genotype-phenotype feedback: phenotypic variations are shaped by the fast stochastic gene-expression dynamics and are coupled to the slow evolution of the distribution of genotypes, each encoded by a gene-regulatory network architecture. We establish that under this coevolution, genotypes responsible for high fitness are selected, leading to the emergence of phenotypic robustness within an intermediate level of environmental noise in reciprocal genetic networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.01403v4</guid>
      <category>q-bio.PE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tuan Minh Pham, Kunihiko Kaneko</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
