<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.AO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.AO</link>
    <description>nlin.AO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.AO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 04:01:18 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Boltzmann approach to collective motion via non-local visual interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.09917</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.09917v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Visual cues play crucial roles in the collective motion of animals, birds, fish, and insects. The interaction mediated by visual information is essentially non-local and has many-body nature due to occlusion, which poses a challenging problem in modeling the emergent collective behavior. In this Letter, we introduce a Boltzmann-equation approach incorporating non-local visual interaction. Occlusion is treated in a self-consistent manner via a coarse-grained density field, which renders the interaction effectively pairwise. Our model also incorporates the recent finding that each organism stochastically selects a neighbor to interact at each instant. We analytically derive the order-disorder transition point, and show that the visual screening effect substantially raises the transition threshold, which does not vanish when the density of the agents or the range of the intrinsic interaction is taken to infinity. Our analysis suggests that the model exhibits a discontinuous transition as in the local interaction models, and but the discontinuity is weakened by the non-locality. Our study clarifies the essential role of non-locality in the visual interactions among moving organisms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.09917v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Susumu Ito, Nariya Uchida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transient Reviving Dynamics with an Exact Solution for Delay Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.04848</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.04848v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a new approach to examine transient dynamics in a class of non-autonomous delay differential equations. Exact solutions for these equations are obtained using the Lambert W function alongside an appropriately chosen initial function. These solutions provide a reliable approximation for transient dynamics when the initial functions are not markedly distinct. We explore a non-autonomous equation that exhibits a distinctive phenomenon of reviving dynamics as an illustrative example. The derived exact solutions effectively encapsulate the qualitative characteristics of this reviving dynamics over various delay values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.04848v3</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.93.094801</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of the Physical Society of Japan, vol. 93, 094801 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kenta Ohira, Toru Ohira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A ubiquitous transfer function links interacting elements to emerging property of complex systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03347</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03347v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the field of complex systems, self-organization magnifies the compounding effects of element interactions by propagating, modifying, and enhancing functionality, ultimately leading to emergent system properties. The intricacies of self-organization make unveiling the elusive link between element interactions and emergent system properties akin to finding the proverbial Holy Grail. In the search for identifying a method to predict system-level properties, we used an inductive approach to bypass the self-organization. By observing drug interactions within biological complex system, system property, efficacy, emerged as a smooth response surface in the multi-dimensional space of drug-system interactions, which can be represented by the Complex System Response (CSR) function. This CSR function has been successfully validated across diverse disease models in cell lines, animals, and clinical trials. Notably, the CSR function reveals that biological complex systems exhibit second-order non-linearity. In this study, we generalized the CSR function to physical complex systems, linking maximum compressive yielding stress to impactful manufacturing parameters of the Selective Laser Melting (SLM) process. Remarkably though anticipated, the CSR function reveals the connection between the macroscale system property (compressive yielding stress) and the microstructure during self-organizing process. In addition, the second-order non-linear CSR functions ensure a single global optimum in complex systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03347v3</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lina Yan, Jeffrey Huy Khong, Aleksandar Kostadinov, Jerry Ying Hsi Fuh, Chih-Ming Ho</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
