<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.AO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.AO</link>
    <description>nlin.AO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.AO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 04:04:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Topologically protected edge oscillations in nonlinear dynamical units</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18699</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18699v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Many examples from quantum and classical physics are known where topological protection is responsible for the robustness of the dynamics. Less explored is the role of topological protection in the context of classical oscillatory systems. As on-site dynamics, we consider prototypical oscillator models with possible applications in biochemical systems. However, our choice of coupling geometry is inspired by models from condensed matter physics which -- in isolation -- guarantee non-trivial topology in momentum space. We choose directed couplings between units on a two-dimensional grid, alternating between weak and strong values, such that oscillations become localized at the edges of the grid while bulk units transition to oscillation-death states, resulting in a frequency chimera-like state. These patterns are resilient to parameter mismatches, additive noise, and structural defects. To explain the robustness of these edge oscillations we use topological characteristics and calculate Zak phases. As it turns out, the edge-localized oscillations result from a bulk-boundary correspondence that applies to our system even though our derived effective Hamiltonian is non-Hermitian. By appropriately tuning the system parameters, it is possible to control which regions of the two-dimensional grid are in an oscillatory state and which settle to oscillation-death states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18699v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayantan Nag Chowdhury, Hildegard Meyer-Ortmanns</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-organized Collapse of Societies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17683</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17683v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Why are human societies unstable? Theories based on the observation of recurring patterns in historical data indicate that economic inequality, as well as social factors are key drivers. So far, models of this phenomenon are more macroscopic in nature. However, basic mechanisms at work could be accessible to minimal mathematical models. Here we combine a simple mechanism for economic growth with a mechanism for the spreading of social dissatisfaction. Broad wealth distributions generated by the economic mechanism eventually trigger social unrest and the destruction of wealth, leading to an emerging pattern of boom and bust. We find that the model time scales compare well with empirical data. The model emphasizes the role of broad (power law) wealth distributions for dynamical social phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17683v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexander Jochim, Stefan Bornholdt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pattern Formation in Robotic Mechanical Metamaterial</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.17853</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.17853v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spatio-temporal patterns emerging from an initial quiescent, uniform state is a phenomenon observed in many dynamical systems sustained far from thermodynamic equilibrium, the practical application of which has only recently begun to be explored. As the underlying dynamics are typically complex, pattern formation is often theoretically analyzed and understood via phenomenological models, which effectively represent the causal mechanisms, but obscure the link between the small-scale interactions/processes and the observed macroscopic behavior. Moreover, efforts to prescribe the patterning response are often undercut by the experimental inaccessibility of the small-scale constituents/processes. This article demonstrates an artificial system (i.e., a robotic mechanical metamaterial) as an accessible and versatile platform within which to explore and prescribe the patterning response of non-equilibrium systems. Specifically, in varying a feedback parameter within the prescribed reaction kinetics, the robotic mechanical metamaterial alternately develops spatial and temporal oscillations in the displacement field following a perturbation of the initial quiescent, uniform state. The platform is amenable to a first-principles analytical description so that corresponding theoretical results possess qualitative and quantitative significance, and maintain connection to the specific system parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.17853v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.PS</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vinod Ramakrishnan, Michael J. Frazier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preserving spreading dynamics and information flow in complex network reduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.18641v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Effectively preserving both the structural and dynamical properties during the reduction of complex networks remains a significant research topic. Existing network reduction methods based on renormalization group or sampling often face challenges such as high computational complexity and the loss of critical dynamic attributes. This paper proposes an efficient network reduction framework based on subgraph extraction, which accurately preserves epidemic spreading dynamics and information flow through a coordinated optimization strategy of node removal and edge pruning. Specifically, a degree centrality-driven node removal algorithm is adopted to preferentially remove low-degree nodes, thereby constructing a smaller-scale subnetwork. Subsequently, an edge pruning algorithm is designed to regulate the edge density of the subnetwork, ensuring that its average degree remains approximately consistent with that of the original network. Experimental results on Erd\"os-R\'enyi random graphs, Barab\'asi-Albert scale-free networks, and real-world social contact networks from various domains demonstrate that this proposed method can reduce the size of networks with heterogeneous structures by more than 85%, while preserving their epidemic dynamics and information flow. These findings provide valuable insights for predicting the dynamical behavior of large-scale real-world networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.18641v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Chen, Housheng Su, Yong Wang, Jie Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Taxonomy of Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.11371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.11371v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A prediction makes a claim about a system's future given knowledge of its past. A retrodiction makes a claim about its past given knowledge of its future. The bidirectional machine is an ambidextrous hidden Markov chain that does both optimally by making explicit in its state structure all statistical correlation in a stochastic process. We introduce an informational taxonomy to profile these correlations via a suite of multivariate information measures. While prior results laid out the different kinds of information contained in isolated measurement of a bit, the associated informations were challenging to calculate explicitly. Overcoming this via bidirectional machine states, we expand that analysis to prediction and retrodiction. The result highlights fourteen new interpretable and calculable measures that characterize a process' informational structure. In addition, we introduce a labeling and indexing scheme that systematizes information-theoretic analyses of complex multivariate systems. Operationalizing this, we provide algorithms to directly calculate all of these quantities in closed form for finitely-modeled processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.11371v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandra Jurgens, James P. Crutchfield</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
