<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.AO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.AO</link>
    <description>nlin.AO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.AO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 04:01:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-hyperuniform Critical States of Active Topological Defects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22911v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Topological defects are fundamental to the collective dynamics of non-equilibrium systems and in active matter, mediating spontaneous flows, dynamic self-organization, and emergent pattern formation. Here, we reveal critical states in active nematics, marked by slowed defect density relaxation, amplified fluctuations, and heightened sensitivity to activity. Near criticality, defect interactions become long-ranged, scaling with system size, and the system enters an anti-hyperuniform regime with giant number fluctuations of topological defects and defect clustering. This transition reflects a dual scaling behavior: fluctuations are uniform at small scales but become anti-hyperuniform at larger scales, \tm{as supported by experimental measurements on large-field-of-view endothelial monolayers. We find that these anti-hyperuniform states with multiscale defect density fluctuations are robust to varying parameters, introducing frictional damping, and changing boundary conditions.} Finally, we show that the observed anti-hyperuniformity originates from defect clustering, distinguishing this transition from defect-unbinding or phase separation processes. Beyond fundamental implications for non-equilibrium systems, these results may inform biological contexts where topological defects are integral to processes such as morphogenesis and collective cellular self-organization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22911v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-6633/ae075e</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Simon Guldager Andersen, Tianxiang Ma, Makito F. Katsume, Kexin Li, Xiao Liu, Martin Cramer Pedersen, Amin Doostmohammadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoding the city: multiscale spatial information of urban income</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22954v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Cities are characterized by the coexistence of general aggregate patterns, along with many local variations. This poses challenges for analyses of urban phenomena, which tend to be either too aggregated or too local, depending on the disciplinary approach. Here, we use methods from statistical learning theory to develop a general methodology for quantifying how much information is encoded in the spatial structure of cities at different scales. We illustrate the approach via the multiscale analysis of income distributions in over 900 US metropolitan areas. By treating the formation of diverse neighborhood structures as a process of spatial selection, we quantify the complexity of explanation needed to account for personal income heterogeneity observed across all US urban areas and each of their neighborhoods. We find that spatial selection is strongly dependent on income levels with richer and poorer households appearing spatially more segregated than middle-income groups. We also find that different neighborhoods present different degrees of income specificity and inequality, motivating analysis and theory beyond averages. Our findings emphasize the importance of multiscalar statistical methods that both coarse-grain and fine-grain data to bridge local to global theories of cities and other complex systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22954v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lu\'is M. A. Bettencourt, Ivanna Rodriguez, Jordan T. Kemp, Jos\'e Lobo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coordination Requires Simplification: Thermodynamic Bounds on Multi-Objective Compromise in Natural and Artificial Intelligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23144v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Information-processing systems coordinating across multiple agents and objectives face fundamental thermodynamic constraints. We show that solutions with maximum utility to act as coordination focal points have much higher selection pressure for being findable across agents rather than accuracy. We derive that the information-theoretic minimum description length of coordination protocols to precision $\varepsilon$ scales as $L(P)\geq NK\log_2 K+N^2d^2\log (1/\varepsilon)$ for $N$ agents with $d$ potentially conflicting objectives and internal model complexity $K$. This scaling forces progressive simplification, with coordination dynamics changing the environment itself and shifting optimization across hierarchical levels. Moving from established focal points requires re-coordination, creating persistent metastable states and hysteresis until significant environmental shifts trigger phase transitions through spontaneous symmetry breaking. We operationally define coordination temperature to predict critical phenomena and estimate coordination work costs, identifying measurable signatures across systems from neural networks to restaurant bills to bureaucracies. Extending the topological version of Arrow's theorem on the impossibility of consistent preference aggregation, we find it recursively binds whenever preferences are combined. This potentially explains the indefinite cycling in multi-objective gradient descent and alignment faking in Large Language Models trained with reinforcement learning with human feedback. We term this framework Thermodynamic Coordination Theory (TCT), which demonstrates that coordination requires radical information loss.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23144v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atma Anand</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Replication and Information Extraction in a Minimal Agent-Environment Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23212v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider an unsupervised classifying agent that evolves by enforcing self-consistency of its labels under continual exposure to a data-generating environment. Because the agent's predictions feed back into its own regularized updates, the dynamics can stabilize into self-sustaining modes of operation, which we coin functional replicators. Remarkably, such replicators can spontaneously align with the latent structure of the environment, despite never being exposed to ground-truth labels or selected for adaptation. Using analytical tools from statistical mechanics and numerical experiments, we show that the onset of this regime corresponds to a transition driven by weak correlations between the agent's initial state and environmental structure. Extending the model to multiple agents, we find that their mutual influence can spontaneously break symmetry and produce consensus, illustrating a minimal setting for decentralized collective learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23212v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastiano Ariosto, Jerome Garnier-Brun, Luca Saglietti, Davide Straziota</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synchronization transitions and spike dynamics in a higher-order Kuramoto model with L\'{e}vy noise</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24554v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Synchronization in various complex networks is significantly influenced by higher-order interactions combined with non-Gaussian stochastic perturbations, yet their mechanisms remain mainly unclear. In this paper, we systematically investigate the synchronization and spike dynamics in a higher-order Kuramoto model subjected to non-Gaussian L\'{e}vy noise. Using the mean order parameter, mean first-passage time, and basin stability, we identify clear boundaries distingusihing synchronization and incoherent states under different stability indexes and scale parameters of L\'{e}vy noise. For fixed coupling parameters, synchronization weakens as the stability index decreases, and even completely disappears when the scale parameter exceeds a critical threshold. By varying coupling parameters, we find significant dynamical phenomena including bifurcations and hysteresis. L\'{e}vy noise smooths the synchronization transitions and requires stronger coupling compared to Gaussian white noise. Furthermore, we define spikes and systematically investigate their statistical and spectral characteristics. The maximum number of spikes is observed at small scale parameter. A generalized spectral analysis further reveals burst-like structure via an edit distance algorithm. Moreover, a power-law distribution is observed in the large inter-window intervals of spikes, showing great memory effects. These findings deepen the understanding of synchronization and extreme events in complex networks driven by non-Gaussian L\'{e}vy noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24554v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Zhao, J\"urgen Kurths, Norbert Marwan, Yong Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
