<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.AO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.AO</link>
    <description>nlin.AO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.AO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 02:42:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Robustness of complexity estimation in event-driven signals against accuracy of event detection method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.06168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.06168v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Complexity has gained recent attention in machine learning for its ability to extract synthetic information from large datasets. Complex dynamical systems are characterized by temporal complexity associated with intermittent birth-death events of self-organizing behavior. These rapid transition events (RTEs) can be modelled as a stochastic point process on the time axis, with inter-event times (IETs) revealing rich dynamics. In particular, IETs with power-law distribution mark a departure from the Poisson statistics and indicate the presence of nontrivial complexity that is quantified by the power-law exponent $\mu$ of the IET distribution. However, detection of RTEs in noisy signals remains a challenge, since false positives can obscure the statistical structure of the underlying process. In this paper, we address the problem of quantifying the effect of the event detection tool on the accuracy of complexity estimation. This is reached through a systematic evaluation of the Event-Driven Diffusion Scaling (EDDiS) algorithm, a tool exploiting event-driven diffusion to estimate temporal complexity.After introducing the event detection method RTE-Finder (RTEF), we assess the performance of the RTEF-EDDiS pipeline using event-driven synthetic signals. The reliability of the RTEF is found to strongly depend on parameters such as the percentile and the number of false positives can be much higher than the number of genuine complex events. Despite this, we found that the complexity estimation is quite robust with respect to the rate of false positives. For the power-law distributed IETs with $\mu\le2.5$, the second moment scaling $H$ appears to even improve as the rate of false positives increases, reaching estimation errors of about 4-7%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.06168v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Cafiso, Paolo Paradisi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A bounded confidence model to predict how group work affects student math anxiety</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06351</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06351v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Math anxiety is negatively correlated with student performance and can result in avoidance of further math/STEM classes and careers. Cooperative learning (i.e., group work) is a proven strategy that can reduce math anxiety and has additional social and pedagogical benefits. However, depending on the group individuals, some peer interactions can mitigate anxiety while others exacerbate it. We propose a mathematical modeling approach to help untangle and explore this complex dynamic. We introduce a modification of the Hegselmann-Krause bounded confidence model, including both attractive and repulsive interactions to simulate how math anxiety levels are affected by pairwise student interactions. The model is simple but provides interesting qualitative predictions. In particular, Monte Carlo simulations show that there is an optimal group size to minimize average math anxiety, and that switching group members randomly at certain frequencies can dramatically reduce math anxiety levels. The model is easily adaptable to incorporate additional personal and societal factors, making it ripe for future research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06351v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew S. Mizuhara, Katherine Toms, Maya Williams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collective motion from quantum-inspired dynamics in visual perception</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18985v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a model of collective behavior in self-propelled active agents that incorporates a perceptual decision-making process. In this framework, the decision-making dynamics is modeled using quantum formalism. The perceptual decision state of each agent is an entangled or superposed state of the decision states for the neighboring agents within the vision cone. We suggest that in this framework, the force driving the movement of active agents is governed by the quantum average of its perception operator, providing a bridge between perceptual decision-making processes and classical dynamics. Additionally, we introduce two perceptual measures of cohesion in the flock, namely, perception strength and perceptual energy, to characterize collective behavior in terms of decision-making dynamics. Our model demonstrates that, with an appropriate choice of perceptual decision state, the well-known Vicsek model of flocking behavior can be derived as a specific case of this quantum-inspired approach. This approach provides fresh insights into collective behavior and multi-agent coordination, revealing how classical patterns of collective behavior emerge naturally from perception.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18985v4</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jyotiranjan Beuria, Mayank Chaurasiya, Laxmidhar Behera</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inferring entropy production in many-body systems using nonequilibrium MaxEnt</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10444v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose a method for inferring entropy production (EP) in high-dimensional stochastic systems, including many-body systems and non-Markovian systems with long memory. Standard techniques for estimating EP become intractable in such systems due to computational and statistical limitations. We infer trajectory-level EP and lower bounds on average EP by exploiting a nonequilibrium analogue of the Maximum Entropy principle, along with convex duality. Our approach uses only samples of trajectory observables (such as spatiotemporal correlation functions). It does not require reconstruction of high-dimensional probability distributions or rate matrices, nor any special assumptions such as discrete states or multipartite dynamics. It may be used to compute a hierarchical decomposition of EP, reflecting contributions from different kinds of interactions, and it has an intuitive physical interpretation as a thermodynamic uncertainty relation. We demonstrate its numerical performance on a disordered nonequilibrium spin model with 1000 spins and a large neural spike-train dataset.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10444v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miguel Aguilera, Sosuke Ito, Artemy Kolchinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
