<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nlin.AO updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.AO</link>
    <description>nlin.AO updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nlin.AO" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 05:14:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Internal reliability and anti-reliability in dynamical networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00079v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider finite dynamical networks and define internal reliability according to the synchronization properties of a replicated unit or a set of units. If the states of the replicated units coincide with their prototypes, they are reliable; otherwise, if their states differ, they are anti-reliable. Quantification of reliability with the transversal Lyapunov exponent allows for a straightforward analysis of different models. For a Kuramoto model of globally coupled phase oscillators with a distribution of natural frequencies, we show that prior to the onset of synchronization, peripheral in frequency units are anti-reliable, while central are reliable. For this model, reliability can be expressed via phase correlations in a sort of a fluctuation-dissipation relation. Sufficiently large sub-networks in the Kuramoto model are always anti-reliable; the same holds for a recurrent neural network, where individual units are always reliable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00079v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tommaso Matteuzzi, Franco Bagnoli, Michele Baia, Stefano Iubini, Arkady Pikovsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural controllability and management of cascading regime shifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00206v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Abrupt transitions in ecosystems can be interconnected, raising challenges for science and management in identifying sufficient interventions to prevent them or recover from undesirable shifts. Here we use principles of network controllability to explore how difficult it is to manage coupled regime shifts. We find that coupled regime shifts are easier to manage when they share drivers, but can become harder to manage if new feedbacks are formed when coupled. Simulation experiments showed that both network structure and coupling strength matter in our ability to manage interconnected systems. This theoretical observation calls for an empirical assessment of cascading regime shifts in ecosystems and warns about our limited ability to control cascading effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00206v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Juan Carlos Rocha, Anne-Sophie Cr\'epin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simple mathematical model for a pairing-induced motion of active and passive particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00411v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a simple mathematical model that describes a paring-induced motion of active and passive particles, which is motivated by our previous paper [Ishikawa et al., Phys. Rev. E 106, 024604 (2022)]. We assume the following features; the active and passive particles are connected with a linear spring, the active particle is driven in the direction of the current velocity, and the passive particle is repelled from the active particle. A straight motion, a circular motion, and a slalom motion were observed by numerical simulation. Theoretical analysis reproduces the bifurcation between the straight and circular motions depending on the magnitude of self-propulsion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00411v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiroaki Ishikawa, Yuki Koyano, Hiroaki Ito, Yutaka Sumino, Hiroyuki Kitahata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deterministic Model of Incremental Multi-Agent Boltzmann Q-Learning: Transient Cooperation, Metastability, and Oscillations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00160</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00160v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multi-Agent Reinforcement Learning involves agents that learn together in a shared environment, leading to emergent dynamics sensitive to initial conditions and parameter variations. A Dynamical Systems approach, which studies the evolution of multi-component systems over time, has uncovered some of the underlying dynamics by constructing deterministic approximation models of stochastic algorithms. In this work, we demonstrate that even in the simplest case of independent Q-learning with a Boltzmann exploration policy, significant discrepancies arise between the actual algorithm and previous approximations. We elaborate why these models actually approximate interesting variants rather than the original incremental algorithm. To explain the discrepancies, we introduce a new discrete-time approximation model that explicitly accounts for agents' update frequencies within the learning process and show that its dynamics fundamentally differ from the simplified dynamics of prior models. We illustrate the usefulness of our approach by applying it to the question of spontaneous cooperation in social dilemmas, specifically the Prisoner's Dilemma as the simplest case study. We identify conditions under which the learning behaviour appears as long-term stable cooperation from an external perspective. However, our model shows that this behaviour is merely a metastable transient phase and not a true equilibrium, making it exploitable. We further exemplify how specific parameter settings can significantly exacerbate the moving target problem in independent learning. Through a systematic analysis of our model, we show that increasing the discount factor induces oscillations, preventing convergence to a joint policy. These oscillations arise from a supercritical Neimark-Sacker bifurcation, which transforms the unique stable fixed point into an unstable focus surrounded by a stable limit cycle.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00160v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Goll, Jobst Heitzig, Wolfram Barfuss</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modified Axelrod Model Showing Opinion Convergence And Polarization In Realistic Scale-Free Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00221</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00221v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Axelrod model is an opinion dynamics model such that each agent on a two-dimensional lattice has a finite number of possible opinions. The model is not realistic as all agents will eventually share the same opinion on every issue. Here we identify certain limitations inherent in the Axelrod model and address them by modifying some of the model's rules. Specifically, by considering agents in a scale-free network and incorporating a more realistic interaction rule with continuous values representing agents' opinions, our modified model offers a more comprehensive exploration of opinion dynamics. Computer simulation of our model shows a notable trend in opinion polarization on all features in the majority of reasonable simulation parameters. To mitigate this polarization, we introduce agents that work actively to reduce opinion differences. However, our findings indicate limited success in the approach. This research contributes to the understanding of opinion dynamics within society and highlights the nuanced complexities that arise when considering factors such as network structure and continuous opinion values. Our results prompt further exploration and open avenues for future investigations into effective methods of reducing opinion polarization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00221v1</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>X. Zou, H. F. Chau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Information bounds production in replicator systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00396v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate minimal replicator systems that are able to use information in a functional manner. Specifically, we consider a population of autocatalytic replicators in a flow reactor, subject to fluctuating environments. We derive operational bounds on replicators production in terms of information-theoretic quantities, reflecting contributions from environmental uncertainty, side information, and distribution mismatch. We also derive the optimal strategy, expressed as a function of both intrinsic replicator parameters and environmental statistics. We compare and contrast our findings with existing information-theoretic formalisms such as Kelly gambling. The results are illustrated on a model of real-world self-assembled molecular replicators. For this system, we demonstrate the benefit of internal memory in environments with temporal correlations, and we propose a plausible experimental setup for detecting the signature of functional information. We briefly discuss the role that information processing may play in guiding the evolution of prebiotic replicator networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00396v1</guid>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jordi Pi\~nero, Damian R. Sowinski, Gourab Ghoshal, Adam Frank, Artemy Kolchinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extracting Interaction Kernels for Many-Particle Systems by a Two-Phase Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.00714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.00714v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper presents a two-phase method for learning interaction kernels of stochastic many-particle systems. After transforming stochastic trajectories of every particle into the particle density function by the kernel density estimation method, the first phase of our approach combines importance sampling with an adaptive threshold strategy to identify key terms in the kernel function, while the second phase uses the whole dataset to refine the coefficients. During the implementation of our method, the mean-field equation plays a key role in reformulating the task of extracting the interaction kernels into a learnable regression problem. We demonstrate the outstanding performance of our approach through extensive numerical examples, including interacting particle systems with a cubic potential, power-law repulsion-attraction potential, piecewise linear potential, as well as a two-dimensional radially symmetric potential.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.00714v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yangxuan Shi, Wuyue Yang, Liu Hong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The clock advance description of the Epidemic Type Aftershock Sequence (ETAS) model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01233</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01233v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this short paper we propose to extend the ETAS model to micro-seismic events. For that we interpret the triggered events in an ETAS model as individual local clock advances of an independent background process. The solution of the ETAS model thus becomes the sum of an infinite Markov chain of independent time adjusted background processses. This allows the incorporation of events at all scales. No artificial small magnitude cutoff is needed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01233v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Holschneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Higher-order triadic percolation on random hypergraphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14213v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we propose a comprehensive theoretical framework combining percolation theory with nonlinear dynamics in order to study hypergraphs with a time-varying giant component. We consider in particular hypergraphs with higher-order triadic interactions that can upregulate or downregulate the hyperedges. Triadic interactions are a general type of signed regulatory interaction that occurs when a third node regulates the interaction between two other nodes. For example, in brain networks, the glia can facilitate or inhibit synaptic interactions between neurons. However, the regulatory interactions may not only occur between regulator nodes and pairwise interactions but also between regulator nodes and higher-order interactions (hyperedges), leading to higher-order triadic interactions. For instance, in biochemical reaction networks, the enzymes regulate the reactions involving multiple reactants. Here we propose and investigate higher-order triadic percolation on hypergraphs showing that the giant component can have a non-trivial dynamics. Specifically, we demonstrate that, under suitable conditions, the order parameter of this percolation problem, i.e., the fraction of nodes in the giant component, undergoes a route to chaos in the universality class of the logistic map. In hierarchical higher-order triadic percolation, we extend this paradigm in order to treat hierarchically nested triadic interactions demonstrating the non-trivial effect of their increased combinatorial complexity on the critical phenomena and the dynamical properties of the process. Finally, we consider other generalizations of the model studying the effect of considering interdependencies and node regulation instead of hyperedge regulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14213v2</guid>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevE.110.064315</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. E 110, 064315 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hanlin Sun, Ginestra Bianconi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimality theory of stigmergic collective information processing by chemotactic cells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15298v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Collective information processing is fundamental in various biological systems, where the cooperation of multiple cells results in complex functions beyond individual capabilities. A distinctive example is collective exploration where chemotactic cells not only sense the gradient of guiding exogeneous cues originating from targets but also generate and modulate endogenous cues to coordinate their collective behaviors. While the optimality of gradient sensing has been studied extensively in the context of single-cell information processing, the optimality of collective information processing that includes both gradient sensing and gradient generation remains underexplored. In this study, we formulate the collective exploration problem as a reinforcement learning (RL) by a population. Based on RL theory, we derive the optimal exploration dynamics of agents and identify their structural correspondence with the Keller-Segel model, the established phenomenological model of collective cellular dynamics. Our theory identifies an optimal coupling relation between gradient sensing and gradient generation and demonstrates that the optimal way to generate a gradient qualitatively differs depending on whether the gradient sensing is logarithmic or linear. The underlying RL structure is leveraged to compare the derived collective dynamics with single-agent searching dynamics, showing that distributed information processing by population enables a fraction of agents to reach the target robustly. Our formulation provides a foundation for understanding the collective information processing mediated by dynamic sensing and modulation of cues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15298v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.CB</category>
      <category>nlin.AO</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaki Kato, Tetsuya J. Kobayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
