<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DL updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DL</link>
    <description>cs.DL updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DL" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 01:45:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Socio-cognitive Networks between Researchers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21067</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21067v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Understanding why researchers cite each other has been a longstanding conjecture in studying scientific networks. Prior research suggests relevance, group cohesion, or honest source crediting as possible factors. However, the dual nature of cognitive and social dimensions underlying citation is often overlooked by not considering the intermediary steps leading up to a citation. For one work to be cited by another, it must first be published by a set of authors. Therefore, we investigate the reasons behind researchers' citations, explicitly examining the interplay of socio-cognitive ties through the interdependence of coauthorship and citation networks. We assess our claims in an empirical analysis by employing the Author-Oriented Relational HyperEvent Model (AuthRHEM) to study Chilean astronomers' citation and collaboration behavior between 2013 and 2015 in a joint framework. We find evidence that when deciding which work to cite, authors prefer other work with novelty and cognitive ties, such as work-to-work relations. At the same time, coherent groups are relevant because coauthors are cocited more frequently in subsequent publications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21067v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alejandro Espinosa-Rada, J\"urgen Lerner, Cornelius Fritz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ontologies for Models and Algorithms in Applied Mathematics and Related Disciplines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.20443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.20443v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In applied mathematics and related disciplines, the modeling-simulation-optimization workflow is a prominent scheme, with mathematical models and numerical algorithms playing a crucial role. For these types of mathematical research data, the Mathematical Research Data Initiative has developed, merged and implemented ontologies and knowledge graphs. This contributes to making mathematical research data FAIR by introducing semantic technology and documenting the mathematical foundations accordingly. Using the concrete example of microfracture analysis of porous media, it is shown how the knowledge of the underlying mathematical model and the corresponding numerical algorithms for its solution can be represented by the ontologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.20443v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-65990-4_14</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>In: Metadata and Semantic Research. MTSR 2023. Communications in Computer and Information Science, vol 2048. Springer, Cham (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bj\"orn Schembera, Frank W\"ubbeling, Hendrik Kleikamp, Christine Biedinger, Jochen Fiedler, Marco Reidelbach, Aurela Shehu, Burkhard Schmidt, Thomas Koprucki, Dorothea Iglezakis, Dominik G\"oddeke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a FAIR Documentation of Workflows and Models in Applied Mathematics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17778v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Modeling-Simulation-Optimization workflows play a fundamental role in applied mathematics. The Mathematical Research Data Initiative, MaRDI, responded to this by developing a FAIR and machine-interpretable template for a comprehensive documentation of such workflows. MaRDMO, a Plugin for the Research Data Management Organiser, enables scientists from diverse fields to document and publish their workflows on the MaRDI Portal seamlessly using the MaRDI template. Central to these workflows are mathematical models. MaRDI addresses them with the MathModDB ontology, offering a structured formal model description. Here, we showcase the interaction between MaRDMO and the MathModDB Knowledge Graph through an algebraic modeling workflow from the Digital Humanities. This demonstration underscores the versatility of both services beyond their original numerical domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17778v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-64529-7_27</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Congress on Mathematical Software (pp. 254-262). Cham: Springer Nature Switzerland (2024, July)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marco Reidelbach, Bj\"orn Schembera, Marcus Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping Literary Space: A Social Network from the Timeline of Cultural Events</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11907v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study applies social network analysis (SNA) to map and analyze literary networks in St Petersburg from 1999 to 2019, using data from the 'SPbLitGuide' newsletter. By examining co-participation in literary events, we reveal the dynamics and structures of these networks, identifying key communities and influential figures. Our network graph, consisting of 14,066 nodes and 127,068 edges, represents a highly interconnected and cohesive small-world network with robust local clustering and extensive collaboration. Focusing on core participants, we refined the graph and applied community detection methods to identify distinct groups with specific aesthetic preferences and personal connections. These findings provide insights into the structure and dynamics of literary groups in St. Petersburg and provide a foundation for further research in the digital humanities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11907v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Levchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
