<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DL updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DL</link>
    <description>cs.DL updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DL" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 03:44:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Web Archives Metadata Generation with GPT-4o: Challenges and Insights</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05409v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Current metadata creation for web archives is time consuming and costly due to reliance on human effort. This paper explores the use of gpt-4o for metadata generation within the Web Archive Singapore, focusing on scalability, efficiency, and cost effectiveness. We processed 112 Web ARChive (WARC) files using data reduction techniques, achieving a notable 99.9% reduction in metadata generation costs. By prompt engineering, we generated titles and abstracts, which were evaluated both intrinsically using Levenshtein Distance and BERTScore, and extrinsically with human cataloguers using McNemar's test. Results indicate that while our method offers significant cost savings and efficiency gains, human curated metadata maintains an edge in quality. The study identifies key challenges including content inaccuracies, hallucinations, and translation issues, suggesting that Large Language Models (LLMs) should serve as complements rather than replacements for human cataloguers. Future work will focus on refining prompts, improving content filtering, and addressing privacy concerns through experimentation with smaller models. This research advances the integration of LLMs in web archiving, offering valuable insights into their current capabilities and outlining directions for future enhancements. The code is available at https://github.com/masamune-prog/warc2summary for further development and use by institutions facing similar challenges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05409v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abigail Yongping Huang, Ashwin Nair, Zhen Rong Goh, Tianrui Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mitigating Consequences of Prestige in Citations of Publications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05584v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: For many public research organizations, funding creation of science and maximizing scientific output is of central interest. Typically, when evaluating scientific production for funding, citations are utilized as a proxy, although these are severely influenced by factors beyond scientific impact. This study aims to mitigate the consequences of the Matthew effect in citations, where prominent authors and prestigious journals receive more citations regardless of the scientific content of the publications. To this end, the study presents an approach to predicting citations of papers based solely on observable characteristics available at the submission stage of a double-blind peer-review process. Combining classical linear models, generalized linear models and utilizing large-scale data sets on biomedical papers based on the PubMed database, the results demonstrate that it is possible to make fairly accurate predictions of citations using only observable characteristics of papers excluding information on authors and journals, thereby mitigating the Matthew effect. Thus, the outcomes have important implications for the field of scientometrics, providing a more objective method for citation prediction by relying on pre-publication variables that are immune to manipulation by authors and journals, thereby enhancing the objectivity of the evaluation process. Our approach is thus important for government agencies responsible for funding the creation of high-quality scientific content rather than perpetuating prestige.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05584v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Balzer, Adhen Benlahlou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LLMs as Research Tools: A Large Scale Survey of Researchers' Usage and Perceptions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05025v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rise of large language models (LLMs) has led many researchers to consider their usage for scientific work. Some have found benefits using LLMs to augment or automate aspects of their research pipeline, while others have urged caution due to risks and ethical concerns. Yet little work has sought to quantify and characterize how researchers use LLMs and why. We present the first large-scale survey of 816 verified research article authors to understand how the research community leverages and perceives LLMs as research tools. We examine participants' self-reported LLM usage, finding that 81% of researchers have already incorporated LLMs into different aspects of their research workflow. We also find that traditionally disadvantaged groups in academia (non-White, junior, and non-native English speaking researchers) report higher LLM usage and perceived benefits, suggesting potential for improved research equity. However, women, non-binary, and senior researchers have greater ethical concerns, potentially hindering adoption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05025v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhehui Liao, Maria Antoniak, Inyoung Cheong, Evie Yu-Yen Cheng, Ai-Heng Lee, Kyle Lo, Joseph Chee Chang, Amy X. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explainable AI through a Democratic Lens: DhondtXAI for Proportional Feature Importance Using the D'Hondt Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05196v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In democratic societies, electoral systems play a crucial role in translating public preferences into political representation. Among these, the D'Hondt method is widely used to ensure proportional representation, balancing fair representation with governmental stability. Recently, there has been a growing interest in applying similar principles of proportional representation to enhance interpretability in machine learning, specifically in Explainable AI (XAI). This study investigates the integration of D'Hondt-based voting principles in the DhondtXAI method, which leverages resource allocation concepts to interpret feature importance within AI models. Through a comparison of SHAP (Shapley Additive Explanations) and DhondtXAI, we evaluate their effectiveness in feature attribution within CatBoost and XGBoost models for breast cancer and diabetes prediction, respectively. The DhondtXAI approach allows for alliance formation and thresholding to enhance interpretability, representing feature importance as seats in a parliamentary view. Statistical correlation analyses between SHAP values and DhondtXAI allocations support the consistency of interpretations, demonstrating DhondtXAI's potential as a complementary tool for understanding feature importance in AI models. The results highlight that integrating electoral principles, such as proportional representation and alliances, into AI explainability can improve user understanding, especially in high-stakes fields like healthcare.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05196v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Turker Berk Donmez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is ChatGPT Transforming Academics' Writing Style?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.08627v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Based on one million arXiv papers submitted from May 2018 to January 2024, we assess the textual density of ChatGPT's writing style in their abstracts through a statistical analysis of word frequency changes. Our model is calibrated and validated on a mixture of real abstracts and ChatGPT-modified abstracts (simulated data) after a careful noise analysis. The words used for estimation are not fixed but adaptive, including those with decreasing frequency. We find that large language models (LLMs), represented by ChatGPT, are having an increasing impact on arXiv abstracts, especially in the field of computer science, where the fraction of LLM-style abstracts is estimated to be approximately 35%, if we take the responses of GPT-3.5 to one simple prompt, "revise the following sentences", as a baseline. We conclude with an analysis of both positive and negative aspects of the penetration of LLMs into academics' writing style.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.08627v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingmeng Geng, Roberto Trotta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gymnasium: A Standard Interface for Reinforcement Learning Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17032v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Reinforcement Learning (RL) is a continuously growing field that has the potential to revolutionize many areas of artificial intelligence. However, despite its promise, RL research is often hindered by the lack of standardization in environment and algorithm implementations. This makes it difficult for researchers to compare and build upon each other's work, slowing down progress in the field. Gymnasium is an open-source library that provides a standard API for RL environments, aiming to tackle this issue. Gymnasium's main feature is a set of abstractions that allow for wide interoperability between environments and training algorithms, making it easier for researchers to develop and test RL algorithms. In addition, Gymnasium provides a collection of easy-to-use environments, tools for easily customizing environments, and tools to ensure the reproducibility and robustness of RL research. Through this unified framework, Gymnasium significantly streamlines the process of developing and testing RL algorithms, enabling researchers to focus more on innovation and less on implementation details. By providing a standardized platform for RL research, Gymnasium helps to drive forward the field of reinforcement learning and unlock its full potential. Gymnasium is available online at https://github.com/Farama-Foundation/Gymnasium</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17032v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Towers, Ariel Kwiatkowski, Jordan Terry, John U. Balis, Gianluca De Cola, Tristan Deleu, Manuel Goul\~ao, Andreas Kallinteris, Markus Krimmel, Arjun KG, Rodrigo Perez-Vicente, Andrea Pierr\'e, Sander Schulhoff, Jun Jet Tai, Hannah Tan, Omar G. Younis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
