<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DL updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DL</link>
    <description>cs.DL updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DL" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 05:00:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Ten (or more!) reasons to register your software with the Astrophysics Source Code Library</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19941v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This presentation covered the benefits of registering astronomy research software with the Astrophysics Source Code Library (ASCL, ascl.net), a free online registry for software used in astronomy research. Indexed by ADS and Clarivate's Web of Science, the ASCL currently contains over 3600 codes, and its entries have been cited over 17,000 times. Registering your code with the ASCL is easy with our online submissions system. Making your software available for examination shows confidence in your research and makes your research more transparent, reproducible, and falsifiable. ASCL registration allows your software to be cited on its own merits and provides a citation method that is trackable and accepted by all astronomy journals, and by journals such as \textit{Science} and \textit{Nature}. Adding your code to the ASCL also allows others to find your code more easily, as it can then be found not only in the ASCL itself, but also in ADS, Web of Science, and Google Scholar.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19941v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alice Allen, Kimberly DuPrie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Freshness and Informativity Weighted Cognitive Extent and Its Correlation with Cumulative Citation Count</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03557v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we revisit cognitive extent, originally defined as the number of unique phrases in a quota. We introduce Freshness and Informative Weighted Cognitive Extent (FICE), calculated based on two novel weighting factors, the lifetime ratio and informativity of scientific entities. We model the lifetime of each scientific entity as the time-dependent document frequency, which is fit by the composition of multiple Gaussian profiles. The lifetime ratio is then calculated as the cumulative document frequency at the publication time $t_0$ divided by the cumulative document frequency over its entire lifetime. The informativity is calculated by normalizing the document frequency across all scientific entities recognized in a title. Using the ACL Anthology, we verified the trend formerly observed in several other domains that the number of unique scientific entities per quota increased gradually at a slower rate. We found that FICE exhibits a strong correlation with the average cumulative citation count within a quota. Our code is available at \href{https://github.com/ZiheHerzWang/Freshness-and-Informativity-Weighted-Cognitive-Extent}{https://github.com/ZiheHerzWang/Freshness-and-Informativity-Weighted-Cognitive-Extent}</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03557v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zihe Wang, Jian Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
