<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DL updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DL</link>
    <description>cs.DL updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DL" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Aug 2025 01:36:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Use of LLMs in preparing accessible scientific papers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00826v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Making scientific papers accessible may require reprocessing old papers to create output compliant with accessibility standards. An important step there is to convert the visual formatting to the logical one. In this report we describe our attempt at zero shot conversion of arXiv papers. Our results are mixed: while it is possible to do conversion, the reliability is not too good. We discuss alternative approaches to this problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00826v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Allison Doami, Christine James, Dan Lu, Lia Prins, Annette Torrence, Boris Veytsman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Foundational Schema.org Mapping for a Legal Knowledge Graph: Representing Brazilian Legal Norms as FRBR Works</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00827v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Structuring legal norms for machine readability is a critical prerequisite for building advanced AI and information retrieval systems, such as Legal Knowledge Graphs (LKGs). Grounded in the Functional Requirements for Bibliographic Records (FRBR) model, this paper proposes a foundational mapping for the abstract legal Work - which is materialized as the Norm node in our legal Graph RAG framework - to the interoperable schema.org/Legislation vocabulary. Using the Normas.leg.br portal as a practical case study, we demonstrate how to describe this Work entity via JSON-LD, considering stable URN identifiers, inter-norm relationships, and lifecycle properties. This structured, formal approach provides the essential first step toward creating a deterministic and verifiable knowledge graph, which can serve as a formalized "ground truth" for Legal AI applications, overcoming the limitations of purely probabilistic models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00827v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hudson de Martim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open Science, Open Innovation? The Role of Open Access in Patenting Activity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00829v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scientific knowledge is a key driver of technological innovation, shaping industrial development and policy decisions worldwide. Understanding how patents incorporate scientific research is essential for assessing the role of academic discoveries in technological progress. Non-Patent References (NPRs) provide a useful indicator of this relationship by revealing the extent to which patents draw upon scientific literature. Here, we show that reliance on scientific research in patents varies significantly across regions. Oceania and Europe display stronger engagement with scientific knowledge, while the Americas exhibit lower reliance. Moreover, NPRs are more likely to be open access than the average scientific publication, a trend that intensifies when Sci-Hub availability is considered. These results highlight the transformative impact of Open Science on global innovation dynamics. By facilitating broader access to research, Open Science strengthens the link between academia and industry, underscoring the need for policies that promote equitable and science-based innovation, particularly in developing regions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00829v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdelghani Maddi (GEMASS), Ahmad Yaman Abdin, Francesco Fdp de Pretis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rxiv-Maker: An Automated Template Engine for Streamlined Scientific Publications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00836</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00836v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scientific publishing increasingly relies on preprint servers for rapid dissemination, yet researchers often struggle with manuscript preparation and quality control. Here we present Rxiv-Maker, a GitHub-native framework that converts markdown content to publication-ready PDFs through automated LaTeX processing. The system addresses reproducibility challenges in computational biology and imaging research by treating manuscripts as executable outputs rather than static documents. Rxiv-Maker integrates version control workflows with automated build environments, enabling collaborative manuscript development whilst maintaining computational provenance. The framework supports programmatic figure generation, essential for microscopy and image analysis workflows where visualisations must reflect current data and processing algorithms. This manuscript, generated entirely using Rxiv-Maker, demonstrates the system's capacity to bridge accessible authoring with professional typesetting, offering researchers a transparent pathway from data to publication that aligns with open science principles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00836v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno M. Saraiva, Guillaume Jaquemet, Ricardo Henriques</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Attribution Crisis in LLM Search Results</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00838</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00838v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Web-enabled LLMs frequently answer queries without crediting the web pages they consume, creating an "attribution gap" - the difference between relevant URLs read and those actually cited. Drawing on approximately 14,000 real-world LMArena conversation logs with search-enabled LLM systems, we document three exploitation patterns: 1) No Search: 34% of Google Gemini and 24% of OpenAI GPT-4o responses are generated without explicitly fetching any online content; 2) No citation: Gemini provides no clickable citation source in 92% of answers; 3) High-volume, low-credit: Perplexity's Sonar visits approximately 10 relevant pages per query but cites only three to four. A negative binomial hurdle model shows that the average query answered by Gemini or Sonar leaves about 3 relevant websites uncited, whereas GPT-4o's tiny uncited gap is best explained by its selective log disclosures rather than by better attribution. Citation efficiency - extra citations provided per additional relevant web page visited - varies widely across models, from 0.19 to 0.45 on identical queries, underscoring that retrieval design, not technical limits, shapes ecosystem impact. We recommend a transparent LLM search architecture based on standardized telemetry and full disclosure of search traces and citation logs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00838v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.35650/AIDP.4114.d.2025</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ilan Strauss, Jangho Yang, Tim O'Reilly, Sruly Rosenblat, Isobel Moure</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic Evaluation and the Marginalization of Single Authorship in Management Science</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00842v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The decline of single authorship in peer-reviewed journals within the current collaboration-oriented knowledge production framework has prompted deeper reflection on the shifting power structures in academic systems. This paper aims to explore the underlying institutional logic and evaluation mechanisms contributing to the marginalization of single-author research in the management field. It further investigates how the discourse of collaborative advantage conceals structural power redistribution and ideological disembedding. Through an analysis of authorship data from top-tier journals, a critical reading of institutional incentive texts, and an empirical review of authorial configurations, the study building on the work of Harzing, Wuchty, and Lariviere constructs a three-dimensional causal chain: collaboration incentives, responsibility dilution, and originality weakening. Findings suggest that single authorship is not explicitly excluded but is gradually sidelined from central publication channels by funding policies, review practices, and performance metrics. Independent thought is thus structurally marginalized within institutionalized collaboration. The paper advocates for a paradigm shift from instrumental rationality to value-based rationality and calls for the restoration of legitimacy and public value for independent research through reforms in evaluation frameworks, journal governance, and research ethics, aiming to safeguard academic diversity and intellectual autonomy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00842v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Author Once, Publish Everywhere: Portable Metadata Authoring with the CEDAR Embeddable Editor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00859v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-quality, "rich" metadata are essential for making research data findable, interoperable, and reusable. The Center for Expanded Data Annotation and Retrieval (CEDAR) has long addressed this need by providing tools to design machine-actionable metadata templates that encode community standards in a computable form. To make these capabilities more accessible within real-world research workflows, we have developed the CEDAR Embeddable Editor (CEE)-a lightweight, interoperable Web Component that brings structured, standards-based metadata authoring directly into third-party platforms. The CEE dynamically renders metadata forms from machine-actionable templates and produces semantically rich metadata in JSON-LD format. It supports ontology-based value selection via the BioPortal ontology repository, and it includes external authority resolution for persistent identifiers such as ORCIDs for individuals and RORs for research organizations. Crucially, the CEE requires no custom user-interface development, allowing deployment across diverse platforms. The CEE has been successfully integrated into generalist scientific data repositories such as Dryad and the Open Science Framework, demonstrating its ability to support discipline-specific metadata creation. By supporting the embedding of metadata authoring within existing research environments, the CEE can facilitate the adoption of community standards and help improve metadata quality across scientific disciplines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00859v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin J. O'Connor, Marcos Martinez-Romero, Attila L. Egyedi, Mete U. Akdogan, Michael V. Dorf, Mark A. Musen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A survey on proximity monitoring and warning in construction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00862v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Various technologies have been applied to monitor the proximity between two construction entities, preventing struck-by accidents and thereby enhancing onsite safety. This study comprehensively reviews related efforts dedicated to proximity monitoring and warning (PMW) based on 97 relevant articles published between 2010 and 2024. The bibliometric analysis reveals the technical roadmap over time, as well as the five most influential leaders and the two largest research networks they have established. The qualitative review is then conducted from four perspectives: influencing factor study, hazard level definition and determination, proximity perception, and alarm issuing and receiving. Finally, the limitations and challenges of current proximity perception are discussed, along with corresponding future research directions, including end-to-end three-dimensional (3D) object detection, real-time 3D reconstruction and updating for dynamic construction scenes, and multimodal fusion. This review presents the current research status, limitations, and future directions of PMW, guiding the future development of PMW systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00862v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuexiong Ding, Qiong Liu, Ankang Ji, Xiaowei Luo, Wen Yi, Albert P. C. Chan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Better Recommendations: Validating AI-generated Subject Terms Through LOC Linked Data Service</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00867v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article explores the integration of AI-generated subject terms into library cataloging, focusing on validation through the Library of Congress Linked Data Service. It examines the challenges of traditional subject cataloging under the Library of Congress Subject Headings system, including inefficiencies and cataloging backlogs. While generative AI shows promise in expediting cataloging workflows, studies reveal significant limitations in the accuracy of AI-assigned subject headings. The article proposes a hybrid approach combining AI technology with human validation through LOC Linked Data Service, aiming to enhance the precision, efficiency, and overall quality of metadata creation in library cataloging practices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00867v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kwok Leong Tang, Yi Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Patents as Knowledge Artifacts: An Information Science Perspective on Global Innovation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00871v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In an age of fast-paced technological change, patents have evolved into not only legal mechanisms of intellectual property, but also structured storage containers of knowledge full of metadata, categories, and formal innovation. This chapter proposes to reframe patents in the context of information science, by focusing on patents as knowledge artifacts, and by seeing patents as fundamentally tied to the global movement of scientific and technological knowledge. With a focus on three areas, the inventions of AIs, biotech patents, and international competition with patents, this work considers how new technologies are challenging traditional notions of inventorship, access, and moral accountability.The chapter provides a critical analysis of AI's implications for patent authorship and prior art searches, ownership issues arising from proprietary claims in biotechnology to ethical dilemmas, and the problem of using patents for strategic advantage in a global context of innovation competition. In this analysis, the chapter identified the importance of organizing information, creating metadata standards about originality, implementing retrieval systems to access previous works, and ethical contemplation about patenting unseen relationships in innovation ecosystems. Ultimately, the chapter called for a collaborative, transparent, and ethically-based approach in managing knowledge in the patenting environment highlighting the role for information professionals and policy to contribute to access equity in innovation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00871v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. S. Rajeevan, B. Mini Devi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Global South Strategy for Evaluating Research Value with ChatGPT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.01882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.01882v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Research evaluation is important for appointments, promotions, departmental assessments, and national science strategy monitoring. Whilst Global North universities often have sufficient senior researchers for effective peer review and enough trust in citation data to use it for supporting indicators, the same is less likely to be true in the Global South. Moreover, Global South research priorities may not align well with citation-based indicators. This article introduces a ChatGPT-based strategy designed to address both limitations, applying it to Mauritius. The strategy involves giving ChatGPT instructions about how to evaluate the quality of research from the perspective of a given Global South nation and then using it to score articles based on these criteria. Results from Mauritius show that ChatGPT's scores for 1,566 journal articles published between 2015 and 2021 have an almost zero correlation with both ChatGPT research quality scores and citation rates. A word association thematic analysis of articles with relatively high scores for value to Mauritius identified a range of plausible themes, including education, policy relevance, and industrial production. Higher scoring articles also tended to mention the country or an important commercial sector in the abstract. Whilst the evidence suggests that assessing the direct value to a country of journal articles using ChatGPT gives plausible results, this approach should be used cautiously because it has unknown accuracy and ignores the wider value of research contributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.01882v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robin Nunkoo, Mike Thelwall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SSBD Ontology: A Two-Tier Approach for Interoperable Bioimaging Metadata</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02084</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02084v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Advanced bioimaging technologies have enabled the large-scale acquisition of multidimensional data, yet effective metadata management and interoperability remain significant challenges. To address these issues, we propose a new ontology-driven framework for the Systems Science of Biological Dynamics Database (SSBD) that adopts a two-tier architecture. The core layer provides a class-centric structure referencing existing biomedical ontologies, supporting both SSBD:repository -- which focuses on rapid dataset publication with minimal metadata -- and SSBD:database, which is enhanced with biological and imaging-related annotations. Meanwhile, the instance layer represents actual imaging dataset information as Resource Description Framework individuals that are explicitly linked to the core classes. This layered approach aligns flexible instance data with robust ontological classes, enabling seamless integration and advanced semantic queries. By coupling flexibility with rigor, the SSBD Ontology promotes interoperability, data reuse, and the discovery of novel biological mechanisms. Moreover, our solution aligns with the Recommended Metadata for Biological Images guidelines and fosters compatibility. Ultimately, our approach contributes to establishing a Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, and Reusable data ecosystem within the bioimaging community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02084v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.DB</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuki Yamagata, Koji Kyoda, Hiroya Itoga, Emi Fujisawa, Shuichi Onami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>USRN Discovery Pilot: Increasing the Discoverability of Open Access Content Through a National Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02379v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents the results of the USRN Discovery Pilot Project, a collaboration of SPARC, the Confederation of Open Access Repositories (COAR), CORE and Antleaf, to enhance the discoverability of research papers in US repositories leveraging CORE as an indexing service for USRN repositories. The project conducted actions in three strategic areas: Assessing and quantitatively measuring discoverability and barriers to it at the beginning and end of the pilot project, conducting interventions to increase discoverability, and supporting interventions by technology and guidelines (provided by CORE services), to minimise effort and maximise effect. The key results of the project include: Around three-quarters of a million research outputs held in the selected US repositories have been made discoverable (a 50% increase) compared to the year before; The project has made available the CORE Data Provider's Guide as well as a selection of new and improved tools to support repositories in increasing their discoverability. These include the CORE Reindexing Button and Index Notification modules, Fresh Finds and the USRN Desirable Characteristics for Digital Publication Repositories checking tool. The project team is now exploring ways to scale out this work to include more repositories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02379v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Petr Knoth, Paul Walk, Matteo Cancellieri, Micheal Upshall, Halyna Torchylo, Jennifer Beamer, Kathleen Shearer, Heather Joseph</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the Role of Gamification in Enhancing Academic Library Services: A Survey of Library Leaders in India</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00906v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study explores the role of gamification in enhancing academic library services in India by surveying library leaders across various institutions. Using game-like elements in non-game contexts, gamification can boost user engagement and improve services such as information literacy and research consultations. Findings reveal moderate awareness and generally positive perceptions of gamification's effectiveness. However, challenges like insufficient staff expertise, infrastructure, and limited funding hinder implementation. The study emphasises the need for additional resources, including staff training and technological upgrades, to unlock the full potential of gamification in academic libraries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00906v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subaveerapandiyan A, Pragya Lohia, Dattatraya Kalbande, Naved Ahmad, Kailash Chand Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interoperable verification and dissemination of software assets in repositories using COAR Notify</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.02335</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.02335v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The discoverability, attribution, and reusability of open research software are often hindered by its obscurity within academic manuscripts. To address this, the SoFAIR project (2024-2025) introduces a comprehensive workflow leveraging machine learning tools for extracting software mentions from research papers. The project integrates repository systems, authors, and services like HAL and Software Heritage to ensure proper archiving, citation, and accessibility of research software in alignment with FAIR principles. To enable interoperable communication across the various systems we present an integration of the COAR Notify Protocol, which facilitates automated, interoperable communication among repositories and authors to validate and disseminate software mentions. This paper outlines the SoFAIR workflow and the implementation of the COAR Notify Protocol, emphasising its potential to enhance the visibility and credibility of research software as first-class bibliographic records.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.02335v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Cancellieri, Martin Docekal, David Pride, Morane Gruenpeter, David Douard, Petr Knoth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>APC waivers and Ukraine's publishing output in Gold OA journals: Evidence from five commercial publishers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.12134v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This study examines the effect of article processing charge (APC) waivers on the participation of Ukrainian researchers in fully Gold Open Access (Gold OA) journals published by the five largest academic publishers - Elsevier, SAGE, Springer Nature, Taylor &amp; Francis, and Wiley - during the period 2019-2024. These publishers were selected because, in response to the full-scale war launched against Ukraine in 2022, all five introduced emergency 100% APC-waiver policies for Ukrainian authors. Using bibliometric data from the Web of Science Core Collection, the study analyses publication trends in Ukrainian-authored articles in fully Gold OA journals of these publishers before and after 2022. The results show a marked post-2022 increase in Ukraine's Gold OA output, particularly in journals published by Springer Nature and Elsevier. Disciplinary and publisher-specific patterns are evident, with especially strong growth in the medical and applied sciences. The findings underscore the potential of targeted support measures during times of crisis, while also illustrating the inherent limitations of APC-based publishing models in fostering equitable scholarly communication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12134v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Serhii Nazarovets</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissecting the gender divide: Authorship and acknowledgment in scientific publications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15237v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The issue of gender bias in scientific publications has been a topic of ongoing debate. One aspect of this debate concerns whether women receive equal credit for their contributions compared to men. Conventional wisdom suggests that women are more likely to be acknowledged than listed as co-authors. In this study, we analyze data from over 20,000 authors and 60,000 acknowledged individuals across nine disciplines in open-access journals. Our results confirm persistent gender disparities: women are more frequently acknowledged than credited as co-authors, especially in roles involving investigation and analysis. To account for status and disciplinary effects, we examined collaboration pair composed of highly cited and less-cited scholars. In collaborations, highly cited scholars are more likely to be listed as an author regardless of gender. Notably, highly cited women in such pairs are even more likely to be co-authors than their men counterparts. Our findings suggest that power dynamics and perceived success heavily influence the distribution of credit in scientific publishing. These results underscore the role of status dynamics in shaping authorship and call for a more nuanced understanding of how gender, power, and recognition interact in scientific publishing. Our findings offer valuable insights for scholars, editors, and funding committed to advancing equity in science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15237v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keigo Kusumegi, Daniel E. Acu\~na, Yukie Sano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interdisciplinarity Revealed by Transitive Reduction of Citation Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1802.06015</link>
      <description>arXiv:1802.06015v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the impact of transitive reduction on citation networks. Our hypothesis is that documents which lose fewer citations under transitive reduction are likely to be interdisciplinary, while a large loss of citations suggests a document is primarily cited within a single discipline. We test this hypothesis by using an artificial model of a citation network and by using data on citations from three sources: academic papers, court decisions and patents. Where needed, we applied modularity-based clustering techniques on a network defined using bibliographic coupling to classify documents by topic. A cluster-dependent measure was then used to classify the nodes as interdisciplinary or intradisciplinary. Our results provide strong support for our hypothesis in three of the four cases, with somewhat weaker but still positive support in the case of patents.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1802.06015v2</guid>
      <category>physics.soc-ph</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.SI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. AlMuhanna, V. Vasiliauskaite, T. S. Evans</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
