<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DL updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DL</link>
    <description>cs.DL updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DL" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 04:02:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Works-magnet: Accelerating Metadata Curation for Open Science</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14430v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The transition to Open Science necessitates robust and reliable metadata. While national initiatives, such as the French Open Science Monitor, aim to track this evolution using open data, reliance on proprietary databases persists in many places. Open platforms like OpenAlex still require significant human intervention for data accuracy. This paper introduces Works-magnet, a project by the French Ministry of Higher Education and Research (MESR) Data Science &amp; Engineering Team. Works-magnet is designed to accelerate the curation of bibliographic and research data metadata, particularly affiliations, by making automated AI calculations visible and correctable. It addresses challenges related to metadata heterogeneity, complex processing chains, and the need for human curation in a diverse research landscape. The paper details Works-magnet's concepts, and the observed limitations, while outlining future directions for enhancing open metadata quality and reusability. The works-magnet app is open source on github https://github.com/dataesr/works-magnet</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14430v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Jeangirard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Procedural Knowledge Libraries: Towards Executable (Research) Memory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14715v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Procedural Knowledge Libraries (PKLs) are frameworks for capturing the full arc of scientific inquiry, not just its outcomes. Whereas traditional libraries store static end products, PKLs preserve the process that leads to those results, including hypotheses, failures, decisions, and iterations. By addressing the loss of tacit knowledge -- typically buried in notebooks, emails, or memory -- PKLs lay a foundation for reproducible, collaborative, and adaptive research. PKLs provide executable, version-controlled records that contextualize each step of a research process. For example, a researcher using Jupyter notebooks could share not just final outputs, but also the reasoning, discarded approaches, and intermediate analyses that informed them. This work proposes a framework for implementing PKLs within the Jupyter ecosystem, supported by a lens-based transformation model and procedural storage schema.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14715v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hamidah Oderinwale</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Open Research Dataset of the 1932 Cairo Congress of Arab Music</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14503v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces ORD-CC32 , an open research dataset derived from the 1932 Cairo Congress of Arab Music recordings, a historically significant collection representing diverse Arab musical traditions. The dataset includes structured metadata, melodic and rhythmic mode tags (maqam and iqa), manually labeled tonic information, and acoustic features extracted using state-of-the-art pitch detection methods. These resources support computational studies of tuning, temperament, and regional variations in Arab music. A case study using pitch histograms demonstrates the potential for data-driven analysis of microtonal differences across regions. By making this dataset openly available, we aim to enable interdisciplinary research in computational ethnomusicology, music information retrieval (MIR), cultural studies, and digital heritage preservation. ORD-CC32 is shared on Zenodo with tools for feature extraction and metadata retrieval.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14503v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Baris Bozkurt (College of Interdisciplinary Studies, Zayed University, Dubai, United Arab Emirates)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chatting with Papers: A Hybrid Approach Using LLMs and Knowledge Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11633v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This demo paper reports on a new workflow \textit{GhostWriter} that combines the use of Large Language Models and Knowledge Graphs (semantic artifacts) to support navigation through collections. Situated in the research area of Retrieval Augmented Generation, this specific workflow represents the creation of local and adaptable chatbots. Based on the tool-suite \textit{EverythingData} at the backend, \textit{GhostWriter} provides an interface that enables querying and ``chatting'' with a collection. Applied iteratively, the workflow supports the information needs of researchers when interacting with a collection of papers, whether it be to gain an overview, to learn more about a specific concept and its context, and helps the researcher ultimately to refine their research question in a controlled way. We demonstrate the workflow for a collection of articles from the \textit{method data analysis} journal published by GESIS -- Leibniz-Institute for the Social Sciences. We also point to further application areas.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11633v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vyacheslav Tykhonov, Han Yang, Philipp Mayr, Jetze Touber, Andrea Scharnhorst</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
