<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS</link>
    <description>cs.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 03:48:57 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Fully Dynamic Adversarially Robust Correlation Clustering in Polylogarithmic Update Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09979v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the dynamic correlation clustering problem with $\textit{adaptive}$ edge label flips. In correlation clustering, we are given a $n$-vertex complete graph whose edges are labeled either $(+)$ or $(-)$, and the goal is to minimize the total number of $(+)$ edges between clusters and the number of $(-)$ edges within clusters. We consider the dynamic setting with adversarial robustness, in which the $\textit{adaptive}$ adversary could flip the label of an edge based on the current output of the algorithm. Our main result is a randomized algorithm that always maintains an $O(1)$-approximation to the optimal correlation clustering with $O(\log^{2}{n})$ amortized update time. Prior to our work, no algorithm with $O(1)$-approximation and $\text{polylog}{(n)}$ update time for the adversarially robust setting was known. We further validate our theoretical results with experiments on synthetic and real-world datasets with competitive empirical performances. Our main technical ingredient is an algorithm that maintains $\textit{sparse-dense decomposition}$ with $\text{polylog}{(n)}$ update time, which could be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09979v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vladimir Braverman, Prathamesh Dharangutte, Shreyas Pai, Vihan Shah, Chen Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal Capacity Modification for Strongly Stable Matchings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10284</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10284v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider the Hospital/Residents (HR) problem in the presence of ties in preference lists. Among the three notions of stability, viz. weak, strong, and super stability, we focus on the notion of strong stability. Strong stability has many desirable properties both theoretically and practically; however, its existence is not guaranteed.
  In this paper, our objective is to optimally increase the quotas of hospitals to ensure that a strongly stable matching exists in the modified instance. First, we show that if ties are allowed in residents' preference lists, it may not be possible to augment the hospital quotas to obtain an instance that admits a strongly stable matching. When residents' preference lists are strict, we explore two natural optimization criteria: (i) minimizing the maximum capacity increase for any hospital (MINMAX), and (ii) minimizing the total capacity increase across all hospitals (MINSUM). We show that the MINMAX problem is NP-hard in general. When hospital preference lists can have ties of length at most $\ell+1$, we give a polynomial-time algorithm that increases each hospital's quota by at most $\ell$, ensuring the resulting instance admits a strongly stable matching.
  We show that the MINSUM problem admits a polynomial-time algorithm. However, when each hospital incurs a cost for each capacity increase, the problem becomes NP-hard, even if the costs are 0 or 1. This also implies that the problem cannot be approximated to any multiplicative factor. We also consider a related problem under the MINSUM objective. Given an HR instance and a forced pair $(r^*,h^*)$, the goal is to decide if it is possible to increase hospital quotas (if necessary) to obtain a strongly stable matching that matches the pair $(r^*,h^*)$. We show a polynomial-time algorithm for this problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10284v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keshav Ranjan, Meghana Nasre, Prajakta Nimbhorkar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fair Secretaries with Unfair Predictions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09854</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09854v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Algorithms with predictions is a recent framework for decision-making under uncertainty that leverages the power of machine-learned predictions without making any assumption about their quality. The goal in this framework is for algorithms to achieve an improved performance when the predictions are accurate while maintaining acceptable guarantees when the predictions are erroneous. A serious concern with algorithms that use predictions is that these predictions can be biased and, as a result, cause the algorithm to make decisions that are deemed unfair. We show that this concern manifests itself in the classical secretary problem in the learning-augmented setting -- the state-of-the-art algorithm can have zero probability of accepting the best candidate, which we deem unfair, despite promising to accept a candidate whose expected value is at least $\max\{\Omega (1) , 1 - O(\epsilon)\}$ times the optimal value, where $\epsilon$ is the prediction error. We show how to preserve this promise while also guaranteeing to accept the best candidate with probability $\Omega(1)$. Our algorithm and analysis are based on a new "pegging" idea that diverges from existing works and simplifies/unifies some of their results. Finally, we extend to the $k$-secretary problem and complement our theoretical analysis with experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09854v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eric Balkanski, Will Ma, Andreas Maggiori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ranking and Unranking of the Planar Embeddings of a Planar Graph</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.10319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.10319v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Let $\mathcal{G}$ be the set of all the planar embeddings of a (not necessarily connected) $n$-vertex graph $G$. We present a bijection $\Phi$ from $\mathcal{G}$ to the natural numbers in the interval $[0 \dots |\mathcal{G}| - 1]$. Given a planar embedding $\mathcal{E}$ of $G$, we show that $\Phi(\mathcal{E})$ can be decomposed into a sequence of $O(n)$ natural numbers each describing a specific feature of $\mathcal{E}$. The function $\Phi$, which is a ranking function for $\mathcal{G}$, can be computed in $O(n)$ time, while its inverse unranking function $\Phi^{-1}$ can be computed in $O(n \alpha(n))$ time. The results of this paper can be of practical use to uniformly at random generating the planar embeddings of a graph $G$ or to enumerating such embeddings with amortized constant delay. Also, they can be used to counting, enumerating or uniformly at random generating constrained planar embeddings of $G$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.10319v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Di Battista, Fabrizio Grosso, Giulia Maragno, Maurizio Patrignani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientability of Undirected Phylogenetic Networks to a Desired Class: Practical Algorithms and Application to Tree-Child Orientation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09776v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The C-Orientation problem asks whether it is possible to orient an undirected graph to a directed phylogenetic network of a desired network class C. This problem arises, for example, when visualising evolutionary data, as popular methods such as Neighbor-Net are distance-based and inevitably produce undirected graphs. The complexity of C-Orientation remains open for many classes C, including binary tree-child networks, and practical methods are still lacking. In this paper, we propose an exact FPT algorithm for C-Orientation that is applicable to any class C and parameterised by the reticulation number and the maximum size of minimal basic cycles, and a very fast heuristic for Tree-Child Orientation. While the state-of-the-art for C-Orientation is a simple exponential time algorithm whose computational bottleneck lies in searching for appropriate reticulation vertex placements, our methods significantly reduce this search space. Experiments show that, although our FPT algorithm is still exponential, it significantly outperforms the existing method. The heuristic runs even faster but with increasing false negatives as the reticulation number grows. Given this trade-off, we also discuss theoretical directions for improvement and biological applicability of the heuristic approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09776v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tsuyoshi Urata, Manato Yokoyama, Haruki Miyaji, Momoko Hayamizu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compressed Game Solving</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.07273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.07273v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We recast move generators for solving board games as operations on compressed sets of strings. We aim for compressed representations with space sublinear in the number of game positions for interesting sets of positions, move generation in time roughly linear in the compressed size and membership tests in constant time. To the extent that we achieve these tradeoffs empirically, we can strongly solve board games in time sublinear in the state space. We demonstrate this concept with the game Breakthrough where we empirically realize compressed representations taking roughly $n^{0.5}$ to $n^{0.7}$ space to store relevant sets of $n$ positions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.07273v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeffrey Considine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FlexFlood: Efficiently Updatable Learned Multi-dimensional Index</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.09205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.09205v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A learned multi-dimensional index is a data structure that efficiently answers multi-dimensional orthogonal queries by understanding the data distribution using machine learning models. One of the existing problems is that the search performance significantly decreases when the distribution of data stored in the data structure becomes skewed due to update operations. To overcome this problem, we propose FlexFlood, a flexible variant of Flood. FlexFlood partially reconstructs the internal structure when the data distribution becomes skewed. Moreover, FlexFlood is the first learned multi-dimensional index that guarantees the time complexity of the update operation. Through experiments using both artificial and real-world data, we demonstrate that the search performance when the data distribution becomes skewed is up to 10 times faster than existing methods. We also found that partial reconstruction takes only about twice as much time as naive data updating.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.09205v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fuma Hidaka, Yusuke Matsui</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic aspects of semistability of quiver representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06493v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the semistability of quiver representations from an algorithmic perspective. We present efficient algorithms for several fundamental computational problems on the semistability of quiver representations: deciding the semistability and $\sigma$-semistability, finding the maximizers of King's criterion, and computing the Harder--Narasimhan filtration. We also investigate a class of polyhedral cones defined by the linear system in King's criterion, which we refer to as King cones. For rank-one representations, we demonstrate that these King cones can be encoded by submodular flow polytopes, enabling us to decide the $\sigma$-semistability in strongly polynomial time. Our approach employs submodularity in quiver representations, which may be of independent interest.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06493v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuni Iwamasa, Taihei Oki, Tasuku Soma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stabilizer bootstrapping: A recipe for efficient agnostic tomography and magic estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.06967v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the task of agnostic tomography: given copies of an unknown $n$-qubit state $\rho$ which has fidelity $\tau$ with some state in a given class $C$, find a state which has fidelity $\ge \tau - \epsilon$ with $\rho$. We give a new framework, stabilizer bootstrapping, for designing computationally efficient protocols for this task, and use this to get new agnostic tomography protocols for the following classes:
  Stabilizer states: We give a protocol that runs in time $\mathrm{poly}(n,1/\epsilon)\cdot (1/\tau)^{O(\log(1/\tau))}$, answering an open question posed by Grewal, Iyer, Kretschmer, Liang [43] and Anshu and Arunachalam [6]. Previous protocols ran in time $\mathrm{exp}(\Theta(n))$ or required $\tau&gt;\cos^2(\pi/8)$.
  States with stabilizer dimension $n - t$: We give a protocol that runs in time $n^3\cdot(2^t/\tau)^{O(\log(1/\epsilon))}$, extending recent work on learning quantum states prepared by circuits with few non-Clifford gates, which only applied in the realizable setting where $\tau = 1$ [33, 40, 49, 66].
  Discrete product states: If $C = K^{\otimes n}$ for some $\mu$-separated discrete set $K$ of single-qubit states, we give a protocol that runs in time $(n/\mu)^{O((1 + \log (1/\tau))/\mu)}/\epsilon^2$. This strictly generalizes a prior guarantee which applied to stabilizer product states [42]. For stabilizer product states, we give a further improved protocol that runs in time $(n^2/\epsilon^2)\cdot (1/\tau)^{O(\log(1/\tau))}$.
  As a corollary, we give the first protocol for estimating stabilizer fidelity, a standard measure of magic for quantum states, to error $\epsilon$ in $n^3 \mathrm{quasipoly}(1/\epsilon)$ time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.06967v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sitan Chen, Weiyuan Gong, Qi Ye, Zhihan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
