<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS</link>
    <description>cs.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>FORWARD: Feasibility Oriented Random-Walk Inspired Algorithm for Radial Reconfiguration in Distribution Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14080</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14080v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider an optimal flow distribution problem in which the goal is to find a radial configuration that minimizes resistance-induced quadratic distribution costs while ensuring delivery of inputs from multiple sources to all sinks to meet their demands. This problem has critical applications in various distribution systems, such as electricity, where efficient energy flow is crucial for both economic and environmental reasons. Due to its complexity, finding an optimal solution is computationally challenging and NP-hard. In this paper, we propose a novel algorithm called FORWARD, which leverages graph theory to efficiently identify feasible configurations in polynomial time. By drawing parallels with random walk processes on electricity networks, our method simplifies the search space, significantly reducing computational effort while maintaining performance. The FORWARD algorithm employs a combination of network preprocessing, intelligent partitioning, and strategic sampling to construct radial configurations that meet flow requirements, finding a feasible solution in polynomial time. Numerical experiments demonstrate the effectiveness of our approach, highlighting its potential for real-world applications in optimizing distribution networks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14080v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joan Vendrell, Russell Bent, Solmaz Kia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bidirectional Dijkstra's Algorithm is Instance-Optimal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14638v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: While Dijkstra's algorithm has near-optimal time complexity for the problem of finding the shortest $st$-path, in practice, other algorithms are often superior on huge graphs. A prominent such example is the bidirectional search, which executes Dijkstra's algorithm from both endpoints in parallel and stops when these executions meet.
  In this paper, we give a strong theoretical justification for the use of such bidirectional search algorithms. We prove that for weighted multigraphs, both directed and undirected, a careful implementation of bidirectional search is instance-optimal with respect to the number of edges it explores. That is, we prove that no correct algorithm can outperform our implementation of bidirectional search on any single instance by more than a constant factor. For unweighted graphs, we show that bidirectional search is instace-optimal up to a factor of $O(\Delta)$ where $\Delta$ is the maximum degree of the graph. We also show that this is the best possible.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14638v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bernhard Haeupler, Richard Hlad\'ik, Vaclav Rozhon, Robert E. Tarjan, Jakub T\v{e}tek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Instance-Optimality in I/O-Efficient Sampling and Sequential Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14643</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14643v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Suppose we have a memory storing $0$s and $1$s and we want to estimate the frequency of $1$s by sampling. We want to do this I/O-efficiently, exploiting that each read gives a block of $B$ bits at unit cost; not just one bit. If the input consists of uniform blocks: either all 1s or all 0s, then sampling a whole block at a time does not reduce the number of samples needed for estimation. On the other hand, if bits are randomly permuted, then getting a block of $B$ bits is as good as getting $B$ independent bit samples. However, we do not want to make any such assumptions on the input. Instead, our goal is to have an algorithm with instance-dependent performance guarantees which stops sampling blocks as soon as we know that we have a probabilistically reliable estimate. We prove our algorithms to be instance-optimal among algorithms oblivious to the order of the blocks, which we argue is the strongest form of instance optimality we can hope for. We also present similar results for I/O-efficiently estimating mean with both additive and multiplicative error, estimating histograms, quantiles, as well as the empirical cumulative distribution function.
  We obtain our above results on I/O-efficient sampling by reducing to corresponding problems in the so-called sequential estimation. In this setting, one samples from an unknown distribution until one can provide an estimate with some desired error probability. We then provide non-parametric instance-optimal results for several fundamental problems: mean and quantile estimation, as well as learning mixture distributions with respect to $\ell_\infty$ and the so-called Kolmogorov-Smirnov distance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14643v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shyam Narayanan, V\'aclav Rozho\v{n}, Jakub T\v{e}tek, Mikkel Thorup</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonadaptive Noisy Group Testing with Optimal Tests and Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14566v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In Group Testing, the objective is to identify K defective items out of N, K&lt;&lt;N, by testing pools of items together and using the least amount of tests possible. In this paper, we propose a non-adaptive probabilistic group testing scheme in the presence of both false positives and false negatives in test outcomes. Our scheme simultaneously achieves the optimal asymptotic bound of O(KlogN) for both the number of tests and the decoding complexity of recovery with high probability, where O hides a constant that depends on the noisy channel. This result generalizes Price and Scarlett's group testing algorithm from the noiseless setting to the Binary Asymmetric Channel (BAC) and Binary Symmetric Channel (BSC) settings, achieving both the optimal number of tests and decoding complexity, which was one of the main open problems of this line of research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14566v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaxin Li, Arya Mazumdar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A subquadratic certification scheme for P5-free graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14658v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In local certification, vertices of a $n$-vertex graph perform a local verification to check if a given property is satisfied by the graph. This verification is performed thanks to certificates, which are pieces of information that are given to the vertices. In this work, we focus on the local certification of $P_5$-freeness, and we prove a $O(n^{3/2})$ upper bound on the size of the certificates, which is (to our knowledge) the first subquadratic upper bound for this property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14658v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Bousquet, S\'ebastien Zeitoun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximate Cartesian Tree Matching: an Approach Using Swaps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.16065</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.16065v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Cartesian tree pattern matching consists of finding all the factors of a text that have the same Cartesian tree than a given pattern. There already exist theoretical and practical solutions for the exact case. In this paper, we propose the first algorithm for solving approximate Cartesian tree pattern matching. We consider Cartesian tree pattern matching with one swap: given a pattern of length m and a text of length n we present two algorithms that find all the factors of the text that have the same Cartesian tree of the pattern after one transposition of two adjacent symbols. The first algorithm uses a characterization of a linear representation of the Cartesian trees called parent-distance after one swap and runs in time Theta(mn) using Theta(m) space. The second algorithm generates all the parent-distance tables of sequences that have the same Cartesian tree than the pattern after one swap. It runs in time O((m^2 + n)log m) and has O(m^2) space complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.16065v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bastien Auvray, Julien David, Richard Groult, Thierry Lecroq</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Tighter Complexity Analysis of SparseGPT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12151v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we improved the analysis of the running time of SparseGPT [Frantar, Alistarh ICML 2023] from $O(d^{3})$ to $O(d^{\omega} + d^{2+a+o(1)} + d^{1+\omega(1,1,a)-a})$ for any $a \in [0, 1]$, where $\omega$ is the exponent of matrix multiplication. In particular, for the current $\omega \approx 2.371$ [Alman, Duan, Williams, Xu, Xu, Zhou 2024], our running time boils down to $O(d^{2.53})$. This running time is due to the analysis of the lazy update behavior in iterative maintenance problems such as [Deng, Song, Weinstein 2022; Brand, Song, Zhou ICML 2024].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12151v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoyu Li, Yingyu Liang, Zhenmei Shi, Zhao Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Palindromes Compression and Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.09984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.09984v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel method for compressing palindromic structures in strings, establishing upper and lower bounds for their efficient representation. We uncover a unique relationship between the Lempel-Ziv parsing of palindromes and the alphabet size, leveraging this insight to propose a compression algorithm that improves space efficiency of Manacher array. Additionally, we present a data structure capable of storing all maximal palindromes (Manacher array) in sublinear space with near-optimal access time. Our approach reduces the memory overhead of storing palindromes, offering a new avenue for optimizing compression algorithms in text processing applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.09984v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Itzhaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Certificates in P and Subquadratic-Time Computation of Radius, Diameter, and all Eccentricities in Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.04660</link>
      <description>arXiv:1803.04660v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In the context of fine-grained complexity, we investigate the notion of certificate enabling faster polynomial-time algorithms. We specifically target radius (minimum eccentricity), diameter (maximum eccentricity), and all-eccentricity computations for which quadratic-time lower bounds are known under plausible conjectures. In each case, we introduce a notion of certificate as a specific set of nodes from which appropriate bounds on all eccentricities can be derived in subquadratic time when this set has sublinear size. The existence of small certificates is a barrier against SETH-based lower bounds for these problems. We indeed prove that for graph classes with small certificates, there exist randomized subquadratic-time algorithms for computing the radius, the diameter, and all eccentricities respectively.Moreover, these notions of certificates are tightly related to algorithms probing the graph through one-to-all distance queries and allow to explain the efficiency of practical radius and diameter algorithms from the literature. Our formalization enables a novel primal-dual analysis of a classical approach for diameter computation that leads to algorithms for radius, diameter and all eccentricities with theoretical guarantees with respect to certain graph parameters. This is complemented by experimental results on various types of real-world graphs showing that these parameters appear to be low in practice. Finally, we obtain refined results for several graph classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1803.04660v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.NI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feodor F. Dragan (UniBuc, ICI), Guillaume Ducoffe (UniBuc, ICI), Michel Habib (IRIF), Laurent Viennot (DI-ENS)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simple Opinion Dynamics for No-Regret Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.08670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.08670v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study a cooperative multi-agent bandit setting in the distributed GOSSIP model: in every round, each of $n$ agents chooses an action from a common set, observes the action's corresponding reward, and subsequently exchanges information with a single randomly chosen neighbor, which may inform its choice in the next round. We introduce and analyze families of memoryless and time-independent protocols for this setting, inspired by opinion dynamics that are well-studied for other algorithmic tasks in the GOSSIP model. For stationary reward settings, we prove for the first time that these simple protocols exhibit best-of-both-worlds behavior, simultaneously obtaining constant cumulative regret scaling like $R(T)/T = \widetilde O(1/T)$, and also reaching consensus on the highest-mean action within $\widetilde O(\sqrt{n})$ rounds. We obtain these results by showing a new connection between the global evolution of these decentralized protocols and a class of zero-sum multiplicative weights update} processes. Using this connection, we establish a general framework for analyzing the population-level regret and other properties of our protocols. Finally, we show our protocols are also surprisingly robust to adversarial rewards, and in this regime we obtain sublinear regret scaling like $R(T)/T = \widetilde O(1/\sqrt{T})$ as long as the number of rounds does not grow too fast as a function of $n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.08670v5</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John Lazarsfeld, Dan Alistarh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Unified Algorithmic Framework for Dynamic Assortment Optimization under MNL Choice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03604</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03604v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider assortment and inventory planning problems with dynamic stockout-based substitution effects, and without replenishment, in two different settings: (1) Customers can see all available products when they arrive, a typical scenario in physical stores. (2) The seller can choose to offer a subset of available products to each customer, which is more common on online platforms. Both settings are known to be computationally challenging, and the current approximation algorithms for the two settings are quite different. We develop a unified algorithm framework under the MNL choice model for both settings. Our algorithms improve on the state-of-the-art algorithms in terms of approximation guarantee and runtime, and the ability to manage uncertainty in the total number of customers and handle more complex constraints. In the process, we establish various novel properties of dynamic assortment planning (for the MNL choice model) that may be useful more broadly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03604v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuo Sun, Rajan Udwani, Zuo-Jun Max Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A logarithmic approximation of linearly-ordered colourings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.19556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.19556v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A linearly ordered (LO) $k$-colouring of a hypergraph assigns to each vertex a colour from the set $\{0,1,\ldots,k-1\}$ in such a way that each hyperedge has a unique maximum element. Barto, Batistelli, and Berg conjectured that it is NP-hard to find an LO $k$-colouring of an LO 2-colourable 3-uniform hypergraph for any constant $k\geq 2$ [STACS'21] but even the case $k=3$ is still open. Nakajima and \v{Z}ivn\'{y} gave polynomial-time algorithms for finding, given an LO 2-colourable 3-uniform hypergraph, an LO colouring with $O^*(\sqrt{n})$ colours [ICALP'22] and an LO colouring with $O^*(\sqrt[3]{n})$ colours [ACM ToCT'23]. Very recently, Louis, Newman, and Ray gave an SDP-based algorithm with $O^*(\sqrt[5]{n})$ colours. We present two simple polynomial-time algorithms that find an LO colouring with $O(\log_2(n))$ colours, which is an exponential improvement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.19556v4</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johan H{\aa}stad, Bj\"orn Martinsson, Tamio-Vesa Nakajima, Stanislav \v{Z}ivn\'y</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fr\'echet Distance in Subquadratic Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.05231</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.05231v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $m$ and $n$ be the numbers of vertices of two polygonal curves in $\mathbb{R}^d$ for any fixed $d$ such that $m \leq n$. Since it was known in 1995 how to compute the Fr\'{e}chet distance of these two curves in $O(mn\log (mn))$ time, it has been an open problem whether the running time can be reduced to $o(n^2)$ when $m = \Omega(n)$. In the mean time, several well-known quadratic time barriers in computational geometry have been overcome: 3SUM, some 3SUM-hard problems, and the computation of some distances between two polygonal curves, including the discrete Fr\'{e}chet distance, the dynamic time warping distance, and the geometric edit distance. It is curious that the quadratic time barrier for Fr\'{e}chet distance still stands. We present an algorithm to compute the Fr\'echet distance in $O(mn(\log\log n)^{2+\mu}\log n/\log^{1+\mu} m)$ expected time for some constant $\mu \in (0,1)$. It is the first algorithm that returns the Fr\'{e}chet distance in $o(mn)$ time when $m = \Omega(n^{\varepsilon})$ for any fixed $\varepsilon \in (0,1]$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.05231v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siu-Wing Cheng, Haoqiang Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Linear Attention in Polynomial Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10101v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Previous research has explored the computational expressivity of Transformer models in simulating Boolean circuits or Turing machines. However, the learnability of these simulators from observational data has remained an open question. Our study addresses this gap by providing the first polynomial-time learnability results (specifically strong, agnostic PAC learning) for single-layer Transformers with linear attention. We show that linear attention may be viewed as a linear predictor in a suitably defined RKHS. As a consequence, the problem of learning any linear transformer may be converted into the problem of learning an ordinary linear predictor in an expanded feature space, and any such predictor may be converted back into a multiheaded linear transformer. Moving to generalization, we show how to efficiently identify training datasets for which every empirical risk minimizer is equivalent (up to trivial symmetries) to the linear Transformer that generated the data, thereby guaranteeing the learned model will correctly generalize across all inputs. Finally, we provide examples of computations expressible via linear attention and therefore polynomial-time learnable, including associative memories, finite automata, and a class of Universal Turing Machine (UTMs) with polynomially bounded computation histories. We empirically validate our theoretical findings on three tasks: learning random linear attention networks, key--value associations, and learning to execute finite automata. Our findings bridge a critical gap between theoretical expressivity and learnability of Transformers, and show that flexible and general models of computation are efficiently learnable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10101v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Morris Yau, Ekin Aky\"urek, Jiayuan Mao, Joshua B. Tenenbaum, Stefanie Jegelka, Jacob Andreas</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
