<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.DS updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS</link>
    <description>cs.DS updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.DS" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 04:00:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Bernstein-Vazirani Algorithm with A CCNOT-Based Oracle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a quantum algorithm to solve Bernstein-Vazirani problem to recover secret strings, using quantum oracles that are based on the Toffoli (CCNOT) logic gate. As in the known algorithm, the proposed algorithm is a polynomial speed-up algorithm. Moreover, the proposed approach allows us to solve new problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18951v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahmoud H. Annaby</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Efficient Frequency-Based Approach for Maximal Square Detection in Binary Matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18974v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a novel frequency-based algorithm that solves the maximal square problem with improved practical speed performance, while maintaining optimal asymptotic complexity. The proposed approach tracks the columnar continuity of the ones through an adaptive frequency vector and dynamic thresholding mechanism, which eliminates the need for nested minimum operations commonly found in standard dynamic programming solutions. Theoretical analysis confirms the time complexity of O(mn) and the space complexity of O(n), with formal loop-invariant proofs ensuring correctness. Comprehensive benchmarking demonstrates speed improvements of 1.3-5x over standard methods for various matrix densities and sizes. Applications in urban planning, environmental modeling, and medical image analysis are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18974v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Swastik Bhandari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Privately Evaluating Untrusted Black-Box Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19268</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19268v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide tools for sharing sensitive data when the data curator doesn't know in advance what questions an (untrusted) analyst might ask about the data. The analyst can specify a program that they want the curator to run on the dataset. We model the program as a black-box function $f$. We study differentially private algorithms, called privacy wrappers, that, given black-box access to a real-valued function $f$ and a sensitive dataset $x$, output an accurate approximation to $f(x)$. The dataset $x$ is modeled as a finite subset of a possibly infinite set $U$, in which each entry represents data of one individual. A privacy wrapper calls $f$ on the dataset $x$ and on some subsets of $x$ and returns either an approximation to $f(x)$ or a nonresponse symbol $\perp$. The wrapper may also use additional information (that is, parameters) provided by the analyst, but differential privacy is required for all values of these parameters. Correct setting of these parameters will ensure better accuracy of the wrapper. The bottleneck in the running time of our wrappers is the number of calls to $f$, which we refer to as queries. Our goal is to design wrappers with high accuracy and low query complexity. We introduce a novel setting, the automated sensitivity detection setting, where the analyst supplies the black-box function $f$ and the intended (finite) range of $f$. In the previously considered setting, the claimed sensitivity bound setting, the analyst supplies additional parameters that describe the sensitivity of $f$. We design privacy wrappers for both settings and show that our wrappers are nearly optimal in terms of accuracy, locality (i.e., the depth of the local neighborhood of the dataset $x$ they explore), and query complexity. In the claimed sensitivity bound setting, we provide the first accuracy guarantees that have no dependence on the size of the universe $U$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19268v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ephraim Linder, Sofya Raskhodnikova, Adam Smith, Thomas Steinke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long Arithmetic Progressions in Sumsets and Subset Sums: Constructive Proofs and Efficient Witnesses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19299</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19299v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Existence of long arithmetic progression in sumsets and subset sums has been studied extensively in the field of additive combinatorics. These additive combinatorics results play a central role in the recent progress of fundamental problems in theoretical computer science including Knapsack and Subset Sum. The non-constructiveness of relevant additive combinatorics results affects their application in algorithms. In particular, several additive combinatorics-based algorithms for Subset Sum work only for the decision version of the problem, but not for the search version.
  We provide constructive proofs for finite addition theorems [S\'ark\H{o}zy'89 '94], which are fundamental results in additive combinatorics concerning the existence of long arithmetic progression in sumsets and subset sums. Our constructive proofs yield a near-linear time algorithm that returns an arithmetic progression explicitly, and moreover, for each term in the arithmetic progression, it also returns its representation as the sum of elements in the base set.
  As an application, we obtain an $\tilde{O}(n)$-time algorithm for the search version of dense subset sum now. Another application of our result is Unbounded Subset Sum, where each input integer can be used an infinite number of times. A classic result on the Frobenius problem [Erd\H{o}s and Graham '72] implies that for all $t \geq 2a^2_{\max}/n$, the decision version can be solved trivially in linear time. It remains unknown whether the search version can be solved in the same time. Our result implies that for all $t \geq ca^2_{\max}/n$ for some constant $c$, a solution for Unbounded Subset Sum can be obtained in $O(n \log a_{\max})$ time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19299v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lin Chen, Yuchen Mao, Guochuan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improved Approximation Algorithms for Three-Dimensional Knapsack</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19365v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the three-dimensional Knapsack (3DK) problem, in which we are given a set of axis-aligned cuboids with associated profits and an axis-aligned cube knapsack. The objective is to find a non-overlapping axis-aligned packing (by translation) of the maximum profit subset of cuboids into the cube. The previous best approximation algorithm is due to Diedrich, Harren, Jansen, Th\"{o}le, and Thomas (2008), who gave a $(7+\varepsilon)$-approximation algorithm for 3DK and a $(5+\varepsilon)$-approximation algorithm for the variant when the items can be rotated by 90 degrees around any axis, for any constant $\varepsilon&gt;0$. Chleb\'{\i}k and Chleb\'{\i}kov\'{a} (2009) showed that the problem does not admit an asymptotic polynomial-time approximation scheme.
  We provide an improved polynomial-time $(139/29+\varepsilon) \approx 4.794$-approximation algorithm for 3DK and $(30/7+\varepsilon) \approx 4.286$-approximation when rotations by 90 degrees are allowed. We also provide improved approximation algorithms for several variants such as the cardinality case (when all items have the same profit) and uniform profit-density case (when the profit of an item is equal to its volume). Our key technical contribution is container packing -- a structured packing in 3D such that all items are assigned into a constant number of containers, and each container is packed using a specific strategy based on its type. We first show the existence of highly profitable container packings. Thereafter, we show that one can find near-optimal container packing efficiently using a variant of the Generalized Assignment Problem (GAP).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19365v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Klaus Jansen, Debajyoti Kar, Arindam Khan, K. V. N. Sreenivas, Malte Tutas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Stochastic Matching with Unknown Arrival Order: Beating $0.5$ against the Online Optimum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19456v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the online stochastic matching problem. Against the offline benchmark, Feldman, Gravin, and Lucier (SODA 2015) designed an optimal $0.5$-competitive algorithm. A recent line of work, initiated by Papadimitriou, Pollner, Saberi, and Wajc (MOR 2024), focuses on designing approximation algorithms against the online optimum. The online benchmark allows positive results surpassing the $0.5$ ratio.
  In this work, adapting the order-competitive analysis by Ezra, Feldman, Gravin, and Tang (SODA 2023), we design a $0.5+\Omega(1)$ order-competitive algorithm against the online benchmark with unknown arrival order. Our algorithm is significantly different from existing ones, as the known arrival order is crucial to the previous approximation algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19456v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enze Sun, Zhihao Gavin Tang, Yifan Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximating $q \rightarrow p$ Norms of Non-Negative Matrices in Nearly-Linear Time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19553v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide the first nearly-linear time algorithm for approximating $\ell_{q \rightarrow p}$-norms of non-negative matrices, for $q \geq p \geq 1$. Our algorithm returns a $(1-\varepsilon)$-approximation to the matrix norm in time $\widetilde{O}\left(\frac{1}{q \varepsilon} \cdot \text{nnz}(\boldsymbol{\mathit{A}})\right)$, where $\boldsymbol{\mathit{A}}$ is the input matrix, and improves upon the previous state of the art, which either proved convergence only in the limit [Boyd '74], or had very high polynomial running times [Bhaskara-Vijayraghavan, SODA '11]. Our algorithm is extremely simple, and is largely inspired from the coordinate-scaling approach used for positive linear program solvers.
  We note that our algorithm can readily be used in the [Englert-R\"{a}cke, FOCS '09] to improve the running time of constructing $O(\log n)$-competitive $\ell_p$-oblivious routings. We thus complement this result with a simple cutting-plane based scheme for computing $\textit{optimal}$ oblivious routings in graphs with respect to any monotone norm. Combined with state of the art cutting-plane solvers, this scheme runs in time $\widetilde{O}(n^6 m^3)$, which is significantly faster than the one based on Englert-R\"{a}cke, and generalizes the $\ell_\infty$ routing algorithm of [Azar-Cohen-Fiat-Kaplan-R\"acke, STOC '03].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19553v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Etienne Objois, Adrian Vladu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lifting Linear Sketches: Optimal Bounds and Adversarial Robustness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19629v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce a novel technique for ``lifting'' dimension lower bounds for linear sketches in the real-valued setting to dimension lower bounds for linear sketches with polynomially-bounded integer entries when the input is a polynomially-bounded integer vector. Using this technique, we obtain the first optimal sketching lower bounds for discrete inputs in a data stream, for classical problems such as approximating the frequency moments, estimating the operator norm, and compressed sensing. Additionally, we lift the adaptive attack of Hardt and Woodruff (STOC, 2013) for breaking any real-valued linear sketch via a sequence of real-valued queries, and show how to obtain an attack on any integer-valued linear sketch using integer-valued queries. This shows that there is no linear sketch in a data stream with insertions and deletions that is adversarially robust for approximating any $L_p$ norm of the input, resolving a central open question for adversarially robust streaming algorithms. To do so, we introduce a new pre-processing technique of independent interest which, given an integer-valued linear sketch, increases the dimension of the sketch by only a constant factor in order to make the orthogonal lattice to its row span smooth. This pre-processing then enables us to leverage results in lattice theory on discrete Gaussian distributions and reason that efficient discrete sketches imply efficient continuous sketches. Our work resolves open questions from the Banff '14 and '17 workshops on Communication Complexity and Applications, as well as the STOC '21 and FOCS '23 workshops on adaptivity and robustness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19629v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Elena Gribelyuk, Honghao Lin, David P. Woodruff, Huacheng Yu, Samson Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplication of 0-1 matrices via clustering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19631v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study applications of clustering (in particular the $k$-center
  clustering problem) in the design of efficient and practical
  deterministic algorithms for computing an approximate and the exact
  arithmetic matrix product of two 0-1 rectangular matrices $A$ and
  $B$ with clustered rows or columns, respectively. Let $\lambda_A$
  and $\lambda_B$ denote the minimum maximum radius of a cluster in an
  $\ell$-center clustering of the rows of $A$ and in a $k$-center
  clustering of the columns of $B,$ respectively. In particular,
  assuming that the matrices have size $n\times n$, we obtain the
  following results.
  A simple deterministic algorithm that approximates each entry of
  the arithmetic matrix product of $A$ and $B$ within the additive
  error of at most $2\lambda_A$ in $O(n^2\ell)$ time or at most
  $2\lambda_B$ in $O(n^2k)$ time.
  A simple deterministic preprocessing of the matrices $A$ and $B$
  in $O(n^2\ell)$ time or $O(n^2k)$ time such that a query asking
  for the exact value of an arbitrary entry of the arithmetic matrix
  product of $A$ and $B$ can be answered in $O(\lambda_A)$ time or
  $O(\lambda_B)$ time, respectively.
  A simple deterministic algorithm for the exact arithmetic matrix
  product of $A$ and $B$ running in time $O(n^2(\ell+k+\min\{\lambda_A,\lambda_B\}))$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19631v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jesper Jansson, Miroslaw Kowaluk, Andrzej Lingas, Mia Persson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Distances Lie: Euclidean Embeddings in the Presence of Outliers and Distance Violations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19093v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Distance geometry explores the properties of distance spaces that can be exactly represented as the pairwise Euclidean distances between points in $\mathbb{R}^d$ ($d \geq 1$), or equivalently, distance spaces that can be isometrically embedded in $\mathbb{R}^d$. In this work, we investigate whether a distance space can be isometrically embedded in $\mathbb{R}^d$ after applying a limited number of modifications. Specifically, we focus on two types of modifications: outlier deletion (removing points) and distance modification (adjusting distances between points). The central problem, Euclidean Embedding Editing (EEE), asks whether an input distance space on $n$ points can be transformed, using at most $k$ modifications, into a space that is isometrically embeddable in $\mathbb{R}^d$.
  We present several fixed-parameter tractable (FPT) and approximation algorithms for this problem. Our first result is an algorithm that solves EEE in time $(dk)^{\mathcal{O}(d+k)} + n^{\mathcal{O}(1)}$. The core subroutine of this algorithm, which is of independent interest, is a polynomial-time method for compressing the input distance space into an equivalent instance of EEE with $\mathcal{O}((dk)^2)$ points.
  For the special but important case of EEE where only outlier deletions are allowed, we improve the parameter dependence of the FPT algorithm and obtain a running time of $\min\{(d+3)^k, 2^{d+k}\} \cdot n^{\mathcal{O}(1)}$. Additionally, we provide an FPT-approximation algorithm for this problem, which outputs a set of at most $2 \cdot {\rm OPT}$ outliers in time $2^d \cdot n^{\mathcal{O}(1)}$. This 2-approximation algorithm improves upon the previous $(3+\varepsilon)$-approximation algorithm by Sidiropoulos, Wang, and Wang [SODA '17]. Furthermore, we complement our algorithms with hardness results motivating our choice of parameterizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19093v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Bentert, Fedor V. Fomin, Petr A. Golovach, M. S. Ramanujan, Saket Saurabh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph neural networks extrapolate out-of-distribution for shortest paths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19173v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neural networks (NNs), despite their success and wide adoption, still struggle to extrapolate out-of-distribution (OOD), i.e., to inputs that are not well-represented by their training dataset. Addressing the OOD generalization gap is crucial when models are deployed in environments significantly different from the training set, such as applying Graph Neural Networks (GNNs) trained on small graphs to large, real-world graphs. One promising approach for achieving robust OOD generalization is the framework of neural algorithmic alignment, which incorporates ideas from classical algorithms by designing neural architectures that resemble specific algorithmic paradigms (e.g. dynamic programming). The hope is that trained models of this form would have superior OOD capabilities, in much the same way that classical algorithms work for all instances. We rigorously analyze the role of algorithmic alignment in achieving OOD generalization, focusing on graph neural networks (GNNs) applied to the canonical shortest path problem. We prove that GNNs, trained to minimize a sparsity-regularized loss over a small set of shortest path instances, exactly implement the Bellman-Ford (BF) algorithm for shortest paths. In fact, if a GNN minimizes this loss within an error of $\epsilon$, it implements the BF algorithm with an error of $O(\epsilon)$. Consequently, despite limited training data, these GNNs are guaranteed to extrapolate to arbitrary shortest-path problems, including instances of any size. Our empirical results support our theory by showing that NNs trained by gradient descent are able to minimize this loss and extrapolate in practice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19173v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert R. Nerem, Samantha Chen, Sanjoy Dasgupta, Yusu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Tight Meta-theorem for LOCAL Certification of MSO$_2$ Properties within Bounded Treewidth Graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.19671</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.19671v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Distributed networks are prone to errors so verifying their output is critical. Hence, we develop LOCAL certification protocols for graph properties in which nodes are given certificates that allow them to check whether their network as a whole satisfies some fixed property while only communicating with their local network. Most known LOCAL certification protocols are specifically tailored to the problem they work on and cannot be translated more generally. Thus we target general protocols that can certify any property expressible within a certain logical framework. We consider Monadic Second Order Logic (MSO$_2$), a powerful framework that can express properties such as non-$k$-colorability, Hamiltonicity, and $H$-minor-freeness. Unfortunately, in general, there are MSO$_2$-expressible properties that cannot be certified without huge certificates. For instance, non-3-colorability requires certificates of size $\Omega(n^2/\log n)$ on general $n$-vertex graphs (G\"o\"os, Suomela 2016). Hence, we impose additional structural restrictions on the graph.
  We provide a LOCAL certification protocol for certifying any MSO$_2$-expressible property on graphs of bounded treewidth and, consequently, a LOCAL certification protocol for certifying bounded treewidth. That is for each integer $k$ and each MSO$_2$-expressible property $\Pi$ we give a LOCAL Certification protocol to certify that a graph satisfies $\Pi$ and has treewidth at most $k$ using certificates of size $\mathcal{O}(\log n)$ (which is asymptotically optimal). Our LOCAL certification protocol requires only one round of distributed communication, hence it is also proof-labeling scheme.
  Our result improves upon work by Fraigniaud, Montealegre, Rapaport, and Todinca (Algorithmica 2024), Bousquet, Feuilloley, Pierron (PODC 2022), and the very recent work of Baterisna and Chang.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.19671v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linda Cook, Eun Jung Kim, Tom\'a\v{s} Masa\v{r}\'ik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Not All Learnable Distribution Classes are Privately Learnable</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00267v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We give an example of a class of distributions that is learnable up to constant error in total variation distance with a finite number of samples, but not learnable under $(\varepsilon, \delta)$-differential privacy with the same target error. This weakly refutes a conjecture of Ashtiani.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00267v3</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mark Bun, Gautam Kamath, Argyris Mouzakis, Vikrant Singhal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Separating Coverage and Submodular: Maximization Subject to a Cardinality Constraint</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.05553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.05553v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider two classic problems: maximum coverage and monotone submodular maximization subject to a cardinality constraint. [Nemhauser--Wolsey--Fisher '78] proved that the greedy algorithm provides an approximation of $1-1/e$ for both problems, and it is known that this guarantee is tight ([Nemhauser--Wolsey '78; Feige '98]). Thus, one would naturally assume that everything is resolved when considering the approximation guarantees of these two problems, as both exhibit the same tight approximation and hardness.
  In this work we show that this is not the case, and study both problems when the cardinality constraint is a constant fraction $c \in (0,1]$ of the ground set. We prove that monotone submodular maximization subject to a cardinality constraint admits an approximation of $1-(1-c)^{1/c}$; This approximation equals $1$ when $c=1$ and it gracefully degrades to $1-1/e$ when $c$ approaches $0$. Moreover, for every $c=1/s$ (for any integer $s \in \mathbb{N}$) we present a matching hardness.
  Surprisingly, for $c=1/2$ we prove that Maximum Coverage admits an approximation of $0.7533$, thus separating the two problems. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first known example of a well-studied maximization problem for which coverage and monotone submodular objectives exhibit a different best possible approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.05553v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuval Filmus, Roy Schwartz, Alexander V. Smal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Subquadratic Time Approximation Algorithm for Individually Fair k-Center</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04943</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04943v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the $k$-center problem in the context of individual fairness. Let $P$ be a set of $n$ points in a metric space and $r_x$ be the distance between $x \in P$ and its $\lceil n/k \rceil$-th nearest neighbor. The problem asks to optimize the $k$-center objective under the constraint that, for every point $x$, there is a center within distance $r_x$. We give bicriteria $(\beta,\gamma)$-approximation algorithms that compute clusterings such that every point $x \in P$ has a center within distance $\beta r_x$ and the clustering cost is at most $\gamma$ times the optimal cost. Our main contributions are a deterministic $O(n^2+ kn \log n)$ time $(2,2)$-approximation algorithm and a randomized $O(nk\log(n/\delta)+k^2/\varepsilon)$ time $(10,2+\varepsilon)$-approximation algorithm, where $\delta$ denotes the failure probability. For the latter, we develop a randomized sampling procedure to compute constant factor approximations for the values $r_x$ for all $x\in P$ in subquadratic time; we believe this procedure to be of independent interest within the context of individual fairness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04943v2</guid>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthijs Ebbens, Nicole Funk, Jan H\"ockendorff, Christian Sohler, Vera Weil</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Unified Theory of Time-Varying Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00206</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00206v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: What is a time-varying graph, a time-varying topological space, or, more generally, a mathematical structure that evolves over time? In this work, we lay the foundations for a general theory of temporal data by introducing categories of narratives. These are sheaves on posets of time intervals that encode snapshots of a temporal object along with the relationships between them. This theory satisfies five desiderata distilled from the burgeoning field of time-varying graphs: (D1) it defines both time-varying objects and their morphisms; (D2) it distinguishes between cumulative and persistent interpretations and provides principled methods for transitioning between them; (D3) it systematically lifts static notions to their temporal analogues; (D4) it is object agnostic; (D5) it integrates with theories of dynamical systems. To achieve this, we build upon existing categorical and sheaf-theoretic approaches to temporal graph theory, generalizing them to any category with limits and colimits. We also formalize tacit intuitions that, while present, often remain implicit in temporal graph theory. Beyond synthesizing and reformulating existing ideas in categorical language, we introduce sheaf-theoretic constructions and prove results that, to our knowledge, have not appeared in the temporal data literature - such as the adjunction between persistent and cumulative narratives. More importantly, we integrate these existing and novel elements into a consistent and coherent framework, setting the stage for a unified theory of time-varying data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00206v3</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Merlin Bumpus, James Fairbanks, Martti Karvonen, Wilmer Leal, Fr\'ed\'eric Simard</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A quantum neural network framework for scalable quantum circuit approximation of unitary matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.00012</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.00012v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we develop a Lie group theoretic approach for parametric representation of unitary matrices. This leads to develop a quantum neural network framework for quantum circuit approximation of multi-qubit unitary gates. Layers of the neural networks are defined by product of exponential of certain elements of the Standard Recursive Block Basis, which we introduce as an alternative to Pauli string basis for matrix algebra of complex matrices of order $2^n$. The recursive construction of the neural networks implies that the quantum circuit approximation is scalable i.e. quantum circuit for an $(n+1)$-qubit unitary can be constructed from the circuit of $n$-qubit system by adding a few CNOT gates and single-qubit gates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.00012v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rohit Sarma Sarkar, Bibhas Adhikari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximating Klee's Measure Problem and a Lower Bound for Union Volume Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00996</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00996v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Union volume estimation is a classical algorithmic problem. Given a family of objects $O_1,\ldots,O_n \subseteq \mathbb{R}^d$, we want to approximate the volume of their union. In the special case where all objects are boxes (also known as hyperrectangles) this is known as Klee's measure problem. The state-of-the-art algorithm [Karp, Luby, Madras '89] for union volume estimation and Klee's measure problem in constant dimension $d$ computes a $(1+\varepsilon)$-approximation with constant success probability by using a total of $O(n/\varepsilon^2)$ queries of the form (i) ask for the volume of $O_i$, (ii) sample a point uniformly at random from $O_i$, and (iii) query whether a given point is contained in $O_i$.
  We show that if one can only interact with the objects via the aforementioned three queries, the query complexity of [Karp, Luby, Madras '89] is indeed optimal, i.e., $\Omega(n/\varepsilon^2)$ queries are necessary. Our lower bound already holds for estimating the union of equiponderous axis-aligned polygons in $\mathbb{R}^2$, and even if the algorithm is allowed to inspect the coordinates of the points sampled from the polygons, and still holds when a containment query can ask containment of an arbitrary (not sampled) point.
  Guided by the insights of the lower bound, we provide a more efficient approximation algorithm for Klee's measure problem improving the $O(n/\varepsilon^2)$ time to $O((n+\frac{1}{\varepsilon^2}) \cdot \log^{O(d)}n)$. We achieve this improvement by exploiting the geometry of Klee's measure problem in various ways: (1) Since we have access to the boxes' coordinates, we can split the boxes into classes of boxes of similar shape. (2) Within each class, we show how to sample from the union of all boxes, by using orthogonal range searching. And (3) we exploit that boxes of different classes have small intersection, for most pairs of classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00996v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CG</category>
      <category>cs.CC</category>
      <category>cs.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karl Bringmann, Kasper Green Larsen, Andr\'e Nusser, Eva Rotenberg, Yanheng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
