<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SD updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SD</link>
    <description>cs.SD updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SD" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 06:33:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>NBM: an Open Dataset for the Acoustic Monitoring of Nocturnal Migratory Birds in Europe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03633v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The persisting threats on migratory bird populations highlights the urgent need for effective monitoring techniques that could assist in their conservation. Among these, passive acoustic monitoring is an essential tool, particularly for nocturnal migratory species that are difficult to track otherwise. This work presents the Nocturnal Bird Migration (NBM) dataset, a collection of 13,359 annotated vocalizations from 117 species of the Western Palearctic. The dataset includes precise time and frequency annotations, gathered by dozens of bird enthusiasts across France, enabling novel downstream acoustic analysis. In particular, we demonstrate that a two-stage object detection model, tailored for the processing of audio data, can be trained on our dataset to retrieve localized bounding box coordinates around each signal of interest in a spectrogram. This object detection approach, which is largely overlooked in the bird sound recognition literature, allows important applications by potentially differentiating individual birds within audio windows. Further, we show that the accuracy of our recognition model on the 45 main species of the dataset competes with state-of-the-art systems trained on much larger datasets. This highlights the interest of fostering similar open-science initiatives to acquire costly but valuable fine-grained annotations of audio files. All data and code are made openly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03633v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis Airale, Adrien Pajot, Juliette Linossier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion in Zero-Shot Learning for Environmental Audio</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03771v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Zero-shot learning enables models to generalize to unseen classes by leveraging semantic information, bridging the gap between training and testing sets with non-overlapping classes. While much research has focused on zero-shot learning in computer vision, the application of these methods to environmental audio remains underexplored, with poor performance in existing studies. Generative methods, which have demonstrated success in computer vision, are notably absent from environmental audio zero-shot learning, where classification-based approaches dominate.
  To address this gap, this work investigates generative methods for zero-shot learning in environmental audio. Two successful generative models from computer vision are adapted: a cross-aligned and distribution-aligned variational autoencoder (CADA-VAE) and a leveraging invariant side generative adversarial network (LisGAN). Additionally, a novel diffusion model conditioned on class auxiliary data is introduced. The diffusion model generates synthetic data for unseen classes, which is combined with seen-class data to train a classifier.
  Experiments are conducted on two environmental audio datasets, ESC-50 and FSC22. Results show that the diffusion model significantly outperforms all baseline methods, achieving more than 25% higher accuracy on the ESC-50 test partition.
  This work establishes the diffusion model as a promising generative approach for zero-shot learning and introduces the first benchmark of generative methods for environmental audio zero-shot learning, providing a foundation for future research in the field.
  Code is provided at https://github.com/ysims/ZeroDiffusion for the novel ZeroDiffusion method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03771v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ysobel Sims, Stephan Chalup, Alexandre Mendes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speech Recognition-based Feature Extraction for Enhanced Automatic Severity Classification in Dysarthric Speech</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03784</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03784v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Due to the subjective nature of current clinical evaluation, the need for automatic severity evaluation in dysarthric speech has emerged. DNN models outperform ML models but lack user-friendly explainability. ML models offer explainable results at a feature level, but their performance is comparatively lower. Current ML models extract various features from raw waveforms to predict severity. However, existing methods do not encompass all dysarthric features used in clinical evaluation. To address this gap, we propose a feature extraction method that minimizes information loss. We introduce an ASR transcription as a novel feature extraction source. We finetune the ASR model for dysarthric speech, then use this model to transcribe dysarthric speech and extract word segment boundary information. It enables capturing finer pronunciation and broader prosodic features. These features demonstrated an improved severity prediction performance to existing features: balanced accuracy of 83.72%.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03784v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yerin Choi, Jeehyun Lee, Myoung-Wan Koo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Missing Melodies: AI Music Generation and its "Nearly" Complete Omission of the Global South</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04100v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in generative AI have sparked renewed interest and expanded possibilities for music generation. However, the performance and versatility of these systems across musical genres are heavily influenced by the availability of training data. We conducted an extensive analysis of over one million hours of audio datasets used in AI music generation research and manually reviewed more than 200 papers from eleven prominent AI and music conferences and organizations (AAAI, ACM, EUSIPCO, EURASIP, ICASSP, ICML, IJCAI, ISMIR, NeurIPS, NIME, SMC) to identify a critical gap in the fair representation and inclusion of the musical genres of the Global South in AI research. Our findings reveal a stark imbalance: approximately 86% of the total dataset hours and over 93% of researchers focus primarily on music from the Global North. However, around 40% of these datasets include some form of non-Western music, genres from the Global South account for only 14.6% of the data. Furthermore, approximately 51% of the papers surveyed concentrate on symbolic music generation, a method that often fails to capture the cultural nuances inherent in music from regions such as South Asia, the Middle East, and Africa. As AI increasingly shapes the creation and dissemination of music, the significant underrepresentation of music genres in datasets and research presents a serious threat to global musical diversity. We also propose some important steps to mitigate these risks and foster a more inclusive future for AI-driven music generation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04100v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atharva Mehta, Shivam Chauhan, Monojit Choudhury</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relationships between Keywords and Strong Beats in Lyrical Music</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04202v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Artificial Intelligence (AI) song generation has emerged as a popular topic, yet the focus on exploring the latent correlations between specific lyrical and rhythmic features remains limited. In contrast, this pilot study particularly investigates the relationships between keywords and rhythmically stressed features such as strong beats in songs. It focuses on several key elements: keywords or non-keywords, stressed or unstressed syllables, and strong or weak beats, with the aim of uncovering insightful correlations. Experimental results indicate that, on average, 80.8\% of keywords land on strong beats, whereas 62\% of non-keywords fall on weak beats. The relationship between stressed syllables and strong or weak beats is weak, revealing that keywords have the strongest relationships with strong beats. Additionally, the lyrics-rhythm matching score, a key matching metric measuring keywords on strong beats and non-keywords on weak beats across various time signatures, is 0.765, while the matching score for syllable types is 0.495. This study demonstrates that word types strongly align with their corresponding beat types, as evidenced by the distinct patterns, whereas syllable types exhibit a much weaker alignment. This disparity underscores the greater reliability of word types in capturing rhythmic structures in music, highlighting their crucial role in effective rhythmic matching and analysis. We also conclude that keywords that consistently align with strong beats are more reliable indicators of lyrics-rhythm associations, providing valuable insights for AI-driven song generation through enhanced structural analysis. Furthermore, our development of tailored Lyrics-Rhythm Matching (LRM) metrics maximizes lyrical alignments with corresponding beat stresses, and our novel LRM file format captures critical lyrical and rhythmic information without needing original sheet music.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04202v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Callie C. Liao, Duoduo Liao, Ellie L. Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Representation Purification for End-to-End Speech Translation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04266v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Speech-to-text translation (ST) is a cross-modal task that involves converting spoken language into text in a different language. Previous research primarily focused on enhancing speech translation by facilitating knowledge transfer from machine translation, exploring various methods to bridge the gap between speech and text modalities. Despite substantial progress made, factors in speech that are not relevant to translation content, such as timbre and rhythm, often limit the efficiency of knowledge transfer. In this paper, we conceptualize speech representation as a combination of content-agnostic and content-relevant factors. We examine the impact of content-agnostic factors on translation performance through preliminary experiments and observe a significant performance deterioration when content-agnostic perturbations are introduced to speech signals. To address this issue, we propose a \textbf{S}peech \textbf{R}epresentation \textbf{P}urification with \textbf{S}upervision \textbf{E}nhancement (SRPSE) framework, which excludes the content-agnostic components within speech representations to mitigate their negative impact on ST. Experiments on MuST-C and CoVoST-2 datasets demonstrate that SRPSE significantly improves translation performance across all translation directions in three settings and achieves preeminent performance under a \textit{transcript-free} setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04266v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengwei Zhang, Yue Zhou, Rui Zhao, Yidong Chen, Xiaodong Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CA-SSLR: Condition-Aware Self-Supervised Learning Representation for Generalized Speech Processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04425v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce Condition-Aware Self-Supervised Learning Representation (CA-SSLR), a generalist conditioning model broadly applicable to various speech-processing tasks. Compared to standard fine-tuning methods that optimize for downstream models, CA-SSLR integrates language and speaker embeddings from earlier layers, making the SSL model aware of the current language and speaker context. This approach reduces the reliance on input audio features while preserving the integrity of the base SSLR. CA-SSLR improves the model's capabilities and demonstrates its generality on unseen tasks with minimal task-specific tuning. Our method employs linear modulation to dynamically adjust internal representations, enabling fine-grained adaptability without significantly altering the original model behavior. Experiments show that CA-SSLR reduces the number of trainable parameters, mitigates overfitting, and excels in under-resourced and unseen tasks. Specifically, CA-SSLR achieves a 10% relative reduction in LID errors, a 37% improvement in ASR CER on the ML-SUPERB benchmark, and a 27% decrease in SV EER on VoxCeleb-1, demonstrating its effectiveness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04425v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yen-Ju Lu, Jing Liu, Thomas Thebaud, Laureano Moro-Velazquez, Ariya Rastrow, Najim Dehak, Jesus Villalba</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>WaveletGPT: Wavelets Meet Large Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12924</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12924v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) have ushered in a new wave of artificial intelligence advancements impacting every scientific field and discipline. They are trained on a simple objective: to predict the next token given the previous context. We live in a world where most of the data around us, e.g., text, audio, and music, has a multi-scale structure associated with it. This paper infuses LLMs with traditional signal processing ideas, namely wavelets, during pre-training to take advantage of the structure. Without adding \textbf{any extra parameters} to a GPT-style LLM architecture, we achieve the same pre-training performance almost twice as fast in text, raw audio, and symbolic music. This is achieved by imposing a structure on intermediate embeddings. When trained for the same number of training steps, we achieve significant gains in performance, which is comparable to pre-training a larger neural architecture. Our architecture allows every next token prediction access to intermediate embeddings at different temporal resolutions in every Transformer decoder block. This work will hopefully pave the way for incorporating multi-rate signal processing ideas into traditional LLM pre-training. Further, we showcase pushing model performance by improving internal structure instead of just going after scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12924v3</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prateek Verma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PerceiverS: A Multi-Scale Perceiver with Effective Segmentation for Long-Term Expressive Symbolic Music Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.08307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.08307v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: AI-based music generation has progressed significantly in recent years. However, creating symbolic music that is both long-structured and expressive remains a considerable challenge. In this paper, we propose PerceiverS (Segmentation and Scale), a novel architecture designed to address this issue by leveraging both Effective Segmentation and Multi-Scale attention mechanisms. Our approach enhances symbolic music generation by simultaneously learning long-term structural dependencies and short-term expressive details. By combining cross-attention and self-attention in a Multi-Scale setting, PerceiverS captures long-range musical structure while preserving musical diversity. The proposed model has been evaluated using the Maestro dataset and has demonstrated improvements in generating music of conventional length with expressive nuances. The project demos and the generated music samples can be accessed through the link: https://perceivers.github.io</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.08307v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yungang Yi, Weihua Li, Matthew Kuo, Quan Bai</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
