<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.SD updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SD</link>
    <description>cs.SD updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.SD" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 04:00:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On-Device Domain Learning for Keyword Spotting on Low-Power Extreme Edge Embedded Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10549v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Keyword spotting accuracy degrades when neural networks are exposed to noisy environments. On-site adaptation to previously unseen noise is crucial to recovering accuracy loss, and on-device learning is required to ensure that the adaptation process happens entirely on the edge device. In this work, we propose a fully on-device domain adaptation system achieving up to 14% accuracy gains over already-robust keyword spotting models. We enable on-device learning with less than 10 kB of memory, using only 100 labeled utterances to recover 5% accuracy after adapting to the complex speech noise. We demonstrate that domain adaptation can be achieved on ultra-low-power microcontrollers with as little as 806 mJ in only 14 s on always-on, battery-operated devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10549v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cristian Cioflan, Lukas Cavigelli, Manuele Rusci, Miguel de Prado, Luca Benini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoPlay: Audio-agnostic Cognitive Scaling for Acoustic Sensing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10796</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10796v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Acoustic sensing manifests great potential in various applications that encompass health monitoring, gesture interface and imaging by leveraging the speakers and microphones on smart devices. However, in ongoing research and development in acoustic sensing, one problem is often overlooked: the same speaker, when used concurrently for sensing and other traditional applications (like playing music), could cause interference in both making it impractical to use in the real world. The strong ultrasonic sensing signals mixed with music would overload the speaker's mixer. To confront this issue of overloaded signals, current solutions are clipping or down-scaling, both of which affect the music playback quality and also sensing range and accuracy. To address this challenge, we propose CoPlay, a deep learning based optimization algorithm to cognitively adapt the sensing signal. It can 1) maximize the sensing signal magnitude within the available bandwidth left by the concurrent music to optimize sensing range and accuracy and 2) minimize any consequential frequency distortion that can affect music playback. In this work, we design a deep learning model and test it on common types of sensing signals (sine wave or Frequency Modulated Continuous Wave FMCW) as inputs with various agnostic concurrent music and speech. First, we evaluated the model performance to show the quality of the generated signals. Then we conducted field studies of downstream acoustic sensing tasks in the real world. A study with 12 users proved that respiration monitoring and gesture recognition using our adapted signal achieve similar accuracy as no-concurrent-music scenarios, while clipping or down-scaling manifests worse accuracy. A qualitative study also manifests that the music play quality is not degraded, unlike traditional clipping or down-scaling methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10796v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yin Li, Rajalakshmi Nanadakumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speech-driven Personalized Gesture Synthetics: Harnessing Automatic Fuzzy Feature Inference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10805</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10805v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Speech-driven gesture generation is an emerging field within virtual human creation. However, a significant challenge lies in accurately determining and processing the multitude of input features (such as acoustic, semantic, emotional, personality, and even subtle unknown features). Traditional approaches, reliant on various explicit feature inputs and complex multimodal processing, constrain the expressiveness of resulting gestures and limit their applicability. To address these challenges, we present Persona-Gestor, a novel end-to-end generative model designed to generate highly personalized 3D full-body gestures solely relying on raw speech audio. The model combines a fuzzy feature extractor and a non-autoregressive Adaptive Layer Normalization (AdaLN) transformer diffusion architecture. The fuzzy feature extractor harnesses a fuzzy inference strategy that automatically infers implicit, continuous fuzzy features. These fuzzy features, represented as a unified latent feature, are fed into the AdaLN transformer. The AdaLN transformer introduces a conditional mechanism that applies a uniform function across all tokens, thereby effectively modeling the correlation between the fuzzy features and the gesture sequence. This module ensures a high level of gesture-speech synchronization while preserving naturalness. Finally, we employ the diffusion model to train and infer various gestures. Extensive subjective and objective evaluations on the Trinity, ZEGGS, and BEAT datasets confirm our model's superior performance to the current state-of-the-art approaches. Persona-Gestor improves the system's usability and generalization capabilities, setting a new benchmark in speech-driven gesture synthesis and broadening the horizon for virtual human technology. Supplementary videos and code can be accessed at https://zf223669.github.io/Diffmotion-v2-website/</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10805v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan Zhang, Zhaohan Wang, Xin Lyu, Siyuan Zhao, Mengjian Li, Weidong Geng, Naye Ji, Hui Du, Fuxing Gao, Hao Wu, Shunman Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Urban Sound Propagation: a Benchmark for 1-Step Generative Modeling of Complex Physical Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10904</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10904v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Data-driven modeling of complex physical systems is receiving a growing amount of attention in the simulation and machine learning communities. Since most physical simulations are based on compute-intensive, iterative implementations of differential equation systems, a (partial) replacement with learned, 1-step inference models has the potential for significant speedups in a wide range of application areas. In this context, we present a novel benchmark for the evaluation of 1-step generative learning models in terms of speed and physical correctness. Our Urban Sound Propagation benchmark is based on the physically complex and practically relevant, yet intuitively easy to grasp task of modeling the 2d propagation of waves from a sound source in an urban environment. We provide a dataset with 100k samples, where each sample consists of pairs of real 2d building maps drawn from OpenStreetmap, a parameterized sound source, and a simulated ground truth sound propagation for the given scene. The dataset provides four different simulation tasks with increasing complexity regarding reflection, diffraction and source variance. A first baseline evaluation of common generative U-Net, GAN and Diffusion models shows, that while these models are very well capable of modeling sound propagations in simple cases, the approximation of sub-systems represented by higher order equations systematically fails. Information about the dataset, download instructions and source codes are provided on our anonymous website: https://www.urban-sound-data.org.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10904v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Spitznagel, Janis Keuper</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multitask frame-level learning for few-shot sound event detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11091</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11091v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper focuses on few-shot Sound Event Detection (SED), which aims to automatically recognize and classify sound events with limited samples. However, prevailing methods methods in few-shot SED predominantly rely on segment-level predictions, which often providing detailed, fine-grained predictions, particularly for events of brief duration. Although frame-level prediction strategies have been proposed to overcome these limitations, these strategies commonly face difficulties with prediction truncation caused by background noise. To alleviate this issue, we introduces an innovative multitask frame-level SED framework. In addition, we introduce TimeFilterAug, a linear timing mask for data augmentation, to increase the model's robustness and adaptability to diverse acoustic environments. The proposed method achieves a F-score of 63.8%, securing the 1st rank in the few-shot bioacoustic event detection category of the Detection and Classification of Acoustic Scenes and Events Challenge 2023.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11091v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang Zou, Genwei Yan, Ruoyu Wang, Jun Du, Meng Lei, Tian Gao, Xin Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Multi-Source Inference for Text Conditioned Music Diffusion Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11706v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multi-Source Diffusion Models (MSDM) allow for compositional musical generation tasks: generating a set of coherent sources, creating accompaniments, and performing source separation. Despite their versatility, they require estimating the joint distribution over the sources, necessitating pre-separated musical data, which is rarely available, and fixing the number and type of sources at training time. This paper generalizes MSDM to arbitrary time-domain diffusion models conditioned on text embeddings. These models do not require separated data as they are trained on mixtures, can parameterize an arbitrary number of sources, and allow for rich semantic control. We propose an inference procedure enabling the coherent generation of sources and accompaniments. Additionally, we adapt the Dirac separator of MSDM to perform source separation. We experiment with diffusion models trained on Slakh2100 and MTG-Jamendo, showcasing competitive generation and separation results in a relaxed data setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11706v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emilian Postolache, Giorgio Mariani, Luca Cosmo, Emmanouil Benetos, Emanuele Rodol\`a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hallucination in Perceptual Metric-Driven Speech Enhancement Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11732v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Within the area of speech enhancement, there is an ongoing interest in the creation of neural systems which explicitly aim to improve the perceptual quality of the processed audio. In concert with this is the topic of non-intrusive (i.e. without clean reference) speech quality prediction, for which neural networks are trained to predict human-assigned quality labels directly from distorted audio. When combined, these areas allow for the creation of powerful new speech enhancement systems which can leverage large real-world datasets of distorted audio, by taking inference of a pre-trained speech quality predictor as the sole loss function of the speech enhancement system. This paper aims to identify a potential pitfall with this approach, namely hallucinations which are introduced by the enhancement system `tricking' the speech quality predictor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11732v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Close, Thomas Hain, Stefan Goetze</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards the Development of a Real-Time Deepfake Audio Detection System in Communication Platforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11778v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Deepfake audio poses a rising threat in communication platforms, necessitating real-time detection for audio stream integrity. Unlike traditional non-real-time approaches, this study assesses the viability of employing static deepfake audio detection models in real-time communication platforms. An executable software is developed for cross-platform compatibility, enabling real-time execution. Two deepfake audio detection models based on Resnet and LCNN architectures are implemented using the ASVspoof 2019 dataset, achieving benchmark performances compared to ASVspoof 2019 challenge baselines. The study proposes strategies and frameworks for enhancing these models, paving the way for real-time deepfake audio detection in communication platforms. This work contributes to the advancement of audio stream security, ensuring robust detection capabilities in dynamic, real-time communication scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11778v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonat John Mathew, Rakin Ahsan, Sae Furukawa, Jagdish Gautham Krishna Kumar, Huzaifa Pallan, Agamjeet Singh Padda, Sara Adamski, Madhu Reddiboina, Arjun Pankajakshan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prompt-Singer: Controllable Singing-Voice-Synthesis with Natural Language Prompt</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11780</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11780v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent singing-voice-synthesis (SVS) methods have achieved remarkable audio quality and naturalness, yet they lack the capability to control the style attributes of the synthesized singing explicitly. We propose Prompt-Singer, the first SVS method that enables attribute controlling on singer gender, vocal range and volume with natural language. We adopt a model architecture based on a decoder-only transformer with a multi-scale hierarchy, and design a range-melody decoupled pitch representation that enables text-conditioned vocal range control while keeping melodic accuracy. Furthermore, we explore various experiment settings, including different types of text representations, text encoder fine-tuning, and introducing speech data to alleviate data scarcity, aiming to facilitate further research. Experiments show that our model achieves favorable controlling ability and audio quality. Audio samples are available at http://prompt-singer.github.io .</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11780v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongqi Wang, Ruofan Hu, Rongjie Huang, Zhiqing Hong, Ruiqi Li, Wenrui Liu, Fuming You, Tao Jin, Zhou Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sound Event Detection and Localization with Distance Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11827v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Sound Event Detection and Localization (SELD) is a combined task of identifying sound events and their corresponding direction-of-arrival (DOA). While this task has numerous applications and has been extensively researched in recent years, it fails to provide full information about the sound source position. In this paper, we overcome this problem by extending the task to Sound Event Detection, Localization with Distance Estimation (3D SELD). We study two ways of integrating distance estimation within the SELD core - a multi-task approach, in which the problem is tackled by a separate model output, and a single-task approach obtained by extending the multi-ACCDOA method to include distance information. We investigate both methods for the Ambisonic and binaural versions of STARSS23: Sony-TAU Realistic Spatial Soundscapes 2023. Moreover, our study involves experiments on the loss function related to the distance estimation part. Our results show that it is possible to perform 3D SELD without any degradation of performance in sound event detection and DOA estimation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11827v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Aleksander Krause, Archontis Politis, Annamaria Mesaros</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unimodal Multi-Task Fusion for Emotional Mimicry Prediciton</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11879</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11879v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, we propose a methodology for the Emotional Mimicry Intensity (EMI) Estimation task within the context of the 6th Workshop and Competition on Affective Behavior Analysis in-the-wild. Our approach leverages the Wav2Vec 2.0 framework, pre-trained on a comprehensive podcast dataset, to extract a broad range of audio features encompassing both linguistic and paralinguistic elements. We enhance feature representation through a fusion technique that integrates individual features with a global mean vector, introducing global contextual insights into our analysis. Additionally, we incorporate a pre-trained valence- arousal-dominance (VAD) module from the Wav2Vec 2.0 model. Our fusion employs a Long Short-Term Memory (LSTM) architecture for efficient temporal analysis of audio data. Utilizing only the provided audio data, our approach demonstrates significant improvements over the established baseline.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11879v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Hallmen, Fabian Deuser, Norbert Oswald, Elisabeth Andr\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notochord: a Flexible Probabilistic Model for Real-Time MIDI Performance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12000v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Deep learning-based probabilistic models of musical data are producing increasingly realistic results and promise to enter creative workflows of many kinds. Yet they have been little-studied in a performance setting, where the results of user actions typically ought to feel instantaneous. To enable such study, we designed Notochord, a deep probabilistic model for sequences of structured events, and trained an instance of it on the Lakh MIDI dataset. Our probabilistic formulation allows interpretable interventions at a sub-event level, which enables one model to act as a backbone for diverse interactive musical functions including steerable generation, harmonization, machine improvisation, and likelihood-based interfaces. Notochord can generate polyphonic and multi-track MIDI, and respond to inputs with latency below ten milliseconds. Training code, model checkpoints and interactive examples are provided as open source software.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12000v1</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.5281/zenodo.7088404</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Shepardson, V., Armitage, J., &amp; Magnusson, T. (2022, September 17). Proceedings of the 3rd Conference on AI Music Creativity</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Victor Shepardson, Jack Armitage, Thor Magnusson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-sided Acoustic Metascreen for Broadband and Individual Reflection and Transmission Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10548v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Acoustic wave modulation plays a pivotal role in various applications, including sound-field reconstruction, wireless communication, and particle manipulation, among others. However, current acoustic metamaterial and metasurface designs typically focus on controlling either reflection or transmission waves, often overlooking the coupling between amplitude and phase of acoustic waves. To fulfill this gap, we propose and experimentally validate a design enabling complete control of reflected and transmitted acoustic waves individually across a frequency range of 4 kHz to 8 kHz, allowing arbitrary combinations of amplitude and phase for reflected and transmitted sound in a broadband manner. Additionally, we demonstrate the significance of our approach for sound manipulation by achieving acoustic diffusion, reflection, focusing, and generating a two-sided 3D hologram at three distinct frequencies. These findings open an alternative avenue for extensively engineering sound waves, promising applications in acoustics and related fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10548v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ao Chen, Xin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PTSD-MDNN : Fusion tardive de r\'eseaux de neurones profonds multimodaux pour la d\'etection du trouble de stress post-traumatique</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10565</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10565v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In order to provide a more objective and quicker way to diagnose post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), we present PTSD-MDNN which merges two unimodal convolutional neural networks and which gives low detection error rate. By taking only videos and audios as inputs, the model could be used in the configuration of teleconsultation sessions, in the optimization of patient journeys or for human-robot interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10565v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>q-bio.NC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Long Nguyen-Phuoc, Renald Gaboriau, Dimitri Delacroix, Laurent Navarro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refining Knowledge Transfer on Audio-Image Temporal Agreement for Audio-Text Cross Retrieval</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10756v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The aim of this research is to refine knowledge transfer on audio-image temporal agreement for audio-text cross retrieval. To address the limited availability of paired non-speech audio-text data, learning methods for transferring the knowledge acquired from a large amount of paired audio-image data to shared audio-text representation have been investigated, suggesting the importance of how audio-image co-occurrence is learned. Conventional approaches in audio-image learning assign a single image randomly selected from the corresponding video stream to the entire audio clip, assuming their co-occurrence. However, this method may not accurately capture the temporal agreement between the target audio and image because a single image can only represent a snapshot of a scene, though the target audio changes from moment to moment. To address this problem, we propose two methods for audio and image matching that effectively capture the temporal information: (i) Nearest Match wherein an image is selected from multiple time frames based on similarity with audio, and (ii) Multiframe Match wherein audio and image pairs of multiple time frames are used. Experimental results show that method (i) improves the audio-text retrieval performance by selecting the nearest image that aligns with the audio information and transferring the learned knowledge. Conversely, method (ii) improves the performance of audio-image retrieval while not showing significant improvements in audio-text retrieval performance. These results indicate that refining audio-image temporal agreement may contribute to better knowledge transfer to audio-text retrieval.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10756v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunsuke Tsubaki, Daisuke Niizumi, Daiki Takeuchi, Yasunori Ohishi, Noboru Harada, Keisuke Imoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy-Based Models with Applications to Speech and Language Processing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10961v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Energy-Based Models (EBMs) are an important class of probabilistic models, also known as random fields and undirected graphical models. EBMs are un-normalized and thus radically different from other popular self-normalized probabilistic models such as hidden Markov models (HMMs), autoregressive models, generative adversarial nets (GANs) and variational auto-encoders (VAEs). Over the past years, EBMs have attracted increasing interest not only from the core machine learning community, but also from application domains such as speech, vision, natural language processing (NLP) and so on, due to significant theoretical and algorithmic progress. The sequential nature of speech and language also presents special challenges and needs a different treatment from processing fix-dimensional data (e.g., images). Therefore, the purpose of this monograph is to present a systematic introduction to energy-based models, including both algorithmic progress and applications in speech and language processing. First, the basics of EBMs are introduced, including classic models, recent models parameterized by neural networks, sampling methods, and various learning methods from the classic learning algorithms to the most advanced ones. Then, the application of EBMs in three different scenarios is presented, i.e., for modeling marginal, conditional and joint distributions, respectively. 1) EBMs for sequential data with applications in language modeling, where the main focus is on the marginal distribution of a sequence itself; 2) EBMs for modeling conditional distributions of target sequences given observation sequences, with applications in speech recognition, sequence labeling and text generation; 3) EBMs for modeling joint distributions of both sequences of observations and targets, and their applications in semi-supervised learning and calibrated natural language understanding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10961v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1561/2000000117</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Foundations and Trends in Signal Processing: Vol. 18: No. 1-2, pp 1-199</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhijian Ou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fine-Grained Engine Fault Sound Event Detection Using Multimodal Signals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11037</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11037v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Sound event detection (SED) is an active area of audio research that aims to detect the temporal occurrence of sounds. In this paper, we apply SED to engine fault detection by introducing a multimodal SED framework that detects fine-grained engine faults of automobile engines using audio and accelerometer-recorded vibration. We first introduce the problem of engine fault SED on a dataset collected from a large variety of vehicles with expertly-labeled engine fault sound events. Next, we propose a SED model to temporally detect ten fine-grained engine faults that occur within vehicle engines and further explore a pretraining strategy using a large-scale weakly-labeled engine fault dataset. Through multiple evaluations, we show our proposed framework is able to effectively detect engine fault sound events. Finally, we investigate the interaction and characteristics of each modality and show that fusing features from audio and vibration improves overall engine fault SED capabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11037v1</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dennis Fedorishin, Livio Forte III, Philip Schneider, Srirangaraj Setlur, Venu Govindaraju</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Audio-Visual Segmentation via Unlabeled Frame Exploitation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11074v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Audio-visual segmentation (AVS) aims to segment the sounding objects in video frames. Although great progress has been witnessed, we experimentally reveal that current methods reach marginal performance gain within the use of the unlabeled frames, leading to the underutilization issue. To fully explore the potential of the unlabeled frames for AVS, we explicitly divide them into two categories based on their temporal characteristics, i.e., neighboring frame (NF) and distant frame (DF). NFs, temporally adjacent to the labeled frame, often contain rich motion information that assists in the accurate localization of sounding objects. Contrary to NFs, DFs have long temporal distances from the labeled frame, which share semantic-similar objects with appearance variations. Considering their unique characteristics, we propose a versatile framework that effectively leverages them to tackle AVS. Specifically, for NFs, we exploit the motion cues as the dynamic guidance to improve the objectness localization. Besides, we exploit the semantic cues in DFs by treating them as valid augmentations to the labeled frames, which are then used to enrich data diversity in a self-training manner. Extensive experimental results demonstrate the versatility and superiority of our method, unleashing the power of the abundant unlabeled frames.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11074v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinxiang Liu, Yikun Liu, Fei Zhang, Chen Ju, Ya Zhang, Yanfeng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QEAN: Quaternion-Enhanced Attention Network for Visual Dance Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11626v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The study of music-generated dance is a novel and challenging Image generation task. It aims to input a piece of music and seed motions, then generate natural dance movements for the subsequent music. Transformer-based methods face challenges in time series prediction tasks related to human movements and music due to their struggle in capturing the nonlinear relationship and temporal aspects. This can lead to issues like joint deformation, role deviation, floating, and inconsistencies in dance movements generated in response to the music. In this paper, we propose a Quaternion-Enhanced Attention Network (QEAN) for visual dance synthesis from a quaternion perspective, which consists of a Spin Position Embedding (SPE) module and a Quaternion Rotary Attention (QRA) module. First, SPE embeds position information into self-attention in a rotational manner, leading to better learning of features of movement sequences and audio sequences, and improved understanding of the connection between music and dance. Second, QRA represents and fuses 3D motion features and audio features in the form of a series of quaternions, enabling the model to better learn the temporal coordination of music and dance under the complex temporal cycle conditions of dance generation. Finally, we conducted experiments on the dataset AIST++, and the results show that our approach achieves better and more robust performance in generating accurate, high-quality dance movements. Our source code and dataset can be available from https://github.com/MarasyZZ/QEAN and https://google.github.io/aistplusplus_dataset respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11626v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhizhen Zhou, Yejing Huo, Guoheng Huang, An Zeng, Xuhang Chen, Lian Huang, Zinuo Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Feature Extraction and Late Fusion Strategy for Audiovisual Emotional Mimicry Intensity Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.11757</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.11757v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we present the solution to the Emotional Mimicry Intensity (EMI) Estimation challenge, which is part of 6th Affective Behavior Analysis in-the-wild (ABAW) Competition.The EMI Estimation challenge task aims to evaluate the emotional intensity of seed videos by assessing them from a set of predefined emotion categories (i.e., "Admiration," "Amusement," "Determination," "Empathic Pain," "Excitement," and "Joy").</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.11757v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Yu, Wangyuan Zhu, Jichao Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Source Diffusion Models for Simultaneous Music Generation and Separation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.02257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.02257v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we define a diffusion-based generative model capable of both music synthesis and source separation by learning the score of the joint probability density of sources sharing a context. Alongside the classic total inference tasks (i.e., generating a mixture, separating the sources), we also introduce and experiment on the partial generation task of source imputation, where we generate a subset of the sources given the others (e.g., play a piano track that goes well with the drums). Additionally, we introduce a novel inference method for the separation task based on Dirac likelihood functions. We train our model on Slakh2100, a standard dataset for musical source separation, provide qualitative results in the generation settings, and showcase competitive quantitative results in the source separation setting. Our method is the first example of a single model that can handle both generation and separation tasks, thus representing a step toward general audio models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.02257v4</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giorgio Mariani, Irene Tallini, Emilian Postolache, Michele Mancusi, Luca Cosmo, Emanuele Rodol\`a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A low latency attention module for streaming self-supervised speech representation learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.13451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.13451v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The transformer is a fundamental building block in deep learning, and the attention mechanism is the transformer's core component. Self-supervised speech representation learning (SSRL) represents a popular use-case for the transformer architecture. Due to transformers' acausal behavior, the use of transformers for SSRL has been predominantly focused on acausal applications. However, several media processing problems, such as speech processing, require real-time solutions. In this paper, we present an implementation of the attention module that enables training of SSRL architectures with low compute and memory requirements, while allowing real-time inference with low and fixed latency. The attention module proposed in this paper includes two components, streaming attention (SA) and low-latency streaming attention (LLSA). The SA represents our proposal for an efficient streaming SSRL implementation, while the LLSA solves the latency build-up problem of other streaming attention architectures, such as the masked acausal attention (MAA), guaranteeing a latency equal to one layer even when multiple layers are stacked. We present a comparative analysis between the vanilla attention, which we will refer here as acausal attention (AA), the SA, and the LLSA, by training a streaming SSRL with automatic speech recognition as downstream task. When training on librispeech-clean-100 and testing on librispeech-test-clean, our low-latency attention module has a word error rate (WER) of 5.84%, which represents a significant improvement over the MAA (WER = 13.82%). Our implementation also reduces the inference latency from 1.92 to 0.16 seconds. The proposed low-latency module preserves many of the benefits of conventional acausal transformers, but also enables latency characteristics that make it applicable to real-time streaming applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.13451v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianbo Ma, Siqi Pan, Deepak Chandran, Andrea Fanelli, Richard Cartwright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>EM-TTS: Efficiently Trained Low-Resource Mongolian Lightweight Text-to-Speech</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.08164v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recently, deep learning-based Text-to-Speech (TTS) systems have achieved high-quality speech synthesis results. Recurrent neural networks have become a standard modeling technique for sequential data in TTS systems and are widely used. However, training a TTS model which includes RNN components requires powerful GPU performance and takes a long time. In contrast, CNN-based sequence synthesis techniques can significantly reduce the parameters and training time of a TTS model while guaranteeing a certain performance due to their high parallelism, which alleviate these economic costs of training. In this paper, we propose a lightweight TTS system based on deep convolutional neural networks, which is a two-stage training end-to-end TTS model and does not employ any recurrent units. Our model consists of two stages: Text2Spectrum and SSRN. The former is used to encode phonemes into a coarse mel spectrogram and the latter is used to synthesize the complete spectrum from the coarse mel spectrogram. Meanwhile, we improve the robustness of our model by a series of data augmentations, such as noise suppression, time warping, frequency masking and time masking, for solving the low resource mongolian problem. Experiments show that our model can reduce the training time and parameters while ensuring the quality and naturalness of the synthesized speech compared to using mainstream TTS models. Our method uses NCMMSC2022-MTTSC Challenge dataset for validation, which significantly reduces training time while maintaining a certain accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.08164v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziqi Liang, Haoxiang Shi, Jiawei Wang, Keda Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multimodal Transformer Distillation for Audio-Visual Synchronization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.15563</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.15563v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Audio-visual synchronization aims to determine whether the mouth movements and speech in the video are synchronized. VocaLiST reaches state-of-the-art performance by incorporating multimodal Transformers to model audio-visual interact information. However, it requires high computing resources, making it impractical for real-world applications. This paper proposed an MTDVocaLiST model, which is trained by our proposed multimodal Transformer distillation (MTD) loss. MTD loss enables MTDVocaLiST model to deeply mimic the cross-attention distribution and value-relation in the Transformer of VocaLiST. Additionally, we harness uncertainty weighting to fully exploit the interaction information across all layers. Our proposed method is effective in two aspects: From the distillation method perspective, MTD loss outperforms other strong distillation baselines. From the distilled model's performance perspective: 1) MTDVocaLiST outperforms similar-size SOTA models, SyncNet, and Perfect Match models by 15.65% and 3.35%; 2) MTDVocaLiST reduces the model size of VocaLiST by 83.52%, yet still maintaining similar performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.15563v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xuanjun Chen, Haibin Wu, Chung-Che Wang, Hung-yi Lee, Jyh-Shing Roger Jang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mega-TTS 2: Boosting Prompting Mechanisms for Zero-Shot Speech Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.07218</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.07218v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Zero-shot text-to-speech (TTS) aims to synthesize voices with unseen speech prompts, which significantly reduces the data and computation requirements for voice cloning by skipping the fine-tuning process. However, the prompting mechanisms of zero-shot TTS still face challenges in the following aspects: 1) previous works of zero-shot TTS are typically trained with single-sentence prompts, which significantly restricts their performance when the data is relatively sufficient during the inference stage. 2) The prosodic information in prompts is highly coupled with timbre, making it untransferable to each other. This paper introduces Mega-TTS 2, a generic prompting mechanism for zero-shot TTS, to tackle the aforementioned challenges. Specifically, we design a powerful acoustic autoencoder that separately encodes the prosody and timbre information into the compressed latent space while providing high-quality reconstructions. Then, we propose a multi-reference timbre encoder and a prosody latent language model (P-LLM) to extract useful information from multi-sentence prompts. We further leverage the probabilities derived from multiple P-LLM outputs to produce transferable and controllable prosody. Experimental results demonstrate that Mega-TTS 2 could not only synthesize identity-preserving speech with a short prompt of an unseen speaker from arbitrary sources but consistently outperform the fine-tuning method when the volume of data ranges from 10 seconds to 5 minutes. Furthermore, our method enables to transfer various speaking styles to the target timbre in a fine-grained and controlled manner. Audio samples can be found in https://boostprompt.github.io/boostprompt/.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.07218v3</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziyue Jiang, Jinglin Liu, Yi Ren, Jinzheng He, Zhenhui Ye, Shengpeng Ji, Qian Yang, Chen Zhang, Pengfei Wei, Chunfeng Wang, Xiang Yin, Zejun Ma, Zhou Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LeBenchmark 2.0: a Standardized, Replicable and Enhanced Framework for Self-supervised Representations of French Speech</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.05472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.05472v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Self-supervised learning (SSL) is at the origin of unprecedented improvements in many different domains including computer vision and natural language processing. Speech processing drastically benefitted from SSL as most of the current domain-related tasks are now being approached with pre-trained models. This work introduces LeBenchmark 2.0 an open-source framework for assessing and building SSL-equipped French speech technologies. It includes documented, large-scale and heterogeneous corpora with up to 14,000 hours of heterogeneous speech, ten pre-trained SSL wav2vec 2.0 models containing from 26 million to one billion learnable parameters shared with the community, and an evaluation protocol made of six downstream tasks to complement existing benchmarks. LeBenchmark 2.0 also presents unique perspectives on pre-trained SSL models for speech with the investigation of frozen versus fine-tuned downstream models, task-agnostic versus task-specific pre-trained models as well as a discussion on the carbon footprint of large-scale model training. Overall, the newly introduced models trained on 14,000 hours of French speech outperform multilingual and previous LeBenchmark SSL models across the benchmark but also required up to four times more energy for pre-training.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.05472v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Titouan Parcollet, Ha Nguyen, Solene Evain, Marcely Zanon Boito, Adrien Pupier, Salima Mdhaffar, Hang Le, Sina Alisamir, Natalia Tomashenko, Marco Dinarelli, Shucong Zhang, Alexandre Allauzen, Maximin Coavoux, Yannick Esteve, Mickael Rouvier, Jerome Goulian, Benjamin Lecouteux, Francois Portet, Solange Rossato, Fabien Ringeval, Didier Schwab, Laurent Besacier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Respiratory Disease Classification and Biometric Analysis Using Biosignals from Digital Stethoscopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.07183</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.07183v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Respiratory diseases remain a leading cause of mortality worldwide, highlighting the need for faster and more accurate diagnostic tools. This work presents a novel approach leveraging digital stethoscope technology for automatic respiratory disease classification and biometric analysis. Our approach has the potential to significantly enhance traditional auscultation practices. By leveraging one of the largest publicly available medical database of respiratory sounds, we train machine learning models to classify various respiratory health conditions. Our method differs from conventional methods by using Empirical Mode Decomposition (EMD) and spectral analysis techniques to isolate clinically relevant biosignals embedded within acoustic data captured by digital stethoscopes. This approach focuses on information closely tied to cardiovascular and respiratory patterns within the acoustic data. Spectral analysis and filtering techniques isolate Intrinsic Mode Functions (IMFs) strongly correlated with these physiological phenomena. These biosignals undergo a comprehensive feature extraction process for predictive modeling. These features then serve as input to train several machine learning models for both classification and regression tasks. Our approach achieves high accuracy in both binary classification (89% balanced accuracy for healthy vs. diseased) and multi-class classification (72% balanced accuracy for specific diseases like pneumonia and COPD). For the first time, this work introduces regression models capable of estimating age and body mass index (BMI) based solely on acoustic data, as well as a model for sex classification. Our findings underscore the potential of intelligent digital stethoscopes to significantly enhance assistive and remote diagnostic capabilities, contributing to advancements in digital health, telehealth, and remote patient monitoring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.07183v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Constantino \'Alvarez Casado, Manuel Lage Ca\~nellas, Matteo Pedone, Xiaoting Wu, Le Nguyen, Miguel Bordallo L\'opez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Face Detection with Audio-Based Region Proposals for Human-Robot Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.08005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.08005v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Efficient face detection is critical to provide natural human-robot interactions. However, computer vision tends to involve a large computational load due to the amount of data (i.e. pixels) that needs to be processed in a short amount of time. This is undesirable on robotics platforms where multiple processes need to run in parallel and where the processing power is limited by portability constraints. Existing solutions often involve reducing image quality which can negatively impact processing. The literature also reports methods to generate regions of interest in images from pixel data. Although it is a promising idea, these methods often involve heavy vision algorithms. In this paper, we evaluate how audio can be used to generate regions of interest in optical images to reduce the number of pixels to process with computer vision. Thereby, we propose a unique attention mechanism to localize a speech source and evaluate its impact on an existing face detection algorithm. Our results show that the attention mechanism reduces the computational load and offers an interesting trade-off between speed and accuracy. The proposed pipeline is flexible and can be easily adapted to other applications such as robot surveillance, video conferences or smart glasses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.08005v2</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>William Aris, Fran\c{c}ois Grondin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero Resource Code-switched Speech Benchmark Using Speech Utterance Pairs For Multiple Spoken Languages</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.03018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.03018v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a new zero resource code-switched speech benchmark designed to directly assess the code-switching capabilities of self-supervised speech encoders. We showcase a baseline system of language modeling on discrete units to demonstrate how the code-switching abilities of speech encoders can be assessed in a zero-resource manner. Our experiments encompass a variety of well-known speech encoders, including Wav2vec 2.0, HuBERT, XLSR, etc. We examine the impact of pre-training languages and model size on benchmark performance. Notably, though our results demonstrate that speech encoders with multilingual pre-training, exemplified by XLSR, outperform monolingual variants (Wav2vec 2.0, HuBERT) in code-switching scenarios, there is still substantial room for improvement in their code-switching linguistic abilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.03018v3</guid>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kuan-Po Huang, Chih-Kai Yang, Yu-Kuan Fu, Ewan Dunbar, Hung-yi Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Comprehensive Evaluation of Augmentations for Robust OOD Self-Supervised Contrastive Phonocardiogram Representation Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.00502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.00502v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Despite the recent increase in research activity, deep-learning models have not yet been widely accepted in several real-world settings, such as medicine. The shortage of high-quality annotated data often hinders the development of robust and generalizable models, which do not suffer from degraded effectiveness when presented with newly-collected, out-of-distribution (OOD) datasets. Contrastive Self-Supervised Learning (SSL) offers a potential solution to labeled data scarcity, as it takes advantage of unlabeled data to increase model effectiveness and robustness. In this research, we propose applying contrastive SSL for detecting abnormalities in 1D phonocardiogram (PCG) samples by learning a generalized representation of the signal. Specifically, we perform an extensive comparative evaluation of a wide range of audio-based augmentations, evaluate trained classifiers on multiple datasets across different downstream tasks, and finally report on the impact of each augmentation in model training. We experimentally demonstrate that, depending on its training distribution, the effectiveness of a fully-supervised model can degrade up to 32% when evaluated on unseen data, while SSL models only lose up to 10% or even improve in some cases. We argue and experimentally demonstrate that, contrastive SSL pretraining can assist in providing robust classifiers which can generalize to unseen, OOD data, without relying on time- and labor-intensive annotation processes by medical experts. Furthermore, the proposed extensive evaluation protocol sheds light on the most promising and appropriate augmentations for robust PCG signal processing, by calculating their effect size on model training. Finally, we provide researchers and practitioners with a roadmap towards producing robust models for PCG classification, in addition to an open-source codebase for developing novel approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.00502v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aristotelis Ballas, Vasileios Papapanagiotou, Christos Diou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FaceTalk: Audio-Driven Motion Diffusion for Neural Parametric Head Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.08459</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.08459v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce FaceTalk, a novel generative approach designed for synthesizing high-fidelity 3D motion sequences of talking human heads from input audio signal. To capture the expressive, detailed nature of human heads, including hair, ears, and finer-scale eye movements, we propose to couple speech signal with the latent space of neural parametric head models to create high-fidelity, temporally coherent motion sequences. We propose a new latent diffusion model for this task, operating in the expression space of neural parametric head models, to synthesize audio-driven realistic head sequences. In the absence of a dataset with corresponding NPHM expressions to audio, we optimize for these correspondences to produce a dataset of temporally-optimized NPHM expressions fit to audio-video recordings of people talking. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first work to propose a generative approach for realistic and high-quality motion synthesis of volumetric human heads, representing a significant advancement in the field of audio-driven 3D animation. Notably, our approach stands out in its ability to generate plausible motion sequences that can produce high-fidelity head animation coupled with the NPHM shape space. Our experimental results substantiate the effectiveness of FaceTalk, consistently achieving superior and visually natural motion, encompassing diverse facial expressions and styles, outperforming existing methods by 75% in perceptual user study evaluation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.08459v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>CVPR 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shivangi Aneja, Justus Thies, Angela Dai, Matthias Nie{\ss}ner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SpeechDPR: End-to-End Spoken Passage Retrieval for Open-Domain Spoken Question Answering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.13463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.13463v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Spoken Question Answering (SQA) is essential for machines to reply to user's question by finding the answer span within a given spoken passage. SQA has been previously achieved without ASR to avoid recognition errors and Out-of-Vocabulary (OOV) problems. However, the real-world problem of Open-domain SQA (openSQA), in which the machine needs to first retrieve passages that possibly contain the answer from a spoken archive in addition, was never considered. This paper proposes the first known end-to-end framework, Speech Dense Passage Retriever (SpeechDPR), for the retrieval component of the openSQA problem. SpeechDPR learns a sentence-level semantic representation by distilling knowledge from the cascading model of unsupervised ASR (UASR) and text dense retriever (TDR). No manually transcribed speech data is needed. Initial experiments showed performance comparable to the cascading model of UASR and TDR, and significantly better when UASR was poor, verifying this approach is more robust to speech recognition errors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.13463v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>eess.AS</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chyi-Jiunn Lin, Guan-Ting Lin, Yung-Sung Chuang, Wei-Lun Wu, Shang-Wen Li, Abdelrahman Mohamed, Hung-yi Lee, Lin-shan Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
