<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MG</link>
    <description>math.MG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jul 2024 01:40:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The copolarity of pseudo-cones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17320v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the copolarity of pseudo-cones has analogous properties as the usual polarity of convex bodies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17320v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rolf Schneider</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Generalized Kissing Numbers of Convex Bodies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17340v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In 1694, Gregory and Newton proposed the problem to determine the kissing number of a rigid material ball. This problem and its higher dimensional generalization have been studied by many mathematicians, including Minkowski, van der Waerden, Hadwiger, Swinnerton-Dyer, Watson, Levenshtein, Odlyzko, Sloane and Musin. In this paper, we introduce and study a further generalization of the kissing numbers for convex bodies and obtain some exact results, in particular for balls in dimensions three, four and eight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17340v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiming Li, Chuanming Zong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the maxmin-$\omega$ eigenspaces and their over-approximation by zones</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16778</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16778v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Maxmin-$\omega$ dynamical systems were previously introduced as a generalization of dynamical systems expressed by tropical linear algebra. To describe steady states of such systems one has to study an eigenproblem of the form $A\otimes_{\omega} x=\lambda+x$ where $\otimes_{\omega}$ is the maxmin-$\omega$ matrix-vector multiplication. This eigenproblem can be viewed in more general framework of nonlinear Perron-Frobenius theory. However, instead of studying such eigenspaces directly we develop a different approach: over-approximation by zones. These are traditionally convex sets of special kind which proved to be highly useful in computer science and also relevant in tropical convexity. We first construct a sequence of zones over-approximating a maxmin-$\omega$ eigenspace. Next, the limit of this sequence is refined in a heuristic procedure, which yields a refined zone and also the eigenvalue $\lambda$ with a high success rate. Based on the numerical experiments, in successful cases there is a column of the difference bound matrix (DBM) representation of the refined zone which yields an eigenvector.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16778v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Syifa'ul Mufid, Ebrahim Patel, Sergei Sergeev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Analytic Stockwell Transform and its Zeros</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17076v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A recent original line of research in time--frequency analysis has shifted the interest in energy maxima toward zeros. Initially motivated by the intriguing uniform spread of the zeros of the spectrogram of white noise, it has led to fruitful theoretical developments combining probability theory, complex analysis and signal processing. In this vein, the present work proposes a characterization of the zeros of the Stockwell Transform of white noise, which consists in an hybrid time--frequency multiresolution representation. First of all, an analytic version of the Stockwell Transform is designed. Then, analyticity is leveraged to establish a connection with the hyperbolic Gaussian Analytic Function, whose zero set is invariant under the isometries of the Poincar\'e disk. Finally, the theoretical spatial statistics of the zeros of the hyperbolic Gaussian Analytic Function and the empirical statistics of the zeros the Analytic Stockwell Transform of white noise are compared through intensive Monte Carlo simulations, supporting the established connection. A publicly available documented Python toolbox accompanies this work.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17076v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Moukadem, Barbara Pascal, Jean-Baptiste Courbot, Nicolas Juillet</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thick braids and other non-trivial homotopy in configuration spaces of hard discs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.16776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.16776v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the homotopy groups of the configuration space of hard discs inside a unit disc, just beyond the first critical radius. In the four-disc case, we find a non-contractible `thick braid' (loop in the configuration space), which contracts in the ordered configuration space of points when we replace each disc by its centre. For $n\ge 5$ discs, we find a non-contractible $(n-3)$-sphere, and we explore the persistence of this homotopy class when the ambient unit disc is deformed. For sufficiently large $n$, we demonstrate the existence of non-trivial $\pi_k$-classes with $k&lt;n-3$ beyond higher critical radii.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.16776v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Ramsey</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
