<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MG</link>
    <description>math.MG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 04:00:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Inequalities for a new hyperbolic type metric</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17387v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study a new hyperbolic type metric recently introduced by Song and Wang. We present formulas for it in the upper half-space and the unit ball domains and find its sharp inequalities with the hyperbolic metric and the triangular ratio metric. We also improve existing ball inclusion results and give bounds for the distortion of this new metric under conformal and quasiregular mappings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17387v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oona Rainio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal partial transport for metric pairs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17674v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article we study Figalli and Gigli's formulation of optimal transport between non-negative Radon measures in the setting of metric pairs. We carry over classical characterisations of optimal plans to this setting and prove that the resulting spaces of measures, $\mathcal{M}_p(X,A)$, are complete, separable and geodesic whenever the underlying space, $X$, is so. We also prove that, for $p&gt;1$, $\mathcal{M}_p(X,A)$ preserves the property of being non-branching, and for $p=2$ it preserves non-negative curvature in the Alexandrov sense. Finally, we prove isometric embeddings of generalised spaces of persistence diagrams $\mathcal{D}_p(X,A)$ into the corresponding spaces $\mathcal{M}_p(X,A)$, generalising a result by Divol and Lacombe. As an application of this framework, we show that several known geometric properties of spaces of persistence diagrams follow from those of $\mathcal{M}_p(X,A)$, including the fact that $\mathcal{D}_2(X,A)$ is an Alexandrov space of non-negative curvature whenever $X$ is a proper non-negatively curved Alexandrov space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17674v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mauricio Che</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recognition of near-duplicate periodic patterns by continuous metrics with approximation guarantees</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.15298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.15298v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes a rigorous solution to the challenging classification problem of periodic patterns under Euclidean isometry and rigid motion. The 3-dimensional case is practically important for solid crystalline materials (periodic crystals) including all medical drugs that are produced in a rigid tablet form.
  Many past invariants based on finite subsets fail when a unit cell of a periodic pattern discontinuously changes under almost any perturbation of atoms, which is inevitable due to noise and atomic vibrations. The major problem is not only to find complete invariants (descriptors with no false negatives and no false positives for all periodic patterns) but to design efficient algorithms for distance metrics on these invariants that should continuously behave under noise.
  The proposed continuous metrics solve this problem in any Euclidean dimension and are algorithmically approximated with small error factors in times that are explicitly bounded in the input size and complexity of a given crystal.
  The proved Lipschitz continuity allows us to confirm all near-duplicates filtered by simpler invariants in major databases of experimental and simulated crystals. This practical detection of near-duplicates will stop the artificial generation of `new' materials from slight perturbations of known crystals. Several such duplicates are under investigation by five journals for data integrity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.15298v2</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olga Anosova, Vitaliy Kurlin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stability in the Banach isometric conjecture and nearly monochromatic Finsler surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02440v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Banach isometric conjecture asserts that a normed space with all of its $k$-dimensional subspaces isometric, where $k\geq 2$, is Euclidean. The first case of $k=2$ is classical, established by Auerbach, Mazur and Ulam using an elegant topological argument. We refine their method to arrive at a stable version of their result: if all $2$-dimensional subspaces are almost isometric, then the space is almost Euclidean. Furthermore, we show that a $2$-dimensional surface, which is not a torus or a Klein bottle, equipped with a near-monochromatic Finsler metric, is approximately Riemannian. The stability is quantified explicitly using the Banach-Mazur distance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02440v2</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gautam Aishwarya, Dmitry Faifman</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
