<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MG</link>
    <description>math.MG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2024 02:07:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Metric conditions that guarantee existence and uniqueness of Optimal Transport maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22567v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate metric conditions that allow to prove existence and uniqueness of a map solving the Monge problem between two marginals in a metric (measure) space, proving two main results. Firstly, we introduce a nonsmooth version of the Riemannian twist condition that we call local metric twist condition, showing, under this assumption on the cost function, existence and uniqueness of optimal transport maps. Secondly, we prove the same result for cost equal to $d^2$ in a metric space $(X, d)$ satisfying a quantitative non-branching assumption, that we call locally-uniformly non-branching.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22567v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shucheng Li, Mattia Magnabosco, Timo Schultz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the existence of $L^p$-Optimal Transport maps for norms on $\mathbb{R}^N$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22576v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove existence of $L^p$-optimal transport maps with $p \in (1,\infty)$ in a class of branching metric spaces defined on $\mathbb{R}^N$. In particular, we introduce the notion of cylinder-like convex function and we prove an existence result for the Monge problem with cost functions of the type $c(x, y) = f(g(y - x))$, where $f: [0, \infty) \rightarrow [0, \infty)$ is an increasing strictly convex function and $g: \mathbb{R}^N \rightarrow [0, \infty)$ is a cylinder-like convex function. When specialised to cylinder-like norm, our results shows existence of $L^p$-optimal transport maps for several "branching'" norms, including all norms in $\mathbb{R}^2$ and all crystalline norms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22576v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guoxi Liu, Mattia Magnabosco, Yicheng Xia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Translation-like Apollonius and triangular surfaces in non-constant curvature Thurston geometries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22955v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the present paper we deal with non-constant curvature Thurston geometries \cite{M97}, \cite{S}, \cite{Sz22-3},\cite{W06}. We define and determine the generalized trans\-lation-like Apollonius surfaces and thus also bisector surfaces as a special case. Moreover, we give a possible definition of the "surface of a translation-like triangle" in each investigated geometry. In our work we will use the projective model of Thurston geometries described by E. Moln\'ar in \cite{M97}.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22955v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G\'eza Csima, Jen\H{o} Szirmai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Weyl law for 1-cycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23192v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove the Weyl law for the volume spectrum for $1$-cycles in $n$-dimensional manifolds which was conjectured by Gromov. We follow the strategy of Guth and Liokumovich of obtaining the Weyl law from parametric versions of the coarea inequality and the isoperimetric inequality. A version of the later for families of $0$-cycles is shown in this article. We also obtain approximation results by $\delta$-localized families, which are used to prove the parametric inequalities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23192v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Staffa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parametric Coarea Inequality for 1-cycles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.23195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.23195v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove the Parametric Coarea Inequality for $1$-cycles conjectured by Guth and Liokumovich.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.23195v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bruno Staffa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Labeled four cycles and the $K(\pi,1)$-conjecture for Artin groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.16847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.16847v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that for a large class of Artin groups with Dynkin diagrams being a tree, the $K(\pi,1)$-conjecture holds. We also establish the $K(\pi,1)$-conjecture for another class of Artin groups whose Dynkin diagrams contain a cycle, which applies to some hyperbolic type Artin groups. This is based on a new approach to the $K(\pi,1)$-conjecture for Artin groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.16847v3</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingyin Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Locally homogeneous RCD spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02390v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The goal of this note is to demonstrate how existing results can be adapted to establish the following result: A locally metric measure homogeneous $\mathrm{RCD}(K,N)$ space is isometric to, after multiplying a positive constant to the reference measure, a smooth Riemannian manifold with the Riemannian volume measure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02390v2</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shouhei Honda, Artem Nepechiy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Dimension Reduction Using Semi-Relaxed Gromov-Wasserstein Distance</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.15959</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.15959v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dimension reduction techniques typically seek an embedding of a high-dimensional point cloud into a low-dimensional Euclidean space which optimally preserves the geometry of the input data. Based on expert knowledge, one may instead wish to embed the data into some other manifold or metric space in order to better reflect the geometry or topology of the point cloud. We propose a general method for manifold-valued multidimensional scaling based on concepts from optimal transport. In particular, we establish theoretical connections between the recently introduced semi-relaxed Gromov-Wasserstein (srGW) framework and multidimensional scaling by solving the Monge problem in this setting. We also derive novel connections between srGW distance and Gromov-Hausdorff distance. We apply our computational framework to analyze ensembles of political redistricting plans for states with two Congressional districts, achieving an effective visualization of the ensemble as a distribution on a circle which can be used to characterize typical neutral plans, and to flag outliers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.15959v2</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ranthony A. Clark, Tom Needham, Thomas Weighill</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orthogonal Fourier Analysis on Domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15361v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper we go over the history of the Fuglede or Spectral Set Conjecture as it has developed over the last 30 years or so. We do not aim to be exhaustive and we do not cover important areas of development such as the results on the problem in classes of finite groups or the version of the problem that focuses on spectral measures instead of sets. The selection of the material has been strongly influenced by personal taste, history and capabilities. We are trying to be more descriptive than detailed and we point out several open questions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15361v3</guid>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mihail N. Kolountzakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
