<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MG</link>
    <description>math.MG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 04:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A note on Laplacian bounds, deformation properties and isoperimetric sets in metric measure spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14132</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14132v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the setting of length PI spaces satisfying a suitable deformation property, it is known that each isoperimetric set has an open representative. In this paper, we construct an example of a length PI space (without the deformation property) where an isoperimetric set does not have any representative whose topological interior is non-empty. Moreover, we provide a sufficient condition for the validity of the deformation property, consisting in an upper Laplacian bound for the squared distance functions from a point. Our result applies to essentially non-branching ${\sf MCP}(K,N)$ spaces, thus in particular to essentially non-branching ${\sf CD}(K,N)$ spaces and to many Carnot groups and sub-Riemannian manifolds. As a consequence, every isoperimetric set in an essentially non-branching ${\sf MCP}(K,N)$ space has an open representative, which is also bounded whenever a uniform lower bound on the volumes of unit balls is assumed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14132v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Enrico Pasqualetto, Tapio Rajala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From disc patterns in the plane to character varieties of knot groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13829v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Motivated by an experimental study of groups generated by reflections in planar patterns of tangent circles, we describe some methods for constructing and studying representation spaces of holonomy groups of infinite covolume hyperbolic $3$-manifolds that arise from unknotting tunnels of links. We include full descriptions of our computational methods, which were guided by simplicity and generality rather than by being particularly efficient in special cases. This makes them easy for non-experts to understand and implement to produce visualisations that can suggest conjectures and support algebraic calculations in the character variety. Throughout, we have tried to make the exposition clear and understandable for graduate students in geometric topology and related fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13829v1</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Elzenaar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The quantum metric structure of quantum SU(2)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.06043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.06043v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a two parameter family of Dirac operators on quantum SU(2) and analyse their properties from the point of view of non-commutative metric geometry. It is shown that these Dirac operators give rise to compact quantum metric structures, and that the corresponding two parameter family of compact quantum metric spaces varies continuously in Rieffel's quantum Gromov-Hausdorff distance. This continuity result includes the classical case where we recover the round 3-sphere up to a global scaling factor on the metric. Our main technical tool is a quantum SU(2) analogue of the Berezin transform, together with its associated fuzzy approximations, the analysis of which also leads to a systematic way of approximating Lipschitz operators by means of polynomial expressions in the generators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.06043v3</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Memoirs of the European Mathematical Society, 18. EMS Press, Berlin, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jens Kaad, David Kyed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lower bounds for incidences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07658v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $p_1,\ldots,p_n$ be a set of points in the unit square and let $T_1,\ldots,T_n$ be a set of $\delta$-tubes such that $T_j$ passes through $p_j$. We prove a lower bound for the number of incidences between the points and tubes under a natural regularity condition (similar to Frostman regularity). As a consequence, we show that in any configuration of points $p_1,\ldots, p_n \in [0,1]^2$ along with a line $\ell_j$ through each point $p_j$, there exist $j\neq k$ for which $d(p_j, \ell_k) \lesssim n^{-2/3+o(1)}$.
  It follows from the latter result that any set of $n$ points in the unit square contains three points forming a triangle of area at most $n^{-7/6+o(1)}$. This new upper bound for Heilbronn's triangle problem attains the high-low limit established in our previous work arXiv:2305.18253.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07658v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Cohen, Cosmin Pohoata, Dmitrii Zakharov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hausdorff dimension of dynamical coverings under mixing properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.13051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.13051v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this article, we estimate the Hausdorff dimension of dynamical coverings with respect to mixing ergodic systems. More precisely, if the ergodic measure is exact-dimensionnal, we establish a formula provided that the system is polynomially fast mixing and if the measure is not exact-dimensionnal, we establish a similar result under super-polynomial speed of mix assumpetion. As an application of our result, we extend the result of Fan-Shmeling-Troubetzkoy for the doubling map on the circle to the case of the times 2, times 3 map on the two dimensional torus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.13051v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Daviaud</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
