<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MG</link>
    <description>math.MG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 05:00:46 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A topological characterization of indecomposable sets of finite perimeter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.18319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.18319v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that a set of finite perimeter is indecomposable if and only if it is, up to a choice of suitable representative, connected in the 1-fine topology. This gives a topological characterization of indecomposability which is new even in Euclidean spaces. Our approach relies crucially on the metric space theory of functions of bounded variation, and we are able to prove our main result in a complete, doubling metric measure space supporting a $1$-Poincar\'{e} inequality and having the two-sidedness property (this class includes all Riemannian manifolds, Carnot groups, and ${\sf RCD}(K,N)$ spaces with $K\in\mathbb R$ and $N&lt;\infty$). As an immediate corollary, we obtain an alternative proof of the decomposition theorem for sets of finite perimeter into maximal indecomposable components.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.18319v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Bonicatto, Panu Lahti, Enrico Pasqualetto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On $\ell_1$ embeddings of finite metric spaces, and sphere-of-influence graphs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.18975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.18975v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the {\em pair-cut cone $PCUT_n$} of metrics on sets with $n\ge 3$ elements, that correspond to linear combinations with non-negative coefficients of the cut-metrics resulting from cuts that are pairs. Given a metric, we fully characterize membership in the pair-cut cone in terms of quantities computed from the metric directly. We also prove a new result by which a metric $d$ that satisfies a system of inequalities, lies in the (full) cut cone of metrics, making it $\ell_1$-embeddable into Euclidean space.
  We give applications of our results to the $\ell_1$-embeddability of simple graphs into Euclidean space as {\em sphere-of-influence graphs}. We exhibit an example of a simple graph that admits no such $\ell_1$-metric in the pair-cut cone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.18975v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stanislav Jabuka, Ehsan Mirbagheri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative polynomial cohomology and applications to $\textrm L^p$-measure equivalence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.18463</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.18463v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce a quantitative version of polynomial cohomology for discrete groups and show that it coincides with usual group cohomology when combinatorial filling functions are polynomially bounded. As an application, we show that Betti numbers of nilpotent groups are invariant by mutually cobounded $\textrm L^p$-measure equivalence. We also use this to obtain new vanishing results for non-cocompact lattices in rank 1 simple Lie groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.18463v1</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Antonio L\'opez Neumann, Juan Paucar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Gr\"unbaum--Rigby configuration as a special K\'arteszi configuration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.18872</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.18872v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In 1990, Branko Gr\"unbaum and John Rigby presented a 4-configuration, known today as the \emph{Gr\"unbaum--Rigby configuration}; it is denoted by $\mathrm{GR}(21_4)$. Independently and earlier, in 1986, Ferenc K\'arteszi published a paper in which he proved a theorem in real geometry that gives rise to a series of 4-configurations $\mathrm{K}(n;\ell,m)$. In an even earlier paper from 1964, he presented a figure which is essentially the same as that given by Gr\"unbaum and Rigby. In this paper, we explore some properties of the \emph{K\'arteszi configurations} and in particular show that $\mathrm{GR}(21_4)$ is isomorphic to $\mathrm{K}(7;2,3)$. We present a theorem that gives necessary and sufficient conditions on parameters $n,\ell,m$ such that the corresponding configuration $\mathrm{K}(n;\ell,m)$ is realisable as a geometric polycyclic configuration with $n$-fold rotational symmetry and no extra incidences.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.18872v1</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G\'abor G\'evay, Gy\"orgy Kiss, Toma\v{z} Pisanski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Complete Characterization of Pythagorean Hodograph Preserving Mappings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.19587</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.19587v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We fully characterize the mappings $\Phi$ that send every Pythagorean-hodograph (PH) curve to a PH curve. We prove that in any dimension, such mappings are precisely the conformal functions whose dilation is the square of a real rational function. In the planar case, this implies (up to conjugation) that $\partial\Phi/\partial z = \Psi^{2}$, where $\Psi$ is meromorphic and satisfies $\operatorname{Res}(\Psi^{2}) = 0$ at every pole. In higher dimensions, PH preservation forces $\Phi$ to be a conformal map; for $n \ge 3$, Liouville's theorem then implies that any local diffeomorphism with this property is (anti-)M\"obius. These results subsume the previously known ``(scaled) PH-preserving'' constructions of mappings $\mathbb{R}^2 \to \mathbb{R}^3$ and align with Ueda's conformal viewpoint on isothermal and spherical geometries. At the level of examples, we demonstrate how PH-preserving mappings relate to the construction of rational PH curves and minimal surfaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.19587v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amedeo Altavilla, Hans-Peter Schr\"ocker, byn\v{e}k \v{S}\'ir, Jan Vr\v{s}ek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Small Volume Bodies of Constant Width with Tetrahedral Symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18428</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18428v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: For every $n\ge 2$, we construct a body $U_n$ of constant width $2$ in $\mathbb{E}^n$ with small volume and symmetries of a regular $n$-simplex. $U_2$ is the Reuleaux triangle. To the best of our knowledge, $U_3$ was not previously constructed, and its volume is smaller than the volume of other three-dimensional bodies of constant width with tetrahedral symmetries. While the volume of $U_3$ is slightly larger than the volume of Meissner's bodies of width $2$, it exceeds the latter by less than $0.137\%$. For all large $n$, the volume of $U_n$ is smaller than the volume of the ball of radius $0.891$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18428v2</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3842/SIGMA.2025.109</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>SIGMA 21 (2025), 109, 8 pages</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Andrii Arman, Andriy Bondarenko, Andriy Prymak, Danylo Radchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Four special Poncelet triangle families about the incircle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.17440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.17440v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We describe four special families of ellipse-inscribed Poncelet triangles about the incircle which maintain certain triangle centers stationary and which also display interesting conservations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.17440v2</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ronaldo A. Garcia, Mark Helman, Dan Reznik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A refinement of bounded cohomology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.03168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.03168v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a refinement of bounded cohomology and prove that the suitable comparison homomorphisms vanish for an amenable group. We investigate in this context Thompson's group F and provide further evidence towards its amenability. We provide a source of nontrivial 1-bounded classes and show that the space of 1-bounded classes in degree 2 is huge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.03168v3</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>\'Swiatos{\l}aw R. Gal, Jarek K\k{e}dra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ahlfors regularity of Patterson-Sullivan measures of Anosov groups and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12398v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: For all Zarski dense Anosov subgroups of a semisimple real algebraic group, we prove that their limit sets are Ahlfors regular for intrinsic conformal premetrics. As a consequence, we obtain that a Patterson-Sullivan measure is Ahlfors regular (and hence equal to the Hausdorff measure) if and only if the associated linear form is symmetric. We also discuss several applications, including analyticity of $(p,q)$-Hausdorff dimensions on the Teichm\"uller spaces, new upper bounds on the growth indicator, and $L^2$-spectral properties of associated locally symmetric manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12398v5</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhadip Dey, Dongryul M. Kim, Hee Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single-cell 3D genome reconstruction in the haploid setting using rigidity theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10700v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This article considers the problem of 3-dimensional genome reconstruction for single-cell data, and the uniqueness of such reconstructions in the setting of haploid organisms. We consider multiple graph models as representations of this problem, and use techniques from graph rigidity theory to determine identifiability. Biologically, our models come from Hi-C data, microscopy data, and combinations thereof. Mathematically, we use unit ball and sphere packing models, as well as models consisting of distance and inequality constraints. In each setting, we describe and/or derive new results on realisability and uniqueness. We then propose a 3D reconstruction method based on semidefinite programming and apply it to synthetic and real data sets using our models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10700v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00285-025-02203-2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Mathematical Biology, Volume 90, article number 45, (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Sean Dewar, Georg Grasegger, Kaie Kubjas, Fatemeh Mohammadi, Anthony Nixon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nested superposition principle for random measures and the geometry of the Wasserstein on Wasserstein space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07523v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the geometric structure of the space of random measures $\mathcal{P}_p(\mathcal{P}_p(X))$, endowed with the Wasserstein on Wasserstein metric, where $(X, d)$ is a complete separable metric space. In this setting, we prove a metric superposition principle, in the spirit of the result by S. Lisini, that will allow us to recover important geometric features of the space. When $X$ is $\mathbb{R}^d$, we study the differential structure of $\mathcal{P}_p(\mathcal{P}_p(\mathbb{R}^d))$ in analogy with the simpler Wasserstein space $\mathcal{P}_p(\mathbb{R}^d)$. We show that continuity equations for random measures involving the abstract concept of derivation acting on cylinder functions can be more conveniently described by suitable non-local vector fields $b:[0,T]\times \mathbb{R}^d \times \mathcal{P}(\mathbb{R}^d) \to \mathbb{R}^d$. In this way, we can: 1) characterize the absolutely continuous curves on the Wasserstein on Wasserstein space; 2) define and characterize its tangent bundle; 3) prove a superposition principle for the solutions to the standard non-local continuity equation in terms of solutions of interacting particle systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07523v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessandro Pinzi, Giuseppe Savar\'e</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mathematical exploration and discovery at scale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02864v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: AlphaEvolve (Novikov et al., 2025) is a generic evolutionary coding agent that combines the generative capabilities of LLMs with automated evaluation in an iterative evolutionary framework that proposes, tests, and refines algorithmic solutions to challenging scientific and practical problems. In this paper we showcase AlphaEvolve as a tool for autonomously discovering novel mathematical constructions and advancing our understanding of long-standing open problems.
  To demonstrate its breadth, we considered a list of 67 problems spanning mathematical analysis, combinatorics, geometry, and number theory. The system rediscovered the best known solutions in most of the cases and discovered improved solutions in several. In some instances, AlphaEvolve is also able to generalize results for a finite number of input values into a formula valid for all input values. Furthermore, we are able to combine this methodology with Deep Think and AlphaProof in a broader framework where the additional proof-assistants and reasoning systems provide automated proof generation and further mathematical insights.
  These results demonstrate that large language model-guided evolutionary search can autonomously discover mathematical constructions that complement human intuition, at times matching or even improving the best known results, highlighting the potential for significant new ways of interaction between mathematicians and AI systems. We present AlphaEvolve as a powerful new tool for mathematical discovery, capable of exploring vast search spaces to solve complex optimization problems at scale, often with significantly reduced requirements on preparation and computation time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02864v3</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>math.CA</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bogdan Georgiev, Javier G\'omez-Serrano, Terence Tao, Adam Zsolt Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
