<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.MG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MG</link>
    <description>math.MG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.MG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 05:00:08 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice-like Packings and Coverings with Congruent Translation Balls and Cylinders in Sol geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03599v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The aim of this paper is to study lattice-like coverings with congruent translation balls and the packings and coverings with a type of translation cylinders in Sol space related to the fundamental lattices. We introduce the notions of the densities of the considered problems and give upper estimate to ball coverings using the radii and the volumes of the circumscribed translation spheres of given {\it translation tetrahedra}. Moreover we determine the exact optimal packing and covering densities of a type of cylinder packings belonging to the fundamental lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03599v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Judit Sajtos, Jen\H{o} Szirmai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On asymptotic Lebesgue's universal covering problem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.04023</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.04023v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Universal cover in $\mathbb{E}^{n}$ is a measurable set that contains a congruent copy of any set of diameter 1. Lebesgue's universal covering problem, posed in 1914, asks for the convex set of smallest area that serves as a universal cover in the plane ($n=2$).
  A simple universal cover in $\mathbb{E}^n$ is provided by the classical theorem of Jung, which states that any set of diameter 1 in an $n$-dimensional Euclidean space is contained in a ball $J_n$ of radius $\sqrt{\tfrac{n}{2n+2}}$; in other words, $J_n$ is a universal cover in $\mathbb{E}^n$.
  We show that in high dimensions, Jung's ball $J_n$ is asymptotically optimal with respect to the volume, namely, for any universal cover $U \subset \mathbb{E}^n$, $$ {\rm Vol}(U) \ge (1-o(1))^n{\rm Vol}(J_n). $$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.04023v1</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrii Arman, Andriy Bondarenko, Andriy Prymak, Danylo Radchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quadratic metric comparisons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03353v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the effects on length spaces imposed by quadratic inequalities on the six distances between the points in every quadruple.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03353v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nina Lebedeva, Anton Petrunin, Vladimir Zolotov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Remarks on a result of Sibony on the Carath\'eodory topology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03901</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03901v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove that if a Carath\'eodory hyperbolic analytic space $X$ is $C_X$-complete, then its natural topology is induced by the Carath\'eodory distance on $X$. This is an improvement of Sibony's result, which concludes the same under the hypothesis that $X$ is $C_X$-finitely compact. This improvement is not merely formal; we also show the existence of uncountably many biholomorphically inequivalent analytic spaces that are not $C_X$-finitely compact but are $C_X$-complete.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03901v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudip Dolai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounded-degree graphs of non-negative Ollivier-Ricci curvature have subexponential growth and diffusive random walk</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2512.03968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2512.03968v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the geometric properties of graphs with non-negative Ollivier-Ricci curvature, a discrete analogue of non-negative Ricci curvature in Riemannian geometry. We prove that for each $d&lt;\infty$ there exists a constant $C_d$ such that if $G=(V,E)$ is a finite graph with non-negative Ollivier-Ricci curvature and with degrees bounded by $d$ then the average log-volume growth and random walk displacement satisfy \[
  \frac{1}{|V|} \sum_{x\in V} \log \#B(x,r) \leq \exp\left[C_d \sqrt{\log r}\right] = r^{o(1)} \] and \[
  \frac{1}{|V|} \sum_{x\in V} \mathbf{E}_x [d(X_0,X_n)^2] \leq n \exp\left[C_d \sqrt{\log n}\right] = n^{1+o(1)} \] for every $n,r\geq 2$. This significantly strengthens a result of Salez (GAFA 2022), who proved that the average displacement of the random walk is $o(n)$ and deduced that non-negatively curved graphs of bounded degree cannot be expanders. Our results also apply to infinite transitive graphs and, more generally, to bounded-degree unimodular random rooted graphs of non-negative Ollivier-Ricci curvature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2512.03968v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Hutchcroft, Florentin M\"unch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variances and central limit theorems for random beta-polytopes and in other geometric models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.21392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.21392v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We prove matching asymptotic lower and upper bounds on the variances of the intrinsic volumes and the number of $k$-faces of $d$-dimensional random beta-polytopes. Using Stein's methods, we establish central limit theorems for the intrinsic volumes. We also prove asymptotic upper bounds on the variances of the volume and vertex number of spherical random polytopes in spherical convex bodies, and hyperbolic random polytopes in convex bodies in hyperbolic space. Moreover, we consider a circumscribed model on the sphere.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.21392v3</guid>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ferenc Fodor, Bal\'azs Gr\"unfelder</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
