<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>physics.pop-ph updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.pop-ph</link>
    <description>physics.pop-ph updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/physics.pop-ph" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2024 02:46:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Timing and Dynamics of the Rosanna Shuffle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06892</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06892v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Rosanna shuffle, the drum pattern from Toto's 1982 hit "Rosanna", is one of the most recognized drum beats in popular music. Recorded by Jeff Porcaro, this drum beat features a half-time shuffle with rapid triplets on the hi-hat and snare drum. In this analysis, we examine the timing and dynamics of the original drum track, focusing on rhythmic variations such as swing factor, microtiming deviations, tempo drift, and the overall dynamics of the hi-hat pattern. Our findings reveal that "Rosanna" exhibits a surprisingly pronounced swing for its genre, along with notable tempo drift typical of tracks recorded without a metronome. Additionally, we observe clear long-range correlations in the microtiming deviations, consistent with previous studies. Notably, the two-bar phrases of the song feature a distinctive repeating pattern in the timing and dynamics of the hi-hat beats, which enhances the song's phrasing. Overall, the Rosanna shuffle boasts a rich array of rhythmic characteristics that solidify its significant place in music history.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06892v2</guid>
      <category>cs.SD</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.pop-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Esa R\"as\"anen, Niko Gullsten, Otto Pulkkinen, Tuomas Virtanen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
