<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.OT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.OT</link>
    <description>stat.OT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.OT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 04:07:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 19 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Risk Quadrangle and Robust Optimization Based on $\varphi$-Divergence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10987v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper studies robust and distributionally robust optimization based on the extended $\varphi$-divergence under the Fundamental Risk Quadrangle framework. We present the primal and dual representations of the quadrangle elements: risk, deviation, regret, error, and statistic. The framework provides an interpretation of portfolio optimization, classification and regression as robust optimization. We furnish illustrative examples demonstrating that many common problems are included in this framework. The $\varphi$-divergence risk measure used in distributionally robust optimization is a special case. We conduct a case study to visualize the risk envelope.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10987v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Peng, Anton Malandii, Stan Uryasev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Type $1$, $2$, $3$ and $4$ $q$-negative binomial distribution of order $k$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.03617</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.03617v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the distributions of waiting times in variations of the negative binomial distribution of order $k$. One variation apply different enumeration scheme on the runs of successes. Another case considers binary trials for which the probability of ones is geometrically varying. We investigate the exact distribution of the waiting time for the $r$-th occurrence of success run of a specified length (non-overlapping, overlapping, at least, exactly, $\ell$-overlapping) in a $q$-sequence of binary trials. The main theorems are Type $1$, $2$, $3$ and $4$ $q$-negative binomial distribution of order $k$ and $q$-negative binomial distribution of order $k$ in the $\ell$-overlapping case. In the present work, we consider a sequence of independent binary zero and one trials with not necessarily identical distribution with the probability of ones varying according to a geometric rule. Exact formulae for the distributions obtained by means of enumerative combinatorics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.03617v4</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jungtaek Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On distribution of runs and patterns in four state trials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2211.00774</link>
      <description>arXiv:2211.00774v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: From a mathematical and statistical point of view, a segment of a DNA strand can be viewed as a sequence of four-state (A, C, G, T) trials. We consider distributions of runs and patterns related to run lengths of multi-state sequences, especially for four states (A, B, C, D). Let $X_{1}, X_{2}, \ldots$ be a sequence of four state i.i.d.\ trials taking values in the set $\mathscr{S}=\{A,\ B,\ C,\ D\}$ of four symbols with probability $P(A)=P_{a}$, $P(B)=P_{b}$, $P(C)=P_{c}$ and $P(D)=P_{d},$ respectively. In this paper, we obtain exact formulae for the probability distribution function for runs of B's the discrete distribution of order $k$, longest run statistics, shortest run statistics, waiting time distribution and the distribution of run lengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2211.00774v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jungtaek Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
