<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>stat.OT updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.OT</link>
    <description>stat.OT updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/stat.OT" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 04:04:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>R2 priors for Grouped Variance Decomposition in High-dimensional Regression</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.11833</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.11833v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce the Group-R2 decomposition prior, a hierarchical shrinkage prior that extends R2-based priors to structured regression settings with known groups of predictors. By decomposing the prior distribution of the coefficient of determination R2 in two stages, first across groups, then within groups, the prior enables interpretable control over model complexity and sparsity. We derive theoretical properties of the prior, including marginal distributions of coefficients, tail behavior, and connections to effective model complexity. Through simulation studies, we evaluate the conditions under which grouping improves predictive performance and parameter recovery compared to priors that do not account for groups. Our results provide practical guidance for prior specification and highlight both the strengths and limitations of incorporating grouping into R2-based shrinkage priors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.11833v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Javier Enrique Aguilar, David Kohns, Aki Vehtari, Paul-Christian B\"urkner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robust Causal Discovery in Real-World Time Series with Power-Laws</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12257</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12257v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Exploring causal relationships in stochastic time series is a challenging yet crucial task with a vast range of applications, including finance, economics, neuroscience, and climate science. Many algorithms for Causal Discovery (CD) have been proposed, but they often exhibit a high sensitivity to noise, resulting in misleading causal inferences when applied to real data. In this paper, we observe that the frequency spectra of typical real-world time series follow a power-law distribution, notably due to an inherent self-organizing behavior. Leveraging this insight, we build a robust CD method based on the extraction of power -law spectral features that amplify genuine causal signals. Our method consistently outperforms state-of-the-art alternatives on both synthetic benchmarks and real-world datasets with known causal structures, demonstrating its robustness and practical relevance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12257v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Tusoni, Giuseppe Masi, Andrea Coletta, Aldo Glielmo, Viviana Arrigoni, Novella Bartolini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hierarchical Temporal Point Process Modeling of Aggressive Behavior Onset in Psychiatric Inpatient Youth with Autism for Branching Factor Estimation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.12424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.12424v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Aggressive behavior in autistic inpatient youth often arises in temporally clustered bursts complicating efforts to distinguish external triggers from internal escalation. The sample population branching factor-the expected number of new onsets triggered by a given event-is a key summary of self-excitation in behavior dynamics. Prior pooled models overestimate this quantity by ignoring patient-specific variability. We addressed this using a hierarchical Hawkes process with an exponential kernel and edge-effect correction allowing partial pooling across patients. This approach reduces bias from high-frequency individuals and stabilizes estimates for those with sparse data. Bayesian inference was performed using the No U-Turn Sampler with model evaluation via convergence diagnostics, power-scaling sensitivity analysis, and multiple Goodness-of-Fit (GOF) metrics: PSIS-LOO the Lewis test with Durbin's modification and residual analysis based on the Random Time Change Theorem (RTCT). The hierarchical model yielded a significantly lower and more precise branching factor estimate mean (0.742 +- 0.026) than the pooled model (0.899 +- 0.015) and narrower intervals than the unpooled model (0.717 +- 0.139). This led to a threefold smaller cascade of events per onset under the hierarchical model. Sensitivity analyses confirmed robustness to prior and likelihood perturbations while the unpooled model showed instability for sparse individuals. GOF measures consistently favored or on par to the hierarchical model. Hierarchical Hawkes modeling with edge-effect correction provides robust estimation of branching dynamics by capturing both within- and between-patient variability. This enables clearer separation of endogenous from exogenous events supports linkage to physiological signals and enhances early warning systems individualized treatment and resource allocation in inpatient care.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.12424v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>stat.OT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Potter, Michael Everett, Deniz Erdogmus, Yuna Watanabe, Tales Imbiriba, Matthew S. Goodwin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
