<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.GN updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.GN</link>
    <description>econ.GN updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.GN" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 04:00:49 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 May 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluating Production Planning and Control Systems in Different Environments: A Comparative Simulation Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02015v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Selecting the appropriate production planning and control systems (PPCS) presents a significant challenge for many companies, as their performance, i.e. overall costs, depends on the production system environment. Key environmental characteristics include the system's structure, i.e. flow shop, hybrid shop, or job shop, and the planned shop load. Besides selecting a suitable PPCS, its parameterization significantly influences the performance. This publication investigates the performance and the optimal parametrization of Material Requirement Planning (MRP), Reorder Point System (RPS) and Constant Work In Progress (ConWIP) at different stochastic multi-item multi-stage production system environments by conduction a comprehensive full factorial simulation study. The results indicate that MRP and ConWIP generally outperform RPS in all observed environments. Moreover, when comparing MRP with ConWIP, the performance clearly varies depending on the specific production system environment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02015v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wolfgang Seiringer, Balwin Bokor, Klaus Altendorfer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Economy and Public Diplomacy: An Analysis of RT's Economic Content and Context on Facebook</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01798v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With globalization's rise, economic interdependence's impacts have become a prominent factor affecting personal lives, as well as national and international dynamics. This study examines RT's public diplomacy efforts on its non-Russian Facebook accounts over the past five years to identify the prominence of economic topics across language accounts. Computational analysis, including word embeddings and statistical methods, investigates how offline economic indicators, like currency values and oil prices, correspond to RT's online economic content changes. The results demonstrate that RT uses message reinforcement associated economic topics as an audience targeting strategy and differentiates their use with changing currency and oil values.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01798v1</guid>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayse D. Lokmanoglu, Carol K. Winkler, Kareem El Damanhoury, Virginia Massignan, Esteban Villa-Turek, Keyu Alexander Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating the economic impact of rationality through reinforcement learning and agent-based modelling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02161</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02161v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Agent-based models (ABMs) are simulation models used in economics to overcome some of the limitations of traditional frameworks based on general equilibrium assumptions. However, agents within an ABM follow predetermined, not fully rational, behavioural rules which can be cumbersome to design and difficult to justify. Here we leverage multi-agent reinforcement learning (RL) to expand the capabilities of ABMs with the introduction of fully rational agents that learn their policy by interacting with the environment and maximising a reward function. Specifically, we propose a 'Rational macro ABM' (R-MABM) framework by extending a paradigmatic macro ABM from the economic literature. We show that gradually substituting ABM firms in the model with RL agents, trained to maximise profits, allows for a thorough study of the impact of rationality on the economy. We find that RL agents spontaneously learn three distinct strategies for maximising profits, with the optimal strategy depending on the level of market competition and rationality. We also find that RL agents with independent policies, and without the ability to communicate with each other, spontaneously learn to segregate into different strategic groups, thus increasing market power and overall profits. Finally, we find that a higher degree of rationality in the economy always improves the macroeconomic environment as measured by total output, depending on the specific rational policy, this can come at the cost of higher instability. Our R-MABM framework is general, it allows for stable multi-agent learning, and represents a principled and robust direction to extend existing economic simulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02161v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone Brusatin, Tommaso Padoan, Andrea Coletta, Domenico Delli Gatti, Aldo Glielmo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
