<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.GN updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.GN</link>
    <description>econ.GN updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.GN" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Jun 2024 01:41:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 27 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Is the logistical engagement of stakeholders in short food chains a crucible of alternativity?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18123v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In response to the negative environmental, social, and economic externalities of the dominant food model, a consensus is emerging on the need to develop alternative food systems capable of facilitating a transition to a more sustainable model. Among these alternatives, short food supply chains (SFSCs) are identified as potential crucibles of alternativity. Defined as distribution channels with a maximum of one intermediary between producer and consumer, SFSCs can contribute to the reterritorialization of food flows and the creation of relational and geographical proximities among food chain actors. This study examines how logistical engagement translates into the choice of SFSC points of sale by consumers and farmers. It evaluates this engagement through the travel times farmers and consumers are willing to endure to sell or buy at an SFSC point of sale, and the prices they are willing to accept or pay for SFSC products. A discrete choice experiment conducted in 2022 with 154 farm managers and 1022 consumers analyzed preferences regarding types of points of sale, sales prices, travel times, and relational proximity. The results show that consumers engaged in SFSCs favour alternative points of sale such as farms and associations, even for longer travel times. Farmers also value these points of sale, with logistical engagement more pronounced among those already marketing through SFSCs. Supermarkets appear less attractive to alternative profiles but serve as entry points for new participants in SFSCs. Relational proximity between farmers and consumers is important, with a preference for direct exchanges during sales. This study highlights the importance of actor engagement in SFSCs and offers perspectives for developing alternative logistics by valuing relational proximity and using conventional points of sale as entry points for new actors in the SFSCs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18123v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Camille Horvath, C\'eline Raimbert, Gwena\"elle Raton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revisiting the capitalist road to communism: unconditional basic income and the post-labor world</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The thesis of a capitalist road to communism (van der Veen and Van Parijs, 1986) asserts that Marx realm of freedom can be reached from within welfare capitalism, skipping socialism, by using a tax-financed unconditional basic income until it is close to disposable income per head, so that the very distinction between paid work and free time is cancelled as a result. We revisit and update this thesis for two reasons: the recent prospect of a post-labor society following the automation revolution in technology, and that welfare capitalism has become more inegalitarian and less hospitable to basic income. We use a simple economic model which incorporates an upward adjustment of basic income to labor-saving technical change and distinguishes between capital that complements labor and capital that is fully substitutable with labor. A baseline simulation of the model shows the economic feasibility of a capitalist transition to communism. Two versions of a scenario incorporating interplay between technical change and market socialist institutional reforms are set out which make the transition politically viable to some extent, depending on the social distribution of power over technology. The most promising version is one in which the productivity of labor and automation capital grow at similar rates. We show in which respects it approximates the ideal of communism. One finding is that communism does not require reaching the final stage of a post-labor society. We conclude with a reflection on the relevance of our present update for the more immediate future of unconditional basic income.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18194v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert van der Veen (University of Amsterdam), Loek Groot (University of Utrecht)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Costly Signalling in DAOs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.18457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.18457v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Decentralised Autonomous Organisations (DAOs) are a new type of digital organisation that uses blockchain infrastructure (e.g. smart contracts, tokens) to coordinate a group of people around a shared mission. Like all organisations, DAOs must attract sources of funding and other resources, and discover and retain a talented community and workforce. To do this, they must signal their true quality. Yet the characteristics of the environment that DAOs operate in (pseudonymous actors, global scale, permissionless entry and exit) makes this difficult. We apply costly signalling theory to explore the information asymmetry problem in DAOs and some of the strategies (behaviours and investments) and institutional solutions (including better signalling mechanisms) that have evolved to solve this problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.18457v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Darcy W. E. Allen, Jason Potts, Julian Waters-Lynch, Max Parasol</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
