<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.GN updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.GN</link>
    <description>econ.GN updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.GN" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 04:03:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Seeing Through Green: Text-Based Classification and the Firm's Returns from Green Patents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02287v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces Natural Language Processing for identifying ``true'' green patents from official supporting documents. We start our training on about 12.4 million patents that had been classified as green from previous literature. Thus, we train a simple neural network to enlarge a baseline dictionary through vector representations of expressions related to environmental technologies. After testing, we find that ``true'' green patents represent about 20\% of the total of patents classified as green from previous literature. We show heterogeneity by technological classes, and then check that `true' green patents are about 1\% less cited by following inventions. In the second part of the paper, we test the relationship between patenting and a dashboard of firm-level financial accounts in the European Union. After controlling for reverse causality, we show that holding at least one ``true'' green patent raises sales, market shares, and productivity. If we restrict the analysis to high-novelty ``true'' green patents, we find that they also yield higher profits. Our findings underscore the importance of using text analyses to gauge finer-grained patent classifications that are useful for policymaking in different domains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02287v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lapo Santarlasci, Armando Rungi, Antonio Zinilli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Green Ammonia: A Techno-Economic Supply Chain Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02412v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Green ammonia is emerging as a strategic intermediary within green energy supply chains, serving effectively as both an industrial commodity and hydrogen carrier. This study provides a techno-economic analysis of green ammonia supply chains, comparing cost-effective pathways from global production to European consumers, and evaluates ammonia alongside alternative hydrogen carriers. Gaseous hydrogen consistently remains the most economical import option for Europe, though ammonia holds a narrowing cost advantage over liquid hydrogen (from 16 % in 2030 to 10 % by 2040). Competitive ammonia suppliers, notably Morocco, the United States, and the United Arab Emirates, benefit from low renewable energy costs, with significant price reductions expected by 2040, driven by falling costs for electricity, electrolysers, and conversion technologies. Optimal transport modes vary by consumer demand and distance: trucks are ideal for low demands at all distances, rail for medium ranges, and pipelines for high-demand scenarios. By 2040, ammonia will primarily serve direct-use applications, as hydrogen consumers increasingly shift to direct hydrogen supplies. Policymakers should prioritize pipeline infrastructure for hydrogen distribution, cautiously invest in ammonia's short- to medium-term infrastructure advantages, and limit long-term reliance on ammonia as a hydrogen carrier to mitigate stranded asset risks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02412v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucien Genge, Felix M\"usgens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Introducing a New Brexit-Related Uncertainty Index: Its Evolution and Economic Consequences</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02439v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Important game-changer economic events and transformations cause uncertainties that may affect investment decisions, capital flows, international trade, and macroeconomic variables. One such major transformation is Brexit, which refers to the multiyear process through which the UK withdrew from the EU. This study develops and uses a new Brexit-Related Uncertainty Index (BRUI). In creating this index, we apply Text Mining, Context Window, Natural Language Processing (NLP), and Large Language Models (LLMs) from Deep Learning techniques to analyse the monthly country reports of the Economist Intelligence Unit from May 2012 to January 2025. Additionally, we employ a standard vector autoregression (VAR) analysis to examine the model-implied responses of various macroeconomic variables to BRUI shocks. While developing the BRUI, we also create a complementary COVID-19 Related Uncertainty Index (CRUI) to distinguish the uncertainties stemming from these distinct events. Empirical findings and comparisons of BRUI with other earlier-developed uncertainty indexes demonstrate the robustness of the new index. This new index can assist British policymakers in measuring and understanding the impacts of Brexit-related uncertainties, enabling more effective policy formulation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02439v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ismet Gocer, Julia Darby, Serdar Ongan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identity and Cooperation in Multicultural Societies: An Experimental Investigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02511v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Immigration has shaped many nations, posing the challenge of integrating immigrants into society. While economists often focus on immigrants' economic outcomes compared to natives (such as education, labor market success, and health) social interactions between immigrants and natives are equally crucial. These interactions, from everyday exchanges to teamwork, often lack enforceable contracts and require cooperation to avoid conflicts and achieve efficient outcomes. However, socioeconomic, ethnic, and cultural differences can hinder cooperation. Thus, evaluating integration should also consider its impact on fostering cooperation across diverse groups. This paper studies how priming different identity dimensions affects cooperation between immigrant and native youth. Immigrant identity includes both ethnic ties to their country of origin and connections to the host country. We test whether cooperation improves by making salient a specific identity: Common identity (shared society), Multicultural identity (ethnic group within society), or Neutral identity. In a lab in the field experiment with over 390 adolescents, participants were randomly assigned to one of these priming conditions and played a Public Good Game. Results show that immigrants are 13 percent more cooperative than natives at baseline. Natives increase cooperation by about 3 percentage points when their multicultural identity is primed, closing the initial gap with immigrant peers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02511v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Natalia Montinari, Matteo Ploner, Veronica Rattini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tertiary Education Completion and Financial Aid Assistance: Evidence from an Information Experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02560v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the role of information among disadvantaged students is crucial in explaining their investment decisions in higher education. Indeed, information barriers on the returns and the gains from completing college may explain a substantial share of variation in students' degree completion. We conduct a field experiment with 7,806 university students in Italy who benefit from financial aid assistance, by providing information, either on the labor market returns of completing college or on the education returns of meeting the academic requirements attached to the financial aid. Our results suggest that only the latter information treatment has a positive effect on academic performance, increasing the number of credits obtained by around 3, and by decreasing the probability of dropout by around 4 percentage points. We also find that the results are mediated by an aspiration lift generated by our treatment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02560v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Bonacini, Giuseppe Pignataro, Veronica Rattini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FinAI-BERT: A Transformer-Based Model for Sentence-Level Detection of AI Disclosures in Financial Reports</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.01991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.01991v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The proliferation of artificial intelligence (AI) in financial services has prompted growing demand for tools that can systematically detect AI-related disclosures in corporate filings. While prior approaches often rely on keyword expansion or document-level classification, they fall short in granularity, interpretability, and robustness. This study introduces FinAI-BERT, a domain-adapted transformer-based language model designed to classify AI-related content at the sentence level within financial texts. The model was fine-tuned on a manually curated and balanced dataset of 1,586 sentences drawn from 669 annual reports of U.S. banks (2015 to 2023). FinAI-BERT achieved near-perfect classification performance (accuracy of 99.37 percent, F1 score of 0.993), outperforming traditional baselines such as Logistic Regression, Naive Bayes, Random Forest, and XGBoost. Interpretability was ensured through SHAP-based token attribution, while bias analysis and robustness checks confirmed the model's stability across sentence lengths, adversarial inputs, and temporal samples. Theoretically, the study advances financial NLP by operationalizing fine-grained, theme-specific classification using transformer architectures. Practically, it offers a scalable, transparent solution for analysts, regulators, and scholars seeking to monitor the diffusion and framing of AI across financial institutions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.01991v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <category>q-fin.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Bilal Zafar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolving CAP Through Automata-Theoretic Economic Design: A Unified Mathematical Framework for Real-Time Partition-Tolerant Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.02464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.02464v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The CAP theorem asserts a trilemma between consistency, availability, and partition tolerance. This paper introduces a rigorous automata-theoretic and economically grounded framework that reframes the CAP trade-off as a constraint optimization problem. We model distributed systems as partition-aware state machines and embed economic incentive layers to stabilize consensus behavior across adversarially partitioned networks. By incorporating game-theoretic mechanisms into the global transition semantics, we define provable bounds on convergence, liveness, and correctness. Our results demonstrate that availability and consistency can be simultaneously preserved within bounded epsilon margins, effectively extending the classical CAP limits through formal economic control.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.02464v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.FL</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Craig S Wright</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advertiser Learning in Direct Advertising Markets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.07015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.07015v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Direct buy advertisers procure advertising inventory at fixed rates from publishers and ad networks. Such advertisers face the complex task of choosing ads amongst myriad new publisher sites. We offer evidence that advertisers do not excel at making these choices. Instead, they try many sites before settling on a favored set, consistent with advertiser learning. We subsequently model advertiser demand for publisher inventory wherein advertisers learn about advertising efficacy across publishers' sites. Results suggest that advertisers spend considerable resources advertising on sites they eventually abandon -- in part because their prior beliefs about advertising efficacy on those sites are too optimistic. The median advertiser's expected CTR at a new site is 0.177\%, four times higher than the true median CTR of 0.045\%.
  We consider how an ad network's pooling of advertiser information remediates this problem. As ads with similar visual elements garner similar CTRs, the network's pooling of information enables advertisers to better predict ad performance at new sites. Counterfactual analyses indicate that gains from pooling advertiser information are substantial: over six months, we estimate a median advertiser welfare gain of \$3,621 (an 18.3\% increase) and a median revenue gain of \$13,558 (a 77.7\% increase) among the 20 largest publishers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.07015v3</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Carl F. Mela, Jason M. T. Roos, Tulio Sousa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning the Probability Distributions of Day-Ahead Electricity Prices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.02867</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.02867v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a novel machine learning approach for probabilistic forecasting of hourly day-ahead electricity prices. In contrast with the recent advances in data-rich probabilistic forecasting, which approximates distributions with few features (such as moments), our method is nonparametric and selects the distribution from all possible empirical distributions learned from the input data without the need for limiting assumptions. The model that we propose is a multioutput neural network that accounts for the temporal dynamics of the probabilities and controls for monotonicity using a penalty. Such a distributional neural network can precisely learn complex patterns from many relevant variables that affect electricity prices. We illustrate the capacity of the developed method on German hourly day-ahead electricity prices and predict their probability distribution via many variables, doing so more accurately than the state-of-the-art benchmarks can, thus revealing new valuable information in the data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.02867v3</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jozef Barunik, Lubos Hanus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generative AI at the Crossroads: Light Bulb, Dynamo, or Microscope?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14588v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: With the advent of generative AI (genAI), the potential scope of artificial intelligence has increased dramatically, but the future effect of genAI on productivity remains uncertain. The effect of the technology on the innovation process is a crucial open question. Some inventions, such as the light bulb, temporarily raise productivity growth as adoption spreads, but the effect fades when the market is saturated; that is, the level of output per hour is permanently higher but the growth rate is not. In contrast, two types of technologies stand out as having longer-lived effects on productivity growth. First, there are technologies known as general-purpose technologies (GPTs). GPTs (1) are widely adopted, (2) spur abundant knock-on innovations (new goods and services, process efficiencies, and business reorganization), and (3) show continual improvement, refreshing this innovation cycle; the electric dynamo is an example. Second, there are inventions of methods of invention (IMIs). IMIs increase the efficiency of the research and development process via improvements to observation, analysis, communication, or organization; the compound microscope is an example. We show that GenAI has the characteristics of both a GPT and an IMI -- an encouraging sign that genAI will raise the \textit{level} of productivity. Even so, genAI's contribution to productivity \textit{growth} will depend on the speed with which that level is attained and, historically, integrating revolutionary technologies into the economy is a protracted process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14588v3</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Martin Baily, David Byrne, Aidan Kane, Paul Soto</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
