<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.GN updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.GN</link>
    <description>econ.GN updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.GN" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 05:06:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>From Policy to Practice. Upper Bound Cost Estimates of Europes Green Hydrogen Ambitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10859</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10859v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As the European countries strive to meet their ambitious climate goals, renewable hydrogen has emerged to aid in decarbonizing energy-intensive sectors and support the overall energy transition. To ensure that hydrogen production aligns with these goals, the European Commission has introduced criteria for additionality, temporal correlation, and geographical correlation. These criteria are designed to ensure that hydrogen production from renewable sources supports the growth of renewable energy. This study assesses the impact of these criteria on green hydrogen production, focusing on production costs and technology impacts. The European energy market is simulated up to 2048 using stochastic programming, applying these requirements exclusively to green hydrogen production without the phased-in compliance period outlined in the EU regulations. The findings show that meeting the criteria will increase expected system costs by 82 EUR billion from 2024 to 2048, largely due to the rapid shift from fossil fuels to renewable energy. The additionality requirement, which mandates the use of new renewable energy installations for electrolysis, proves to be the most expensive, but also the most effective in accelerating renewable energy adoption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10859v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Hordvei, S. Hummelen, M. Petersen, S. Backe, P. Granado</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bribery, Secrecy, and Communication: Theory and Evidence from Firms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10877v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper studies if firms pay different types of bribes, and if corrupt bureaucrats have perfect information about resources of bribe-paying firms. We construct a model of corruption that allows for multiple informational scenarios in a single market for bribes and empirically test these scenarios on the original dataset of 429 firms operating in Tajikistan. The results indicate that firms simultaneously make voluntary and involuntary bribe payments, firms hide resources from corrupt bureaucrats to reduce involuntary bribe payments, and bureaucrats who receive voluntary bribe payments do not share bribery-relevant information with other bureaucrats.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10877v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jafar M. Olimov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Floods do not sink prices, historical memory does: How flood risk impacts the Italian housing market</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12116</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12116v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Do home prices incorporate flood risk in the immediate aftermath of specific flood events, or is it the repeated exposure over the years that plays a more significant role? We address this question through the first systematic study of the Italian housing market, which is an ideal case study because it is highly exposed to floods, though unevenly distributed across the national territory. Using a novel dataset containing about 550,000 mortgage-financed transactions between 2016 and 2024, as well as hedonic regressions and a difference-in-difference design, we find that: (i) specific floods do not decrease home prices in areas at risk; (ii) the repeated exposure to floods in flood-prone areas leads to a price decline, up to 4\% in the most frequently flooded regions; (iii) responses are heterogeneous by buyers' income and age. Young buyers (with limited exposure to prior floods) do not obtain any price reduction for settling in risky areas, while experienced buyers do. At the same time, buyers who settle in risky areas have lower incomes than buyers in safe areas in the most affected regions. Our results emphasize the importance of cultural and institutional factors in understanding how flood risk affects the housing market and socioeconomic outcomes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12116v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna Bellaver, Lorenzo Costantini, Ariadna Fosch, Anna Monticelli, David Scala, Marco Pangallo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potato Potahto in the FAO-GAEZ Productivity Measures? Nonclassical Measurement Error with Multiple Proxies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12141v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The FAO-GAEZ crop productivity data are widely used in Economics. However, the existence of measurement error is rarely recognized in the empirical literature. We propose a novel method to partially identify the effect of agricultural productivity, deriving bounds that allow for nonclassical measurement error by leveraging two proxies. These bounds exhaust all the information contained in the first two moments of the data. We reevaluate three influential studies, documenting that measurement error matters and that the impact of agricultural productivity on economic outcomes may be smaller than previously reported. Our methodology has broad applications in empirical research involving mismeasured variables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12141v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Araujo, Vitor Possebom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Planning minimum regret $CO_2$ pipeline networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.12035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.12035v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The transition to a low-carbon economy necessitates effective carbon capture and storage (CCS) solutions, particularly for hard-to-abate sectors. Herein, pipeline networks are indispensable for cost-efficient $CO_2$ transportation over long distances. However, there is deep uncertainty regarding which industrial sectors will participate in such systems. This poses a significant challenge due to substantial investments as well as the lengthy planning and development timelines required for $CO_2$ pipeline projects, which are further constrained by limited upgrade options for already built infrastructure. The economies of scale inherent in pipeline construction exacerbate these challenges, leading to potential regret over earlier decisions. While numerous models were developed to optimize the initial layout of pipeline infrastructure based on known demand, a gap exists in addressing the incremental development of infrastructure in conjunction with deep uncertainty. Hence, this paper introduces a novel optimization model for $CO_2$ pipeline infrastructure development, minimizing regret as its objective function and incorporating various upgrade options, such as looping and pressure increases. The model's effectiveness is also demonstrated by presenting a comprehensive case study of Germany's cement and lime industries. The developed approach quantitatively illustrates the trade-off between different options, which can help in deriving effective strategies for $CO_2$ infrastructure development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.12035v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephan Bogs, Ali Abdelshafy, Grit Walther</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissertation Paths: Advisors and Students in the Economics Research Production Function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01533</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01533v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Elite economics PhD programs aim to train graduate students for a lifetime of academic research. This paper asks how advising affects graduate students' post-PhD research productivity. Advising is highly concentrated: at the eight highly-selective schools in our study, a minority of advisors do most of the advising work. We quantify advisor attributes such as an advisor's own research output and aspects of the advising relationship like coauthoring and research field affinity that might contribute to student research success. Students advised by research-active, prolific advisors tend to publish more, while coauthoring has no effect. Student-advisor research affinity also predicts student success. But a school-level aggregate production function provides much weaker evidence of causal effects, suggesting that successful advisors attract students likely to succeed-without necessarily boosting their students' chances of success. Evidence for causal effects is strongest for a measure of advisors' own research output. Aggregate student research output appears to scale linearly with graduate student enrollment, with no evidence of negative class-size effects. An analysis of gender differences in research output shows male and female graduate students to be equally productive in the first few years post-PhD, but female productivity peaks sooner than male productivity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01533v5</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joshua Angrist, Marc Diederichs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>When Do Voters Stop Caring? Estimating the Shape of Voter Utility Function</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03196v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we address a longstanding puzzle over the functional form that better approximates voter's political utility. Though it has become the norm in the literature to represent the voters' political utility with concave loss functions, for decades scholars have underscored this assumption's potential shortcomings. Yet there exists little to no evidence to support one functional form assumption over another. We fill this gap by first identifying electoral settings where the different functional forms generate divergent predictions about voter behavior. Then, we assess which functional form better matches observed voter and abstention behavior using Cast Vote Record (CVR) data that captures the anonymized ballots of millions of voters in the 2020 U.S. general election. Our findings indicate that concave loss functions fail to predict voting and abstention behavior and it is the reverse S-shaped loss functions, such as the Gaussian function, that better match the observed voter behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03196v2</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aleksandra Conevska, Can Mutlu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capitalizing on a Crisis: A Computational Analysis of all Five Million British Firms During the Covid-19 Pandemic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09383</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09383v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The Covid-19 pandemic brought unprecedented changes to business ownership in the UK which affects a generation of entrepreneurs and their employees. Nonetheless, the impact remains poorly understood. This is because research on capital accumulation has typically lacked high-quality, individualized, population-level data. We overcome these barriers to examine who benefits from economic crises through a computationally orientated lens of firm creation. Leveraging a comprehensive cache of administrative data on every UK firm and all nine million people running them, combined with probabilistic algorithms, we conduct individual-level analyses to understand who became Covid entrepreneurs. Using these techniques, we explore characteristics of entrepreneurs--such as age, gender, region, business experience, and industry--which potentially predict Covid entrepreneurship. By employing an automated time series model selection procedure to generate counterfactuals, we show that Covid entrepreneurs were typically aged 35-49 (40.4%), men (73.1%), and had previously held roles in existing firms (59.4%). For most industries, growth was disproportionately concentrated around London. It was therefore existing corporate elites who were most able to capitalize on the Covid crisis and not, as some hypothesized, young entrepreneurs who were setting up their first businesses. In this respect, the pandemic will likely impact future wealth inequalities. Our work offers methodological guidance for future policymakers during economic crises and highlights the long-term consequences for capital and wealth inequality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09383v2</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s42001-025-00360-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Computational Social Science, 8(2), 1-29 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Naomi Muggleton, Charles Rahal, Aaron Reeves</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
