<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA</link>
    <description>math.OA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2024 02:55:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Duality, extreme points and hulls for noncommutative partial convexity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13267v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This article studies generalizations of (matrix) convexity, including partial convexity and biconvexity, under the umbrella of $\Gamma$-convexity. Here $\Gamma$ is a tuple of free symmetric polynomials determining the geometry of a $\Gamma$-convex set. The paper introduces the notions of $\Gamma$-operator systems and $\Gamma$-ucp maps and establishes a Webster-Winkler type categorical duality between $\Gamma$-operator systems and $\Gamma$-convex sets. Next, a notion of an extreme point for $\Gamma$-convex sets is defined, paralleling the concept of a free extreme point for a matrix convex set. To ensure the existence of such points, the matricial sets considered are extended to include an operator level. It is shown that the $\Gamma$-extreme points of an operator $\Gamma$-convex set $K$ are in correspondence with the free extreme points of the operator convex hull of $\Gamma(K).$ From this result, a Krein-Milman theorem for $\Gamma$-convex sets follows. Finally, relying on the results of Helton and the first two authors, a construction of an approximation scheme for the $\Gamma$-convex hull of the matricial positivity domain {(also known as a free semialgebraic set)} $D_p$ of a free symmetric polynomial $p$ is given. The approximation consists of a decreasing family of $\Gamma$-analogs of free spectrahedra, whose projections, under mild assumptions, in the limit yield the $\Gamma$-convex hull of $D_p.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13267v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Igor Klep, Scott McCullough, Tea \v{S}trekelj</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notions of entropy for unitary representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13751</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13751v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the last twenty years, Lewis Bowen's sofic entropy and its annealed version (originally called the `f-invariant') have taken a central place in the ergodic theory of actions of non-amenable groups. In this work we pursue these notions of entropy across the analogy between ergodic theory and representation theory. We arrive at new quantities associated to unitary representations of groups and representations of other C*-algebras. We find connections to both classical constructs in operator theory and the study of tuples of independent random unitary matrices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13751v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.SP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Austin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The $C^*$-algebras of completely solvable Lie groups are solvable</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13923</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13923v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove that if a connected and simply connected Lie group $G$ admits connected closed normal subgroups $G_1\subseteq G_2\subseteq \cdots \subseteq G_m=G$ with $\dim G_j=j$ for $j=1,\dots,m$, then its group $C^*$-algebra has closed two-sided ideals $\{0\}=\mathcal{J}_0\subseteq \mathcal{J}_1\subseteq\cdots\subseteq\mathcal{J}_n=C^*(G)$ with $\mathcal{J}_j/\mathcal{J}_{j-1}\simeq \mathcal{C}_0(\Gamma_j,\mathcal{K}(\mathcal{H}_j))$ for a suitable locally compact Hausdorff space $\Gamma_j$ and a separable complex Hilbert space $\mathcal{H}_j$, where $\mathcal{C}_0(\Gamma_j,\cdot)$ denotes the continuous mappings on $\Gamma_j$ that vanish at infinity, and $\mathcal{K}(\mathcal{H}_j)$ is the $C^*$-algebra of compact operators on $\mathcal{H}_j$ for $j=1,\dots,n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13923v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ingrid Beltita, Daniel Beltita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Random permutations acting on $k$--tuples have near--optimal spectral gap for $k=\mathrm{poly}(n)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.13941</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.13941v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend Friedman's theorem to show that, for any fixed $r$, the random $2r$--regular Schreier graphs depicting the action of $r$ random permutations of $[n]$ on $k_{n}$--tuples of distinct elements in $[n]$ are a.a.s. weakly Ramanujan, for any $k_{n}\leq n^{\frac{1}{12}-\epsilon}.$ Previously this was known only for $k$--tuples where $k$ is fixed. In fact, we prove the stronger result of strong convergence of random matrices in irreducible representations of $S_{n}$ of quasi--exponential dimension.
  We also give a new bound for the expected stable irreducible character of a random permutation obtained via a word map, showing that $\mathbb{E}\left[\chi^{\mu}\left(w(\sigma_{1},\dots,\sigma_{r})\right)\right]=O\left(n^{-k}\right)$, where $k$ is the number of boxes outside the first row of the Young diagram $\mu,$ solving one aspect of a conjecture of Hanany and Puder. We obtain this bound using an extension of Wise's $w$--cycle conjecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.13941v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ewan Cassidy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free Integral Calculus I</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.04039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.04039v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the problem of conditional expectations in free random variables and provide closed formulas for the conditional expectation of resolvents of arbitrary non-commutative polynomials in free random variables onto the subalgebra of an arbitray subset of the variables. More precisely, given a linearization of the resolvent we compute a linearization of its conditional expectation. The coefficients of the expressions obtained in this process involve certain Boolean cumulant functionals which can be computed by solving a system of equations. On the way towards the main result we introduce a non-commutative differential calculus which allows to evaluate conditional expectations and the said Boolean cumulant functionals. We conclude the paper with several known and new examples which illustrate the working of the developed machinery and two appendices. The first appendix contains a purely algebraic approach to Boolean cumulants and the second appendix provides a crash course on linearizations of rational series.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.04039v4</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Franz Lehner, Kamil Szpojankowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Crystallization of C*-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.08665</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.08665v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a C$^*$-algebra $A$ with an almost periodic time evolution $\sigma$, we define a new C$^*$-algebra $A_c$, which we call the crystal of $(A,\sigma)$, that represents the zero temperature limit of $(A, \sigma)$. We prove that there is a one-to-one correspondence between the ground states of $(A,\sigma)$ and the states on $A_c$, justifying the name. In order to investigate further the relation between low temperature equilibrium states on $A$ and traces on $A_c$, we define a Fock module $\mathcal F$ over the crystal and construct a vacuum representation of $A$ on $\mathcal F$. This allows us to show, under relatively mild assumptions, that for sufficiently large inverse temperatures $\beta$ the $\sigma$-KMS$_\beta$-states on $A$ are induced from traces on $A_c$ by means of the Fock module. In the second part, we compare the K-theoretic structures of $A$ and $A_c$. Previous work by various authors suggests that they have (rationally) isomorphic K-groups. We analyze this phenomenon in detail, confirming it under favorable conditions, but showing that, in general, there is apparently no easy way to relate these groups. As examples, we discuss in particular Exel's results on semi-saturated circle actions, and recent results of Miller on the K-theory of inverse semigroup C$^*$-algebras. In relation to the latter, we introduce the notion of a scale $N$ on an inverse semigroup $I$ and define a new inverse semigroup $I_c$, which we call the crystal of $(I,N)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.08665v4</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcelo Laca, Sergey Neshveyev, Makoto Yamashita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Trace spaces of full free product $C^*$-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15985v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the space of traces associated with arbitrary full free products of unital, separable $C^*$-algebras. We show that, unless certain basic obstructions (which we fully characterize) occur, the space of traces always results in the same object: the Poulsen simplex, that is, the unique infinite-dimensional metrizable Choquet simplex whose extreme points are dense. Moreover, we show that whenever such a trace space is the Poulsen simplex, the extreme points are dense in the Wasserstein topology. Concretely for the case of groups, we find that, unless the trivial character is isolated in the space of characters, the space of traces of any free product of non-trivial countable groups is the Poulsen simplex. Our main technical contribution is a new perturbation result for pairs of von Neumann subalgebras $(M_{1},M_{2})$ of a tracial von Neumann algebra $M$, providing necessary conditions under which $M_{1}$ and a small unitary perturbation of $M_{2}$ generate a II$_{1}$ factor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15985v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Ioana, Pieter Spaas, Itamar Vigdorovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
