<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA</link>
    <description>math.OA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Oct 2024 02:25:15 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Elementary equivalence and disintegration of tracial von Neumann algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05529v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We prove an analog of the disintegration theorem for tracial von Neumann algebras in the setting of elementary equivalence rather than isomorphism, showing that elementary equivalence of two direct integrals implies fiberwise elementary equivalence under mild, and necessary, hypotheses. This verifies a conjecture of Farah and Ghasemi. Our argument uses a continuous analog of ultraproducts where an ultrafilter on a discrete index set is replaced by a character on a commutative von Neumann algebra, which is closely related to Keisler randomizations of metric structures. We extend several essential results on ultraproducts, such as {\L}o\'s's theorem and countable saturation, to this more general setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05529v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.LO</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Gao, David Jekel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diagonal comparison of ample C*-diagonals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05967</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05967v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce diagonal comparison, a regularity property of diagonal pairs where the sub-C*-algebra has totally disconnected spectrum, and establish its equivalence with the concurrence of strict comparison of the ambient C*-algebra and dynamical comparison of the underlying dynamics induced by the partial action of the normalisers. As an application, we show that for diagonal pairs arising from principal minimal transformation groupoids with totally disconnected unit space, diagonal comparison is equivalent to tracial Z-stability of the pair and that it is implied by finite diagonal dimension.
  In-between, we show that any projection of the diagonal sub-C*-algebra can be uniformly tracially divided, and explore a property of conditional expectations onto abelian sub-C*-algebras, namely containment of every positive element in the hereditary subalgebra generated by its conditional expectation. We show that the expectation associated to a C*-pair with finite diagonal dimension is always hereditary in that sense, and we give an example where this property does not occur.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05967v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grigoris Kopsacheilis, Wilhelm Winter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncommutative spherical maximal inequality associated with automorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we establish a noncommutative spherical maximal inequality associated with automorphisms on von Neumann algebras, extending Magyar-Stein-Wainger's discrete spherical maximal inequality to the noncommutative setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06035v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cheng Chen, Guixiang Hong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non Kahzdan's groups and a new approximation property for tracial von Neumann algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06579v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define a new approximation property for tracial von Neumann algebras, called \textit{weakly mixing approximation property}, and we prove that it is equivalent to the negation of Kazhdan's Property (T) for discrete groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06579v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Jolissaint</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Skein Theory for Affine A Subfactor Planar Algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.05519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.05519v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Kuperberg Program asks to find presentations of planar algebras and use these presentations to prove results about their corresponding categories purely diagrammatically. This program has been completed for index less than 4 and is ongoing research for index greater than 4. We give generators-and-relations presentations for the affine A subfactor planar algebras of index 4. Exclusively using the planar algebra language, we give new proofs to how many such planar algebras exist. Categories corresponding to these planar algebras are monoidally equivalent to cyclic pointed fusion categories. We give a proof of this by defining a functor yielding a monoidal equivalence between the two categories. The categories are also monoidally equivalent to a representation category of a cyclic subgroup of SU(2). We give a new proof of this fact, explicitly using the diagrammatic presentations found. This gives novel diagrammatics for these representation categories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.05519v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Melody Molander</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Units of $\mathbb{Z}/p\mathbb{Z}$-equivariant $K$-theory and bundles of UHF-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06947</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06947v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We consider infinite tensor product actions of $G = \mathbb{Z}/p\mathbb{Z}$ on the UHF-algebra $D = \text{End}(V)^{\otimes \infty}$ for a finite-dimensional unitary $G$-representation $V$ and determine the equivariant homotopy type of the group $\text{Aut}(D \otimes \mathbb{K})$, where $\mathbb{K}$ are the compact operators on $\ell^2(G) \otimes H_0$ for a separable Hilbert space $H_0$ with $\dim(H_0) = \infty$. We show that this group carries an equivariant infinite loop space structure revealing it as the first space of a naive $G$-spectrum, which we prove to be equivalent to the positive units $gl_1(KU^D)_+$ of equivariant $KU^D$-theory. Here, $KU^D$ is a $G$-spectrum representing $X \mapsto K_*^G(C(X) \otimes D)$. As a consequence the first group of the cohomology theory associated to $gl_1(KU^D)_+$ classifies equivariant $D \otimes \mathbb{K}$-bundles over finite CW-complexes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06947v1</guid>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Valerio Bianchi, Ulrich Pennig</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unitarity and strong graded locality of holomorphic vertex operator superalgebras with central charge at most 24</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove that all nice holomorphic vertex operator superalgebras (VOSAs) with central charge at most 24 and with non-trivial odd part are unitary, apart from the hypothetical ones arising as fake copies of the shorter moonshine VOSA or of the latter tensorized with a real free fermion VOSA. Furthermore, excluding the ones with central charge 24 of glueing type III and with no real free fermion, we show that they are all strongly graded-local. In particular, they naturally give rise to holomorphic graded-local conformal nets. In total, we are able to prove that 910 of the 969 nice holomorphic VOSAs with central charge 24 and with non-trivial odd part are strongly graded-local, without counting hypothetical fake copies of the shorter moonshine VOSA tensorized with a real free fermion VOSA.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07099v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiziano Gaudio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximate representability of finite abelian group actions on the Razak-Jacelon algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2302.10550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2302.10550v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $A$ be a simple separable nuclear monotracial C$^*$-algebra, and let $\alpha$ be an outer action of a finite abelian group $\Gamma$ on $A$. In this paper, we show that $\alpha\otimes \mathrm{id}_{\mathcal{W}}$ on $A\otimes\mathcal{W}$ is approximately representable if and only if the characteristic invariant of $\tilde{\alpha}$ is trivial, where $\mathcal{W}$ is the Razak-Jacelon algebra and $\tilde{\alpha}$ is the induced action on the injective II$_1$ factor $\pi_{\tau_{A}}(A)^{''}$. As an application of this result, we classify such actions up to conjugacy and cocycle conjugacy. In particular, we show the following: Let $A$ and $B$ be simple separable nuclear monotracial C$^*$-algebras, and let $\alpha$ and $\beta$ be outer actions of a finite abelian group $\Gamma$ on $A$ and $B$, respectively. Assume that the characteristic invariants of $\tilde{\alpha}$ and $\tilde{\beta}$ are trivial. Then $\alpha\otimes \mathrm{id}_{\mathcal{W}}$ and $\beta\otimes \mathrm{id}_{\mathcal{W}}$ are conjugate (resp. cocycle conjugate) if and only if $\tilde{\alpha}$ on $\pi_{\tau_{A}}(A)^{''}$ and $\tilde{\beta}$ on $\pi_{\tau_{B}}(B)^{''}$ are conjugate (resp. cocycle conjugate). We also construct the model actions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2302.10550v4</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Norio Nawata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuclearity and CPC*-systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.01332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.01332v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We write arbitrary separable nuclear C*-algebras as limits of inductive systems of finite-dimensional C*-algebras with completely positive connecting maps. The characteristic feature of such CPC*-systems is that the maps become more and more orthogonality preserving. This condition makes it possible to equip the limit, a priori only an operator space, with a multiplication turning it into a C*-algebra. Our concept generalizes the NF systems of Blackadar and Kirchberg beyond the quasidiagonal case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.01332v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kristin Courtney, Wilhelm Winter</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General solidity phenomena and anticoarse spaces for type $\mathrm{III}_1$ factors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.18106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.18106v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: By developing a theory of anticoarse spaces in the purely infinite setting and using 1-bounded entropy techniques along with recent strong convergence results in random matrix theory, we show that free Araki--Woods factors offer the first examples of type $\mathrm{III}$ factors satisfying vastly general degrees of indecomposability phenomena. Notably this includes strong solidity with respect to any weakening of the normalizer currently in the literature and the Peterson--Thom property.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.18106v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ben Hayes (with an appendix by Stefaan Vaes), David Jekel (with an appendix by Stefaan Vaes), Srivatsav Kunnawalkam Elayavalli (with an appendix by Stefaan Vaes), Brent Nelson (with an appendix by Stefaan Vaes)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local Hilbert--Schmidt stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.13155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.13155v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We introduce a notion of local Hilbert--Schmidt stability, motivated by the recent definition by Bradford of local permutation stability, and give examples of (non-residually finite) groups that are locally Hilbert--Schmidt stable but not Hilbert--Schmidt stable. For amenable groups, we provide a criterion for local Hilbert--Schmidt stability in terms of group characters, by analogy with the character criterion of Hadwin and Shulman for Hilbert--Schmidt stable amenable groups. Furthermore, we study the (very) flexible analogues of local Hilbert--Schmidt stability, and we prove several results analogous to the classical setting. Finally, we prove that infinite sofic, respectively hyperlinear, property (T) groups are never locally permutation stable, respectively locally Hilbert--Schmidt stable. This strengthens the result of Becker and Lubotzky for classical stability, and answers a question of Lubotzky.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.13155v2</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Fournier-Facio, Maria Gerasimova, Pieter Spaas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rings of almost everywhere defined functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.13063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.13063v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The following representation theorem is proven: A partially ordered commutative ring $R$ is a subring of a ring of almost everywhere defined continuous real-valued functions on a compact Hausdorff space $X$ if and only if $R$ is archimedean and localizable. Here we assume that the positive cone of $R$ is closed under multiplication and stable under multiplication with squares, but actually one of these assumptions implies the other. An almost everywhere defined function on $X$ is one that is defined on a dense open subset of $X$. A partially ordered commutative ring $R$ is archimedean if the underlying additive partially ordered abelian group is archimedean, and $R$ is localizable essentially if its order is compatible with the construction of a localization with sufficiently large, positive denominators. As applications we discuss the $\sigma$-bounded case, lattice-ordered commutative rings ($f$-rings), partially ordered fields, and commutative operator algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.13063v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Sch\"otz</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
