<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA</link>
    <description>math.OA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 01:40:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 01 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Non-linear classification of finite-dimensional simple $C^*$-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21582v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A Banach space characterization of simple real or complex $C^*$-algebras is given which even characterizes the underlying field. As an application, it is shown that if $\mathfrak A_1$ and $\mathfrak A_2$ are Birkhoff-James isomorphic simple $C^*$-algebras over the fields $\mathbb F_1$ and $\mathbb F_2$, respectively and if $\mathfrak A_1$ is finite-dimensional with dimension greater than one, then $\mathbb F_1=\mathbb F_2$ and $\mathfrak A_1$ and $\mathfrak A_2$ are (isometrically) $\ast$-isomorphic $C^*$-algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21582v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bojan Kuzma, Sushil Singla</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reflection positivity and its relation to disc, half plane and the strip</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21123</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21123v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We develop a novel perspective on reflection positivity (RP) on the strip by systematically developing the analogies with the unit disc and the upper half plane in the complex plane. These domains correspond to the three conjugacy classes of one-parameter groups in the M\"obius group (elliptic for the disc, parabolic for the upper half plane and hyperbolic for the strip). In all cases, reflection positive functions correspond to positive functionals on $H^\infty$ for a suitable involution. For the strip, reflection positivity naturally connects with Kubo--Martin--Schwinger (KMS) conditions on the real line and further to standard pairs, as they appear in Algebraic Quantum Field Theory. We also exhibit a curious connection between Hilbert spaces on the strip and the upper half plane, based on a periodization process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21123v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maria Stella Adamo, Karl-Hermann Neeb, Jonas Schober</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral theorems for positive algebra homomorphisms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.10690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2109.10690v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $X$ be a locally compact Hausdorff space, let $A$ be a partially ordered algebra, and let $\pi\colon \mathrm{C}_{\mathrm c}(X)\to A$ be a positive algebra homomorphism. Under conditions on $A$ that are satisfied in a good number of cases of practical interest, it is shown that $\pi$ is represented by a unique regular spectral measure $\mu$ on the Borel $\sigma$-algebra of $X$, taking its values in the positive idempotents in $A$. The measure $\mu$, which is $\sigma$-additive in an ordered sense, represents $\pi$ via the order integral (a generalisation of the Lebesgue integral) that goes back to J.D.M. Wright and which was investigated earlier by the authors.
  The positive algebra homomorphism $\pi$ can be extended from $\mathrm{C}_{\mathrm c}(X)$ to a positive linear map from the accompanying $L^1$-space of $\mu$ into $A$. It is shown that, quite often, this $L^1$-space is closed under multiplication, so that it is a vector lattice algebra, and that the extended map from $L^1$ into $A$ is not only an algebra homomorphism but, even when $A$ is not a vector lattice, also a vector lattice homomorphism in a sense that is explained in the paper. When $ A$ has the countable sup property, the image of $L^1$ (or of its positive cone) is described in terms of consecutive ups and downs of the image of ${\mathrm C}_{\mathrm c}(X)$ (or of its positive cone).
  The general results are applied in three different contexts, showing how various spectral theorems have a common order-theoretical root: representations on Banach lattices, on Hilbert spaces, and (the algebra need not consist of operators) spectral theory for JBW-algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2109.10690v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marcel de Jeu, Xingni Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proof of Audenaert-Kittaneh's Conjecture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.05456</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.05456v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By using the Three-lines theorem for a certain analytic function defined in terms of the trace and a duality argument method, we prove Audenaert-Kittaneh's conjecture related to $p$-Schatten classes. This generalizes the main result obtained by McCarthy in [Israel J. Math. 5 (1967)].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.05456v3</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Israel J. Math. 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Teng Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
