<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA</link>
    <description>math.OA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Oct 2025 01:43:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On ergodicity of linear actions on $\mathbb{R}^n$ and factoriality of group von Neumann algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23864v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give some natural conditions on actions of discrete countable groups on abelian locally compact groups of Lie type that imply factoriality of the group von Neumann algebras of their semidirect products. This allows us to give a fairly large class of examples of locally compact groups whose group von Neumann algebras are factors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23864v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soham Chakraborty, Chinmay Tamhankar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral-Geometric Deformations of Function Algebras on Manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24184</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24184v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a novel method for deforming the algebra of smooth functions on a compact Riemannian manifold based on spectral data rather than group actions or Poisson structures. The deformation is defined through spectral coefficients of the Laplacian and a weight function satisfying a fusion-type cocycle condition, producing a noncommutative product that depends intrinsically on Laplacian spectrum of the manifold. We develop the analytic and algebraic foundations of this construction, establishing associativity, continuity, and the existence of a group structure on admissible weights. We show that the construction is functorial with respect to spectrum-preserving maps of manifolds. This spectral-geometric deformation quantization approach provides a fully intrinsic analytic model of noncommutative geometry based solely on spectral data of the manifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24184v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amandip Sangha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On preservers of strong Birkhoff-James orthogonality between $C^*$-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24308</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24308v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It is shown that every linear strong Birkhoff-James isomorphism between unital $C^*$-algebras is a $*$-isomorphism followed by a unitary multiplication. Moreover, as a partial extension of this result to the non-unital case, the form of (possibly nonlinear) strong Birkhoff-James isomorphisms between compact $C^*$-algebras are determined. A nonlinear characterization of compact $C^*$-algebras in terms of strong Birkhoff-James orthogonality is also given.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24308v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bojan Kuzma, Srdjan Stefanovi\'c, Ryotaro Tanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the embeddings of selfadjoint operator spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24326</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24326v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate when a map on a selfadjoint operator space $E$ is an embedding, i.e., when its unitisation in the sense of Werner is completely isometric. Combining with results of Russell, of Ng, and of Dessi, the second and the last author, it is shown that this is equivalent to: (a) extending bounded positive functionals on each matrix level with the same norm; (b) extending quasistates to quasistates in each matrix level; (c) extending completely bounded completely positive maps with the same cb-norm; and (d) the map being a gauge maximal isometry in the sense of Russell. If $E$ is approximately positively generated and $\mathrm{C}^*(E)$ is unital, or if $E_{sa}$ is singly generated, then completely positive maps on $E\subseteq\mathcal{B}(H)$ have completely positive extensions on $\mathrm{C}^*(E)$, but possibly not with the same cb-norm; and this is not enough for the inclusion $E \subseteq \mathrm{C}^*(E)$ to be an embedding. We show that the inclusion $E \subseteq \mathrm{C}^*(E)$ is always an embedding when $E$ is completely approximately 1-generated, and we fully resolve the case when $E_{sa}$ is singly generated. Combining with the works of Salomon, Humeniuk--Kennedy--Manor, and previous work of the third author, we show that if the inclusion $E \subseteq \mathrm{C}^*(E)$ is an embedding, then rigidity at zero, in the sense of Salomon, coincides with $E$ being approximately positively generated. Consequently, we show that $E$ is approximately positively generated if and only if $M_n(E)$ is approximately positively generated for all $n\in \mathbb{N}$, thus extending a previous result of Humeniuk--Kennedy--Manor to the approximation setting. As an application we show that hyperrigidity of $E$ in $\mathrm{C}^*(E)$ allows to identify $\mathrm{C}^*(E)$ as the C*-envelope of $E$ in several (non-unital) contexts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24326v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexandros Chatzinikolaou, Evgenios T. A. Kakariadis, Se-Jin Kim, Ioannis Apollon Paraskevas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Injective envelopes of $C^*$-algebras as maximal rigid multiplier covers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24441v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a noncommutative analogue of B{\l}aszczyk's elegant two-step construction of the Gleason cover: \emph{first maximise irreducibility, then compactify}. The key insight is that extremal disconnectedness emerges naturally from a maximality principle rather than being imposed by hand.
  Fixing a faithful embedding of a $C^*$-algebra $A$ into a product $\prod_i \mathcal B(H_i)$ of concrete factors, we introduce the notion of \emph{$A$-carrier ideals}: closed two-sided ideals $J\lhd \prod_i \mathcal B(H_i)$ generated by $A$ as a~bimodule and show via the Kuratowski--Zorn lemma that there exists a \emph{maximal $A$-irreducible} such ideal $J_{\max}$. Here irreducibility means that no proper quotient of $J_{\max}$ allows $A$ to embed completely isometrically into its multiplier algebra. We prove that the canonical inclusion $A\hookrightarrow M(J_{\max})$ is both \emph{rigid} (any completely positive map fixing $A$ is the identity) and \emph{essential} (no non-trivial quotient preserves $A$ isometrically), the two defining properties of Hamana's injective envelope. This yields the identification \[ I(A)\ \cong\ M(J_{\max}) \] canonically over $A$, realising the injective envelope as a single multiplier algebra. In the commutative case $A=C(X)$ we recover B{\l}aszczyk's picture: starting from a maximal regular refinement $(X,T^\ast)$ with irreducible identity map, the Gleason space is $G(X)=\beta(X,T^\ast)$ and $I(C(X))\cong C(G(X))\cong M(C_0(U))$ for any dense open $U\subseteq G(X)$. The paradigm \emph{maximise first, then compactify} thus provides a unified conceptual framework for both the topological and operator-algebraic versions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24441v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.GN</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomasz Kania</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncommutative BKW-Operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24470</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24470v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by the classical Bohman-Korovkin-Wulbert (BKW) operators, we initiate a study of noncommutative BKW-operators. Let $A$ be a unital $C^*$-algebra, and $S$ be a set of generators of $A$. A unital completely positive (UCP)-map $\phi: A\rightarrow B(H)$ is said to be a \textit{noncommutative BKW-operator} for $S$ with respect to norm or weak operator topology (WOT) or strong operator topology (SOT) if for any sequence of UCP-maps $\phi_n:A\rightarrow B(H)$, $n=1,2,...,$ $\lim_{n\rightarrow \infty}\phi_n(s)=\phi(s),\forall ~s\in S$ in norm (or WOT or SOT) $\Rightarrow \lim_{n\rightarrow \infty}\phi_n(a)=\phi(a), \forall ~a\in A$ in norm (or WOT or SOT, respectively). We identify a connection between noncommutative BKW-operators and the unique CP-extension of UCP-maps. We have discussed several examples and explored different notions of noncommutative BKW-operators and their interconnections. Additionally, we introduce the concept of hyperrigidity with respect to a UCP-map and characterize it along the lines of Arveson. Although independent yet related to noncommutative BKW-operators, we provide a noncommutative version of operator version of the Korovkin theorem recently proposed by D. Popa.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24470v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arunkumar C. S.,  Sruthymurali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Selfless Reduced Free Products and Graph Products of $\mathrm{C}^\ast$-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24675v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Under mild assumptions, we prove that reduced free products and reduced graph products of $\mathrm{C}^\ast$-algebras are selfless in the sense of L. Robert, without assuming the rapid decay property. In particular, our main theorems yield numerous new examples of simple, monotracial $\mathrm{C}^\ast$-algebras with strict comparison, stable rank one, and admitting a unique unital embedding of the Jiang-Su algebra $\mathcal{Z}$ up to approximate unitary equivalence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24675v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Felipe Flores, Mario Klisse, M\'iche\'al \'O Cobhthaigh, Matteo Pagliero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Derivations of Tensor Products of Perm Algebras and Associative Algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23613v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The study of derivations and their generalizations on non-associative algebras has proven to be fundamental in understanding the internal symmetries and algebraic dynamics of such structures. In this paper, we investigate derivations and diderivations of tensor product dialgebras arising from the combination of a perm algebra and a unital associative algebra. We provide decomposition theorems that characterize these operators in terms of derivations of the individual factors and suitable multiplication maps. Explicit coordinate formulas are also derived, allowing concrete descriptions of the action of derivations and diderivations with respect to natural bases. These results extend classical decomposition theorems for tensor products beyond the associative setting, highlighting the interplay between perm algebras and non-associative algebraic frameworks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23613v1</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Gregorio Rodr\'iguez-Nieto, Olga Patricia Salazar-D\'iaz, Andr\'es Sarrazola-Alzate, Ra\'ul Vel\'asquez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing extreme singular values of free operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23987v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A recent development in random matrix theory, the intrinsic freeness principle, establishes that the spectrum of very general random matrices behaves as that of an associated free operator. This reduces the study of such random matrices to the deterministic problem of computing spectral statistics of the free operator. In the self-adjoint case, the spectral edges of the free operator can be computed exactly by means of a variational formula due to Lehner. In this note, we provide variational formulas for the largest and smallest singular values in the non-self-adjoint case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23987v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Emre Parmaksiz, Ramon van Handel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tracial approximation and ${\cal Z}$-stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.04013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.04013v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $A$ be a unital separable non-elementary amenable simple stably finite C*-algebra such that its tracial state space has a $\sigma$-compact countable-dimensional extremal boundary. We show that $A$ is ${\cal Z}$-stable if and only if it has strict comparison and stable rank one. We show that this result also holds for non-unital cases (which may not be Morita equivalent to unital ones).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.04013v3</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huaxin Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
