<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA</link>
    <description>math.OA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Structural properties of reduced $C^*$-algebras associated with higher-rank lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12737v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present the first examples of higher-rank lattices whose reduced $C^{*}$-algebras satisfy strict comparison, stable rank one, selflessness, uniqueness of embeddings of the Jiang--Su algebra, and allow explicit computations of the Cuntz semigroup. This resolves a question raised in recent groundbreaking work of Amrutam, Gao, Kunnawalkam Elayavalli, and Patchell, in which they exhibited a large class of finitely generated non-amenable groups satisfying these properties. Our proof relies on quantitative estimates in projective dynamics, crucially using the exponential mixing for diagonalizable flows. As a result, we obtain an effective mixed-identity-freeness property, which, combined with V. Lafforgue's rapid decay theorem, yields the desired conclusions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12737v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Itamar Vigdorovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>W$^*$-superrigidity for property (T) groups with infinite center</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12742</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12742v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose for study a natural version of Connes' Rigidity Conjecture (1980) that involves property (T) groups with infinite center. Using methods at the rich intersection between von Neumann algebras and geometric group theory, we identify several instances where this conjecture holds. Notably, we also generalize the main W$^*$-superrigidity result from [CIOS21] to the category of twisted group factors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12742v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ionu\c{t} Chifan, Adriana Fern\'andez Quero, Denis Osin, Hui Tan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parabolic noncommutative geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12938v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce to spectral noncommutative geometry the notion of tangled spectral triple, which encompasses the anisotropies arising in parabolic geometry as well as the parabolic commutator bounds arising in so-called ``bad Kasparov products''. Tangled spectral triples incorporate anisotropy by replacing the unbounded operator in a spectral triple that mimics a Dirac operator with several unbounded operators mimicking directional Dirac operators. We allow for varying and dependent orders in different directions, controlled by using the tools of tropical combinatorics. We study the conformal equivariance of tangled spectral triples as well as how they fit into $K$-homology by means of producing higher order spectral triples. Our main examples are hypoelliptic spectral triples constructed from Rockland complexes on parabolic geometries; we also build spectral triples on nilpotent group $C^*$-algebras from the dual Dirac element and crossed product spectral triples for parabolic dynamical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12938v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Magnus Fries, Magnus Goffeng, Ada Masters</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Groupoids, equivalence bibundles and bimodules for noncommutative solenoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13251v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Let $p$ be a prime number and $\mathcal{S}_p$ the $p$-solenoid. For $\alpha\in \mathbb{R}\times \mathbb{Q}_p$ we consider in this paper a naturally associated action groupoid $S_\alpha:=\mathbb{Z} [1/p]\ltimes_\alpha \mathcal{S}_p \rightrightarrows \mathcal{S}_p$ whose $C^*-$algebra is a model for the noncommutative solenoid $\mathcal{A}_\alpha^\mathscr{S}$ studied by Latremoli\`ere and Packer. Following the geometric ideas of Connes and Rieffel to describe the Morita equivalences of noncommutative torus using the Kronecker foliation on the torus, we give an explicit description of the geometric/topologic equivalence bibundle for groupoids $S_\alpha$ and $S_\beta$ whenever $\alpha,\beta\in \mathbb{R}\times \mathbb{Q}_p$ are in the same orbit of the $GL_2(\mathbb{Z}[1/p])$ action by linear fractional transformations. As a corollary, for $\alpha,\beta\in \mathbb{R}\times \mathbb{Q}_p$ as above we get an explicit description of the imprimitivity bimodules for the associated noncommutative solenoids.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13251v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paulo Carrillo Rouse, Laurent Guillaume</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A noncommutative generalization of Hunter's positivity theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12376v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Hunter proved that the complete homogeneous symmetric polynomials of even degree are positive definite. We prove a noncommutative generalization of this result, in which the scalar variables are replaced with hermitian operators. We provide a sharp lower bound and a sum of hermitian squares representation that are novel even in the scalar case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12376v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stephan Ramon Garcia, Jurij Vol\v{c}i\v{c}</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stable homotopy theory of invertible gapped quantum spin systems I: Kitaev's $\Omega$-spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12618</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12618v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We provide a mathematical realization of a proposal by Kitaev, on the basis of the operator-algebraic formulation of infinite quantum spin systems. Our main results are threefold. First, we construct an $\Omega$-spectrum $\mathit{IP}_*$ whose homotopy groups are isomorphic to the smooth homotopy group of invertible gapped quantum systems on Euclidean spaces. Second, we develop a model for the homology theory associated with the $\Omega$-spectrum $\mathit{IP}_*$, describing it in terms of the space of quantum systems placed on an arbitrary subspace of a Euclidean space. This involves introducing the concept of localization flow, a semi-infinite path of quantum systems with decaying interaction range, inspired by Yu's localization C*-algebra in coarse index theory. Third, we incorporate spatial symmetries given by a crystallographic group $\Gamma $ and define the $\Omega$-spectrum $\mathit{IP}_*^\Gamma$ of $\Gamma$-invariant invertible phases. We propose a strategy for computing the homotopy group $\pi_n(\mathit{IP}_d^\Gamma )$ that uses the Davis--L\"{u}ck assembly map and its description by invertible gapped localization flow. In particular, we show that the assembly map is split injective, and hence $\pi_n(\mathit{IP}_d^\Gamma)$ contains a computable direct summand.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12618v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>math.AT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yosuke Kubota</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free denoising via overlap measures and c-freeness techniques</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20792v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the problem of free denoising. For free selfadjoint random variables $a,b$, where we interpret $a$ as a signal and $b$ as noise, we find $E(a|a+b)$. To that end, we study a probability measure $\mu^{( \mathrm{ov} )}_{a,a+b}$ on $\mathbb{R}^2$ which we call the overlap measure. We show that $\mu^{( \mathrm{ov} )}_{a,a+b}$ is absolutely continuous with respect to the product measure $\mu_a\times \mu_{a+b}$. The Radon-Nikodym derivative gives direct access to $E(a|a+b)$. We show that analogous results hold in the case of multiplicative noise when $a,b$ are positive and the aim is to find $E(a|a^{1/2}ba^{1/2})$. In a parallel development we show that, for a general selfadjoint expression $P(a,b)$ made with $a$ and $b$, finding $E(a|P(a,b))$ is equivalent to finding the distribution of $P(a,b)$ in a certain two-state probability space $(\mathcal{A},\varphi,\chi)$, where $a,b$ are c-free with respect to $(\varphi,\chi)$ in the sense of Bo\.zejko-Leinert-Speicher. We discuss how free denoising (which is set in the framework of an abstract $W^{*}$-probability space) relates to the notion of ''matrix denoising'' previously discussed in the random matrix literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20792v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maxime Fevrier, Alexandru Nica, Kamil Szpojankowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Classification of ITPFI factors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.10807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.10807v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we prove precise descriptions for each of type-$III_0$, type-$III_{\lambda}$ and type-$III_1$ ITPFI factors based on their asymptotic ratio set.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.10807v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tianyi Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Involutive Markov categories and the quantum de Finetti theorem</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.09666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.09666v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Markov categories have recently emerged as a powerful high-level framework for probability theory and theoretical statistics. Here we study a quantum version of this concept, called involutive Markov categories. These are equivalent to Parzygnat's quantum Markov categories, but we argue that they offer a simpler and more practical approach. Our main examples of involutive Markov categories have pre-C*-algebras, including infinite-dimensional ones, as objects, together with completely positive unital maps as morphisms in the picture of interest. In this context, we prove a quantum de Finetti theorem for both the minimal and the maximal C*-tensor norms, and we develop a categorical description of such quantum de Finetti theorems which amounts to a universal property of state spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.09666v3</guid>
      <category>math.CT</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Fritz, Antonio Lorenzin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The fermionic massless modular Hamiltonian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07888</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07888v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We provide an explicit expression for the modular hamiltonian of the von Neumann algebras associated to the unit double cone for the (fermionic) quantum field theories of the 2-component Weyl (helicity 1/2) field, and of the 4-component massless Dirac and Majorana fields. To this end, we represent the one particle spaces of these theories in terms of solutions of the corresponding wave equations, and obtain the action of the modular group on them. As an application, we compute the relative entropy between the vacuum of the massless Majorana field and one particle states associated to waves with Cauchy data localized in the spatial unit ball.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07888v2</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cs.IT</category>
      <category>math.IT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00220-025-05253-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Communications in Mathematical Physics vol. 406 (2025), n. 81</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Francesca La Piana, Gerardo Morsella</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Banach bimodule-valued positive maps: Inequalities and induced representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.24113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.24113v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider representations induced by general positive and completely positive sesquilinear maps with values in ordered Banach bimodules, such as the space of trace-class operators and the spaces of bounded linear operators from a von Neumann algebra into the dual of another von Neumann algebra. Also, we deduce some new inequalities for these maps.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.24113v5</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giorgia Bellomonte, Stefan Ivkovic, Camillo Trapani</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
