<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA</link>
    <description>math.OA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Apr 2025 01:53:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Robustness of topological phases on aperiodic lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.04817</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.04817v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the robustness of topological phases on aperiodic lattices by constructing *-homomorphisms from the groupoid model to the coarse-geometric model of observable C*-algebras. These *-homomorphisms induce maps in K-theory and Kasparov theory. We show that the strong topological phases in the groupoid model are detected by position spectral triples. We show that topological phases coming from stacking along another Delone set are always weak in the coarse-geometric sense.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.04817v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuezhao Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological full groups arising from Cuntz and Cuntz-Toeplitz algebras and their crossed products</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05145v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the topological full groups arising from the Cuntz and Cuntz-Toeplitz algebras and their crossed products with the Cartan subalgebras of Cuntz and Cuntz-Toeplitz algebras. We study the normal subgroups and abelianization of these groups and completely determine the KMS states of the reduced crossed products with respect to some canonical gauge actions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05145v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryoya Arimoto, Taro Sogabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inclusions of Operator Algebras from Tensor Categories: beyond irreducibility</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.05247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.05247v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We derive faithful inclusions of C*-algebras from a coend-type construction in unitary tensor categories. This gives rise to different potential notions of discreteness for an inclusion in the non-irreducible case, and provides a unified framework that encloses the theory of compact quantum group actions. We also provide examples coming from semi-circular systems and from factorization homology. In the irreducible case, we establish conditions under which the C*-discrete and W*-discrete conditions are equivalent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.05247v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Hataishi, Roberto Hern\'andez Palomares</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Filtered Calculus and crossed products by R-actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.13532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.13532v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show an isomorphism between the kernel of the C*-algebra of the tangent groupoid of a filtered manifold and the crossed product of the order 0 pseudodifferential operators in the associated filtered calculus by a natural R-action. This isomorphism is constructed in the same way as in the classical pseudodifferential calculus by Debord and Skandalis. The proof however relies on a structure result for the C*-algebra of graded nilpotent Lie groups which did not appear in the commutative case. A consequence of this structure result is a decomposition of the principal symbol algebra, generalizing the decomposition of Epstein and Melrose in the case of contact manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.13532v4</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cl\'ement Cren (LAMA)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial models for boolean actions in the infinite measure-preserving setup</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.02401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.02401v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that up to a null set, every infinite measure-preserving action of a locally compact Polish group can be turned into a continuous measure-preserving action on a locally compact Polish space where the underlying measure is Radon. We also investigate the distinction between spatial and boolean actions in the infinite measure-preserving setup. In particular, we extend Kwiatkowska and Solecki's Point Realization Theorem to the infinite measure setup. We finally obtain a streamlined proof of a recent result of Avraham-Re'em and Roy: L\'evy groups cannot admit nontrivial continuous measure-preserving actions on Polish spaces when the measure is locally finite.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.02401v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Apr 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabien Hoareau, Fran\c{c}ois Le Ma\^itre</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
