<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA</link>
    <description>math.OA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 04:00:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Law of large numbers for non-linear traces of the Choquet type on finite factors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22280v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduced non-linear traces of the Choquet type and the Sugeno type on semi-finite factors M in [36] as a non-commutative analog of the Choquet integral and Sugeno integral for non-additive measures. We need a weighted dimension function on the projections of M, which is an analog of a monotone measure. In this paper, we study the law of large numbers for non-linear traces of the Choquet type on finite factors M. Since averages do not converge in general, we study the range of their accumulation points, that is, we estimate their limit supremum and limit infimum. We examine the trials of sequences consisting of self-adjoint operators, which appear in coin toss or Powers' binary shifts. We have also found some unexpected examples of Powers' binary shifts which satisfy what we call the uniform norm law of large numbers. This is an attempt at non-linear and non-commutative probability theory on matrix algebras and factors of type II_1.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22280v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masaru Nagisa, Yasuo Watatani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Approximately Macroscopically Unique States and Quantum Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22692v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that Mumford's Approximately Macroscopically Unique (AMU) states exist for quantum systems consisting of unbounded self-adjoint operators when the commutators are small. In particular, AMU states always exist in position and momentum systems when the Planck constant $|\hbar|$ is sufficiently small. However, we show that these standard quantum mechanical systems are far away from classical mechanical (commutative) systems even when $|\hbar|\to 0.$</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22692v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huaxin Lin, Hang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-local Dirichlet forms, Gibbs measures, and a Hodge theorem for Cantor sets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22742</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22742v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper I study properties of the generators $\triangle_\gamma$ of non-local Dirichlet forms $\mathcal{E}^\mu_\gamma$ on ultrametric spaces which are the path space of simple stationary Bratteli diagrams. The measures used to define the Dirichlet forms are taken to be the Gibbs measures $\mu_\psi$ associated to H\"older continuous potentials $\psi$ for one-sided shifts. I also define a cohomology $H_{lc}(X_B)$ for $X_B$ which can be seen as dual to the homology of Bowen and Franks. Besides studying spectral properties of $\triangle_\gamma$, I show that for $\gamma$ large enough (with sharp bounds depending on the diagram and the measure theoretic entropy $h_{\mu_\psi}$ of $\mu_\psi$) there is a unique harmonic representative of any class $c\in H_{lc}(X_B)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22742v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rodrigo Trevi\~no</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bessel duality of Gabor systems: A von Neumann algebraic perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23575v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Bessel duality of regular Gabor systems states that a Gabor system over a lattice is a Bessel sequence if and only if the corresponding Gabor system over the adjoint lattice is a Bessel sequence. We show that this fundamental result of time-frequency analysis can be deduced from a theorem in the theory of bimodules over von Neumann algebras, namely that under certain conditions, their left and right bounded vectors coincide.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23575v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulrik Enstad, Franz Luef</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some Examples of Bicrossed Products with the Rapid Decay Property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2203.13706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2203.13706v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider bicrossed products obtained by twisting compact semi-direct products by a suitable finite subgroup. Under some restriction, we give a practical criterion for the discrete dual of such bicrossed products to have the rapid decay property (property (RD)). Using this theory, we construct some examples of discrete quantum groups with (RD) but do not grow polynomially. Further examples that do not satisfy the hypothesis of our main result are also constructed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2203.13706v3</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10468-024-10308-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Algebras and Representation Theory 28 (2025) 101-123</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hua Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A martingale approach to noncommutative stochastic calculus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.09856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.09856v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a new approach to noncommutative stochastic calculus that is, like the classical theory, based primarily on the martingale property. Using this approach, we introduce a general theory of stochastic integration and quadratic (co)variation for a certain class of noncommutative processes, analogous to semimartingales, that includes both the $q$-Brownian motions and classical matrix-valued Brownian motions. As applications, we obtain Burkholder--Davis--Gundy inequalities (with $p \geq 2$) for continuous-time noncommutative martingales and a noncommutative It\^{o}'s formula for "adapted $C^2$ maps," including trace $\ast$-polynomial maps and operator functions associated to the noncommutative $C^2$ scalar functions $\mathbb{R} \to \mathbb{C}$ introduced by Nikitopoulos, as well as the more general multivariate tracial noncommutative $C^2$ functions introduced by Jekel, Li, and Shlyakhtenko.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.09856v3</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jfa.2025.111200</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Functional Analysis 290 (2026), Article 111200</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>David A. Jekel, Todd A. Kemp, Evangelos A. Nikitopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Characterizations of zero singular ideal in \'etale groupoid C*-algebras via compressible maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07262v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We show the singular ideal in a non-Hausdorff \'etale groupoid C*-algebra is zero if and only if every unit is contained, at the level of group representation theory, in the collection of subgroups of the unit's isotropy group obtained as limit sets of nets in the "Hausdorff part" of the unit space. This is achieved through a study of the interplay between the Hausdorff cover and restriction maps on C*-algebras of groupoids to reductions by closed locally invariant subsets, which we show are compressible to *-homomorphisms and therefore have many of the same properties. We also prove a simpler algebraic characterization of zero singular ideal that holds whenever the isotropy group C*-algebras satisfy a certain ideal intersection property. We prove this property holds for all direct limits of virtually torsion free solvable groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07262v3</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jeremy B. Hume</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On amplified graph C*-algebras as cores of Cuntz-Krieger algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16430</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16430v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given a finite directed acyclic graph $R$, we construct from it two graphs $E_R$ and $F_R$, one by adding a loop at every vertex of $R$ and one by replacing every arrow of $R$ by countably infinitely many arrows. We show that the graph C*-algebra $C^*(F_R)$ is isomorphic to the AF core of $C^*(E_R)$. Examples include C*-algebras of a quantum flag manifolds and quantum teardrops. We discuss in detail the quantum Grassmannian $Gr_q(2,4)$ and use our description as AF core to study its CW-structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16430v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco D'Andrea, Sophie Emma Zegers</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shift equivalence implies flow equivalence for shifts of finite type</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14629v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Shifts of finite type defined from shift equivalent matrices must be flow equivalent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14629v2</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mike Boyle</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Uniqueness theorems for $L^p$-operator graph algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15591v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We continue the study of $L^p$-operator algebras associated with directed graphs initiated by Corti\~nas and Rodr\'iguez, and we establish $L^p$-analogs of both the gauge-invariant and the Cuntz-Krieger uniqueness theorems. The first of these asserts that for a graph $Q$, a gauge-equivariant spatial representation of its Leavitt path algebra $L_Q$ on an $L^p$-space generates an injective representation whenever the idempotents associated to the vertices of $Q$ are nonzero. The second of these theorems states that, in the setting just described, the same conclusion holds if gauge-equivariance is replaced by the assumption that every cycle in $Q$ has an entry. Additionally, we show that for acyclic graphs, such representations are automatically isometric.
  While our general approach is inspired by the proofs in the C*-algebra setting, a careful analysis of spatial representations of graphs on $L^p$-spaces is required. In particular, we exploit the interplay between analytical properties of Banach algebras, such as the role of hermitian elements, and geometric notions specific to $L^p$-spaces, such as spatial implementation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15591v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Eusebio Gardella, Siri Tinghammar</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
