<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA</link>
    <description>math.OA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 04:00:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Spectral continuity for \'etale groupoids with the Rapid decay property</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24145v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the reduced groupoid C*-algebras of continuous fields of \'etale groupoids satisfying the rapid decay property yield continuous fields of C*-algebras. This establishes a new sufficient criterion that applies in the non-amenable case where the full and reduced groupoid algebras may differ. Potential applications include convergence of spectra in inverse systems of finite-index subgroups and magnetic models on hyperbolic lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24145v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tom Stoiber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multiplicative trace and spectrum preservers on stochastic matrices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.22743</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.22743v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We characterize maps $\phi_i: \mathcal{S} \to \mathcal{S}$, $i=1, \ldots, m$ and $m\ge 1$, that have the multiplicative spectrum or trace preserving property:
  \begin{eqnarray*}
  \textrm{spec} (\phi_1(A_1)\cdots \phi_m(A_m)) &amp;=&amp; \textrm{spec} (A_1\cdots A_m),\quad\text{or}\quad
  \textrm{tr} (\phi_1(A_1)\cdots \phi_m(A_m)) &amp;=&amp; \textrm{tr} (A_1\cdots A_m),
  \end{eqnarray*}
  where $\mathcal{S}$ is the set of $n\times n$ doubly stochastic, row stochastic, or column stochastic matrices, or the space spanned by one of these sets.
  Linearity is assumed when $m=1$. We show that every stochastic matrix contains a real doubly stochastic component that carries the spectral information.
  In consequence, the multiplicative spectrum or trace preservers on these sets $ \mathcal{S} $ are linked to the
  corresponding preservers on the space of doubly stochastic matrices.
  Moreover, when $m\ge 3$, multiplicative trace preservers always coincide with multiplicative spectrum preservers.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.22743v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ming-Cheng Tsai, Huajun Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relative higher index theory on quotients of Roe algebras and positive scalar curvature at infinity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23380</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23380v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we employ quotients of Roe algebras as index containers for elliptic differential operators to study the existence problem of Riemannian metrics with positive scalar curvature on non-compact complete Riemannian manifolds. The non-vanishing of such an index locates the precise direction at infinity of the obstructions to positive scalar curvature, and may be viewed as a refinement of the positive scalar curvature problem. To achieve this, we formulate the relative coarse Baum-Connes conjecture and the relative coarse Novikov conjecture, together with their maximal versions, for general metric spaces as a program to compute the $K$-theory of the quotients of the Roe algebras relative to specific ideals. We show that if the metric space admits a relative fibred coarse embedding into Hilbert space or an $\ell^p$-space, certain cases of these conjectures can be verified, which yield obstructions to the existence of uniformly positive scalar curvature metrics in specified directions at infinity. As an application, we prove that the maximal coarse Baum-Connes conjecture holds for finite products of certain expander graphs that fail to admit fibred coarse embeddings into Hilbert space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23380v1</guid>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang Guo, Qin Wang, Chen Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncommutative localizations and joint spectra of a contractive quantum plane</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23539</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23539v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the present paper we investigate the localizations in the sense of J. L. Taylor of the Arens-Michael-Fr\'echet algebras occurred within the formal geometry of a contractive q-plane. It turns out that all noncommutative Fr\'echet algebras obtained by the Fr\'echet sheaves of the formal geometry are indeed localizations. That topological homology property of the structure sheaf results in the key properties of Taylor and Putinar spectra of the Banach q-modules.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23539v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anar Dosi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Positive contractive projections in Schatten Spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23701v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We characterize the positively 1-complemented subspaces of $S^p$, for $1\leq p&lt;\infty$, where $S^p$ denotes the Schatten spaces. Building on the work of Arazy and Friedman, who described the 1-complemented subspaces of $S^p$, for $1\leq p\neq 2 &lt;\infty$, we establish that there are five mutually distinct types of indecomposable positively 1-complemented subspaces in $S^p$. Moreover, every positively 1-complemented subspace of $S^p$ can be expressed as a direct sum of some of these indecomposable subspaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23701v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Estelle Boffy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Chern classes of almost representations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23950v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For a discrete group $\Gamma$, we study vector bundles $E_\rho$ on compact subsets of $B\Gamma$ associated to almost representations $\rho:\Gamma \to U(n)$. We compute the first Chern class of $E_\rho$ in terms of $\rho$. When $\rho$ is both projective and almost multiplicative, we determine its Chern character. These invariants yield obstructions to perturbing almost representations to those arising from projective representations. For residually finite amenable groups, the $K$-theory classes of $E_\rho$ classify almost representations up to stable equivalence. Finally, for $\mathbb{Z}^d$, $\mathbb{Z}\times \mathbb{H}_3$, and $\mathbb{H}_3\times \mathbb{H}_3$, we construct explicit almost representations with prescribed Chern classes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23950v1</guid>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marius Dadarlat, Forrest Glebe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twisted crossed products of Banach algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24106v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given a locally compact group $G$, a nondegenerate Banach algebra $A$ with a contractive approximate identity, a twisted action $(\alpha, \sigma)$ of $G$ on $A$, and a family $\mathcal{R}$ of uniformly bounded representations of $A$ on Banach spaces, we define the twisted crossed product $F_\mathcal{R}(G,A,\alpha, \sigma)$. When $\mathcal{R}$ consists of contractive representations, we show that $F_\mathcal{R}(G,A,\alpha, \sigma)$ is a Banach algebra with a contractive approximate identity, which can also be characterized by an isometric universal property.
  As an application, we specialize to the $L^p$-operator algebra setting, defining both the $L^p$-twisted crossed product and the reduced version. Finally, we give a generalization of the so-called Packer-Raeburn trick to the $L^p$-setting, showing that any $L^p$-twisted crossed product is "stably" isometrically isomorphic to an untwisted one.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24106v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alonso Delf\'in, Carla Farsi, Judith Packer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$C^*$-extreme points of unital completely positive maps on real $C^*$-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15362v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we investigate the general properties and structure of $C^*$-extreme points within the $C^*$-convex set $\mathrm{UCP}(\mathcal{A},B(\mathcal{H}))$ of all unital completely positive (UCP) maps from a unital real $C^*$-algebra $\mathcal{A}$ to the algebra $B(\mathcal{H})$ of all bounded real linear maps on a real Hilbert space $\mathcal{H}$. We analyze the differences in the structure of $C^*$-extreme points between the real and complex $C^*$-algebra cases. In particular, we show that the necessary and sufficient conditions for a UCP map between matrix algebras to be a $C^*$-extreme point are identical in both the real and complex matrix algebra cases. We also observe significant differences in the structure of $C^*$-extreme points when $\mathcal{A}$ is a commutative real $C^*$-algebra compared to when $\mathcal{A}$ is a commutative complex $C^*$-algebra. We provide a complete classification of the $C^*$-extreme points of $\mathrm{UCP}(\mathcal{A},B(\mathcal{H}))$, where $\mathcal{A}$ is a unital commutative real $C^*$-algebra and $\mathcal{H}$ is a finite-dimensional real Hilbert space. As an application, we classify all $C^*$-extreme points in the $C^*$-convex set of all contractive skew-symmetric real matrices in $M_n(\mathbb{R})$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15362v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anand O. R, K. Sumesh, Arindam Sutradhar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong convergence to operator-valued semicirculars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.19940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.19940v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We establish a framework for weak and strong convergence of matrix models to operator-valued semicircular systems parametrized by operator-valued covariance matrices $\eta = (\eta_{i,j})_{i,j \in I}$. Non-commutative polynomials are replaced by covariance polynomials that can involve iterated applications of $\eta_{i,j}$, leading to the notion of covariance laws. We give sufficient conditions for weak and strong convergence of general Gaussian random matrices and deterministic matrices to a $B$-valued semicircular family and generators of the base algebra $B$. In particular, we obtain operator-valued strong convergence for continuously weighted Gaussian Wigner matrices, such as Gaussian band matrices with a continuous cutoff, and we construct natural strongly convergent matrix models for interpolated free group factors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.19940v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Jekel, Yoonkyeong Lee, Brent Nelson, Jennifer Pi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of $q$-commuting contractions-II: Regular dilation, Brehmer's positivity and von Neumann's inequality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.10232</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.10232v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is well-known that a commuting family of contractions possesses a regular unitary dilation if and only if it satisfies Brehmer's positivity condition. We extend this theorem to any family $\mathcal T$ of $q$-commuting contractions with $\|q\|=1$ by showing the equivalence of the following three statements: $(i)$ $\mathcal T$ admits a regular $q$-unitary dilation; $(ii)$ $\mathcal T$ satisfies Brehmer's positivity condition; $(iii)$ $\mathcal T$ admits a $Q$-unitary dilation for a family of $Q$-commuting unitaries. We achieve the first part of the result by an application of Stinespring's dilation theorem on a particular completely positive map acting on a quotient algebra of a group $C^*$-algebra, where the underlying group is a free group, and the second part is obtained by an application of Naimark's theorem. Next, we find several cases when $\mathcal{T}$ admits a regular $q$-unitary dilation and establish a von Neumann type inequality for such a $q$-commuting family.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.10232v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sourav Pal, Prajakta Sahasrabuddhe, Nitin Tomar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A nonstanadard analysis approach to limit operators and Fredholmness in Roe-like algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08130</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08130v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $(X,d)$ be a uniformly locally finite metric space, and $T$ an operator in the uniform Roe algebra $C_u^*(X)$ (or uniform quasi-local algebra $C_{ql}^*(X)$). In this paper, we introduce the concept of limit operators of $T$ on galaxies in the nonstandard extension of $X$, and prove that $T$ is a generalized Fredholm operator with respect to the ghost ideal in $C_u^*(X)$ (or $C_{ql}^*(X)$) if and only if all limit operators on afar galaxies are invertible, and their inverses are uniformly bounded. In particular, if $X$ has Yu's Property A, then $T$ is a Fredholm operator if and only if all limit operators on afar galaxies are invertible. Using techniques in nonstandard analysis, our result strengthens a work of \v{S}pakula--Willett \cite{SpW} on the characterization of Fredholmness by using less limit operators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08130v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liang Guo, Jin Qian, Qin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bimodule Quantum Markov Semigroups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.09576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.09576v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a systematic investigation of bimodule quantum Markov semigroups within the framework of quantum Fourier analysis. Building on the structure of quantum symmetries, we introduce the concepts of bimodule equilibrium and bimodule detailed balance conditions, which not only generalize the classical notions of equilibrium and detailed balance but also expose interesting structures of quantum channels. We demonstrate that the evolution of densities governed by the bimodule quantum Markov semigroup is the bimodule gradient flow for the relative entropy with respect to quantum symmetries. Consequently, we obtain bimodule logarithmic Sobelov inequalities and bimodule Talagrand inequality with respect to a hidden density from higher dimensional structure. Furthermore, we establish a bimodule Poincar\'{e} inequality for irreducible inclusions and relative ergodic bimodule quantum semigroups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.09576v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinsong Wu, Zishuo Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
