<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA</link>
    <description>math.OA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 04:00:11 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The atoms of graph product von Neumann algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.09000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.09000v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We completely classify the atomic summands in a graph product $(M,\varphi) = *_{v \in \mathcal{G}} (M_v,\varphi_v)$ of von Neumann algebras with faithful normal states. Each type I factor summand $(N,\psi)$ is a tensor product of type I factor summands $(N_v,\psi_v)$ in the individual algebras. The existence of such a summand and its weight in the direct sum can be determined from the $(N_v,\psi_v)$'s using explicit polynomials associated to the graph.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.09000v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ian Charlesworth, David Jekel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Critical points of random polynomials and finite free cumulants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08910v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A result of Hoskins and Steinerberger [Int. Math. Res. Not., (13):9784-9809, 2022] states that repeatedly differentiating a random polynomials with independent and identically distributed mean zero and variance one roots will result, after an appropriate rescaling, in a Hermite polynomial. We use the theory of finite free probability to extend this result in two natural directions: (1) We prove central limit theorems for the fluctuations around these deterministic limits for the polynomials and their roots. (2) We consider a generalized version of the Hoskins and Steinerberger result by removing the finite second moment assumption from the roots. In this case the Hermite polynomials are replaced by a random Appell sequence conveniently described through finite free probability and an infinitely divisible distribution. We use finite free cumulants to provide compact proofs of our main results with little prerequisite knowledge of free probability required.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08910v1</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Octavio Arizmendi, Andrew Campbell, Katsunori Fujie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Online Learning Control Strategies for Industrial Processes with Application for Loosening and Conditioning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.08983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.08983v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper proposes a novel adaptive Koopman Model Predictive Control (MPC) framework, termed HPC-AK-MPC, designed to address the dual challenges of time-varying dynamics and safe operation in complex industrial processes. The framework integrates two core strategies: online learning and historically-informed safety constraints. To contend with process time-variance, a Recursive Extended Dynamic Mode Decomposition (rEDMDc) technique is employed to construct an adaptive Koopman model capable of updating its parameters from real-time data, endowing the controller with the ability to continuously learn and track dynamic changes. To tackle the critical issue of safe operation under model uncertainty, we introduce a novel Historical Process Constraint (HPC) mechanism. This mechanism mines successful operational experiences from a historical database and, by coupling them with the confidence level of the online model, generates a dynamic "safety corridor" for the MPC optimization problem. This approach transforms implicit expert knowledge into explicit, adaptive constraints, establishing a dynamic balance between pursuing optimal performance and ensuring robust safety. The proposed HPC-AK-MPC method is applied to a real-world tobacco loosening and conditioning process and systematically validated using an "advisor mode" simulation framework with industrial data. Experimental results demonstrate that, compared to historical operations, the proposed method significantly improves the Process Capability Index (Cpk) for key quality variables across all tested batches, proving its substantial potential in enhancing control performance while guaranteeing operational safety.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.08983v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yue Wu, Jianfu Cao, Ye Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Noncommutative Choquet theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.08436</link>
      <description>arXiv:1905.08436v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a new and extensive theory of noncommutative convexity along with a corresponding theory of noncommutative functions. We establish noncommutative analogues of the fundamental results from classical convexity theory, and apply these ideas to develop a noncommutative Choquet theory that generalizes much of classical Choquet theory.
  The central objects of interest in noncommutative convexity are noncommutative convex sets. The category of compact noncommutative sets is dual to the category of operator systems, and there is a robust notion of extreme point for a noncommutative convex set that is dual to Arveson's notion of boundary representation for an operator system.
  We identify the C*-algebra of continuous noncommutative functions on a compact noncommutative convex set as the maximal C*-algebra of the operator system of continuous noncommutative affine functions on the set. In the noncommutative setting, unital completely positive maps on this C*-algebra play the role of representing measures in the classical setting.
  The continuous convex noncommutative functions determine an order on the set of unital completely positive maps that is analogous to the classical Choquet order on probability measures. We characterize this order in terms of the extensions and dilations of the maps, providing a powerful new perspective on the structure of completely positive maps on operator systems.
  Finally, we establish a noncommutative generalization of the Choquet-Bishop-de Leeuw theorem asserting that every point in a compact noncommutative convex set has a representing map that is supported on the extreme boundary. In the separable case, we obtain a corresponding integral representation theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1905.08436v4</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenneth R. Davidson, Matthew Kennedy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo-Cartan Inclusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01975v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A pseudo-Cartan inclusion is a regular inclusion having a Cartan envelope. Unital pseudo-Cartan inclusions were classified by Pitts; we extend this classification to include the non-unital case. The class of pseudo-Cartan inclusions coincides with the class of regular inclusions having the faithful unique pseudo-expectation property and can also be described using the ideal intersection property. We describe the twisted groupoid associated with the Cartan envelope of a pseudo-Cartan inclusion. These results significantly extend previous results obtained for the unital setting.
  We explore properties of pseudo-Cartan inclusions and the relationship between a pseudo-Cartan inclusion and its Cartan envelope. For example, if $\mathcal D\subseteq \mathcal C$ is a pseudo-Cartan inclusion with Cartan envelope $\mathcal B\subseteq \mathcal A$, then $\mathcal C$ is simple if and only if $\mathcal A$ is simple. Also every regular $*$-automorphism of $\mathcal C$ uniquely extends to a $*$-automorphism of $\mathcal A$. We show that the inductive limit of pseudo-Cartan inclusions with suitable connecting maps is a pseudo-Cartan inclusion, and the minimal tensor product of pseudo-Cartan inclusions is a pseudo-Cartan inclusion. Further, we describe the Cartan envelope of pseudo-Cartan inclusions arising from these constructions. We conclude with some applications and a few open questions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01975v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David R. Pitts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Morita equivalence classes for crossed product of rational rotation algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19869</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19869v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We study the Morita equivalence classes of crossed products of rotation algebras $A_\theta$, where $\theta$ is a rational number, by finite and infinite cyclic subgroups of $\mathrm{SL}(2, \mathbb{Z})$. We show that for any such subgroup $F$, the crossed products $A_\theta \rtimes F$ and $A_{\theta'} \rtimes F$ are strongly Morita equivalent, where both $\theta$ and $\theta'$ are rational. Combined with previous results for irrational values of $\theta$, our result provides a complete classification of the crossed products $A_\theta \rtimes F$ up to Morita equivalence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19869v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayan Chakraborty, Pratik Kumar Kundu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On closure operations in the space of subgroups and applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10222v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We establish some interactions between uniformly recurrent subgroups (URSs) of a group $G$ and cosets topologies $\tau_\mathcal{N}$ on $G$ associated to a family $\mathcal{N}$ of normal subgroups of $G$. We show that when $\mathcal{N}$ consists of finite index subgroups of $G$, there is a natural closure operation $\mathcal{H} \mapsto \mathrm{cl}_\mathcal{N}(\mathcal{H})$ that associates to a URS $\mathcal{H}$ another URS $\mathrm{cl}_\mathcal{N}(\mathcal{H})$, called the $\tau_\mathcal{N}$-closure of $\mathcal{H}$. We give a characterization of the URSs $\mathcal{H}$ that are $\tau_\mathcal{N}$-closed in terms of stabilizer URSs. This has consequences on arbitrary URSs when $G$ belongs to the class of groups for which every faithful minimal profinite action is topologically free. We also consider the largest amenable URS $\mathcal{A}_G$, and prove that for certain coset topologies on $G$, almost all subgroups $H \in \mathcal{A}_G$ have the same closure. For groups in which amenability is detected by a set of laws (a property that is variant of the Tits alternative), we deduce a criterion for $\mathcal{A}_G$ to be a singleton based on residual properties of $G$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10222v3</guid>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dominik Francoeur, Adrien Le Boudec</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Band-dominated and Fourier-band-dominated operators on locally compact abelian groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.17442</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.17442v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By relating notions from quantum harmonic analysis and band-dominated operator theory, we prove that over any locally compact abelian group $G$, the operator algebra $\mathcal C_1$ from quantum harmonic analysis agrees with the intersection of band-dominated operators and Fourier band-dominated operators. As an application, we characterize the compactness of operators acting on $L^2(G)$ and compare it with previous results in the discrete case. In particular, our results can be seen as a generalization of the limit operator concept to the non-discrete world. Moreover, we briefly discuss property $A'$ for arbitrary locally compact abelian groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.17442v2</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert Fulsche, Raffael Hagger</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
