<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA</link>
    <description>math.OA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 02:51:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum expanders and property (T) discrete quantum groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01974v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Families of expander graphs were first constructed by Margulis from discrete groups with property (T). Within the framework of quantum information theory, several authors have generalised the notion of an expander graph to the setting of quantum channels. In this work, we use discrete quantum groups with property (T) to construct quantum expanders in two ways. The first approach obtains a quantum expander family by constructing the requisite quantum channels directly from finite-dimensional irreducible unitary representations, extending earlier work of Harrow using groups. The second approach directly generalises Margulis' original construction and is based on a quantum analogue of a Schreier graph using the theory of coideals. To obtain examples of quantum expanders, we apply our machinery to discrete quantum groups with property (T) coming from compact bicrossed products.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01974v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Brannan, Eric Culf, Matthijs Vernooij</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudo-Cartan Inclusions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01975</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01975v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We define a new class of regular inclusions, the pseudo-Cartan inclusions. We show this class coincides with the class of regular inclusions having a Cartan envelope and also with the class of regular inclusions with the faithful unique pseudo-expectation property. We describe the twisted groupoid associated with the Cartan envelope of a pseudo-Cartan inclusion. These results significantly extend previous results obtained for the unital setting.
  We explore properties of pseudo-Cartan inclusions and the relationship between a pseudo-Cartan inclusion and its Cartan envelope. For example, if $D \subseteq C$ is a pseudo-Cartan inclusion with Cartan envelope $B \subseteq A$, then $C$ is simple if and only if $A$ is simple. We show how to construct pseudo-Cartan inclusions from a given Cartan inclusion, that the inductive limit of pseudo-Cartan inclusions with suitable connecting maps is a pseudo-Cartan inclusion, and the minimal tensor product of pseudo-Cartan inclusions is a pseudo-Cartan inclusion. Further, we describe the Cartan envelope of pseudo-Cartan inclusions arising from these constructions. We give some applications and conclude with a few open questions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01975v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David R. Pitts</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Boundary actions of Bass-Serre Trees and the applications to $C^*$-algebras</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02039</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02039v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we study Bass-Serre theory from the perspectives of $C^*$-algebras and topological dynamics. In particular, we investigate the actions of fundamental groups of graphs of groups on their Bass-Serre trees and the associated boundaries, through which, we identify new families of $C^*$-simple groups including certain tubular groups and fundamental groups of certain graphs of groups with one vertex group acylindrically hyperbolic. In addition, we obtain characterizations of $C^*$-simplicity for Generalized Baumslag-Solitar (GBS) groups and outer automorphism groups $\operatorname{Out}(BS(p, q))$ of Baumslag-Solitar groups. These $C^*$-simple groups also provide new examples of highly transitive groups. Moreover, we demonstrate that natural boundary actions of these $C^*$-simple fundamental groups of graphs of groups give rise to the new purely infinite crossed product $C^*$-algebras.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02039v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Ma, Daxun Wang, Wenyuan Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discrete octonionic analysis: a unified approach to the split-octonionic and classical settings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.02227</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.02227v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Various problems of mathematical physics consider octonions and split-octonions as a mathematical structure, which underpins the eight-dimensional nature of these problems. Therefore, it is not surprising that octonionic analysis has become an area of active research in recent years. One of the main goals of octonionic analysis is to develop tools of an octonionic operator calculus for solving boundary value problems of mathematical physics that benefit from the use of the octonionic structure. However, when we want to apply the operator calculus in practice, it becomes evident that adequate discrete counterparts of continuous constructions need to be defined. In previous works, we have proposed several approaches to discretise the classical continuous octonionic analysis. However, the split-octonionic case, which is particularly important for practical applications concretely investigated in the last years, has not been considered until now. Therefore, one of the goals of this paper is to explain how to particularly address the discrete split-octonionic setting. Additionally, we propose a general umbrella to cover all different discrete octonionic settings in one unified approach that also encompasses the different eight-dimensional algebraic structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.02227v1</guid>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rolf S\"oren Krau{\ss}har, Anastasiia Legatiuk, Dmitrii Legatiuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A characterization of absolutely dilatable Schur multipliers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.08436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.08436v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $M$ be a von Neumann algebra equipped with a normal semi-finite faithful trace (nsf trace in short) and let $T\colon M\to M$ be a contraction. We say that $T$ is absolutely dilatable if there exist another von Neumann algebra $M'$ equipped with a nsf trace, a $w^*$-continuous trace preserving unital $*$-homomorphim $J\colon M\to M'$ and a trace preserving $*$-automomorphim $U\colon M'\to M'$ such that $T^k=E U^k J$ for all integer $k\geq 0$, where $E\colon M'\to M$ is the conditional expectation associated with $J$. Given a $\sigma$-finite measure space $(\Omega,\mu)$, we characterize bounded Schur multipliers $\phi\in L^\infty(\Omega^2)$ such that the Schur multiplication operator $T_\phi\colon B(L^2(\Omega))\to B(L^2(\Omega))$ is absolutely dilatable. In the separable case, they are characterized by the existence of a von Neumann algebra $N$ with a separable predual, equipped with a normalized normal faithful trace $\tau_N$, and of a $w^*$-continuous essentially bounded function $d\colon\Omega\to N$ such that $\phi(s,t)=\tau_N(d(s)^*d(t))$ for almost every $(s,t)\in\Omega^2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.08436v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles Duquet, Christian Le Merdy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new approach to deformation of C*-algebras via coactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.09997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.09997v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We revisit the procedure of deformation of $C^*$-algebras via coactions of locally compact groups and extend the methods to cover deformations for maximal, reduced, and exotic coactions for a given group $G$ and circle-valued Borel $2$-cocycles on $G$. In the special case of reduced (or normal) coactions our deformation method substantially differs from -- but turns out to be equivalent to -- the ones used by previous authors, specially those given by Bhowmick, Neshveyev, and Sangha in [7].
  Our approach yields all expected results, like a good behaviour of deformations under nuclearity, continuity of fields of $C^*$-algebras and $K$-theory invariance under mild conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.09997v3</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alcides Buss, Siegfried Echterhoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deformation of Fell bundles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.04369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.04369v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we study deformations of $C^*$-algebras that are given as cross-sectional $C^*$-algebras of Fell bundles over locally compact groups $G$. Our deformation comes from a direct deformation of the Fell bundles via certain parameters, like automorphisms of the Fell bundle, group cocycles, or central group extensions of $G$ by the circle group $\mathbb{T}$, and then taking cross-sectional algebras of the deformed Fell bundles. We then show that this direct deformation method is equivalent to the deformation via the dual coactions by similar parameters as studied previously in [4,7].</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.04369v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alcides Buss, Siegfried Echterhoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the extension of positive maps to Haagerup non-commutative $L^p$-spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04400v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $M$ be a von Neumann algebra, let $\varphi$ be a normal faithful state on $M$ and let $L^p(M,\varphi)$ be the associated Haagerup non-commutative $L^p$-spaces, for $1\leq p\leq\infty$. Let $D\in L^1(M,\varphi)$ be the density of $\varphi$. Given a positive map $T\colon M\to M$ such that $\varphi\circ T\leq C_1\varphi$ for some $C_1\geq 0$, we study the boundedness of the $L^p$-extension $T_{p,\theta}\colon D^{\frac{1-\theta}{p}} M D^{\frac{\theta}{p}}\to L^p(M,\varphi)$ which maps $D^{\frac{1-\theta}{p}} x D^{\frac{\theta}{p}}$ to $D^{\frac{1-\theta}{p}} T(x) D^{\frac{\theta}{p}}$ for all $x\in M$. Haagerup-Junge-Xu showed that $T_{p,\frac12}$ is always bounded and left open the question whether $T_{p,\theta}$ is bounded for $\theta\not=\frac12$. We show that for any $1\leq p&lt;2$ and any $\theta\in [0,2^{-1}(1-\sqrt{p-1})]\cup[2^{-1}(1+\sqrt{p-1}), 1]$, there exists a completely positive $T$ such that $T_{p,\theta}$ is unbounded. We also show that if $T$ is $2$-positive, then $T_{p,\theta}$ is bounded provided that $p\geq 2$ or $1\leq p&lt;2$ and $\theta\in[1-p/2,p/2]$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04400v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christian Le Merdy, Safoura Zadeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absolute dilations of ucp self-adjoint Fourier multipliers: the non unimodular case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.06074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.06074v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\varphi$ be a normal semi-finite faithful weight on a von Neumann algebra $A$,let $(\sigma^\varphi_r)_{r\in{\mathbb R}}$ denote the modular automorphism group of $\varphi$, and let $T\colon A\to A$ be a linear map. We say that $T$ admits an absolute dilation if there exist another von Neumann algebra $M$ equipped with a normal semi-finite faithful weight $\psi$, a $w^*$-continuous, unital and weight-preserving $*$-homomorphism $J\colon A\to M$ such that $\sigma^\psi\circ J=J\circ \sigma^\varphi$, as well as a weight-preserving $*$-automorphism $U\colon M\to M$ such that $T^k={\mathbb E}_JU^kJ$ for all integer $k\geq 0$, where ${\mathbb E}_J\colon M\to A$ is the conditional expectation associated with $J$. Given any locally compact group $G$ and any real valued function $u\in C_b(G)$, we prove that if $u$ induces a unital completely positive Fourier multiplier $M_u\colon VN(G) \to VN(G)$, then $M_u$ admits an absolute dilation. Here $VN(G)$ is equiped with its Plangherel weight $\varphi_G$. This result had been settled by the first named author in the case when $G$ is unimodular so the salient point in this paper is that $G$ may be non unimodular, and hence $\varphi_G$ may not be a trace. The absolute dilation of $M_u$ implies that for any $1&lt;p&lt;\infty$, the $L^p$-realization of $M_u$ can be dilated into an isometry acting on a non-commutative $L^p$-space. We further prove that if $u$ is valued in $[0,1]$, then the $L^p$-realization of $M_u$ is a Ritt operator with a bounded $H^\infty$-functional calculus.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.06074v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charles Duquet, Christian Le Merdy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On inner-amenability and boundary actions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01447v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\Gamma$ be a discrete countable group. The first main result of this work is that if $\Gamma$ is ICC inner-amenable non-amenable then it cannot satisfy the (AO)-property, answering a question posed by C. Anantharaman-Delaroche. It is also proved that if $\Gamma$ is a "sufficiently large" discrete subgroup of a product of locally compact second countable bi-exact groups, then it cannot be inner-amenable. Both these results generalize the well-known fact that ICC non-amenable inner-amenable discrete countable groups cannot be bi-exact.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01447v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.GR</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacopo Bassi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Brown measure of a sum of two free nonselfadjoint random variables, one of which is R-diagonal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.12379</link>
      <description>arXiv:2209.12379v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Suppose that $X_{1}$ and $X_{2}$ are two $*$-free (generally unbounded) random variables with Brown measures $\mu_{X_{1}}$ and $\mu_{X_{2}}$, respectively. Using properties of classical free additive convolutions, we develop a method for calculating $\mu_{X_{1}+X_{2}}$when $X_{2}$ is $R$-diagonal. This method determines a density relative to Lebesgue measure on an open set whose closure contains the support of $\mu_{X_{1}+X_{2}}$. Effective calculations are possible in important cases. Biane and Lehner were the first to make significant progress on the problem we consider, even in some cases in which neither $X_{1}$ nor $X_{2}$ is $R$-diagonal. Our examples overlap with theirs, but we emphasize the use of subordination functions. When $X_{2}$ is circular, $\mu_{X_{1}+X_{2}}$ was studied earlier using two different approaches, one involving Hamilton-Jacobi equations, and another using standard free probability techniques. Our work extends the second approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2209.12379v2</guid>
      <category>math.PR</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hari Bercovici, Ping Zhong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A collection of cancellative, singly aligned, non-embeddable monoids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.20197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.20197v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By classical results of Malcev, cancellative monoids need not be group-embeddable. In this paper, we describe and give presentations for and study an infinite family $\mathcal{M}_n$ of cancellative monoids which are not group-embeddable, originating from Malcev's original work. We show that $\mathcal{M}_n$ is singly aligned for $n \geq 2$, owing to applications in the study of $\mathrm{C}^*$-algebras by Brix, Bruce and Dor-On. We finish by showing that $\mathcal{M}_1$ is not singly aligned, but is $2$-aligned.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.20197v2</guid>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Milo Edwardes, Daniel Heath</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
