<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.OA updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA</link>
    <description>math.OA updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.OA" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 04:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Finite index quantum subgroups of discrete quantum groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14044</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14044v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that finite index quantum subgroups of a discrete quantum group are induced from finite index quantum subgroups of the unimodularization. As an application, we classify all finite index quantum subgroups of free products of the duals of connected simply-connected compact Lie groups. We also put proofs for some fundamental facts on finite index right coideals of compact quantum groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14044v1</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mao Hoshino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpolation categories for Conformal Embeddings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13641v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we give a diagrammatic description of the categories of modules coming from the conformal embeddings $\mathcal{V}(\mathfrak{sl}_N,N) \subset \mathcal{V}(\mathfrak{so}_{N^2-1},1)$. A small variant on this construction (morally corresponding to a conformal embedding of $\mathfrak{gl}_N$ level $N$ into $\mathfrak{o}_{N^2-1}$ level $1$) has uniform generators and relations which are rational functions in $q = e^{2 \pi i/4N}$, which allows us to construct a new continuous family of tensor categories at non-integer level which interpolate between these categories. This is the second example of such an interpolation category for families of conformal embeddings after Zhengwei Liu's interpolation categories $\mathcal{V}(\mathfrak{sl}_N, N\pm 2) \subset \mathcal{V}(\mathfrak{sl}_{N(N\pm 1)/2},1)$ which he constructed using his classification Yang-Baxter planar algebras. Our approach is different from Liu's, we build a two-color skein theory, with one strand coming from $X$ the image of defining representation of $\mathfrak{sl}_N$ and the other strand coming from an invertible object $g$ in the category of local modules, and a trivalent vertex coming from a map $X \otimes X^* \rightarrow g$. We anticipate small variations on our approach will yield interpolation categories for every infinite discrete family of conformal embeddings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13641v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cain Edie-Michell, Noah Snyder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Atiyah-Schmid formula for reductive groups</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13929v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We prove the Atiyah-Schmid formula for tempered and projective tempered representations of reductive groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13929v1</guid>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Commutants of a certain class of Toeplitz operators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14200v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A major open problem in the Theory of Toeplitz operators on the analytic Bergman space over the unit disk is the characterization of the commutant of a given Toeplitz operator--that is, the set of all bounded Toeplitz operators that commute with it. In this paper, we provide a complete description of bounded Toeplitz operators $T_f$, where the symbol $f$ has a truncated polar decomposition, that commute with a Toeplitz operator whose symbol is the sum of a quasihomogeneous function and a bounded analytic function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14200v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aissa Bouhali, Issam Louhichi, Abdel Rahman Yousef</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absolute continuity of polynomially bounded tuples</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14256v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Absolute continuity of polynomially bounded n-tuples of commuting contractions in a Hilbert space is studied. A necessary and sufficient condition is found in Constantin Apostol's ``weakened $C_{0,\cdot}$ assumption'', asserting the convergence to 0 of the powers of each operator in a specific topology. Kosiek with Octavio considered tuples satisfying the von-Neumann Inequality. We extend their results to a wider class of tuples, where there may be no unitary dilation and the bounding constant may be greater than 1. Our proof uses decompositions of A-measures with respect to bands of measures related to Gleason parts of the polydisc algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14256v1</guid>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Foks, Krzysztof Rudol</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The quantum metric structure of quantum SU(2)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.06043</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.06043v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a two parameter family of Dirac operators on quantum SU(2) and analyse their properties from the point of view of non-commutative metric geometry. It is shown that these Dirac operators give rise to compact quantum metric structures, and that the corresponding two parameter family of compact quantum metric spaces varies continuously in Rieffel's quantum Gromov-Hausdorff distance. This continuity result includes the classical case where we recover the round 3-sphere up to a global scaling factor on the metric. Our main technical tool is a quantum SU(2) analogue of the Berezin transform, together with its associated fuzzy approximations, the analysis of which also leads to a systematic way of approximating Lipschitz operators by means of polynomial expressions in the generators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.06043v3</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <category>math.MG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Memoirs of the European Mathematical Society, 18. EMS Press, Berlin, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jens Kaad, David Kyed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor category equivariant KK-theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.07255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.07255v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce Kasparov's bivariant K-theory that is equivariant under symmetries of a C*-tensor category. It is motivated by some dualities in quantum group equivariant KK-theory, and the classification theory of inclusions of C*-algebras. The fundamental properties of the KK-theory, i.e., the existence of the Kasparov product, Cuntz's picture, universality, and triangulated category structure, hold true in this generalization as well. Moreover, we further prove a new property specific to this theory; the invariance of KK-theory under weak Morita equivalence of the tensor categories. As an example, we study the Baum-Connes type property for $3$-cocycle twists of discrete groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.07255v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.KT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.aim.2024.109848</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Math. 453 (2024), 109848</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yuki Arano, Kan Kitamura, Yosuke Kubota</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Invariant subalgebras of the reduced group $C^*$-algebra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.09548</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.09548v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $\Gamma$ be a countable discrete group. We say that $\Gamma$ has $C^*$-invariant subalgebra rigidity (ISR) property if every $\Gamma$-invariant $C^*$-subalgebra $\mathcal{A}\le C_r^*(\Gamma)$ is of the form $C_r^*(N)$ for some normal subgroup $N\triangleleft\Gamma$. We show that all torsion-free, non-amenable (cylindrically) hyperbolic groups with property-AP and a finite direct product of such groups have this property. We also prove that an infinite group $\Gamma$ has the C$^*$-ISR property only if $\Gamma$ is simple amenable or $C^*$-simple.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.09548v2</guid>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tattwamasi Amrutam, Yongle Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
