<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 04:00:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>The art of modeling nuclear reactions with weakly bound nuclei: status and perspectives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00175v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We give an overview of the theoretical description of nuclear reactions involving weakly-bound nuclei. Some of the more widespread reaction formalisms employed in the analysis of these reactions are briefly introduced, including various recent developments. We put special emphasis on the continuum-discretized coupled-channel (CDCC) method and its extensions to incorporate core and target excitations as well as its application to three-body projectiles. The role of the continuum for one-nucleon transfer reactions is also discussed. The problem of the evaluation of inclusive breakup cross sections is addressed within the Ichimura-Austern-Vincent (IAV) model. Other methods, such as those based on a semiclasical description of the scattering process, are also briefly introduced and some of their applications are discussed and a brief discussion on topics of current interest, such as nucleon-nucleon correlations, uncertainty evaluation and non-locality is presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00175v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. M. Moro, J. Casal, M. Gomez-Ramos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pairing phase transition in the odd-A nuclei: identification and classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00423</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00423v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The investigation into the pairing phase transition in the odd-A nucleus 161Dy utilizes a sophisticated blend of covariant density functional theory and the shell-model-like approach. It is discerned that variations in thermodynamic quantities at the critical temperature do not exclusively align with pairing phase transitions. The presence of an S-shaped heat capacity curve, often interpreted as an indication of such transitions, does not offer a definitive confirmation. Additional factors, including the blocking effect, can modify the heat capacity curve and impede the transition process. The pairing phase transition in 161Dy, occurring around 0.7 to 1.0 MeV, is unequivocally characterized as a first-order transition. Furthermore, an exploration into the impact of varying strengths of pairing correlations on these transitions reveals a nonlinear relationship, adding complexity to the transition dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00423v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yumeng Wang, Yuhang Gao, Lang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Improving relativistic energy density functionals with tensor couplings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00425</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00425v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Energy density functionals (EDFs) have been used extensively with great success to calculate properties of nuclei and to predict the equation of state (EOS) of dense nuclear matter. Besides non-relativistic EDFs, mostly of the Skyrme or Gogny type, relativistic EDFs of different types are in widespread use. In these latter approaches, the effective in-medium interaction is described by an exchange of mesons between nucleons. In most cases, only minimal meson-nucleon couplings are considered. The effects of additional tensor couplings were rarely investigated. In this work, a new relativistic EDF with tensor couplings and density dependent minimal meson-nucleon couplings will be presented. The parameters of the model are determined using a carefully selected set of experimental data with realistic uncertainties that are determined self-consistently. Predictions for various nuclear observables, the nuclear matter equation of state, and properties of neutron stars are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00425v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stefan Typel, Shalom Shlomo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian analysis of (3+1)D relativistic nuclear dynamics with the RHIC beam energy scan data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00537</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00537v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work presents a Bayesian inference study for relativistic heavy-ion collisions in the Beam Energy Scan program at the Relativistic Heavy-Ion Collider. The theoretical model simulates event-by-event (3+1)D collision dynamics using hydrodynamics and hadronic transport theory. We analyze the model's 20-dimensional posterior distributions obtained using three model emulators with different accuracy and demonstrate the essential role of training an accurate model emulator in the Bayesian analysis. Our analysis provides robust constraints on the Quark-Gluon Plasma's transport properties and various aspects of (3+1)D relativistic nuclear dynamics. By running full model simulations with 100 parameter sets sampled from the posterior distribution, we make predictions for $p_{\rm T}$-differential observables and estimate their systematic theory uncertainty. A sensitivity analysis is performed to elucidate how individual experimental observables respond to different model parameters, providing useful physics insights into the phenomenological model for heavy-ion collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00537v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Syed Afrid Jahan, Hendrik Roch, Chun Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal relationships for neutron stars from perturbative approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00646v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The universal relationships for compact stars have been investigated employing perturbative approach using canonical (APR) and Brussels-Montreal Skyrme (BSk22, BSk24, BSk26) equations of state describing hadronic matter of neutron stars. The neutron star matter has been considered to be $\beta$-equilibrated neutron-proton-electron-muon matter at the core with a rigid crust. The multipole moments of a slowly rotating neutron star characterize its external gravitational field. These variables are dependent on the interior structure of the neutron star described by the equation of state of the neutron star matter. The properties of neutron stars, such as the mass, the radius, the dimensionless moment of inertia, the compactness, the Love number, the dimensionless tidal deformability and the dimensionless quadrupole moment have been calculated and relations among these quantities have been explored. It is found that most of these relations do not depend sensitively on the details of the internal structure of neutron stars. Such universality implies that the measurement of a single quantity appearing in a universal relation would automatically provide information about the others, notwithstanding the fact that those may not be accessible observationally. These can be used to estimate deformability of compact stars through moment of inertia measurements, to quantify spin in binary inspirals by breaking degeneracies in the detection of gravitational waves and test General Relativity in a way that is independent of nuclear structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00646v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debasis Atta, Vinay Singh, D. N. Basu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subspace-projected multireference covariant density functional theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00691</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00691v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multireference density functional theory (MR-DFT) has been a pivotal method for studying nuclear spectroscopy and neutrinoless double-beta ($0\nu\beta\beta$) decay. However, quantifying their theoretical uncertainties has been a significant challenge due to the computational demands. This study introduces a subspace-projected covariant density functional theory (SP-CDFT), which efficiently emulates MR-CDFT calculations for nuclear low-lying states. This approach leverages the eigenvector continuation method combined with the quantum-number projected generator coordinate method, based on a relativistic energy density functional (EDF). We apply SP-CDFT to investigate the correlations among the physical quantities of nuclear matter, nuclear low-lying spectroscopy, and the nuclear matrix elements (NMEs) of $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay in the two heaviest candidate nuclei. Our findings reveal generally strong correlations between the NMEs of $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay and the excitation energy of the $2_1^+$ state, as well as the $E2$ transition strength, although these correlations vary significantly among nuclei. The Bayesian analysis, which integrates the properties of nuclear matter and low-lying states, yields mean values and statistical uncertainties for the NMEs 4.33(5) for $^{136}$Xe and 5.51(14) for $^{150}$Nd. This work also paves the way for refining nuclear EDF parameters using spectroscopic data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00691v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>X. Zhang, C. C. Wang, C. R. Ding, J. M. Yao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Smile of Cheshire Cat At High Density</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00692v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Baryons in finite nuclei, nuclear matter and dense compact-star matter are described in terms of Cheshire Cat for QCD. A potential conceptual link, admittedly short in mathematical rigor, between their manifestations is made by what's called Cheshire Cat Principle. Put in terms taken ``dual" to QCD variables, going to very high density exposes quantum Hall droplets -- or pancakes -- at which the dilaton-limit fixed point with $g_A\to 1$, $f_\pi\to f_\chi$ -- where $f_\pi$ and $f_\chi$ are respectively the pion and dilaton decay constants -- and the baryon parity-doubling are reached. This scenario suggests a thus-far totally unexplored structure of dual baryonic matter at high density which does neither require nor rule out (rapid) first-order phase transitions from hadrons to quarks in the core of compact stars on the verge of gravitational collapse.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00692v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mannque Rho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Computing Universal Thermalization Dynamics in a (2+1)D Lattice Gauge Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00069v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Simulating non-equilibrium phenomena in strongly-interacting quantum many-body systems, including thermalization, is a promising application of near-term and future quantum computation. By performing experiments on a digital quantum computer consisting of fully-connected optically-controlled trapped ions, we study the role of entanglement in the thermalization dynamics of a $Z_2$ lattice gauge theory in 2+1 spacetime dimensions. Using randomized-measurement protocols, we efficiently learn a classical approximation of non-equilibrium states that yields the gap-ratio distribution and the spectral form factor of the entanglement Hamiltonian. These observables exhibit universal early-time signals for quantum chaos, a prerequisite for thermalization. Our work, therefore, establishes quantum computers as robust tools for studying universal features of thermalization in complex many-body systems, including in gauge theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00069v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Mueller, Tianyi Wang, Or Katz, Zohreh Davoudi, Marko Cetina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An alternative way to decipher the nature of the doubly charmed tetraquark $T_{cc}(3875)^+$: its antiparticle $T_{{\bar c}{\bar c}}(3875)^-$ photoproduction off nuclei near threshold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00360</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00360v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the inclusive photoproduction of $T_{{\bar c}{\bar c}}(3875)^-$ mesons (which are the antiparticles of the doubly charmed tetraquarks $T_{cc}(3875)^+$ discovered recently by the LHCb Collaboration) from nuclei in the near-threshold energy region within the nuclear spectral function approach by considering incoherent direct (${\gamma}p(n) \to D^+(D^0){T_{{\bar c}{\bar c}}(3875)^-}\Lambda^+_c$) photon--nucleon $T_{{\bar c}{\bar c}}(3875)^-$ creation processes as well as five possible different scenarios for their internal structure with the main goal of clarifying the possibility to decipher this structure (and, hence, that of $T_{cc}(3875)^+$) in photoproduction via integral and differential observables. We calculate the absolute and relative excitation functions for $T_{{\bar c}{\bar c}}(3875)^-$ production off $^{12}$C and $^{184}$W target nuclei at near-threshold photon beam energies of 30--38 GeV, the absolute differential cross sections for their production off these target nuclei at laboratory polar angles of 0$^{\circ}$--10$^{\circ}$ as well as the A and momentum dependences of the relative (transparency ratios) cross sections for $T_{{\bar c}{\bar c}}(3875)^-$ production at photon energy of 35 GeV within the adopted scenarios for the $T_{{\bar c}{\bar c}}(3875)^-$ meson intrinsic structure. We demonstrate that the absolute and relative observables considered show a certain sensitivity to these scenarios. Therefore, the measurement of such observables in future experiments at the proposed high-luminosity electron-ion colliders EIC and EicC in the US and China in the near-threshold energy region might shed light on the $T_{cc}(3875)^+$ internal structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00360v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Ya. Paryev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Second-order nonlocal shifts of scattered wave-packets: What can be measured by Goos-H\"anchen and Imbert-Fedorov effects ?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00375</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00375v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The scattering of wavepackets with arbitrary energy dispersion on surfaces has been analyzed. Expanding up to second order in scattering shifts, it is found that besides the known Goos-H\"anchen or Imbert-Fedorov spatial offset, as well as the Wigner delay time, new momentum and frequency shifts appear. Furthermore, the width of the scattered wave packet becomes modified as well, which can lead to a shrinking of pulses by multiple scattering. For a model of dielectric material characterized by a longitudinal and transverse dielectric function the shifts are calculated analytically. From the Goos-H\"anchen and Imbert-Fedorov shifts one can access the longitudinal and transversal dielectric function. Perfectly aligned crystal symmetry axes with respect to scattering beam shows no Imbert-Fedorov effect. It is found that the Goos-H\"anchen and Imbert-Fedorov effect are absent for homogeneous materials. Oppositely it is found that the Wigner delay time and the shrinking of the temporal pulse width allows to access the dielectric function independent on the beam geometry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00375v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Morawetz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fully strange tetraquark resonant states as the cousins of $X(6900)$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00503</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00503v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We conduct systematic calculations of the S-wave fully strange systems with ``normal" $\left(J^{P C}=0^{++}, 1^{+-}, 2^{++}\right)$ and ``exotic" $\left(J^{P C}=0^{+-}, 1^{++}, 2^{+-}\right)$ C-parities, which are the strange analogue of the fully charmed tetraquark state $X(6900)$. Within a constituent quark potential model, we employ the Gaussian expansion method to solve the four-body Schr\"odinger equation and the complex scaling method to identify resonant states. We obtain a series of resonant states and zero-width states in the mass range of 2.7 to 3.3 GeV, with their widths ranging from less than 1 MeV to about 50 MeV. Their rms radii strongly indicate that they are compact tetraquark states. Among these states, the $T_{4s,2^{++}}(2714)$ may be the most likely one to be observed experimentally. We urge the experimental exploration of the $2^{++}$ $s s \bar{s} \bar{s}$ state around 2.7 GeV in the $\phi\phi$ channel. Since the lowest S-wave $s s \bar{s} \bar{s}$ state is around 2.7 GeV, the compact P-wave $s s \bar{s} \bar{s}$ states are expected to be heavier. Hence, $\phi(2170)$ and $X(2370)$ are unlikely to be compact tetraquark states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00503v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yao Ma, Wei-Lin Wu, Lu Meng, Yan-Ke Chen, Shi-Lin Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hot and Dense QCD Shear Viscosity at (almost) NLO</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00524</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00524v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The next-to-leading order weak-coupling shear viscosity of QCD was computed 6 years ago.
  However, these results have never been applied at finite baryon chemical potential $\mu$, even though intermediate-energy heavy ion collisions and merging neutron stars may explore the Quark-Gluon Plasma in a regime where baryon chemical potentials are large.
  Here, we extend the next-to-leading order shear viscosity calculations to finite $\mu$, and we show that, while the convergence of the weak-coupling expansion is questionable for achievable plasmas, it is somewhat better at $\mu &gt; T$ than at $\mu=0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00524v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Isabella Danhoni, Guy D. Moore</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the role of nuclear parameters on oscillation modes in hot Neutron Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00739</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00739v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent studies have revealed that certain nuclear parameters are more dominant than others in governing global neutron star properties, such as its structure or oscillation mode characteristics. Although neutron stars can in general assumed to be cold, in astrophysical scenarios such as newly born neutron stars or remnants of binary neutron star mergers, finite temperature effects play a non-negligible role. In this work, we perform a consistent and systematic investigation of the role of nuclear parameters and thermal effects on neutron star properties and fluid oscillation modes within a full general relativistic scheme. We impose constraints on the parameter space of the relativistic mean field model using state-of-the-art information from terrestrial experiments and multi-messenger astrophysical data. We find effective nucleon mass to be the most important nuclear parameter controlling astrophysical observables of hot neutron stars, similar to the cold beta equilibrated matter. However, we conclude that the interplay among saturation properties and astrophysical observables depends not only on the thermal configurations considered but also on the constraints imposed. We also investigated the role of nuclear saturation parameters on some universal relations for hot NSs which are important in gravitational wave asteroseismology. Our investigation confirmed that these relations are mostly insensitive to nuclear saturation properties and mainly affected by variation of charge fraction in the star.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00739v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nilaksha Barman, Bikram Keshari Pradhan, Debarati Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Compositeness of near-threshold $s$-wave resonances</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.12635</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.12635v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The near-threshold clustering phenomenon is well understood by the low-energy universality, for shallow bound states below the threshold. Nevertheless, the characteristics of resonances slightly above the threshold still lack thorough elucidation. We introduce a novel probabilistic interpretation scheme for complex compositeness of resonances, in which resonances with unphysically large decay widths are inherently excluded. Employing this scheme to analyze resonances via the effective range expansion, we demonstrate that near-threshold resonances have small composite fraction, in sharp contrast to shallow bound states below the threshold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.12635v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomona Kinugawa, Tetsuo Hyodo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A three-parameter characterization of neutron stars' mass-radius relation and equation of state</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17647v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Numerous models of neutron star (NS) equation of state (EoS) exist based on different superdense-matter physics approaches. Nevertheless, some NS properties show universal (EoS-independent) relations. Here, we propose a novel class of such universalities. Despite different physics inputs, a wide class of realistic nucleonic, hyperonic, and hybrid EoS models can be accurately described using only three parameters. For a given EoS, these are the mass and radius of the maximum-mass NS (or pressure and density in its center) and the radius of a half-maximum-mass star. With such a parametrization, we build universal analytic expressions for mass-radius and pressure-density relations. They form a semi-analytic mapping from the mass-radius relation to the EoS in NS cores (the so-called inverse Oppenheimer-Volkoff mapping). This mapping simplifies the process of inferring the EoS from observations of NS masses and radii. Applying it to current NS observations we set new limits on the high-density end of the EoS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17647v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dmitry D. Ofengeim, Peter S. Shternin, Tsvi Piran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measuring differential particle correlations in relativistic nuclear collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.19169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.19169v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study explores the transverse momentum ($p_T$) dependencies of Symmetric and Asymmetric Correlations (SC and ASC) with one and two particles of interest in Au+Au collisions at 200 GeV. Leveraging the AMPT model, the investigation delves into the sensitivity of these correlations to the final state effects, providing valuable insights into their potential for constraining the final state effects' $p_T$ dependencies. The HIJING model is employed as a benchmark for non-flow correlations, shedding light on their impact on interpreting SC and ASC data. Moreover, the study points out that differential SC and ASC with one and two particles of interest (POIs) typically incorporate contributions from event-plane angle fluctuations. Consequently, this work highlights the significance of SC and ASC with one and two POIs as valuable tools for investigating the $p_T$ nature of the final state effects and advocates for comprehensive experimental measurements across various beam energies and system sizes to enhance our understanding and provide additional constraints for theoretical models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.19169v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Niseem Magdy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic $|G_E/G_M|$ ratios of hyperons at large timelike $q^2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21397v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In recent years, it has become possible to measure not only the magnitude of the electric ($G_E$) and magnetic ($G_M$) form factors of spin $\frac{1}{2}$ baryons, but also to measure the relative phases of those quantities in the timelike kinematic region. Aiming to interpret present $|G_E/G_M|$ data on hyperons of the baryon octet, as well as to predict future data, we present model calculations of that ratio for large invariant 4-momentum square $q^2$ in the timelike region ($q^2&gt;0$). Without any further parameter fitting, we extend to the timelike region a covariant quark model previously developed to describe the kinematic spacelike region ($q^2 \le 0$) of the baryon octet form factors. The model takes into account both the effects of valence quarks and the excitations of the meson cloud which dresses the baryons. We report here that our results are in good agreement with very recent data from BESIII, within the uncertainty limits of our model. We also make new predictions which may be tested in the near future, when the range of the present measurements is expanded to the 20--50 GeV$^2$ region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21397v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Ramalho, M. T. Pe\~na, K. Tsushima, Myung-Ki Cheoun</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
