<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 04:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Neutron skins: A perspective from dispersive optical models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16097</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16097v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An overview is presented of neutron skin predictions obtained using an empirical nonlocal dispersive optical model (DOM). The DOM links both scattering and bound-state experimental data through a subtracted dispersion relation which allows for fully-consistent, data-informed predictions for nuclei where such data exists. Large skins were predicted for both ${}^{48}$Ca ($R^{48}_\textrm{skin}=0.25 \pm 0.023$ fm in 2017) and $^{208}$Pb ($R^{208}_\textrm{skin}=0.25 \pm 0.05$ fm in 2020). While the DOM prediction in $^{208}$Pb is within 1$\sigma$ of the subsequent PREX-2 measurement, the DOM prediction in $^{48}$Ca is over 2$\sigma$ larger than the thin neutron skin resulting from CREX. From the moment it was revealed, the thin skin in ${}^{48}$Ca has puzzled the nuclear-physics community as no adequate theories simultaneously predict both a large skin in ${}^{208}$Pb and a small skin in ${}^{48}$Ca. The DOM is unique in its ability to treat both structure and reaction data on the same footing, providing a unique perspective on this $R_\textrm{skin}$ puzzle. It appears vital that more neutron data be measured in both the scattering and bound-state domain for ${}^{48}$Ca to clarify the situation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16097v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. C. Atkinson, W. H. Dickhoff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gamow shell model description of neutron-rich He hyper-isotopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16223v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Gamow shell model (GSM) framework has been extended to the study of weakly bound hypernuclei. As a first application, the neutron-rich He hyper-isotope chains, from 6{\Lambda}He to 9{\Lambda}He have been investigated to accurately account for the loosely bound or neutron-unbound character of hypernuclear many-body states. The energy spectra calculated with a phenomenological Hamiltonian show good agreement with experimental data. In particular, neutron-emitting resonant states are predicted for the neutron-rich nuclei 5-7He and the hypernucleus 6{\Lambda}He. Furthermore, one-neutron densities exhibit the long-range character of weakly bound and resonant states. This study demonstrates that GSM is a practical tool for describing the complex structure of hypernuclei, especially for those close to drip lines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16223v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Li, N. Michel, J. G. Li, Xian-Rong Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of nuclear deformation and orientation about symmetry axis of target nucleus on heavy-ion fusion dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16436v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nuclear shape and orientation degrees of freedom are incorporated into the calculation of the double-folding nuclear potential within the relativistic mean-field (RMF) formalism. The quadrupole deformations ($\beta_2$), nuclear densities and the effective nucleon-nucleon (NN) interaction potential are obtained using the RMF approach for the Hybrid, NL3$^*$ and NL3 parameterizations. The calculated quadrupole deformations are included in the target densities through the nuclear radius. The deformation and orientation-dependent microscopic nuclear potentials are further employed to obtain fusion barrier characteristics and cross-sections for 12 even-even heavy-ion reactions with doubly magic spherical $^{16}$O and $^{48}$Ca as projectiles along with deformed targets from different mass regions. The results obtained for the relativistic R3Y NN potential are compared with those of the Reid version of the non-relativistic M3Y NN potential as well as with the available experimental data. A decrease in the barrier height and increase in the cross-section is observed upon the inclusion of target quadrupole deformations in the nuclear density distributions at the target orientation angles, $\theta_2\le58^\circ$ for the R3Y NN potential and at $\theta_2\le60^\circ$ for the M3Y NN potential. On comparing the $\theta_2$-integrated cross-section calculated using M3Y and R3Y NN potentials with spherical and deformed densities, one observes that the deformed densities and the relativistic R3Y NN potential obtained for the Hybrid parameter set provide better agreement with the available experimental data for all the considered reactions. Moreover, the modifications in the characteristics of the fusion barrier and hence in the cross-section with the inclusion of nuclear shape degrees of freedom and orientations are found to become more prominent in reactions forming heavier compound nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16436v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.110.024601</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. C 110, 024601 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shilpa Rana, M. Bhuyan, Raj Kumar, B. V. Carlson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Persistence of the N = 50 shell closure over the isotopic chains of Sc, Ti, V and Cr nuclei using relativistic energy density functional</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16588</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16588v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The analytical expression of the density-dependent binding energy per nucleon for the relativistic mean field (RMF), also known as the relativistic energy density functional (Relativistic-EDF), is used to obtain the isospin-dependent symmetry energy and its components for the isotopic chain of Sc, Ti, V, and Cr nuclei. The procedure of the coherent density fluctuation model is employed to formulate the Relativistic-EDF and Brueckner energy density functional (Brueckner-EDF) at local density. A few signatures of shell and/or sub-shell closure are observed in the symmetry energy and its components, i.e., surface and volume symmetry energy, far from the beta-stable region for odd-A Sc and V, and even-even Ti and Cr nuclei with non-linear NL3 and G3 parameter sets. A comparison is made with the results obtained from Relativistic-EDF and Brueckner-EDF with both NL3 and G3 for the considered isotopic chains. We find Relativistic-EDF outperforms the Brueckner-EDF in predicting the shell and/or sub-shell closure of neutron-rich isotopes at N = 50 for these atomic nuclei. Moreover, a relative comparison has been made for the results obtained with the non-linear NL3 and G3 parameter sets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16588v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S0217732323501146</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Modern Physics Letters A Vol. 38, No. 24n25, 2350114 (2023)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Praveen K. Yadav, Raj Kumar, M. Bhuyan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distinguishing the sources of dielectron anisotropic flow at low beam energies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16603v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present calculations of dielectron anisotropic flow in heavy-ion collisions at HADES beam energies from a hadronic transport approach. The ongoing experimental analysis employs the traditional reaction plane method to evaluate the flow coefficients $v_n$ and claims to see isotropic radiation from the thermal quark-gluon plasma. We show in this work, that in the region above the pion mass, the dilepton flow measurement might suffer from cancellation effects that mask the complicated underlying dynamics. Contributions from different baryonic and mesonic resonances show collective behaviour with different signs and lead to an overall vanishing elliptic flow. To differentiate the different contributions, we propose to employ the scalar product method, which exploits the previously measured hadronic flow to create different reference planes. As a proof of concept, we calculate the $v_2$ of dielectrons for Ag+Ag collisions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}}=2.55$ $\mathrm{GeV}$ with both methods and investigate the contribution of each source, concluding that the scalar product method provides the proton and pion tagged flow coefficients as two distinct measurements, disentangling the various dilepton sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16603v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renan Hirayama, Hannah Elfner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bounds on the minimum sound speed above neutron star densities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16738</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16738v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that the existence of massive neutron stars and asymptotic freedom of QCD place robust upper bounds on the lowest sound speed of the ultra-dense matter unattainable in neutron stars. Our approach does not rely on explicitly representing the equation of state in the density range $\sim 2-40 n_0$, and does not require probabilistic interpretations. The upper limit decreases rapidly when the maximum mass of neutron stars is greater than about $2.5M_\odot$. Discovery of $\sim 3 M_\odot$ neutron stars would strongly support first-order phase transitions at high baryon densities</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16738v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dake Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The X17 boson and the d(p,e+ e-)3He and d(n,e+ e-)3H processes: a theoretical analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16744v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The present work deals with the e+ e- pair production in the d(p,e+e-)3He and d(n,e+ e-)3H processes, in order to evidentiate possible effects due to the exchange of a hypothetical low-mass boson, the so-called X17. These processes are studied for energies of the incident beams in the range 18-30 MeV, in order to have a sufficient energy to produce such a boson, whose mass is estimated to be around 17 MeV. We first analyze them as a purely electromagnetic processes, in the context of a state-of-the-art approach to nuclear strong-interaction dynamics and nuclear electromagnetic currents, derived from chiral effective field theory chiEFT. Next, we examine how the exchange of a hypothetical low-mass boson would impact the cross sections for such processes. We consider several possibilities, that this boson is either a scalar, pseudoscalar, vector, or axial particle. The main aim of the study is to exploit the specular structure of the 3He and 3H nuclei to investigate the isospin dependency of the X17-nucleon interaction, as the alleged "proto-phobicity".</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16744v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Viviani, E. Filandri, L. Girlanda, C. Gustavino, A. Kievsky, L. E. Marcucci</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum decoherence from complex saddle points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16627</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16627v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum decoherence is the effect that bridges quantum physics to well-understood classical physics. As such, it plays a crucial role in understanding the mysterious nature of quantum physics represented by Schr\"odinger's cat, for example. Quantum decoherence is also a source of quantum noise that has to be well under control in quantum computing and in various experiments based on quantum technologies. Here we point out that quantum decoherence can be captured by $\textit{complex}$ saddle points in the Feynman path integral in much the same way as quantum tunneling can be captured by instantons. In particular, we present some first-principle calculations in the Caldeira-Leggett model, which reproduce the predicted scaling behavior of quantum decoherence with respect to the parameters of the environment such as the temperature and the coupling to the system of interest. We also discuss how to extend our work to general models by Monte Carlo calculations using a recently developed method to overcome the sign problem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16627v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Nishimura, Hiromasa Watanabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flavor Dependence of Charged Pion Fragmentation Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16640v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We have measured the flavor dependence of multiplicities for pi^+ and pi^- production in semi-inclusive deep-inelastic scattering (SIDIS) on proton and deuteron targets to explore a possible charge symmetry violation in fragmentation functions. The experiment used an electron beam with energies of 10.2 and 10.6 GeV at Jefferson Lab and the Hall-C spectrometers. The electron kinematics spanned the range 0.3&lt;x&lt;0.6, 2&lt;Q^2&lt;5.5 GeV^2, and 4&lt;W^2&lt;11 GeV^2. The pion fractional momentum range was 0.3&lt; z &lt;0.7, and the transverse momentum range was 0&lt;p_T&lt;0.25 GeV/c. Assuming factorization at low p_T and allowing for isospin breaking, we find that the results can be described by two ``favored" and two ``un-favored" effective low $p_T$ fragmentation functions that are flavor-dependent. However, they converge to a common flavor-independent value at the lowest x or highest W of this experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16640v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Bhatt, P. Bosted, S. Jia, W. Armstrong, D. Dutta, R. Ent, D. Gaskell, E. Kinney, H. Mkrtchyan, S. Ali, R. Ambrose, D. Androic, C. Ayerbe Gayoso, A. Bandari, V. Berdnikov, D. Bhetuwal, D. Biswas, M. Boer, E. Brash, A. Camsonne, J. P. Chen, J. Chen, M. Chen, E. M. Christy, S. Covrig, S. Danagoulian, M. Diefenthaler, B. Duran, M. Elaasar, C. Elliot, H. Fenker, E. Fuchey, J. O. Hansen, F. Hauenstein, T. Horn, G. M. Huber, M. K. Jones, M. L. Kabir, A. Karki, B. Karki, S. J. D. Kay, C. Keppel, V. Kumar, N. Lashley-Colthirst, W. B. Li, D. Mack, S. Malace, P. Markowitz, M. McCaughan, E. McClellan, D. Meekins, R. Michaels, A. Mkrtchyan, G. Niculescu, I. Niculescu, B. Pandey, S. Park, E. Pooser, M. Rehfuss, B. Sawatzky, G. R. Smith, H. Szumila-Vance, A. S. Tadepalli, V. Tadevosyan, R. Trotta, H. Voskanyan, S. A. Wood, Z. Ye, C. Yero, X. Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pseudogap regime of the unitary Fermi gas with lattice auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo in the continuum limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.16676</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.16676v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The unitary Fermi gas (UFG) is a strongly correlated system of two-species (spin-1/2) fermions with a short-range attractive interaction modeled by a contact interaction and has attracted much interest across different disciplines. The UFG is considered a paradigm for strongly correlated superfluids and has been investigated extensively, with generally good agreement found between theory and experiment. However, the extent of a pseudogap regime above the critical temperature $T_c$ for superfluidity is still debated both theoretically and experimentally. Here we study thermodynamic properties of the UFG across the superfluid phase transition using finite-temperature lattice auxiliary-field quantum Monte Carlo (AFMC) methods in the canonical ensemble of fixed particle numbers. We extrapolate our lattice AFMC results to the continuous time and continuum limits, thus removing the systematic error associated with the finite filling factor of previous AFMC studies. We determine the critical temperature to be $T_c=0.16(1)\, T_{F}$. For the largest particle number studied $N=114$, the energy-staggering pairing gap is suppressed above a pairing scale temperature of $T^{*}\approx 0.2\,T_F$. The spin susceptibility displays moderate suppression above $T_c$ with a spin gap temperature of $T_s\approx 0.2 \,T_F$. We also calculate a free energy-staggering pairing gap, which shows substantially reduced statistical errors when compared with the energy-staggering gap, allowing for a clear signature of pairing correlations in the finite-size system. All results indicate that the pseudogap regime is narrow, with pseudogap signatures emerging at temperatures below $T^{*}\approx 0.2 \, T_F$. The reduced statistical errors of the free energy gap enable an extrapolation at low temperatures, allowing an estimate of the zero-temperature pairing gap $\Delta_E = 0.576(24) \, \epsilon_F$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.16676v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Jensen, C. N. Gilbreth, Y. Alhassid</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine learning study to identify collective flow in small and large colliding systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.09937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.09937v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Collective flow has been found to be similar between small colliding systems ($p$ $+$ $p$ and $p$ $+$ A collisions) and large colliding systems (peripheral A $+$ A collisions) at the CERN Large Hadron Collider. In order to study the differences of collective flow between small and large colliding systems, we employ a point cloud network to identify $p$ $+$ Pb collisions and peripheral Pb $+$ Pb collisions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}} =$ 5.02 TeV generated from a multiphase transport model (AMPT). After removing the discrepancies in the pseudorapidity distribution and the $p_{\rm T}$ spectra, we capture the discrepancy in collective flow. Although the verification accuracy of our PCN is limited due to similar event-by-event distributions of elliptic and triangular flow, we demonstrate that collective flow between $p$ $+$ Pb collisions and peripheral Pb $+$ Pb collisions becomes more distinct with increasing final hadron multiplicity and parton scattering cross section. This study not only highlights the potential of PCN techniques in advancing the understanding of collective flow in varying colliding systems, but more importantly lays the groundwork for the future PCN-related research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.09937v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.110.024910</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.C 110 (2024) 2, 024910</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shuang Guo, Han-Sheng Wang, Kai Zhou, Guo-Liang Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing collectivity in heavy-ion collisions with fluctuations of the $p_T$ spectrum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.17313v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Event-by-event fluctuations in the initial stages of ultrarelativistic nucleus-nucleus collisions depend little on rapidity. The hydrodynamic expansion which occurs in later stages then gives rise to correlations among outgoing particles which depend weakly on their relative rapidity. Azimuthal correlations, through which anisotropic flow ($v_n(p_T)$) is defined, have been the most studied. Here we study a new observable introduced in 2020 by Schenke, Shen and Teaney and dubbed $v_0(p_T)$, which quantifies the relative change in the $p_T$ spectrum induced by a fluctuation. We describe how it can be measured. Using hydrodynamic simulations, we make quantitative predictions for $v_0(p_T)$ of charged and identified hadrons. We then discuss how $v_0(p_T)$ relates to two phenomena which have been measured: The increase of the mean transverse momentum in ultracentral collisions, and the event-by-event fluctuations of the transverse momentum per particle $[ p_T]$. We show that $v_0(p_T)$ determines the dependence of these quantities on the $p_T$ cuts implemented in the analysis. We quantitatively explain the rise of $\sigma_{p_T}$ observed by ATLAS as the upper $p_T$-cut is increased from $2$ to $5$~GeV/$c$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.17313v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2024.138985</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physics Letters B, Volume 857, October 2024, 138985</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tribhuban Parida, Rupam Samanta, Jean-Yves Ollitrault</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vertex correction to nuclear matrix elements of double-$\beta$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.13254</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.13254v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The predicted neutrinoless double-$\beta$ ($0\nu\beta\beta$) decay is the crucial phenomenon to prove the existence of the Majorana neutrino, which gives a foundation to leptogenesis to explain the matter prevalence of the universe. The nuclear matrix element (NME) of $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay is an important theoretical quantity to determine the effective neutrino mass and help the detector design for the next generation of the $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay search. Reliable calculation of this NME is a long-standing problem because of the diversity of the predicted values of the NME. The main reason for this difficulty is that the effective strength of the Gamow-Teller transition operator $g_A$ for this decay is unknown. I will show the lowest-order vertex corrections for the $0\nu\beta\beta$ and the $2\nu\beta\beta$ NME of $^{136}$Xe in the framework of the hybrid application of the quantum field theory to the leptons and the Rayleigh-Schr\"{o}dinger perturbation to the nucleus. The unperturbed nuclear states are obtained by the quasiparticle random-phase approximation. These corrections reduce the $0\nu\beta\beta$ NME by 30%. The effective $g_A$ referring to this reduced NME is also obtained, and it is shown for the first time that the effective $g_A$ for the $0\nu\beta\beta$ NME is not quite different from that for the $2\nu\beta\beta$ NME; the difference is only 10%. This indicates the possibility that the phenomenological effective $g_A$ to reproduce the experimental half-life of the $2\nu\beta\beta$ decay can be approximately used for the calculation of the $0\nu\beta\beta$ NME.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.13254v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Terasaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for baryon junctions in photonuclear processes and isobar collisions at RHIC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2205.05685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2205.05685v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: During the early development of Quantum Chromodynamics, it was proposed that baryon number could be carried by a non-perturbative Y-shaped topology of gluon fields, called the gluon junction, rather than by the valence quarks as in the QCD standard model. A puzzling feature of ultra-relativistic nucleus-nucleus collisions is the apparent substantial baryon excess in the midrapidity region that could not be adequately accounted for in most conventional models of quark and diquark transport. The transport of baryonic gluon junctions is predicted to lead to a characteristic exponential distribution of net-baryon density with rapidity and could resolve the puzzle. In this context we point out that the rapidity density of net-baryons near midrapidity indeed follows an exponential distribution with a slope of $-0.61\pm0.03$ as a function of beam rapidity in the existing global data from A+A collisions at AGS, SPS and RHIC energies. To further test if quarks or gluon junctions carry the baryon quantum number, we propose to study the absolute magnitude of the baryon vs. charge stopping in isobar collisions at RHIC. We also argue that semi-inclusive photon-induced processes ($\gamma+p$/A) at RHIC kinematics provide an opportunity to search for the signatures of the baryon junction and to shed light onto the mechanisms of observed baryon excess in the mid-rapidity region in ultra-relativistic nucleus-nucleus collisions. Such measurements can be further validated in A+A collisions at the LHC and $e+p$/A collisions at the EIC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2205.05685v5</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjc/s10052-024-12834-2</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. C (2024) 84:590</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nicole Lewis, Wendi Lv, Mason Alexander Ross, Chun Yuen Tsang, James Daniel Brandenburg, Zi-Wei Lin, Rongrong Ma, Zebo Tang, Prithwish Tribedy, Zhangbu Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new formulation of strong-field magnetohydrodynamics for neutron stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.01636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.01636v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a formulation of magnetohydrodynamics which can be used to describe the evolution of strong magnetic fields in neutron star interiors. Our approach is based on viewing magnetohydrodynamics as a theory with a one-form global symmetry and developing an effective field theory for the hydrodynamic modes associated with this symmetry. In the regime where the local velocity and temperature variations can be neglected, we derive the most general constitutive relation consistent with symmetry constraints for the electric field in the presence of a strong magnetic field. This constitutive relation not only reproduces the phenomena of Ohmic decay, ambipolar diffusion, and Hall drift derived in a phenomenological model by Goldreich and Reisenegger, but also reveals new terms in the evolution of the magnetic field which cannot easily be seen from such microscopic models. This formulation gives predictions for novel diffusion behaviors of small perturbations around a constant background magnetic field, and for the two-point correlation functions among various components of the electric and magnetic fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.01636v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shreya Vardhan, Sa\v{s}o Grozdanov, Samuel Leutheusser, Hong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic field at nucleus for ionized atoms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.14535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.14535v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The study of the magnetic properties of atoms and nuclei was performed. A linear dependence between the strength of the magnetic field at the nucleus and the effective charge divided by the major quantum number were analyzed and explained. The calculations of the magnetic field at the nucleus were done for a wide set of electron configurations within the framework of relativistic Dirac-Hartree-Fock method. Results are compared to experimental results of $g$-factor measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.14535v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrzej Tucholski, Zygmunt Patyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Simulation-Based Inference of the Neutron Star Equation of State directly from Telescope Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.00287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.00287v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Neutron stars provide a unique opportunity to study strongly interacting matter under extreme density conditions. The intricacies of matter inside neutron stars and their equation of state are not directly visible, but determine bulk properties, such as mass and radius, which affect the star's thermal X-ray emissions. However, the telescope spectra of these emissions are also affected by the stellar distance, hydrogen column, and effective surface temperature, which are not always well-constrained. Uncertainties on these nuisance parameters must be accounted for when making a robust estimation of the equation of state. In this study, we develop a novel methodology that, for the first time, can infer the full posterior distribution of both the equation of state and nuisance parameters directly from telescope observations. This method relies on the use of neural likelihood estimation, in which normalizing flows use samples of simulated telescope data to learn the likelihood of the neutron star spectra as a function of these parameters, coupled with Hamiltonian Monte Carlo methods to efficiently sample from the corresponding posterior distribution. Our approach surpasses the accuracy of previous methods, improves the interpretability of the results by providing access to the full posterior distribution, and naturally scales to a growing number of neutron star observations expected in the coming years.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.00287v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.IM</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Len Brandes, Chirag Modi, Aishik Ghosh, Delaney Farrell, Lee Lindblom, Lukas Heinrich, Andrew W. Steiner, Fridolin Weber, Daniel Whiteson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetric cumulant $sc_{2,4} \left \{ 4 \right \}$ and asymmetric cumulant $ac_{2} \left \{ 3 \right \}$ from transverse momentum conservation and flow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.05782</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.05782v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Multiparticle cumulants method can be used to reveal long-range collectivity in small and large colliding systems. The four-particle symmetric cumulant $sc_{2,4} \left \{ 4 \right \}$, three-particle asymmetric cumulant $ac_{2} \left \{ 3 \right \}$, and the normalized cumulants $nsc_{2,4} \left \{ 4 \right \}$ and $nac_{2} \left \{ 3 \right \}$ from the transverse momentum conservation and flow are calculated. The interplay between the two effects is also investigated. Our results are in a good agreement with the recent ATLAS measurements of multiparticle azimuthal correlations with the subevent cumulant method, which provides insight into the origin of collective flow in small systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.05782v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.110.024901</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.C 110 (2024) 2, 024901</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Lin Pei, Guo-Liang Ma, Adam Bzdak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the (in)consistency of perturbation theory at finite temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.02009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.02009v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A well-known difficulty of perturbative approaches to quantum field theory at finite temperature is the necessity to address theoretical constraints that are not present in the vacuum theory. In this work, we use lattice simulations of scalar correlation functions in massive $\phi^{4}$ theory to analyse the extent to which these constraints affect the perturbative predictions. We find that the standard perturbative predictions deteriorate even in the absence of infrared divergences at relatively low temperatures, and that this is directly connected to the analytic structure of the propagators used in the expansion. This suggests that the incorporation of non-perturbative thermal effects in the propagators is essential for a consistent perturbative formulation of scalar quantum field theories at finite temperature. By utilising the spectral constraints imposed on finite-temperature correlation functions, we explore how these effects manifest themselves in the lattice data, and discuss why the presence of distinct thermoparticle excitations provides a potential resolution to these issues.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.02009v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP08(2024)167</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JHEP 08 (2024) 167</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Peter Lowdon, Owe Philipsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Corrections to adiabatic behavior for long paths</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10294v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The cost and the error of the adiabatic theorem for preparing the final eigenstate are discussed in terms of path length. Previous studies in terms of the norm of the Hamiltonian and its derivatives with the spectral gap are limited in their ability to describe the cost of adiabatic state preparation for certain physically large systems. We argue that total time is not a good measure for determining the computational difficulty of adiabatic quantum computation by developing a no-go theorem. From the result of time-periodic Hamiltonian cases, we suggest that there are proxies for computational cost which typically grow as path length increases when the error is kept fixed and small and consider possible conjectures on how general the behavior is.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10294v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas D. Cohen, Hyunwoo Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Backward DVCS on the pion in Sullivan processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03011</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03011v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The purpose of this work is to do a systematic feasibility study of measuring in backward region deeply virtual Compton scattering on the pion in Sullivan processes in the framework of collinear QCD factorization where pion to photon transition distribution amplitudes (TDAs) describe the photon content of the $\pi$ meson. Our approach employs TDAs based on the overlap of light front wave functions, using a previously developed pion light-front wave function and deriving a consistent model for the light front wave functions of the photon. This work is expected to lead us to an estimate of the cross-sections that could be measured in the future U.S. and China's electron-ion colliders. It will also provide a comparison with the forward Sullivan DVCS case, which gives access to pion GPDs and for which a strong signal is expected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03011v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 30 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abigail Rodrigues Castro, Cedric Mezrag, Jose M. Morgado Ch\'avez, Bernard Pire</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
