<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 05:00:03 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven analysis of dipole strength functions using artificial neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02876</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02876v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a data-driven analysis of dipole strength functions across the nuclear chart, employing an artificial neural network to model and predict nuclear dipole responses. We train the network on a dataset of experimentally measured dipole strength functions for 216 different nuclei. To assess its predictive capability, we test the trained model on an additional set of 10 new nuclei, where experimental data exist. Our results demonstrate that the artificial neural network not only accurately reproduces known data but also identifies potential inconsistencies in certain experimental datasets, indicating which results may warrant further review or possible rejection. Additionally, for nuclei where experimental data are sparse or unavailable, the network confirms theoretical calculations, reinforcing its utility as a predictive tool in nuclear physics. Finally, utilizing the predicted electric dipole polarizability, we extract the value of the symmetry energy at saturation density and find it consistent with results from the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02876v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiguang Jiang, Tim Egert, Sonia Bacca, Francesca Bonaiti, Peter von Neumann Cosel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Landau quantization on neutrino emission and absorption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02925</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02925v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Some neutron stars known as magnetars possess very strong magnetic fields, with surface fields as large as $10^{15}\,\rm G$ and internal fields that are possibly stronger. Recent observations of the radio pulsar GLEAM-X J1627 suggest it may have a surface field as strong as $10^{16} \,\rm G$. In the presence of a strong magnetic field, the energy levels of electrons and protons are quantized and the Direct Urca process allows neutron stars to cool rapidly, even at low density. For the case of magnetic fields $B \geq 10^{16}\,\rm G$, we find features in the emissivity due to energy quantization that are not captured by the frequently employed quasiclassical approximation where energy levels are treated as nearly continuous. Resonances can result in amplification of the neutrino emissivity at specific densities compared to a calculation that neglects quantization, particularly at low temperature. These effects are not important for the thermal evolution of an entire neutron star, but may be relevant for phenomena that depend on behavior at specific densities. We present a fully relativistic calculation of the Direct Urca rate in a strong magnetic field using the standard V-A weak Lagrangian incorporating mean field nuclear effects and discuss approaches to the numerical challenge the modified wavefunctions present and a new semi-analytic approximation. These tools are also applicable to calculating neutrino opacities in strong magnetic fields in the ejecta of binary neutron star mergers. We calculate the opacities for neutrinos capturing on free nucleons at sub-saturation densities and temperatures exceeding an MeV. We find an enhancement to capture processes of the lowest energy neutrinos by an order of magnitude or more due to suppression of electron Pauli blocking in the case of capture on neutrons, and from the effect of the nucleon magnetic moments in the case of capture on protons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02925v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mia Kumamoto, Catherine Welch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized susceptibilities of net-baryon number based on the 3-dimensional Ising universality class</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03014v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Assuming the equilibrium of the QCD system, we have investigated the critical behavior of sixth-, eighth- and tenth-order susceptibilities of net-baryon number, through mapping the results in the three-dimensional Ising model to that of QCD. Both the leading critical contribution as well as sub-leading critical contribution from the Ising model are discussed. When considering only the leading critical contribution, the density plots for susceptibilities of the same order demonstrate a consistent general pattern independent on values of mapping parameters. As the critical point is approached from the crossover side, a negative dip followed by a positive peak is observed in the $\mu_B$ dependence of the three different orders of susceptibilities. When sub-leading critical contribution is taken into account, modifications become apparent in the density plots of the susceptibilities. The emergence of negative dips in the $\mu_B$ dependence of the susceptibilities is not an absolute phenomenon, while the positive peak structure is a more robust feature of the critical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03014v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xue Pan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of nuclear masses on r-process nucleosynthesis: bulk properties versus shell effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Decomposing theoretical nuclear mass predictions into a liquid-drop parametrization and local shell effects shows that r-process abundances are virtually insensitive to large variations of the masses which originate from nuclear bulk properties of the model, such as the symmetry energy. Therefore, experimental and theoretical studies of masses devoted to r-process applications, such as the nucleosynthesis in the ejecta of neutron star mergers, should focus on the physical origin of local changes in mass trends without necessarily providing highly accurate mass determinations of individual nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03243v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel A. Giuliani, Gabriel Mart\'inez-Pinedo, Andreas Bauswein, Vimal Vijayan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evolution of Shell Structure at $N=32$ and 34: Insights from Realistic Nuclear Forces and the Role of Tensor Component</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03265v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The evolution of nuclear shell structures at $N=32$ and 34 are studied in nuclei far from the stability line using effective interactions derived from realistic nuclear forces. The state-of-the-art \textit{ab initio} in-medium similarity renormalization group method is used for this purpose. The calculated results are consistent with experimental observations, and predictions are made where experimental data are unavailable. The shell gaps are analyzed from the evolution of effective single-particle energies, and various facets of nuclear interaction, such as central, spin-orbit, and tensor parts, are addressed by spin-tensor decomposition of the effective interactions. The roles played by these components in the development of shell closure, particularly by the tensor components, were highlighted throughout the study. Then, we discussed the low-lying structure of the exotic $N=32$ isotones below Ca. The present work demonstrates essential components of nuclear force in shaping magic numbers far from stability and provides deeper insights into the structure of exotic nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03265v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Subhrajit Sahoo, Praveen C. Srivastava</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of hyperons on structural properties of neutron stars and hybrid stars within four-dimensional Einstein-Gauss-Bonnet gravity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03348</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03348v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the impact of hyperons and phase transition to quark matter on the structural properties of neutron stars within the four-dimensional Einstein-Gauss-Bonnet gravity (EGB). We employ the density-dependent relativistic mean-field model (DDME2) for the hadronic phase and the density-dependent quark mass (DDQM) model for the quark phase to construct hadronic and hybrid equations of state (EoSs) that are consistent with the astrophysical constraints. The presence of hyperons softens the EoS and with a phase transition, the EoS further softens, and the speed of sound squared drops to around 0.2 for the maximum mass configuration which lies in the pure quark phase. Adjusting the Gaussian-Bonnet coupling constant $\alpha$ within its allowed range results in a decrease in the mass-radius relationship for negative $\alpha$, and an increase for positive $\alpha$. In addition, functions are fitted to the maximum mass and its associated radius as a function of constant $\alpha$ to observe its impact on these properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03348v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ishfaq Ahmad Rather, Grigoris Panotopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>General Relativistic Hartree-Fock Calculations for Neutron Star</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.02990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.02990v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the global structures of neutron stars within the framework of general relativity, treating the entire star as a quantum-degenerate system. Rather than relying on the Tolman-Oppenheimer-Volkoff (TOV) equation, we solve the Einstein-Cartan (EC) field equations self-consistently, incorporating the energy-momentum tensor contributions from neutrons. Neutron wave functions are obtained by solving the Dirac equation in a curved spacetime with both torsion and curvature effects. Given that neutron stars contain about 10^57 particles, we adopt a scaled h-bar approach to efficiently describe the quantum state of highly degenerate system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.02990v1</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoki Onishi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A deep neural network approach to solve the Dirac equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.03090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.03090v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We extend the method from [Naito, Naito, and Hashimoto, Phys. Rev. Research 5, 033189 (2023)] to solve the Dirac equation not only for the ground state but also for low-lying excited states using a deep neural network and the unsupervised machine learning technique. The variational method fails because of the Dirac sea, which is avoided by introducing the inverse Hamiltonian method. For low-lying excited states, two methods are proposed, which have different performances and advantages. The validity of this method is verified by the calculations with the Coulomb and Woods-Saxon potentials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.03090v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chuanxin Wang, Tomoya Naito, Jian Li, Haozhao Liang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-dependent nuclear energy-density functional theory toolkit for neutron star crust: Dynamics of a nucleus in a neutron superfluid</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17499</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17499v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a new numerical tool designed to probe the dense layers of neutron star crusts. It is based on the time-dependent Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov theory with generalized Skyrme nuclear energy-density functionals of the Brussels-Montreal family. We use it to study the time evolution of a nucleus accelerating through superfluid neutron medium in the inner crust of a neutron star. We extract an effective mass in the low velocity limit. We observe a threshold velocity and specify mechanisms of dissipation: phonon emission, Cooper pairs breaking, and vortex rings creation. These microscopic effects are of key importance for understanding various neutron star phenomena. Moreover, the mechanisms we describe are general and apply also to other fermionic superfluids interacting with obstacles like liquid helium or ultracold gases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17499v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevX.14.041054</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review X 14, 041054 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniel P\c{e}cak, Agata Zdanowicz, Nicolas Chamel, Piotr Magierski, Gabriel Wlaz{\l}owski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proto-neutron stars with quark cores</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.10386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.10386v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work investigates the evolution of proto-neutron stars (PNSs) from birth as neutrino-rich objects to maturity as cold-catalyzed neutrino-poor objects with nucleonic and non-nucleonic degrees of freedom. The focus is on the star's core where the nucleons, hyperons, and the $\Delta$-isobars are expected to dissolve into a ``soup" of deconfined quarks, at higher baryon densities, to establish a possible hadron-quark phase transition. We separately calculate the nuclear equations of state (EoS) for the hadronic matter (composed of all the baryon octet and $\Delta$-isobars) and the strange quark matter (SQM) under the same thermodynamic conditions characteristic of PNS and proto-strange star (PSS) evolution and construct the hybrid EoS using Maxwell's construction. The study allows us to determine the hadron-quark phase transitions along the evolution lines of the star. We observed a phase transition from hadronic matter to quark matter (QM) phase when the neutrinos have completely escaped from the star's core. The EoSs utilized are constrained to meet the $2\,\rm M_\odot$ threshold in accordance with the observational data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.10386v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adamu Issifu, D\'ebora P. Menezes, Zeinab Rezaei, Tobias Frederico</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Semiclassical Features of Wobbling and Chiral Properties in Nuclei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.11073</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.11073v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A semiclassical approach is used to describe the wobbling and chiral motion in even-even and odd-even nuclei The trial function involved in the variational equation for the quantal action is a coherent state for the SU(2 ) group associated to a triaxial rotor for the case of an even-even system and a coherent state for the group SU(2)$\otimes$ SU(2) describing the particle-core system. Application is made for $^{158}$Er and $^{161, 163, 165,167}$Lu, ${135}$Pr. Th parameters involved in the coherent state expression are complex numbers depending on time and play the role of the phase space generalized conjugate coordinates whose equation of motion may be brought to the Hamilton canonical form.Within a harmonic approximation one analytically obtains the wobbling frequencies which are further used to calculate the excitation energies for the states forming a band. A new procedure to quantize the classical orbitals is proposed. In the new picture the electromagnetic transition probabilities are calculated both for the in-band and the intraband transitions. Additionally, for odd systems, some other observable like aligned angular momentum, excitation energies relative to a reference spectrum, dynamic moment of energies are calculated and compared with the corresponding experimental data.In the parameter space one identified several nuclear phases with specific properties. An example is given where the wobbling and chiral motions coexist. The existence of a transversal wobbling is widely commented. A new boson representation for the angular momenta is proposed. The approach was successfully applied to $^{135}$Pr. One concludes that semiclassical description is an efficient tool to account quantitatively for the wobbling and chiral properties in nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.11073v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Apolodor Aristotel Raduta, Cristian Mircea Raduta, Robert Poenaru</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resummed spin hydrodynamics from quantum kinetic theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07143v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, the equations of dissipative relativistic spin hydrodynamics based on quantum kinetic theory are derived. Employing the inverse-Reynolds dominance (IReD) approach, a resummation scheme based on a power counting in Knudsen and inverse Reynolds numbers is constructed, leading to hydrodynamic equations that are accurate to second order. It is found that the spin dynamics can be characterized by eleven equations: six of them describe the evolution of the components of the spin potential, while the remaining five provide the equation of motion of a dissipative irreducible rank-two tensor. For a simple truncation, the first- and second-order transport coefficients are computed explicitly.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07143v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Wagner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of octupole shape degree of freedom in neutron-rich odd-mass xenon isotopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01262</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01262v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Influences of the octupole shape degree of freedom on low-energy spectra of neutron-rich odd-mass xenon isotopes are studied within the interacting boson-fermion model that is based on the nuclear density functional theory. The interacting-boson Hamiltonian describing low-energy quadrupole and octupole collective states of the even-even nuclei $^{140,142,144}$Xe, single-particle energies, and occupation probabilities for an unpaired neutron in the odd-mass nuclei $^{141,143,145}$Xe, are determined based on the axially symmetric quadrupole-octupole deformation-constrained self-consistent mean-field calculations with a choice of the energy density functional and pairing interaction. Strength parameters of the boson-fermion interactions are empirically determined to reproduce a few low-lying levels of each odd-mass nucleus. The mean-field calculation predicts for $^{142}$Xe a potential energy surface that is notably soft in the octupole deformation with a non-zero octupole global minimum. The octupole correlations are shown to be relevant in positive-parity excited states of $^{143,145}$Xe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01262v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.110.064306</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review C 110, 064306 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>K. Nomura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reveal short range interactions between $u/d$ quarks in the $NN$, $D_{03}$, and $D_{30}$ systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01993v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The dynamic mechanism of short range interactions between $u/d$ quarks remains an open and challenging problem. In order to reveal this quark dynamics, we perform a systematic analysis of $NN$, $D_{03}$, and $D_{30}$ systems in the (extended) chiral SU(3) constituent quark models. By comparing results calculated with different models and different parameter sets, the effects of one gluon exchange and vector meson exchange terms are carefully examined. The results indicate that the vector meson exchange interactions dominate the short range interactions between $u/d$ quarks, whereas the small residual one gluon exchange coupling strength is also allowed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01993v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s11433-024-2541-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sci.China Phys.Mech.Astron. 68 (2025) 232011</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Qi-Fang L\"u, Yu-Bing Dong, Peng-Nian Shen, Zong-Ye Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Circularly polarized photon emission from magnetized chiral plasmas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06271</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06271v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the emission of circularly polarized photons from a magnetized quark-gluon plasma with nonzero quark-number and chiral charge chemical potentials. These chemical potentials qualitatively influence the differential emission rates of circularly polarized photons. A nonzero net electric charge density, induced by quark-number chemical potentials, enhances the overall emission of one circular polarization over the other, while a nonzero chiral charge density introduces a spatial asymmetry in the emission with respect to reflection in the transverse plane. The signs of the electrical and chiral charge densities determine which circular polarization dominates overall and whether the emission preferentially aligns with or opposes the magnetic field. Based on these findings, we propose that polarized photon emission is a promising observable for characterizing the quark-gluon plasma produced in heavy-ion collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06271v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinyang Wang, Igor A. Shovkovy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlations and fluctuations in a magnetized PNJL model with and without inverse magnetic catalysis effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10217</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10217v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The correlation $\chi^{BQ}_{11}$ and quadratic fluctuations $\chi^B_2,\ \chi^Q_2,\ \chi^T_2$ of baryon number $B$, electric charge $Q$ and temperature $T$ are investigated in a two-flavor Polyakov loop extended Nambu-Jona-Lasinio (PNJL) model at finite temperature and magnetic field. The inverse magnetic catalysis (IMC) effect is introduced through the magnetic field dependent parameters $G(eB)$ or $T_0(eB)$, and we make comparison of the results in the cases with and without IMC effect. With nonvanishing magnetic field, the correlation $\chi^{BQ}_{11}$ and fluctuations $\chi^B_2,\ \chi^Q_2,\ \chi^T_2$ increase with temperature, and then show the peak around the pseudocritical temperatures of chiral restoration and deconfinement phase transitions in the cases with and without the IMC effect. The correlation and fluctuations along the phase transition line under external magnetic field are characterized by the scaled correlation ${\hat {\chi}}_{11}^{BQ}=\frac{\chi_{11}^{BQ}(eB,T_{pc}^c(eB))}{\chi_{11}^{BQ}(eB=0,T_{pc}^c(eB=0))}$ and scaled fluctuations ${\hat {\chi}}_2^{B(Q,T)}=\frac{\chi_2^{B(Q,T)}(eB,T_{pc}^c(eB))}{\chi_2^{B(Q,T)}(eB=0,T_{pc}^c(eB=0))}$ at the pseudocritical temperature $T_{pc}^c$ of chiral restoration phase transition. ${\hat {\chi}}_{11}^{BQ},\ {\hat {\chi}}_2^{B}$, and ${\hat {\chi}}_2^{Q}$ increase with magnetic fields, and the inclusion of IMC effect leads to some enhancement in their values. However, ${\hat {\chi}}_2^{T}$ is altered by the IMC effect. Without IMC effect, ${\hat \chi}^T_2$ slightly increases and then decreases with magnetic fields. Taking into account of the IMC effect by $G(eB)$, ${\hat \chi}^T_2$ monotonically increases with magnetic fields, and by $T_0(eB)$, it is a nonmonotonic function of magnetic field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10217v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shijun Mao</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
