<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2024 02:45:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Rotating Neutron Stars with the Relativistic Ab Initio Calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02878v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The equation of state (EOS) of extremely dense matter is crucial for understanding the properties of rotating neutron stars. Starting from the widely used realistic Bonn potentials rooted in a relativistic framework, we derive EOSs by performing the state-of-the-art relativistic Brueckner-Hartree-Fock (RBHF) calculations in the full Dirac space. The self-consistent and simultaneous consideration of both positive- and negative-energy states (NESs) of the Dirac equation allows us to avoid the uncertainties present in calculations where NESs are treated using approximations. To manifest the impact of rotational dynamics, several structural properties of neutron stars across a wide range of rotation frequencies and up to the Keplerian limit are obtained, including the gravitational and baryonic masses, the polar and equatorial radii, and the moments of inertia. Our theoretical predictions align well with the latest astrophysical constraints from the observations on massive neutron stars and joint mass-radius measurements. The maximum mass for rotating configurations can reach up to $2.93M_{\odot}$ for Bonn A potential, while the radius of a $1.4M_\odot$ neutron star for non-rotating case can be extended to around 17 km through the constant baryonic mass sequences. Relations with good universalities between the Keplerian frequency and static mass as well as radius are obtained, from which the radius of the black widow PSR J0952-0607 is predicted to be less than 19.58 km. Furthermore, to understand how rotation deforms the equilibrium shape of a neutron star, the eccentricity is also calculated. The approximate universality between the eccentricity at the Keplerian frequency and the gravitational mass is found.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02878v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoying Qu, Sibo Wang, Hui Tong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tetrahedral shape and Lambda impurity effect in $^{80}$Zr with a multidimensionally constrained relativistic Hartree-Bogoliubov model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02946</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02946v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates the tetrahedral structure in $^{80}$Zr and Lambda ($\Lambda$) impurity effect in $^{81}_{~\Lambda}$Zr using the multidimensionally constrained relativistic Hartree-Bogoliubov model. The ground states of both $^{80}$Zr and $^{81}_{~\Lambda}$Zr exhibit a tetrahedral configuration, accompanied by prolate and axial-octupole shape isomers. Our calculations reveal there are changes in the deformation parameters $\beta_{20}$, $\beta_{30}$, and $\beta_{32}$ upon $\Lambda$ binding to $^{80}$Zr, except for $\beta_{32}$ when $\Lambda$ occupies $p$-orbits. Compared to the two shape isomers, the $\Lambda$ particle exhibits weaker binding energy in the tetrahedral state when occupying the $1/2^+[000](\Lambda_s)$ or $1/2^-[110]$ single-particle states. In contrast, the strongest binding occurs for the $\Lambda$ particle in the $1/2^-[101]$ state with tetrahedral shape. Besides, a large $\Lambda$ separation energy may not necessarily correlate with a significant overlap between the density distributions of the $\Lambda$ particle and the nuclear core, particularly for tetrahedral hypernuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02946v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Yang, Yu-Ting Rong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Potential signature of new magicity from universal aspects of nuclear charge radii</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03076</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03076v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Shell quenching phenomena in nuclear charge radii are typically observed at the well-established neutron magic numbers. However, the recent discovery of potential new magic numbers at the neutron numbers $N = 32$ and $N = 34$ has sparked renewed interest in this mass region. This work further inspects into the charge radii of nuclei around the $N = 28$ shell closure using the relativistic Hartree-Bogoliubov model. We incorporate meson exchange and point-coupling effective nucleon-nucleon interactions alongside the Bogoliubov transformation for pairing corrections. To accurately capture the odd-even staggering and shell closure effects observed in charge radii, neutron-proton correlations around Fermi surface are explicitly considered. The charge radii of Ca and Ni isotopes are used to test the theoretical model and show an improvement with neutron-proton pairing corrections, in particular for neutron-rich isotopes. Our calculations reveal a inverted parabolic-like trend in the charge radii along the $N = 28$ isotones for proton numbers $Z$ between 20 and 28. Additionally, the shell closure effect of $Z = 28$ persists across the $N = 28$, 30, 32, and 34 isotonic chains, albeit with a gradual weakening trend. Notably, the significantly abrupt changes in charge radii are observed across $Z = 22$ along both the $N = 32$ and $N = 34$ isotonic chains. This kink at $Z = 22$ comes from the sudden decrease of the neuron-proton correlation around Fermi surfaces across $Z = 22$ for $N = 30$, 32, and 34 isotones, and might provide a signature for identifying the emergence of neutron magic numbers $N = 32$ and 34. Furthermore, the calculated charge radii for these isotonic chains ($N = 28$, 30, 32, and 34) can serve as reliable guidelines for future experimental measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03076v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dan Yang, Yu-Ting Rong, Rong An, Rui-Xiang Shi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable Quantum Simulations of Scattering in Scalar Field Theory on 120 Qubits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02486v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Simulations of collisions of fundamental particles on a quantum computer are expected to have an exponential advantage over classical methods and promise to enhance searches for new physics. Furthermore, scattering in scalar field theory has been shown to be BQP-complete, making it a representative problem for which quantum computation is efficient. As a step toward large-scale quantum simulations of collision processes, scattering of wavepackets in one-dimensional scalar field theory is simulated using 120 qubits of IBM's Heron superconducting quantum computer ibm_fez. Variational circuits compressing vacuum preparation, wavepacket initialization, and time evolution are determined using classical resources. By leveraging physical properties of states in the theory, such as symmetries and locality, the variational quantum algorithm constructs scalable circuits that can be used to simulate arbitrarily-large system sizes. A new strategy is introduced to mitigate errors in quantum simulations, which enables the extraction of meaningful results from circuits with up to 4924 two-qubit gates and two-qubit gate depths of 103. The effect of interactions is clearly seen, and is found to be in agreement with classical Matrix Product State simulations. The developments that will be necessary to simulate high-energy inelastic collisions on a quantum computer are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02486v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikita A. Zemlevskiy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sketch of the resolution of the axial U(1) problem without chiral anomaly</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.02792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.02792v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a mechanism which explains the masses of $\eta$ and $\eta'$ mesons without invoking the explicit violation of $U(1)_A$ symmetry by the chiral anomaly. It is shown that the U(1) problem, the problem for which the prediction of $\eta$ and $\eta'$ masses in the simple chiral perturbation theory largely deviates from the experimental values, is actually resolved by considering the first order contribution of the disconnected meson correlator with respect to the quark mass. The bound of Weinberg $m_\eta^2 \le 3 m_\pi^2$ is fulfilled by considering the negative squared mass of $\eta$ or $\eta'$ which is just the saddle point of the QCD effective potential, and 20% level agreements with experimental data are obtained by just fitting one low energy constant. We provide the leading chiral Lagrangian due to the disconnected contribution in 3-flavor QCD, and also discuss the 2- and 4-flavor cases as well as the consistency of our mechanism with the chiral restoration at high temperature found in lattice calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.02792v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nodoka Yamanaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice QCD calculation of the subtraction function in forward Compton amplitude</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03141v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The subtraction function plays a pivotal role in calculations involving the forward Compton amplitude, which is crucial for predicting the Lamb shift in muonic atom, as well as the proton-neutron mass difference. In this work, we present a lattice QCD calculation of the subtraction function using two domain wall fermion gauge ensembles at the physical pion mass. We utilize a recently proposed subtraction point, demonstrating its advantage in mitigating statistical and systematic uncertainties by eliminating the need for ground-state subtraction. Our results reveal significant contributions from $N\pi$ intermediate states to the subtraction function. Incorporating these contributions, we compute the proton, neutron and nucleon isovector subtraction functions at photon momentum transfer $Q^2\in[0,2]$ GeV$^2$. For the proton subtraction function, we compare our lattice results with chiral perturbation theory prediction at low $Q^2$ and with the results from the perturbative operator-product expansion at high $Q^2$. Finally, using these subtraction functions as input, we determine their contribution to two-photon exchange effects in the Lamb shift and isovector nucleon electromagnetic self-energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03141v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Fu, Xu Feng, Lu-Chang Jin, Chuan Liu, Shi-Da Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-extensive (3+1)-dimensional hydrodynamics for relativistic heavy-ion collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12405v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A non-extensive (3+1)-dimensional hydrodynamic model for multi-particle production processes, NEX-CLVisc, is developed in the framework of CLVisc where the viscous corrections are turned off. It assumes that the non-extensive effects consistently exist in the initial conditions set by the optical Glauber model, the equation of state and the hadron kinetic freeze-out procedure. The model is then applied to simulate the pseudo-rapidity ($\eta$) distribution, the transverse momentum ($p_{\rm T}$) spectra and the $p_{\rm T}$-differential elliptic flow ($v_2$) of charged particles in Pb-Pb collisions at $\sqrt{s_{\rm NN}}=$ 2.76 TeV and 5.02 TeV, respectively. It is found that the model can reasonably well reproduce the experimental data of the $\eta$ distribution and the charged-particle spectra in a $p_{\rm T}$ range up to 6-8 GeV/c. When compared with the ideal hydrodynamic model, the $p_{\rm T}$-differential $v_2$ of charged particles is suppressed in the NEX-CLVisc model, which is similar to that observed in the hydrodynamic model with a shear viscous correction. Moreover, due to the lack of the viscous corrections and the event-by-event fluctuation, the model can only describe the $p_{\rm T}$-differential $v_2$ up to 3-4 GeV/c, which is smaller than its applicable range for the particle $p_{\rm T}$ spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12405v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-Hao Shi, Zhi-Ying Qin, Jin-Peng Zhang, Jian Cao, Ze-Fang Jiang, Wen-Chao Zhang, Hua Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mode entanglement and isospin pairing in two-nucleon systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.12583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.12583v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we explore the entanglement and correlation in two-nucleon systems using isospin formalism. With the help of Slater decomposition, we derive analytical expressions for various entanglement measures. Specifically, we analyse the one- and two-mode entropies, mutual informations, and a basis-independent characteristic known as the one-body entanglement entropy.
  To understand the impact of pairing, we consider interactions involving isovector and isoscalar L=0 pairing terms. Our findings show that certain pairing interactions can maximize one-body entanglement entropy of ground states when both total angular momentum and total isospin have zero projections.
  We provide numerical examples for the sd shell and explore the mutual informations in LS coupled and jj coupled single-particle bases. We find that the shell structure and angular momentum coupling significantly impact the measures of entanglement. We outline the implications of conserving angular momentum and isospin on one-mode entropies, irrespective of particle number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.12583v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J Kov\'acs, A T Kruppa, \"O Legeza, P Salamon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic fluid dynamics in a 'hydro' frame</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.19015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.19015v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this letter, we investigate how field redefinition influences the spectrum of linearized perturbations in relativistic fluid dynamics. We show that the hydrodynamic modes do not get affected under local field redefinition, whereas the non-hydrodynamic modes do. These non-hydrodynamic modes can be removed through a suitable all-order field redefinition. This process leads to a new frame containing only hydrodynamic modes, which we refer to as the hydro frame. Additionally, we demonstrate that the resulting stress-energy tensor may constitute an infinite series in momentum space, with the radius of convergence associated with the removed non-hydrodynamic mode, highlighting its role in the hydrodynamic expansion's validity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.19015v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sayantani Bhattacharyya, Sukanya Mitra, Shuvayu Roy, Rajeev Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scattering wave packets of hadrons in gauge theories: Preparation on a quantum computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.00840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.00840v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum simulation holds promise of enabling a complete description of high-energy scattering processes rooted in gauge theories of the Standard Model. A first step in such simulations is preparation of interacting hadronic wave packets. To create the wave packets, one typically resorts to adiabatic evolution to bridge between wave packets in the free theory and those in the interacting theory, rendering the simulation resource intensive. In this work, we construct a wave-packet creation operator directly in the interacting theory to circumvent adiabatic evolution, taking advantage of resource-efficient schemes for ground-state preparation, such as variational quantum eigensolvers. By means of an ansatz for bound mesonic excitations in confining gauge theories, which is subsequently optimized using classical or quantum methods, we show that interacting mesonic wave packets can be created efficiently and accurately using digital quantum algorithms that we develop. Specifically, we obtain high-fidelity mesonic wave packets in the $Z_2$ and $U(1)$ lattice gauge theories coupled to fermionic matter in 1+1 dimensions. Our method is applicable to both perturbative and non-perturbative regimes of couplings. The wave-packet creation circuit for the case of the $Z_2$ lattice gauge theory is built and implemented on the Quantinuum H1-1 trapped-ion quantum computer using 13 qubits and up to 308 entangling gates. The fidelities agree well with classical benchmark calculations after employing a simple symmetry-based noise-mitigation technique. This work serves as a step toward quantum computing scattering processes in quantum chromodynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.00840v3</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zohreh Davoudi, Chung-Chun Hsieh, Saurabh V. Kadam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integral identities and universal relations for solitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05789</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05789v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that any nonlinear field theory giving rise to static solutions with finite energy like, e.g., topological solitons, allows us to derive an infinite number of integral identities which any such solution has to obey. These integral identities can always be understood as being generated by field transformations and their related Noether currents. We also explain why all integral identities generated by coordinate transformations become trivial for Bogomolnyi-Prasad-Sommerfield (BPS) solitons, i.e., topological solitons which saturate a topological energy bound. Finally, we consider applications of these identities to a broad class of nonlinear scalar theories, including the Skyrme model. More concretely, we find nontrivial integral identities that can be seen as model-independent relations between certain physical properties of the solitons in such theories, and we comment on the possible connection between these new relations and those already found in the context of astrophysical compact objects. We also demonstrate the usefulness of said identities to estimate the precision of the numerical calculation of soliton observables.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05789v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christoph Adam, Alberto Garcia Martin-Caro, Carlos Naya, Andrzej Wereszczynski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion coefficient matrix for multiple conserved charges: a Kubo approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.18718</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.18718v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The strongly interacting matter created in relativistic heavy-ion collisions possesses several conserved quantum numbers, such as baryon number, strangeness, and electric charge. The diffusion process of these charges can be characterized by a diffusion matrix that describes the mutual influence of the diffusion of various charges. We derive the Kubo relations for evaluating diffusion coefficients as elements of a diffusion matrix. We further demonstrate that in the weak coupling limit, the diffusion matrix elements obtained through Kubo relations reduce to those obtained from kinetic theory with an appropriate identification of the relaxation times. We illustrate this evaluation in a toy model of two interacting scalar fields with two conserved charges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.18718v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sourav Dey, Amaresh Jaiswal, Hiranmaya Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Color superconductivity and speed of sound in the two-flavor quark-meson diquark model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12361v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss the properties of the two-flavor quark-meson diquark (QMD) model as a renormalizable low-energy model for QCD in the 2SC phase of QCD. The effective degrees of freedom are the mesons (sigma and pions), quarks, and diquarks. Some of the parameters of the model can be determined by expressing them in terms of the vacuum meson masses and the pion decay constant using the on-shell renormalization scheme. The remaining parameters are considered free, although they in principle can be calculated from QCD. The thermodynamic potential is calculated in a mean-field approximation taking only quark loops into account. In this approximation, we derive a set of renormalization group equations for the running masses and couplings. The solutions to these equations are used to improve the thermodynamic potential $\Omega$ and thereby thermodynamic quantities. Four parameter sets are chosen and the phase diagram in the $\bar{\mu}$--$T$ plane is obtained (with $\bar{\mu}={1\over3}\mu_B$). We also calculate the speed of sound $c_s$ as a function of $\bar{\mu}$ at vanishing temperature. For large values of $\bar{\mu}$, the speed of sound approaches the conformal limit $c_s={1\over\sqrt{3}}$ from above, in disagreement with perturbative calculations, but agreement with hard-dense-loop resummed perturbation theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12361v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jens O. Andersen, Mathias P. N{\o}dtvedt</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
