<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 01:48:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A sign of three-nucleon short-range correlation from an analysis of nuclear mass and short-range correlation probability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01882v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Three-nucleon short-range correlation ($3N$ SRC) represents a rare and intriguing part of the nuclear dynamics at short distance, beyond the two-nucleon short-range correlation ($2N$ SRC). To search its existence is a hot topic in the ongoing and future high-energy nuclear experiments and the developments of nuclear theory. In this study, we found a positive sign of $3N$ SRC in nuclei, by analyzing the correlation between the per-nucleon nuclear mass and the probability of a nucleon in $2N$ SRC state, with the current experimental measurements of $^2$H, $^3$He, $^4$He, $^9$Be, $^{12}$C, $^{27}$Al, $^{56}$Fe, Cu, $^{197}$Au and $^{208}$Pb from SLAC, CLAS, and JLab Hall C collaborations. The effective masses of the nucleons in $2N$ SRC and $3N$ SRC are also extracted from the analysis, which provide some references for the nuclear medium effect study. The probability of $3N$ SRC is much smaller than that of $2N$ SRC, thus requiring high-luminosity experiments to confirm its existence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01882v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Na-Na Ma, Rong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Benchmarking $\Lambda$NN three-body forces and first predictions for A=3-5 hypernuclei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02064v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Explicit expressions for the leading chiral hyperon-nucleon-nucleon three-body forces have been derived by Petschauer et al [Phys. Rev. C93.014001 (2016)]. An important prerequisite for including these three-body forces in few- and many-body calculations is the accuracy and efficiency of their partial-wave decomposition. A careful benchmark of the {\Lambda}NN potential matrix elements, computed using two robust and efficient partial-wave decomposition methods, is presented. In addition, results of a first quantitative assessment for the contributions of $\Lambda$NN forces to the separation energies in A=3-5 hypernuclei are reported.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02064v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hoai Le, Johann Haidenbauer, Hiroyuki Kamada, Michio Kohno, Ulf-G. Mei{\ss}ner, Kazuya Miyagawa, Andreas Nogga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimating Inverse Scattering Potentials for \textit{n-p} System Using Variational Monte Carlo \&amp; Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02137</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02137v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Riccati-type nonlinear differential equation, also named the Variable Phase Approach or Phase Function Method, is used to construct local inverse potentials for the $^3S_1$ and $^1S_0$ states of the deuteron. These potentials have been optimized by adjusting Morse potential parameters using the Variational Monte Carlo (VMC) and Multilayer perceptron (MLP) type Neural Networks (NN). The inverse potentials obtained from VMC and NN show almost identical parameters. In VMC all three parameters are varied to obtain the phase shifts while in NN the 3D-parameter problem is converted to a 1D-parameter optimization problem. Recently, the GRANADA group published a comprehensive partial wave analysis of scattering data, which includes 6713 \textit{np} phase shift data points from 1950 to 2013. Using the final experimental data points from GRANADA, we obtained the parameters for the Morse potential by minimizing the mean square error (MSE) as the cost function. Various quantum functions, such as phase $\delta(r)$, amplitude $A(r)$, and wave function $u(r)$, are described up to 5\textit{fm} with energies $E_{\ell ab}=[1-350 MeV]$ for $^3S_1$ and $^1S_0$ state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02137v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anil Khachi, Gabor Balassa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vortex Rings in Event-by-Event Relativistic Heavy-Ion Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02212v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present event-by-event simulations for central asymmetric light+heavy and Au+Au collisions to investigate the formation and evolution of vortex-ring structures in the longitudinal flow velocity profile. The production-plane polarization of $\Lambda$ hyperons, defined w.r.t. the $\Lambda$ momentum and the beam, can track the "vortex-ring" feature in the event, a characteristic vortical structure generated by longitudinal flow gradients. We make comprehensive model predictions for the rapidity-dependent vortex-ring observables for different collision system sizes at $\sqrt{s_\mathrm{NN}} = 200$ and 72 GeV. Our predictions at the latter energy can be explored in the future LHCb fixed-target experiment at the Large Hadron Collider.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02212v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Dobrigkeit Chinellato, Michael Annan Lisa, Willian Matioli Serenone, Chun Shen, Jun Takahashi, Giorgio Torrieri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Light clusters in hot nuclear matter: calibrating the interaction with heavy-ion collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02307</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02307v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose a Bayesian inference estimation of in-medium modification of the cluster self-energies from light nuclei multiplicities measured in selected samples of central $^{136,124}$Xe$+^{124,112}$Sn collisions with the INDRA apparatus. The data are interpreted with a relativistic quasi-particle cluster approach in the mean-field approximation without any prior assumption on the thermal parameters of the model. An excellent reproduction is obtained for H and He isotope multiplicities, and compatible posterior distributions are found for the unknown thermal parameters.
  We conclude that the cluster-$\sigma$-meson coupling is temperature dependent, becoming weaker when the temperature increases, in agreement with microscopic quantum statistical calculations. This implies a faster decrease of the light cluster abundances with temperature than previously estimated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02307v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tiago Cust\'odio, Alex Rebillard-Souli\'e, R\'emi Bougault, Di\'ego Gruyer, Francesca Gulminelli, Tuhin Malik, Helena Pais, Constan\c{c}a Provid\^encia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A chiral quark model analysis of the $\bar KN$ interaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01759v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work we analyze the $\bar KN$ interaction in the framework of a constituent quark model. The near-threshold elastic and charge exchange cross sections are evaluated, finding a good agreement with the experimental data. Furthermore, the possible existence of $\bar KN$ bound states are explored, finding two poles in the isoscalar $J^P=\frac{1}{2}^-$ sector that can be interpreted as the experimental $\Lambda(1405)$ state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01759v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Conde-Correa, T. Aguilar, A. Capelo-Astudillo, A. Duenas-Vidal, J. Segovia, P. G. Ortega</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Plasma Induced Variation of Electron Capture and Bound-State $\beta$ Decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01787</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01787v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The slow neutron capture ($s$-process) synthesises ~50% of all elements in the universe heavier than iron, whose abundances are determined by the competition between neutron capture and nuclear $\beta$-decay rates. The latter are expected to vary inside hot and dense plasmas such as those found in $s$-process nucleosynthesis sites. Here, we present a new and general theoretical study of the effect of local and non-local thermodynamic equilibrium ((N)LTE) plasmas on $\beta$-decays, using orbital electron capture (EC) decays in $^{7}$Be as a model case. We begin from the model of Takahashi and Yokoi to calculate the lepton phase volume of $^{7}$Be as a function of its ionisation state and excitation level, and consequently, the configuration-dependent EC decay rate. We then calculate the in-plasma ion charge state distribution (CSD) and level population distribution (LPD) for a grid of plasma density and temperatures, using the population kinetics code FLYCHK. By combining the configuration-dependent EC rate with the CSD and LPD, we calculate the in-plasma orbital EC rate in $^{7}$Be. The results show a strong correlation between the half-life and thermodynamic conditions of the plasma, underlining the importance of measuring decay rates in laboratory plasmas and the relevance of high precision atomic configuration models. The model discussed in this work is capable of calculating EC and bound state $\beta$ decay (BSBD) rates in both low-density NLTE and high-density LTE plasmas. We conclude by validating our model with state-of-the-art data in literature on isotopes of Pr and Dy, and by proposing future extension of the model to laboratory magnetoplasmas and stellar interiors aimed at improving nucleosynthesis models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01787v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bharat Mishra, Angelo Pidatella, Simone Taioli, Stefano Simonucci, David Mascali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of short range interactions between $u/d$ quarks in the $NN$, $D_{03}$, and $D_{30}$ systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01993</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01993v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The dynamic mechanism of short range interaction between $u/d$ quarks is still an open and challenging problem. In order to reveal this quark dynamics, we perform a systematic analysis of $NN$, $D_{03}$, and $D_{30}$ systems in the (extended) chiral SU(3) constituent quark models. By comparing results calculated with different models and different parameter sets, the effects of one gluon exchange and vector meson exchange terms are carefully examined. The results indicate that the vector meson exchange interactions dominate the short range interactions between $u/d$ quarks, while the small residual one gluon exchange coupling strength is also allowed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01993v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi-Fang L\"u, Yu-Bing Dong, Peng-Nian Shen, Zong-Ye Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jet quenching for hadron-tagged jets in $pA$ collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01997</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01997v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We calculate the medium modification factor $I_{pA}$ for 5.02 TeV $p$+Pb collisions. We use the Monte-Carlo Glauber model to determine the parameters of the quark-gluon plasma fireball in $pA$ jet events. Our calculations show that the jet quenching effect for $I_{pA}$ turns out to be rather small. We have found that the theoretical $I_{pA}$ as a function of the underlying event charged multiplicity density, within errors, agrees with data from ALICE for 5.02 TeV $p$+Pb collisions. However, the experimental errors are too large to draw a firm conclusion on the possible presence of jet quenching.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01997v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. G. Zakharov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The role of the effective range in strongly-interacting few-body systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02135</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02135v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Strongly interacting systems appear in several areas of physics and are characterized by attractive interactions that can almost, or just barely, loosely bind two particles. Although this definition is made at the two-body level, this gives rise to fascinating effects in larger systems, including the so-called Efimov physics. In this context, the zero-range theory aims to describe low-energy properties based only on the scattering length. However, for a broad range of physical applications, the finite range of the interactions plays an important role. In this work, I discuss some aspects of finite-range effects in strongly interacting systems. I present the zero-range and shapeless universalities in two-body systems with applications in atomic and nuclear physics. I derived an analytical expression for the $s$-wave bound-state spectrum of the modified P\"oschl-Teller potential for two particles in three dimensions, which is compared with the approximations to illustrate their usefulness. Concerning three identical bosons, I presented a trimer energy scaling function that explicitly includes the effective range. The implications for larger systems are briefly discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02135v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00601-024-01942-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Few-Body Syst. 65, 70 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Madeira</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymptotic normalization coefficients for $\alpha+ {}^{12}{\rm C}$ synthesis and the $S$-factor for ${}^{12}{\rm C}(\alpha, \,\gamma){}^{16}{\rm O}$ radiative capture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.20255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.20255v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The $^{12}{\rm C}(\alpha,\gamma)^{16}$O reaction, determining the survival of carbon in red giants, is of interest for nuclear reaction theory and nuclear astrophysics. A specific feature of the $^{16}$O nuclear structure is the presence of two subthreshold bound states, (6.92 MeV, 2$^+$) and (7.12 MeV, 1$^-$), that dominate the behavior of the low-energy $S$-factor. The strength of these subthreshold states is determined by their asymptotic normalization coefficients (ANCs), which need to be known with high accuracy. Recently, using a model-independent extrapolation method, Blokhintsev {\it et al.} [Eur. Phys. J. A {\bf 59} (2023) 162] determined the ANCs for the $\alpha$-particle removal taking into account three subthreshold states in $^{16}$O. The goal of this paper is to address four main problems elucidating the impact of the subthreshold ANCs on the low-energy $S$-factor. Firstly, we analyse the connection between variations of the subthreshold ANCs and the low-energy $S$-factor, in particular, at the most effective energy of $300$ keV. Secondly, we calculate contributions to the $S(300\,{\rm keV})$-factor from the subthreshold $1^{-}$ and $2^{+}$ resonances, that are controlled by the subthreshold ANCs. We also evaluate the contribution of the uncertainties of the subthreshold ANCs to the budget of the low-energy $S$-factor uncertainty, especially, the $S(300\,{\rm keV})$-factor. Thirdly, we analyse interference of the subthreshold resonances (SRs) with higher resonances and with the $E1$ and $E2$ direct captures to the ground state. Finally, we investigate a correlated effect of the subthreshold and ground-state ANCs on the low-energy $S$-factor and, in particular, on the $S(300\,{\rm keV})$-factor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.20255v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. M. Mukhamedzhanov, R. J. deBoer, B. F. Irgaziev, L. D. Blokhintsev, A. S. Kadyrov, D. A. Savin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low-energy theorems for neutron-proton scattering in $\chi$EFT using a perturbative power counting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.10292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.10292v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Low-energy theorems (LETs) for effective-range parameters in nucleon-nucleon scattering encode properties of the long-range part of the nuclear force. We compute LETs for S-wave neutron-proton scattering using chiral effective field theory with a modified version of Weinberg power counting. Corrections to the leading order amplitude are included in distorted-wave perturbation theory and we incorporate contributions up to the third order in the power counting. We find that LETs in the $^1S_0$ and $^3S_1$ partial waves agree well with empirical effective-range parameters. At the same time, phase shifts up to laboratory scattering energies of about 100 MeV can be reproduced. We show that it is important to consider the pion mass splitting in the one-pion exchange potential in the $^1S_0$ partial wave while the effect is negligible in the $^3S_1$ partial wave. We conclude that pion exchanges, as treated in this power counting, accurately describe the long-range part of the $S$-wave nuclear interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.10292v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s00601-024-01938-w</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Few-Body Syst. 65, 69 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Oliver Thim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Contribution to differential $\pi^0$ and $\gamma_\mathrm{dir}$ modification in small systems from color fluctuation effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.17660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.17660v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A major complication in the search for jet quenching in proton- or deuteron-nucleus collision systems is the presence of physical effects which influence the experimental determination of collision centrality in the presence of a hard process. For example, in the proton color fluctuation picture, protons with a large Bjorken-$x$ ($x \gtrsim 0.1$) parton interact more weakly with the nucleons in the nucleus, leading to a smaller (larger) than expected yield in large (small) activity events. A recent measurement by PHENIX compared the yield of neutral pion and direct photon production in $d$+Au collisions, under the argument that the photon yields correct for such biases, and the difference between the two species is thus attributable to final-state effects (i.e., jet quenching). The main finding suggests a significant degree of jet quenching for hard processes in small systems. In this paper, I argue that the particular photon and pion events selected by PHENIX arise from proton configurations with significantly different Bjorken-$x$ distributions, and thus are subject to different magnitudes of modification in the color fluctuation model. Using the results of a previous global analysis of RHIC and LHC data, I show that potentially all of the pion-to-photon difference in PHENIX data can be described by a proton color fluctuation picture at a quantitative level before any additional physics from final-state effects is required. This finding reconciles the interpretation of the PHENIX measurement with others at RHIC and LHC, which have found no observable evidence for jet quenching in small systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.17660v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.110.L011901</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRC 110 (2024) L011901</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Dennis V. Perepelitsa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demonstration of the Rodeo Algorithm on a Quantum Computer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2110.07747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2110.07747v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The rodeo algorithm is an efficient algorithm for eigenstate preparation and eigenvalue estimation for any observable on a quantum computer. This makes it a promising tool for studying the spectrum and structure of atomic nuclei as well as other fields of quantum many-body physics. The only requirement is that the initial state has sufficient overlap probability with the desired eigenstate. While it is exponentially faster than well-known algorithms such as phase estimation and adiabatic evolution for eigenstate preparation, it has yet to be implemented on an actual quantum device. In this work, we apply the rodeo algorithm to determine the energy levels of a random one-qubit Hamiltonian, resulting in a relative error of $0.08\%$ using mid-circuit measurements on the IBM Q device Casablanca. This surpasses the accuracy of directly-prepared eigenvector expectation values using the same quantum device. We take advantage of the high-accuracy energy determination and use the Hellmann-Feynman theorem to compute eigenvector expectation values for a different random one-qubit observable. For the Hellmann-Feynman calculations, we find a relative error of $0.7\%$. We conclude by discussing possible future applications of the rodeo algorithm for multi-qubit Hamiltonians.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2110.07747v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhengrong Qian, Jacob Watkins, Gabriel Given, Joey Bonitati, Kenneth Choi, Dean Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identification of a natural fieldlike entanglement resource in trapped-ion chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.08842</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.08842v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The electromagnetic trapping of ion chains can be regarded as a process of non-trivial entangled quantum state preparation within Hilbert spaces of the local axial motional modes. To begin uncovering properties of this entanglement resource produced as a byproduct of conventional ion-trap quantum information processing, the quantum continuous-variable formalism is herein utilized to focus on the leading-order entangled ground state of local motional modes in the presence of a quadratic trapping potential. The decay of entanglement between disjoint subsets of local modes is found to exhibit features of entanglement structure and responses to partial measurement reminiscent of the free massless scalar field vacuum. With significant fidelities between the two, even for large system sizes, a framework is established for initializing quantum field simulations via "imaging" extended entangled states from natural sources, rather than building correlations through deep circuits of few-body entangling operators. By calculating probabilities in discrete Fock subspaces of the local motional modes, considerations are presented for locally transferring these pre-distributed entanglement resources to the qudits of ion internal energy levels, improving this procedure's anticipated experimental viability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.08842v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevA.109.062419</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. A 109, 062419 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Natalie Klco, D. H. Beck</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How far can we see back in time in high-energy collisions using charm hadrons?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.14282</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.14282v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We use open charm production to estimate how far we can see back in time in high-energy hadron-hadron collisions. We analyze the transverse momentum distributions of the identified D mesons from pp, p--Pb and A--A collisions at the ALICE and STAR experiments covering the energy range from $\sqrt{s_{\rm NN}} = 200$~GeV up to 7~TeV. Within a non-extensive statistical framework, the common Tsallis parameters for D mesons represent higher temperature and more degrees of freedom than that of light-flavour hadrons. Assuming Bjorken-expansion, the production of D mesons corresponds to a significantly earlier proper time, $\tau_{\rm D} = (0.18 \pm 0.06) \tau_{\rm LF}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.14282v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Laszlo Gyulai, Gabor Biro, Robert Vertesi, Gergely Gabor Barnafoldi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Glue in hadrons at medium resolution and the QCD instanton vacuum</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.03047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.03047v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss a general framework for the evaluation of the gluonic form factors in light hadrons at low momentum transfer, in the QCD instanton vacuum. At medium resolution of the order of the inverse mean instanton size, the glue is mostly localized in single or pair of pseudoparticles, and globally constrained by the fluctuations of their topological charges. These pseudoparticles trap light quarks, giving rise to emerging multiflavor 't Hooft interactions. We explicitly evaluate the gluonic scalar, pseudoscalar, energy-momentum tensor (EMT), and the leading C-odd and C-even three gluons hadronic form factors, at next to leading order (NLO) in the instanton density, including molecular clusters of like and unlike instantons. We use the results for the EMT to address the contribution of the gluons in Ji$^\prime$s mass and spin sum rules, at low resolution. When evolved, our results for the mass and spin composition of the nucleon, are shown to be in good agreement with the recently reported lattice results at higher resolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.03047v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Yang Liu, Edward Shuryak, Ismail Zahed</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
