<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 02:30:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>New insight into the N/Z and mass equilibration in heavy-ion collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00974v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The dynamics of N/Z and mass equilibration are investigated in the reactions 112,124Sn + 239Pu by employing the isospin-dependent quantum molecular dynamics model. It is found that N/Z and mass equilibration take place at different collision stages. The N/Z relaxation is observed in the approaching phase (from first contact to deepest contact) with a very short time, whereas interestingly we find for the first time that mass equilibration only takes place in the separation phase (from the deepest contact to re-separation), which are explained by investigating the dynamical asymmetry between the approaching and separation phases. The mass equilibration also could be clarified with a dynamical potential energy surface. Our results provide a new insight into the equilibration dynamics of the quantum systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00974v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Yang, Zehong Liao, Zepeng Gao, Long Zhu, Jun Su, Cheng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamics of the parity-doublet model: Asymmetric and neutron matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01302</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01302v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We consider isospin-asymmetric matter in the parity-doublet model within an extended mean-field calculation, increasing continuously the neutron excess all the way to pure neutron matter. We compute the liquid-gas and the chiral phase transitions occurring at zero to moderate temperatures, but put special emphasis on the phase structure of matter at zero temperature and large baryon densities. The calculation of the free energy involves the solution of gap equations. This is achieved by transforming these gap equations into ordinary differential equations that control the flow with increasing baryon density of various physical quantities: the isoscalar condensate, the densities of protons and neutrons, as well as those of their respective chiral partners. In this formulation, the initial conditions for the differential equations determine the entire phase structure. It is further demonstrated that the threshold for the onset of the population of the chiral partners is exclusively determined by the fermionic parameters, most notably by the chiral-invariant mass of the nucleon. We underline the role of a parity symmetry energy in driving the equilibration of the nucleons and their parity partners across the chiral transition. We provide a detailed analysis of the changes in the matter properties as one varies the neutron excess, including a special discussion of the chiral limit, and we compare systematically the parity-doublet model to its corresponding singlet model, where the chiral partner of the nucleon is neglected. Finally, we focus on neutron matter and compute the equation of state and the speed of sound. The results are confronted to those of other calculations as well as to recent Bayesian analyses of neutron-star observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01302v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\"urgen Eser, Jean-Paul Blaizot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cluster production and the chemical freeze-out in expanding hot dense matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01399v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss medium effects on light cluster production in the QCD phase diagram by relating Mott transition lines to those for chemical freeze-out. In heavy-ion collisions at highest energies provided by the LHC, light cluster abundances should follow the statistical model because of low baryon densities. Chemical freeze-out in this domain is correlated with the QCD crossover transition. At low energies, in the nuclear fragmentation region, where the freeze-out interferes with the liquid-gas phase transition, self-energy and Pauli blocking effects are important. We demonstrate that at intermediate energies the chemical freeze-out line correlates with the maximum mass fraction of nuclear bound states, in particular $\alpha$ particles. In this domain, the HADES, FAIR and NICA experiments can give new insights.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01399v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Blaschke, S. Liebing, G. R\"opke, B. D\"onigus</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of dark energy on the structure of neutron stars: The vacuum case</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01006v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The potential role of a cosmic vacuum dark component in the properties of neutron stars is investigated. It is assumed that the static, spherically symmetric distribution of matter within neutron stars is supported by two distinct components: ordinary matter and a vacuum fluid. For normal matter we use a set of state-of-the-art nuclear matter equations of state, each grounded in nuclear physics experiments. The vacuum energy component is inhomogeneously distributed within the star and obeys the standard equation of state ($p_v = -\epsilon_v$). This is characterized by an energy density fraction $y = \epsilon_m/ (\epsilon_m + \epsilon_v)$, which we model as either a constant or radius-dependent. Our findings reveal that the inclusion of vacuum energy significantly affects the mass-radius relationships in neutron stars, influencing both the maximum achievable masses and the qualitative form of these relationships. Some constraints from current multimessenger observational data limiting the amount of vacuum energy within neutron stars are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01006v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. F. Araujo, J. A. S. Lima, G. Lugones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pole analysis for the $D^{*}\bar K$-$D\bar{K^*}$ coupled-channel system</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01197</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01197v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: By solving the Lippmann-Schwinger equation, possible hadronic molecules in the $D^*\bar K$-$D\bar K^*$ coupled-channel system are investigated with the one-meson exchange potentials, where both vector and pseudoscalar mesons are considered as exchange particles. We find an S-wave virtual state with mass $2472(18)$ MeV, and a resonance with mass $M=2747(31)$ and width $\Gamma=7(3)$ MeV. In the $D^* \bar K$ invariant mass distribution, the virtual state appears as a cusp at the $D^*\bar K$ threshold, while the resonance potentially manifests as a dip. In particular, we take into account the $D\bar K \pi$ three-body dynamics due to the on-shell pion exchange and the finite decay widths for $D^*$ and $\bar K^*$. Additionally, the cutoff dependence and the SU(4) breaking effect are investigated in our work. Our results also indicate that the accurate measurement for the decay width of the $D\bar K^*$ resonance can help us to evaluate the SU(4) breaking effect in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01197v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pan-Pan Shi, F. Gil-Dom\'inguez, R. Molina, Meng-Lin Du</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperons during proto-neutron star deleptonization and the emission of dark flavored particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01406v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Complementary to high-energy experimental efforts, indirect astrophysical searches of particles beyond the standard model have long been pursued. The present article follows the latter approach and considers, for the first time, the self-consistent treatment of the energy losses from dark flavored particles produced in the decay of hyperons during a core-collapse supernova (CCSN). To this end, general relativistic supernova simulations in spherical symmetry are performed, featuring six-species Boltzmann neutrino transport, and covering the long-term evolution of the nascent remnant proto-neutron star (PNS) deleptonization for several tens of seconds. A well-calibrated hyperon equation of state (EOS) is therefore implemented into the supernova simulations and tested against the corresponding nucleonic model. It is found that supernova observables, such as the neutrino signal, are robustly insensitive to the appearance of hyperons for the simulation times considered in the present study. The presence of hyperons enables an additional channel for the appearance of dark sector particles, which is considered at the level of the $\Lambda$ hyperon decay. Assuming massless particles that escape the PNS after being produced, these channels expedite the deleptonizing PNS and the cooling behaviour. This, in turn, shortens the neutrino emission timescale. The present study confirms the previously estimated upper limits on the corresponding branching ratios for low and high mass PNS, by effectively reducing the neutrino emission timescale by a factor of two. This is consistent with the classical argument deduced from the neutrino detection associated with SN1987A.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01406v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Fischer, Jorge Martin Camalich, Hristijan Kochankovski, Laura Tolos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An effective gauge field theory of the nucleon interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.06133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.06133v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We discuss the possibility of constructing an effective gauge field theory of the nucleon interations based on the ideas of isotopic invariance as well as hypercharge invariance as a local gauge symmetry and spontaneous breaking of this symmetry. The constructed model predicts the structure of interactions of protons and neutrons with $\rho$- and $\sigma$-mesons, with pi-mesons and photons, as well as interactions of these particles with each other. The Lagrangian of the model consists of several parts parts involving dimension 4 and 5 gauge invariant operators. Feynman rules for physical degrees of freedom as follow from the Lagrangian define the structure of diagrams for one-boson exchanges between nucleons predicting the internucleon one-boson exchange potential as well as nucleon scattering amplitudes. The range of applicability of the model is discussed and estimates are made of the resulting coupling constants. The model predicts the mass of the neutral $\rho^0$-meson to be about $1\,MeV$ larger than the mass of the charged mesons $\rho^{\pm}$. The vector $\omega$-meson, which is a sterile particle with respect to the considered gauge group $SU_I(2)\times U_Y(1)$, can be added to the scheme by means of a gauge-invariant operator of dimension 5, as shown in Appendix ~A.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.06133v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1572-9494/ad5f85</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Eduard Boos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extraction of the neutron F2 structure function from inclusive proton and deuteron deep-inelastic scattering data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.16851</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.16851v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The available world deep-inelastic scattering data on proton and deuteron structure functions F2p, F2d, and their ratios, are leveraged to extract the free neutron F2n structure function, the F2n/F2p ratio, and associated uncertainties using the latest nuclear effect calculations in the deuteron. Special attention is devoted to the normalization of the proton and deuteron experimental datasets and to the treatment of correlated systematic errors, as well as the quantification of procedural and theoretical uncertainties. The extracted F2n dataset is utilized to evaluate the Q2 dependence of the Gottfried sum rule and the nonsinglet F2p - F2n moments. To facilitate replication of our study, as well as for general applications, a comprehensive DIS database including all recent JLab 6 GeV measurements, the extracted F2n, a modified CTEQ-JLab global PDF fit named CJ15nlo_mod, and grids with calculated proton, neutron and deuteron DIS structure functions at next-to-leading order, are discussed and made publicly available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.16851v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.074036</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shujie Li, Alberto Accardi, Matteo Cerutti, Ishara. P. Fernando, Cynthia E. Keppel, Wally Melnitchouk, Peter Monaghan, Gabriel Niculescu, Maria I. Niculescu, Jeff. F. Owens</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exclusive $J/\psi$, $\psi(2s)$, and $e^{+}e^{-}$ pair production in Au$+$Au ultra-peripheral collisions at RHIC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.13632</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.13632v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Measurements of exclusive $J/\psi$, $\psi(2s)$, and electron-positron ($e^{+}e^{-}$) pair photoproduction in Au$+$Au ultra-peripheral collisions are reported by the STAR experiment at $\sqrt{s_{_\mathrm{NN}}}=200~\rm{GeV}$. We report several first measurements at the Relativistic Heavy-Ion Collider, which are i) $J/\psi$ photoproduction with large momentum transfer up to $2.2~\rm{(GeV/c)^{2}}$, ii) coherent $J/\psi$ photoproduction associated with neutron emissions from nuclear breakup, iii) the rapidity dependence of incoherent $J/\psi$ photoproduction, iv) the $\psi(2s)$ photoproduction cross section at mid-rapidity, and v) $e^{+}e^{-}$ pair photoproduction up to high invariant mass of 6 $\rm{GeV/c^2}$. For measurement ii), the coherent $J/\psi$ total cross section of $\gamma^{\ast} + \rm{Au} \rightarrow J/\psi + \rm{Au}$ as a function of the center-of-mass energy $W_{\rm{\gamma* N}}$ has been obtained without photon energy ambiguities. The data are quantitatively compared with the Monte Carlo models STARlight, Sartre, BeAGLE, and theoretical calculations of gluon saturation with color glass condensate, nuclear shadowing with leading twist approximation, Quantum Electrodynamics, and the Next-to-Leading Order perturbative QCD. At the photon-nucleon center-of-mass energy of 25.0 GeV, the coherent and incoherent $J/\psi$ cross sections of Au nuclei are found to be $71\pm10\%$ and $36\pm7\%$, respectively, of that of free protons. These data provide an important experimental constraint for nuclear parton distribution functions and a unique opportunity to advance the understanding of the nuclear modification effect at the top RHIC energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.13632v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.110.014911</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator> STAR Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of strong nuclear suppression in exclusive $J/\psi$ photoproduction in Au$+$Au ultra-peripheral collisions at RHIC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.13637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.13637v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report a measurement of exclusive $J/\psi$ photoproduction in Au$+$Au ultra-peripheral collisions at $\sqrt{s_{_\mathrm{NN}}}=200$ GeV using the STAR detector. For the first time, i) the rapidity correlation between $J/\psi$ photoproduction and neutron emission from nuclear breakups has been experimentally measured; ii) nuclear suppression factors are measured for both the coherent and incoherent $J/\psi$ production. At photon-nucleon center-of-mass energy of 25.0 GeV, the coherent and incoherent $J/\psi$ cross sections of Au nuclei are found to be $71\pm10\%$ and $36\pm7\%$, respectively, of that of free protons. The stronger suppression observed in the incoherent production provides a new experimental handle to study the initial-state parton density in heavy nuclei. Data are compared with theoretical models quantitatively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.13637v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.052301</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator> STAR Collaboration</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrinoless Double Beta Decay without Vacuum Majorana Neutrino Mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.15016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.15016v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a proof-of-concept extension to the Standard Model that can generate a non-vanishing neutrinoless double beta decay ($0\nu\beta\beta$) signal without the existence of Majorana neutrinos or lepton number violation in the zero-density vacuum-ground-state Lagrangian. We propose that the $0\nu\beta\beta$ can be induced by the capture of an ultralight scalar field, a potential dark matter candidate, that carries two units of lepton number. This makes the observable $0\nu\beta\beta$ spectrum indistinguishable from the usual $0\nu\beta\beta$ mechanisms by any practical means. We find that a non-zero $0\nu\beta\beta$ rate does not require neutrinos to be fundamentally Majorana particles. However, for sizeable decay rates within the range of next-generation experiments, the neutrino will, generally, acquire an (effective) Majorana mass as the scalar field undergoes a transition to the Bose-Einstein condensate phase. We also discuss the distinction between the aforementioned scenario and the case in which the emission of a lepton-number-two scalar leads to $0\nu\beta\beta$, exhibiting discernible qualitative features that make it experimentally distinguishable from the conventional scenario.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.15016v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luk\'a\v{s} Gr\'af, Sudip Jana, Oliver Scholer, Nele Volmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Curvature of the chiral phase transition line from the magnetic equation of state of (2+1)-flavor QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09390</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09390v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We analyze the dependence of the chiral phase transition temperature on baryon number and strangeness chemical potentials by calculating the leading order curvature coefficients in the light and strange quark flavor basis as well as in the conserved charge ($B, S$) basis. Making use of scaling properties of the magnetic equation of state (MEoS) and including diagonal as well as off-diagonal contributions in the expansion of the energy-like scaling variable that enters the parametrization of the MEoS, allows to explore the variation of $T_c(\mu_B,\mu_S) = T_c ( 1 - (\kappa_2^B \hat{\mu}_B^2 + \kappa_2^S \hat{\mu}_S^2 + 2\kappa_{11}^{BS} \hat{\mu}_B \hat{\mu}_S))$ along different lines in the $(\mu_B,\mu_S)$ plane. On lattices with fixed cut-off in units of temperature, $aT=1/8$, we find $\kappa_2^B=0.015(1)$, $\kappa_2^S=0.0124(5)$ and $\kappa_{11}^{BS}=-0.0050(7)$. We show that the chemical potential dependence along the line of vanishing strangeness chemical potential is about 10\% larger than along the strangeness neutral line. The latter differs only by about $3\%$ from the curvature on a line of vanishing strange quark chemical potential, $\mu_s=0$. We also show that close to the chiral limit the strange quark mass contributes like an energy-like variable in scaling relations for pseudo-critical temperatures. The chiral phase transition temperature decreases with decreasing strange quark mass, $T_c(m_s)= T_c(m_s^{\rm phy}) (1 - 0.097(2) (m_s-m_s^{\rm phys})/m_s^{\rm phy}+{\cal O}((\Delta m_s)^2)$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09390v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.114516</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 109 (2024) 114516</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>H. -T. Ding, O. Kaczmarek, F. Karsch, P. Petreczky, Mugdha Sarkar, C. Schmidt, Sipaz Sharma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutron-quark stars: Discerning viable alternatives for the higher-density part of the equation of state of compact stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09446v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: By taking into account the latest observations and theoretical constraints, we investigate the merger and post-merger of binary neutron stars (NSs) with general-relativistic numerical simulations employing hadronic and hybrid equations of state (EOSs). We name our hybrid stars neutron-quark stars (NQS), because the transition from hadrons to quarks starts at a density lower than the central density of $\sim 1 M_{\odot}$ stars. We address two viable scenarios for the transition to quark matter: a crossover or a strong first-order phase transition (1PT). We find that a crossover transition is in principle observable when both the inspiral and post-merger signals are detected because the post-merger gravitational-wave (GW) main frequency $f_2$ is generally lower than that of hadronic models with the same tidal deformability ($\Lambda$). Since it is viable according to current multi-messenger constraints, we also highlight the possibility of an EOS with a strong 1PT that takes place at 1.8 times the nuclear saturation density, with a stiff quark EOS after the transition. It is the first time that mergers of binary NQSs with a deconfined quark-matter core are studied numerically in full general relativity. In this case, although ($\Lambda$, compactness) lies significantly outside the hadronic relation, ($\Lambda$, $f_2$) is close to the relation valid for hadronic EOSs. We also point out a linear correlation, valid within the observational constraints and not sensitive to the presence of a hadron-quark transition, between the emitted energy in GWs and their frequency.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09446v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sudipta Hensh, Yong-Jia Huang, Toru Kojo, Luca Baiotti, Kentaro Takami, Shigehiro Nagataki, Hajime Sotani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Soft-gluon exchange matters: isotropic screening in QCD kinetic theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.09605</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.09605v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: QCD kinetic theory simulations are a prominent tool for studying the nonequilibrium initial stages in heavy-ion collisions. Despite their success, all implementations rely on approximations of the hard thermal loop (HTL) screened matrix elements in the collision terms. In this paper, we present our results for different isotropic screening prescriptions in the elastic collision term for gluons. In particular, we go beyond the simple Debye-like screening form that is used in all current implementations and apply the isotropic HTL matrix element instead. For isotropic systems, the evolution is nearly unchanged, but when studying the equilibration process in a Bjorken expanding plasma, we find qualitative and quantitative differences in a range of moments of the distribution function, such as a decrease in the maximum pressure anisotropy by up to 50%. In contrast, we find no significant qualitative impact on the jet quenching parameter or on the late-time hydrodynamization dynamics of anisotropic plasmas but observe systematically smaller values of $\eta/s$ by about 10% that coincide with perturbative calculations at small couplings. Our study reveals that the choice of the screening prescription can lead to large corrections at early times, but is less important close to equilibrium.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.09605v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kirill Boguslavski, Florian Lindenbauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cold nuclear matter effects on azimuthal decorrelation in heavy-ion collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19243v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The assumption of factorization lies at the core of calculations of medium effects on observables computable in perturbative Quantum Chromodynamics. In this work we examine this assumption, for which we propose a setup to study hard processes and bulk nuclear matter in heavy-ion collisions on the same footing using the Glauber modelling of heavy nuclei. To exemplify this approach, we calculate the leading-order corrections to azimuthal decorrelation in Drell-Yan and boson-jet processes due to cold nuclear matter effects, not considering radiation. At leading order in both the hard momentum scale and the nuclear size, the impact-parameter dependent cross section is found to factorize for both processes. The factorization formula involves a convolution of the hard cross section with the medium-modified parton distributions, and, for boson-jet production, the medium-modified jet function.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19243v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>N\'estor Armesto, Florian Cougoulic, Bin Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
