<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2024 04:00:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>$K_{1}^{\pm}$ mesons moving in nuclear matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04532v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Observing the mass shifts of mesons immersed in nuclear matter is interesting, as the changes are expected to shed light on the effects of chiral symmetry breaking on the origin of hadron masses. At the same time, it is important to understand the momentum dependence of the masses for spin-1 mesons, as the changes manifest differently across the two polarization modes. Here, the mass shifts of $K_{1}^{\pm}$ mesons with finite three-momentum in nuclear medium are studied in the QCD sum rule approach. We find that the mass of $K_{1}^{+}$($K_{1}^{-}$) meson is increased(decreased) by the non-trivial momentum effect in both the transverse and longitudinal modes. Specifically, compared to its rest mass in the nuclear medium, in the transverse mode, the mass of $K_{1}^{+}(K_{1}^{-})$ is observed to shift by +2(-55) MeV, while in the longitudinal mode, the mass shift is +13(-11) MeV, all at a momentum of 0.5 GeV. Exploring the medium modifications of $K_{1}$ meson through kaon beams at J-PARC will provide insights on the partial restoration of chiral symmetry in nuclear matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04532v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seokwoo Yeo, HyungJoo Kim, Su Houng Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Branch-cut in the shear-stress response function of massless $\lambda \varphi^4$ with Boltzmann statistics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04679</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04679v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using an analytical result for the eigensystem of the linearized collision term for a classical system of massless scalar particles with quartic self-interactions, we show that the shear-stress linear response function possesses a branch-cut singularity that covers the whole positive imaginary semi-axis. This is demonstrated in two ways: (1) by truncating the exact, infinite linear system of linear equations for the rank-two tensor modes, which reveals the cut touching the origin; and (2) by employing the Trotterization techniques to invert the linear response problem. The former shows that the first pole tends towards the origin and the average separation between consecutive poles tends towards zero as power laws in the dimension of the basis. The latter allows one to obtain the response function in closed form in terms of Tricomi hypergeometrical functions, which possess a branch-cut on the above-mentioned semi-axis. This suggests that the presence of a cut along the imaginary frequency axis of the shear stress correlator, inferred from previous numerical analyses of weakly coupled scalar $\lambda \varphi^4$ theories, does not arise due to quantum statistics but instead emerges from the fundamental properties of this system's interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04679v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel S. Rocha, Isabella Danhoni, Kevin Ingles, Gabriel S. Denicol, Jorge Noronha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconciling the HESS J1731-347 constraints with Parity doublet model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The recent discovery of a central compact object (CCO) within the supernova remnant HESS J1731-347, characterized by a mass of approximately $0.77^{+0.20}_{-0.17} M_{\odot}$ and a radius of about $10.4^{+0.86}_{-0.78}$ km, has opened up a new window for the study of compact objects. This CCO is particularly intriguing because it is the lightest and smallest compact object ever observed, raising questions and challenging the existing theories. To account for this light compact star, a mean-field model within the framework of parity doublet structure is applied to describe the hadron matter. Inside the model, part of the nucleon mass is associated with the chiral symmetry breaking while the other part is from the chiral invariant mass $m_0$ which is insensitive to the temperature/density. The value of $m_0$ affects the nuclear equation of state for uniform nuclear matter at low density and exhibits strong correlations with the radii of neutron stars.
  We point out that HESS J1731-347 can be explained as the lightest neutron star for $m_0 \simeq 850$\,MeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04786v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bikai Gao, Yan Yan, Masayasu Harada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic description of induced fission in a configuration interaction approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05500v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Even though more than 80 years have passed since the discovery of fission, its microscopic understanding has still been unclear. To clarify the underlying mechanics of induced fission, we analyze the distribution of a fission width using a miscropic framework based on a configuration-interaction approach. The distribution is known to follow a chi-squared distribution, which is characterized by the effective number of decay channels, $\nu$. We introduce an effective Hamitonian for the space of compound nucleus states and estimate $\nu$ from the rank of the imaginary part of the effective Hamiltonian. Applying the model to $^{235}$U(n,f), we succesfully reproduce the empirical value of $\nu=2.3\pm1.1$. We also find that $\nu$ is insensitve to the number of fission channels, which is consistent with an experimental finding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05500v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. Uzawa, K. Hagino, G. F. Bertsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-order phase transitions in the cores of neutron stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05637v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: I explore various scenarios for the phase transition within neutron-star matter. I do so by generating large model-agnostic ensemble using Gaussian Processes, both with and without explicit inclusion of first-order phase transitions (PTs). The ensemble is conditioned with state-of-the-art astrophysical and theoretical inputs in a fully Bayesian approach. I study how the current data affect the posterior probability of the location and the strength of the first-order PT. I find that peak structure of the sound speed is stable against inclusion of PTs. Furthermore, while the current data cannot differentiate between a crossover and a first-order PT, it suggests an exceedingly low probability of the absence of either within the stable branch of neutron stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05637v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Oleg Komoltsev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QCD Predictions for Meson Electromagnetic Form Factors at High Momenta: Testing Factorization in Exclusive Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04412</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04412v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report the first lattice QCD computation of pion and kaon electromagnetic form factors, $F_M(Q^2)$, at large momentum transfer up to 10 and 28 $\mathrm{GeV}^2$, respectively. Utilizing physical masses and two fine lattices, we achieve good agreement with JLab experimental results at $Q^2 \lesssim 4~\mathrm{GeV}^2$. For $Q^2 \gtrsim 4~\mathrm{GeV}^2$, our results provide $\textit{ab-initio}$ QCD benchmarks for the forthcoming experiments at JLab 12 GeV and future electron-ion colliders. We also test the QCD collinear factorization framework utilizing our high-$Q^2$ form factors at next-to-next-to-leading order in perturbation theory, which relates the form factors to the leading Fock-state meson distribution amplitudes. Comparisons with independent lattice QCD calculations using the same framework demonstrate, within estimated uncertainties, the universality of these nonperturbative quantities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04412v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heng-Tong Ding, Xiang Gao, Andrew D. Hanlon, Swagato Mukherjee, Peter Petreczky, Qi Shi, Sergey Syritsyn, Rui Zhang, Yong Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum mechanical aspects of coherent photoproduction: the limits of coherence, and multiple vector mesons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04450v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum mechanics is central to coherent photoproduction in ultra-peripheral collisions (UPCs). This writeup will discuss some surprising aspects of UPCs that stem from these quantum mechanical roots. The Good-Walker (GW) paradigm, which connects coherent photoproduction with the target nucleus remaining in its ground state. This contrasts with a semi-classical picture, where coherence depends on the positions of the individual nucleons and the momentum transfer. Unlike the GW approach, the semiclassical picture is consistent with the observed data on coherent photoproduction with nuclear breakup, and with coherent photoproduction in peripheral collisions. The semiclassical approach allows for a wider variety of coherent UPC reactions, such as coherent photoproduction of charged mesons, including some non $q\overline q$ exotica. Quantum mechanics is also key to the coherent photoproduction of multiple vector mesons by the interactions of a single ion pair. The vector mesons share a common impact parameter, and so can exhibit richer interference patterns than single mesons. At forward rapidities, the cross sections to produce multiple identical vector mesons are enhanced due to superradiance. With enough statistics, multi-meson events may provide an opportunity to observe stimulated decays.}</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04450v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Spencer R. Klein</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of the chiral magnetic effect on particle-pair elliptic anisotropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05032v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Chiral Magnetic Effect (CME) is a phenomenon in which electric charge is separated by a strong magnetic field from local domains of chirality imbalance in quantum chromodynamics. The CME-sensitive, azimuthal correlator difference $\Delta\gamma$ between opposite-sign (OS) and same-sign (SS) charged hadron pairs is contaminated by a major physics background proportional to the particle elliptic anisotropy ($v_2$). The CME signal, on the other hand, contributes to the difference in the pair elliptic anisotropies between OS and SS pairs ($\Delta v_{2,\rm pair}$). We investigate $\Delta v_{2,\rm pair}$ and found its sensitivity to CME to be similar to that of the $\Delta\gamma$ observable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05032v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Han-Sheng Li, Yicheng Feng, Fuqiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-parton distributions in massive QED2: Towards quantum computation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05112v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We analyze the quasi-parton distributions of the lightest $\eta'$ meson in massive two-dimensional Quantum electrodynamics (QED2) by performing a digital quantum simulation on a classical computer (exact diagonalization). The Hamiltonian and boost operators are mapped onto spin qubits in a spatial lattice with open boundary conditions. The lowest excited state in the exact diagonalization is shown to interpolate continuously between an anomalous $\eta'$ state at strong coupling,and a non-anomalous heavy meson at weak coupling, with a cusp at the critical point. The boosted $\eta'$ state follows relativistic kinematics but with large deviations in the luminal limit. The spatial quasi-parton distribution function and amplitude for the $\eta'$ state are computed numerically for increasing rapidity both at strong and weak coupling, and compared to the exact light front results. The numerical results from the boosted form of the spatial parton distributions, compare fairly with the inverse Fourier transformation of the luminal parton distributions, derived in the lowest Fock space approximation. Our analysis points out some of the limitations facing the current lattice program for the parton distributions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05112v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sebastian Grieninger, Kazuki Ikeda, Ismail Zahed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analysis of $B_s^0 \to X(3872) [\psi(2S)] \pi^+\pi^- (K^+ K^-)$ decays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05114</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05114v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We have phenomenologically investigated the decays $B_s^0 \to X(3872) \pi^+\pi^- (K^+ K^-)$ and $B_s^0 \to \psi(2S) \pi^+ \pi^- (K^+K^-)$. In our analysis, the scalar meson $f_0(980)$ is formed through the final state interactions of coupled channels $\pi \pi$ and $K\bar{K}$. Our findings indicate that the $\pi^+\pi^-$ invariant mass distribution of the $B_s^0 \to \psi(2S)\pi^+\pi^-$ decay can be accurately reproduced. Furthermore, we have explored the $\pi^+\pi^- (K^+ K^-)$ invariant mass distribution of the $B_s^0 \to X(3872) \pi^+\pi^- (K^+ K^-)$ decay, accounting for the different production mechanisms between $X(3872)$ and $\psi(2S)$, up to a global factor. It is found that the production rates for $X(3872)$ and $\psi(2S)$ are much different, which indicates that the structure of $X(3872)$ is more complicated than the $\psi(2S)$, which is a conventional $c\bar{c}$ state. Additionally, we have considered the contributions from $f_0(1500)$ to $\pi^+\pi^-$ and the $\phi$ meson to $K^+ K^-$ in our analysis. Utilizing the model parameters, we have calculated the branching fraction of $B_s^0 \to X(3872) K^+ K^-$, and anticipate that the findings of our study can be experimentally tested in the future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05114v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao-Nan Wang, Li-Sheng Geng, Gang Li, Ju-Jun Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>T-odd Parton Distribution Functions and Azimuthal Anisotropy at High Transverse Momentum in $p$-$p$ and $p$-$A$ Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05287v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Various azimuthal anisotropies ($v_1, v_2, v_3, v_4$), at high transverse momentum (high-$p_T$), are shown to arise from the asymmetric scattering of transverse polarized quarks and gluons, arising from unpolarized nucleons (the Boer-Mulders' effect) and resulting in unpolarized hadrons (the Collins effect). Combined with the asymmetric scattering of partons from polarization independent but transverse momentum dependent (TMD) distributions, we obtain a possible mechanism to understand the azimuthal anisotropy of hadrons at large transverse momentum observed in $p$-$p$ collisions. Constraining the ratio of polarization dependent TMD distributions to polarization independent distributions by comparing with the data from $p$-$p$ collisions, we find that a simple $A^{1/3}$ enhancement of the intrinsic transverse momentum $(k_\perp^2)$ distribution, of the initial state partons from the proton, straightforwardly yields the azimuthal anisotropy at high $p_T$ in $p$-$A$ collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05287v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ismail Soudi, Abhijit Majumder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reduction of (pseudo-)Critical Temperatures of Chiral Restoration and Deconfinement Phase Transitions in a Magnetized PNJL Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05294</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05294v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the chiral restoration and deconfinement phase transitions under external magnetic field in frame of a Pauli-Villars regularized PNJL model. A running Polyakov loop scale parameter $T_0(eB)$ is introduced to mimic the reaction of the gluon sector to the presence of magnetic fields. It is found that a decreasing $T_0(eB)$ with magnetic fields can realize the inverse magnetic catalysis phenomena of chiral condensates of $u$ and $d$ quarks, increase of Polyakov loop and the reduction of (pseudo-)critical temperatures of chiral restoration and deconfinement phase transitions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05294v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shijun Mao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$c {\bar c}$ and $b {\bar b}$ suppression in Glasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05315v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study investigates the evolution and dissociation dynamics of $c\bar{c}$ and $b\bar{b}$ pairs within the Glasma medium, resulting from the collision of ultra-relativistic heavy ions. An attractive potential is used to create the pairs, but the strong Glasma fields dominate over it, causing an increase in pair separation and subsequent dissociation. The observed finite probability of dissociation for these states reveals the intricate interplay between QCD dynamics and the suppression of $c\bar{c}$ and $b\bar{b}$ states during the Glasma phase. The research highlights differences between $c\bar{c}$ and $b\bar{b}$ pairs, revealing the role of quark flavor in the dissociation process. Dissociation spectra analysis indicates a peak shift towards higher momentum, reflecting a slight energy gain by the pairs. This investigation provides valuable insights into the complex dynamics of $c\bar{c}$ and $b\bar{b}$ pairs in the Glasma, which may help in better interpretation of experimental results on further integration with subsequent phases of the created matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05315v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator> Pooja, Mohammad Yousuf Jamal, Partha Pratim Bhaduri, Marco Ruggieri, Santosh K. Das</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on the dense matter equation of state from young and cold isolated neutron stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.05371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.05371v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neutron stars are the dense and highly magnetic relics of supernova explosions of massive stars. The quest to constrain the Equation of State (EoS) of ultra-dense matter and thereby probe the behavior of matter inside neutron stars, is one of the core goals of modern physics and astrophysics. A promising method involves investigating the long-term cooling of neutron stars, and comparing theoretical predictions with various sources at different ages. However, limited observational data, and uncertainties in source ages and distances, have hindered this approach. In this work, re-analyzing XMM-Newton and Chandra data from dozens of thermally emitting isolated neutron stars, we have identified three sources with unexpectedly cold surface temperatures for their young ages. To investigate these anomalies, we conducted magneto-thermal simulations across diverse mass and magnetic fields, considering three different EoS. We found that the "minimal" cooling model, failed to explain the observations, regardless the mass and the magnetic field, as validated by a machine learning classification method. The existence of these young cold neutron stars suggests that any dense matter EoS must be compatible with a fast cooling process at least in certain mass ranges, eliminating a significant portion of current EoS options according to recent meta-modelling analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.05371v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessio Marino (Institute of Space Sciences ICE, CSIC, Institut d'Estudis Espacials de Catalunya IEEC), Clara Dehman (Institute of Space Sciences ICE, CSIC, Institut d'Estudis Espacials de Catalunya IEEC), Konstantinos Kovlakas (Institute of Space Sciences ICE, CSIC, Institut d'Estudis Espacials de Catalunya IEEC), Nanda Rea (Institute of Space Sciences ICE, CSIC, Institut d'Estudis Espacials de Catalunya IEEC), Jose A. Pons (Universitat d'Alacant), D. Vigan\`o (Institute of Space Sciences ICE, CSIC, Institut d'Estudis Espacials de Catalunya IEEC)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Implications of comprehensive nuclear and astrophysics data on the equations of state of neutron star matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.06018</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.06018v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The equations of state (EoSs) governing neutron star (NS) matter obtained for both non-relativistic and relativistic mean-field models are systematically confronted with a diverse set of terrestrial data and astrophysical observations within the Bayesian framework. The terrestrial data, spans from bulk properties of finite nuclei to the heavy-ion collisions, constrain the symmetric nuclear matter EoS and the symmetry energy up to twice the saturation density ($\rho_0$= 0.16 fm$^{-3}$). The astrophysical observations encompass the NS radius, the tidal deformability, and the lower bound on maximum mass. Three distinct posterior distributions of EoSs are generated by gradually updating the priors with different constraints: (i) only the maximum NS mass, (ii) incorporating additional terrestrial data, (iii) combining both the terrestrial data and astrophysical observations. These EoS distributions are then compared using the Kullback-Liebler divergence which highlights the significant constraints imposed on the EoSs by the currently available lower bound of NS maximum mass and terrestrial data. The remaining astrophysical observations marginally refine the EoS within the density range $\sim$ 2-3$\rho_0$. It is observed that the relativistic mean field model yields stiffer EoS around the saturation density, but predict smaller values of the speed of sound and proton fraction in the interior of massive stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.06018v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sk Md Adil Imam, Tuhin Malik, Constan\c{c}a Provid\^encia, B. K. Agrawal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithm to Obtain Inverse Potentials for $\alpha-\alpha$ Scattering using Variable Phase Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19173</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19173v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: An algorithm$^{\ref{Fig1}}$ has been developed with the purpose of obtaining inverse potentials, where the Riccati-type non-linear differential equation, also called phase equation, has been kept in tandem with the Variational Monte Carlo method. The optimization of Gaussian function parameters is achieved such that the experimental phase shifts are reproduced. The obtained SPS for various $\ ell$ channels has been compared with experimental ones with mean absolute percentage error (MAPE) as a measure. The model parameters have been optimised by suitable optimisation technique by looking for minimum value of MAPE. The results for $\ell$=0$^+$, 2$^+$ and 4$^+$ partial waves have been obtained, to match with experimental SPS, with MAPE values of $2.9$, $4.6$ and $6.2$ respectively for data up to $23$ MeV, while for higher states 6$^+$, 8$^+$ and 10$^+$ has MAPE of $3.2, 4.5$ and $5.9$ respectively for data from $53-120$ MeV. On extrapolation for data in range E$_{\ell ab.}$ = $23-120$ MeV, using the optimised parameters, the SPS are found to be in close agreement with experimental ones for the first three channels.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19173v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anil Khachi, Shikha Awasthi, Lalit Kumar, O. S. K. S Sastri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Mechanical Softening of the Hypertriton Transverse Momentum Spectrum in Heavy-Ion Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02701v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding the properties of hypernuclei helps to constrain the interaction between hyperon and nucleon, which is known to play an essential role in determining the properties of neutron stars. Experimental measurements have suggested that the hypertriton ($^3_\Lambda \text{H}$), the lightest hypernucleus, exhibits a halo structure with a deuteron core encircled by a $\Lambda$ hyperon at a distance of about 10 fm. This large $\Lambda-d$ distance in $^3_\Lambda \text{H}$ wave function is found to cause a suppressed $^3_\Lambda \text{H}$ yield and a softening of its transverse momentum ($p_T$) spectrum in relativistic heavy-ion collisions. Within the coalescence model based on nucleons and $\Lambda$ hyperons from a microscopic hybrid hydro model with a hadronic afterburner for nuclear cluster production in Pb-Pb collisions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}}$= 5.02 TeV, we show how this softening of the hypertriton $p_T$ spectrum appears and leads to a significantly smaller mean $p_T$ for $^3_\Lambda \text{H}$ than for helium-3 ($^3$He). The latter is opposite to the predictions from the blast-wave model which assumes that $^3_\Lambda \text{H}$ and $^3$He are thermally produced at the kinetic freeze-out of heavy ion collisions. The discovered quantum mechanical softening of the (anti-)hypertriton spectrum can be experimentally tested in relativistic heavy-ion collisions at different collision energies and centralities and used to obtain valuable insights to the mechanisms for light (hyper-)nuclei production in these collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02701v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dai-Neng Liu, Che Ming Ko, Yu-Gang Ma, Francesco Mazzaschi, Maximiliano Puccio, Qi-Ye Shou, Kai-Jia Sun, Yuan-Zhe Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin alignment of $K^\ast$ induced by strange-baryon density inhomogeneity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.02860</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.02860v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The difference between the spin alignments of $K^\ast$ and those of $\phi$ at the low collision energies is a puzzle raised by the recent experiments. Unlike $\phi$ meson, $K^\ast$, carrying a unit strange charge, should react to strange chemical potential $\mu_S$. In this paper, we shall first convince you that $\mu_S$ is not small in a brayon-rich medium for keeping strange neutrality, and then derive the spin alignment induced by the gradient of $\mu_S$, and hence of baryon chemical potential $\mu_B$, using linear response theory, with the transport coefficients expressed, without any approximation, in terms of the $K^\ast$'s in-medium spectral properties by employing Ward-Takahashi identity. It turns out that such an effect applies mainly to the particles whose longitudinal and transverse modes diverge, and induces only the local spin alignment in a static medium. The magnitudes of these coefficients will be further estimated under the quasi-particle approximation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.02860v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photon and dilepton emission anisotropy for a magnetized quark-gluon plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.07557</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.07557v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the higher-order anisotropy coefficients $v_4$ and $v_6$ in the photon and dilepton emission from a hot magnetized quark-gluon plasma. Together with the earlier predictions for $v_2$, these results show a distinctive pattern of the anisotropy coefficients in several kinematic regimes. In the case of photon emission, nonzero coefficients $v_n$ (with even $n$) have opposite signs at small and large values of the transverse momentum (i.e., $k_T\lesssim \sqrt{|eB|}$ and $k_T\gtrsim \sqrt{|eB|}$, respectively). Additionally, the $v_n$ signs alternate with increasing $n$, and their approximate values decrease as $1/n^2$ in magnitude. The anisotropy of dilepton emission is well pronounced only at large transverse momenta and small invariant masses (i.e., when $k_T\gtrsim \sqrt{|eB|}$ and $M\lesssim \sqrt{|eB|}$). The corresponding $v_4$ and $v_6$ coefficients are of the same magnitude and show a similar alternating sign pattern with increasing $n$ as in the photon emission.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.07557v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.056008</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 056008 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Xinyang Wang, Igor A. Shovkovy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>JLab spectral functions of argon in NuWro and their implications for MicroBooNE</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.13369</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.13369v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Short-Baseline Neutrino program in Fermilab aims to resolve the nature of the low-energy excess events observed in LSND and MiniBooNE, and analyze with unprecedented precision neutrino interactions with argon. These studies require reliable estimate of neutrino cross sections, in particular for charged current quasielastic scattering (CCQE). Here, we report updates of the NuWro Monte Carlo generator that, most notably, bring the state-of-the-art spectral functions to model the ground state properties of the argon nucleus, and improve the accuracy of the cross sections at low energies by accounting for the effects of the nuclear Coulomb potential. We discuss these developments in the context of electron and neutrino interactions, by comparing updated NuWro predictions to experimental data from Jefferson Laboratory Hall A and MicroBooNE. The MicroBooNE CCQE data are described with the $\chi^2$ per degree of freedom of 0.7, compared with 1.0 in the local Fermi gas model. The largest improvement is observed for the angular distributions of the produced protons, where the $\chi^2$ reduces nearly by half. Being obtained using the axial form factor parametrization from MINERvA, our results indicate a~consistency between the CCQE measurements in MINERvA and MicroBooNE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.13369v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.109.073004</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 109, 073004 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rwik Dharmapal Banerjee, Artur M. Ankowski, Krzysztof M. Graczyk, Beata E. Kowal, Hemant Prasad, Jan T. Sobczyk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Long-lived doubly charged scalars in the left-right symmetric model: catalyzed nuclear fusion and collider implications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.15145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.15145v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that the doubly charged scalar from the $SU(2)_R$-triplet Higgs field in the Left-Right Symmetric Model has its mass governed by a hidden symmetry so that its value can be much lower than the $SU(2)_R$ breaking scale. This makes it a long-lived particle while being consistent with all existing theoretical and experimental constraints. Such long-lived doubly charged scalars have the potential to trigger catalyzed fusion processes in light nuclei, which may have important applications for energy production. We show that it could also bear consequences on the excess of large ionization energy loss ($dE/dx$) recently observed in collider experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.15145v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2024.138616</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. B 852 (2024) 138616</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Evgeny Akhmedov, P. S. Bhupal Dev, Sudip Jana, Rabindra N. Mohapatra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutron radius determination of 133Cs and its impact on the interpretation of CEvNS-CsI measurement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.03566</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.03566v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Proton-$^{133}$Cs elastic scattering at low momentum transfer is performed using an in-ring reaction technique at the Cooler Storage Ring at the Heavy Ion Research Facility in Lanzhou. Recoil protons from the elastic collisions between the internal H$_2$-gas target and the circulating $^{133}$Cs ions at 199.4 MeV/u are detected by a silicon-strip detector. The matter radius of $^{133}$Cs is deduced by describing the measured differential cross sections using the Glauber model. Employing the adopted proton distribution radius, a point-neutron radius of 4.86(21) fm for $^{133}$Cs is obtained. With the newly determined neutron radius, the weak mixing angle sin$^2 \theta_W$ is independently extracted to be 0.227(28) by fitting the coherent elastic neutrino-nucleus scattering data. Our work limits the sin$^2 \theta_W$ value in a range smaller than the ones proposed by the previous independent approaches, and would play an important role in searching new physics via the high precision CE$\nu$NS-CsI cross section data in the near future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.03566v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Huang, S. Y. Xia, Y. F. Li, X. L. Tu, J. T. Zhang, C. J. Shao, K. Yue, P. Ma, Y. F. Niu, Z. P. Li, Y. Kuang, X. Q. Liu, J. F. Han, P. Egelhof, Yu. A. Litvinov, M. Wang, Y. H. Zhang, X. H. Zhou, Z. Y. Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
