<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 04:00:10 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Quarkyonic matter with chiral symmetry restoration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16649v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a novel unified approach to describe the dense symmetric nuclear matter by combining the quarkyonic matter framework with the parity doublet model. This integration allows for a consistent treatment of the transition from hadronic to quark degrees of freedom while incorporating chiral symmetry restoration effects. Our model introduces a chiral invariant mass for both baryons and constituent quarks, enabling a smooth crossover between hadronic and quark matter in symmetric nuclear matter. We derive the equation of state (EOS) for this hybrid system and investigate its thermodynamic properties. The model predicts a gradual onset of quark degrees of freedom at high densities while maintaining aspects of confinement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16649v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bikai Gao, Masayasu Harada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interactions of omega mesons in nuclear matter and with nuclei</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16895</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16895v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In-medium interactions of omega-mesons in infinite nuclear matter and finite nuclei are investigated in a microscopic approach with nucleon-nucleon and nucleon-resonance particle-hole polarization modes. The nuclear polarization tensor formalism is used. Covariant mean-field self-energies are taken into account. Longitudinal and transversal self-energies are derived. The theoretical results are applied to finite nuclei in local density approximation. Applications to recent data on the in-medium width of omega mesons in 93-Nb are presented. The data are well described by self-energies containing S-wave and P-wave resonances. Low-energy parameters are determined. For the first time a spectrum of omega-nucleus bound states is obtained, albeit with reduced lifetimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16895v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Horst Lenske</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model for the Glauber-type calculations of beam fragmentation at low energies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16962v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the present paper momentum distributions of nuclei produced in the heavy ion beam fragmentation at the relatively low energies (below 100 $A\cdot$MeV) are studied. For this study, a new theoretical approach is developed on the basis of the Glauber model modified for taking into account the energy and momentum conservation laws. In this approach, the longitudinal momentum of the most neutron rich nuclei, $^{10}$Be, $^9$Li, $^8$He, produced in a few neutron removal reactions in the $^{11}$B fragmentation in the Be target at a beam energy of 35 $A\cdot$MeV are calculated. The region of applicability of the new approach is discussed. This approach gives the asymmetric longitudinal momentum distributions at low energies, and the asymmetry is defined by the kinematical locus and geometry of the reaction (central of peripheral reactions). We analyze the changes of the phase volume and the longitudinal momentum distributions with the beam energy and number of the removed nucleons. The results of the calculations are compared to the parametrizations widely used for estimates of nuclear production in fragmentation for planning of nuclear experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16962v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. N. Ismailova, Yu. L. Parfenova, P. G. Sharov, D. M. Janseitov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wiedemann-Franz law violation domain for graphene and nonrelativistic systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.01061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.01061v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Systematic and comparative research on Lorenz ratios for graphene and nonrelativistic systems has been studied to identify their Wiedemann-Franz law violation domain. Fermi energy and temperature are the main governing parameters for deciding the values of the Lorenz ratio, which is basically thermal conductivity divided by electrical conductivity times temperature times Lorenz number. Metals as three-dimensional nonrelativistic electron gas locate at higher Fermi-energy by temperature domain, where Lorenz ratio remains one. Hence, they obey the Wiedemann-Franz law. By creating higher doping in a two-dimensional graphene system, one can again reach a higher Fermi-energy by temperature domain and get a constant Lorenz ratio. For both graphene and non-relativistic systems, the Lorenz ratio goes below one if we go lower Fermi-energy by temperature domain, which is possible for the graphene system by decreasing the doping concentration. Experimentally observed greater than one Lorenz ratio in this lower Fermi-energy by temperature domain or Dirac Fluid domain indicates that non-fluid expressions of Lorenz ratio should be replaced by fluid-type expressions. We have noticed a divergent trend of Lorenz ratio in the Dirac Fluid domain using its fluid-type expression, and it matches with the trend of experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.01061v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thandar Zaw Win, Cho Win Aung, Gaurav Khandal, Sabyasachi Ghosh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Angles on Energy Correlators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16368</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16368v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Energy correlators have recently come to the forefront of jet substructure studies at colliders due to their remarkable properties: they naturally separate physics at different scales, are robust to contamination from soft radiation, and offer a direct connection with quantum field theory. The current parametrization used for energy correlators, however, is based on redundant pairwise angles with complex phase space restrictions. In this Letter, we introduce a new parametrization of energy correlators that features a simpler phase space structure and preserves information about the orientation of jet constituents. Further, our parametrization drastically reduces the computational cost to compute energy correlators on experimental data; whereas the time to compute a traditional projected N-point energy correlator scales as M^N/N! on a jet with M particles, our new parametrization achieves a scaling of M^2 log(M) independently of N. Theoretical calculations for our new energy correlators differ from those of traditional parametrizations only at next-to-next-to-leading logarithmic accuracy and beyond, and we expect that our simpler phase space structure will simplify those calculations. We also discuss how to extend our parametrization to resolved N-point energy correlators that encode angular distances between greater numbers of particles, and we propose two possible generalizations for probing multi-prong jets and testing jet scaling behaviour.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16368v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Alipour-fard, Ankita Budhraja, Jesse Thaler, Wouter J. Waalewijn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universality in the Near-Side Energy-Energy Correlator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16371v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the energy-energy correlator (EEC) of hadrons produced on the same side in $e^+e^-$ annihilation or in leading jets in $pp$ collisions. We observe a remarkable universality of the correlator. Using a non-perturbative transverse momentum dependent (TMD) fragmentation function to model the transition from the ``free-hadron" region to the perturbative collinear region, we are able to describe the near-side shapes and peaks over a wide range of energy for both the $e^+e^-$ annihilation and the $pp$ jet substructure measurements in terms of just two parameters. We present further predictions for the ratio of the projected three-point energy correlator to the EEC. The excellent agreement between our calculations and the experimental data may provide new insights into the role of non-perturbative physics for EECs, and suggests the possibility of exploring non-perturbative TMDs using theoretical tools developed for the energy correlators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16371v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaohui Liu, Werner Vogelsang, Feng Yuan, Hua Xing Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meson spin alignment and baryon polarization from coalescence with spin-vorticity non-equilibrium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16448v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We estimate both the polarization of spin $1/2$ baryons and the spin density matrix coefficients of spin $1$ mesons using a thermal model that incorporates vorticity and polarization to describe quarks, along with a coalescence formalism where spin and vorticity are not in equilibrium. We find that while our model is not predictive due to its considerable number of free parameters, it has the potential to explain several seemingly puzzling features of experimental spin measurements, such as the absence of baryon polarization alongside significant vector meson spin alignment. We suggest the measuring meson spin off-diagonal matrix elements, and examining the dependence of polarization observables on azimuthal angles, as methods to falsify this model and gain insights into the freezeout details of baryon and meson spin structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16448v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kayman J. Gon\c{c}alves, Giorgio Torrieri, Radoslaw Ryblewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double $\phi$ Production in $\bar{p}p$ Reactions Near Threshold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16615v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We use an effective Lagrangian approach to investigate the double $\phi$ production processes in $\bar{p}p$ reactions near the threshold. We describe a notable violation of the Okubo-Zweig-Iizuka rule in $\bar{p}p\to\phi\phi$ reactions near the threshold by meson and baryon exchanges with hadronic degrees of freedom. Our study includes $t$- and $u$-channel diagrams that incorporate nucleon ground ($N$) and excited states ($N^\ast$), as well as $f$ and $\eta(2225)$ mesons in the $s$ channel. The excited states of the nucleon in the $t$ and $u$ channels encompass $N^\ast(1535, 1/2^-)$, $N^\ast(1650, 1/2^-)$, and $N^\ast(1895, 1/2^-)$, all of which are known to have significant coupling to strangeness. Our calculations suggest that the $N$ exchange in $t$ and $u$ diagrams contributes to a rapid increase in the total cross-section of $\bar{p}p\to\phi\phi$ reactions very close to the threshold. The diagrams involving $N^\ast(1650, 1/2^-)$ and $N^\ast(1895, 1/2^-)$ make a prominent contribution to the near-threshold cross sections, compared to the $N^\ast(1535, 1/2^-)$ exchange diagram. In the $s$ channel, the presence of three $f_0$ mesons ($f_0(2020)$, $f_0(2100)$, and $f_0(2200)$) and three $f_2$ mesons ($f_2(1950)$, $f_2(2010)$, and $f_2(2150)$) leads to a distinct peaking structure in the total cross sections, while the $\eta(2225)$ appears to contribute negligibly. Furthermore, the $\bar{\Lambda}\Lambda$ threshold results in a cusp structure in the total cross sections near 2231 MeV. Additionally, polarization observables offer crucial insights into the individual processes involved in the $\bar{p}p\to\phi\phi$ reactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16615v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dayoung Lee, Jung Keun Ann, Seung-il Nam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Astrophysical constraints on neutron star $f$-modes with a nonparametric equation of state representation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16689</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16689v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We constrain the fundamental-mode ($f$-mode) oscillation frequencies of nonrotating neutron stars using a phenomenological Gaussian process model for the unknown dense-matter equation of state conditioned on a suite of gravitational-wave, radio and X-ray observations. We infer the quadrupolar $f$-mode frequency preferred by the astronomical data as a function of neutron star mass, with error estimates that quantify the impact of equation of state uncertainty, and compare it to the contact frequency for inspiralling neutron-star binaries, finding that resonance with the orbital frequency can be achieved for the coalescences with the most unequal mass ratio. For an optimally configured binary neutron star merger, we estimate the gravitational waveform's tidal phasing due to $f$-mode dynamical tides as $7^{+2}_{-3}$ rad at merger. We assess prospects for distinguishing $f$-mode dynamical tides with current and future-generation gravitational-wave observatories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16689v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sailesh Ranjan Mohanty, Utkarsh Mali, H. C. Das, Bharat Kumar, Philippe Landry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated Quantum Circuit Monte-Carlo Simulation for Heavy Quark Thermalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16863v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Heavy quark thermalization in the quark-gluon plasma (QGP) is one of the most promising phenomena for understanding the strong interaction, where their energy loss and momentum broadening at low momentum can be well described by a stochastic process with drag and diffusion terms. We propose an accelerated quantum circuit Monte-Carlo (aQCMC) framework that ultilizes the quantum amplitude estimation (QAE) algorithm to simulate heavy quark thermalization with quadratically less resources. Specifically, we simulate the thermalization of a heavy quark in both 1D and 2D and in isotropic and anisotropic mediums using an ideal quantum simulator and compare that to analytical thermal expectations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16863v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenyang Qian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coupled-channel analysis of the near-threshold $e^+e^-\to N\bar{N}$ cross sections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16873v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The possible existence of nucleon-antinucleon bound states has been studied for decades. We investigate the $e^+e^-\to p\bar{p}$ and $e^+e^-\to n\bar{n}$ cross sections in the nonrelativistic effective field theory framework. The proton-antiproton and neutron-antineutron coupled-channel final state interactions are considered and found responsible for near-threshold enhancements. Both the proton-neutron mass difference and the Coulomb interaction between $p$ and $\bar{p}$ are considered, and the $N\bar{N}$ strong interactions are taken into account through a short-distance optical potential. By fitting the low energy constants in the amplitudes to the data for the near-threshold $e^+e^-\to N\bar{N}$ cross sections from the BESIII and SND Collaborations, a $N\bar{N}$ quasi-bound state is found just above the $p\bar{p}$ threshold, and another $N\bar{N}$ pole is found on the unphysical Riemann sheet, farther away from the threshold. The constructed coupled-channel amplitude with Coulomb effects also offers a framework that can be used directly in experimental analyses on fine structures near the $N\bar{N}$ thresholds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16873v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhao-Sai Jia, Zhen-Hua Zhang, Feng-Kun Guo, Gang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vortex Avalanches and Collective Motion in Neutron Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16878v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We simulate the dynamics of about 600 quantum vortices in a spinning-down cylindrical container using a Gross--Pitaevskii model. For the first time, we find convincing spatial-temporal evidence of avalanching behaviour resulting from vortex depinning and collective motion. During a typical avalanche, about 10 to 20 vortices exit the container in a short period, producing a glitch in the superfluid angular momentum and a localised void in the vorticity. After the glitch, vortices continue to depin and circulate around the vorticity void in a similar manner to that seen in previous point-vortex simulations. We present evidence of collective vortex motion throughout this avalanche process. We also show that the effective Magnus force can be used to predict when and where avalanches will occur. Lastly, we comment on the challenge of extrapolating these results to conditions in real neutron stars, which contain many orders of magnitude more vortices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16878v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I-Kang Liu, Andrew W. Baggaley, Carlo F. Barenghi, Toby S. Wood</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resolved photoproduction in {\tt MadGraph5\_aMC@NLO}</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.17061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.17061v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The upcoming Electron-Ion Collider (EIC), with its high luminosity, will offer an unprecedented opportunity to explore the internal structure of atomic nucleus over an extended energy range from $\sqrt{s_{ep}} =$ 45 GeV to $\sqrt{s_{ep}} =$ 140 GeV. A particularly promising aspect of this collider is the study of the partonic structure with quasi-real photons which can also be studied in inclusive ultra-peripheral collisions at the Large Hadron Collider (LHC). In this work, we present our validation of resolved photoproduction at fixed order for (next-to-)leading order using \texttt{MadGraph5\_aMC@NLO}, a widely adopted framework at the LHC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.17061v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PoS(DIS2024)185</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Laboni Manna, Anton Safronov, Carlo Flore, Daniel Kikola, Jean-Philippe Lansberg, Olivier Mattelaer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meson-nucleus bound states in quark meson coupling model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19896v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The formations of the $K(\bar{K})$, $D(\bar{D})$, and $B(\bar{B})$ meson-nucleus bound states in ${\rm{^{16}O}}$, ${\rm{^{40}Ca}}$, ${\rm{^{90}Zr}}$, ${\rm{^{197}Au}}$, and ${\rm{^{208}Pb}}$ nucleus are investigated using the quark meson coupling model. The model relies on a mean field description of non-overlapping nucleon bags bound by the self-consistent interactions of scalar ($\sigma$, $\delta$) and vector ($\omega$, $\rho$) mesons with the (anti)quarks inside the bags, which is further extended to explore the properties of nuclei. We estimate the meson-nucleus bound state energies by solving the Klein-Gordon equations with the real potentials calculated self-consistently within the model, using a coordinate space approach. The calculations are carried out for different nuclear interactions. The effects of Coulomb interaction are considered in the present study for the charged mesons. Our study indicates the formation of rather deeply bound $B$-mesic states at the very central region of the nuclei, compared to the $D$ and $K$ mesons, offering a more promising probe to explore subtle nuclear medium effects. The investigations of such bound states are of particular interest for the upcoming $\rm{\bar{P}ANDA}$ at FAIR, J-PARC-E29, and JLab experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19896v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arpita Mondal, Amruta Mishra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong Coupling of Hydrodynamics and Reactions in Nuclear Statistical Equilibrium for Modeling Convection in Massive Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.14786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.14786v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We build on the simplified spectral deferred corrections (SDC) coupling of hydrodynamics and reactions to handle the case of nuclear statistical equilibrium (NSE) and electron/positron captures/decays in the cores of massive stars. Our approach blends a traditional reaction network on the grid with a tabulated NSE state from a very large, O(100) nuclei, network. We demonstrate how to achieve second-order accuracy in the simplified-SDC framework when coupling NSE to hydrodynamics, with the ability to evolve the star on the hydrodynamics timestep. We discuss the application of this method to convection in massive stars leading up to core-collapse. We also show how to initialize the initial convective state from a 1D model in a self-consistent fashion. All of these developments are done in the publicly available Castro simulation code and the entire simulation methodology is fully GPU accelerated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.14786v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael Zingale, Zhi Chen, Eric T. Johnson, Max P. Katz, Alexander Smith Clark</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Polarisability of Octet Baryons via Lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.01064</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.01064v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Drawing on recent advances in lattice-QCD background-field techniques, the magnetic polarisability of octet baryons is calculated from the first principles of QCD. The results are presented in the context of new constituent quark-model calculations providing a framework for understanding the lattice results and a direct comparison with simulation results at unphysical quark masses. Using smeared quark sources, low-lying Laplacian eigenmode projection and final-state Landau mode projection, considerable attention is devoted to ensuring single-state isolation in the lattice correlation functions. We also introduce new weighting methods to reduce the sensitivity to correlation-function fits, averaging over many fits based on merit drawn from the full correlated $\chi^2$ of the fits. The techniques are implemented on the $32^3 \times 64$, 2+1-flavour dynamical-fermion lattices provided by the PACS-CS collaboration following the introduction of uniform magnetic fields quantised to the lowest nontrivial values available. After some fine tuning of the constituent quark model parameters, we find the model captures the patterns observed in the lattice QCD results very well, providing important insights into the physics underpinning the magnetic polarisabilities. Finally, comparison with the most recent results from experiment proceeds through an effective field theory formalism which incorporates estimates of finite-volume corrections and small electro-quenching corrections as the results are brought to the physical point. We find excellent agreement with experiment where available, including the proton and neutron polarisabilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.01064v3</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.110.074514</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110, 074514 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Kabelitz (University of Adelaide), Ryan Bignell (Trinity College), Waseem Kamleh (University of Adelaide), Derek Leinweber (University of Adelaide)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On convergence properties of GPD expansion through Mellin/conformal moments and orthogonal polynomials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04133</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04133v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We examine convergence properties of reconstructing the generalized parton distributions (GPDs) through the universal moment parameterization (GUMP). We provide a heuristic explanation for the connection between the formal summation/expansion and the Mellin-Barnes integral in the literature, and specify the exact convergence condition. We derive an asymptotic condition on the conformal moments of GPDs to satisfy the boundary condition at $x=1$ and subsequently develop an approximate formula for GPDs when $x&gt;\xi$. Since experimental observables constraining GPDs can be expressed in terms of double or even triple summations involving their moments, scale evolution factors, and Wilson coefficients, etc., we propose a method to handle the ordering of the multiple summations and convert them into multiple Mellin-Barnes integrals via analytical continuations of integer summation indices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04133v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao-Cheng Zhang, Xiangdong Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on the $U(1)_{B-L}$ model from global QCD analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.01205</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.01205v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We perform the first global QCD analysis of electron-nucleon deep-inelastic scattering and related high-energy data including the beyond the Standard Model $U(1)_{B-L}$ gauge boson, $Z'$. Contrary to the dark photon case, we find no improvement in the $\chi^2$ relative to the baseline result. The finding allows us to place exclusion limits on the coupling constant of the $Z'$ with mass in the range $M_{Z'} = 2$ GeV to 160 GeV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.01205v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>X. G. Wang, N. T. Hunt-Smith, W. Melnitchouk, N. Sato, A. W. Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Baryon and Meson Excited States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.11196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.11196v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The masses of eight baryon sets and nine meson sets of three or more equal-quantum excited states are fitted by a simple two-parameter logarithm function, M(n) = a Ln(n) + b, where $n$ is the order of excitation. The conjecture is made that accurately measured masses of all equal-quantum baryon and meson excited states would be related by the logarithm function used here; at least for the mass range of currently known excited states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.11196v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. David Roper (VPI), Igor Strakovsky (GWU)</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
