<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 04:00:09 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Self-consistent single-nucleon potential at positive energy produced by semi-realistic interaction and its examination via nucleon-nucleus elastic scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Based on the variational principle, self-consistent single-particle (s.p.) potentials at positive energies are discussed, which correspond to the real part of the optical potential as the single folding potential (SFP). The nuclear-matter s.p. potential produced by the semi-realistic nucleonic interaction M3Y-P6, which has links to the bare nucleonic interaction, resembles those extracted from the empirical optical potential Applying M3Y-P6 both to the self-consistent mean-field calculations for the target nucleus and to the SFP for the scattered nucleon, we find that the differential cross-sections of the nucleon-nucleus elastic scattering are reproduced almost comparably to the empirical potentials up to $80\,\mathrm{MeV}$ incident energy. The results demonstrate that the s.p. potential compatible with available experimental data can be derived from a single energy-independent effective interaction in this wide energy range.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19961v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>H. Nakada, K. Ishida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vortical waves in a quantum fluid with vector, axial and helical charges. I. Non-dissipative transport</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19755v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Due to the spin-orbit coupling, Dirac fermions, submerged in a thermal bath with finite macroscopic vorticity, exhibit a spin polarisation along the direction parallel to the vorticity vector $\boldsymbol{\Omega}$. Due to the symmetries of the Lagrangian for free massless Dirac particles, there are three independent and classically conserved currents corresponding to the vector, axial, and helical charges. The constitutive relations for the charge currents and the stress-energy tensor at thermal equilibrium, derived in the framework of quantum field theory at finite temperature, reveal vorticity-induced contributions that deviate from the perfect fluid form. In this paper, we consider the mode structure of the corresponding hydrodynamical theory and derive collective excitations associated with coherent fluctuations of all three charges. We show that the chirally imbalanced rotating fluid should possess non-reciprocal gapless waves that propagate with different velocities along and opposite to the vorticity vector. We also uncover a strictly unidirectional mode, which we call the Axial Vortical Wave, propagating in the background of the axial charge density. We point out an unexpected instability in the limit of degenerate matter and discuss possible solutions when helicity and axial charge non-conservation is taken into account.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19755v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio Morales-Tejera, Victor E. Ambru\c{s}, Maxim N. Chernodub</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vortical waves in a quantum fluid with vector, axial and helical charges. II. Dissipative effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.19756</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.19756v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we consider the effect of interactions on the local, average polarization of a quantum plasma of massless fermion particles characterized by vector, axial, and helical quantum numbers. Due to the helical and axial vortical effects, perturbations in the vector charge in a rotating plasma can lead to chiral and helical charge transfer along the direction of the vorticity vector. At the same time, interactions between the plasma constituents lead to the dissipation of the helical charge through helicity-violating pair annihilation (HVPA) processes and of the axial charge through the axial anomaly. We will discuss separately a QED-like plasma, in which we ignore background electromagnetic fields and thus the axial charge is roughly conserved, as well as a QCD-like plasma, where instanton effects lead to the violation of the axial charge conservation, even in the absence of background chromomagnetic fields. The non-conservation of helicity and chirality leads to a gapping of the Helical, Axial and mixed, Axial-Helical vortical waves that prevents their infrared modes from propagating. On the other hand, usual dissipative effects, such as charge diffusion, lead to significant damping of ultraviolet modes. We end this paper with a discussion of the regimes where these vortical waves may propagate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.19756v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio Morales-Tejera, Victor E. Ambru\c{s}, Maxim N. Chernodub</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superfluid extension of the self-consistent time-dependent band theory for neutron star matter: Anti-entrainment versus superfluid effects in the slab phase</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.03327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.03327v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Background: The inner crust of neutron stars consists of a Coulomb lattice of neutron-rich nuclei, immersed in a sea of superfluid neutrons with background relativistic electron gas. A proper quantum mechanical treatment for such a system under a periodic potential is the band theory of solids. The effect of band structure on the effective mass of dripped neutrons, the so-called \textit{entrainment effect}, is currently in a debatable situation, and it has been highly desired to develop a nuclear band theory taking into account neutron superfluidity in a fully self-consistent manner.
  Purpose: The main purpose of the present work is twofold: 1) to develop a formalism of the time-dependent self-consistent band theory, taking full account of nuclear superfluidity, based on time-dependent density functional theory (TDDFT) extended for superfluid systems, and 2) to quantify the effects of band structure and superfluidity on crustal properties, applying the formalism to the slab phase of nuclear matter in the $\beta$ equilibrium.
  Results: Static calculations have been performed for a range of baryon (nucleon) number density ($n_b=0.04-0.07$ fm$^{-3}$) under the $\beta$-equilibrium condition with and without superfluidity, for various inter-slab spacings. From a dynamic response to an external potential, we extract the collective mass of a slab and that of protons immersed in neutron superfluid. From the results, we find that the collective mass of a slab is substantially reduced by 57.5--82.5\% for $n_b=0.04-0.07$ fm$^{-3}$, which corresponds to an enhancement of conduction neutron number density and, thus, to a reduction of the neutron effective mass, which we call the anti-entrainment effect. We discuss novel phenomena associated with superfluidity, quasiparticle resonances in the inner crust, which are absent in normal systems.
  *shortened due to the arXiv word limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.03327v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenta Yoshimura, Kazuyuki Sekizawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuclear shape evolution of neutron-deficient Au and kink structure of Pb isotopes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18377v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Recent experiments using advanced laser spectroscopy technique revealed that the charge radii of neutron-deficient gold (Au) isotopes exhibit significant changes in ground state deformation: odd-even shape staggering in the $N = 98 \sim 100$ region and abrupt change of charge radii from $N =$ 108. In this study, we examine the abnormal shape evolution of the nuclear charge radii. To understand the nuclear structure underlying this phenomenon, we exploit the deformed relativistic Hartree-Bogoliubov theory in continuum (DRHBc). The significant change in mean-squared charge radii ($\delta {&lt; r^2 &gt;}$) turns out to originate from nuclear shape transitions between prolate deformation and small oblate deformation due to the shape coexistence possibility. We elucidate the nuclear shape evolution by analyzing the evolution of occupation probability for single-particle states. In addition, the abrupt kink structure in the nuclear charge radius of lead (Pb) isotopes near the $N =$ 126 shell is also investigated and reproduced quite well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18377v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Myeong-Hwan Mun, Eunja Ha, Yong-Beom Choi, Myung-Ki Cheoun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Photon Content of the Neutron</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.10497</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.10497v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we complete our CT18qed study with the neutron's photon parton distribution function (PDF), which is essential for the nucleus scattering phenomenology. Two methods, CT18lux and CT18qed, based on the LUXqed formalism and the DGLAP evolution, respectively, to determine the neutron's photon PDF have been presented. Various low-$Q^2$ non-perturbative variations have been carefully examined, which are treated as additional uncertainties on top of those induced by quark and gluon PDFs. The impacts of the momentum sum rule as well as isospin symmetry violation have been explored, and turn out to be negligible. A detailed comparison with other neutron's photon PDF sets has been performed, which shows a great improvement in the precision and a reasonable uncertainty estimation in our results. Finally, two phenomenological implications are demonstrated with photon-initiated processes: neutrino-nucleus $W$-boson production, which is important for the near-future TeV--PeV neutrino observations, and the axion-like particle production at a high-energy muon beam-dump experiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.10497v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Keping Xie, Bei Zhou, T. J. Hobbs</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic description of elastic photon-proton and photon-photon scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.12890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.12890v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the elastic photon-proton and photon-photon scattering in a holographic QCD model, focusing on the Regge regime. Considering contributions of the Pomeron and Reggeon exchange, the total and differential cross sections are calculated. While our model involves several parameters, by virtue of the universality of the Pomeron and Reggeon, for most of them the values determined in the preceding study on the proton-proton and proton-antiproton scattering can be employed. Once the two adjustable parameters, the Pomeron-photon and Reggeon-photon coupling constant, are determined with the experimental data of the total cross sections, predicting the both cross sections in a wide kinematic region, from the GeV to TeV scale, becomes possible. We show that the total cross section data can be well described within the model, and our predictions for the photon-proton differential cross section are consistent with the data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.12890v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2023.138343</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Akira Watanabe, Zabihullah Ahmadi, Zhibo Liu, Wei Xie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarized fragmenting jet functions in Inclusive and Exclusive Jet Production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.00672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.00672v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, we present a complete theoretical framework for analyzing the distribution of polarized hadrons within jets, with and without measuring the transverse momentum relative to the standard jet axis. Using soft-collinear effective theory (SCET), we derive the factorization and provide the theoretical calculation of both semi-inclusive and exclusive fragmenting jet functions (FJFs) under longitudinal and transverse polarization. With the polarized FJFs, one gains access to a variety of new observables that can be used for extracting both collinear and transverse momentum dependent parton distribution functions (PDFs) and fragmentation functions (FFs). As examples, we provide numerical results for the spin asymmetry $A_{TU,T}^{\cos(\phi _S - \hat{\phi}_{S_h})}$ from polarized semi-inclusive hadron-in-jet production in polarized $pp$ collisions at RHIC kinematics, where a transversely polarized quark would lead to the transverse spin of the final-state hadron inside the jet and is thus sensitive to the transversity fragmentation functions. Similarly, another spin asymmetry, $A_{TU, L}^{\cos(\phi _q - \phi _{S})}$ from polarized exclusive hadron-in-jet production in polarized $ep$ collisions at EIC kinematics would allow us to access the helicity fragmentation functions. These observables demonstrate promising potential in investigating transverse momentum dependent PDFs and FFs and are worthwhile for further measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.00672v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP03(2024)142</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Zhong-Bo Kang, Hongxi Xing, Fanyi Zhao, Yiyu Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards the quark mass dependence of $T_{cc}^+$ from lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14715v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The $DD^*$ scattering phase shifts in the $T_{cc}^+=cc\bar{u}\bar{d}$ channel are extracted from lattice QCD for five different charm quark masses and a fixed light-quark mass corresponding to $m_\pi\simeq 280$ MeV. The phase shifts are analysed employing two approaches: effective range expansion and Lippmann-Schwinger equation derived in the effective field theory. In the latter case, the results imply an attraction at short range parametrised by contact terms and a slight repulsion at long range mediated by one-pion exchange with $m_\pi &gt;m_{D^*}-m_D$. The poles in the amplitude across the complex energy plane are extracted and their trajectories are discussed as the charm quark mass is varied. Two complex conjugate poles corresponding to a resonance below threshold are found for $m_c$ close to the physical value. They turn into a pair of virtual states at the largest $m_c$ studied. With further increasing $m_c$, one virtual pole representing $T_{cc}^+$ is expected to move towards the two-body threshold and turn into a bound state. The light-quark mass dependence of the $T_{cc}^+$ pole is briefly discussed using the data on $DD^*$ scattering from other lattice collaborations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14715v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara Collins, Alexey Nefediev, M. Padmanath, Sasa Prelovsek</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
