<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 04:00:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A non-Hermitian quantum mechanics approach for extracting and emulating continuum physics based on bound-state-like calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03309</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03309v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work develops a new method for computing a finite quantum system's continuum states and observables by applying a subspace projection (or reduced basis) method used in model order reduction studies to ``discretize'' the system's continuous spectrum. The method extracts the continuum physics from solving Schr\"odinger equations with bound-state-like boundary conditions and emulates this extraction in the space of the input parameters. This parameter emulation can readily be adapted to emulate other continuum calculations as well, e.g., those based on complex energy or Lorentz integral transform methods. Here, I give an overview of the key aspects of the formalism and some informative findings from numerical experimentation with two- and three-body systems, which indicates the non-Hermitian quantum mechanics nature of the method. A potential connection with (near-)optimal rational approximation studied in Math literature is also discussed. Further details are provided in a separate paper.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03309v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xilin Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A new method to clarify contribution of chiral magnetic effect in small collision system $p^{\uparrow} + A$ involving a transversely polarized proton</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02939v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: With experimental data of DIS involving transversely polarized proton, we have calculated the 3-D charge density inside the polarized proton, which is found to have a significant non-spherical symmetry. Then we have calculated the property of electromagnetic field (E-M field) generated by a single transversely polarized proton ($p^{\uparrow}$). Based on them, the E-M field generated in small collision system $p^{\uparrow}+A$ are studied. We find that the orientation of this E-M field has a significant dependence on the polarization direction of the proton, and the correlator ($\Delta\gamma$ ) has also significant dependence on the angle between reaction plane and polarization direction. This finding provides us a new method for probing the chiral magnetic effect (CME).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02939v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gui-Zhen Wu, Zong-Wei Zhang, Chen Gao, Yi Xu, Wei-Tian Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid approach to perfect and dissipative spin hydrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03106v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A hybrid framework of spin hydrodynamics is proposed that combines the results of kinetic theory for particles with spin 1/2 with the Israel-Stewart method of introducing non-equilibrium dynamics. The framework of kinetic theory is used to define the perfect-fluid description that conserves baryon number, energy, linear momentum and spin part of angular momentum. This leads to the entropy conservation although, in the presence of spin degrees of freedom, the perfect-fluid formalism includes extra terms whose structure is usually attributed to dissipation. The genuine dissipative terms appear from the condition of positive entropy production in non-equilibrium processes. They are responsible for the transfer between the spin and orbital parts of angular momentum, with the total angular momentum being conserved.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03106v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zbigniew Drogosz, Wojciech Florkowski, Mykhailo Hontarenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jet definition and TMD factorisation in SIDIS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.03129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.03129v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Using the colour dipole picture of Deep Inelastic Scattering (DIS) and the Colour Glass Condensate effective theory, we study semi-inclusive jet production in DIS at small $x$ in the limit where the photon virtuality $Q^2$ is much larger than the transverse momentum squared $P_\perp^2$ of the produced jet. In this limit, the cross-section is dominated by aligned jet configurations, that is, quark-antiquark pairs in which one of the fermions -- the would-be struck quark in the Breit frame -- carries most of the longitudinal momentum of the virtual photon. We show that physically meaningful jet definitions in DIS are such that the effective axis of the jet sourced by the struck quark is controlled by its virtuality rather than by its transverse momentum. For such jet definitions, we show that the next-to-leading order (NLO) cross-section admits factorisation in terms of the (sea) quark transverse momentum dependent (TMD) distribution, which in turn satisfies a universal DGLAP and Sudakov evolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.03129v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul Caucal, Edmond Iancu, A. H. Mueller, Feng Yuan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of the determination of nuclear deformation using high-energy heavy-ion scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.19008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.19008v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Background: Nuclear deformation provides a crucial characteristic of nuclear structure. Conventionally, the quadrupole deformation length of a nucleus, $\delta_{2}$, has often been determined based on a macroscopic model through a deformed nuclear potential with the deformation length $\delta^{\rm (pot)}_{2}$, which is determined to reproduce the nuclear scattering data. This approach assumes $\delta_{2}=\delta^{\rm (pot)}_{2}$ although there is no theoretical foundation. Purpose: We clarify the relationship between $\delta_{2}$ and $\delta^{\rm (pot)}_{2}$ for high-energy heavy-ion scattering systematically to evaluate the validity of the conventional approach to determine the nuclear deformation. Method: The deformation lengths for the $^{12}$C inelastic scattering by $^{12}$C, $^{16}$O, $^{40}$Ca, and $^{208}$Pb targets at $E/A$ = 50--400 MeV are examined. First, we perform microscopic coupled-channel (CC) calculations to relate $\delta_{2}$ of the deformed density into the inelastic scattering cross section. Second, we use the deformed potential model to determine $\delta^{\rm (pot)}_{2}$ so as to reproduce the microscopic CC result. We then compare $\delta^{\rm (pot)}_{2}$ with $\delta_{2}$. Results: We find that $\delta^{\rm (pot)}_{2}$ is about 20--40 \% smaller than presumed $\delta_{2}$, showing strong energy and target dependence. Further analysis, which considers higher-order deformation effects beyond the derivative model, reveals that $\delta^{\rm (pot)}_{2}$ is still about 15--35 \% smaller than $\delta_{2}$. Conclusion: Our results suggest that one needs to be careful when the deformed potential model for the high-energy heavy-ion scattering is used to extract the nuclear deformation. The conventional approach may underestimate the deformation length $\delta_2$ systematically.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.19008v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.110.024604</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. C 110, 024604 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shin Watanabe, Takenori Furumoto, Wataru Horiuchi, Tadahiro Suhara, Yasutaka Taniguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin entanglement in two-proton emission from $^6$Be</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.11136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.11136v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper presents a theoretical evaluation of coupled-spin entanglement in the two-proton ($2p$) radioactive emission. The three-body model of $^{6}$Be with the proton-proton interaction, which is adjusted to reproduce the experimental energy release, is utilized. Time-dependent calculation is performed to compute the coupled-spin state of the emitted two protons. The spin-correlation function $S$ as the Clauser-Horne-Shimony-Holt (CHSH) indicator is evaluated as $\abs{S} \cong 2.65$. Namely, the $2p$-spin entanglement beyond the limit of local-hidden-variable (LHV) theory is suggested. This entanglement is sensitive to the proton-proton interaction. The short-lived (broad-width) $2p$~state has the weaker spin entanglement. In parallel, the core-proton interactions do not harm this entanglement during the time-dependent decaying process. The CHSH measurement can be a novel probe into the effective nuclear interaction inside finite systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.11136v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomohiro Oishi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic hydrodynamics with phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.14773</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.14773v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Assessing the applicability of hydrodynamic expansions close to phase transition points is crucial from either theoretical or phenomenological points of view. We explore this within the gauge/gravity duality, using the Einstein-Klein-Gordon model, a bottom-up string theory construction. This model incorporates a parameter, $B_4$, that simulates different types of phase transitions in the strongly coupled field theory existing at the boundary. We thoroughly examine the thermodynamics and dynamics of time-dependent, linearized perturbations in the spin-2, spin-1, and spin-0 sectors. Our findings suggest that "hydrodynamic series breakdown near transition points" is valid exclusively for second-order phase transitions, not for crossovers or first-order phase transitions. Additionally, we observe that the high-temperature and low-temperature limits of the radius of convergence for the hydrodynamic series ($q^2_c$) are equal. We also discover that the relationship $(\text{Max}\vert q^2_c \vert)_{\text{spin-2}} &lt; (\text{Max}\vert q^2_c\vert)_{\text{spin-0}} &lt; (\text{Max}\vert q^2_c \vert)_{\text{spin-1}}$ is consistent for different spin sectors, regardless of the phase transition type. At the chaos point, we observe the emergence of pole-skipping behavior for both gravity and scalar perturbations at $\omega_n = - 2\pi T n i$. Lastly, comparing the chaos momentum with $q^2_c$, we find that $q^2_{ps} &lt; q^2_c$, except for extremely high temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.14773v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. Taghinavaz</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
