<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 04:00:12 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancement of Alpha Decay due to Medium Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the effect of medium on radioactive alpha decay and other similar decays. The initial state in these type of decays is a quasi-bound state with energy greater than zero. Such a state has very large amplitude in the nuclear region and is exponentially suppressed at larger distances. The decay rate of such states is known to decrease rapidly with decrease in the Q-value. Here we study such a decay within a medium. We assume a simple spherically symmetric repulsive potential model for the medium. This models the cumulative effect of all nuclei in the medium which at short distances present repulsive Coulomb interaction. We find that as the Q-value becomes very small, the medium effects lead to a substantial enhancement in rate. In contrast, for large Q-values, the medium effects are negligible. We briefly comment on application to real systems and the experimental implications of this result.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22194v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pankaj Jain, Harishyam Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pairing gap as a new observable for critical points in the region of A=100</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22292v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study used the pairing gap to identify nuclei as candidates for critical point symmetry around Z=40 and A=100. Nuclei around A = 100 display complex shape evolution and configuration crossing patterns. We utilized the experimental and algebraic frameworks of the interacting boson model and the newly developed interacting boson-fermion model to study the isotopes of Mo and Ru. The results show significant variations in these quantities across nuclei located at the E(5) and X(5) critical points, analyzed through different observables. We also examined another region that is suitable for a shape phase transition. Furthermore, our findings suggest new candidates for critical points in other phase transitional regions for different isotopic chains.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22292v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hossein Emami, Hadi Sabri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Origin of the electric hexadecapole isomer in $^{93}$Mo</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22352</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22352v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a shell-model analysis of $^{93}$Mo to investigate the unusual behavior of its ${21/2}^+$ isomer -- a prominent candidate for nuclear excitation by electronic capture. This state is unique as its decay is dominated by a slow electric hexadecapole $E4$ transition, while the typically much faster electric quadrupole $E2$ decay path is energetically forbidden. We investigate the microscopic origin of this phenomenon by examining in detail the structure of the wave functions of the initial and final states, and the $E4$ transition matrix elements. This analysis of $^{93}$Mo is contrasted with that of its particle-hole conjugate, $^{99}$Cd, where such an $E4$ transition is absent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22352v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Maheshwari, P. Van Isacker, P. M. Walker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of evaluated nuclear data in the prediction of inherent neutron sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22382v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quantifying inherent neutron sources in matter, particularly $(\alpha, n)$ reactions and spontaneous fission, is important in nuclear engineering and other fields. The SOURCES code is a common tool for calculating the yield and spectrum of such neutrons. This paper critically examines all modelling assumptions and nuclear data in SOURCES and proposes alternative approaches where applicable. For $(\alpha, n)$ reactions, we show that the alpha emission lines for $^{235}\mathrm{U}$ should be updated. Furthermore, we compare four different stopping power data sets for alpha particles slowing down and propose measurements to constrain mixed oxide nuclear fuel data. We use the computer code PHITS to show that energy and angular straggling during the slowing down of alpha particles in the material of interest is unimportant. Then, we compare the cross section and emission spectrum of $(\alpha, n)$ reactions in SOURCES to recently evaluated data libraries. Importantly, the modelling of SOURCES for the emission spectrum seems too simple and may need to be updated. Finally, we compare data on spontaneous fission and show that while the neutron yield from SOURCES is reliable, some discrepancy is found with the neutron spectrum of evaluated data libraries. Complementing this work is an implementation of spontaneous fission in the Monte Carlo code OpenMC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22382v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sigtryggur Hauksson, Ilaria Casalbore, Daniele Tomatis, Nunzio Burgio</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An End-to-End Generative Diffusion Model for Heavy-Ion Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22515v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Heavy-ion collision physics has entered the high precision era, demanding theoretical models capable of generating huge statistics to compare with experimental data. However, traditional hybrid models, which combine hydrodynamics and hadronic transport, are computationally intensive, creating a significant bottleneck. In this work, we introduce DiffHIC, an end-to-end generative diffusion model, to emulate ultra-relativistic heavy-ion collisions. The model takes initial entropy density profiles and transport coefficients as input and directly generates two-dimensional final-state particle spectra. Our results demonstrate that DiffHIC achieves a computational speedup of approximately $10^5$ against traditional simulations, while accurately reproducing a wide range of physical observables, including integrated and differential anisotropic flow, multi-particle correlations, and momentum fluctuations. This framework provides a powerful and efficient tool for phenomenological studies in the high-precision era of heavy-ion physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22515v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing-An Sun, Li Yan, Charles Gale, Sangyong Jeon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-local orbital-free density functional theory knocks on nuclear shell effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22546v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Incorporating nuclear shell effects within the framework of orbital-free density functional theory (DFT) has remained a longstanding challenge in nuclear physics. While the Hohenberg-Kohn theorem formally guarantees the existence of an orbital-free density functional that is capable of describing all many-body effects, including shell effects, practical attempts since the 1970s have consistently failed to capture such effects. This persistent difficulty has even led to the misconception that the orbital-free DFT is inherently unable to describe nuclear shell effects. Here we develop a {\it non-local} orbital-free DFT approach for atomic nuclei and demonstrate that nuclear shell effects can be successfully incorporated into the orbital-free DFT through the construction of a non-local kinetic energy density functional. In particular, we show that the non-local orbital-free functional yields a nucleon localization function that, as an established indicator of shell effects, exhibits consistent behavior with the exact Kohn-Sham solution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22546v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xinhui Wu, Gianluca Col\`o, Kouichi Hagino, Pengwei Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nucleon-nucleon scattering up to next-to-leading order in manifestly Lorentz-invariant chiral effective field theory: low phases and the deuteron</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22648</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22648v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recently the nucleon-nucleon interaction derived using time-ordered perturbation theory in manifestly Lorentz-invariant chiral effective field theory was shown to yield promising results for peripheral neutron-proton scattering. In this work we study low partial waves at next-to-leading order by treating the potential non-perturbatively in the Kadyshevsky equation. Reasonable description of the phase shifts in the $S$ and $P$ waves as well as the deuteron properties is observed, which can be regarded as a feasibility study for the application of our formalism to the few- and many-body calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22648v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiu-Lei Ren, E. Epelbaum, J. Gegelia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Baryon and electric charge stoppings in nuclear collisions and the role of strangeness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22793</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22793v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: It has been challenging to quantitatively understand the stopping of incoming nucleons in nuclear collisions, and recently it has been proposed that comparing the baryon stopping with electric charge stopping can help address the question. Here we focus on the $B/Q\times Z/A$ ratio, which can strongly depend on rapidity although its value is one for the full phase space. We find that this ratio is very sensitive to the difference between strange and anti-strange rapidity distributions (the $s-\bar s$ asymmetry), and slightly more anti-strange quarks at mid-rapidity would lead to a ratio well below one. This is the case for Zr+Zr and Ru+Ru isobar collisions at $200A$ GeV from a multi-phase transport (AMPT) model. Without the $s-\bar s$ asymmetry, the AMPT model would give a mid-rapidity $B/Q\times Z/A$ ratio at or above one. In addition, the AMPT model gives $B/\Delta Q\times \Delta Z/A&lt;1$ at mid-rapidity for isobar collisions at all centralities, which strongly contradicts the recent data from the STAR Collaboration. We further find that the $B/\Delta Q\times \Delta Z/A$ ratio is very sensitive to the net-light quark ($u,d$) stoppings, but it is less sensitive to the $s-\bar s$ asymmetry than the $B/Q\times Z/A$ ratio by a factor of 3.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22793v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mason Alexander Ross, Zi-Wei Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Calculation of Particle Pair Correlation Functions with Classical Trajectory Approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23030</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23030v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Femtoscopic interferometry is a powerful tool for probing the spatio-temporal evolution of emission sources in heavy-ion collisions. A major challenge in the field is formulating a self-consistent description of the source function, final-state interactions between the particle pair, and interactions inherent to the source itself. To address this, we have developed a novel Monte Carlo model for calculating two-particle correlation functions in a classic framework. The model incorporates self-consistently the emission source of thermal equilibrium and three-body final state interactions. Application of the model shows satisfactory fit to experimental data, revealing that the correlation function is highly sensitive to the source's spatio-temporal extent. In contrast, the temperature parameter governing the emitted particles' energy spectra has a negligible influence. Our approach offers the potential to extract the spatio-temporal information from the emission source, thereby advancing the applicability of femtoscopic interferometry in the Fermi energy domain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23030v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sheng Xiao, Yijie Wang, Zhigang Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ground-state properties of finite nuclei in relativistic Hartree-Bogoliubov theory with an improved quark mass density-dependent model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23165v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A relativistic Hartree-Bogoliubov (RHB) model based on quark-meson coupling is developed, with a new parametrization derived from experimental observables. Using this model, we systematically investigate the ground-state properties of even-even nuclei spanning $8\leq Z\leq118$, including binding energies, quadrupole deformations, root-mean-square (rms) charge radii, two-nucleon separation energies, two-nucleon shell gaps, and $\alpha$-decay energies. Comparisons with available experimental data demonstrate that this subnucleon-based RHB model reliably describes the ground-state properties of finite nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23165v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1674-1137/ae0997</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chinese Physics C Vol. 50, No. 1 (2026) 014105</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Renli Xu, Chen Wu, Jian Liu, Bin Hong, Jie Peng, Xiong Li, Ruxian Zhu, Zhizhen Zhao, Zhongzhou Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-strange and charmed hadrons: A novel probe for the QCD equation of state at high baryon densities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23353v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nuclear experiments near and below the threshold of hyperon production have shown that the production of Kaons is a sensitive probe for the dense QCD equation of state. At beam energies up to 1.5AGeV, strangeness production can probe the equation of state for densities up to approximately twice nuclear saturation. In this paper we will discuss the possibilities of extending this range in density by the study of multi-strange baryons as well as charmed hadrons in the SIS100 beam energy range up to 10AGeV. Here, densities up to five times nuclear saturation can be reached and the production of multi-strange and charmed hadrons shows a strong sensitivity to the equation of state. On the other hand a precise prediction of the effect of the equation of state will require knowledge of the fundamental production cross section near the elementary production threshold in p+p collisions which is yet not measured for the hadrons discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23353v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Steinheimer, Tom Reichert, Marcus Bleicher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observable Signatures of Quarkyonic Phase in Neutron Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23405</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23405v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this letter, we perform Bayesian inference on quarkyonic equation-of-state models and find they remain viable under all current astrophysical constraints. Crucially, we identify a novel observational diagnostic- the slope of the M-R relation at fixed mass versus the central sound speed. Quarkyonic stars occupy a distinct region (high central $c_s^2$ and positive $\frac{dR}{dM}$) from purely nucleonic stars. This could be tested by future radius measurements of two stars of different mass. Our results indicate that if a neutron star falls in the quarkyonic region, it would be strong evidence for quarkyonic matter in its core.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23405v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Probit J Kalita, Tuhin Malik, Tianqi Zhao, Bharat Kumar, James M. Lattimer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QCD in strong magnetic fields: fluctuations of conserved charges and EoS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21731</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21731v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Strong magnetic fields can profoundly affect the equilibrium properties, characterized by the equation of state and bulk thermodynamics of strongly interacting matter. Although such fields are expected in off-central heavy-ion collisions, directly measuring their experimental imprints remains extremely challenging. To address this, we propose the baryon-electric charge correlations $\chi^{\rm BQ}_{11}$ and the chemical potential ratio $\mu_{\rm Q}/\mu_{\rm B}$ as magnetic-field-sensitive probes, based on (2+1)-flavor QCD lattice simulations at physical pion masses. Along the transition line, $\chi^{\rm BQ}_{11}$ and $(\mu_{\rm Q}/\mu_{\rm B})_{\rm LO}$ in Pb-Pb collisions increase by factors of 2.1 and 2.4 at $eB \simeq 8M_\pi^2$, respectively. To bridge theoretical predictions and experimental observations, we construct HRG-based proxies and apply systematic kinematic cuts to emulate STAR and ALICE detector acceptances. Furthermore, we extend this investigation to the QCD equation of state, and examine the leading-order thermodynamic coefficients for strangeness-neutral scenarios up to $eB \simeq 0.8 {\rm GeV}^2 \sim 45 m_{\pi}^2$, revealing intriguing non-monotonic structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21731v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Heng-Tong Ding, Jin-Biao Gu, Arpith Kumar, Sheng-Tai Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First non-zero measurement of a nuclear electric dipole moment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21768</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21768v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper reports the first non-zero measurement of a nuclear electric dipole moment using a novel method based on the rate of change of a supercurrent first proposed in 2016~\cite{https://doi.org/10.48550/arxiv.1604.02152} and fleshed out in this current paper. The theory, experimental concept and implementation are described in detail. The non-zero nuclear electric dipole moment measured with over 1000 hours of data was that of $^{181}$Ta producing a best value $|d_\text{e}^\text{Ta}|=(3.39\pm0.31_\text{stat})\cdot10^{-32}e\cdot\text{cm}$ and $|d_\text{e}^\text{Ta}|=(3.39\pm3.18)\cdot10^{-32}e\cdot\text{cm}&gt;0$ at 99.985\%CL. There is an uncertainty on the value of overall multiplicative parameters such as the self-inductance of the superconducting circuit ($\pm4\%$), the mutual inductance between the SQUID pickup coil and the sample wire ($\pm15\%$), and the magnitude of the solenoid current ($\pm5\%$). An upper-limit was estimated for the control element, $^{207}$Pb, $|d_\text{e}^\text{Pb}|\lesssim1.2\cdot10^{-31}e\cdot\text{cm}$ at 95\%CL.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21768v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gary Pr\'ezeau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interactions of Neutrino Wave Packets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22005v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The low energy effective field theory of interacting neutrinos derived from the Standard Model may be framed as a pointlike interaction and thereby modeled on a lattice of neutrino momenta. We identify a path to take a continuum limit of this lattice problem in the Center of Momentum frame. In this limit, the weak interaction is found to become trivial between incoming plane waves describing ultrarelativistic particles, unless finite neutrino wave packet sizes are taken into consideration. We follow up with an analytic treatment of interacting neutrino wave packets, demonstrating the importance of the wave packet size for characterizing neutrino-neutrino scattering in dense environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22005v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michael J. Cervia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heavy-Flavor Fragmentation and Jet Structure from HF-NRevo: Bridging to Heavy-Ion Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22449v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present recent progress on the Heavy-Flavor Non-Relativistic Evolution (HF-NRevo) framework, designed to describe leading-power fragmentation of heavy-flavored hadrons at moderate to large transverse momentum. Starting from NLO NRQCD calculations for all partonic channels into pseudoscalar quarkonia, we construct the NRFF1.0 collinear fragmentation functions via DGLAP evolution in a variable-flavor number scheme. We outline future prospects in the heavy-ion context, where HF-NRevo can serve as a baseline for modeling in-medium modifications of heavy-flavor fragmentation in nuclear collisions. Its accurate modeling of the partonic hierarchy and threshold effects makes it ideally suited to explore jet-quenching sensitivity, energy-loss mechanisms, and the emergence of medium-modified fragmentation functions in the quark-gluon plasma. Moreover, it provides a natural baseline for implementing in-medium hadronization scenarios, including quarkonium regeneration and fragmentation-function apparent-shape distortion. These developments provide new handles for exploring heavy-flavor dynamics at the HL-LHC and future collider facilities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22449v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Giovanni Celiberto, Francesca Lonigro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent spin polarization from $\rho$ meson condensation in rotating hadronic matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22755v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The behavior of vector mesons in extreme environments provides a unique probe of non-perturbative Quantum Chromodynamics. We investigate the conditions for Bose-Einstein condensation (BEC) of spin-1 $\rho$ mesons in dense rotating hadronic matter, a regime relevant to the peripheral heavy-ion collisions and the interiors of rapidly rotating neutron stars. When the $\rho$ meson chemical potential ($\mu_\rho$) approaches its effective mass ($m_\rho^*$), a phase transition to BEC occurs. We demonstrate that this transition is non-trivially influenced by global rotation, which couples to the spin of the $\rho$ mesons, leading to a macroscopic spin alignment of the condensate along the axis of rotation. This interplay between condensation and rotation results in distinct polarization patterns, which can serve as a possible signature of a BEC in experiments. The results suggest that rapidly rotating neutron stars may harbor an anisotropic, spin-polarized $\rho$-condensed phase, which could impact their equation of state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22755v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kshitish Kumar Pradhan, Dushmanta Sahu, Raghunath Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytic $G_0W_0$ gradients based on a double-similarity transformation equation-of-motion coupled-cluster treatment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23275</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23275v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The accurate prediction of ionization potentials (IPs) is central to understanding molecular reactivity, redox behavior, and spectroscopic properties. While vertical IPs can be accessed directly from electronic excitations at fixed nuclear geometries, the computation of adiabatic IPs requires nuclear gradients of the ionized states, posing a major theoretical and computational challenge, especially within correlated frameworks. Among the most promising approaches for IP calculations is the many-body Green's function $GW$ method, which provides a balanced compromise between accuracy and computational efficiency. Furthermore, it is applicable to both finite and extended systems. Recent work has established formal connections between $GW$ and coupled-cluster doubles (CCD) theory, leading to the first derivation of analytic $GW$ nuclear gradients via a unitary CCD framework. In this work, we present an alternative, fully analytic formulation of $GW$ nuclear gradients based on a modified version of the traditional equation-of-motion CCD formalism, enabling the inclusion of missing correlation effects in the traditional CCD methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23275v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marios-Petros Kitsaras, Johannes T\"olle, Pierre-Fran\c{c}ois Loos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Determination of the Muon Lifetime in $^{76}$Se with the MONUMENT experiment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23401</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23401v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ordinary muon capture provides a benchmark for the nuclear physics models of neutrinoless double beta decay under comparable momentum transfer conditions. The total capture strength defines the lifetime of the muonic atom. The muon lifetime in $^{76}$Se, the daughter nucleus of $^{76}$Ge, was determined with improved accuracy by the MONUMENT collaboration, using an array of high-purity germanium detectors and a set of scintillator counters at the $\pi$E1 muon beam line of the Paul Scherrer Institute. The new value of (135.1 $\pm$ 0.5) ns agrees with phenomenological calculations based on the quasiparticle random phase approximation with unquenched axial-vector coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23401v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. R. Araujo, D. Bajpai, L. Baudis, V. Belov, E. Bossio, T. E. Cocolios, H. Ejiri, M. Fomina, K. Gusev, I. H. Hashim, M. Heines, S. Kazartsev, A. Knecht, E. Mondrag\'on, Z. W. Ng, I. Ostrovskiy, N. Rumyantseva, S. Sch\"onert, M. Schwarz, A. Shehada, E. Shevchik, M. Shirchenko, Y. Shitov, J. Suhonen, S. M. Vogiatzi, C. Vogl, C. Wiesinger, I. Zhitnikov, D. Zinatulina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pentaquarks on the light front, and their mixture with baryons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23404</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23404v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In previous papers we developed the light front formulation for Hamiltonians and wave functions (WFs) for mesons and baryons, with both confinement and chiral symmetry breaking. For baryons limited to the lowest Fock component with three quarks, the longitudinal WF is valued in an equilateral triangle with momentum fractions $x_i,i=1,2,3$. The WF was developed both numerically and using a basis function that diagonalizes the Laplacian with Dirichlet boundary conditions. In this paper we extend this analysis to $n$ quark states, and specialize to pentaquarks ($n=5$). We determine their masses and WFs, and address the mixing between baryons and pentaquarks, the issue central to understanding the observed antiquark sea of baryons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23404v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Miesch, Edward Shuryak, Ismail Zahed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anti-Flatness and Non-Local Magic in Two-Particle Scattering Processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23426v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Non-local magic and anti-flatness provide a measure of the quantum complexity in the wavefunction of a physical system. Supported by entanglement, they cannot be removed by local unitary operations, thus providing basis-independent measures, and sufficiently large values underpin the need for quantum computers in order to perform precise simulations of the system at scale. Towards a better understanding of the quantum-complexity generation by fundamental interactions, the building blocks of many-body systems, we consider non-local magic and anti-flatness in two-particle scattering processes, specifically focusing on low-energy nucleon-nucleon scattering and high-energy Moller scattering. We find that the non-local magic induced in both interactions is four times the anti-flatness (which is found to be true for any two-qubit wavefunction), and verify the relation between the Clifford-averaged anti-flatness and total magic. For these processes, the anti-flatness is a more experimentally accessible quantity as it can be determined from one of the final-state particles, and does not require spin correlations. While the MOLLER experiment at the Thomas Jefferson National Accelerator Facility does not include final-state spin measurements, the results presented here may add motivation to consider their future inclusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23426v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. E. P. Robin, M. J. Savage</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model-independent mass determination of near-threshold states from short-range production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23468</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23468v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel observable for the precision measurements of a wide class of near-threshold dimer states: the short-range production rate of a dimer--spectator two-body system, composed of the given near-threshold state and one of its constituents. Within the framework of nonrelativistic effective field theory, these production rates exhibit characteristic line shapes for the specific partial wave and reach a model-independent minimum. This feature enables a precise extraction of their masses from experimental data, provided that the line shape can be resolved with sufficient accuracy. Applying this novel method to both the $T_{b\bar{b}1}(10610)B$ and $T_{b\bar{b}1}(10650)B^*$ systems allows for a precise determination of the binding energy $\delta$ of the $T_{b\bar{b}1}(10610)$ and $T_{b\bar{b}1}(10650)$ via the relation of $\delta=-{E_{\text{dip}}^{\text{exp}}}/{0.1983}$ once the respective dip position $E_{\text{dip}}^{\text{exp}}$ is experimentally identified.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23468v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yong-Hui Lin, Hans-Werner Hammer, Ulf-G. Mei{\ss}ner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emulators for Scarce and Noisy Data: Application to Auxiliary-Field Diffusion Monte Carlo for Neutron Matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.03680</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.03680v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding the equation of state (EOS) of pure neutron matter is necessary for interpreting multimessenger observations of neutron stars. Reliable data analyses of these observations require well-quantified uncertainties for the EOS input, ideally propagating uncertainties from nuclear interactions directly to the EOS. This, however, requires calculations of the EOS for a prohibitively large number of nuclear Hamiltonians, solving the nuclear many-body problem for each one. Quantum Monte Carlo methods, such as auxiliary-field diffusion Monte Carlo (AFDMC), provide precise and accurate results for the neutron matter EOS, but they are very computationally expensive, making them unsuitable for the fast evaluations necessary for uncertainty propagation. Here, we employ parametric matrix models to develop fast emulators for AFDMC calculations of neutron matter and use them to directly propagate uncertainties of coupling constants in the Hamiltonian to the EOS. As these uncertainties include estimates of the effective field theory truncation uncertainty, this approach provides robust uncertainty estimates for use in astrophysical data analyses. This Letter will enable novel applications such as using astrophysical observations to put constraints on coupling constants for nuclear interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.03680v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/9928-wyjm</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 142501 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Cassandra L. Armstrong, Pablo Giuliani, Kyle Godbey, Rahul Somasundaram, Ingo Tews</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chiral symmetry and peripheral neutron-$\alpha$ scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.09961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.09961v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose and demonstrate that peripheral neutron-$\alpha$ scattering at low energies can serve as a sensitive and clean probe of the long-range three-nucleon forces. To this aim, we perform {\it ab initio} quantum Monte Carlo calculations using two- and three-nucleon interactions derived in chiral effective field theory up to third expansion order. We show that the longest-range three-nucleon force stemming from the two-pion exchange plays a crucial role in the proper description of the neutron-$\alpha$ $D$-wave phase shifts. Our Letter reveals the predictive power of chiral symmetry in the few-body sector and opens a new direction for probing and constraining three-nucleon forces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.09961v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/45g7-bmp6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 172502 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yilong Yang, Evgeny Epelbaum, Jie Meng, Lu Meng, Pengwei Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase transitions in the inner crust of neutron stars within the superfluid band theory: Competition between $^1\text{S}_0$ pairing and spin polarization under finite temperature and magnetic field</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.06250</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.06250v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Phase transitions of matter under changes of external environment such as temperature and magnetic field have attracted great interests to various quantum many-body systems. Several phase transitions must have occurred in neutron stars as well such as transitions from normal to superfluid/superconducting phases and crust formation. In this work, we extend the superfluid band theory, which has been formulated in our previous work [K. Yoshimura and K. Sekizawa, Phys. Rev. C 109, 065804 (2024)] based on the Kohn-Sham density functional theory (DFT) for superfluid systems, into the finite temperature and finite magnetic field systems. As a result of the finite temperature calculations, we find that the superfluidity of neutrons dissapears at around $k_\text{B}T=0.6$--$0.9\,$ MeV, and ``melting'' of nuclear slabs, that is, a structural change into the uniform matter, takes place at around $k_\text{B}T=2.5$--$4.5\,$ MeV. We also reveal that these transition temperatures exhibit a systematical dependence on the baryon densities. By turning on the magnetic field, we find that protons' spin gets polarized at around $B=10^{16}\,$G, whereas neutrons' spin is kept unpolarized on average up to around $B=10^{17}\,$G. Intriguingly, our microscopic calculations reveal that neutrons' spin is actually polarized locally inside and outside of the slab already at $B\sim10^{16}\,$G, while keeping the system unpolarized in total. As a conclusion, we have demonstrated validity and usefulness of the fully self-consistent superfluid nuclear band theory for describing neutron star matter under arbitrary temperature and magnetic field. Critical temperatures and magnetic fields have been predicted for 1) superfluid to normal transition, 2) crust formation, and 3) spin polarization, under conditions relevant to realistic neutron star environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.06250v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kenta Yoshimura, Kazuyuki Sekizawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New angular momentum coupling method based on Wigner rotation theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00940v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a new method for constructing the total angular momentum of many-nucleon states. We find that the restrictions imposed by the fermion antisymmetry on the total state are fully absorbed into the single-j space when the broken rotational symmetry of the product state is restored by angular momentum projection. For different j-shells, any total angular momentum that obeys the selection rule is allowed, just as for non-identical particles. The method based on this reorganization is conceptually different from the traditional J and m schemes and may help to improve the efficiency of angular momentum coupling in nuclear many-body calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00940v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junchao Guo, Yang Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extraction of ground-state nuclear deformations from ultra-relativistic heavy-ion collisions: Nuclear structure physics context</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.05208v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The collective-flow-assisted nuclear shape-imaging method in ultra-relativistic heavy-ion collisions has recently been used to characterize nuclear collective states. In this paper, we assess the foundations of the shape-imaging technique employed in these studies. We argue that some current UHIC nuclear imaging techniques neglect fundamental aspects of spontaneous symmetry-breaking and symmetry-restoration in colliding ions and incorrectly infer one-body multipole moments from studies of nucleonic correlations. Therefore, the impact of this approach on nuclear structure research has been overstated. Conversely, efforts to incorporate existing knowledge on nuclear shapes into analysis pipelines can be beneficial for benchmarking tools and calibrating models used to extract information from ultra-relativistic heavy-ion experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.05208v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Dobaczewski, A. Gade, K. Godbey, R. V. F. Janssens, W. Nazarewicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous improvements in accuracy and generalization of nuclear mass and charge radius predictions using multi-task Gaussian process approaches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.17357</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.17357v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a multi-task Gaussian process (GP) machine learning model to simultaneously predict nuclear masses and charge radii across the nuclear chart. Utilizing 12 physical input features, our multi-task GP consistently outperforms single-task learning, achieving root-mean-square deviations of 0.136 MeV for masses and 0.007 fm for charge radii. The correlations between the two observables are explicitly analyzed within the multi-task learning framework. Three complementary tests, including random data partitions, extrapolations toward nuclei far from stability, and Garvey-Kelson relation analysis, confirm the model's stability, extrapolation reliability, and local physical consistency. Furthermore, by employing the Shapley Additive Explanations (SHAP) method, we interpret the importance of different features for mass and radius predictions across distinct nuclear regions. These results demonstrate the effectiveness of the multi-task GP approach for high-accuracy nuclear property predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.17357v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weihu Ye, Niu Wan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$f$ and $p$ mode oscillation of proto-neutron stars with systematic variation of the nucleon effective mass</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.07000</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.07000v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop equation of state (EoS) of proto-neutron stars (PNSs) at various stages of evolution by varying entropy per baryon $S$, using the Korea-IBS-Daegu-SKKU density functional model. With finite values for both temperature and density, we systematically investigate the influence of nucleon effective mass on EoS of PNSs, for different values of isoscalar effective mass $\mu_S^*$. For high entropy values, we aim to replicate conditions of failed core-collapse supernovae forming black holes. At each stage of evolution, structural and non-radial oscillation (fundamental $f$-mode and first pressure $p_1$-mode) properties are computed under isentropic conditions by varying $\mu_S^*$. We focus on the effects of $S$ and $\mu_S^*$ on oscillation frequencies $f_f$ and $f_{p_1}$ adopting complete general relativistic formalism and Cowling approximation. Thermal effects reduce the values of $f_f$ and $f_{p_1}$ of PNSs compared to those of cold NSs, consequently detection of the former gets facilitated. For high-mass PNSs, this reduction is more pronounced for $f_{p_1}$ than $f_f$. Moreover, lower values of $\mu_S^*$ reduce $f_f$ and $f_{p_1}$ further. Universality of mass-scaled angular frequency ($\omega_fM$) with compactness ($C$) and tidal deformability ($\Lambda$) are obtained as non-linear fits that shift upwards (downwards) in $\omega_fM-C$ ($\omega_fM-\Lambda$) plane for increasing values of $S$. For fixed $S$, the universality is also retained for variation of $\mu_S^*$. $S$ shows stronger correlation than $\mu_S^*$ with structural and oscillation properties of (P)NSs. Strength of correlation of $S$ is more prominent with $f_{p_1}$ than $f_f$ while the trend is opposite for $\mu_S^*$. These findings suggest that detection of oscillation frequencies by upcoming GW detectors, could potentially indicate the evolutionary stage of a star during its transition from supernova to cold NS.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.07000v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atanu Guha, Debashree Sen, Hana Gil, Hajime Togashi, Chang Ho Hyun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutron Skin from Conserved Charge Measurements at Collider Experiments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.21644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.21644v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a novel method for measuring the neutron skin of heavy nuclei using collider experiments. Specifically, we demonstrate that the neutron skin thickness of the lead nucleus can be extracted in $p$+$^{208}$Pb collisions by analyzing a double ratio: The ratio of net electric charge to net baryon number measured near the lead-going rapidity, taken for high-multiplicity events and divided by the same ratio for low-multiplicity events. We compute the expected sensitivity of the double ratio to the neutron skin within a comprehensive (3+1)D relativistic hydrodynamic framework that incorporates multiple conserved charge currents and a charge-dependent lattice-QCD-based equation of state. We provide predictions for both $p$+$^{208}$Pb collisions at ${\sqrt{s_{\mathrm{NN}}}=72}$~GeV and $\sqrt{s_{\mathrm{NN}}}=5.02$~TeV, corresponding to the center of mass energies realized in the SMOG2 fixed-target setup at LHCb and the LHC collider mode, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.21644v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gr\'egoire Pihan, Akihiko Monnai, Bj\"orn Schenke, Chun Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Field Theoretic Approach to Interacting Two Body Tunneling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.11656</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.11656v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Two body tunneling problems are hard to treat analytically due to the incompatibility between tunneling and perturbation theory. The lack of classical solutions of the Euclidean Lagrangian of continuous systems further thwarts semi-classical expansions. To develop an analytic theory which provides insight on interacting two-particle tunneling, we use new results to derive the Bethe-Salpeter equation of a tunneling field theory with Yukawa coupling. We show that in the one plus one dimensional case a closed solution in the instantaneous positive-energy regime is permitted. We then compute the scattering amplitude by perturbing on interparticle interaction and recover the Lippmann-Schwinger equation to confirm physical consistency and relevancy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.11656v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guo Ye</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Universal Relation for the Neutron Star Maximum Mass within Relativistic Mean-Field Theories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.15356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.15356v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We obtain a universal relation for the neutron star maximum mass arising from a particular combination of the saturation density ($n_0$), the effective mass ($m^*$), and (when present) the vector meson self-coupling constant ($\zeta$) within the relativistic mean-field model framework. Observations of massive neutron stars heavier than $\sim 2M_{\odot}$ have eliminated the softest equation of state from consideration and impose strong constraints on nuclear interactions used to model dense nuclear matter. To date there have been numerous attempts to refine relativistic mean-field models by including the presence of additional mesons, such as the delta meson, and couplings. We show that current RMF models, including our own constructions, exhibit a maximum neutron star mass that is primarily determined by the combination of the saturation density, the effective mass at saturation, and the vector meson self-coupling constant. When constraining the pure neutron matter equation of state using chiral effective field theory (ChEFT) at low densities, 250 parameter sets were generated to derive an empirical formula for the maximum mass of neutron stars and apply the formula with the present relativistic mean field models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.15356v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gihwan Nam, Yeunhwan Lim, Jeremy W. Holt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computing nuclear response functions with time-dependent coupled-cluster theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19940</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19940v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We compute nuclear response functions by solving the time-dependent A-body Schr\"odinger equation, recording the time-dependent transition moment and extracting spectral information via Fourier transforms. The solution of the time-dependent many-body problem accounts for correlations on top of the mean field by taking advantage of a time-dependent formulation of coupled-cluster theory. As a validation, we focus on electric dipole transitions in $^4$He and $^{16}$O and compare moments of the response function distribution to the results of an equivalent static framework, finding negligible discrepancies. We investigate how proton and neutron densities evolve in time, and we see the traditional picture of soft and giant dipole resonances as collective oscillations of protons and neutrons emerging from our calculations in $^{16}$O and $^{24}$O. This method also allows us to investigate the behavior of the nucleus in the presence of a strong electric field. In that regime, the behavior of the system becomes chaotic. Qualitatively, the spectral information obtained in this limit is in line with previous time-dependent mean-field results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19940v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesca Bonaiti, Cody Balos, Kyle Godbey, Gaute Hagen, Thomas Papenbrock, Carol S. Woodward</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bose-Einstein Condensation and Dissipative Dynamics in a Relativistic Pion Gas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2212.09288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2212.09288v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Pion condensation in ultra-relativistic collisions presents a compelling theoretical phenomenon with significant implications for the dynamics of hadronic matter. Various theoretical frameworks offer insight into the nature of high-temperature Bose-Einstein condensation (BEC). The present study investigates the dissipative behavior of a relativistic pion gas undergoing Bose-Einstein condensation (BEC) in ultra-relativistic heavy-ion collisions. Further, we obtain viscosity ($\eta$), bulk viscosity ($\zeta$), and speed of sound ($c_s$) by employing the Boltzmann transport equation with the relaxation time approximation. Findings show a substantial drop in $\eta/s$ and $\zeta/s$ with the fractional increase in condensation. This effect is becoming more evident in larger systems approaching the thermodynamic limit. Alongside the reduction in viscosities, the speed of sound also decreases with increasing condensation, indicating a softening of the equation of state. The analysis of finite-size effects reveals that larger systems exhibit more pronounced signatures of BEC. These results suggest that pion condensation can influence the hydrodynamic evolution of the hadronic phase in heavy-ion collisions, with consequential implications for interpreting collective flow observables and the underlying equation of state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2212.09288v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/4lh7-6nvj</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review D 112, 074031 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kshitish Kumar Pradhan, Dushmanta Sahu, Captain R. Singh, Raghunath Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AdS/CFT and the Double-Copy: A Unified Perspective Across Various Phenomenological Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.11418</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.11418v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This study utilizes theoretical tools including the double copy relation and AdS/CFT correspondence. Applying analogies, we establish a system to discuss the associations and equivalence relations among QCD, QED, and various (mixed) gauge field theory based quantum many-body effective models. By employing mathematical techniques on the background spacetime, these relations are extended to extreme regimes while ensuring model independence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.11418v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jia-rui Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simulating lattice fermion doubling with a Floquet drive</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.10601</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.10601v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We consider a recently discovered mathematical correspondence between the spectra of a naively discretized lattice fermion and that of a periodically driven (i.e., Floquet) quantum system and enhance it into an infrared equivalence between the two systems. The equivalence can be framed as a duality relation, allowing us to simulate a two-flavor discrete-time fermion theory on the lattice side, where the two flavors arise from time discretization, using a single-flavor fermion theory on the Floquet side. Our demonstration establishes an equivalence between (i) the fermion content, (ii) the correlation functions, and consequently (iii) observables of the two theories in the infrared, going substantially beyond the previously discovered spectral equivalence. We also show how interactions may be incorporated into this enhanced infrared equivalence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.10601v5</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ra\'ul A. Brice\~no, William Gyory, Thomas Iadecola, Srimoyee Sen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward extracting scattering phase shift from integrated correlation functions on quantum computers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14474</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14474v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Based on a established relation in Refs.~\cite{Guo:2023ecc,Guo:2024zal,Guo:2024pvt} that relates the integrated correlation functions for a trapped system to the infinite volume scattering phase shifts through a weighted integral, we propose to extract the infinite volume scattering phase shifts through quantum simulation of the integrated correlation functions of trapped two-particle systems on quantum computers. The integrated correlation function can be computed by an ancilla-based algorithm proposed in Ref.~\cite{PhysRevA.64.022319}. The proposal is demonstrated with a simple contact interaction fermion model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14474v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the validity of the complex Langevin method near the deconfining phase transition in QCD at finite density</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06551v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In our previous paper [JHEP 10 (2020) 144], we found that the complex Langevin (CL) method works for QCD at finite density on the $16^3 \times 32$ lattice in the low-temperature high-density regime within the range $\mu / T = 1.6 - 9.6$ with $\mu$ and $T$ being the quark chemical potential and the temperature, which enabled us to see a clear trend towards the formation of the Fermi sphere. Here we investigate the validity of the CL method on the $24^3 \times 12$ lattice in the deconfined phase near the deconfinement phase transition. As before, we use four-flavor staggered fermions and judge the validity using the criterion based on the probability distribution of the drift term. The spatial extent is $L = (1.3 - 2.7 {\rm ~fm} )&gt; \Lambda_{\rm LQCD}^{-1} \sim 1{\rm ~fm}$, in contrast to our previous study with $L &lt; \Lambda_{\rm LQCD}^{-1}$. We find that the CL method works in a broad region up to $\mu / T = 4.8$, while it starts to fail as we approach the phase boundary due to the singular drift problem, which can be understood qualitatively by extending the Banks-Casher relation to the case at finite density.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06551v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP10(2025)108</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. High Energ. Phys. 2025, 108 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shoichiro Tsutsui, Yuhma Asano, Yuta Ito, Hideo Matsufuru, Yusuke Namekawa, Jun Nishimura, Shinji Shimasaki, Asato Tsuchiya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proton Structure Functions from Holographic Einstein-Dilaton Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13649v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the proton structure functions $F_1$ and $F_2$ in the context of holography. We develop a general framework that extends previous holographic calculations of $F_1$ and $F_2$ to the case where the bulk geometry stems from bottom-up Einstein-Dilaton models, which are commonly used in the literature to describe some properties of QCD in the strong coupling regime. We focus on a choice of the dilaton potential that leads to a holographic model able to reproduce known lattice QCD results for the glueball masses at zero temperature and pure Yang-Mills thermodynamics above deconfinement. Once the parameters of the background holographic model are fixed, we introduce probe fermionic and gauge fields in the bulk {\it a la} Polchinski and Strassler to determine the corresponding structure functions. This particular realization of the model can successfully describe the proton mass and provide results for $F_2$ at large $x$ in very good agreement with experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13649v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayrton da Cruz Pereira do Nascimento, Henrique Boschi-Filho, Jorge Noronha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Quark Stars with Quark-Quark Phase Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.00776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.00776v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We explore the possibility of phase transitions between different quark matter phases occurring within quark stars, giving rise to the hybrid quark stars (HybQSs). First, we obtain the generic phase diagram of possible mass-radius relation forms for the HybQSs. Then, utilizing a well-established general parameterization of interacting quark matter, we construct quark star models featuring sharp first-order quark-quark phase transitions of various types, in contrast to the hadron-quark transition in conventional hybrid stars. We systematically investigate how recent observations, such as the pulsar mass measurement $M_{\rm TOV}\gtrsim2M_{\odot}$ and the GW170817's tidal deformability bound $\Lambda_{1.4M_{\odot}}&lt;800$, constrain the viable parameter space. We also identified twin stars in some of the HybQS parameter space. Furthermore, we found that the quark-quark phase transitions in hybrid quark stars may also cause the deviation from the approximate universal relation between the dominant postmerger frequency $f_{\rm peak}$ and tidal deformability $\Lambda_{1.35M_{\odot}}$, which was previously believed to only be caused by the hadron-quark phase transitions in hybrid neutron stars. This work unveils new possibilities of phase transitions and the resulting new types of compact stars in realistic astrophysical scenarios.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.00776v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zongcan Yang, Tianxiong Zeng, Yan Yan, Wen-Li Yuan, Chen Zhang, Enping Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward extracting scattering phase shift from integrated correlation functions V: complex $\phi^4$ field model in $3+1$ dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12881v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In Ref.~\cite{Guo:2024zal} and associated studies, a relativistic finite-volume formalism in $1+1$ dimensions is proposed to extract infinite-volume scattering phaseshift.
  It is based on the difference of integrated correlation functions (ICF) rather than energy spectrum in the finite volume, and can be regarded as complementary to the well-known L\"{uscher} formalism.
  In the present work, the formalism is further extended into $3+1$ dimensional spacetime. The aim is to explore and demonstrate the challenges in applying the formalism to more practical settings. Specifically, Monte Carlo simulations of a complex $\phi^4$ relativistic field model are carried out in both 2+1 and 3+1 dimensions on lattices of varying sizes, and phaseshifts for the contact interaction are extracted from the formalism using modest computing resources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12881v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Guo, Frank X. Lee, Andrei Alexandru</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
