<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 21 Mar 2025 01:54:26 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Study of event and particle selection effects on elliptic flow background at the isobar experiments based on AMPT model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14815v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Measurement of the Chiral Magnetic Effect (CME) has been a popular topic of high-energy nuclear physics in the last decade. The flow correlation $\gamma$ between charged hadron pairs of the same and opposite charges and their difference $\Delta \gamma$ were measured to separate the CME-driven signal from the collective flow background especially second-order elliptic $v_{2}$. The STAR experiment have stepped further to the isobar experiment to compare $\gamma$ and $\Delta \gamma$ between Ru+Ru and Zr+Zr ~\cite{PhysRevC.105.014901}, which were theoretically expected to produce the same elliptic flow background but different CME signals. However, the measured flow backgrounds also differ between Ru+Ru and Zr+Zr, indicating more fine-tuning of RP and centrality definition necessary.
  This analysis applied the AMPT model~\cite{PhysRevC.72.064901} to simulate the same collision system and energy as the STAR isobar experiment. Since the AMPT model does not include magnetic field effects, we expect comparing its output between Ru+Ru and Zr+Zr collision systems can provide an insight of the possible bias of flow background definition, and help improve the measurement of CME signal in real experiments. Multiple combinations of centrality and flow definition were chosen to study how the $v_2$ and their difference would be affected, especially by varying the particles selection of charge versus neutral properties and broadening (pseudo-)rapidity regions, while STAR CME work relied on charged-only particles at central rapidity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14815v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Wang, Hua Pei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fine-tunings in nucleosynthesis and the emergence of life: Status and perspectives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15162v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We discuss the fine-tunings of nuclear reactions in the Big Bang and in stars and draw some conclusions on the emergence of the light elements and the life-relevant elements carbon and oxygen. We also stress how to improve these calculations in the future. This requires a concerted effort of different communities, especially in nuclear reaction theory, lattice QCD for few-nucleon systems, stellar evolution calculations, particle physics and philosophy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15162v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulf-G. Mei{\ss}ner, Bernard Ch. Metsch, Helen Meyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nuclear Physics under the low-energy, high intensity frontier</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15224v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite numerous achievements and recent progress, nuclear physics is often (wrongly) considered an old field of research nowadays. However, developments in theoretical frameworks and reliable experimental techniques have made the field mature enough to explore many new frontiers. In this regard, extending existing knowledge to an emerging field of physics -- where particles interact with a relatively low-energy but high intensity field (intense enough so that multi-particle processes become comparable or more important than one-to-one processes) -- can lead to exciting discoveries. Investigations can be realized under a highly time-compressed beam source (e.g., particle sources generated by laser-matter interaction using high-power laser systems). Here we focus on a new scheme, where high-power laser systems are exploited as a driver to generate energetic ($\gamma$-ray) photons. Together with additional low-energy photons provided by a second, less intense laser, a multi-photon absorption scheme enables a very attainable manipulation of nuclear transitions including isomer pumping and depletion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15224v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. -J. Yang, V. Horny, D. Doria, K. Spohr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron capture of superheavy nuclei with realistic lepton wave functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14613v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The superheavy nuclei push the periodic table of the elements and the chart of the nuclides to their limits, providing a unique laboratory for studies of the electron-nucleus interactions. The most important weak decay mode in known superheavy nuclei is electron capture (EC). In the standard calculations of EC, the lepton wave functions are usually considered in the lowest-order approximation. In this work, we investigate the sensitivity of EC rates on the choice of the electron wave functions by (i) assuming the single-particle approximation for the electron wave functions, and (ii) carrying out Dirac-Hartree-Fock (DHF) calculations. The nuclear response is generated based on the state-of-the-art quasiparticle random phase approximation employing relativistic nuclear energy density functional theory. We show that using the improved lepton wave functions reduces the EC rates up to 40\% in the superheavy nucleus oganesson ($Z=118$). Interestingly, because of screening effects, the difference between the EC rates obtained with the DHF and single-particle calculations is fairly small.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14613v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Ravli\'c, P. Schwerdtfeger, W. Nazarewicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Lithium and Beryllium to Study Structure and Evolution of Rotating Stars</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.14804</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.14804v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The chemical composition of the Sun is still a highly controversial issue. No solar model has yet been able to simultaneously reproduce the solar lithium and beryllium abundances, along with helioseismic results, including the rotation profile. Lithium and beryllium are fragile elements that are highly sensitive to the physical conditions, as well as to transport and mixing processes within and below the convective zone (CZ). Uncovering the transport mechanisms responsible for the depletion of Li and Be in the Sun is crucial for using them as tools to understand stellar interiors and the associated transport and mixing processes. We constructed rotating solar models based on Magg's abundance scale, incorporating the effects of convective overshoot and magnetic fields. The rotating model exhibits superior sound speed and density profile and successfully reproduces the observed ratios $r_{02}$ and $r_{13}$. It also matches the seismically inferred CZ depth, surface helium abundance, and rotation profile, as well as the detected Li and Be abundances and neutrino fluxes within $1\sigma$. The depletion of Li is dominated by convective overshoot and rotational mixing, while Be depletion is primarily driven by gravitational settling and rotational mixing. The presence of the tachocline accelerates Li depletion but slows down Be depletion. These distinct depletion mechanisms result in the surface abundances of Li and Be evolving differently over time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.14804v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3847/1538-4357/adb730</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Wuming Yang, Haibo Yuan, Yaqian Wu, Shaolan Bi, Zhijia Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of hadron interactions and compositeness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15376v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Plenty of hadrons have been established experimentally, yet the nonperturbative nature of the strong interaction complicates a comprehensive understanding of their internal structure, particularly for exotic hadrons that extend beyond conventional mesons and baryons. One prominent candidate for the internal structure of exotic hadrons is the hadronic molecule, a loosely bound system of hadrons analogous to atomic nuclei. Understanding such systems requires precise knowledge of hadron interactions, which traditional scattering experiments struggle to provide, especially in the low-energy region. Recent advances, including precise baryon-baryon interaction measurements, femtoscopy techniques that probe momentum correlations between particles, and first-principles lattice QCD calculations, have significantly improved our understanding of hadron interactions. Here, we review these recent developments, demonstrate the successful application of femtoscopy to antikaon-nucleon interactions, utilize the concept of compositeness to quantify the hadronic molecular component of the Lambda(1405), and discuss both experimental and theoretical prospects, including future studies at J-PARC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15376v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tetsuo Hyodo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutron emission from the photon-induced reactions in ultraperipheral ultrarelativistic heavy-ion collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17865v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The ultraperipheral collisions are the source of various interesting phenomena based on photon-induced reactions. We calculate cross sections for single and any number of n, p, $\alpha$, $\gamma$-rays in ultraperipheral heavy-ion collision for LHC energies. We analyze the production of a given number of neutrons relevant for a recent ALICE experiment, for $\sqrt{s_{NN}}$ = 5.02~TeV. In our approach, we include both single and multiple photon exchanges as well as the fact that not all photon energies are used in the process of equilibration of the residual nucleus. We propose a simple two-component model in which only part of photon energy $E_\gamma$ is changed into the excitation energy of the nucleus ($E_{exc} \neq E_{\gamma}$) and compare its results with outcomes of HIPSE and EMPIRE codes. The role of high photon energies for small neutron multiplicities is discussed. Emission of a small number of neutrons at high photon energies seems to be crucial to understand the new ALICE data. All effects work in the desired direction, but the description of the cross section of four- and five-neutron emission cross sections from first principles is rather demanding. The estimated emission of charged particles such as protons, deuterons and $\alpha$ is shortly discussed and confronted with very recent ALICE data, obtained with the proton Zero Degree Calorimeter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17865v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pawel Jucha, Mariola Klusek-Gawenda, Antoni Szczurek, Michal Ciemala, Katarzyna Mazurek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two- versus three-body approach to femtoscopic hadron-deuteron correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08283v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The three-body approach to hadron-deuteron correlations is shown to turn into a two-body approach if the three-particle hadron-deuteron wave function factorizes into the deuteron wave-function and the wave function of a hadron motion relative to the deuteron. Then, the hadron-deuteron correlation function is as in the two-body approach only the source radius somewhat changes. For this reason, as we argue, the two-body approach works well for kaon-deuteron correlations but it fails for proton-deuteron ones in case of small sources. Applying the three-body approach generalized to the case where the radius of the hadron source is different from the nucleon source radius, we derive the source radius formula which used in the two-body approach gives the correlation function as in the `factorized' three-body one. The formula is discussed in the context of existing and future experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08283v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stanislaw Mrowczynski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Entanglement as a probe of hadronization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22331v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recently, it was discovered that the proton structure at high energies exhibits maximal entanglement. This leads to a simple relation between the proton's parton distributions and the entropy of hadrons produced in high-energy inelastic interactions that has been experimentally confirmed. In this letter, we extend this approach to the production of jets. Here, the maximal entanglement predicts a relation between the jet fragmentation function and the entropy of hadrons produced in jet fragmentation. We test this relation using the ATLAS Collaboration data on jet production at the Large Hadron Collider and find good agreement between the prediction based on maximal entanglement within the jet and the data. This study represents the first use of the quantum entanglement framework in the experimental study of the hadronization process, offering a new perspective on the transition from perturbative to non-perturbative QCD. Our results open the door to a more comprehensive understanding of the quantum nature of hadronization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22331v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.111902</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jaydeep Datta, Abhay Deshpande, Dmitri E. Kharzeev, Charles Joseph Na\"im, Zhoudunming Tu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
