<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 02:49:35 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Implications of a Weakening N = 126 Shell Closure Away from Stability for r-Process Astrophysical Conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02690v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The formation of the third r-process abundance peak near A = 195 is highly sensitive to both nuclear structure far from stability and the astrophysical conditions that produce the heaviest elements. In particular, the N = 126 shell closure plays a crucial role in shaping this peak. Experimental data hints that the shell weakens as proton number departs from Z = 82, a trend largely missed by global mass models. To investigate its impact on r-process nucleosynthesis, we employ both standard global models with strong closures and modified Duflo-Zuker (DZ) models that reproduce the weakening, combined with three sets of beta minus decay rates. Strong shell closures generate sharply peaked abundances, whereas weakened closures consistent with the experimental trend produce broader, flatter patterns. Accurately reproducing the solar third peak under weakened shell strength requires highly neutron-rich conditions (Ye &lt;= 0.175) and slower decay rates. These results demonstrate that a weakening N = 126 shell closure away from stability imposes significant constraints on the astrophysical environments of the r-process and underscores the need for precise mass measurements and improved characterization of beta minus decay properties in this region.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02690v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mengke Li, Gail C. McLaughlin, Rebecca Surman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Role of universal function of the nuclear proximity potential: A systematic study on the alpha-decay of heavy/super-heavy nuclei and {\alpha}-induced reactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02764v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The idea of the universal function is fundamental advantage of proximity potential model. We present a systematic study of the role of universal function of the proximity potential model on alpha decay process for 250 ground state to ground state transitions using WKB approximation. In order to realize this goal, five universal functions proposed in the proximity models gp 77, Guo 2013, Ngo 80, Zhang 2013 and Prox. 2010 have been incorporated into the formalism of Prox. 77. The obtained results show that the radial behavior of universal function affects the penetration probability of the {\alpha} particle. The theoretical {\alpha} decay half lives are calculated and compared with the corresponding experimental data. It is shown that the Prox. 77 with Guo 2013 universal function provides the best fit to the available data. The role of the different universal functions in the {\alpha} decay half lives of super heavy nuclei (SHN) with Z from 104 to 118 are also studied. It is shown that the experimental half lives in the super heavy mass region are described well using the Prox. 77 with Zhang 2013 universal function. In this paper, the validity of the original and modified forms of the proximity 77 potential is also examined for complete fusion reactions between {\alpha} particle and 10 different target nuclei. Our results show that the measured {\alpha} induced fusion reaction cross sections can be well reproduced using the Prox. 77 with Zhang 2013 universal function for the reactions involving light and medium nuclei. Whereas, the Prox. 77 with Guo 2013 universal function model demonstrates a reliable agreement with the experimental data at sub-barrier energies for heavier systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02764v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/x48g-zd24</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>S. Mohammadi, R. Gharaei, S. A. Alavi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imprints of dynamic fluidization on dilepton production</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02862v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a newly developed hybrid hadronic transport + hydrodynamics framework geared towards heavy ion collisions at low to intermediate beam energies, and report on the resulting excitation function of dileptons. In this range of energies, it is unclear how to properly initialize the hydrodynamic evolution. Due to the cumulative electromagnetic radiation throughout the collision, dilepton observables are sensitive to the initial condition. In this work, we study how the dilepton ``thermometer'' is affected by employing dynamical initial conditions, in contrast to the traditional fixed-time approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02862v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Renan G\'oes-Hirayama, Zuzana Paul\'inyov\'a, Joscha Egger, Iurii Karpenko, Hannah Elfner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Production of spectator neutrons, protons and light fragments on fixed targets at NICA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02992</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02992v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Ultrarelativistic Quantum Molecular Dynamics (UrQMD) model was connected to a set of models called Ablation Monte Carlo (AMC) to identify excited spectator fragments on completion of the UrQMD modeling of nucleus-nucleus collisions and then simulate spectator decays. The UrQMD-AMC approach combines the Minimum Spanning Tree (MST) clustering algorithm, which associates individual nucleons with excited clusters termed prefragments, with decay models of excited nuclei from the Geant4 toolkit. The relevant decay model for the prefragments decay is selected based on their mass and excitation energy, and includes nuclear evaporation, statistical multifragmentation, and Fermi breakup models. The UrQMD-AMC approach was validated by comparing its results with data on the rapidity and transverse momentum distributions of neutrons and light fragments from 600A MeV Sn + Sn and 10.6A GeV Au + Ag collisions. This approach supplements the evolution of individual nucleons during a nucleus-nucleus collision simulated with UrQMD with nucleon clustering to simulate also the production of spectator nuclear fragments, which are not produced in the UrQMD model alone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02992v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. O. Svetlichny (Institute for Nuclear Research, Russian Academy of Sciences, Moscow, Russia, Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology, Dolgoprudny, Russia), E. Y. Vasyagina (Institute for Nuclear Research, Russian Academy of Sciences, Moscow, Russia, Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology, Dolgoprudny, Russia), S. D. Savenkov (Institute for Nuclear Research, Russian Academy of Sciences, Moscow, Russia, Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology, Dolgoprudny, Russia), I. A. Pshenichnov (Institute for Nuclear Research, Russian Academy of Sciences, Moscow, Russia, Moscow Institute of Physics and Technology, Dolgoprudny, Russia)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Principal Components of Nuclear Mass Model Residuals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03020</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03020v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Principal Component Analysis (PCA) is applied to the residuals of six widely used nuclear mass models to uncover systematic deviations and identify missing physical effects in theoretical nuclear mass predictions. By analyzing the principal components of nuclear mass model residuals, this study reveals that no single dominant pattern governs the discrepancies across models. Instead, the residual structures are largely uncorrelated, indicating that current nuclear mass models fail to capture underlying nuclear residual effects in distinct and model-specific ways. These findings suggest that improvements to nuclear mass models should be guided by model-specific residual analyses rather than a one-size-fits-all approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03020v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Y. Huang, X. H. Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Predictions in modified Glauber model of total charged-particle yields centrality dependence in O+O and Ne+Ne collisions at LHC</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03079v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this article we present the results of application of the Monte Carlo modified Glauber model for the predictions of collision centrality dependence of the total charged-particle yields for 16O +16O and 20Ne+20Ne colliding systems at the LHC.
  Our model differs from the Standard Glauber model by the effective account of the energy losses in successive inelastic nucleon-nucleon collisions. For this purpose, a single model parameter k is defined as a mean fraction of the momentum loss that happens in any binary nucleon collision due to the production of multiple particles. Therefore, the decrease of the nucleon momentum after each inelastic collision leads to a corresponding reduction of the inelastic cross section and the mean multiplicity yield in the subsequent interaction. All these effects are taken into account in the MC model in each of the subsequent inelastic binary interactions.
  We discuss the purely geometrical effects for these light colliding systems that could be considered useful in future studies of QGP properties in energy density scanning. Predictions in this single parameter model are based on the previous successful analysis of non-linear centrality dependence of charged particle yields observed in Pb+Pb collisions by ALICE at the LHC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03079v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Svetlana Simak, Grigory Feofilov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Application of the holographic equations of state for modeling experiments on heavy ion collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03157</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03157v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we propose a method for numerical modeling of the nuclear matter properties within the framework of relativistic heavy-ion collisions using a holographic equation of state. Machine learning methods were applied to address the regression and optimization issues during the calibration of the relevant parameters using the LQCD results for quark masses that approximate the physical values. Numerical simulations are performed using the iEBE-MUSIC and vHLLE-SMASH frameworks, which incorporate certain relativistic hydrodynamics solvers. We modify the code by implementing a tabulated holographic equation of state, enabling simulations of quark-gluon plasma evolution with dynamically generated initial conditions via the 3D Monte Carlo Glauber Model and SMASH. Finally, the spectra of produced hadrons are computed using a hybrid iSS+UrQMD and Hadron Sampler+SMASH approaches at the freeze-out stage.12 p</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03157v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Anufriev, V. N. Kovalenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ArgoLOOM: agentic AI for fundamental physics from quarks to cosmos</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.02426</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.02426v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Progress in modern physics has been supported by a steadily expanding corpus of numerical analyses and computational frameworks, which in turn form the basis for precision calculations and baseline predictions in experimental programs. These tools play a central role in navigating a complex landscape of theoretical models and current and potential observables to identify and understand fundamental interactions in physics. In addition, efforts to search for new fundamental interactions increasingly have a cross-disciplinary nature, such that understanding and leveraging interoperabilities among computational tools may be a significant enhancement. This work presents a new agentic AI framework, which we call ArgoLOOM, designed to bridge methodologies and computational analyses across cosmology, collider physics, and nuclear science. We describe the system contours, key internal aspects, and outline its potential for unifying scientific discovery pipelines. In the process, we demonstrate the use of ArgoLOOM on two small-scale problems to illustrate its conceptual foundations and potential for extensibility into a steadily growing agentic framework for fundamental physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.02426v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. D. Bakshi, P. Barry, C. Bissolotti, I. Cloet, S. Corrodi, Z. Djurcic, S. Habib, K. Heitmann, T. J. Hobbs, W. Hopkins, S. Joosten, B. Kriesten, N. Ramachandra, A. Wells, M. Zurek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical framework for nuclear parameter uncertainties in nucleosynthesis modeling of r- and i-process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.03138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.03138v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Propagating nuclear uncertainties to nucleosynthesis simulations is key to understand the impact of theoretical uncertainties on the predictions, especially for processes far from the stability region, where nuclear properties are scarcely known. While systematic (model) uncertainties have been thoroughly studied, the statistical (parameter) ones have been more rarely explored, as constraining them is more challenging. We present here a methodology to determine coherently parameter uncertainties by anchoring the theoretical uncertainties to the experimentally known nuclear properties through the use of the Backward Forward Monte Carlo method. We use this methodology for two nucleosynthesis processes: the intermediate neutron capture process (i-process) and the rapid neutron capture process (r-process). We determine coherently for the i-process the uncertainties from the (n,$\gamma$) rates while we explore the impact of nuclear mass uncertainties for the r-process. The effect of parameter uncertainties on the final nucleosynthesis is in the same order as model uncertainties, suggesting the crucial need for more experimental constraints on key nuclei of interest. We show how key nuclear properties, such as relevant (n,$\gamma$) rates impacting the i-process tracers, could enhance tremendously the prediction of stellar evolution models by experimentally constraining them.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.03138v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epja/s10050-025-01510-y 10.1140/epja/s10050-025-01510-y</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>S. Martinet, G. Goriely, A. Choplin, L. Siess</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Imaging nuclei by smashing them at high energies: how are their shapes revealed after destruction?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.16071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.16071v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-energy nuclear collisions have recently emerged as a promising ``imaging-by-smashing'' approach that may reveal the intrinsic shapes of atomic nuclei. Here, I outline a conceptual framework for this technique, explaining how nuclear shapes are encoded during quark-gluon plasma formation and evolution, and how they can be decoded from final-state particle distributions. I highlight the method's potential to advance our understanding of both nuclear structure and quark-gluon plasma physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.16071v4</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Rept.Prog.Phys. 88 (2025) 9, 092301</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jiangyong Jia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling of acceleration in heavy-ion collisions: occurrence of temperature below the Unruh temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.10146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.10146v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: It has recently been shown that extremely strong electric fields can be created in central collisions of heavy ions, due to which the Schwinger effect can be significant. A direct analogue of the electric field in hydrodynamics is the acceleration of the medium. Using the parton-hadron-string dynamics (PHSD) framework we model the Au-Au collisions at intermediate collision energies $\sqrt{s_{NN}}=4.5-11.5\,$GeV and obtain the spatial distribution of acceleration at different time moments. The present study demonstrates that extremely high acceleration of the order of 1 GeV may be generated in both central and non-central collisions, and that the distribution exhibits a core-corona structure. Consequently, in contrast to the case with an electric field, the Unruh effect is expected to be significant. It is demonstrated that for the confined phase the temperature is less than the Unruh temperature. Conversely, in the deconfined phase, the relationship is inverse. The obtained results thus support the prediction about the existence of states with $T&lt;T_U$ at the early stages of the collision and the associated complementary description of thermalization in terms of the novel phase transition at the Unruh temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.10146v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>G. Yu. Prokhorov, D. A. Shohonov, O. V. Teryaev, N. S. Tsegelnik, V. I. Zakharov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Gauge Theory Bootstrap: Predicting pion dynamics from QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19332</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19332v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Gauge Theory Bootstrap [arXiv:2309.12402, arXiv:2403.10772] computes the strongly coupled pion dynamics by considering the most general scattering matrix, form factors and spectral densities and matching them with perturbative QCD at high energy and with weakly coupled pions at low energy. In this work, we show that further constraints on the spectral densities significantly reduce the possible solutions to a small set of qualitatively similar ones. Quantitatively, the precise solution is controlled by the asymptotic value of the form factors and SVZ sum rules. We also introduce an iterative procedure that, starting from a generic feasible point, converges to a unique solution parameterized by the UV input. For the converged solution we compute masses and widths of resonances that appear, scattering lengths and effective ranges of partial waves, low energy coefficients in the effective action. Additionally, we use these results to discuss the thermodynamics of a pion gas including pair correlations of pions with same and opposite charge.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19332v2</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifei He, Martin Kruczenski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inclusion of the Longitudinal Momentum-Transfer Component and Kinematic Factors in a diffraction approach for H(d,p)X Reactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.06579</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.06579v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this work, within the framework of the Glauber-Sitenko approximation, an analysis of the differential cross section for deuteron breakup into a proton in the reaction H(d,p)X is presented. The study is carried out using various parameterizations of the deuteron wave function, including the single-Gaussian parametrization, the multi-Gaussian K2 parametrization, and models based on the Av18 and NijmI nucleon-nucleon potentials. Special attention is given to the effects of small longitudinal components of the transferred momentum (Qz &lt; 0.5 GeV/c) and the transverse momentum of the proton-neutron pair (p_perp &lt; 0.5 GeV/c) in the anti-laboratory reference frame. The results are compared with experimental data, particularly in the region of longitudinal momenta p\_3 = 0.25-0.5 GeV/c, where quark effects are expected to manifest. Preliminary estimates show a decrease in the cross section with increasing transverse momentum, as well as a relatively small shift (and growth) of the cross-section maximum due to the inclusion of the longitudinal component Qz.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.06579v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ya. D. Krivenko-Emetov, B. I. Sidorenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Confronting the production mechanisms of nuclei with deuteron and proton-triggered balance functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03195v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In ultra high-energy collisions, nuclei with very low binding energies are not expected to survive the dense and hot final state environment. The traditional view has therefore been that nuclei form via coalescence after the hot environment has dissipated. However, statistical thermal models, where hadrons are produced from a fireball at thermal equilibrium, can describe the relative abundances of light nuclei in pp and heavy-ion collisions at the LHC equally well. In this paper we investigate if balance functions triggered by protons and deuterons can be used to distinguish between the two production mechanisms. The coalescence model is investigated using PYTHIA, while the statistical thermal model is examined using the Thermal FIST package. We find that for both models the same simple relation between proton and deuteron triggered balance functions is applicable. However, there is a striking difference between the two models when the transverse momentum of trigger particles is varied. This dependence offers a promising observable to discriminate between the two production scenarios that goes beyond nuclei production. Furthermore, we find that deuteron-meson balance functions vanish identically for both models due to baryon number conservation and isospin symmetry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03195v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sushanta Tripathy, Peter Christiansen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gluon Condensation as a Unifying Mechanism for Special Spectra of Cosmic Gamma Rays and Low-Momentum Pion Enhancement at the Large Hadron Collider</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00847</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00847v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Decoding the internal structure of the proton is a fundamental challenge in physics. Historically, any new discovery about the proton has fuelled advances in several scientific fields. We have reported that gluons inside the proton accumulate near the critical momentum due to chaotic phenomena, forming gluon condensation. Surprisingly, the pion distribution predicted by this gluon distribution for the production of high-energy proton collisions could answer two puzzles in astronomy and high-energy physics. We find that during ultrahigh-energy cosmic ray collisions, gluon condensation may abruptly produce a large number of low-momentum pions, whose electromagnetic decays have the typical breakout properties appearing in various cosmic gamma-ray spectra. On the other hand, the Large Hadron Collider (LHC), which is well below the cosmic ray energy scale, also shows weak but recognisable signs of gluon condensation, which had been mistaken for BEC pions. The connection between these two phenomena, which occur at different scales in the Universe, supports the existence of a new structure within the proton-gluon condensation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00847v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Zhu, Jianhong Ruan, Xurong Chen, Yuchen Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
