<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 05:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Continuum Effects and the Trojan Horse Mechanism in Halo Nuclei-Induced Reactions: Implications for Heavy Isotope Synthesis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20672v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nonelastic breakup (NEB) reactions induced by the halo nucleus $^{11}$Be on $^{64}$Zn at 28.7 MeV are investigated using the Ichimura-Austern-Vincent (IAV) model combined with the Continuum Discretized Coupled Channels (CDCC) method. NEB cross sections calculated with full CDCC wave functions (including continuum states), ground-state-only CDCC wave functions, and single-channel calculations are compared. The results indicate that continuum effects are negligible and that NEB cross sections are dominated by the ground-state contribution. This validates the use of simpler models like the distorted wave Born approximation for such reactions. Additionally, by varying the binding energy in a toy model, the feasibility of using halo nuclei in the Trojan Horse Method (THM) for synthesizing heavy isotopes is explored. It is demonstrated that THM significantly enhances sub-barrier fusion cross sections due to the weak binding of halo nuclei, offering a promising approach for the synthesis of new elements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20672v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin Lei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bound-state formation and thermalization within the Lindblad approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.21047</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.21047v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The Lindblad equation, as one approach to open quantum systems, describes the density matrix of a particle or a chain of interacting particles, which are in contact with a thermal bath. Still, it is not fully understood yet, how arbitrary systems evolve towards a stationary distribution, which guarantees thermalization in a thermodynamical context, and how to systematically incorporate the variety of assumptions that are made in this approach in order to preserve thermal Gibbs states. Despite these shortcomings, Lindblad dynamics was successfully employed in heavy-ion physics (quarkonia) and also became of interest in quantum-computer applications.
  In this paper, we consider a problem borrowed from heavy-ion collisions, namely the formation of bound states, as for example the deuteron, in the non-relativistic regime by using the already well understood techniques of Lindblad dynamics. However, only recently, we were able to extend this toolbox by showing, that the position-space Lindblad equation can be reformulated in terms of a diffusion-advection equation with sources and therefore provides a hydrodynamical formulation of a dissipative quantum master equation. Making use of this advanced machinery and insights, we describe the possible formation of a bound state, which is realized by a P\"oschl-Teller-like potential, of a particle in interaction with a heat bath in a 1-dim setting. We analyse the possibility of a thermalization and the time-scale of the formation, population and depopulation of the bound state. Finally, we also show an example of a much deeper potential, where we allow for three bound states, just in the spirit of quarkonia. Besides this, we discuss general aspects of open quantum systems, like decoherence, entropy production etc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.21047v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jan Rais, Hendrik van Hees, Carsten Greiner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge symmetry breaking in hypernuclei within RMF model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.21161</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.21161v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the charge symmetry breaking (CSB) effect in the binding energy of mirror hypernuclei in the mass region $A=7\sim 48$ in relativistic mean field (RMF) models introducing $NN$ and $\Lambda N$ interactions. The phenomenological $\Lambda N$ CSB interaction is introduced and the strength parameter is fitted to reproduce the experimental binding energy difference between the mirror hypernuclei $^{12}_\Lambda$B and $^{12}_\Lambda$C. This model is applied to calculate the CSB energy anomaly in mirror hypernuclei with the mass $A=7\sim48$. The model is further applied to predict the binding energy difference of mirror hypernuclei of $A$=40 with the isospin $T=1/2$, $3/2$ and $5/2$ nuclei together with various hyper Ca isotopes and their mirror hypernuclei. Finally the binding energy systematics of $A=$48 hypernuclei are predicted with/without the CSB effect by the PK1 and TM2 energy density functionals (EDFs).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.21161v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ting-Ting Sun, Yusuke Tanimura, Hiroyuki Sagawa, Emiko Hiyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing double hadron resonance by complex momentum representation method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20660</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20660v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Resonances are ubiquitous phenomena in nature, and physicists have developed many methods to explore resonant states. Of particular note is the complex momentum representation(CMR) method, which has been developed and widely used in the study of resonant states in atomic, molecular and nuclear physics. Here, for the first time, we have developed this novel method to study hadron resonant states. The CMR method is applied to probe the bound and resonant states for the $\Lambda_cD(\bar{D})$ and $\Lambda_c\Lambda_c(\bar{\Lambda}_c)$ systems, in which the resonant states are exposed clearly in complex momentum plane and the resonance parameters can be determined precisely without imposing unphysical parameters. The results show that the CMR method has achieving higher accuracy than other widely used methods. This method is not only very effective for narrow resonances, but also can be reliably applied to broad resonances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20660v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wen-Wan He, Mao Song, Jian-You Guo, Xuan Luo, Gang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativistic configuration-interaction density functional theory: Nonaxial effects on nuclear $\beta\beta$ decay</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2304.12009</link>
      <description>arXiv:2304.12009v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The relativistic configuration-interaction density functional theory is developed for even-even and odd-odd nuclei and is used to predict the nuclear matrix element of the neutrinoless $\beta\beta$ ($0\nu\beta\beta$) decay in nucleus $^{76}$Ge, amongst the most promising $\beta\beta$-decay candidates. The nonaxial deformation, i.e., triaxiality, which poses severe challenges in evaluating the nuclear matrix element of $^{76}$Ge, is incorporated within a full model space for the first time. The spectroscopic properties of the $\beta\beta$-decay partners $^{76}$Ge and $^{76}$Se, and the nuclear matrix element governing the two-neutrino $\beta\beta$ ($2\nu\beta\beta$) decay in $^{76}$Ge are well reproduced, providing solid examinations for the validity of theoretical calculations. The inclusion of the triaxial degree of freedom enhances the nuclear matrix element of the $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay significantly by a factor around two. The present results indicate that the goals of next-generation experiments searching for the $0\nu\beta\beta$ decay in $^{76}$Ge can be achieved using only a quarter amount of the experimental materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2304.12009v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.scib.2024.04.071</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Science Bulletin 69, 2017-2020 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Y. K. Wang, P. W. Zhao, J. Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Triple-$\alpha$ reaction rates below $T_9=3$ by a non-adiabatic three-body model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03600</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03600v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The triple-$\alpha$ reaction from the ternary continuum states at off-resonant energies, $\alpha+\alpha+\alpha\rightarrow^{12}$C, remains an open question. This direct process is estimated using a non-adiabatic Faddeev hyperspherical harmonics $R$-matrix expansion method. After reviewing the model, the resultant photo-disintegration of $^{12}$C($2^+_1\rightarrow 0^+$) is shown to be much smaller than the values predicted by the adiabatic models for $0.15 \le E \le 0.35$ MeV. Despite the large difference, the derived reaction rates are illustrated to be concordant with the current evaluated rates for $0.08 \le T_9 \le 3$. The difference below $E=0.20$ MeV can be seen in the rates for $T_9 \le 0.07$. In comparison with the calculations, the rates are found to be reduced by about 10$^{-4}$ at $T_9=0.05$, because of an accurate description for $^8$Be break-up. Uncertainties of the rates are also estimated by examining sensitivity to 3$\alpha$ potentials. With introducing three-body $S$-factors and a resonant term, the present rates are expressed in an analytic form, and they are provided in a tabular form for astrophysical applications. To update the evaluated rates, non-resonant sequential process between $\alpha+^8$Be could be eliminated by hand. The astrophysical impact is not expected to be large, although the rates are reduced around $T_9=0.05$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03600v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Katsuma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The boson number hypothesis and the boson number odd-even effect in $^{196-204}$Hg</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.14881</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.14881v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the SU3-IBM the oblate shape is described by the \textrm{SU(3)} third-order Casimir operator in the large-$N$ limit. However for finite $N$, this interaction can produce a boson number odd-even effect. In this Letter, we find that, the unique odd-even effect really exists in the nuclei $^{196-204}$Hg. This finding implies that realistic low-lying excitations are sensitive to certain boson number $N$. The boson number hypothesis is verified for the first time since the advent of the interacting boson model. This also proves the accuracy and validity of the SU3-IBM directly. The SU(3) symmetry and the higher-order interactions are both indispensable for understanding the nuclear quadrupole deformations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.14881v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tao Wang, Chun-xiao Zhou, Lorenzo Fortunato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electromagnetic form factors of ${}^6$Li, ${}^7$Li, and ${}^7$Be in cluster effective field theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.20202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.20202v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Effective field theory (EFT) provides a powerful model-independent theoretical framework for illuminating complicated interactions across a wide range of physics areas and subfields. In this work, we consider the low-energy deuteron-Helium-4, triton-Helium-4, and helion-Helium-4 systems at low energies in cluster EFT. In particular, we focus on the deuteron + Helium-4 cluster configuration of the Lithium-6 nucleus, the triton + Helium-4 cluster configuration of the Lithium-7 nucleus, and the Helium-3-Helium-4 configuration of the Beryllium-7 nucleus, respectively. We illustrate how to directly extract the asymptotic normalization coefficient and several observables using experimental measurement of the electromagnetic form factors of these nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.20202v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Son T. Nguyen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlation between the curvature and some properties of the neutron star</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2012.13673</link>
      <description>arXiv:2012.13673v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: According to the general theory of relativity, a massive body induces curvature in the surrounding spacetime. In this study, the surface curvature (SC) of neutron stars is computed using various curvature quantities derived from the relativistic mean-field, density-dependent RMF, and Skyrme-Hartree-Fock equations of states. Neutron star properties, including mass, radius, compactness, and central density, are calculated utilizing the Tolman-Oppenheimer-Volkoff equations. The analysis reveals a significant cubic correlation between the SC and compactness for the canonical 1.4 $M_{\odot}$ neutron star, with a correlation coefficient of 0.99, indicating an almost linear relationship. A similarly significant inverse cubic correlation is observed between the SC and the radius of the canonical star. However, these correlations diminish for the maximum mass NS. Furthermore, a universal relation between the SC and the dimensionless tidal deformability ($\Lambda$) for the canonical neutron star is established. Using the tidal deformability constraint of GW170817 ($\Lambda_{1.4} = 190_{-120}^{+390}$), the surface curvature is limited to SC$_{1.4} (10^{14}) = 2.87^{+0.30}_{-0.78}$ at a confidence level 90\%. Furthermore, the tidal deformability constraint of the secondary component in the GW190814 event ($\Lambda_{1.4} = 616_{-158}^{+273}$) offers a more stringent limit, with the result of SC$_{1.4} (10^{14}) = 2.03^{+0.27}_{-0.36}$. These findings indicate that the GW190814 event imposes more rigorous constraints on SC compared to GW170817.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2012.13673v4</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1142/S0218301325500090</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>International Journal of Modern Physics E, 2550009 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S. K. Biswal, H. C. Das, Ankit Kumar, Bharat Kumar, Rashmita Jena, Padmalaya Dash, S. K. Patra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inelastic and elastic parton scatterings in the strongly interacting quark-gluon plasma</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.03105</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.03105v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the role of inelastic processes in the strongly interacting quark-gluon plasma (sQGP) based on the effective dynamical quasi-particle model (DQPM). In the DQPM the non-perturbative properties of the sQGP at finite temperature $T$ and baryon chemical potential $\mu_B$ are described in terms of strongly interacting off-shell partons (quarks and gluons) with dynamically generated spectral functions whose properties are adjusted to reproduce the lQCD EoS for the QGP in thermodynamic equilibrium. For the first time the massive gluon radiation processes from the off-shell quark-quark ($q+q$) and quark-gluon ($q+g$) scatterings are calculated explicitly within leading order Feynman diagrams with effective propagators and vertices from the DQPM without any further approximations. We present the results for the energy and temperature dependencies of the total and differential radiative cross sections and compare them to the corresponding elastic cross sections. We show that our results reproduce the pQCD calculations in the limit of zero masses and widths of quasiparticles. Also we study the $\mu_B$ dependence of the inelastic cross sections. Moreover, we present estimates for the transition rate and relaxation time of radiative versus elastic scatterings in the sQGP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.03105v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.109.024911</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Ilia Grishmanovskii, Olga Soloveva, Taesoo Song, Carsten Greiner, Elena Bratkovskaya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Supernovae to Neutron Stars: A Systematic Approach to Axion Production at Finite Density</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.10945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.10945v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We present a systematic study of QCD axion production in environments with finite baryon density and temperature, implying significant changes to axion phenomenology. Within heavy baryon chiral perturbation theory, we derive the effective Lagrangian describing axion interactions with nucleons and mesons up to next-to-leading-order in the chiral expansion. We focus on corrections to the axion-nucleon couplings from higher orders and finite density. These couplings are modified by up to an order of magnitude near nuclear saturation density, significantly impacting axion production in supernovae and neutron stars. Density-dependent corrections enhance the axion luminosity in supernovae by an order of magnitude, strengthening current best bounds by a factor of three. We stress the importance of including all axion production channels up to a given chiral order for a consistent luminosity calculation and classify the missing contributions up to the third chiral order. The modified axion-nucleon couplings also affect neutron star cooling rates via axion emission. A re-evaluation of existing neutron star cooling bounds, constrained to regions where perturbative control is reliable, weakens these bounds by a factor of four. Lastly, our results have implications for terrestrial axion searches that rely on precise knowledge of axion-nucleon couplings.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.10945v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/JHEP02(2025)138</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Konstantin Springmann, Michael Stadlbauer, Stefan Stelzl, Andreas Weiler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of threshold resummation for large-$x$ PDF in large momentum effective theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12910</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12910v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Parton distribution functions (PDFs) at large $x$ are challenging to extract from experimental data, yet they are essential for understanding hadron structure and searching for new physics beyond the Standard Model. Within the framework of the large momentum $P^z$ expansion of lattice quasi-PDFs, we investigate large $x$ PDFs, where the matching coefficient is factorized into the hard kernel, related to the active quark momentum $x P^z$, and the threshold soft function, associated with the spectator momentum $(1-x) P^z$. The renormalization group equation of the soft function enables the resummation of the threshold double logarithms $\alpha^{k} \ln^{2k}(1-x)$, which is crucial for a reliable and controllable calculation of large $x$ PDFs. Our analysis with pion valence PDFs indicates that perturbative matching breaks down when the spectator momentum $(1-x)P^z$ approaches $\Lambda_{\rm QCD}$, but remains valid when both $x P^z$ and $(1-x)P^z$ are much larger than $\Lambda_{\rm QCD}$. Additionally, we incorporate leading renormalon resummation within the threshold framework, demonstrating good perturbative convergence in the region where both spectator and active quark momenta are perturbative scales.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12910v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiangdong Ji, Yizhuang Liu, Yushan Su, Rui Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fully charmed P-wave tetraquark resonant states in the quark model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.17962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.17962v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We conduct the first comprehensive P-wave four-body dynamical calculations of the fully charmed tetraquark systems within the quark potential model. We apply the Gaussian expansion method to solve the four-body Schr\"odinger equation, incorporating both dimeson and diquark-antidiquark spatial configurations. The matrix elements of P-wave states are calculated analytically using the infinitesimally-shifted Gaussian basis functions. With the complex scaling method, we obtain several fully charmed P-wave resonant states with compact tetraquark configuration in the mass region of $(7.0,7.2)$ GeV, including states with exotic quantum numbers $J^{PC}=0^{--},1^{-+}$. However, we find no resonant states with the mass $M&lt;7$ GeV and width $\Gamma&lt;200$ MeV. Combining the present investigation with our previous results on S-wave fully charmed tetraquark systems, we find no candidates for the experimental states $X(6400)$ and $X(6600)$ in the quark model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.17962v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.034044</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Lin Wu, Shi-Lin Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Block Lanczos for lattice QCD spectroscopy and matrix elements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04444</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04444v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent work introduced a new framework for analyzing correlation functions with improved convergence and signal-to-noise properties, as well as rigorous quantification of excited-state effects, based on the Lanczos algorithm and spurious eigenvalue filtering with the Cullum-Willoughby test. Here, we extend this framework to the analysis of correlation-function matrices built from multiple interpolating operators in lattice quantum chromodynamics (QCD) by constructing an oblique generalization of the block Lanczos algorithm, as well as a new physically motivated reformulation of the Cullum-Willoughby test that generalizes to block Lanczos straightforwardly. The resulting block Lanczos method directly extends generalized eigenvalue problem (GEVP) methods, which can be viewed as applying a single iteration of block Lanczos. Block Lanczos provides qualitative and quantitative advantages over GEVP methods analogous to the benefits of Lanczos over the standard effective mass, including faster convergence to ground- and excited-state energies, explicitly computable two-sided error bounds, straightforward extraction of matrix elements of external currents, and asymptotically constant signal-to-noise. No fits or statistical inference are required. Proof-of-principle calculations are performed for noiseless mock-data examples as well as two-by-two proton correlation-function matrices in lattice QCD.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04444v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel C. Hackett, Michael L. Wagman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Moments from Momentum Derivatives in Lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19862v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that the traditional moments approach in lattice QCD, based on operator product expansion (OPE), can be realized in a way that utilizes derivatives in momentum rather than in distance. This also avoids power divergent mixings, and thus allows to extract moments order by order, to all orders in principle. Moreover, by exploiting the symmetry of lattice matrix elements,we can determine the even and odd moments separately. As a demonstrative example, we determine the first three moments beyond the tensor charge gT of the isovector quark transversity distribution in the nucleon.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19862v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuoyi Pang, Jian-Hui Zhang, Dian-Jun Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Bogomol'nyi-Prasad-Sommerfield bound with a first-order system in the 2D Gross-Pitaevskii equation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.04092</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.04092v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A novel Bogomol'nyi-Prasad-Sommerfield (BPS) bound for the Gross-Pitaevskii equations in two spatial dimensions is presented. The energy can be bound from below in terms of the combination of two boundary terms, one related to the vorticity (but "dressed" by the condensate profile) and the second to the "skewness" of the configurations. The bound is saturated by configurations that satisfy a system of two first-order partial differential equations when such a BPS system is satisfied, the Gross-Pitaevskii equations are also satisfied. The analytic solutions of this BPS system in the present manuscript represent configurations with fractional vorticity living in an annulus. Using these techniques, we present the first analytic examples of this kind. The hydrodynamical interpretation of the BPS system is discussed. The implications of these results are outlined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.04092v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrizio Canfora, Pablo Pais</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Monte Carlo Event Generation for Neutrino-Nucleus Exclusive Cross Sections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14452</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14452v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Modern neutrino-nucleus cross section predictions need to incorporate sophisticated nuclear models to achieve greater predictive precision. However, the computational complexity of these advanced models often limits their practicality for experimental analyses. To address this challenge, we introduce a new Monte Carlo method utilizing Normalizing Flows to generate surrogate cross sections that closely approximate those of the original model while significantly reducing computational overhead. As a case study, we built a Monte Carlo event generator for the neutrino-nucleus cross section model developed by the Ghent group. This model employs a Hartree-Fock procedure to establish a quantum mechanical framework in which both the bound and scattering nucleon states are solutions to the mean-field nuclear potential. The surrogate cross sections generated by our method demonstrate excellent accuracy with a relative effective sample size of more than $98.4 \%$, providing a computationally efficient alternative to traditional Monte Carlo sampling methods for differential cross sections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14452v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mathias El Baz, Federico S\'anchez, Natalie Jachowicz, Kajetan Niewczas, Ashish Kumar Jha, Alexis Nikolakopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
