<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 02:28:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Proton halo structures and 22Al</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07759</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07759v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Inspired by the recent debate as to whether the proton drip-line nucleus 22Al demonstrates a halo structure in its ground state and in order to assess such a possibility, we have analyzed theoretical results obtained within the relativistic density functional theory in 22Al and in a number of neighboring nuclei especially along isotopic, isotonic, and isobaric chains. The theory includes self-consistently the effects of pairing, deformation and the continuum. We employ two different functional parameterizations, PC-F1 and PC-PK1. Although the valence proton of the 22Al nucleus is found very loosely bound, in concordance with experimental data, its spatial distribution is found to hardly penetrate the potential barrier. Its wave function is found to consist predominately of l=2 components, for which halo formation is disfavored. Comparisons with results for isobars reveal a somewhat more extended density distribution than that of the stable or neutron-rich counterparts, but comparisons along isotopic, isotonic, and isobaric chains reveal no discontinuities in size evolution, which, if present, might have signaled exotic structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07759v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Panagiota Papakonstantinou, Myeonghwan Mun, Cong Pan, Kaiyuan Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Halo Structures in p-Shell Hypernuclei with Natural Orbitals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08013v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We extend the concept of natural orbitals as an optimized single-particle basis for ab initio nuclear many-body calculations to hypernuclei and show that their superior properties, in particular accelerated convergence and independence of the underlying harmonic-oscillator frequency, can be directly transferred to the hypernuclear regime as demonstrated in no-core shell model calculations for selected p-shell hypernuclei. Moreover, the radial single-particle wavefunctions associated with the natural-orbital basis yield important structural information with respect to the different particle species allowing us to identify a hyperon halo in {\Lambda}He5. We further explore nucleonic and hyperonic halo structures in A=6 and A=7 singly-strange hypernuclei based on one-body densities and point-particle radii obtained from no-core shell model calculations with realistic interactions from chiral effective field theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08013v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marco Kn\"oll, Robert Roth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure and chemical potentials in the inner crust of a cold neutron star within Hartree-Fock and extended Thomas-Fermi methods</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08075v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Self-consistent mean-field methods with Skyrme-type effective interactions and semiclassical approximations, such as the Thomas-Fermi approach and its extensions are particularly well-suited for describing in a thermodynamically consistent way the various phases of the dense matter present in the interior of neutron stars. These methods have been applied to predict the composition of the different regions, including the inner crust constituted by nuclear clusters coexisting with free neutrons and electrons. Because of the computational cost, the energy is typically calculated for a few selected average baryon number densities, and the results are interpolated to obtain the pressure numerically. However, this may introduce systematic errors in the calculations of the global structure of a neutron star and its dynamical evolution. In this paper, we show how the full equation of state can be consistently calculated within the same framework by deriving exact formulas for the chemical potentials and for the pressure that can be easily implemented in existing computer codes. These formulas are applicable to both catalyzed and accreted crusts. We discuss in each case the suitable conditions to impose to determine the composition. Numerical examples are also presented and discussed. Results from refined calculations of the BSk24 equation of state for the inner crust of nonaccreted neutron stars and the corresponding adiabatic index are provided.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08075v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicolas Chamel, Nikolai N. Shchechilin, Andrey I. Chugunov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy dependence of transverse momentum fluctuations in Au+Au collisions from a multiphase transport model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08209v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Event-by-event mean transverse momentum fluctuations ($\langle p_\mathrm{T}\rangle$) serve as a sensitive probe of initial state overlap geometry and energy density fluctuations in relativistic heavy-ion collisions. We present a systematic investigation of $\langle p_\mathrm{T}\rangle$ fluctuations in \auau collisions at $\mathrm{\sqrt{s_{NN}}} =$3.0-19.6 GeV, examining their centrality and energy dependence with the framework of an improved multiphase transport (AMPT) model. The centrality dependence of the $p_\mathrm{T}$ cumulants up to fourth order deviates significantly from simple powering-law scaling. Scaled cumulants are performed, with variances aligning well with the trends observed in the experimental data. Employing a two-subevent method, short-range correlations are slightly suppressed compared to the standard approach. Furthermore, baryons exhibit more pronounced $\langle p_\mathrm{T}\rangle$ fluctuations than mesons, potentially attributable to the effect of radial flow. These results provide referenced insights into the role of initial state fluctuations across different energies in heavy-ion collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08209v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liuyao Zhang, Jinhui Chen, Chunjian Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two- versus three-body approach to femtoscopic hadron-deuteron correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08283v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The three-body approach to hadron-deuteron correlations is shown to turn into a two-body approach if the three-particle hadron-deuteron wave function factorizes into the deuteron wave-function and the wave function of a hadron motion relative to the deuteron. Then, the hadron-deuteron correlation function is as in the two-body approach only the source radius somewhat changes. For this reason, as we argue, the two-body approach works well for kaon-deuteron correlations but it fails for proton-deuteron ones in case of small sources. Applying the three-body approach generalized to the case where the radius of the hadron source is different from the nucleon source radius, we derive the source radius formula which used in the two-body approach gives the correlation function as in the `factorized' three-body one. The formula is discussed in the context of existing and future experimental data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08283v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stanislaw Mrowczynski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mixing interactions and effects in the NJL-model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07658</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07658v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The flavor-dependent quark-antiquark contact interactions recently derived for flavor U(3) Nambu-Jona-Lasinio model, due to vacuum polarization, are articulated with the resulting mixing effects in view. The formal effects of the explicit mixing interactions, $G_{i\neq j}$, are detailed firstly for the meson mixing problem without the inclusion of 't Hooft interactions induced by instantons. Secondly, it is shown that these mixings, in the scalar channel of quark-antiquark interactions, might give rise to quark mixing in the gap equations. Sixth order quark-antiquark interactions from vacuum polarization, that break $U_A(1)$ symmetry, also contribute.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07658v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F. L. Braghin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generic framework for non-perturbative QCD in light hadrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07776v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper aims to serve as an introductory resource for disseminating the concept to individuals with interests in quantum chromodynamics (QCD) for hadrons. We discuss several topological aspects of the QCD vacuum and briefly review recent progress on this intuitive unifying framework for the lowlying hadron physics rooted in QCD by introducing the vacuum as a liquid of instantons and anti-instantons. We develop systematic density expansion on the dilute vacuum with diagrammatical Feynman rules to calculate the vacuum expectation values and generalize the calculations to hadronic matrix element (charges), and hadronic form factors using the instanton liquid (IL) ensemble. The IL ensemble prediction are well-consistent with those of recent lattice QCD calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07776v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Yang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Self-similar inverse cascade from generalized symmetries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07781</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07781v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate the role of generalized symmetries in driving non-equilibrium and non-linear phenomena, specifically focusing on turbulent systems. While conventional turbulence studies have revealed inverse cascades driven by conserved quantities integrated over the entire space, such as helicity in three spatial dimensions, the influence of higher-form symmetries, whose conserved charges are defined by integration over subspaces, remains largely unexplored. We demonstrate a novel mechanism where higher-form symmetries naturally induce a self-similar inverse cascade. Taking axion electrodynamics with non-linear topological interaction as a paradigmatic example, we show that the conserved charge associated with its 1-form symmetry drives the system toward large-scale coherent structures through a universal scaling behavior characterized by analytically determined scaling exponents. Our findings suggest that higher-form symmetries can provide a fundamental organizing principle for understanding non-equilibrium phenomena and the emergence of coherent structures in turbulent systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07781v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuji Hirono, Kohei Kamada, Naoki Yamamoto, Ryo Yokokura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modified Coherence and the Transverse Extent of Jets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07823</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07823v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a study of the transverse size of parton showers and their diminishing interaction with the medium in the high virtuality stage of jet evolution. We consider the process of a hard quark produced in deep inelastic scattering off a large nucleus. Single gluon radiation from this quark, in the absence of scattering, is re-derived using wave-packets. This allows for a derivation of the quantum uncertainty size of the hard quark, at the point of splitting. This uncertainty size is then incorporated within a Monte-Carlo shower routine yielding transverse shower sizes noticeably larger than the classical antenna size of the shower. No clear relation is found between the full uncertainty size of the shower and the virtuality of the originating parton. The single gluon emission from the hard quark is then re-analysed for the case of single rescattering off the remainder of the nucleus. A relation is derived between the jet transport coefficient $\hat{q}$ and the gluon Transverse Momentum Dependent Parton Distribution Function (gTMDPDF). Solving this relation, for a simple case, clearly demonstrates the weakening of $\hat{q}$ with the virtuality of the hard splitting parton.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07823v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amit Kumar, Abhijit Majumder, Chathuranga Sirimanna, Yasuki Tachibana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Covariant analysis of electromagnetic current on the light cone: exposition with scalar Yukawa theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07826</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07826v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present the first systematic investigation of the Lorentz covariance of the charge form factor for a strongly coupled scalar theory in (3+1)-dimensions. Our results are based on the non-perturbative solution of the scalar Yukawa theory with a Fock sector expansion including up to thee-particles (one mock nucleon plus two mock pions or two mock nucleons plus one mock anti-nucleon). The light-front Hamiltonian is constructed and renormalized using a Fock sector dependent scheme. The derived eigenvalue equation is then solved non-perturbatively to obtain the wave functions, which are then used to compute the current matrix element.
  We perform a covariant analysis of the current matrix element taking into account possible violation of the Poincar\'e symmetry due to the Fock sector truncation. The physical form factor depends on two boost invariants $\zeta, \Delta^2_\perp$, instead of the single Lorentz invariant $Q^2$. Instead of adopting the conventional Drell-Yan frame $\zeta = 0$, we evaluate the form factor in general frames, and use the frame dependence to quantitatively gauge the loss of the Lorentz covariance. Our numerical result shows that as more Fock sectors are included, the frame dependence reduces dramatically. In particular, the anti-nucleon degree of freedom plays an important role in the reduction of the frame dependence, even though it only takes a small portion within the state vector. We also find that there is no zero-mode contribution to the current for the scalar Yukawa theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07826v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenyu Zhang, Yang Li, James P. Vary</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quarkonia and Deconfined Quark-Gluon Matter in Heavy-Ion Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08290</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08290v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this report, we present an experimental overview of quarkonium results obtained in nucleus-nucleus heavy-ion collisions, with a focus on the data collected at the LHC. We discuss the current understanding of charmonium and bottomonium behavior in the deconfined medium produced in such collisions, comparing the various observables now accessible to state-of-the-art theoretical models. We also discuss the open points and how future heavy-ion experiments aim to clarify these aspects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08290v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Andronic, R. Arnaldi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deciphering Hypertriton and Antihypertriton Spins from Their Global Polarizations in Heavy-Ion Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12015</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12015v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding the properties of hypernuclei is crucial for constraining the nature of hyperon-nucleon ($Y\text{-}N$) interactions, which plays a key role in determining the inner structure of compact stars. The lightest hypernuclei and antihypernuclei are the hypertriton ($^3_\Lambda\text{H}$), which consists of a pair of nucleons and a $\Lambda$ hyperon, and its antinucleus (${^3_{\bar{\Lambda}}}\overline{\rm H}$). Significant knowledge has recently been acquired regarding the mass, lifetime, and binding energy of $^3_\Lambda\text{H}$. However, its exact spin, whether $\frac{1}{2}$ or $\frac{3}{2}$, remains undetermined in both experimental and theoretical studies. Here, we present a novel method of using the hypertriton global polarization in heavy-ion collisions to decipher not only its total spin but also its internal spin structure. This method is based on the finding that its three different spin structures exhibit distinct beam energy dependence of its global polarization when it is produced in these collisions from the coalescence of proton, neutron and $\Lambda$. Future observations of the hypertriton and antihypertriton global polarizations thus provide the opportunity to unveil the spin structures of hypertriton and antihypertriton and their production mechanisms in heavy-ion collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12015v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai-Jia Sun, Dai-Neng Liu, Yun-Peng Zheng, Jin-Hui Chen, Che Ming Ko, Yu-Gang Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$ {}^{164} \mathrm{Pb} $: A possible heaviest $ N = Z $ doubly magic nucleus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.12095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.12095v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We confirm by using the Skyrme Hartree-Fock-Bogoliubov calculation that $ {}^{164} \mathrm{Pb} $ is a possible heaviest $ N = Z $ doubly magic nucleus whose lifetime is long enough to be measured on accelerator experiments. We estimate the proton-emission and alpha-decay half-lives of $ {}^{164} \mathrm{Pb} $. The estimated proton-emission half-life ranges from $ 0.1 \, \mathrm{ps} $ to $ 10 \, \mathrm{ns} $, while the alpha decay can be safely neglected.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.12095v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevResearch.7.013050</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Research 7, 013050 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tomoya Naito, Masaaki Kimura, Masaki Sasano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental Method to Constrain Preferential Emission and Spectator Dynamics in Heavy-Ion Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06977</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06977v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a novel experimental method to quantify contribution of preferential emission to the pseudorapidity distribution of produced particles in heavy-ion collisions using correlations between spectator asymmetry and final-state multiplicity. Within a transport model, the magnitude of this correlator increases from mid to forward rapidities, reflecting the impact of preferential emission and capturing fluctuations in sources of particle production. The correlator demonstrates sensitivity to spectator number fluctuations arising from evaporation or fragmentation, providing a handle to constrain such dynamics. This method serves as a powerful tool to probe particle production mechanisms and the space-time evolution of spectator matter in heavy-ion collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06977v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vipul Bairathi, Somadutta Bhatta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>L\'evy walk of pions in heavy-ion collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.10373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.10373v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The process of L\'evy walk, i.e., movement patterns described by heavy-tailed random walks, plays a role in various phenomena, from chemical and microbiological systems through marine predators to climate change. Recent experiments have suggested that this phenomenon also appears in heavy-ion collisions. However, the theoretical interpretation supporting such findings is still debated. In high-energy collisions of heavy nuclei, the strongly interacting Quark Gluon Plasma is created, which, similarly to the early Universe, undergoes a rapid expansion and transition back to hadronic matter. In the subsequent expanding hadron gas, particles interact until kinetic freeze-out, when their momenta stop changing, and they freely transition toward the detectors. Measuring spatial freeze-out distributions is a crucial tool in understanding the dynamics of the created matter and the interactions among its constituents. In this paper, we introduce a three-dimensional analysis of the spatial freeze-out distribution of pions (the most abundant particles in such collisions). Utilising Monte-Carlo simulations of high-energy collisions, we show that the chain of processes ending in a final state pion has a step length distribution leading to L\'evy-stable distributions. Subsequently, we show that simulated pion freeze-out distributions indeed exhibit heavy tails and can be described by a three-dimensional elliptically contoured symmetric L\'evy-stable distribution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.10373v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D\'aniel Kincses, M\'arton Nagy, M\'at\'e Csan\'ad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mirror and triplet energy differences in $sd$-shell nuclei using microscopic interactions with isospin-symmetry breaking effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.00765</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.00765v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we developed and tested two different isospin symmetry-breaking (ISB) versions of the microscopic DJ16A interaction. Starting with the isospin symmetric DJ16A interaction, we introduced two different Coulomb interactions- Coulomb-CD and Coulomb-w/SRC- along with phenomenological charge symmetry breaking (CSB) and charge independence breaking (CIB) effects. Then, we employed these interactions to calculate $b$- and $c$-parameters of the isobaric multiplet mass equation for $|T_z| = 1/2$ and $|T_z| = 1$ nuclei across the $sd$-shell. Our results indicate that the DJ16A$^\dagger$ interaction provides the most accurate $b$-parameter predictions between the two DJ16A-based interactions. Additionally, we explored mirror energy differences (MEDs) in low-energy spectra around $A = 20$ and demonstrated that large MEDs are primarily associated with high occupancies of the $1s_{1/2}$ orbital. Furthermore, $E2$ transition strengths were calculated using both DJ16A-based ISB interactions agreed with the experimental data, with minimal ISB effects observed on these transitions. Overall, the DJ16A$^\dagger$ interaction serves as a complementary set to the newly developed USD-family interactions, USDC, and USDCm and can be further tested for other mirror nuclei across the $sd$-shell to study nuclear structure properties and ISB effects in nuclear $\beta$-decay.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.00765v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chandan Sarma, Praveen C. Srivastava, Toshio Suzuki, Noritaka Shimizu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transverse momentum dependent factorization for SIDIS at next-to-leading power</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2306.09495</link>
      <description>arXiv:2306.09495v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The semi-inclusive deep-inelastic scattering (SIDIS) is the golden process for investigating the nucleon's transverse momentum-dependent (TMD) structure. We present the complete expression for SIDIS structure functions in the TMD factorization formalism at the next-to-leading power. All perturbative elements of the factorization theorem -- coefficient functions and evolution kernels -- are presented at one-loop accuracy. We found several differences with earlier derivations, which are due to accounting for nontrivial kinematics of the quark-gluon interference terms. As a side result, we present the definition and evolution of twist-three TMD fragmentation functions, including the leading-order evolution kernel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2306.09495v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone Rodini, Alexey Vladimirov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing new bosons and nuclear structure with ytterbium isotope shifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07792</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07792v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this Letter, we present mass-ratio measurements on highly charged Yb$^{42+}$ ions with a precision of $4\times 10^{-12}$ and isotope-shift measurements on Yb$^{+}$ on the $^{2}$S$_{1/2}$ $\to$ $^{2}$D$_{5/2}$ and $^{2}$S$_{1/2}$ $\to$ $^{2}$F$_{7/2}$ transitions with a precision of $4\times 10^{-9}$ for the isotopes $^{168,170,172,174,176}$Yb. We present a new method that allows us to extract higher-order changes in the nuclear charge distribution along the Yb isotope chain, benchmarking ab-initio nuclear structure calculations. Additionally, we perform a King plot analysis to set bounds on a fifth force in the keV$/c^2$ to MeV$/c^2$ range coupling to electrons and neutrons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07792v2</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Menno Door, Chih-Han Yeh, Matthias Heinz, Fiona Kirk, Chunhai Lyu, Takayuki Miyagi, Julian C. Berengut, Jacek Biero\'n, Klaus Blaum, Laura S. Dreissen, Sergey Eliseev, Pavel Filianin, Melina Filzinger, Elina Fuchs, Henning A. F\"urst, Gediminas Gaigalas, Zolt\'an Harman, Jost Herkenhoff, Nils Huntemann, Christoph H. Keitel, Kathrin Kromer, Daniel Lange, Alexander Rischka, Christoph Schweiger, Achim Schwenk, Noritaka Shimizu, Tanja E. Mehlst\"aubler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strangeness $+1$ light multiquark baryons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04078v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In view of the renewing experimental interest for searching strangeness $+1$ baryons at J-PARC, we study the existence of light baryon resonances with strangeness +1 generated in the $K$-$(N^*/\Delta^*)$ system, where $N^*$ represents either $N^*(1535)$/$N^*(1650)$/$N^*(1700)$, and $\Delta^*$ corresponds to $\Delta(1620)$. The description of the properties of the aforementioned states requires considering the dynamics involved in the coupled pseudoscalar-baryon and vector-baryon systems with strangeness $S=0$ in the s-wave. For the purpose of our current study, we consider the pseudoscalar-baryon (PB) and vector-baryon channels (VB) to which the mentioned $N^*$ and $\Delta^*$ resonances couple and solve the Faddeev equations for the coupled channel system $K$-$\text{PB}$, $K$-$\text{VB}$, with all interactions being in the s-wave. Despite some strong attraction present in two of the subsystems, we do not find clear evidence supporting the formation of strangeness +1 states, with spin-parity $J^P=1/2^+$, in the energy region $2000-2200$ MeV. However, the case of spin-parity $J^P=3/2^+$ seems more promising, showing the formation of a resonance with a mass around 2167 MeV, with a width of 90-100 MeV. We suggest that a signal of such a state could be found in processes with final states like $KN$, $K^*(892) N$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04078v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brenda B. Malabarba, K. P. Khemchandani, A. Martinez Torres, Seung-il Nam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strange quark matter as dark matter: 40 years later, a reappraisal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12094v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Forty years ago Witten suggested that dark matter could be composed of macroscopic clusters of strange quark matter. This idea was very popular for several years, but it dropped out of fashion once lattice QCD calculations indicated that the confinement/deconfinement transition, at small baryonic chemical potential, is not first order, which seemed to be a crucial requirement in order to produce large clusters of quarks. Here we revisit the conditions under which strangelets can be produced in the Early Universe. We discuss the impact of an instability in the hadronic phase separating a low density, positive-strange-charge phase from a high-density phase with a negative strange charge. This second phase can rapidly stabilize by forming color-superconducting gaps. The strangelets then undergo partial evaporation. In this way, we obtain distributions of their sizes in agreement with the observational constraints and we discuss the many astrophysical and cosmological implications of these objects. Finally, we examine the most promising techniques to detect this type of strangelets. We also show that strangelets can exist with masses $\lesssim10^{17} \mathrm g$, while primordial black holes are ruled out in that mass range, allowing us to distinguish between these two dark matter candidates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12094v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.CO</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Di Clemente, Marco Casolino, Alessandro Drago, Massimiliano Lattanzi, Claudia Ratti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutrino many-body flavor evolution: the full Hamiltonian</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16690</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16690v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study neutrino flavor evolution in the quantum many-body approach using the full neutrino-neutrino Hamiltonian, including the usually neglected terms that mediate non-forward scattering processes. Working in the occupation number representation with plane waves as single-particle states, we explore the time evolution of simple initial states with up to $N=10$ neutrinos. We discuss the time evolution of the Loschmidt echo, one body flavor and kinetic observables, and the one-body entanglement entropy. For the small systems considered, we observe `thermalization' of both flavor and momentum degrees of freedom on comparable time scales, with results converging towards expectation values computed within a microcanonical ensemble. We also observe that the inclusion of non-forward processes generates a faster flavor evolution compared to the one induced by the truncated (forward) Hamiltonian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16690v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 110 (2024) 12, 123028</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Vincenzo Cirigliano, Srimoyee Sen, Yukari Yamauchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipative tidal effects to next-to-leading order and constraints on the dissipative tidal deformability using gravitational wave data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.02584</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.02584v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dissipative tidal interactions can be used to probe the out-of-equilibrium physics of neutron stars using gravitational wave observations. In this paper, we present the first post-Newtonian (PN) corrections to the orbital dynamics of a binary system containing objects whose tidal interactions have a dissipative contribution. We derive the 1PN-accurate equations of motion in the center-of-mass frame and a generalized energy-balance law that is valid for dissipative tidal interactions. We show how mass and energy loss due to the absorption of orbital energy change the orbital dynamics and derive the next-to-leading order correction to the gravitational wave phase of a binary system in a quasi-circular orbit containing initially non-spinning components. We then use this waveform model to constrain, for the first time, the individual dissipative tidal deformabilities of each of the binary components that generated the GW170817 event using real data. We find that the GW170817 data requires $\Xi_{1} \lesssim 1121$ and $\Xi_{2} \lesssim 1692$ at 90\% confidence, where $\Xi_{1,2}$ are the individual tidal deformabilities of the primary and secondary binary components that produced the GW170817 event.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.02584v3</guid>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhishek Hegade K. R., Justin L. Ripley, Nicol\'as Yunes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperons during proto-neutron star deleptonization and the emission of dark flavoured particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01406v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Complementary to high-energy experimental efforts, indirect astrophysical searches of particles beyond the standard model have long been pursued. The present article follows the latter approach and considers, for the first time, the self-consistent treatment of the energy losses from dark flavoured particles produced in the decay of hyperons during a core-collapse supernova (CCSN). To this end, general relativistic supernova simulations in spherical symmetry are performed, featuring six-species Boltzmann neutrino transport, and covering the long-term evolution of the nascent remnant proto-neutron star (PNS) deleptonization for several tens of seconds. A well-calibrated hyperon equation of state (EOS) is therefore implemented into the supernova simulations and tested against the corresponding nucleonic model. It is found that supernova observables, such as the neutrino signal, are robustly insensitive to the appearance of hyperons for the simulation times considered in the present study. The presence of hyperons enables an additional channel for the appearance of dark sector particles, which is considered at the level of the $\Lambda$ hyperon decay. Assuming massless particles that escape the PNS after being produced, these channels expedite the deleptonizing PNS and the cooling behaviour. This, in turn, shortens the neutrino emission timescale. The present study confirms the previously estimated upper limits on the corresponding branching ratios for low and high mass PNS, by effectively reducing the neutrino emission timescale by a factor of two. This is consistent with the classical argument deduced from the neutrino detection associated with SN1987A.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01406v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1475-7516/2025/01/061</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>JCAP01(2025)061</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Tobias Fischer, Jorge Martin Camalich, Hristijan Kochankovski, Laura Tolos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-transition-induced collapse of proto-compact stars and its implication for supernova explosions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.16189</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.16189v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A hadron-quark phase transition (PT) may trigger supernova explosions during stellar core collapse. However, both success and failure have occurred in previous attempts to explode dying stars via this mechanism. We systematically explore the outcomes of the PT-induced collapse of mock proto-compact stars (PCSs) with a constant entropy and lepton fraction, with spherically symmetric general relativistic hydrodynamic simulations and a controlled series of hybrid equations of state. Our results reveal the qualitative dependence of successful and failed explosions on the PT and quark matter characteristics. A small portion ($\sim\!0.04\%\!-\!1\%$) of the released binding energy $\Delta E_B$ transforms into the diagnostic explosion energy $E_{\rm exp,diag}$, which saturates at $\sim\!6\times10^{51}$ erg near the black hole formation. Note that our $E_{\rm exp,diag}$ represents an upper limit of the final explosion energies in realistic supernova simulations. We draw the phase diagrams indicative of the possible fates of supernova explosions driven by hadron-quark PTs, where the control parameters are the onset density, energy gap of the PT, and the quark matter speed of sound. Our findings can guide further self-consistent investigations on PT-driven core-collapse supernovae and help identify hadron-quark PT-induced PCS collapse from future observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.16189v2</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xu-Run Huang, Shuai Zha, Ming-chung Chu, Evan P. O'Connor, Lie-Wen Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous $U(1)_A$ couplings and the Columbia plot</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08185</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08185v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: When the quark masses are lighter than those in QCD, the standard lore is that a chiral transition of first order must emerge for three, light flavors. Recently, however, numerical simulations on the lattice suggest that the chiral transition is of second order in the chiral limit. Using an extended linear sigma model in the mean field approximation, we study the relation between terms which break the anomalous, $U(1)_A$ symmetry and the order of the chiral phase transition, especially how a chiral transition of second order can arise for three, massless flavors. We note that in an (unphysical) region of the "Columbia" phase diagram, when the strange quark mass is light and negative, corresponding to topological angle $\theta=\pi$, the $CP$ symmetry is spontaneously broken.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08185v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.016014</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys.Rev.D 111 (2025) 1, 016014</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Francesco Giacosa, Gy\H{o}z\H{o} Kov\'acs, P\'eter Kov\'acs, Robert D. Pisarski, Fabian Rennecke</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical constraints on pseudo-gauge transformations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.06249</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.06249v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Classical pseudo-gauge transformations are discussed in the context of hydrodynamic models of heavy-ion collisions. A decomposition of the pseudo-gauge transformation into Lorentz-invariant tensors is made, which allows for better interpretation of its physical consequences. For pseudo-gauge transformations connecting two symmetric energy-momentum tensors, we find that the super-potential $\Phi^{\lambda \mu \nu}$ must obey a conservation law of the form $\partial_\lambda \Phi^{\lambda \mu \nu} = 0$. This equation, referred to below as the STS condition, represents a constraint that is hardly possible to be satisfied for tensors constructed out of the basic hydrodynamic variables such as temperature, baryon chemical potential, and the hydrodynamic flow. However, in a special case of the boost-invariant flow, the STS condition is automatically fulfilled and a non-trivial residual pseudo-gauge transformation defined by a single scalar field is allowed. In this case the bulk and shear viscosity coefficients become pseudo-gauge dependent; however, their specific linear combination appearing in the equations of motion remains pseudo-gauge invariant. This finding provides new insights into the role of pseudo-gauge transformations and pseudo-gauge invariance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.06249v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2025.139244</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett. B 861 (2025) 139244</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zbigniew Drogosz, Wojciech Florkowski, Mykhailo Hontarenko, Radoslaw Ryblewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
