<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Feb 2025 02:49:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of a repulsive three-body interaction on the $DD^{(*)}K$ molecule</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00438</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00438v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The hadronic molecular picture of the observed exotic states has inspired numerous investigations into few-body systems. Recently, the lattice effective field theory studied the effect of a three-body interaction on the binding energy of the $DD^{*}K$ system, revealing an intriguing phenomenon in the binding energy. This work uses the Gaussian expansion method to explore the underlying physics. Our results show that as the repulsive three-body interaction strengthens, the spatial size of the $DD^{(*)}K$ bound state gradually increases. Further enhancement of the three-body interaction causes the $DD^{(*)}K$ three-body bound state to break into a $D^{(*)}K$ two-body bound state, accompanied by a distant $D$ meson. The identical nature of the two $D$ mesons leads to the fact that the $DDK$ system consistently resembles an isosceles triangle-shaped spatial configuration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00438v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ya-Wen Pan, Jun-Xu Lu, Emiko Hiyama, Li-Sheng Geng, Atsushi Hosaka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time Evolution of Prompt Gamma-Ray Emission in $^{252}$Cf(sf) and $^{233,235}$U($n$,f) Reactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00599</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00599v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the time evolution of prompt fission $\gamma$ emission due to the presence of ns to ms isomers in the fragments produced in the neutron-induced fission of $^{233,235}$U and in the spontaneous fission of $^{252}$Cf. Calculations performed with the CGMF fission event generator are compared with recent experimental data on $^{252}$Cf(sf) and $^{235}$U($n$,f) obtained with the DANCE+NEUANCE setup at the Los Alamos Neutron Science Center. Of particular interest are the average $\gamma$-ray energy spectrum as a function of time since scission, $\phi(\epsilon_\gamma,t)$, the increase of the average $\gamma$-ray multiplicity over time, $N_\gamma(t)$, and its evolution in time as a function of the fission fragment mass, $N_\gamma(A,t)$. The time evolution of isomeric ratios in post-neutron emission fission fragments can be defined and used to test and reveal some deficiencies in our knowledge of the low-lying levels of neutron-rich nuclei produced in fission reactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00599v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Patrick Talou, Amy E. Lovell, Ionel Stetcu, Gencho Rusev, Toshihiko Kawano, Marian Jandel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The nucleon structure from an AdS/QCD model in the Veneziano limit</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00771v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We employ the VQCD model, a holographic approach that dynamically simulates essential QCD characteristics, including linear mass spectra, confinement, asymptotic freedom, and magnetic charge screening, while incorporating quark flavor effects. Using this model, we first calculate the proton mass spectrum and the wave function, incorporating anomalous dimensions to refine our results. Next, we compute the proton structure functions across a range of Bjorken $x$ values using consistent parameters. Furthermore, we derive the proton electromagnetic form factor by solving the electromagnetic field's motion equation, accounting for background effects, and demonstrate qualitative consistency with results from free electromagnetic fields coupled to fermions. Finally, we calculate the gravitational form factors by introducing an effective graviton mass $m$ arising from chiral symmetry breaking and the proton energy-momentum tensor. Our calculations yield results that are in excellent agreement with experimental data and lattice QCD computations, validating the VQCD model as a robust tool for studying proton properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00771v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiali Deng (CCNU), Defu Hou (CCNU)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kaon Modification in Pion Medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00819</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00819v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kaon properties in pion medium are studied. The dense pion medium is produced in high-energy heavy-ion collisions. The consideration is based on the chiral nucleon-kaon-pion Lagrangian. It is found that the pion medium does not produce a substantive contribution but enhances the effect of the baryon matter. Numerical estimate shows that this enhancement factor induced by the pion medium does not exceed 11\% at the freeze-out stage of heavy-ion collisions, i.e. it is small. However, the impact of this enhancement can be higher in actual nuclear collisions because the effect of the in-medium (anti)kaon modification is accumulated during the (anti)kaon evolution before the freeze-out when the pion density is higher.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00819v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu. B. Ivanov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neutron-transfer induced breakup of the Borromean nucleus $^9$Be</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01165v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We address the problem of evaluating neutron-transfer induced breakup cross sections caused by the Borromean nucleus $^{9}$Be, using the reaction $^{197}$Au($^{9}$Be,$^{8}$Be)$^{198}$Au as a test case. This reaction was recently measured over a wide range of incident energies around the Coulomb barrier. To deal with the high density of $^{198}$Au states that can be potentially populated in this reaction, we employ the Ichimura, Austern, Vicent model, in which the spectrum of physical states for this system is replaced by the solutions of a complex n+$^{197}$Au potential, accounting effectively for the fragmentation of single-particle states into physical states. Furthermore, to account for the unbound nature of the emitted $^{8}$Be system, we employ a three-body model of $^{9}$Be. The calculated stripping cross sections are found to be in good agreement with existing data over a wide range of incident energies. The importance of taking into account the energy spread of the single-particle strength of the outgoing $^{8}$Be and the target-like residual nucleus is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01165v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2024.138766</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Lett B 855 (2024) 138766</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G. Villanueva, A. M. Moro, J. Casal, Jin Lei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Demystifying the fusion mechanism in heavy-ion collisions: A six-dimensional Langevin dissipative dynamics approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01292v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an in-depth investigation of heavy-ion fusion dynamics using a six-dimensional Langevin framework that enables unrestricted motion of the asymmetry parameter. The stochastic formalism naturally incorporates friction effects and energy fluctuations, providing a detailed understanding of the fusion process. The dynamics transition into the overdamped regime, facilitating rapid neck stabilization while effectively capturing the interplay between shape and rotational degrees of freedom. This approach achieves excellent agreement with experimental spin distributions and fusion cross-sections, establishing a robust foundation for forthcoming studies on the synthesis of superheavy elements and the exploration of the enigmatic fusion hindrance mechanism.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01292v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2025.139302</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Yannen Jaganathen, Micha{\l} Kowal, Krzysztof Pomorski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>$NJ/\psi$ and $N\eta_c$ interactions from lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00054</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00054v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The interaction between nucleon and charmonia ($J/\psi$ and $\eta_c$) is expected to deepen our understanding of various aspects in nonperturbative QCD ranging from the origin of nucleon mass to $J/\psi$ mass modification in nuclear medium and properties of hidden-charm pentaquark states. Here, we present the low-energy $NJ/\psi$ and $N\eta_c$ interactions based on ($2+1$) flavor lattice QCD simulations with nearly physical pion mass $m_\pi=146$ MeV. The interactions, extracted from the spacetime correlations of the nucleon and charmonium system by using the HAL QCD method, are found to be attractive in all distances and manifest a characteristic long-range tail consistent with the two-pion exchange interaction. The resulting scattering lengths are around $0.3$ fm, $0.4$ fm and $0.2$ fm for $NJ/\psi$ with spin $3/2$, with spin $1/2$, and $N\eta_c$, respectively. Our results are orders of magnitude larger than those from the photoproduction experiments assuming the vector meson dominance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00054v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yan Lyu, Takumi Doi, Tetsuo Hatsuda, Takuya Sugiura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transverse force distributions in the proton from lattice QCD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00325v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Single-spin asymmetries observed in polarised deep-inelastic scattering are important probes of hadron structure. The Sivers asymmetry provides information about the transverse momentum of the struck quark and can be related to final-state interactions. Understanding these asymmetries at the quark level has been the subject of much interest in QCD phenomenology. In this contribution, we present a lattice QCD calculation of the transverse spatial distribution of a colour-Lorentz force acting on the struck quark in a proton. Our lattice calculations employ $N_f = 2 + 1$ flavours of dynamical fermions at the SU(3) symmetric point across three lattice spacings. We determine a central, spin-independent confining force, as well as spin-dependent force distributions with local forces larger than the QCD string tension. These distributions offer a new, complimentary picture that underlies the Sivers asymmetry in transversely polarised deep-inelastic scattering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00325v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. U. Can, J. A. Crawford, R. Horsley, P. E. L. Rakow, G. Schierholz, H. St\"uben, R. D. Young, J. M. Zanotti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fractional vorticity, Bogomol'nyi-Prasad-Sommerfield systems and complex structures for the (generalized) spinor Gross-Pitaevskii equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00578</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00578v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The (generalized) Gross-Pitaevskii equation (GPE) for a complex scalar field in two spatial dimensions is analyzed. It is shown that there is an infinite family of self-interaction potentials which admit Bogomol'nyi-Prasad-Sommerfield (BPS) bounds together with the corresponding first-order BPS systems. For each member of this family, the solutions of the first-order BPS systems are automatically solutions of the corresponding second-order generalized GPE. The simplest topologically non-trivial solutions of these first-order BPS systems describe configurations with quantized fractional vorticity. The corresponding fraction is related to the degree of non-linearity. The case in which the self-interaction potential is of order six (namely $|\Psi|^{6}$, which is a relevant theory both in relativistic quantum field theories in $(2+1)$ dimensions in connection with the quantum Hall effect as well as in the theory of the supersolids) is analyzed in detail. Such formalism can also be extended to the case of quantum mixtures with multi-component GPEs. The relationship between these techniques and supersymmetry will be discussed. In particular, despite several standard features, we will show that there are multi-component GPEs that are not supersymmetric (at least, not in the standard sense) and possess a BPS system of the above type.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00578v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabrizio Canfora, Pablo Pais</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double-beta decay of $^{150}$Nd to excited levels of $^{150}$Sm</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.00748</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.00748v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The $2\nu2\beta$ decay of $^{150}$Nd to the first excited 740.5 keV $0^{+}_{1}$ level of $^{150}$Sm was measured over 5.845 yr with the help of a four-crystal low-background HPGe $\gamma$ spectrometry system in the underground low-background laboratory STELLA of LNGS-INFN. A 2.381 kg highly purified Nd-containing sample was employed as the decay source. The expected de-excitation gamma-quanta of the $0^{+}_{1}$ level with energies 334.0 keV and 406.5 keV were observed both in one-dimensional spectrum and in coincidence data resulting in the half-life $T_{1/2}=[0.83^{+0.18}_{-0.13}\mathrm{(stat)}^{+0.16}_{-0.19}\mathrm{(syst)}]\times 10^{20}$ yr. Interpreting an excess of the 334.0-keV peak area as an indication of the $2\beta$ decay of $^{150}$Nd to the 334.0 keV $2^+_1$ excited level of $^{150}$Sm with a half-life of $T_{1/2}=[1.5^{+2.3}_{-0.6}\mathrm{(stat)}\pm 0.4\mathrm{(syst)}]\times10^{20}$ yr, the $2\nu2\beta$ half-life of $^{150}$Nd for the transition to the 0$^{+}_{1}$ level is $T_{1/2}=[1.03^{+0.35}_{-0.22}\mathrm{(stat)}^{+0.16}_{-0.19}\mathrm{(syst)}]\times 10^{20}$ yr, in agreement with the previous experiments. Both half-life values reasonably agree with the theoretical calculations in the framework of proton-neutron QRPA with isospin restoration combined with like nucleon QRPA for description of excited states in the final nuclei. For $2\nu2\beta$ and $0\nu2\beta$ transitions of $^{150}$Nd and $^{148}$Nd to several excited levels of $^{150}$Sm and $^{148}$Sm, limits were set at level of $T_{1/2}&gt;10^{20}-10^{21}$ yr.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.00748v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. S. Barabash, P. Belli, R. Bernabei, R. S. Boiko, F. Cappella, V. Caracciolo, R. Cerulli, F. A. Danevich, D. L. Fang, F. Ferella, A. Incicchitti, V. V. Kobychev, S. I. Konovalov, M. Laubenstein, A. Leoncini, V. Merlo, S. Nisi, O. Nitescu, D. V. Poda, O. G. Polischuk, I. B. -K. Shcherbakov, F. Simkovic, A. Timonina, V. S. Tinkova, V. I. Tretyak, V. I. Umatov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Out-of-equilibrium Chiral Magnetic Effect via Kubo formulas</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01155</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01155v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this proceedings article, we present the first steps towards the determination of the out-of-equilibrium conductivity of the Chiral Magnetic Effect (CME) in the presence of strong interactions. Using linear response theory, we obtain an analytical expression for the spectral function associated with this effect at one-loop in perturbation theory. In addition, we provide a first estimate of the CME conductivity by calculating the associated Euclidean correlator using quenched Wilson fermions and dynamical staggered fermions in physical Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD) simulations. In particular, we focus on the midpoint of the correlator, which can be used as a proxy of the full conductivity. We present results in a wide range of temperatures, showing how this observable is suppressed at low temperatures, while at high temperatures it approaches the perturbation theory prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01155v1</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. B. Brandt, G. Endr\H{o}di, E. Garnacho-Velasco, G. Mark\'o, A. D. M. Valois</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Renormalization-group approach to the Kohn-Luttinger superconductivity: Amplification of the pairing gap from $\ell^4$ to $\ell$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01169</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01169v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We revisit the renormalization group (RG) analysis of the Kohn-Luttinger (KL) mechanism for superconductivity. The KL mechanism leads to superconductivity in a system with a repulsive bare interaction. The key ingredient is the screening effect that renders the induced interaction attractive in channels with nonzero angular momentum $\ell \neq 0$, thereby triggering the Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer (BCS) instability. According to the original argument, the resulting gap is exponentially small, with its exponent scaling as $-\ell^4$. However, the KL mechanism was originally formulated within perturbation theory, where the series is known to converge poorly in certain cases -- most notably, for the p-wave paring gap induced by a repulsive s-wave contact interaction. This poor convergence may be attributed to a divergent integrand in a specific class of diagrams containing both the BCS logarithm and the Kohn anomaly, suggesting that one must resum the Kohn anomaly contributions separately from the BCS logarithm. In this work, we incorporate the Kohn anomaly contribution into the beta function of the RG equation governing the BCS instability near the Fermi surface. Our solution shows that the KL gap exponent is then proportional to $-\ell$, indicating a significant enhancement of the KL mechanism beyond the previously known result. To illustrate this, we study the spin-triplet p-wave pairing gap arising from a repulsive s-wave contact interaction and compare our RG-based results with those obtained from the Bethe-Salpeter equation in perturbation theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01169v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuki Fujimoto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraining the Chiral Magnetic Effect in the heavy-ion collisions using AVFD model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01195</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01195v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Anomalous Viscous Fluid Dynamics (AVFD) framework is utilized to generate $^{197}_{79}Au+^{197}_{79}Au$, $^{96}_{44}Ru+^{96}_{44}Ru$, and $^{96}_{40}Zr+^{96}_{40}Zr$ collision events at $\sqrt{s_{\mathrm{NN}}}$ = 200 GeV, aiming to investigate the Chiral Magnetic Effect (CME). The CME signal is modulated through the axial charge per entropy density ($n_5/s$), varied as 0.0, 0.1, and 0.2 to produce distinct data sets with varying CME signal strengths. Additionally, a 33$\%$ local charge conservation (LCC) is implemented in each event. These data sets are analyzed using CME-sensitive two- and three-particle correlators. Furthermore, the Sliding Dumbbell Method (SDM) is employed to identify potential CME-like events within each data set. The identified events exhibit characteristics consistent with CME. The CME fraction in these events is quantified while accounting for backgrounds derived from charge shuffle events and correlated background contributions. No enhancement in the CME signal is observed in $Ru+Ru$ collisions compared to $Zr+Zr$ collisions, despite the presence of four additional protons in $^{96}_{44}Ru$ nuclei compared to $^{96}_{40}Zr$ nuclei.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01195v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jagbir Singh, Anjali Sharma, Ankita Nain, Madan M. Aggarwal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasinormal modes of nonthermal fixed points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.01622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.01622v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quasinormal modes play a prominent role in relaxation of diverse physical systems to equilibria, ranging from astrophysical black holes to tiny droplets of quark-gluon plasma at RHIC and LHC accelerators. We propose that a novel kind of quasinormal modes govern the direct approach to self-similar time evolution of nonthermal fixed points, whose relevance ranges from high energy physics to cold atom gases. We utilize black hole perturbation theory techniques to compute the spectrum of these far from equilibrium quasinormal modes for a kinetic theory with a Focker-Planck collision kernel in isotropic and homogeneous states. Our conclusion is that quasinormal modes of nonthermal fixed points give rise to a tower of progressively more decaying power-law contributions. A byproduct of our analysis is a precise determination and improved understanding of the distribution function characterizing nonthermal fixed points.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.01622v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matisse De Lescluze, Michal P. Heller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tensor polarization and the dissipative damping of vector meson in QCD Medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.11890</link>
      <description>arXiv:2206.11890v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Unexpectedly large and puzzling spin alignment, and thus tensor polarization, of vector mesons has been observed in heavy-ion collisions. Given that tensor polarization represents a fluctuation of spin, we derive, for the first time, a fluctuation-dissipation relation for tensor polarization, where the polarization is proportional to first-order hydrodynamic gradients (e.g., the shear-stress tensor), with dissipative coefficients depending on the particle's damping properties, as characterized by its spectral function. Phenomenologically, we find that the dissipative contributions have the potential to generate substantial spin alignment and give rise to complex behaviors, providing insights that may help explain the puzzling phenomena observed in experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2206.11890v4</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Feng Li, Shuai Y. F. Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics of the conserved net-baryon density near QCD critical point within inhomogeneous quark-gluon plasma profile</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.12325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.12325v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper investigates the dynamics of the net-baryon multiplicity fluctuations near the QCD critical point, within the inhomogeneous temperature and baryon chemical potential profile of quark-gluon plasma from the hydrodynamics. The Langevin dynamics of conserved net-baryon density are solved numerically within the temperature and chemical potential profile borrowing from hydrodynamic simulation. It is found that the local systems at different rapidities reach the critical point at different proper times, owing to the inhomogeneous temperature and chemical potential. As a result, it is observed the pronounced enhancement of the magnitude for the net-baryon multiplicity fluctuations with large rapidity acceptance at the freeze-out surface, which is the consequence of the combined effect of critical slowing down and inhomogeneous profile.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.12325v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.111.014915</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. C 111, 014915 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shanjin Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward QCD on Quantum Computer: Orbifold Lattice Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12045</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12045v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We propose an orbifold lattice formulation of QCD suitable for quantum simulations. We show explicitly how to encode gauge degrees of freedom into qubits using noncompact variables, and how to write down a simple truncated Hamiltonian in the coordinate basis. We show that SU(3) gauge group variables and quarks in the fundamental representation can be implemented straightforwardly on qubits, for arbitrary truncation of the gauge manifold.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12045v4</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Georg Bergner, Masanori Hanada, Enrico Rinaldi, Andreas Schafer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding Gravitational Form Factors with the Weizs\"acker-Williams Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.12840</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.12840v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding the internal structure of nucleons and nuclei has been a topic of enduring interest in high-energy physics. Gravitational form factors (GFFs) provide an important portal for us to probe the energy-momentum/mass distribution of nucleons and nuclei. This letter presents the study of the photon and gluon momentum GFFs, also known as the A-GFFs, of relativistic hadrons using the Weizs\"acker-Williams method. To begin, we express the photon A-GFFs in terms of charge form factors and discuss the corresponding photon radius. Furthermore, an integral relation between the gluon A-GFF and the Laplacian of dipole scattering amplitude is derived in the small-$x$ framework, and it allows us to unravel the gluon energy momentum distribution inside hadrons through measurements at the upcoming Electron-Ion Collider. In addition, we generalize the analysis to study the A-GFF of nuclei and propose employing the nuclear gluon mean square radius, together with the charge distribution, to constrain the neutron distribution for large nuclei. This work provides an interesting perspective into the fundamental structure of high-energy hadrons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.12840v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoshikazu Hagiwara, Xuan-Bo Tong, Bo-Wen Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Can charm fluctuation be a better probe to study QCD critical point?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13255</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13255v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the diffusion properties of an interacting hadron gas and evaluate the diffusion coefficient matrix for the baryon, strange, electric, and charm quantum numbers. For the first time, this study sheds light on the charm current and estimates the diffusion matrix coefficient for the charmed states by treating them as a part of the quasi-thermalized medium. We explore the diffusion matrix coefficient as a function of temperature and center-of-mass energy. A van der Waals-like interaction is assumed between the hadrons, including attractive and repulsive interactions. The calculation of diffusion coefficients is based on relaxation time approximation to the Boltzmann transport equation. A good agreement with available model calculations is observed in the hadronic limit. To conclude the study, we discuss, with a detailed explanation, that charm fluctuation is expected to be a better tool for probing the QCD critical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13255v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevD.111.014029</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 111, 014029 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kangkan Goswami, Kshitish Kumar Pradhan, Dushmanta Sahu, Jayanta Dey, Raghunath Sahoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gravitational form factors of glueballs in Yang-Mills theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02706v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work presents preliminary results of the first determination of the energy-momentum tensor form factors of the scalar glueball, referred to as gravitational form factors (GFFs). The calculation has been carried out in lattice Yang-Mills theory at a single lattice spacing. Using variationally optimized operators, the matrix elements are extracted from ratios of three-point functions to two-point functions. The glueball GFFs and their kinematic dependence are compared to those of other hadrons from previous calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02706v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan Abbott, Daniel C. Hackett, Dimitra A. Pefkou, Fernando Romero-L\'opez, Phiala Shanahan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lattice QCD calculation of the subtraction function in forward Compton amplitude</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03141v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The subtraction function plays a pivotal role in calculations involving the forward Compton amplitude, which is crucial for predicting the Lamb shift in muonic atom, as well as the proton-neutron mass difference. In this work, we present a lattice QCD calculation of the subtraction function using two domain wall fermion gauge ensembles at the physical pion mass. We utilize a recently proposed subtraction point, demonstrating its advantage in mitigating statistical and systematic uncertainties by eliminating the need for ground-state subtraction. Our results reveal significant contributions from $N\pi$ intermediate states to the subtraction function. Incorporating these contributions, we compute the proton, neutron and nucleon isovector subtraction functions at photon momentum transfer $Q^2\in[0,2]$ GeV$^2$. For the proton subtraction function, we compare our lattice results with chiral perturbation theory prediction at low $Q^2$ and with the results from the perturbative operator-product expansion at high $Q^2$. Finally, using these subtraction functions as input, we determine their contribution to two-photon exchange effects in the Lamb shift and isovector nucleon electromagnetic self-energy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03141v2</guid>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yang Fu, Xu Feng, Lu-Chang Jin, Chuan Liu, Shi-Da Wen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generic framework for non-perturbative QCD in light hadrons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.07776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.07776v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper aims to serve as an introductory resource for disseminating the concept of instanton liquid model to individuals with interests in quantum chromodynamics (QCD) for hadrons. We discuss several topological aspects of the QCD vacuum and briefly review recent progress on this intuitive unifying framework for the lowlying hadron physics rooted in QCD by introducing the vacuum as a liquid of pseudoparticles. We develop systematic density expansion on the dilute vacuum with diagrammatical Feynman rules to calculate the vacuum expectation values (VEVs) and generalize the calculations to hadronic matrix element (charges), and hadronic form factors using the instanton liquid model (ILM). The ILM prediction are well-consistent with those of recent lattice QCD calculations. Thereby, the nonperturbative physics can be well-controlled by only a few parameters: instanton size $\rho$ and instanton density $n_{I+A}$, and current quark mass $m$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.07776v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei-Yang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study on axial fields in the dynamically assisted Schwinger effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.14283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.14283v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Dynamically assisted Schwinger effect, the generation of fermion-antifermion pairs in vacuum under a strong, slow-varying field and a weak, high-frequency field, has become a promising avenue to probe the vacuum structure and the nonlinear dynamics of QED. However, the role of axial fields in this phenomenon has remained underexplored. This study aims at analyzing how spatial axial fields influence particle production in the dynamically assisted Schwinger effect. Employing the high-frequency effective theory based on the Floquet-Magnus expansion, we demonstrate that a spatial axial field can occur as the effective field of a circular polarized high-frequency plane wave and significantly increase the number of fermions produced across different timescales. This enhancement offers both theoretical insights and useful tools for the experimental implementation of the Schwinger effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.14283v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Feb 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengpeng Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
