<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 04:00:14 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>An improved formula for Wigner function and spin polarization in a decoupling relativistic fluid at local thermodynamic equilibrium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14301v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an upgraded formula for Wigner function and spin polarization of fermions emitted by a relativistic fluid at local thermodynamic equilibrium at the decoupling which improves the one obtained in refs. [1, 2] and used in numerical simulations of relativistic nuclear collisions. By using a new expansion method, applicable to decoupling hypersurfaces with arbitrary geometry, we reproduce the known term proportional to thermal vorticity and obtain an upgraded form of the spin-shear term which captures the dependence on the geometry. The new method also includes additional contributions whose physical nature is to be assessed. The new expression also naturally excludes contributions from space-time gradients in the normal direction of the hypersurface, providing a theoretical justification for the isothermal condition previously imposed a priori. This framework can be extended to particles with arbitrary spin.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14301v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin-Li Sheng, Francesco Becattini, Daniele Roselli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Secondary bow with ripples in $^{12}$C+$^{12}$C rainbow scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14535v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report, {for the first time, the emergence of} a secondary bow with ripples in $^{12}$C+$^{12}$C nuclear rainbow scattering. This finding was achieved by studying the experimental angular distributions in $^{12}$C+$^{12}$C scattering at incident energies $E_L$= 240 and 300 MeV, utilizing an extended double-folding model. This model accurately describes all diagonal and off-diagonal coupling potentials derived from the microscopic wave functions for $^{12}$C. Although the observed angular distributions of rainbow scattering at large angles (approaching $90^\circ$) are complicated by the symmetrization of two identical bosonic nuclei, the Airy minimum, associated with a dynamically generated secondary bow with ripples, is clearly identified at approximately 77$^\circ$ for 240 MeV in the fall-off region of the primary nuclear rainbow. This {finding}, along with previous findings in the $^{16}$O+$^{12}$C and $^{13}$C+$^{12}$C systems, {reinforces} the concept of a secondary bow in nuclear rainbow scattering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14535v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epja/s10050-025-01685-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>European Physical Journal A (2025) 61:209 (September issue)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>S. Ohkubo, Y. Hirabayashi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematic Bayesian Evaluation of Resonance Parameters in 19Ne for the 15O(alpha,gamma)19Ne and 18F(p,alpha)15O Reactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14570v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive evaluation of the nuclear structure properties of 19Ne using a novel and rigorous Bayesian statistical framework. Precise characterization of 19Ne resonance parameters is critical for accurately determining reaction rates of the astrophysically significant 15O(alpha, gamma)19Ne and 18F(p, alpha)15O reactions, which govern breakout from the hot CNO cycle in X-ray bursts and influence gamma-ray emission in novae, respectively. By reconstructing likelihood functions from published experimental data, including asymmetric uncertainties and upper or lower limits, we derive posterior distributions for resonance energies, decay widths, and branching ratios. Our Bayesian approach systematically incorporates previously reported discrepancies among measurements, providing a statistically robust and consistent treatment of these uncertainties. The evaluated resonance parameters and associated uncertainties provide crucial input for stellar nucleosynthesis modeling, contributing to a refined understanding of explosive astrophysical phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14570v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. H. Kim, K. Y. Chae, C. H. Kim, C. D. Nesaraja, M. S. Smith</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Informed Prior Distributions with Normalizing Flows for Bayesian Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the use of normalizing flow (NF) models as flexible priors in Bayesian inference with Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) sampling. Trained on posteriors from previous analyses, these models can be used as informative priors, capturing non-trivial distributions and correlations, in subsequent inference tasks. We compare different training strategies and loss functions, finding that training based on Kullback-Leibler (KL) divergence and unsupervised learning consistently yield the most accurate reproductions of reference distributions. Applied in sequential Bayesian workflows, MCMC with the NF-based priors reproduces the results of one-shot joint inferences well, provided the target distributions are unimodal. In cases with pronounced multi-modality or dataset tension, distortions may arise, underscoring the need for caution in multi-stage Bayesian inference. A comparison between the pocoMC MCMC sampler and the standard emcee sampler further demonstrates the importance of advanced and robust algorithms for exploring the posterior space. Overall, our results establish NF-based priors as a practical and efficient tool for sequential Bayesian inference in high-dimensional parameter spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14911v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hendrik Roch, Chun Shen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refining the deep sub-barrier 12C+12C excitation function with STELLA</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14717</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14717v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Purpose: We have investigated the cross section around the lowest direct coincident gamma-particle measurements, where previously only limits could be established with the aim of obtaining a detailed description of the excitation function. We have furthermore analysed the ratio of extreme decay branching into the first excited state of daughter nuclei with alpha or proton emission at relative kinetic energies where previous measurements are in disagreement with each other. Conclusions: Our findings in the astrophysics RoI support reaction-rate models with a lower average S-factor trend, that deviates significantly from standard extrapolations between 2.2 MeV and 2.6 MeV, for stellar carbon burning simulations of up to 25 Msol stars. Based on our data, an overall increase of the S-factor at deep subbarrier energy cannot be confirmed. The extremely low ratio of the branching into the first excited state with proton over alpha emission of ~ 2% at 3.23 MeV might indicate the presence of alpha cluster compound states in 24Mg. This highly favours {\alpha} emission with fundamental consequences in possible stellar carbon burning sites.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14717v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>astro-ph.SR</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevC.111.065804</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>J. Nippert, S. Courtin, M. Heine, D. G. Jenkins, P. Adsley, A. Bonhomme, R. Canavan, D. Curien, T. Dumont, E. Gregor, G. Harmant, E. Monpribat, L. Morrison, M. Moukaddam, M. Richer, M. Rudigier, J. G. Vega Romero, W. N. Catford, P. Cotte, S. Della Negra, G. Haefner, F. Hammache, J. Lesrel, S. Pascu, Zs. Podoly\'ak, P. H. Regan, I. Ribaud, N. de S\'er\'eville, C. Stodel, J. Vesi\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Study of Heavy Quarkonia Melting in QGP Using Deep Neural Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14970v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Machine learning techniques have emerged as powerful tools for tackling non-perturbative challenges in quantum chromodynamics. In this study, we introduce a data-driven framework employing deep neural networks to systematically predict the temperature-dependent behavior of the screening mass $m_D(T)$ and the strong coupling constant $\alpha_s(T)$ within a quark-gluon plasma medium. These medium-sensitive quantities are subsequently employed to compute the thermal widths $\Gamma_{\text{n}}(T)$ and binding energies $E_B(T)$ of heavy quarkonia states, specifically charmonia and bottomonia, by numerically solving the Schr\"odinger equation with medium-modified heavy quark potentials. To estimate the dissociation temperatures $T_d$ of various quarkonia states, we employ two complementary dissociation criteria: the conventional one, where $2E_B(T_d) = \Gamma_{\text{n}}(T_d)$, and an additional lower bound criterion defined by $E_B(T) = 3T$. This dual-criterion approach provides a more constrained and physically motivated estimate of the temperature range over which quarkonia states dissolve in the QGP environment. Our machine learning-enhanced predictions show excellent agreement with available lattice QCD results, especially for the ground states $\Upsilon(1S)$ and $J/\psi$, and offer new perspectives on the sequential suppression pattern detected in relativistic heavy-ion collision experiments. Overall, this work advances the quantitative description of quarkonium suppression and demonstrates the prospect of modern machine learning methods to bridge theoretical predictions and experimental observations, thereby contributing significantly to QGP tomography.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14970v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Yousuf Jamal, Fu-Peng Li, Long-Gang Pang, Guang-You Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extracting the Speed of Sound in Heavy-Ion Collisions: A Study of Quantum-Initiated Fluctuations and Thermalization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02777</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02777v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The thermalization of quark-gluon plasma created in heavy-ion collisions is crucial for understanding its behavior as a relativistic fluid and the thermodynamic properties of the Quantum Chromodynamics (QCD). This study investigates the role of fluctuations in the relationship between transverse momentum and particle multiplicity, with a particular focus on their impact on extracting the QCD speed of sound. In a thermalized quark-gluon plasma, these fluctuations mostly originate from quantum fluctuations in the colliding nuclei, and exhibit a Gaussian distribution as a consequence of their independence from thermodynamic response. In contrast, non-thermalized systems display non-Gaussian fluctuations, reflecting the breakdown of thermalization. By leveraging the Gaussianity condition of quantum-initiated fluctuations, the physical value of the speed of sound can be extracted statistically, even in the presence of significant event-by-event fluctuations. This framework provides a robust diagnostic tool for probing thermalization and extracting thermodynamic properties in both large and small collision systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02777v4</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Shan Mu, Jing-An Sun, Li Yan, Xu-Guang Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Testing Variational Perturbation Theory for Effective Actions Using the Gaudin-Yang Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02919</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02919v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The background field formalism based on effective actions is a compelling framework for developing an effective field theory for nuclear density functional theory. Among the challenges in carrying out this development is handling both the particle-hole and pairing channels beyond the mean-field level, which includes how to incorporate collective degrees of freedom. Here we use the exactly solvable one-dimensional Gaudin-Yang model as a theoretical laboratory to explore candidate approaches. We compare Variational Perturbation Theory (VPT) to ordinary many-body perturbation theory and the inversion method, all to second order in their respective expansions, and verify issues with Hubbard-Stratonovich auxiliary fields. VPT outperforms the other approaches at this level over a wide range of densities. The next steps to extend this approach toward nuclei are outlined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02919v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pranav Sharma, R. J. Furnstahl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Computing Universal Thermalization Dynamics in a (2+1)D Lattice Gauge Theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.00069</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.00069v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Simulating non-equilibrium phenomena in strongly-interacting quantum many-body systems, including thermalization, is a promising application of near-term and future quantum computation. By performing experiments on a digital quantum computer consisting of fully-connected optically-controlled trapped ions, we study the role of entanglement in the thermalization dynamics of a $Z_2$ lattice gauge theory in 2+1 spacetime dimensions. Using randomized-measurement protocols, we efficiently learn a classical approximation of non-equilibrium states that yields the gap-ratio distribution and the spectral form factor of the entanglement Hamiltonian. These observables exhibit universal early-time signals for quantum chaos, a prerequisite for thermalization. Our work, therefore, establishes quantum computers as robust tools for studying universal features of thermalization in complex many-body systems, including in gauge theories.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.00069v2</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-60177-7</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Communications 16, 5492 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Niklas Mueller, Tianyi Wang, Or Katz, Zohreh Davoudi, Marko Cetina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extension of the integrated hydrokinetic model to nuclear collision energies relevant for the RHIC Beam-Energy Scan program and the research program at GSI-FAIR</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.00458</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.00458v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The present work is devoted to developing the integrated hydrokinetic model (iHKM) for relativistic nucleus-nucleus collisions. While the previous cycle of works on this topic focused on ultra-relativistic collisions at the top RHIC and different LHC energies, the current work addresses relativistic collisions at the lower energies, specifically ranging from approximately 2 to 50 GeV per nucleon pair in the center-of-mass colliding system. In such collisions, the formation times for the initial state of dense matter can be up to three orders of magnitude longer than those in ultra-relativistic collisions. This difference reflects a fundamentally distinct nature and formation process, particularly regarding the possible stages of initial state evolution, including thermalization (which may be only partial at very low collision energies), subsequent hydrodynamic expansion, and the final transition of matter evolution into a hadronic cascade. These stages, which are fully realized in ultra-relativistic reactions, can also occur within the energy range of BES RHIC, albeit with distinct time scales. This publication not only advances the theoretical development of iHKM (referred to, if necessary, as the {\it{extended}} version of the integrated Hydrokinetic Model, iHKM{\it{e}}), but also provides examples of model applications for calculating observables. A systematic description across a wide range of experimental energies, which is preliminary yet quite satisfactory, for spectra, flow, and femtoscopy, will follow this study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.00458v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/2g39-y1d1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. C 112, 034906 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Musfer Adzhymambetov, Yuri Sinyukov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review on recent progress in the study of the $N^*(920)$ subthreshold singularity and the $\sigma/f_0(500)$ meson</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.24674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.24674v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We summarize recent results on studies of $\pi\pi$ and $\pi N$ scatterings. They include the finding of a negative-parity nucleon pole with a mass lower than the nucleon mass, and the pole trajectory of $f_0(500)$ as the pion mass varies. The results are obtained from model-independent dispersion analyses. We also study the thermal properties of $f_0(500)$ based on the $O(N)$ $\sigma$ model and $N/D$ method.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.24674v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qu-Zhi Li, Zhiguang Xiao, Han-Qing Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vertex corrections and wavefunction renormalization for atoms, nuclei, and other heavy composite particles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.05540</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.05540v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study QED corrections to operator matrix elements involving heavy composite particles (e.g., heavy-mesons, nuclei, and atoms). We define a new notion of reducible and irreducible graphs which is useful for systems with many discrete excited states. The equivalence of the LSZ reduction formula and old fashioned perturbation theory is explicitly demonstrated. The self energy and vertex corrections are defined (to all orders), and the one-loop corrections are reduced to operator matrix elements which may be evaluated by hadronic, nuclear, or atomic theorists. The gauge dependence of the various pieces are studied in detail at one loop, and cancellation of spurious contributions are demonstrated in a class of covariant gauges; Coulomb gauge is also discussed. The formalism is applied to superallowed beta decay where the one-loop structure is connected to existing literature based on current algebra techniques. We further identify the well known $O(Z^2\alpha^2)$ isospin breaking correction from the intranuclear Coulomb field as arising from two-loop diagrams. We comment on future applications of our results to the radiative corrections necessary in extractions of $|V_{ud}|$, in particular for corrections that required beyond one-loop order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.05540v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryan Plestid, Mark B. Wise</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
