<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>nucl-th updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th</link>
    <description>nucl-th updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/nucl-th" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 05:00:28 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>"Observations on the possible electromagnetic nature of nucleon interactions and pions" -- historical manuscript from 1969 by B. W. Ninham and C. Pask</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06058</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06058v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This manuscript presents an historical perspective prepared by Barry Ninham and Colin Pask in 1969 on the connection between quantum electrodynamics theory and nucleon interactions. A new theory of strong interactions based on electromagnetic considerations is proposed. Energy and force range magnitudes are correctly given. A new theory of the pion emerges and the pion mass and lifetime are calculated. No strong interaction coupling constant is required.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06058v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>physics.hist-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.36253/Substantia-3509</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Substantia, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mathias Bostr\"om, Drew F. Parsons</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fixed-energy inverse scattering with radial basis function neural networks and its application to neutron-alpha interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06086v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper proposes a data-driven method to solve the fixed-energy inverse scattering problem for radially symmetric potentials using radial basis function (RBF) neural networks in an open-loop control system. The method estimates the scattering potentials in the Fourier domain by training an appropriate number of RBF networks, while the control step is carried out in the coordinate space by using the measured phase shifts as control parameters. The system is trained by both finite and singular input potentials and is capable of modeling a great variety of scattering events. The method is applied to neutron-alpha scattering at 10 MeV incident neutron energy, where the underlying central part of the potential is estimated by using the measured l = 0, 1, 2 phase shifts as inputs. The obtained potential is physically sensible, and the recalculated phase shifts are within a few percent relative error.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06086v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1093/ptep/ptad131</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Prog. Theor. Exp. Phys. 2023, (2023) 113A01</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G\'abor Balassa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bayesian Constraints on the Neutron Star Equation of State with a Smooth Hadron-Quark Crossover</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06696v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We perform a Bayesian inference of the dense-matter equation of state (EOS) within a unified framework that incorporates hadronic matter, quark matter, and a smooth hadron--quark crossover. The EOS is constrained using physical consistency filters, gravitational-wave data from GW170817, NICER mass--radius measurements, and hypothetical future high-precision radius data. We find that current observations strongly constrain the density dependence of the nuclear symmetry energy, particularly its slope and curvature, while the highest-density hadronic parameters and quark-matter parameters remain only weakly constrained. The posterior distributions favor a crossover centered at an energy density $\overline{\varepsilon}\sim(4$--$6)\varepsilon_0$ with a width $\Gamma\sim(0.5$--$1.0)\varepsilon_0$, where $\varepsilon_0$ is the energy density of symmetric nuclear matter at saturation. The most probable radius of a canonical neutron star is $R_{1.4}\simeq 11.5-13.0$ km, and the maximum mass is $M_{\rm TOV}\simeq 2.2\,M_\odot$. Overall, present data primarily probe the low-to-intermediate density EOS and provide limited direct sensitivity to quark matter and genuinely high-density physics, highlighting the need for next-generation precision radius measurements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06696v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xavier Grundler, Bao-An Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Many-body effects on dense matter with hyperons at finite temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06815v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we present the first extension of the Many-Body Forces (MBF) Model to finite temperature. The MBF Model describes nuclear matter in a relativistic quantum hadrodynamics formalism that takes many-body forces into account through a field dependence of the nuclear interaction coupling constants. Assuming nuclear matter to be charge neutral, beta-equilibrated, and populated by the baryon octet, electrons, and muons, we explore the parameters of the model, three different hyperon coupling schemes (also introduced here for the first time in MBF), and temperature effects to describe basic properties of nuclear matter, including the speed of sound, compressibility, and adiabatic index. We also investigate the mass-radius relation of compact stars by solving the Tolman-Oppenheimer-Volkoff equations at zero and finite temperature, including scenarios with fixed entropy per baryon. Our original results at finite temperature open the path to a new description of proto-neutron stars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06815v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael B\'an Jacobsen, Ricardo Luciano Sonego Farias, Veronica Dexheimer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holographic Charged Transport with Higher Derivatives</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06144</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06144v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We compute the first-order hydrodynamic transport coefficients (shear viscosity $\eta$, bulk viscosity $\zeta$, and charge conductivity $\sigma$) for a broad class of strongly coupled, four-dimensional charged relativistic gauge theory plasma with holographic gravitational duals containing higher-derivative corrections. The landscape of our holographic models captures non-conformal gauge theories with an arbitrary number of relevant coupling constants and a general scalar potential in the gravitational dual, allowing for a systematic exploration of charged transport along generic holographic RG flows. The leading-order higher-derivative corrections probe gauge theories with non-equal central charges $c\ne a$ at the ultraviolet fixed point, and enable the engineering of diverse temperature and charge density profiles for the viscosities and the conductivity. Our results establish the membrane paradigm in higher-derivative holographic models: all the transport coefficients are extracted from the black brane horizon values of the gravitational scalars, and various functions defining the gravitational holographic dual.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06144v1</guid>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alex Buchel, Sera Cremonini, Mohammad Moezzi, George Tringas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Neutron Star Observations Point Towards Exotic Matter: Existing Explanations and a Prospective Proposal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06170v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Multi-messenger astronomical observations of neutron stars, together with more precise calculations and constraints coming from dense matter microphysics, are generating tension with regard to equations of state models used to describe neutron star cores. Assuming an abrupt first-order phase transition with a slow conversion speed between phases, we propose different slow stable hybrid star configurations aiming to reconcile all current constraints simultaneously; within this framework, we also introduce a novel non-CSS parametrization to the quark matter equation of state and discuss its strengths and limitations. We analyze our model results in conjunction with a review of other relevant theoretical possibilities existing in the literature. We found that modern neutron star observations seem to favor the existence of some type of exotic matter in the neutron star cores; in particular, our slow stable hybrid star scenario remains a proposal capable of satisfying these constraints. However, due both to the existing skepticism regarding some of the adopted hypotheses in most extreme neutron star measurements and to the precise adjustment needed for the equation-of-state parameters, significant tension and open questions remain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06170v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/sym18010027</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Symmetry 2026, 18(1), 27</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mauro Mariani, Ignacio F. Ranea-Sandoval</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quasi-elastic scattering for the nuclear ground state structure: An intriguing case of $^{30}$Si</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06580</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06580v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quasi-elastic (QEL) scattering measurements have been performed using the $^{28, 30}$Si projectiles off the $^{90}$Zr target at energies around the Coulomb barrier. Coupled-channels (CC) calculations were carried out in a large parameter space of quadrupole and hexadecapole deformations for the N=Z, $^{28}$Si and N=Z+2, $^{30}$Si nuclei. $^{28}$Si at the N=Z line is observed to be uniquely oblate shaped in its ground state. In contrast, for $^{30}$Si with just two additional neutrons -- oblate, prolate, and spherical CC descriptions are equally compatible with the measurements. To further investigate the nuclear structure evolution with varying neutron number, shell-model calculations were performed. These calculations reveal a sudden change in the nuclear structure aspects at $^{30}$Si in going from $^{28}$Si to $^{30}$Si. Combined reaction and structure analyses consistently indicate that $^{30}$Si does not possess a well-defined intrinsic shape, and it is a potential candidate for ``shape fluctuations" in its ground state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06580v1</guid>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.physletb.2026.140239</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Y. K. Gupta, B. Maheshwari, G. K. Prajapati, A. K. Jain, K. Hagino, B. N. Joshi, A. Pal, N. Sirswal, Pawan Singh, S. Dubey, V. V. Desai, V. Ranga, V. B. Katariya, D. Patel, H. Vyas, S. Panwar, B. V. John, I. Mazumdar, B. K. Nayak, U. Garg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics of strong electromagnetic fields in relativistic heavy-ion collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06697v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: I discuss several roles of the strong electromagnetic fields created by relativistic heavy-ion collisions. These phenomena call for theoretical and experimental developments to understand dynamics of quark-gluon plasma (QGP) as well as purely electromagnetic processes in the ultraperipheral collisions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06697v1</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jspc.2026.100301</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Koichi Hattori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proton-Size Resolution of the Hyperfine Puzzle in Hydrogen</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2602.06929</link>
      <description>arXiv:2602.06929v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Baym and Farrar (arXiv:2601.02300v1) have recently pointed out a puzzle in understanding the role of the hyperfine interaction in the ground state of a hydrogen atom. If one uses a variational wave function in which the Bohr radius, $a_0$ is replaced by a variational radius parameter, $R$, first-order perturbation theory can give a contribution to the energy proportional to $-1/R^3$. This raises the question of why the hyperfine interaction does not lead to collapse of hydrogen. I show that including the effects of the non-zero size of the proton leads to a resolution of the puzzle such that the variational procedure yields a value of $R$ that is indistinguishable from $a_0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2602.06929v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gerald A. Miller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Initial Baryon Stopping and Angular Momentum in Heavy-Ion Collisions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.02192</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.02192v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Noncentral heavy-ion collisions create fireballs with large initial orbital angular momentum that is expected to induce strong vorticity in the hot bulk fluid and generate global spin polarization of the produced particles. As the collision beam energy $\sqrt{s_{\rm NN}}$ decreases to approach the two-nucleon-mass threshold, this initial angular momentum approaches zero. One may thus expect that the observed global spin polarization should reach a maximum and then drop to zero as increased stopping competes with decreased initial momentum. Recent experimental measurements, however, appear to show a continual rise of hyperon polarization even down to $\sqrt{s_{\rm NN}} =$ 2.42 GeV, suggesting a peak very near threshold which is difficult to interpret and calls for a better understanding of angular momentum initial conditions, especially at low energy. Here, we develop a new Glauber-based initial state model ("Glauber+") to investigate the initial distribution of angular momentum with respect to rapidity as well as the dependence of this distribution on initial baryon stopping across a wide range of collisional beam energy. We estimate that the angular momentum per produced final charged particle at mid-rapidity peaks around 5 GeV, which may present a potential challenge to an interpretation of the spin polarization measurements near threshold as being a consequence of the initial angular momentum of the colliding system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.02192v3</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/lz5s-98rc</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. C 112, 064911 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Alex Akridge, Daniel Gallimore, Hector Morales, Jinfeng Liao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NuLattice: Ab initio computations of atomic nuclei on lattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.08771</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.08771v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce NuLattice, a Python software package for ab initio computations of atomic nuclei on lattices. The computational tools consist of Hartree Fock, the coupled cluster method, the in-medium similarity renormalization group, and full configuration interaction. At present, the employed interactions are from pion-less effective field theory at leading order and consist of two-body and three-body contacts. We present results for light nuclei $^{2}$H, $^{3,4}$He, $^{8}$Be, $^{12}$C, and $^{16}$O. NuLattice algorithms exploit the sparsity and locality of lattice interactions, and as a result computations can be run on laptops.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.08771v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epja/s10050-025-01764-6</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Eur. Phys. J. A 62, 28 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>M. Rothman, B. Johnson-Toth, G. Hagen, M. Heinz, T. Papenbrock</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-strange and charmed hadrons: A novel probe for the QCD equation of state at high baryon densities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23353v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Nuclear experiments near and below the threshold of hyperon production have shown that the production of Kaons is a sensitive probe for the dense QCD equation of state. At beam energies up to 1.5AGeV, strangeness production can probe the equation of state for densities up to approximately twice nuclear saturation. In this paper we will discuss the possibilities of extending this range in density by the study of multi-strange baryons as well as charmed hadrons in the SIS100 beam energy range up to $10A$GeV. Here, densities up to five times nuclear saturation can be reached and the production of multi-strange and charmed hadrons shows a strong sensitivity to the equation of state. On the other hand a precise prediction of the effect of the equation of state will require knowledge of the fundamental production cross section near the elementary production threshold in p+p collisions which is yet not measured for the hadrons discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23353v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjs/s11734-026-02125-0</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jan Steinheimer, Tom Reichert, Marcus Bleicher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Systematics of the chemical freeze-out line in the high baryon density regime explored at SIS100</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.01413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.01413v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The systematic uncertainties of chemical freeze-out fits at SIS100 energies (Au+Au reactions at $\sqrt{s_{NN}}=3-5$ GeV) are studied using UrQMD simulations. Although hadron production in UrQMD does not occur on a sharp chemical freeze-out hyper-surface, the extracted fit quality is shown to be very good. The extracted chemical parameters depend on the selected hadron species as well as the underlying equation of state (EoS) of the matter. Including light nuclei and anti-protons in the fit increases the expected freeze-out temperature, while a stiffer EoS increases the obtained chemical potential. Similarly, the baryon densities extracted by the thermal fits depend on the choice of hadrons as well as the underlying equation of state. These results are important for the upcoming CBM@FAIR physics program and highlight that a degree of caution is advised when one relates the chemical freeze-out curve to features on the QCD phase diagram like the critical endpoint or a possible phase transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.01413v2</guid>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1140/epjs/s11734-026-02126-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Emma Lilith Hofmann, Tom Reichert, Volodymyr Vovchenko, Jan Steinheimer, Marcus Bleicher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigating the role of nuclear parameters in Neutron Star oscillations: a model comparison</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04373v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recent studies based on the relativistic mean field (RMF) model found certain nuclear empirical parameters, in particular the nucleon effective mass, to be strongly correlated with observable properties of Neutron Stars (NSs), such as the frequencies of $f-$mode oscillations. This shows the potential to constrain the values of effective mass from future observations of $f-$modes. One of our primary goals of this work is to investigate whether such correlations are physical or an artifact of the underlying nuclear model. To test this, we perform a comparative study of the correlations between NS astrophysical observables and nuclear physics parameters using two different equation of state models based on RMF theory and non-relativistic Meta-Modelling (MM) scheme. The nuclear meta-model does not assume any underlying nuclear model and therefore allows us to test the model dependence of the results. The calculations of the $f-$mode characteristics are performed within the relativistic Cowling approximation. We use state-of-the-art nuclear microscopic calculations at low density and multi-messenger astrophysical data at high-density within a Bayesian-inspired scheme to constrain the parameter space of the nuclear models. From the posterior distribution, we probe the underlying correlations among nuclear parameters and with NS observables. We find that the correlation between the symmetry energy and its slope is physical, while that of the nucleon effective mass with NS observables is model-dependent. The study shows that the effective mass governs the high density behaviour in RMF models, while in the MM it is controlled by the higher order saturation parameters, and hence probes the possibility of constraining them from future $f$-mode observations. The findings of this investigation are interesting both for astrophysics as well as nuclear physics communities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04373v3</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nuclphysa.2025.123267</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nucl.Phys.A 1066 (2026) 123267</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rajesh Maiti, Debarati Chatterjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interactions of Neutrino Wave Packets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22005</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22005v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The low energy effective field theory of interacting neutrinos derived from the Standard Model may be framed as a pointlike interaction and thereby modeled on a lattice of neutrino momenta. We identify a path to take a continuum limit of this lattice problem in the center of momentum frame. In this limit, the weak interaction is found to become trivial between incoming plane waves describing ultrarelativistic particles, unless finite neutrino wave packet sizes are taken into consideration. We follow up with an analytic treatment of interacting neutrino wave packets, demonstrating the importance of the wave packet size for characterizing neutrino-neutrino scattering in dense environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22005v3</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/r54h-jj1f</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. D 113, 043010 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Michael J. Cervia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic geometry in hadron resonance gas model at real and imaginary baryon chemical potential and a simple sufficient condition for quark deconfinement</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.16762</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.16762v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The thermodynamic geometry of the hadron resonance gas model with (without) excluded volume effects (EVE) of baryons is investigated. The case with imaginary mu, where mu is the baryon chemical potential, is investigated as well as the one with real mu. We calculate the scalar curvature R and use the R=0 criterion to investigate the phase structure in the mu^2-T plane where T is the temperature. The curve on which R=0 continues analytically from the imaginary mu region, where the lattice QCD is feasible, to the real mu one. In the presence of EVE, there are rich phase structures in the large real mu region as well as the Roberge-Weiss like region where mu is imaginary and a singularity appears, while there is no phase structure in the large real $\mu$ region in the absence of EVE. The limitation temperature of the baryon gas is also obtained by using the baryon number fluctuation. The LQCD predicted critical point locates almost on the curve of the limitation temperature we determined. A simple sufficient condition, n_B&gt;1/(2v_B)$, is obtained for the quark deconfinement in the large real mu region, where n_B and v_B are the net baryon number density and the volume of a baryon, respectively.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.16762v2</guid>
      <category>hep-ph</category>
      <category>hep-ex</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>nucl-ex</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Feb 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riki Oshima, Hiroaki Kouno, Motoi Tachibana, Kouji Kashiwa</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
