<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.EM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.EM</link>
    <description>econ.EM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.EM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 20:51:01 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Factors in Fashion: Factor Analysis towards the Mode</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.19287</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.19287v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The modal factor model represents a new factor model for dimension reduction in high dimensional panel data. Unlike the approximate factor model that targets for the mean factors, it captures factors that influence the conditional mode of the distribution of the observables. Statistical inference is developed with the aid of mode estimation, where the modal factors and the loadings are estimated through maximizing a kernel-type objective function. An easy-to-implement alternating maximization algorithm is designed to obtain the estimators numerically. Two model selection criteria are further proposed to determine the number of factors. The asymptotic properties of the proposed estimators are established under some regularity conditions. Simulations demonstrate the nice finite sample performance of our proposed estimators, even in the presence of heavy-tailed and asymmetric idiosyncratic error distributions. Finally, the application to inflation forecasting illustrates the practical merits of modal factors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.19287v1</guid>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Sun, Yundong Tu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthetic Difference in Differences for Repeated Cross-Sectional Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20199</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.20199v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The synthetic difference-in-differences method provides an efficient method to estimate a causal effect with a latent factor model. However, it relies on the use of panel data. This paper presents an adaptation of the synthetic difference-in-differences method for repeated cross-sectional data. The treatment is considered to be at the group level so that it is possible to aggregate data by group to compute the two types of synthetic difference-in-differences weights on these aggregated data. Then, I develop and compute a third type of weight that accounts for the different number of observations in each cross-section. Simulation results show that the performance of the synthetic difference-in-differences estimator is improved when using the third type of weights on repeated cross-sectional data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.20199v1</guid>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yoann Morin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>New Tests of Equal Forecast Accuracy for Factor-Augmented Regressions with Weaker Loadings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20415</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.20415v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We provide the theoretical foundation for the recently proposed tests of equal forecast accuracy and encompassing by Pitarakis (2023a) and Pitarakis (2023b), when the competing forecast specification is that of a factor-augmented regression model, whose loadings are allowed to be homogeneously/heterogeneously weak. This should be of interest for practitioners, as at the moment there is no theory available to justify the use of these simple and powerful tests in such context.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.20415v1</guid>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luca Margaritella, Ovidijus Stauskas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reinforcing RCTs with Multiple Priors while Learning about External Validity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2112.09170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2112.09170v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper introduces a framework for incorporating prior information into the design of sequential experiments. These sources may include past experiments, expert opinions, or the experimenter's intuition. We model the problem using a multi-prior Bayesian approach, mapping each source to a Bayesian model and aggregating them based on posterior probabilities. Policies are evaluated on three criteria: learning the parameters of payoff distributions, the probability of choosing the wrong treatment, and average rewards. Our framework demonstrates several desirable properties, including robustness to sources lacking external validity, while maintaining strong finite sample performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2112.09170v5</guid>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <category>math.ST</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>stat.TH</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frederico Finan, Demian Pouzo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Estimation of Heterogeneous Treatment Effects Using a Conditional Moment Based Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.15829</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.15829v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose a new estimator for heterogeneous treatment effects in a partially linear model (PLM) with multiple exogenous covariates and a potentially endogenous treatment variable. Our approach integrates a Robinson transformation to handle the nonparametric component, the Smooth Minimum Distance (SMD) method to leverage conditional mean independence restrictions, and a Neyman-Orthogonalized first-order condition (FOC). By employing regularized model selection techniques like the Lasso method, our estimator accommodates numerous covariates while exhibiting reduced bias, consistency, and asymptotic normality. Simulations demonstrate its robust performance with diverse instrument sets compared to traditional GMM-type estimators. Applying this method to estimate Medicaid's heterogeneous treatment effects from the Oregon Health Insurance Experiment reveals more robust and reliable results than conventional GMM approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.15829v3</guid>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaolin Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GARCHX-NoVaS: A Model-free Approach to Incorporate Exogenous Variables</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.13346</link>
      <description>arXiv:2308.13346v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, we explore the forecasting ability of a recently proposed normalizing and variance-stabilizing (NoVaS) transformation with the possible inclusion of exogenous variables. From an applied point-of-view, extra knowledge such as fundamentals- and sentiments-based information could be beneficial to improve the prediction accuracy of market volatility if they are incorporated into the forecasting process. In the classical approach, these models including exogenous variables are typically termed GARCHX-type models. Being a Model-free prediction method, NoVaS has generally shown more accurate, stable and robust (to misspecifications) performance than that compared to classical GARCH-type methods. This motivates us to extend this framework to the GARCHX forecasting as well. We derive the NoVaS transformation needed to include exogenous covariates and then construct the corresponding prediction procedure. We show through extensive simulation studies that bolster our claim that the NoVaS method outperforms traditional ones, especially for long-term time aggregated predictions. We also provide an interesting data analysis to exhibit how our method could possibly shed light on the role of geopolitical risks in forecasting volatility in national stock market indices for three different countries in Europe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2308.13346v3</guid>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kejin Wu, Sayar Karmakar, Rangan Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inference in Auctions with Many Bidders Using Transaction Prices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2311.09972</link>
      <description>arXiv:2311.09972v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper studies inference in first- and second-price sealed-bid auctions with many bidders, using an asymptotic framework where the number of bidders increases while the number of auctions remains fixed. Relevant applications include online, treasury, spectrum, and art auctions. Our approach enables asymptotically exact inference on key features such as the winner's expected utility, the seller's expected revenue, and the tail of the valuation distribution using only transaction price data. Our simulations demonstrate the accuracy of the methods in finite samples. We apply our methods to Hong Kong vehicle license auctions, focusing on high-priced, single-letter plates.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2311.09972v3</guid>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico A. Bugni, Yulong Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Under the null of valid specification, pre-tests cannot make post-test inference liberal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.03725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.03725v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Consider a parameter of interest, which can be consistently estimated under some conditions. Suppose also that we can at least partly test these conditions with specification tests. We consider the common practice of conducting inference on the parameter of interest conditional on not rejecting these tests. We show that if the tested conditions hold, conditional inference is valid, though possibly conservative. This holds generally, without imposing any assumption on the asymptotic dependence between the estimator of the parameter of interest and the specification test.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.03725v2</guid>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Cl\'ement de Chaisemartin, Xavier D'Haultf{\oe}uille</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>To Bag is to Prune</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2008.07063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2008.07063v5 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: It is notoriously difficult to build a bad Random Forest (RF). Concurrently, RF blatantly overfits in-sample without any apparent consequence out-of-sample. Standard arguments, like the classic bias-variance trade-off or double descent, cannot rationalize this paradox. I propose a new explanation: bootstrap aggregation and model perturbation as implemented by RF automatically prune a latent "true" tree. More generally, randomized ensembles of greedily optimized learners implicitly perform optimal early stopping out-of-sample. So there is no need to tune the stopping point. By construction, novel variants of Boosting and MARS are also eligible for automatic tuning. I empirically demonstrate the property, with simulated and real data, by reporting that these new completely overfitting ensembles perform similarly to their tuned counterparts -- or better.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2008.07063v5</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philippe Goulet Coulombe</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
