<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>econ.EM updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.EM</link>
    <description>econ.EM updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/econ.EM" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 05:00:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Detecting and Mitigating Treatment Leakage in Text-Based Causal Inference: Distillation and Sensitivity Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02400</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02400v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Text-based causal inference increasingly employs textual data as proxies for unobserved confounders, yet this approach introduces a previously undertheorized source of bias: treatment leakage. Treatment leakage occurs when text intended to capture confounding information also contains signals predictive of treatment status, thereby inducing post-treatment bias in causal estimates. Critically, this problem can arise even when documents precede treatment assignment, as authors may employ future-referencing language that anticipates subsequent interventions. Despite growing recognition of this issue, no systematic methods exist for identifying and mitigating treatment leakage in text-as-confounder applications. This paper addresses this gap through three contributions. First, we provide formal statistical and set-theoretic definitions of treatment leakage that clarify when and why bias occurs. Second, we propose four text distillation methods -- similarity-based passage removal, distant supervision classification, salient feature removal, and iterative nullspace projection -- designed to eliminate treatment-predictive content while preserving confounder information. Third, we validate these methods through simulations using synthetic text and an empirical application examining International Monetary Fund structural adjustment programs and child mortality. Our findings indicate that moderate distillation optimally balances bias reduction against confounder retention, whereas overly stringent approaches degrade estimate precision.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02400v1</guid>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adel Daoud, Richard Johansson, Connor T. Jerzak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Time-Aware Synthetic Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03099</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.03099v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The synthetic control (SC) framework is widely used for observational causal inference with time-series panel data. SC has been successful in diverse applications, but existing methods typically treat the ordering of pre-intervention time indices interchangeable. This invariance means they may not fully take advantage of temporal structure when strong trends are present. We propose Time-Aware Synthetic Control (TASC), which employs a state-space model with a constant trend while preserving a low-rank structure of the signal. TASC uses the Kalman filter and Rauch-Tung-Striebel smoother: it first fits a generative time-series model with expectation-maximization and then performs counterfactual inference. We evaluate TASC on both simulated and real-world datasets, including policy evaluation and sports prediction. Our results suggest that TASC offers advantages in settings with strong temporal trends and high levels of observation noise.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.03099v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Saeyoung Rho, Cyrus Illick, Samhitha Narasipura, Alberto Abadie, Daniel Hsu, Vishal Misra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensitivity Analysis in Unconditional Quantile Effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.14298</link>
      <description>arXiv:2303.14298v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This paper proposes a framework to analyze the effects of counterfactual policies on the unconditional quantiles of an outcome variable. For a given counterfactual policy, we obtain identified sets for the effect of both marginal and global changes in the proportion of treated individuals. To conduct a sensitivity analysis, we introduce the quantile breakdown frontier, a curve that (i) indicates whether a sensitivity analysis is possible or not, and (ii) when a sensitivity analysis is possible, quantifies the amount of selection bias consistent with a given conclusion of interest across different quantiles. To illustrate our method, we perform a sensitivity analysis on the effect of unionizing low income workers on the quantiles of the distribution of (log) wages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2303.14298v4</guid>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Martinez-Iriarte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized method of moments with partially missing data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.21988</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.21988v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider a generalized method of moments framework in which a part of the data vector is missing for some units in a completely unrestricted, potentially endogenous way. In this setup, the parameters of interest are usually only partially identified. We characterize the identified set for such parameters using the support function of the convex set of moment predictions consistent with the data. This identified set is sharp, valid for both continuous and discrete data, and straightforward to estimate. We also propose a statistic for testing hypotheses and constructing confidence regions for the true parameter, show that standard nonparametric bootstrap may not be valid, and suggest a fix using the bootstrap for directionally differentiable functionals of Fang and Santos (2019). A set of Monte Carlo simulations demonstrates that both our estimator and the confidence region perform well when samples are moderately large and the data have bounded supports.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.21988v2</guid>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Grigory Franguridi, Hyungsik Roger Moon</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Distributionally Robust Synthetic Control: Ensuring Robustness Against Highly Correlated Controls and Weight Shifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.02632</link>
      <description>arXiv:2511.02632v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The synthetic control method estimates the causal effect by comparing the treated unit's outcomes to a weighted average of control units that closely match its pre-treatment outcomes, assuming the relationship between treated and control potential outcomes remains stable before and after treatment. However, the estimator may become unreliable when these relationships shift or when control units are highly correlated. To address these challenges, we introduce the Distributionally Robust Synthetic Control (DRoSC) method, which accommodates potential shifts in relationships and addresses high correlations among control units. The DRoSC method targets a novel causal estimand defined as the optimizer of a worst-case optimization problem considering all possible weights compatible with the pre-treatment period. When the identification conditions for the classical synthetic control method hold, the DRoSC method targets the same causal effect as the synthetic control; when these conditions are violated, we demonstrate that this new causal estimand is a conservative proxy for the non-identifiable causal effect. We further show that the DRoSC estimator's limiting distribution is non-normal and propose a novel inferential approach. We demonstrate its performance through numerical studies and an analysis of the economic impact of terrorism in the Basque Country.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2511.02632v2</guid>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <category>econ.EM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Taehyeon Koo, Zijian Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
