<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE</link>
    <description>cs.CE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 04:00:17 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Population Activity Recovery: Milestones Unfolding, Temporal Interdependencies, and Relationship with Physical and Social Vulnerability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14720</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14720v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding sequential community recovery milestones is crucial for proactive recovery planning and monitoring. This study investigates these milestones related to population activities to examine their temporal interdependencies and evaluate the relationship between recovery milestones and physical (residential property damage) and social vulnerability (household income). This study leverages post-2017 Hurricane Harvey mobility data from Harris County to specify and analyze temporal recovery milestones and their interdependencies. The analysis examined four key milestones: return to evacuated areas, recovery of essential and nonessential services, and the rate of home-switch (moving out of residences). Robust linear regression validates interdependencies between across milestone lags and sequences: achieving earlier milestones accelerates subsequent recovery milestones. The study thus identifies six primary recovery milestone sequences. We found that social vulnerability accounted through the median household income level, rather than physical vulnerability to flooding accounted through the property damage extent, correlates with recovery delays between milestones. We studied variations in recovery sequences across lower and upper quantiles of property damage extent and median household income: lower property damage extent and lower household income show greater representation in the (slowest to recover) sequence, while households with greater damage and higher income are predominant in the group with the (fastest recovery sequences). Milestone sequence variability aligns closely with social vulnerability, independent of physical vulnerability. Understanding the variation in recovery sequences, milestone interdependencies, and social vulnerability disparities provides crucial evidence for targeted interventions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14720v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Flavia Ioana Patrascu, Ali Mostafavi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-informed neural networks for parameter learning of wildfire spreading</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14591v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Wildland fires pose terrifying natural hazards, underscoring the urgent need to develop data-driven and physics-informed digital twins for wildfire prevention, monitoring, intervention, and response. In this direction of research, this work introduces a physics-informed neural network (PiNN) to learn the unknown parameters of an interpretable wildfire spreading model. The considered wildfire spreading model integrates fundamental physical laws articulated by key model parameters, essential for capturing the complex behavior of wildfires. The proposed machine learning approach leverages the theory of artificial neural networks with the physical constraints governing wildfire dynamics, such as the first principles of mass and energy conservation. Training of the PiNN for physics-informed parameter identification is realized using data of the temporal evolution of one- and two-dimensional (plane surface) fire fronts that have been obtained from a high-fidelity simulator of the wildfire spreading model under consideration. The parameter learning results demonstrate the remarkable predictive ability of the proposed PiNN in uncovering the unknown coefficients in both the one- and two-dimensional fire spreading scenarios. Additionally, this methodology exhibits robustness by identifying the same parameters in the presence of noisy data. The proposed framework is envisioned to be incorporated in a physics-informed digital twin for intelligent wildfire management and risk assessment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14591v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantinos Vogiatzoglou, Costas Papadimitriou, Vasilis Bontozoglou, Konstantinos Ampountolas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Latent diffusion models for parameterization and data assimilation of facies-based geomodels</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.14815</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.14815v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Geological parameterization entails the representation of a geomodel using a small set of latent variables and a mapping from these variables to grid-block properties such as porosity and permeability. Parameterization is useful for data assimilation (history matching), as it maintains geological realism while reducing the number of variables to be determined. Diffusion models are a new class of generative deep-learning procedures that have been shown to outperform previous methods, such as generative adversarial networks, for image generation tasks. Diffusion models are trained to "denoise", which enables them to generate new geological realizations from input fields characterized by random noise. Latent diffusion models, which are the specific variant considered in this study, provide dimension reduction through use of a low-dimensional latent variable. The model developed in this work includes a variational autoencoder for dimension reduction and a U-net for the denoising process. Our application involves conditional 2D three-facies (channel-levee-mud) systems. The latent diffusion model is shown to provide realizations that are visually consistent with samples from geomodeling software. Quantitative metrics involving spatial and flow-response statistics are evaluated, and general agreement between the diffusion-generated models and reference realizations is observed. Stability tests are performed to assess the smoothness of the parameterization method. The latent diffusion model is then used for ensemble-based data assimilation. Two synthetic "true" models are considered. Significant uncertainty reduction, posterior P$_{10}$-P$_{90}$ forecasts that generally bracket observed data, and consistent posterior geomodels, are achieved in both cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.14815v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guido Di Federico, Louis J. Durlofsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase-field simulations opening new horizons in corrosion research</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15013v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work overviews a new, recent success of phase-field modelling: its application to predicting the evolution of the corrosion front and the associated structural integrity challenges. Despite its important implications for society, predicting corrosion damage has been an elusive goal for scientists and engineers. The application of phase-field modelling to corrosion not only enables tracking the electrolyte-metal interface but also provides an avenue to explicitly simulate the underlying mesoscale physical processes. This lays the grounds for developing the first generation of mechanistic corrosion models, which can capture key phenomena such as film rupture and repassivation, the transition from activation- to diffusion-controlled corrosion, interactions with mechanical fields, microstructural and electrochemical effects, intergranular corrosion, material biodegradation, and the interplay with other environmentally-assisted damage phenomena such as hydrogen embrittlement.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15013v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. Mart\'inez-Pa\~neda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tempora-Fusion: Time-Lock Puzzle with Efficient Verifiable Homomorphic Linear Combination</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.15070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.15070v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To securely transmit sensitive information into the future, Time-Lock Puzzles (TLPs) have been developed. Their applications include scheduled payments, timed commitments, e-voting, and sealed-bid auctions. Homomorphic TLP is a key variant of TLP that enables computation on puzzles from different clients. This allows a solver/server to tackle only a single puzzle encoding the computation's result. However, existing homomorphic TLPs lack support for verifying the correctness of the computation results. We address this limitation by introducing Tempora-Fusion, a TLP that allows a server to perform homomorphic linear combinations of puzzles from different clients while ensuring verification of computation correctness. This scheme avoids asymmetric-key cryptography for verification, thus paving the way for efficient implementations. We discuss our scheme's application in various domains, such as federated learning, scheduled payments in online banking, and e-voting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.15070v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aydin Abadi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Explicit Primitive Conservative Solver for the Euler Equations with Arbitrary Equation of State</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07710</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07710v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work presents a procedure to solve the Euler equations by explicitly updating, in a conservative manner, a generic thermodynamic variable such as temperature, pressure or entropy instead of the total energy. The presented procedure is valid for any equation of state and spatial discretization. When using complex equations of state such as Span-Wagner, choosing the temperature as the generic thermodynamic variable yields great reductions in the computational costs associated to thermodynamic evaluations. Results computed with a state of the art thermodynamic model are presented, and computational times are analyzed. Particular attention is dedicated to the conservation of total energy, the propagation speed of shock waves and jump conditions. The procedure is thoroughly tested using the Span-Wagner equation of state through the CoolProp thermodynamic library and the Van der Waals equation of state, both in the ideal and non-ideal compressible fluid-dynamics regimes, by comparing it to the standard total energy update and analytical solutions where available.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07710v3</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.compfluid.2024.106340</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Computers &amp; Fluids (2024) 279:106340</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Sirianni, Alberto Guardone, Barbara Re, R\'emi Abgrall</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Reasoning Models for 3D Floorplanning in EDA: Learning from Imperfections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.10538</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.10538v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce Dreamweaver, which belongs to a new class of auto-regressive decision-making models known as large reasoning models (LRMs). Dreamweaver is designed to improve 3D floorplanning in electronic design automation (EDA) via an architecture that melds advancements in sequence-to-sequence reinforcement learning algorithms. A significant advantage of our approach is its ability to effectively reason over large discrete action spaces, which is essential for handling the numerous potential positions for various functional blocks in floorplanning. Additionally, Dreamweaver demonstrates strong performance even when trained on entirely random trajectories, showcasing its capacity to leverage sub-optimal or non-expert trajectories to enhance its results. This innovative approach contributes to streamlining the integrated circuit (IC) design flow and reducing the high computational costs typically associated with floorplanning. We evaluate its performance against a current state-of-the-art method, highlighting notable improvements.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.10538v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fin Amin, Nirjhor Rouf, Tse-Han Pan, Md Kamal Ibn Shafi, Paul D. Franzon</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
