<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE</link>
    <description>cs.CE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 04:00:50 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 19 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>PyTOaCNN: Topology optimization using an adaptive convolutional neural network in Python</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12244</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12244v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper introduces an adaptive convolutional neural network (CNN) architecture capable of automating various topology optimization (TO) problems with diverse underlying physics. The proposed architecture has an encoder-decoder-type structure with dense layers added at the bottleneck region to capture complex geometrical features. The network is trained using datasets obtained by the problem-specific open-source TO codes. Tensorflow and Keras are the main libraries employed to develop and to train the model. Effectiveness and robustness of the proposed adaptive CNN model are demonstrated through its performance in compliance minimization problems involving constant and design-dependent loads and in addressing bulk modulus optimization. Once trained, the model takes user's input of the volume fraction as an image and instantly generates an output image of optimized design. The proposed CNN produces high-quality results resembling those obtained via open-source TO codes with negligible performance and volume fraction errors. The paper includes complete associated Python code (Appendix A) for the proposed CNN architecture and explains each part of the code to facilitate reproducibility and ease of learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12244v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Khaish Singh Chadha, Prabhat Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Large Language Models for Synthetic Participatory Planning of Shared Automated Electric Mobility Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12317</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12317v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Unleashing the synergies of rapidly evolving mobility technologies in a multi-stakeholder landscape presents unique challenges and opportunities for addressing urban transportation problems. This paper introduces a novel synthetic participatory method, critically leveraging large language models (LLMs) to create digital avatars representing diverse stakeholders to plan shared automated electric mobility systems (SAEMS). These calibratable agents collaboratively identify objectives, envision and evaluate SAEMS alternatives, and strategize implementation under risks and constraints. The results of a Montreal case study indicate that a structured and parameterized workflow provides outputs with high controllability and comprehensiveness on an SAEMS plan than generated using a single LLM-enabled expert agent. Consequently, the approach provides a promising avenue for cost-efficiently improving the inclusivity and interpretability of multi-objective transportation planning, suggesting a paradigm shift in how we envision and strategize for sustainable and equitable transportation systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12317v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiangbo Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Internet sentiment exacerbates intraday overtrading, evidence from A-Share market</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12001v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Market fluctuations caused by overtrading are important components of systemic market risk. This study examines the effect of investor sentiment on intraday overtrading activities in the Chinese A-share market. Employing high-frequency sentiment indices inferred from social media posts on the Eastmoney forum Guba, the research focuses on constituents of the CSI 300 and CSI 500 indices over a period from 01/01/2018, to 12/30/2022. The empirical analysis indicates that investor sentiment exerts a significantly positive impact on intraday overtrading, with the influence being more pronounced among institutional investors relative to individual traders. Moreover, sentiment-driven overtrading is found to be more prevalent during bull markets as opposed to bear markets. Additionally, the effect of sentiment on overtrading is observed to be more pronounced among individual investors in large-cap stocks compared to small- and mid-cap stocks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12001v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Peng Yifeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FastVPINNs: Tensor-Driven Acceleration of VPINNs for Complex Geometries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12063v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Variational Physics-Informed Neural Networks (VPINNs) utilize a variational loss function to solve partial differential equations, mirroring Finite Element Analysis techniques. Traditional hp-VPINNs, while effective for high-frequency problems, are computationally intensive and scale poorly with increasing element counts, limiting their use in complex geometries. This work introduces FastVPINNs, a tensor-based advancement that significantly reduces computational overhead and improves scalability. Using optimized tensor operations, FastVPINNs achieve a 100-fold reduction in the median training time per epoch compared to traditional hp-VPINNs. With proper choice of hyperparameters, FastVPINNs surpass conventional PINNs in both speed and accuracy, especially in problems with high-frequency solutions. Demonstrated effectiveness in solving inverse problems on complex domains underscores FastVPINNs' potential for widespread application in scientific and engineering challenges, opening new avenues for practical implementations in scientific machine learning.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12063v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thivin Anandh, Divij Ghose, Himanshu Jain, Sashikumaar Ganesan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Preserving Nature's Ledger: Blockchains in Biodiversity Conservation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12086</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12086v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the contemporary era, biodiversity conservation emerges as a paramount challenge, necessitating innovative approaches to monitoring, preserving, and enhancing the natural world. This paper explores the integration of blockchain technology in biodiversity conservation, offering a novel perspective on how digital resilience can be built within ecological contexts. Blockchain, with its decentralized and immutable ledger and tokenization affordances, presents a groundbreaking solution for the accurate monitoring and tracking of environmental assets, thereby addressing the critical need for transparency and trust in conservation efforts. Unlike previous more theoretical approaches, by addressing the research question of how blockchain supports digital resilience in biodiversity conservation, this study presents a grounded framework that justifies which blockchain features are essential to decipher specific data contribution and data leveraging processes in an effort to protect our planet's biodiversity, while boosting potential economic benefits for all actors involved, from local farmers, to hardware vendors and artificial intelligence experts, to investors and regular users, volunteers and donors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12086v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.CR</category>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cs.ET</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kostas Kryptos Chalkias, Angelos Kostis, Ali Alnuaimi, Peter Knez, John Naulty, Allen Salmasi, Ryan Servatius, Rodrigo Veloso</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
