<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE</link>
    <description>cs.CE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 04:00:51 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 18 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>A waypoint based approach to visibility in performance based fire safety design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.11439</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.11439v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In performance-based fire safety design, ensuring safe egress, e.g. by visibility of safety signs, is a crucial safety goal. Compliance with the building requirements is often demonstrated by simulations of smoke spread. Numerical models like the Fire Dynamics Simulator generally compute visibility as a local quantity using the light extinction coefficient, without the consideration of the actual light path to a safety sign. Here, visibility maps are introduced, providing an approach for post-processing fire simulation data. They indicate safe areas along egress routes, with respect to visibility. At each location, the available visibility is calculated using Jin's law, as an integrated value of the extinction coefficient along the line of sight to the closest exit sign. The required visibility results from the distance between those points. Additional parameters like view angle or visual obstructions are considered. The presented method allows for temporal visibility assessment, e.g. in an ASET-RSET analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.11439v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kristian B\"orger, Alexander Belt, Lukas Arnold</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multivariate sensitivity-adaptive polynomial chaos expansion for high-dimensional surrogate modeling and uncertainty quantification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.09871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.09871v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This work develops a novel basis-adaptive method for constructing anisotropic polynomial chaos expansions of multidimensional (vector-valued, multi-output) model responses. The adaptive basis selection is based on multivariate sensitivity analysis metrics that can be estimated by post-processing the polynomial chaos expansion and results in a common anisotropic polynomial basis for the vector-valued response. This allows the application of the method to problems with up to moderately high-dimensional model inputs (in the order of tens) and up to very high-dimensional model responses (in the order of thousands). The method is applied to different engineering test cases for surrogate modeling and uncertainty quantification, producing highly accurate results with low data and computational demand.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.09871v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dimitrios Loukrezis, Eric Diehl, Herbert De Gersem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature Prediction for Stored Grain: A Multi-model Fusion Approach Based on Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07175</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07175v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Temperature fluctuations significantly affect microorganism growth and pest activities in grain pile, precise monitoring and forecasting temperature of stored grain are essential for maintaining the quality and safety of grain storage. This paper proposes a multi-model fusion approach to predict grain temperature using historical temperature data of stored grain and meteorological data from the region. Firstly, four distinct machine learning models, namely Adaboost, decision tree, extra trees, and random forest, are fine-tuned through parameter optimization to enhance their predictive capabilities respectively; Subsequently, these optimized models are fused to form different ensemble models, which are compared for predidction accuracy to obtain the optimal fusion model. In essence, the fusion process integrates the predictions of each individual model as new feature inputs into the fusion models. Furthermore, random forest is utilized to identify the key factors influencing grain temperature, providing insights into the importance of different influencing factors. The experimental results demonstrate that the proposed fusion models can achieve higher prediction accuracy and robustness compared with the single-model prediction methods. Additionally, the analysis of feature importance also offers empirical evidence for understanding the factors influencing grain temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07175v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Donghao Chen, Binkun Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>COBRAPRO: A MATLAB toolbox for Physics-based Battery Modeling and Co-simulation Parameter Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10022</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10022v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: COBRAPRO is a new open-source physics-based battery modeling software with the capability to conduct closed-loop parameter optimization using experimental data. Physics-based battery models require systematic parameter calibration to accurately predict battery behavior across different usage scenarios. While parameter calibration is essential to predict the dynamic behavior of batteries, many existing open-source DFN modeling tools lack integrated parameter identification routines. COBRAPRO addresses this gap by featuring an embedded parameter optimization framework that optimizes the model parameters by minimizing the error between the simulated and experimentally observed current-voltage data. With COBRAPRO, users can non-invasively identify unknown battery model parameters for any given battery chemistry.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10022v2</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sara Ha, Simona Onori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AAVDiff: Experimental Validation of Enhanced Viability and Diversity in Recombinant Adeno-Associated Virus (AAV) Capsids through Diffusion Generation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.10573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.10573v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Recombinant adeno-associated virus (rAAV) vectors have revolutionized gene therapy, but their broad tropism and suboptimal transduction efficiency limit their clinical applications. To overcome these limitations, researchers have focused on designing and screening capsid libraries to identify improved vectors. However, the large sequence space and limited resources present challenges in identifying viable capsid variants. In this study, we propose an end-to-end diffusion model to generate capsid sequences with enhanced viability. Using publicly available AAV2 data, we generated 38,000 diverse AAV2 viral protein (VP) sequences, and evaluated 8,000 for viral selection. The results attested the superiority of our model compared to traditional methods. Additionally, in the absence of AAV9 capsid data, apart from one wild-type sequence, we used the same model to directly generate a number of viable sequences with up to 9 mutations. we transferred the remaining 30,000 samples to the AAV9 domain. Furthermore, we conducted mutagenesis on AAV9 VP hypervariable regions VI and V, contributing to the continuous improvement of the AAV9 VP sequence. This research represents a significant advancement in the design and functional validation of rAAV vectors, offering innovative solutions to enhance specificity and transduction efficiency in gene therapy applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.10573v2</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lijun Liu, Jiali Yang, Jianfei Song, Xinglin Yang, Lele Niu, Zeqi Cai, Hui Shi, Tingjun Hou, Chang-yu Hsieh, Weiran Shen, Yafeng Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
