<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE</link>
    <description>cs.CE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 04:00:59 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 Apr 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Reduced and All-at-Once Approaches for Model Calibration and Discovery in Computational Solid Mechanics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.16980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.16980v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In the framework of solid mechanics, the task of deriving material parameters from experimental data has recently re-emerged with the progress in full-field measurement capabilities and the renewed advances of machine learning. In this context, new methods such as the virtual fields method and physics-informed neural networks have been developed as alternatives to the already established least-squares and finite element-based approaches. Moreover, model discovery problems are starting to emerge and can also be addressed in a parameter estimation framework. These developments call for a new unified perspective, which is able to cover both traditional parameter estimation methods and novel approaches in which the state variables or the model structure itself are inferred as well. Adopting concepts discussed in the inverse problems community, we distinguish between all-at-once and reduced approaches. With this general framework, we are able to structure a large portion of the literature on parameter estimation in computational mechanics - and we can identify combinations that have not yet been addressed, two of which are proposed in this paper. We also discuss statistical approaches to quantify the uncertainty related to the estimated parameters, and we propose a novel two-step procedure for identification of complex material models based on both frequentist and Bayesian principles. Finally, we illustrate and compare several of the aforementioned methods with mechanical benchmarks based on synthetic and real data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.16980v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ulrich R\"omer, Stefan Hartmann, Jendrik-Alexander Tr\"oger, David Anton, Henning Wessels, Moritz Flaschel, Laura De Lorenzis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermodynamic topology optimization for hardening materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2103.03567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2103.03567v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Topology optimization is an important basis for the design of components. Here, the optimal structure is found within a design space subject to boundary conditions. Thereby, the specific material law has a strong impact on the final design. An important kind of material behavior is hardening: then a, for instance, linear-elastic structure is not optimal if plastic deformation will be induced by the loads. Since hardening behavior has a remarkable impact on the resultant stress field, it needs to be accounted for during topology optimization. In this contribution, we present an extension of the thermodynamic topology optimization that accounts for this non-linear material behavior due to the evolution of plastic strains. For this purpose, we develop a novel surrogate model that allows to compute the plastic strain tensor corresponding to the current structure design for arbitrary hardening behavior. We show the agreement of the model with the classic plasticity model for monotonic loading. Furthermore, we demonstrate the interaction of the topology optimization for hardening material behavior results in structural changes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2103.03567v4</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Miriam Kick, Philipp Junker</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
