<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE</link>
    <description>cs.CE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 04:00:30 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Reduced order modelling of Hopf bifurcations for the Navier-Stokes equations through invariant manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26542v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This work introduces a parametric simulation-free reduced order model for incompressible flows undergoing a Hopf bifurcation, leveraging the parametrisation method for invariant manifolds. Unlike data-driven approaches, this method operates directly on the governing equations, eliminating the need for full-order simulations. The proposed model is computed at a single value of the bifurcation parameter yet remains valid over a range of values. The approach systematically constructs an invariant manifold and embedded dynamics, providing an accurate and efficient reduction of the original system. The ability to capture pre-critical steady states, the bifurcation point, and post-critical limit cycle oscillations is demonstrated by a strong agreement between the reduced order model and full order simulations, while achieving significant computational speed-up.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26542v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alessio Colombo, Alessandra Vizzaccaro, Cyril Touz\'e, Andr\'e de F. Stabile, Luc Pastur, Attilio Frangi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A fast spectral overlapping domain decomposition method with discretization-independent conditioning bounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25991v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: A domain decomposition method for the solution of general variable-coefficient elliptic partial differential equations on regular domains is introduced. The method is based on tessellating the domain into overlapping thin slabs or shells, and then explicitly forming a reduced linear system that connects the different domains. Rank-structure ('H-matrix structure') is exploited to handle the large dense blocks that arise in the reduced linear system. Importantly, the formulation used is well-conditioned, as it converges to a second kind Fredholm equation as the precision in the local solves is refined. Moreover, the dense blocks that arise are far more data-sparse than in existing formulations, leading to faster and more efficient H-matrix arithmetic. To form the reduced linear system, black-box randomized compression is used, taking full advantage of the fact that sparse direct solvers are highly efficient on the thin sub-domains. Numerical experiments demonstrate that our solver can handle oscillatory 2D and 3D problems with as many as 28 million degrees of freedom.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25991v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simon Dirckx, Anna Yesypenko, Per-Gunnar Martinsson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning to Manage Investment Portfolios beyond Simple Utility Functions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.26165</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.26165v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: While investment funds publicly disclose their objectives in broad terms, their managers optimize for complex combinations of competing goals that go beyond simple risk-return trade-offs. Traditional approaches attempt to model this through multi-objective utility functions, but face fundamental challenges in specification and parameterization. We propose a generative framework that learns latent representations of fund manager strategies without requiring explicit utility specification.
  Our approach directly models the conditional probability of a fund's portfolio weights, given stock characteristics, historical returns, previous weights, and a latent variable representing the fund's strategy. Unlike methods based on reinforcement learning or imitation learning, which require specified rewards or labeled expert objectives, our GAN-based architecture learns directly from the joint distribution of observed holdings and market data.
  We validate our framework on a dataset of 1436 U.S. equity mutual funds. The learned representations successfully capture known investment styles, such as "growth" and "value," while also revealing implicit manager objectives. For instance, we find that while many funds exhibit characteristics of Markowitz-like optimization, they do so with heterogeneous realizations for turnover, concentration, and latent factors.
  To analyze and interpret the end-to-end model, we develop a series of tests that explain the model, and we show that the benchmark's expert labeling are contained in our model's encoding in a linear interpretable way.
  Our framework provides a data-driven approach for characterizing investment strategies for applications in market simulation, strategy attribution, and regulatory oversight.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.26165v1</guid>
      <category>q-fin.PM</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1145/3768292.3770426</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Maarten P. Scholl, Mahmoud Mahfouz, Anisoara Calinescu, J. Doyne Farmer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Meshless projection model-order reduction via reference spaces for smoothed-particle hydrodynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.07830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.07830v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A model-order reduction framework for the meshless smoothed-particle hydrodynamics (SPH) method is presented. The proposed framework introduces the concept of modal reference spaces to overcome the challenges of discovering low-dimensional subspaces from unstructured, dynamic, and mixing numerical topology that occurs in SPH simulations. These reference spaces enable a low-dimensional representation of the field equations while maintaining the inherent meshless qualities of SPH. Modal reference spaces are constructed by projecting snapshot data onto a reference space where low-dimensionality of field quantities can be discovered via traditional modal decomposition techniques (e.g., the proper orthogonal decomposition (POD)). Modal quantities are mapped back to the meshless SPH space via scattered data interpolation during the online predictive stage. The proposed model-order reduction framework is cast into the meshless Galerkin POD and the Adjoint Petrov-Galerkin projection model-order reduction (PMOR) formulation. The PMORs are tested on three numerical experiments: 1) the Taylor--Green vortex; 2) the lid-driven cavity; and 3) the flow past an open cavity. Results show good agreement in reconstructed and predictive velocity fields, which showcase the ability of this framework to evolve the field equations in a low-dimensional subspace on an unstructured, dynamic, and mixing numerical topology. Results also show that the pressure field is sensitive to the projection error due to the stiff weakly-compressible assumption made in the current SPH framework, but this sensitivity can be alleviated through nonlinear approximations, such as the APG approach. The proposed meshless model-order reduction framework reports up to 90,000x dimensional compression within 10% error in quantities of interest, marking a step toward drastic cost reduction in SPH simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.07830v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Steven N. Rodriguez, Steven L. Brunton, Liam K. Magargal, Parisa Khodabakhshi, Justin W. Jaworski, Nicoleta A. Apetre, John C. Steuben, John G. Michopoulos, Athanasios Iliopoulos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surrogate-Assisted Evolutionary Optimization Based on Interpretable Convolution Network</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16386v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: When performing evolutionary optimization for computationally expensive objective, surrogate-assisted evolutionary algorithm(SAEA) is an effective approach. However, due to the limited availability of data in these scenarios, it can be challenging to create a highly accurate surrogate model, leading to reduced optimization effectiveness. To address this issue, we propose an Interpretable Convolution Network(ICN) for offline surrogate-assited evolutionary optimization. ICN retains the non-linear expression ability of traditional neural networks, while possessing the advantages of clear physical structure and the ability to incorporate prior knowledge during network parameter design and training process. We compare ICN-SAEA with tri-training method(TT-DDEA) and model-ensemble method(DDEA-SA) in several benchmark problems. Experimental results show that ICN-SAEA is better in searching optimal solution than compared algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16386v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lihong Xu, Wenxiang Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>UniField: Joint Multi-Domain Training for Universal Surface Pressure Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.24106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.24106v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Aerodynamic simulation of the surface pressure field around objects is crucial for many engineering problems. In recent years, deep neural networks have emerged as an efficient alternative to traditional, computationally expensive CFD simulations for modeling surface pressure fields. However, data scarcity remains a fundamental challenge, limiting the application of neural networks. To address this limitation, we propose to integrate aerodynamic data from multiple subfields and conduct joint training to learn more general field representations. We consolidate five different datasets covering various fields, including automobiles, trains, aircraft, and general shapes. Facing significant data differences across different domains, we propose UniField, which employs a domain-agnostic Transformer module to extract general point cloud features and customizes domain-specific flow-conditioned adapters to adapt to the flow information in different subfields. Despite the fact that aerodynamic data from different subfields are typically governed by different equations, we compare models trained jointly on all data with those trained separately on individual datasets and find that the jointly-trained model commonly demonstrates better performance. This indicates that these data complement each other to help the model learn better flow field representations. These results highlight the potential of UniField as a universal flow field representation model and lay the foundation for broader applications of neural networks in aerodynamic analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.24106v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junhong Zou, Zhenxu Sun, Yueqing Wang, Wei Qiu, Zhaoxiang Zhang, Zhen Lei, Xiangyu Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fourier Neural Operators for Two-Phase, 2D Mold-Filling Problems Related to Metal Casting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25697v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We formulate mold filling in metal casting as a 2D neural operator learning problem that maps geometry and boundary data on an unstructured mesh to time resolved flow quantities, replacing expensive transient CFD. In the proposed method, a graph based encoder aggregates local neighborhood information on the input mesh and encodes geometry and boundary data, a Fourier spectral core operates on a regular latent grid to capture global interactions across the domain, and a graph based decoder projects the latent fields to a target mesh. The model is trained to jointly predict velocity components, pressure, and liquid volume fraction over a fixed rollout horizon and generalizes across different ingate locations and process settings. On held out geometries and inlet conditions, it reproduces large scale advection and the fluid-air interface evolution with localized errors near steep gradients. The mean relative L2 error is about 5% across all fields, and inference is two to three orders of magnitude faster than conventional CFD, enabling design in the loop exploration. Ablation studies show monotonic accuracy degradation under stronger spatial subsampling of input vertices and a smoother decline under temporal subsampling. Halving the training set yields only a small increase in error. These results establish neural operators as accurate and data efficient surrogates for 2D mold filling and enable rapid optimization of gating systems in casting workflows.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25697v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Edgard Moreira Minete, Mathis Immertreu, Fabian Teichmann, Sebastian M\"uller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards Automated Quality Assurance of Patent Specifications: A Multi-Dimensional LLM Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.25402</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.25402v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Although AI drafting tools have gained prominence in patent writing, the systematic evaluation of AI-generated patent content quality represents a significant research gap. To address this gap, We propose to evaluate patents using regulatory compliance, technical coherence, and figure-reference consistency detection modules, and then generate improvement suggestions via an integration module. The framework is validated on a comprehensive dataset comprising 80 human-authored and 80 AI-generated patents from two patent drafting tools. Evaluation is performed on 10,841 total sentences, 8,924 non-template sentences, and 554 patent figures for the three detection modules respectively, achieving balanced accuracies of 99.74%, 82.12%, and 91.2% against expert annotations. Additional analysis was conducted to examine defect distributions across patent sections, technical domains, and authoring sources. Section-based analysis indicates that figure-text consistency and technical detail precision require particular attention. Mechanical Engineering and Construction show more claim-specification inconsistencies due to complex technical documentation requirements. AI-generated patents show a significant gap compared to human-authored ones. While human-authored patents primarily contain surface-level errors like typos, AI-generated patents exhibit more structural defects in figure-text alignment and cross-references.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.25402v2</guid>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuqian Chai, Chaochao Wang, Weilei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
