<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE</link>
    <description>cs.CE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 04:00:13 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerated Medicines Development using a Digital Formulator and a Self-Driving Tableting DataFactory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17411</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17411v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pharmaceutical tablet formulation and process development, traditionally a complex and multi-dimensional decision-making process, necessitates extensive experimentation and resources, often resulting in suboptimal solutions. This study presents an integrated platform for tablet formulation and manufacturing, built around a Digital Formulator and a Self-Driving Tableting DataFactory. By combining predictive modelling, optimisation algorithms, and automation, this system offers a material-to-product approach to predict and optimise critical quality attributes for different formulations, linking raw material attributes to key blend and tablet properties, such as flowability, porosity, and tensile strength. The platform leverages the Digital Formulator, an in-silico optimisation framework that employs a hybrid system of models - melding data-driven and mechanistic models - to identify optimal formulation settings for manufacturability. Optimised formulations then proceed through the self-driving Tableting DataFactory, which includes automated powder dosing, tablet compression and performance testing, followed by iterative refinement of process parameters through Bayesian optimisation methods. This approach accelerates the timeline from material characterisation to development of an in-specification tablet within 6 hours, utilising less than 5 grams of API, and manufacturing small batch sizes of up to 1,440 tablets with augmented and mixed reality enabled real-time quality control within 24 hours. Validation across multiple APIs and drug loadings underscores the platform's capacity to reliably meet target quality attributes, positioning it as a transformative solution for accelerated and resource-efficient pharmaceutical development.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17411v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Faisal Abbas, Mohammad Salehian, Peter Hou, Jonathan Moores, Jonathan Goldie, Alexandros Tsioutsios, Victor Portela, Quentin Boulay, Roland Thiolliere, Ashley Stark, Jean-Jacques Schwartz, Jerome Guerin, Andrew G. P. Maloney, Alexandru A. Moldovan, Gavin K. Reynolds, J\'er\^ome Mantanus, Catriona Clark, Paul Chapman, Alastair Florence, Daniel Markl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Scattering Matrix Synthesis for Hybrid Systems with Multiple Scatterers and Antennas Using Independent Structure Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17616</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17616v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents a unified formulation for calculating the generalized scattering matrix (GS-matrix) of hybrid systems involving multiple scatterers and antennas. The GS-matrix of the entire system is synthesized through the scattering matrices and GS-matrices of each independent component, using the addition theorem of vector spherical wavefunctions and fully matrix-based operations. Since our formulation is applicable to general antenna-scatterer hybrid systems, previous formulas for multiple scattering and antenna arrays become special cases of our approach. This also establishes our formulation as a universal domain decomposition method for analyzing the electromagnetic performance of hybrid systems. We provide numerous numerical examples to comprehensively demonstrate the capabilities and compatibility of the proposed formulation, including its potential application in studying the effects of structural rotation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17616v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenbo Shi, Shichen Liang, Jin Pan, Xin Gu, Le Zuo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Financial Wind Tunnel: A Retrieval-Augmented Market Simulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17909</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17909v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Market simulator tries to create high-quality synthetic financial data that mimics real-world market dynamics, which is crucial for model development and robust assessment. Despite continuous advancements in simulation methodologies, market fluctuations vary in terms of scale and sources, but existing frameworks often excel in only specific tasks. To address this challenge, we propose Financial Wind Tunnel (FWT), a retrieval-augmented market simulator designed to generate controllable, reasonable, and adaptable market dynamics for model testing. FWT offers a more comprehensive and systematic generative capability across different data frequencies. By leveraging a retrieval method to discover cross-sectional information as the augmented condition, our diffusion-based simulator seamlessly integrates both macro- and micro-level market patterns. Furthermore, our framework allows the simulation to be controlled with wide applicability, including causal generation through "what-if" prompts or unprecedented cross-market trend synthesis. Additionally, we develop an automated optimizer for downstream quantitative models, using stress testing of simulated scenarios via FWT to enhance returns while controlling risks. Experimental results demonstrate that our approach enables the generalizable and reliable market simulation, significantly improve the performance and adaptability of downstream models, particularly in highly complex and volatile market conditions. Our code and data sample is available at https://anonymous.4open.science/r/fwt_-E852</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17909v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-fin.CP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bokai Cao, Xueyuan Lin, Yiyan Qi, Chengjin Xu, Cehao Yang, Jian Guo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>(G)I-DLE: Generative Inference via Distribution-preserving Logit Exclusion with KL Divergence Minimization for Constrained Decoding</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18050v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We propose (G)I-DLE, a new approach to constrained decoding that leverages KL divergence minimization to preserve the intrinsic conditional probability distribution of autoregressive language models while excluding undesirable tokens. Unlike conventional methods that naively set banned tokens' logits to $-\infty$, which can distort the conversion from raw logits to posterior probabilities and increase output variance, (G)I-DLE re-normalizes the allowed token probabilities to minimize such distortion. We validate our method on the K2-Eval dataset, specifically designed to assess Korean language fluency, logical reasoning, and cultural appropriateness. Experimental results on Qwen2.5 models (ranging from 1.5B to 14B) demonstrate that G-IDLE not only boosts mean evaluation scores but also substantially reduces the variance of output quality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18050v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hanwool Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Power of Small LLMs in Geometry Generation for Physical Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18178</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18178v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Engineers widely rely on simulation platforms like COMSOL or ANSYS to model and optimise processes. However, setting up such simulations requires expertise in defining geometry, generating meshes, establishing boundary conditions, and configuring solvers. This research aims to simplify this process by enabling engineers to describe their setup in plain language, allowing a Large Language Model (LLM) to generate the necessary input files for their specific application. This novel approach allows establishing a direct link between natural language and complex engineering tasks. Building on previous work that evaluated various LLMs for generating input files across simple and complex geometries, this study demonstrates that small LLMs - specifically, Phi-3 Mini and Qwen-2.5 1.5B - can be fine-tuned to generate precise engineering geometries in GMSH format. Through Low-Rank Adaptation (LoRA), we curated a dataset of 480 instruction-output pairs encompassing simple shapes (squares, rectangles, circles, and half circles) and more complex structures (I-beams, cylindrical pipes, and bent pipes). The fine-tuned models produced high-fidelity outputs, handling routine geometry generation with minimal intervention. While challenges remain with geometries involving combinations of multiple bodies, this study demonstrates that fine-tuned small models can outperform larger models like GPT-4o in specialised tasks, offering a precise and resource-efficient alternative for engineering applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18178v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ossama Shafiq, Bahman Ghiassi, Alessio Alexiadis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Physics Inverse Design of Varifocal Optical Devices using Data-Driven Surrogates and Differential Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18911v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Designing a new varifocal architecture in AR glasses poses significant challenges due to the complex interplay of multiple physics disciplines, including innovated piezo-electric material, solid mechanics, electrostatics, and optics. Traditional design methods, which treat each physics separately, are insufficient for this problem as they fail to establish the intricate relationships among design parameters in such a large and sensitive space, leading to suboptimal solutions. To address this challenge, we propose a novel design pipeline, mPhDBBs (multi-Physics Differential Building Blocks), that integrates these diverse physics through a graph neural network-based surrogate model and a differentiable ray tracing model. A hybrid optimization method combining evolutionary and gradient approaches is employed to efficiently determine superior design variables that achieve desired optical objectives, such as focal length and focusing quality. Our results demonstrate the effectiveness of mPhDBBs, achieving high accuracy with minimal training data and computational resources, resulting in a speedup of at least 1000 times compared to non-gradient-based methods. This work offers a promising paradigm shift in product design, enabling rapid and accurate optimization of complex multi-physics systems, and demonstrates its adaptability to other inverse design problems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18911v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zeqing Jin, Zhaocheng Liu, Nagi Elabbasi, Zachary Ulissi, Grace X. Gu, Zhaoyu Nie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intanify AI Platform: Embedded AI for Automated IP Audit and Due Diligence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17374</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17374v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this paper we introduce a Platform created in order to support SMEs' endeavor to extract value from their intangible assets effectively. To implement the Platform, we developed five knowledge bases using a knowledge-based ex-pert system shell that contain knowledge from intangible as-set consultants, patent attorneys and due diligence lawyers. In order to operationalize the knowledge bases, we developed a "Rosetta Stone", an interpreter unit for the knowledge bases outside the shell and embedded in the plat-form. Building on the initial knowledge bases we have created a system of red flags, risk scoring, and valuation with the involvement of the same experts; these additional systems work upon the initial knowledge bases and therefore they can be regarded as meta-knowledge-representations that take the form of second-order knowledge graphs. All this clever technology is dressed up in an easy-to-handle graphical user interface that we will showcase at the conference. The initial platform was finished mid-2024; therefore, it qualifies as an "emerging application of AI" and "deployable AI", while development continues. The two firms that provided experts for developing the knowledge bases obtained a white-label version of the product (i.e. it runs under their own brand "powered by Intanify"), and there are two completed cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17374v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Dorfler, V., Dryden, D., &amp; Lee, V. (2025, 25 February - 4 March 2025). Intanify AI Platform: Embedded AI for Automated IP Audit and Due Diligence AAAI 2025: The 39th Annual AAAI Conference on Artificial Intelligence, Philadelphia, PA</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Viktor Dorfler, Dylan Dryden, Viet Lee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Adjoint Sensitivities for the Optimization of Nonlinear Structural Dynamics via Spectral Submanifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17431v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work presents an optimization framework for tailoring the nonlinear dynamic response of lightly damped mechanical systems using Spectral Submanifold (SSM) reduction. We derive the SSM-based backbone curve and its sensitivity with respect to parameters up to arbitrary polynomial orders, enabling efficient and accurate optimization of the nonlinear frequency-amplitude relation. We use the adjoint method to derive sensitivity expressions, which drastically reduces the computational cost compared to direct differentiation as the number of parameters increases. An important feature of this framework is the automatic adjustment of the expansion order of SSM-based ROMs using user-defined error tolerances during the optimization process. We demonstrate the effectiveness of the approach in optimizing the nonlinear response over several numerical examples of mechanical systems. Hence, the proposed framework extends the applicability of SSM-based optimization methods to practical engineering problems, offering a robust tool for the design and optimization of nonlinear mechanical structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17431v1</guid>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matteo Pozzi, Jacopo Marconi, Shobhit Jain, Mingwu Li, Francesco Braghin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating and enhancing thermodynamic simulations of electrochemical interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.17870</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.17870v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electrochemical interfaces are crucial in catalysis, energy storage, and corrosion, where their stability and reactivity depend on complex interactions between the electrode, adsorbates, and electrolyte. Predicting stable surface structures remains challenging, as traditional surface Pourbaix diagrams tend to either rely on expert knowledge or costly $\textit{ab initio}$ sampling, and neglect thermodynamic equilibration with the environment. Machine learning (ML) potentials can accelerate static modeling but often overlook dynamic surface transformations. Here, we extend the Virtual Surface Site Relaxation-Monte Carlo (VSSR-MC) method to autonomously sample surface reconstructions modeled under aqueous electrochemical conditions. Through fine-tuning foundational ML force fields, we accurately and efficiently predict surface energetics, recovering known Pt(111) phases and revealing new LaMnO$_\mathrm{3}$(001) surface reconstructions. By explicitly accounting for bulk-electrolyte equilibria, our framework enhances electrochemical stability predictions, offering a scalable approach to understanding and designing materials for electrochemical applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.17870v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaochen Du, Mengren Liu, Jiayu Peng, Hoje Chun, Alexander Hoffman, Bilge Yildiz, Lin Li, Martin Z. Bazant, Rafael G\'omez-Bombarelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strategic Prompt Pricing for AIGC Services: A User-Centric Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18168</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18168v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The rapid growth of AI-generated content (AIGC) services has created an urgent need for effective prompt pricing strategies, yet current approaches overlook users' strategic two-step decision-making process in selecting and utilizing generative AI models. This oversight creates two key technical challenges: quantifying the relationship between user prompt capabilities and generation outcomes, and optimizing platform payoff while accounting for heterogeneous user behaviors. We address these challenges by introducing prompt ambiguity, a theoretical framework that captures users' varying abilities in prompt engineering, and developing an Optimal Prompt Pricing (OPP) algorithm. Our analysis reveals a counterintuitive insight: users with higher prompt ambiguity (i.e., lower capability) exhibit non-monotonic prompt usage patterns, first increasing then decreasing with ambiguity levels, reflecting complex changes in marginal utility. Experimental evaluation using a character-level GPT-like model demonstrates that our OPP algorithm achieves up to 31.72% improvement in platform payoff compared to existing pricing mechanisms, validating the importance of user-centric prompt pricing in AIGC services.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18168v1</guid>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiang Li, Bing Luo, Jianwei Huang, Yuan Luo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DeepFund: Will LLM be Professional at Fund Investment? A Live Arena Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18313</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18313v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large Language Models (LLMs) have demonstrated impressive capabilities across various domains, but their effectiveness in financial decision making, particularly in fund investment, remains inadequately evaluated. Current benchmarks primarily assess LLMs understanding of financial documents rather than their ability to manage assets or analyze trading opportunities in dynamic market conditions. A critical limitation in existing evaluation methodologies is the backtesting approach, which suffers from information leakage when LLMs are evaluated on historical data they may have encountered during pretraining. This paper introduces DeepFund, a comprehensive platform for evaluating LLM based trading strategies in a simulated live environment. Our approach implements a multi agent framework where LLMs serve as both analysts and managers, creating a realistic simulation of investment decision making. The platform employs a forward testing methodology that mitigates information leakage by evaluating models on market data released after their training cutoff dates. We provide a web interface that visualizes model performance across different market conditions and investment parameters, enabling detailed comparative analysis. Through DeepFund, we aim to provide a more accurate and fair assessment of LLMs capabilities in fund investment, offering insights into their potential real world applications in financial markets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18313v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changlun Li, Yao Shi, Yuyu Luo, Nan Tang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Differentiable Simulator for Electrically Reconfigurable Electromagnetic Structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18479</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18479v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces a novel CUDA-enabled PyTorch-based framework designed for the gradient-based optimization of such reconfigurable electromagnetic structures with electrically tunable parameters. Traditional optimization techniques for these structures often rely on non-gradient-based methods, limiting efficiency and flexibility. Our framework leverages automatic differentiation, facilitating the application of gradient-based optimization methods. This approach is particularly advantageous for embedding within deep learning frameworks, enabling sophisticated optimization strategies.
  We demonstrate the framework's effectiveness through comprehensive simulations involving resonant structures with tunable parameters. Key contributions include the efficient solution of the inverse problem. The framework's performance is validated using three different resonant structures: a single-loop copper wire (Unit-Cell) as well as an 8x1 and an 8x8 array of resonant unit cells with multiple inductively coupled unit cells (1d and 2d Metasurfaces). Results show precise in-silico control over the magnetic field's component normal to the surface of each resonant structure, achieving desired field strengths with minimal error. The proposed framework is compatible with existing simulation software.
  This PyTorch-based framework sets the stage for advanced electromagnetic control strategies for resonant structures with application in e.g. MRI, providing a robust platform for further exploration and innovation in the design and optimization of resonant electromagnetic structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18479v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Johannes M\"uller, Dennis Philipp, Matthias G\"unther</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A locking-free isogeometric thin shell formulation based on higher order accurate diagonalized strain projection via approximate dual splines</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16685v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present a novel isogeometric discretization approach for the Kirchhoff-Love shell formulation based on the Hellinger-Reissner variational principle. For mitigating membrane locking, we discretize the independent strains with spline basis functions that are one degree lower than those used for the displacements. To enable computationally efficient condensation of the independent strains, we first discretize the variations of the independent strains with approximate dual splines to obtain a projection matrix that is close to a diagonal matrix. We then diagonalize this strain projection matrix via row-sum lumping. Due to this diagonalization, the static condensation of the independent strain fields becomes computationally inexpensive, as no matrix needs to be inverted. At the same time, our approach maintains higher-order accuracy at optimal rates of convergence. We illustrate the numerical properties and the performance of our approach through numerical benchmarks, including a curved Euler-Bernoulli beam and the examples of the shell obstacle course.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16685v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thi-Hoa Nguyen, Ren\'e R. Hiemstra, Dominik Schillinger</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active Learning for Neural PDE Solvers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.01536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.01536v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Solving partial differential equations (PDEs) is a fundamental problem in science and engineering. While neural PDE solvers can be more efficient than established numerical solvers, they often require large amounts of training data that is costly to obtain. Active learning (AL) could help surrogate models reach the same accuracy with smaller training sets by querying classical solvers with more informative initial conditions and PDE parameters. While AL is more common in other domains, it has yet to be studied extensively for neural PDE solvers. To bridge this gap, we introduce AL4PDE, a modular and extensible active learning benchmark. It provides multiple parametric PDEs and state-of-the-art surrogate models for the solver-in-the-loop setting, enabling the evaluation of existing and the development of new AL methods for neural PDE solving. We use the benchmark to evaluate batch active learning algorithms such as uncertainty- and feature-based methods. We show that AL reduces the average error by up to 71% compared to random sampling and significantly reduces worst-case errors. Moreover, AL generates similar datasets across repeated runs, with consistent distributions over the PDE parameters and initial conditions. The acquired datasets are reusable, providing benefits for surrogate models not involved in the data generation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.01536v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Musekamp, Marimuthu Kalimuthu, David Holzm\"uller, Makoto Takamoto, Mathias Niepert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leveraging Multi-modal Representations to Predict Protein Melting Temperatures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.04526</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.04526v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Accurately predicting protein melting temperature changes (Delta Tm) is fundamental for assessing protein stability and guiding protein engineering. Leveraging multi-modal protein representations has shown great promise in capturing the complex relationships among protein sequences, structures, and functions. In this study, we develop models based on powerful protein language models, including ESM-2, ESM-3 and AlphaFold, using various feature extraction methods to enhance prediction accuracy. By utilizing the ESM-3 model, we achieve a new state-of-the-art performance on the s571 test dataset, obtaining a Pearson correlation coefficient (PCC) of 0.50. Furthermore, we conduct a fair evaluation to compare the performance of different protein language models in the Delta Tm prediction task. Our results demonstrate that integrating multi-modal protein representations could advance the prediction of protein melting temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.04526v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daiheng Zhang, Yan Zeng, Xinyu Hong, Jinbo Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
