<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE</link>
    <description>cs.CE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 04:00:48 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Representative Volume Element: Existence and Extent in Cracked Heterogeneous Medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08320v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Acknowledging the ever-increasing demand for composites in the engineering industry, this paper focuses on the failure of composites at the microscale and augmenting the use of multiscale modelling techniques to make them better for various applications. This work aims to increase the representativeness of the volume element by attenuating the mesh and size sensitivities in representative volume element (RVE) modelling. A technique to alleviate mesh sensitivity in RVE modelling is proposed, which equalises the fracture energy observed from computational analysis with the real phenomenon, thereby keeping the response independent of the bandwidth of strain localisation. Based on the hypothesis that ensuring periodicity of strain, in addition to displacement periodicity across the domain boundary and supplementing the capability of periodic boundary conditions (PBCs) to attenuate the size dependency in RVE modelling, a set of modified PBCs (MPBCs) are formulated. One thousand two hundred RVE samples falling into combinations of five fibre volume fractions and four RVE sizes are analysed under transverse loading, and the ability of MPBCs to attenuate the effect of RVE size on the precision of material response, particularly in the inelastic regime, is verified. This work also focuses on various factors affecting damage initiation in 2D composite RVEs. The arrangement of a pair of fibres with their members placed close to each other, such that the angle between the direction of loading and an imaginary line drawn between their centres is less, is observed to make the region between them more favourable to damage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08320v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.mechmat.2023.104748</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Sankar R, H. and Singh, H. (2023). Representative volume element: Existence and extent in cracked heterogeneous medium. Mechanics of Materials, 184, 104748</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hari Sankar R, Harpreet Singha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic Collusion of Pricing and Advertising on E-commerce Platforms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08325</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08325v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Online sellers have been adopting AI learning algorithms to automatically make product pricing and advertising decisions on e-commerce platforms. When sellers compete using such algorithms, one concern is that of tacit collusion - the algorithms learn to coordinate on higher than competitive. We empirically investigate whether these concerns are valid when sellers make pricing and advertising decisions together, i.e., two-dimensional decisions. Our empirical strategy is to analyze competition with multi-agent reinforcement learning, which we calibrate to a large-scale dataset collected from Amazon.com products. Our first contribution is to find conditions under which learning algorithms can facilitate win-win-win outcomes that are beneficial for consumers, sellers, and even the platform, when consumers have high search costs. In these cases the algorithms learn to coordinate on prices that are lower than competitive prices. The intuition is that the algorithms learn to coordinate on lower advertising bids, which lower advertising costs, leading to lower prices. Our second contribution is an analysis of a large-scale, high-frequency keyword-product dataset for more than 2 million products on Amazon.com. Our estimates of consumer search costs show a wide range of costs for different product keywords. We generate an algorithm usage and find a negative interaction between the estimated consumer search costs and the algorithm usage index, providing empirical evidence of beneficial collusion. Finally, we analyze the platform's strategic response. We find that reserve price adjustments will not increase profits for the platform, but commission adjustments will. Our analyses help alleviate some worries about the potentially harmful effects of competing learning algorithms, and can help sellers, platforms and policymakers to decide on whether to adopt or regulate such algorithms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08325v1</guid>
      <category>econ.GN</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.GT</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>q-fin.EC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hangcheng Zhao, Ron Berman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Language Models Can Understand Spectra: A Multimodal Model for Molecular Structure Elucidation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08441v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Structure elucidation is a fundamental technique for understanding the microscopic composition of matter and is widely applied across various disciplines in the natural sciences and engineering. However, existing methods often rely heavily on prior databases or known structural information, making it difficult to resolve unknown structures. In addition, complex structures typically require the joint analysis of multiple spectroscopic modalities. This process heavily depends on expert domain knowledge and is often accompanied by high costs in terms of both time and instrumentation. To address these challenges, we propose SpectraLLM, the first large language model designed to support multi-modal spectroscopic joint reasoning. SpectraLLM is capable of processing either single or multiple spectroscopic inputs and performing end-to-end structure elucidation. By integrating continuous and discrete spectroscopic modalities into a shared semantic space, SpectraLLM learns to uncover substructural patterns that are consistent and complementary across spectra, enabling precise molecular structure elucidation. We pretrain and fine-tune SpectraLLM in the domain of small molecules, and evaluate it on six standardized, publicly available chemical datasets. The model achieves state-of-the-art performance, significantly outperforming existing approaches trained on single modalities. Notably, SpectraLLM demonstrates strong robustness and generalization even for single-spectrum inference, while its multi-modal reasoning capability further improves the accuracy of structural prediction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08441v1</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yunyue Su, Jiahui Chen, Zao Jiang, Zhenyi Zhong, Liang Wang, Qiang Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Projection-based multifidelity linear regression for data-scarce applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.08517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.08517v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Surrogate modeling for systems with high-dimensional quantities of interest remains challenging, particularly when training data are costly to acquire. This work develops multifidelity methods for multiple-input multiple-output linear regression targeting data-limited applications with high-dimensional outputs. Multifidelity methods integrate many inexpensive low-fidelity model evaluations with limited, costly high-fidelity evaluations. We introduce two projection-based multifidelity linear regression approaches that leverage principal component basis vectors for dimensionality reduction and combine multifidelity data through: (i) a direct data augmentation using low-fidelity data, and (ii) a data augmentation incorporating explicit linear corrections between low-fidelity and high-fidelity data. The data augmentation approaches combine high-fidelity and low-fidelity data into a unified training set and train the linear regression model through weighted least squares with fidelity-specific weights. Various weighting schemes and their impact on regression accuracy are explored. The proposed multifidelity linear regression methods are demonstrated on approximating the surface pressure field of a hypersonic vehicle in flight. In a low-data regime of no more than ten high-fidelity samples, multifidelity linear regression achieves approximately 3% - 12% improvement in median accuracy compared to single-fidelity methods with comparable computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.08517v1</guid>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vignesh Sella, Julie Pham, Karen Willcox, Anirban Chaudhuri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Out of the Past: An AI-Enabled Pipeline for Traffic Simulation from Noisy, Multimodal Detector Data and Stakeholder Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.21349</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.21349v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: How can a traffic simulation be designed to faithfully reflect real-world traffic conditions? One crucial step is modeling the volume of traffic demand. But past demand modeling approaches have relied on unrealistic or suboptimal heuristics, and they have failed to adequately account for the effects of noisy and multimodal data on simulation outcomes. In this work, we integrate advances in AI to construct a three-step, end-to-end pipeline for systematically modeling traffic demand from detector data: computer vision for vehicle counting from noisy camera footage, combinatorial optimization for vehicle route generation from multimodal data, and large language models for iterative simulation refinement from natural language feedback. Using a road network from Strongsville, Ohio as a testbed, we show that our pipeline accurately captures the city's traffic patterns in a granular simulation. Beyond Strongsville, incorporating noise and multimodality makes our framework generalizable to municipalities with different levels of data and infrastructure availability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.21349v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rex Chen, Karen Wu, John McCartney, Norman Sadeh, Fei Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>PC-SRGAN: Physically Consistent Super-Resolution Generative Adversarial Network for General Transient Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06502v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Machine Learning, particularly Generative Adversarial Networks (GANs), has revolutionised Super-Resolution (SR). However, generated images often lack physical meaningfulness, which is essential for scientific applications. Our approach, PC-SRGAN, enhances image resolution while ensuring physical consistency for interpretable simulations. PC-SRGAN significantly improves both the Peak Signal-to-Noise Ratio and the Structural Similarity Index Measure compared to conventional SR methods, even with limited training data (e.g., only 13% of training data is required to achieve performance similar to SRGAN). Beyond SR, PC-SRGAN augments physically meaningful machine learning, incorporating numerically justified time integrators and advanced quality metrics. These advancements promise reliable and causal machine-learning models in scientific domains. A significant advantage of PC-SRGAN over conventional SR techniques is its physical consistency, which makes it a viable surrogate model for time-dependent problems. PC-SRGAN advances scientific machine learning by improving accuracy and efficiency, enhancing process understanding, and broadening applications to scientific research. We publicly release the complete source code of PC-SRGAN and all experiments at https://github.com/hasan-rakibul/PC-SRGAN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06502v3</guid>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1109/TPAMI.2025.3596647</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence (2025) 1-8</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Md Rakibul Hasan, Pouria Behnoudfar, Dan MacKinlay, Thomas Poulet</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
