<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE</link>
    <description>cs.CE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 04:01:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Improving Unsupervised Task-driven Models of Ventral Visual Stream via Relative Position Predictivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08316</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08316v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Based on the concept that ventral visual stream (VVS) mainly functions for object recognition, current unsupervised task-driven methods model VVS by contrastive learning, and have achieved good brain similarity. However, we believe functions of VVS extend beyond just object recognition. In this paper, we introduce an additional function involving VVS, named relative position (RP) prediction. We first theoretically explain contrastive learning may be unable to yield the model capability of RP prediction. Motivated by this, we subsequently integrate RP learning with contrastive learning, and propose a new unsupervised task-driven method to model VVS, which is more inline with biological reality. We conduct extensive experiments, demonstrating that: (i) our method significantly improves downstream performance of object recognition while enhancing RP predictivity; (ii) RP predictivity generally improves the model brain similarity. Our results provide strong evidence for the involvement of VVS in location perception (especially RP prediction) from a computational perspective.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08316v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dazhong Rong, Hao Dong, Xing Gao, Jiyu Wei, Di Hong, Yaoyao Hao, Qinming He, Yueming Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topology and geometry optimization of grid-shells under self-weight loading</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08645</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08645v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This manuscript presents an approach for simultaneously optimizing the connectivity and elevation of grid-shell structures acting in pure compression (or pure tension) under the combined effects of a prescribed external loading and the design-dependent self-weight of the structure itself. The method derived herein involves solving a second-order cone optimization problem, thereby ensuring convexity and obtaining globally optimal results for a given discretization of the design domain. Several numerical examples are presented, illustrating characteristics of this class of optimal structures. It is found that, as self-weight becomes more significant, both the optimal topology and the optimal elevation profile of the structure change, highlighting the importance of optimizing both topology and geometry simultaneously from the earliest stages of design. It is shown that this approach can obtain solutions with greater accuracy and several orders of magnitude more quickly than a standard 3D layout/truss topology optimization approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08645v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Helen E. Fairclough, Karol Bolbotowski, Linwei He, Andrew Liew, Matthew Gilbert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Value of Information-based assessment of strain-based thickness loss monitoring in ship hull structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07427</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07427v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent advances in Structural Health Monitoring (SHM) have attracted industry interest, yet real-world applications, such as in ship structures remain scarce. Despite SHM's potential to optimise maintenance, its adoption in ships is limited due to the lack of clearly quantifiable benefits for hull maintenance. This study employs a Bayesian pre-posterior decision analysis to quantify the value of information (VoI) from SHM systems monitoring corrosion-induced thickness loss (CITL) in ship hulls, in a first-of-its-kind analysis for ship structures. We define decision-making consequence cost functions based on exceedance probabilities relative to a target CITL threshold, which can be set by the decision-maker. This introduces a practical aspect to our framework, that enables implicitly modelling the decision-maker's risk perception. We apply this framework to a large-scale, high-fidelity numerical model of a commercial vessel and examine the relative benefits of different CITL monitoring strategies, including strain-based SHM and traditional on-site inspections.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07427v1</guid>
      <category>stat.AP</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas E. Silionis, Konstantinos N. Anyfantis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>QUEST: QUantum-Enhanced Shared Transportation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08074</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08074v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce ``Windbreaking-as-a-Service'' (WaaS) as an innovative approach to shared transportation in which larger ``windbreaker'' vehicles provide aerodynamic shelter for ``windsurfer'' vehicles, thereby reducing drag and fuel consumption. As a computational framework to solve the large-scale matching and assignment problems that arise in WaaS, we present \textbf{QUEST} (Quantum-Enhanced Shared Transportation). Specifically, we formulate the pairing of windbreakers and windsurfers -- subject to timing, speed, and vehicle-class constraints -- as a mixed-integer quadratic problem (MIQP). Focusing on a single-segment prototype, we verify the solution classically via the Hungarian Algorithm, a Gurobi-based solver, and brute-force enumeration of binary vectors. We then encode the problem as a Quadratic Unconstrained Binary Optimization (QUBO) and map it to an Ising Hamiltonian, enabling the use of the Quantum Approximate Optimization Algorithm (QAOA) and other quantum and classical annealing technologies. Our quantum implementation successfully recovers the optimal assignment identified by the classical methods, confirming the soundness of the QUEST pipeline for a controlled prototype. While QAOA and other quantum heuristics do not guarantee a resolution of the fundamental complexity barriers, this study illustrates how the WaaS problem can be systematically translated into a quantum-ready model. It also lays the groundwork for addressing multi-segment scenarios and potentially leveraging quantum advantage for large-scale shared-transportation instances.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08074v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.DM</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chinonso Onah, Neel Miscasci, Carsten Othmer, Kristel Michielsen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sensitivity-Constrained Fourier Neural Operators for Forward and Inverse Problems in Parametric Differential Equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08740v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Parametric differential equations of the form du/dt = f(u, x, t, p) are fundamental in science and engineering. While deep learning frameworks such as the Fourier Neural Operator (FNO) can efficiently approximate solutions, they struggle with inverse problems, sensitivity estimation (du/dp), and concept drift. We address these limitations by introducing a sensitivity-based regularization strategy, called Sensitivity-Constrained Fourier Neural Operators (SC-FNO). SC-FNO achieves high accuracy in predicting solution paths and consistently outperforms standard FNO and FNO with physics-informed regularization. It improves performance in parameter inversion tasks, scales to high-dimensional parameter spaces (tested with up to 82 parameters), and reduces both data and training requirements. These gains are achieved with a modest increase in training time (30% to 130% per epoch) and generalize across various types of differential equations and neural operators. Code and selected experiments are available at: https://github.com/AMBehroozi/SC_Neural_Operators</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08740v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdolmehdi Behroozi, Chaopeng Shen and, Daniel Kifer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Addressing the Current Challenges of Quantum Machine Learning through Multi-Chip Ensembles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.08782</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.08782v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum Machine Learning (QML) holds significant promise for solving computational challenges across diverse domains. However, its practical deployment is constrained by the limitations of noisy intermediate-scale quantum (NISQ) devices, including noise, limited scalability, and trainability issues in variational quantum circuits (VQCs). We introduce the multi-chip ensemble VQC framework, which partitions high-dimensional computations across smaller quantum chips to enhance scalability, trainability, and noise resilience. We show that this approach mitigates barren plateaus, reduces quantum error bias and variance, and maintains robust generalization through controlled entanglement. Designed to align with current and emerging quantum hardware, the framework demonstrates strong potential for enabling scalable QML on near-term devices, as validated by experiments on standard benchmark datasets (MNIST, FashionMNIST, CIFAR-10) and real world dataset (PhysioNet EEG).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.08782v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junghoon Justin Park, Jiook Cha, Samuel Yen-Chi Chen, Huan-Hsin Tseng, Shinjae Yoo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A thermoelastic plate model for shot peen forming metal panels based on effective torque</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.05236</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.05236v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A common technique used in factories to shape metal panels is shot peen forming. The impacts between the hard steel shot and the softer metal of the panel cause localized plastic deformation used to improve the fatigue properties of the material's surface. The residual stress distribution imparted by impacts also results in bending, which suggests that a torque is associated with it. In this paper, we model shot peen forming as the application of spatially varying torques to a Kirchhoff plate, opting to use the language of thermoelasticity in order to introduce these torque distributions. First, we derive the governing equations for the thermoelastic thin plate model and show that only a torque-type resultant of the temperature distribution shows up in the bending equation. Next, to calibrate from the shot peen operation an empirical effective torque parameter used in the thermoelastic model, a simple and non-invasive test is devised. This test relies only on measuring the maximum displacement of a uniformly shot peened plate as opposed to characterizing the residual stress distribution. After discussing how to handle the unconventional fully-free boundary conditions germane for peened plates, we introduce an approach to solving the inverse problem whereby the peening distribution required to obtain a specified plate contour can be obtained. Given the non-unique relationship between peening distributions and the displacement at discrete points, we explore a regularization of the inverse problem which gives rise to shot peen distributions that match the capabilities of equipment in the factory. In order to validate our proposed model, an experiment with quantified uncertainty is designed and carried out which investigates the agreement between the predictions of the calibrated model and real shot peen forming operations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.05236v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Conor Rowan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Decoding Futures Price Dynamics: A Regularized Sparse Autoencoder for Interpretable Multi-Horizon Forecasting and Factor Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.06795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.06795v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Commodity price volatility creates economic challenges, necessitating accurate multi-horizon forecasting. Predicting prices for commodities like copper and crude oil is complicated by diverse interacting factors (macroeconomic, supply/demand, geopolitical, etc.). Current models often lack transparency, limiting strategic use. This paper presents a Regularized Sparse Autoencoder (RSAE), a deep learning framework for simultaneous multi-horizon commodity price prediction and discovery of interpretable latent market drivers. The RSAE forecasts prices at multiple horizons (e.g., 1-day, 1-week, 1-month) using multivariate time series. Crucially, L1 regularization ($\|\mathbf{z}\|_1$) on its latent vector $\mathbf{z}$ enforces sparsity, promoting parsimonious explanations of market dynamics through learned factors representing underlying drivers (e.g., demand, supply shocks). Drawing from energy-based models and sparse coding, the RSAE optimizes predictive accuracy while learning sparse representations. Evaluated on historical Copper and Crude Oil data with numerous indicators, our findings indicate the RSAE offers competitive multi-horizon forecasting accuracy and data-driven insights into price dynamics via its interpretable latent space, a key advantage over traditional black-box approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.06795v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhijit Gupta</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
