<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE</link>
    <description>cs.CE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 Oct 2025 01:48:29 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Error bounded compression for weather and climate applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22265</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22265v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As the resolution of weather and climate simulations increases, the amount of data produced is growing rapidly from hundreds of terabytes to tens of petabytes. The huge size becomes a limiting factor for broader adoption, and its fast growth rate will soon exhaust all the available storage devices. To address these issues, we present EBCC (Error Bounded Climate-data Compressor). It follows a two-layer approach: a base compression layer using JPEG2000 to capture the bulk of the data with a high compression ratio, and a residual compression layer using wavelet transform and SPIHT encoding to efficiently eliminate long-tail extreme errors introduced by the base compression layer. It incorporates a feedback rate-control mechanism for both layers that adjusts compression ratios to achieve the specified maximum error target. We evaluate EBCC alongside other established compression methods on benchmarks related to weather and climate science including error statistics, a case study on primitive and derived variables near a hurricane, evaluation of the closure of the global energy budget, and a Lagrangian air parcel trajectory simulation. This is the first time that trajectory simulation is used to benchmark compression methods. Our method concentrates most errors near zero, while others tend to distribute errors uniformly within the error bound. EBCC outperforms other methods in the benchmarks at relative error targets ranging from 0.1% to 10% and achieves compression ratios from 15x to more than 300x. In the energy budget closure and Lagrangian trajectory benchmarks, it can achieve more than 100x compression while keeping errors within natural variability derived from ERA5 uncertainty members. This verifies the effectiveness of EBCC in creating heavily compressed weather and climate datasets suitable for downstream applications. The source code of EBCC is available in github.com/spcl/EBCC.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22265v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Langwen Huang, Luigi Fusco, Florian Scheidl, Jan Zibell, Michael Armand Sprenger, Sebastian Schemm, Torsten Hoefler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Smart Sensor Placement: A Correlation-Aware Attribution Framework (CAAF) for Real-world Data Modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22517</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22517v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Optimal sensor placement (OSP) is critical for efficient, accurate monitoring, control, and inference in complex real-world systems. We propose a machine-learning-based feature attribution framework to identify OSP for the prediction of quantities of interest. Feature attribution quantifies input contributions to a model's output; however, it struggles with highly correlated input data often encountered in real-world applications. To address this, we propose a Correlation-Aware Attribution Framework (CAAF), which introduces a clustering step before performing feature attribution to reduce redundancy and enhance generalizability. We first illustrate the core principles of the proposed framework through a series of validation cases, then demonstrate its effectiveness in real-world dynamical systems, such as structural health monitoring, airfoil lift prediction, and wall-normal velocity estimation for turbulent channel flow. The results show that the CAAF outperforms alternative approaches that typically struggle due to the presence of nonlinear dynamics, chaotic behavior, and multi-scale interactions, and enables the effective application of feature attribution for identifying OSP in real-world environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22517v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sze Chai Leung, Di Zhou, H. Jane Bae</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Capsule Network-Based Multimodal Fusion for Mortgage Risk Assessment from Unstructured Data Sources</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22987</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22987v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mortgage risk assessment traditionally relies on structured financial data, which is often proprietary, confidential, and costly. In this study, we propose a novel multimodal deep learning framework that uses cost-free, publicly available, unstructured data sources, including textual information, images, and sentiment scores, to generate credit scores that approximate commercial scorecards. Our framework adopts a two-phase approach. In the unimodal phase, we identify the best-performing models for each modality, i.e. BERT for text, VGG for image data, and a multilayer perceptron for sentiment-based features. In the fusion phase, we introduce the capsule-based fusion network (FusionCapsNet), a novel fusion strategy inspired by capsule networks, but fundamentally redesigned for multimodal integration. Unlike standard capsule networks, our method adapts a specific mechanism in capsule networks to each modality and restructures the fusion process to preserve spatial, contextual, and modality-specific information. It also enables adaptive weighting so that stronger modalities dominate without ignoring complementary signals.
  Our framework incorporates sentiment analysis across distinct news categories to capture borrower and market dynamics and employs GradCAM-based visualizations as an interpretability tool. These components are designed features of the framework, while our results later demonstrate that they effectively enrich contextual understanding and highlight the influential factors driving mortgage risk predictions. Our results show that our multimodal FusionCapsNet framework not only exceeds individual unimodal models but also outperforms benchmark fusion strategies such as addition, concatenation, and cross attention in terms of AUC, partial AUC, and F1 score, demonstrating clear gains in both predictive accuracy and interpretability for mortgage risk assessment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22987v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mahsa Tavakoli, Rohitash Chandra, Cristian Bravo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>P1GPT: a multi-agent LLM workflow module for multi-modal financial information analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23032v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in large language models (LLMs) have enabled multi-agent reasoning systems capable of collaborative decision-making. However, in financial analysis, most frameworks remain narrowly focused on either isolated single-agent predictors or loosely connected analyst ensembles, and they lack a coherent reasoning workflow that unifies diverse data modalities. We introduce P1GPT, a layered multi-agent LLM framework for multi-modal financial information analysis and interpretable trading decision support. Unlike prior systems that emulate trading teams through role simulation, P1GPT implements a structured reasoning pipeline that systematically fuses technical, fundamental, and news-based insights through coordinated agent communication and integration-time synthesis. Backtesting on multi-modal datasets across major U.S. equities demonstrates that P1GPT achieves superior cumulative and risk-adjusted returns, maintains low drawdowns, and provides transparent causal rationales. These findings suggest that structured reasoning workflows, rather than agent role imitation, offer a scalable path toward explainable and trustworthy financial AI systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23032v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen-Che Lu, Yun-Cheng Chou, Teng-Ruei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>GroupSHAP-Guided Integration of Financial News Keywords and Technical Indicators for Stock Price Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23112</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23112v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in finance-specific language models such as FinBERT have enabled the quantification of public sentiment into index-based measures, yet compressing diverse linguistic signals into single metrics overlooks contextual nuances and limits interpretability. To address this limitation, explainable AI techniques, particularly SHAP (SHapley Additive Explanations), have been employed to identify influential features. However, SHAP's computational cost grows exponentially with input features, making it impractical for large-scale text-based financial data. This study introduces a GRU-based forecasting framework enhanced with GroupSHAP, which quantifies contributions of semantically related keyword groups rather than individual tokens, substantially reducing computational burden while preserving interpretability. We employed FinBERT to embed news articles from 2015 to 2024, clustered them into coherent semantic groups, and applied GroupSHAP to measure each group's contribution to stock price movements. The resulting group-level SHAP variables across multiple topics were used as input features for the prediction model. Empirical results from one-day-ahead forecasting of the S&amp;P 500 index throughout 2024 demonstrate that our approach achieves a 32.2% reduction in MAE and a 40.5% reduction in RMSE compared with benchmark models without the GroupSHAP mechanism. This research presents the first application of GroupSHAP in news-driven financial forecasting, showing that grouped sentiment representations simultaneously enhance interpretability and predictive performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23112v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ICAIF 2025 Workshop</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Minjoo Kim, Jinwoong Kim, Sangjin Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Common Task Framework For a Critical Evaluation of Scientific Machine Learning Algorithms</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23166</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23166v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Machine learning (ML) is transforming modeling and control in the physical, engineering, and biological sciences. However, rapid development has outpaced the creation of standardized, objective benchmarks - leading to weak baselines, reporting bias, and inconsistent evaluations across methods. This undermines reproducibility, misguides resource allocation, and obscures scientific progress. To address this, we propose a Common Task Framework (CTF) for scientific machine learning. The CTF features a curated set of datasets and task-specific metrics spanning forecasting, state reconstruction, and generalization under realistic constraints, including noise and limited data. Inspired by the success of CTFs in fields like natural language processing and computer vision, our framework provides a structured, rigorous foundation for head-to-head evaluation of diverse algorithms. As a first step, we benchmark methods on two canonical nonlinear systems: Kuramoto-Sivashinsky and Lorenz. These results illustrate the utility of the CTF in revealing method strengths, limitations, and suitability for specific classes of problems and diverse objectives. Next, we are launching a competition around a global real world sea surface temperature dataset with a true holdout dataset to foster community engagement. Our long-term vision is to replace ad hoc comparisons with standardized evaluations on hidden test sets that raise the bar for rigor and reproducibility in scientific ML.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23166v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philippe Martin Wyder, Judah Goldfeder, Alexey Yermakov, Yue Zhao, Stefano Riva, Jan P. Williams, David Zoro, Amy Sara Rude, Matteo Tomasetto, Joe Germany, Joseph Bakarji, Georg Maierhofer, Miles Cranmer, J. Nathan Kutz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DRO-Based Computation Offloading and Trajectory Design for Low-Altitude Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23202v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The low-altitude networks (LANs) integrating unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) and high-altitude platforms (HAPs) have become a promising solution for the rising computation demands. However, the uncertain task sizes and high mobility of UAVs pose great challenges to guarantee the quality of service. To address these issues, we propose an LAN architecture where UAVs and HAPs collaboratively provide computation offloading for ground users. Moreover, the uncertainty sets are constructed to characterize the uncertain task size, and a distributionally robust optimization problem is formulated to minimize the worst-case delay by jointly optimizing the offloading decisions and UAV trajectories. To solve the mixed-integer min-max optimization problem, we design the distributionally robust computation offloading and trajectories optimization algorithm. Specifically, the original problem is figured out by iteratively solving the outerlayer and inner-layer problems. The convex outer-layer problem with probability distributions is solved by the optimization toolkit. As for the inner-layer mixed-integer problem, we employ the Benders decomposition. The decoupled master problem concerning the binary offloading decisions is solved by the integer solver, and UAV trajectories in the sub-problem are optimized via the successive convex approximation. Simulation results show the proposed algorithm outperforms traditional optimization methods in balancing the worst-case delay and robustness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23202v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guanwang Jiang, Ziye Jia, Can Cui, Lijun He, Qiuming Zhu, Qihui Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning the PTM Code through a Coarse-to-Fine, Mechanism-Aware Framework</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Post-translational modifications (PTMs) form a combinatorial "code" that regulates protein function, yet deciphering this code - linking modified sites to their catalytic enzymes - remains a central unsolved problem in understanding cellular signaling and disease. We introduce COMPASS-PTM, a mechanism-aware, coarse-to-fine learning framework that unifies residue-level PTM profiling with enzyme-substrate assignment. COMPASS-PTM integrates evolutionary representations from protein language models with physicochemical priors and a crosstalk-aware prompting mechanism that explicitly models inter-PTM dependencies. This design allows the model to learn biologically coherent patterns of cooperative and antagonistic modifications while addressing the dual long-tail distribution of PTM data. Across multiple proteome-scale benchmarks, COMPASS-PTM establishes new state-of-the-art performance, including a 122% relative F1 improvement in multi-label site prediction and a 54% gain in zero-shot enzyme assignment. Beyond accuracy, the model demonstrates interpretable generalization, recovering canonical kinase motifs and predicting disease-associated PTM rewiring caused by missense variants. By bridging statistical learning with biochemical mechanism, COMPASS-PTM unifies site-level and enzyme-level prediction into a single framework that learns the grammar underlying protein regulation and signaling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23492v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingjie Zhang, Hanqun Cao, Zijun Gao, Yu Wang, Shaoning Li, Jun Xu, Cheng Tan, Jun Zhu, Chang-Yu Hsieh, Chunbin Gu, Pheng Ann Heng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vertex and front-tracking methods for the modeling of microstructure evolution at the solid state: a brief review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21818v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In mesoscopic scale microstructure evolution modeling, two primary numerical frameworks are used: Front-Capturing (FC) and Front-Tracking (FT) ones. FC models, like phase-field or level-set methods, indirectly define interfaces by tracking field variable changes. On the contrary, FT models explicitly define interfaces using interconnected segments or surfaces. In historical FT methodologies, Vertex models were first developed and consider the description of the evolution of polygonal structures in terms of the motion of points where multiple boundaries meet. Globally, FT-type approaches, often associated with Lagrangian movement, enhance spatial resolution in 3D surfacic and 2D lineic problems using techniques derived from finite element meshing and remeshing algorithms. These efficient approaches, by nature, are well adapted to physical mechanisms correlated to interface properties and geometries. They also face challenges in managing complex topological events, especially in 3D. However, recent advances highlight their potential in computational efficiency and analysis of mobility and energy properties, with possible applications in intragranular phenomena.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21818v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Marc Bernacki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CreditXAI: A Multi-Agent System for Explainable Corporate Credit Rating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22222v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the domain of corporate credit rating, traditional deep learning methods have improved predictive accuracy but still suffer from the inherent 'black-box' problem and limited interpretability. While incorporating non-financial information enriches the data and provides partial interpretability, the models still lack hierarchical reasoning mechanisms, limiting their comprehensive analytical capabilities. To address these challenges, we propose CreditXAI, a Multi-Agent System (MAS) framework that simulates the collaborative decision-making process of professional credit analysts. The framework focuses on business, financial, and governance risk dimensions to generate consistent and interpretable credit assessments. Experimental results demonstrate that multi-agent collaboration improves predictive accuracy by more than 7% over the best single-agent baseline, confirming its significant synergistic advantage in corporate credit risk evaluation. This study provides a new technical pathway to build intelligent and interpretable credit rating models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22222v1</guid>
      <category>cs.MA</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yumeng Shi, Zhongliang Yang, Yisi Wang, Linna Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LAMP: Data-Efficient Linear Affine Weight-Space Models for Parameter-Controlled 3D Shape Generation and Extrapolation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22491</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22491v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Generating high-fidelity 3D geometries that satisfy specific parameter constraints has broad applications in design and engineering. However, current methods typically rely on large training datasets and struggle with controllability and generalization beyond the training distributions. To overcome these limitations, we introduce LAMP (Linear Affine Mixing of Parametric shapes), a data-efficient framework for controllable and interpretable 3D generation. LAMP first aligns signed distance function (SDF) decoders by overfitting each exemplar from a shared initialization, then synthesizes new geometries by solving a parameter-constrained mixing problem in the aligned weight space. To ensure robustness, we further propose a safety metric that detects geometry validity via linearity mismatch. We evaluate LAMP on two 3D parametric benchmarks: DrivAerNet++ and BlendedNet. We found that LAMP enables (i) controlled interpolation within bounds with as few as 100 samples, (ii) safe extrapolation by up to 100% parameter difference beyond training ranges, (iii) physics performance-guided optimization under fixed parameters. LAMP significantly outperforms conditional autoencoder and Deep Network Interpolation (DNI) baselines in both extrapolation and data efficiency. Our results demonstrate that LAMP advances controllable, data-efficient, and safe 3D generation for design exploration, dataset generation, and performance-driven optimization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22491v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ghadi Nehme, Yanxia Zhang, Dule Shu, Matt Klenk, Faez Ahmed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph Neural Network Assisted Genetic Algorithm for Structural Dynamic Response and Parameter Optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.22839</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.22839v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The optimization of structural parameters, such as mass(m), stiffness(k), and damping coefficient(c), is critical for designing efficient, resilient, and stable structures. Conventional numerical approaches, including Finite Element Method (FEM) and Computational Fluid Dynamics (CFD) simulations, provide high-fidelity results but are computationally expensive for iterative optimization tasks, as each evaluation requires solving the governing equations for every parameter combination. This study proposes a hybrid data-driven framework that integrates a Graph Neural Network (GNN) surrogate model with a Genetic Algorithm (GA) optimizer to overcome these challenges. The GNN is trained to accurately learn the nonlinear mapping between structural parameters and dynamic displacement responses, enabling rapid predictions without repeatedly solving the system equations. A dataset of single-degree-of-freedom (SDOF) system responses is generated using the Newmark Beta method across diverse mass, stiffness, and damping configurations. The GA then searches for globally optimal parameter sets by minimizing predicted displacements and enhancing dynamic stability. Results demonstrate that the GNN and GA framework achieves strong convergence, robust generalization, and significantly reduced computational cost compared to conventional simulations. This approach highlights the effectiveness of combining machine learning surrogates with evolutionary optimization for automated and intelligent structural design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.22839v2</guid>
      <category>cs.NE</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sagnik Mukherjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards a Generalizable AI for Materials Discovery: Validation through Immersion Coolant Screening</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23371</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23371v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Artificial intelligence (AI) has emerged as a powerful accelerator of materials discovery, yet most existing models remain problem-specific, requiring additional data collection and retraining for each new property. Here we introduce and validate GATE (Geometrically Aligned Transfer Encoder) -- a generalizable AI framework that jointly learns 34 physicochemical properties spanning thermal, electrical, mechanical, and optical domains. By aligning these properties within a shared geometric space, GATE captures cross-property correlations that reduce disjoint-property bias -- a key factor causing false negatives in multi-criteria screening. To demonstrate its generalizability, GATE -- without any problem-specific reconfiguration -- was directly applied to the discovery of immersion cooling fluids for data centers, a stringent real-world challenge defined by the Open Compute Project (OCP). Screening billions of candidates, GATE identified 92,861 molecules as promising for practical deployment. Four were experimentally or literarily validated, showing strong agreement with wet-lab measurements and performance comparable to or exceeding a commercial coolant. These results establish GATE as a ready-to-use, generalizable AI platform readily applicable across diverse materials discovery tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23371v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyunseung Kim, Dae-Woong Jeong, Changyoung Park, Won-Ji Lee, Ha-Eun Lee, Ji-Hye Lee, Rodrigo Hormazabal, Sung Moon Ko, Sumin Lee, Soorin Yim, Chanhui Lee, Sehui Han, Sang-Ho Cha, Woohyung Lim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tree-Cotree-Based IETI-DP for Eddy Current Problems in Time-Domain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.23446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.23446v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For low-frequency electromagnetic problems, where wave-propagation effects can be neglected, eddy current formulations are commonly used as a simplification of the full Maxwell's equations. In this setup, time-domain simulations, needed to capture transient startup responses or nonlinear behavior, are often computationally expensive. We propose a novel tearing and interconnecting approach for eddy currents in time-domain and investigate its scalability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.23446v1</guid>
      <category>math.NA</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.NA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mario Mally, Rafael V\'azquez, Sebastian Sch\"ops</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Error estimation and step size control with minimal subsystem interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17353v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We review error estimation methods for co-simulation, in particular methods that are applicable when the subsystems provide minimal interfaces. By this, we mean that subsystems do not support rollback of time steps, do not output derivatives, and do not provide any other information about their internals besides the output variables that are required for coupling with other subsystems. Such "black-box" subsystems are common in industrial applications, and the ability to couple them and run large-system simulations is one of the major attractions of the co-simulation paradigm. We also describe how the resulting error indicators may be used to automatically control macro time step sizes to strike a good balance between simulation speed and accuracy. The various elements of the step size control algorithm are presented in pseudocode so that readers may implement them and test them in their own applications. We provide practicable advice on how to use error indicators to judge the quality of a co-simulation, how to avoid common pitfalls, and how to configure the step size control algorithm.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17353v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.simpat.2025.103209</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Simulation Modelling Practice and Theory, volume 145 (2025), 103209</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Lars T. Kyllingstad, Severin Sadjina, Stian Skjong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Convolutional Hierarchical Deep Learning Neural Networks-Tensor Decomposition (C-HiDeNN-TD): a scalable surrogate modeling approach for large-scale physical systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.00329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.00329v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A common trend in simulation-driven engineering applications is the ever-increasing size and complexity of the problem, where classical numerical methods typically suffer from significant computational time and huge memory cost. Methods based on artificial intelligence have been extensively investigated to accelerate partial differential equations (PDE) solvers using data-driven surrogates. However, most data-driven surrogates require an extremely large amount of training data. In this paper, we propose the Convolutional Hierarchical Deep Learning Neural Network-Tensor Decomposition (C-HiDeNN-TD) method, which can directly obtain surrogate models by solving large-scale space-time PDE without generating any offline training data. We compare the performance of the proposed method against classical numerical methods for extremely large-scale systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.00329v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>NeurIPS 2024 workshop on Data-driven and Differentiable Simulations, Surrogates, and Solvers</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Jiachen Guo, Chanwook Park, Xiaoyu Xie, Zhongsheng Sang, Gregory J. Wagner, Wing Kam Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magneto-thermally Coupled Field Simulation of Homogenized Foil Winding Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.13010</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.13010v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Foil windings have, due to their layered structure, different properties than conventional wire windings, which make them advantageous for high frequency applications. Both electromagnetic and thermal analyses are relevant for foil windings. These two physical areas are coupled through Joule losses and temperature dependent material properties. For an efficient simulation of foil windings, homogenization techniques are used to avoid resolving the single turns. Therefore, this paper comprises a coupled magneto-thermal simulation that uses a homogenization method in the electromagnetic and thermal part. A weak coupling with different time step sizes for both parts is presented. The method is verified on a simple geometry and showcased for a pot transformer that uses a foil and a wire winding.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.13010v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1186/s40323-025-00315-4</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advanced Modeling and Simulation in Engineering Sciences, vol. 12, no. 1, Oct. 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Silas Weinert, Jonas Bundschuh, Yvonne Sp\"ack-Leigsnering, Herbert De Gersem</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BikeBench: A Bicycle Design Benchmark for Generative Models with Objectives and Constraints</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.00830</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.00830v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce BikeBench, an engineering design benchmark for evaluating generative models on problems with multiple real-world objectives and constraints. As generative AI's reach continues to grow, evaluating its capability to understand physical laws, human guidelines, and hard constraints grows increasingly important. Engineering product design lies at the intersection of these difficult tasks, providing new challenges for AI capabilities. BikeBench evaluates AI models' capabilities to generate bicycle designs that not only resemble the dataset, but meet specific performance objectives and constraints. To do so, BikeBench quantifies a variety of human-centered and multiphysics performance characteristics, such as aerodynamics, ergonomics, structural mechanics, human-rated usability, and similarity to subjective text or image prompts. Supporting the benchmark are several datasets of simulation results, a dataset of 10,000 human-rated bicycle assessments, and a synthetically generated dataset of 1.6M designs, each with a parametric, CAD/XML, SVG, and PNG representation. BikeBench is uniquely configured to evaluate tabular generative models, large language models (LLMs), design optimization, and hybrid algorithms side-by-side. Our experiments indicate that LLMs and tabular generative models fall short of hybrid GenAI+optimization algorithms in design quality, constraint satisfaction, and similarity scores, suggesting significant room for improvement. We hope that BikeBench, a first-of-its-kind benchmark, will help catalyze progress in generative AI for constrained multi-objective engineering design problems. We provide code, data, an interactive leaderboard, and other resources at https://github.com/Lyleregenwetter/BikeBench.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.00830v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lyle Regenwetter, Yazan Abu Obaideh, Fabien Chiotti, Ioanna Lykourentzou, Faez Ahmed</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>IKNet: Interpretable Stock Price Prediction via Keyword-Guided Integration of News and Technical Indicators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.07661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.07661v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The increasing influence of unstructured external information, such as news articles, on stock prices has attracted growing attention in financial markets. Despite recent advances, most existing newsbased forecasting models represent all articles using sentiment scores or average embeddings that capture the general tone but fail to provide quantitative, context-aware explanations of the impacts of public sentiment on predictions. To address this limitation, we propose an interpretable keyword-guided network (IKNet), which is an explainable forecasting framework that models the semantic association between individual news keywords and stock price movements. The IKNet identifies salient keywords via FinBERTbased contextual analysis, processes each embedding through a separate nonlinear projection layer, and integrates their representations with the time-series data of technical indicators to forecast next-day closing prices. By applying Shapley Additive Explanations the model generates quantifiable and interpretable attributions for the contribution of each keyword to predictions. Empirical evaluations of S&amp;P 500 data from 2015 to 2024 demonstrate that IKNet outperforms baselines, including recurrent neural networks and transformer models, reducing RMSE by up to 32.9% and improving cumulative returns by 18.5%. Moreover, IKNet enhances transparency by offering contextualized explanations of volatility events driven by public sentiment.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.07661v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinwoong Kim, Sangjin Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning Satellite Pattern-of-Life Identification: A Diffusion-based Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.10814</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.10814v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As Earth's orbital satellite population grows exponentially, effective space situational awareness becomes critical for collision prevention and sustainable operations. Current approaches to monitor satellite behaviors rely on expert knowledge and rule-based systems that scale poorly. Among essential monitoring tasks, satellite pattern-of-life (PoL) identification, analyzing behaviors like station-keeping maneuvers and drift operations, remains underdeveloped due to aerospace system complexity, operational variability, and inconsistent ephemerides sources. We propose a novel generative approach for satellite PoL identification that significantly eliminates the dependence on expert knowledge. The proposed approach leverages orbital elements and positional data to enable automatic pattern discovery directly from observations. Our implementation uses a diffusion model framework for end-to-end identification without manual refinement or domain expertise. The architecture combines a multivariate time-series encoder to capture hidden representations of satellite positional data with a conditional denoising process to generate accurate PoL classifications. Through experiments across diverse real-world satellite operational scenarios, our approach demonstrates superior identification quality and robustness across varying data quality characteristics. A case study using actual satellite data confirms the approach's transformative potential for operational behavior pattern identification, enhanced tracking, and space situational awareness.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.10814v3</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yongchao Ye, Xinting Zhu, Xuejin Shen, Xiaoyu Chen, S. Joe Qin, Lishuai Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interpretable Neural ODEs for Gene Regulatory Network Discovery under Perturbations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.02409</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.02409v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Modern high-throughput biological datasets with thousands of perturbations provide the opportunity for large-scale discovery of causal graphs that represent the regulatory interactions between genes. Differentiable causal graphical models have been proposed to infer a gene regulatory network (GRN) from large scale interventional datasets, capturing the causal gene regulatory relationships from genetic perturbations. However, existing models are limited in their expressivity and scalability while failing to address the dynamic nature of biological processes such as cellular differentiation. We propose PerturbODE, a novel framework that incorporates biologically informative neural ordinary differential equations (neural ODEs) to model cell state trajectories under perturbations and derive the causal GRN from the neural ODE's parameters. We demonstrate PerturbODE's efficacy in trajectory prediction and GRN inference across simulated and real over-expression datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.02409v4</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <category>stat.ME</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zaikang Lin, Sei Chang, Aaron Zweig, Minseo Kang, Elham Azizi, David A. Knowles</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cohort-attention Evaluation Metric against Tied Data: Studying Performance of Classification Models in Cancer Detection</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12755</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12755v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Artificial intelligence (AI) has significantly improved medical screening accuracy, particularly in cancer detection and risk assessment. However, traditional classification metrics often fail to account for imbalanced data, varying performance across cohorts, and patient-level inconsistencies, leading to biased evaluations. We propose the Cohort-Attention Evaluation Metrics (CAT) framework to address these challenges. CAT introduces patient-level assessment, entropy-based distribution weighting, and cohort-weighted sensitivity and specificity. Key metrics like CATSensitivity (CATSen), CATSpecificity (CATSpe), and CATMean ensure balanced and fair evaluation across diverse populations. This approach enhances predictive reliability, fairness, and interpretability, providing a robust evaluation method for AI-driven medical screening models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12755v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Longfei Wei, Fang Sheng, Jianfei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ChromFound: Towards A Universal Foundation Model for Single-Cell Chromatin Accessibility Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.12638v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The advent of single-cell Assay for Transposase-Accessible Chromatin using sequencing (scATAC-seq) offers an innovative perspective for deciphering regulatory mechanisms by assembling a vast repository of single-cell chromatin accessibility data. While foundation models have achieved significant success in single-cell transcriptomics, there is currently no foundation model for scATAC-seq that supports zero-shot high-quality cell identification and comprehensive multi-omics analysis simultaneously. Key challenges lie in the high dimensionality and sparsity of scATAC-seq data, as well as the lack of a standardized schema for representing open chromatin regions (OCRs). Here, we present ChromFound, a foundation model tailored for scATAC-seq. ChromFound utilizes a hybrid architecture and genome-aware tokenization to effectively capture genome-wide long contexts and regulatory signals from dynamic chromatin landscapes. Pretrained on 1.97 million cells from 30 tissues and 6 disease conditions, ChromFound demonstrates broad applicability across 6 diverse tasks. Notably, it achieves robust zero-shot performance in generating universal cell representations and exhibits excellent transferability in cell type annotation and cross-omics prediction. By uncovering enhancer-gene links undetected by existing computational methods, ChromFound offers a promising framework for understanding disease risk variants in the noncoding genome.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12638v3</guid>
      <category>q-bio.GN</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifeng Jiao, Yuchen Liu, Yu Zhang, Xin Guo, Yushuai Wu, Chen Jiang, Jiyang Li, Hongwei Zhang, Limei Han, Xin Gao, Yuan Qi, Yuan Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOOSE-Chem3: Toward Experiment-Guided Hypothesis Ranking via Simulated Experimental Feedback</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.17873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.17873v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Hypothesis ranking is vital for automated scientific discovery, especially in cost-intensive, throughput-limited natural science domains. Current methods focus on pre-experiment ranking, relying solely on language model reasoning without empirical feedback. We introduce experiment-guided ranking, which prioritizes hypotheses based on feedback from prior tests. Due to the impracticality of real experiments, we propose a simulator grounded in domain-specific concepts that models hypothesis performance as a function of similarity to a hidden ground truth, perturbed by noise. Validated against 124 hypotheses with experimentally reported outcomes, the simulator approximates real results with consistent trend alignment. Although deviations exist, they mimic wet-lab noise, promoting more robust ranking strategies. We frame experiment-guided ranking as a sequential decision-making problem and propose an in-context reinforcement learning (ICRL) framework. Our LLM-based policy decomposes hypotheses into functional elements, clusters them by mechanistic roles, and prioritizes recombinations based on feedback. Experiments show our approach significantly outperforms pre-experiment baselines and strong ablations. Our toolkit, comprising the simulator and ICRL framework, enables systematic research on experiment-guided ranking, with the policy serving as a strong proof of concept.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.17873v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wanhao Liu, Zonglin Yang, Jue Wang, Lidong Bing, Di Zhang, Dongzhan Zhou, Yuqiang Li, Houqiang Li, Erik Cambria, Wanli Ouyang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOOSE-Chem2: Exploring LLM Limits in Fine-Grained Scientific Hypothesis Discovery via Hierarchical Search</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.19209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.19209v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs) have shown promise in automating scientific hypothesis generation, yet existing approaches primarily yield coarse-grained hypotheses lacking critical methodological and experimental details. We introduce and formally define the new task of fine-grained scientific hypothesis discovery, which entails generating detailed, experimentally actionable hypotheses from coarse initial research directions. We frame this as a combinatorial optimization problem and investigate the upper limits of LLMs' capacity to solve it when maximally leveraged. Specifically, we explore four foundational questions: (1) how to best harness an LLM's internal heuristics to formulate the fine-grained hypothesis it itself would judge as the most promising among all the possible hypotheses it might generate, based on its own internal scoring-thus defining a latent reward landscape over the hypothesis space; (2) whether such LLM-judged better hypotheses exhibit stronger alignment with ground-truth hypotheses; (3) whether shaping the reward landscape using an ensemble of diverse LLMs of similar capacity yields better outcomes than defining it with repeated instances of the strongest LLM among them; and (4) whether an ensemble of identical LLMs provides a more reliable reward landscape than a single LLM. To address these questions, we propose a hierarchical search method that incrementally proposes and integrates details into the hypothesis, progressing from general concepts to specific experimental configurations. We show that this hierarchical process smooths the reward landscape and enables more effective optimization. Empirical evaluations on a new benchmark of expert-annotated fine-grained hypotheses from recent literature show that our method consistently outperforms strong baselines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.19209v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>stat.ML</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zonglin Yang, Wanhao Liu, Ben Gao, Yujie Liu, Wei Li, Tong Xie, Lidong Bing, Wanli Ouyang, Erik Cambria, Dongzhan Zhou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Automated Constitutive Model Discovery by Pairing Sparse Regression Algorithms with Model Selection Criteria</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16040</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.16040v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The automated discovery of constitutive models from data has recently emerged as a promising alternative to the traditional model calibration paradigm. In this work, we present a fully automated framework for constitutive model discovery that systematically pairs three sparse regression algorithms (Least Absolute Shrinkage and Selection Operator (LASSO), Least Angle Regression (LARS), and Orthogonal Matching Pursuit (OMP)) with three model selection criteria: $K$-fold cross-validation (CV), Akaike Information Criterion (AIC), and Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC). This pairing yields nine distinct algorithms for model discovery and enables a systematic exploration of the trade-off between sparsity, predictive performance, and computational cost. While LARS serves as an efficient path-based solver for the $\ell_1$-constrained problem, OMP is introduced as a tractable heuristic for $\ell_0$-regularized selection. The framework is applied to both isotropic and anisotropic hyperelasticity, utilizing both synthetic and experimental datasets. Results reveal that all nine algorithm-criterion combinations perform consistently well in discovering isotropic and anisotropic materials, yielding highly accurate constitutive models. These findings broaden the range of viable discovery algorithms beyond $\ell_1$-based approaches such as LASSO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.16040v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge-Humberto Urrea-Quintero, David Anton, Laura De Lorenzis, Henning Wessels</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
