<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cs.CE updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE</link>
    <description>cs.CE updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cs.CE" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2026 02:34:43 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Fast Surrogate Models for Adaptive Aircraft Trajectory Prediction in En route Airspace</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.03075v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Trajectory prediction (TP) is crucial for ensuring safety and efficiency in modern air traffic management systems. It is, for example, a core component of conflict detection and resolution tools, arrival sequencing algorithms, capacity planning, as well as several future concepts. However, TP accuracy within operational systems is hampered by a range of epistemic uncertainties such as the mass and performance settings of aircraft and the effect of meteorological conditions on aircraft performance. It can also require considerable computational resources.
  This paper proposes a method for adaptive TP that has two components: first, a fast surrogate TP model based on linear state space models (LSSM)s with an execution time that was 6.7 times lower on average than an implementation of the Base of Aircraft Data (BADA) in Python. It is demonstrated that such models can effectively emulate the BADA aircraft performance model, which is based on the numerical solution of a partial differential equation (PDE), and that the LSSMs can be fitted to trajectories in a dataset of historic flight data. Secondly, the paper proposes an algorithm to assimilate radar observations using particle filtering to adaptively refine TP accuracy. Comparison with baselines using BADA and Kalman filtering demonstrate that the proposed framework improves system identification and state estimation for both climb and descent phases, with 46.3% and 64.7% better estimates for time to top of climb and bottom of descent compared to the best performing benchmark model. In particular, the particle filtering approach provides the flexibility to capture non-linear performance effects including the CAS-Mach transition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.03075v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nick Pepper, Marc Thomas, Zack Xuereb Conti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Probabilistic Digital Twin of UK En Route Airspace for Training and Evaluating AI Agents for Air Traffic Control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.03113v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This paper presents the first probabilistic Digital Twin of operational en route airspace, developed for the London Area Control Centre. The Digital Twin is intended to support the development and rigorous human-in-the-loop evaluation of AI agents for Air Traffic Control (ATC), providing a virtual representation of real-world airspace that enables safe exploration of higher levels of ATC automation.
  This paper makes three significant contributions: firstly, we demonstrate how historical and live operational data may be combined with a probabilistic, physics-informed machine learning model of aircraft performance to reproduce real-world traffic scenarios, while accurately reflecting the level of uncertainty inherent in ATC. Secondly, we develop a structured assurance case, following the Trustworthy and Ethical Assurance framework, to provide quantitative evidence for the Digital Twin's accuracy and fidelity. This is crucial to building trust in this novel technology within this safety-critical domain. Thirdly, we describe how the Digital Twin forms a unified environment for agent testing and evaluation. This includes fast-time execution (up to x200 real-time), a standardised Python-based ``gym'' interface that supports a range of AI agent designs, and a suite of quantitative metrics for assessing performance. Crucially, the framework facilitates competency-based assessment of AI agents by qualified Air Traffic Control Officers through a Human Machine Interface. We also outline further applications and future extensions of the Digital Twin architecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.03113v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nick Pepper, Adam Keane, Amy Hodgkin, Dewi Gould, Edward Henderson, Lynge Lauritsen, Christos Vlahos, George De Ath, Richard Everson, Richard Cannon, Alvaro Sierra Castro, John Korna, Ben Carvell, Marc Thomas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OpenFOAM computational fluid dynamics (CFD) solver for magnetohydrodynamic open cycles, applied to the Sakhalin pulsed magnetohydrodynamic generator (PMHDG)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02406</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02406v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In the current study, we present a mathematical and computational fluid dynamics (CFD) model for simulating open-cycle linear Faraday-type continuous-electrode channels of magnetohydrodynamic (MHD) power generators, operating on combustion plasma. The model extends the Favre-averaged Navier-Stokes equations to account for the electric properties of the flowing plasma gas and its reaction to the applied magnetic field. The model takes into account various effects, such as the Lorentz force, turbulence, compressibility, and energy extraction from the plasma, and it adopts an electric potential technique along with the low magnetic Reynolds number (Rem) approximation. The model is numerically implemented using the multiphysics open-source computer programming environment "OpenFOAM," which combines the finite volume method (FVM) and the object-oriented programming (OOP) concept. The capabilities of the model are demonstrated by simulating the supersonic channel of the large-scale pulsed MHD generator (PMHDG) called "Sakhalin", with the aid of collected data and empirical expressions in the literature about its tested operation. Sakhalin was the world's largest PMHDG, with a demonstrated peak electric power output of 510 MW. Sakhalin operated on solid-propellant plasma (SPP), and it had a single supersonic divergent Faraday-type continuous-electrode channel with a length of 4.5 m. We check the validity of the model through comparisons with independent results for the Sakhalin PMHDG. Then, we process our three-dimensional simulation results to provide scalar characteristics of the Sakhalin channel, one-dimensional profiles along the longitudinal centerline, and three-dimensional distributions in the entire channel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02406v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>physics.flu-dyn</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s42452-025-07744-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Discover Applied Sciences. 7(10):1108 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Osama A. Marzouk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>LendNova: Towards Automated Credit Risk Assessment with Language Models</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02573</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02573v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Credit risk assessment is essential in the financial sector, but has traditionally depended on costly feature-based models that often fail to utilize all available information in raw credit records. This paper introduces LendNova, the first practical automated end-to-end pipeline for credit risk assessment, designed to utilize all available information in raw credit records by leveraging advanced NLP techniques and language models. LendNova transforms risk modeling by operating directly on raw, jargon-heavy credit bureau text using a language model that learns task-relevant representations without manual feature engineering. By automatically capturing patterns and risk signals embedded in the text, it replaces manual preprocessing steps, reducing costs and improving scalability. Evaluation on real-world data further demonstrates its strong potential in accurate and efficient risk assessment. LendNova establishes a baseline for intelligent credit risk agents, demonstrating the feasibility of language models in this domain. It lays the groundwork for future research toward foundation systems that enable more accurate, adaptable, and automated financial decision-making.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02573v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>AAAI 2026, Workshop on Agentic AI in Financial Services</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kiarash Shamsi, Danijel Novokmet, Joshua Peters, Mao Lin Liu, Paul K Edwards, Vahab Khoshdel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Spectral Modeling and Control of Soft-Robotic Muscles from Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.03247</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.03247v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Artificial muscles are essential for compliant musculoskeletal robotics but complicate control due to nonlinear multiphysics dynamics. Hydraulically amplified electrostatic (HASEL) actuators, a class of soft artificial muscles, offer high performance but exhibit memory effects and hysteresis. Here we present a data-driven reduction and control strategy grounded in spectral submanifold (SSM) theory. In the adiabatic regime, where inputs vary slowly relative to intrinsic transients, trajectories rapidly converge to a low-dimensional slow manifold. We learn an explicit input-to-output map on this manifold from forced-response trajectories alone, avoiding decay experiments that can trigger hysteresis. We deploy the SSM-based model for real-time control of an antagonistic HASEL-clutch joint. This approach yields a substantial reduction in tracking error compared to feedback-only and feedforward-only baselines under identical settings. This record-and-control workflow enables rapid characterization and high-performance control of soft muscles and muscle-driven joints without detailed physics-based modeling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.03247v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo Bettini, Amirhossein Kazemipour, Robert K. Katzschmann, George Haller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MDAgent2: Large Language Model for Code Generation and Knowledge Q&amp;A in Molecular Dynamics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.02075</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.02075v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Molecular dynamics (MD) simulations are essential for understanding atomic-scale behaviors in materials science, yet writing LAMMPS scripts remains highly specialized and time-consuming tasks. Although LLMs show promise in code generation and domain-specific question answering, their performance in MD scenarios is limited by scarce domain data, the high deployment cost of state-of-the-art LLMs, and low code executability. Building upon our prior MDAgent, we present MDAgent2, the first end-to-end framework capable of performing both knowledge Q&amp;A and code generation within the MD domain. We construct a domain-specific data-construction pipeline that yields three high-quality datasets spanning MD knowledge, question answering, and code generation. Based on these datasets, we adopt a three stage post-training strategy--continued pre-training (CPT), supervised fine-tuning (SFT), and reinforcement learning (RL)--to train two domain-adapted models, MD-Instruct and MD-Code. Furthermore, we introduce MD-GRPO, a closed-loop RL method that leverages simulation outcomes as reward signals and recycles low-reward trajectories for continual refinement. We further build MDAgent2-RUNTIME, a deployable multi-agent system that integrates code generation, execution, evaluation, and self-correction. Together with MD-EvalBench proposed in this work, the first benchmark for LAMMPS code generation and question answering, our models and system achieve performance surpassing several strong baselines.This work systematically demonstrates the adaptability and generalization capability of large language models in industrial simulation tasks, laying a methodological foundation for automatic code generation in AI for Science and industrial-scale simulations. URL: https://github.com/FredericVAN/PKU_MDAgent2</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.02075v3</guid>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuofan Shi, Hubao A, Yufei Shao, Dongliang Huang, Hongxu An, Chunxiao Xin, Haiyang Shen, Zhenyu Wang, Yunshan Na, Gang Huang, Xiang Jing</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Network topology of the Euro Area interbank market</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.15611</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.15611v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The rapidly increasing availability of large amounts of granular financial data, paired with the advances of big data related technologies induces the need of suitable analytics that can represent and extract meaningful information from such data. In this paper we propose a multi-layer network approach to distill the Euro Area (EA) banking system in different distinct layers. Each layer of the network represents a specific type of financial relationship between banks, based on various sources of EA granular data collections. The resulting multi-layer network allows one to describe, analyze and compare the topology and structure of EA banks from different perspectives, eventually yielding a more complete picture of the financial market. This granular information representation has the potential to enable researchers and practitioners to better apprehend financial system dynamics as well as to support financial policies to manage and monitor financial risk from a more holistic point of view.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.15611v2</guid>
      <category>q-fin.ST</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/978-3-031-63630-1_1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>In: Mingione, M., Vichi, M., Zaccaria, G. (eds), High-quality and Timely Statistics. CESS 2022. Studies in Theoretical and Applied Statistics. Springer, Cham (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ilias Aarab, Thomas Gottron</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FCMBench: A Comprehensive Financial Credit Multimodal Benchmark for Real-world Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.00150</link>
      <description>arXiv:2601.00150v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: As multimodal AI becomes widely used for credit risk assessment and document review, a domain-specific benchmark is urgently needed that (1) reflects documents and workflows specific to financial credit applications, (2) includes credit-specific understanding and real-world robustness, and (3) preserves privacy compliance without sacrificing practical utility. Here, we introduce FCMBench-V1.0 -- a large-scale financial credit multimodal benchmark for real-world applications, covering 18 core certificate types, with 4,043 privacy-compliant images and 8,446 QA samples. The FCMBench evaluation framework consists of three dimensions: Perception, Reasoning, and Robustness, including 3 foundational perception tasks, 4 credit-specific reasoning tasks that require decision-oriented understanding of visual evidence, and 10 real-world acquisition artifact types for robustness stress testing. To reconcile compliance with realism, we construct all samples via a closed synthesis-capture pipeline: we manually synthesize document templates with virtual content and capture scenario-aware images in-house. This design also mitigates pre-training data leakage by avoiding web-sourced or publicly released images. FCMBench can effectively discriminate performance disparities and robustness across modern vision-language models. Extensive experiments were conducted on 23 state-of-the-art vision-language models (VLMs) from 14 top AI companies and research institutes. Among them, Gemini 3 Pro achieves the best F1(\%) score as a commercial model (64.61), Qwen3-VL-235B achieves the best score as an open-source baseline (57.27), and our financial credit-specific model, Qfin-VL-Instruct, achieves the top overall score (64.92). Robustness evaluations show that even top-performing models suffer noticeable performance drops under acquisition artifacts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2601.00150v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <category>cs.MM</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jan 2026 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yehui Yang, Dalu Yang, Wenshuo Zhou, Fangxin Shang, Yifan Liu, Jie Ren, Haojun Fei, Qing Yang, Yanwu Xu, Tao Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
