<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.SG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SG</link>
    <description>math.SG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2024 01:40:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jul 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Shifted symplectic structure on Poisson Lie algebroid and generalized complex geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15598</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15598v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Generalized complex geometry was classically formulated by the language of differential geometry. In this paper, we reformulated a generalized complex manifold as a holomorphic symplectic differentiable formal stack in a homotopical sense. Meanwhile, by developing the machinery for shifted symplectic formal stack, we prove that the coisotropic intersection inherits shifted Poisson structure. Generalized complex branes are also studied.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15598v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yingdi Qin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Gauged linear sigma model in geometric phase. II. the virtual cycle</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14545</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14545v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We provide the detailed construction of the virtual cycles needed for defining the cohomological field theory associated to a gauged linear sigma model in geometric phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14545v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gang Tian, Guangbo Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On a metric symplectization of a contact metric manifold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.15057</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.15057v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article, we investigate metric structures on the symplectization of a contact metric manifold and prove that there is a unique metric structure, which we call the metric symplectization, for which each slice of the symplectization has a natural induced contact metric structure. We then study the curvature properties of this metric structure and use it to establish equivalent formulations of the $(\kappa, \mu)$-nullity condition in terms of the metric symplectization. We also prove that isomorphisms of the metric symplectizations of $(\kappa, \mu)$-manifolds determine $(\kappa, \mu)$-manifolds up to D-homothetic transformations. These classification results show that the metric symplectization provides a unified framework to classify Sasakian manifolds, K-contact manifolds and $(\kappa, \mu)$-manifolds in terms of their symplectizations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.15057v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sannidhi Alape</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Local mirror symmetry via SYZ</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.12863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2105.12863v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this note, we explain how mirror symmetry for basic local models in the Gross-Siebert program can be understood through the non-toric blowup construction described by Gross-Hacking-Keel. This is part of a program to understand the symplectic geometry of affine cluster varieties through their SYZ fibrations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2105.12863v2</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Gammage</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Open/Closed BPS Correspondence and Integrality</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.13542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2307.13542v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove the integrality and finiteness of open BPS invariants of toric Calabi-Yau 3-folds relative to Aganagic-Vafa outer branes, defined from open Gromov-Witten invariants by the Labastida-Mari\~no-Ooguri-Vafa formula. Specializing to disk invariants, we extend the open/closed correspondence of Gromov-Witten invariants to BPS invariants and prove the integrality of a class of genus-zero BPS invariants of toric Calabi-Yau 4-folds, thereby providing additional examples for the conjecture of Klemm-Pandharipande.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2307.13542v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Song Yu</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
