<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.SG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SG</link>
    <description>math.SG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 09 Jan 2025 02:34:24 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Para-Holomorphic Algebroids and Para-Complex Connections</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.03519</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.03519v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The goal of this paper is to develop the theory of Courant algebroids with integrable para-Hermitian vector bundle structures by invoking the theory of Lie bialgebroids. We consider the case where the underlying manifold has an almost para-complex structure, and use this to define a notion of para-holomorphic algebroid. We investigate connections on para-holomorphic algebroids and determine an appropriate sense in which they can be para-complex. Finally, we show through a series of examples how the theory of exact para-holomorphic algebroids with a para-complex connection is a generalization of both para-K\"{a}hler geometry and the theory of Poisson-Lie groups.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.03519v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aidan Patterson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Log Floer cohomology for oriented log symplectic surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2207.06894</link>
      <description>arXiv:2207.06894v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This article provides the first extension of Lagrangian Intersection Floer cohomology to Poisson structures which are almost everywhere symplectic, but degenerate on a lowerdimensional submanifold. The main result of the article is the definition of Lagrangian intersection Floer cohomology, referred to as log Floer cohomology, for orientable surfaces equipped with log symplectic structures. We show that this cohomology is invariant under suitable isotopies and that it is isomorphic to the log de Rham cohomology when computed for a single Lagrangian.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2207.06894v3</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Charlotte Kirchhoff-Lukat</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vanishing cycles of symplectic foliations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.07090</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.07090v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Several results in recent years have shown that the usual generalizations of taut foliations to higher dimensions, based only on topological concepts, lead to a theory that lacks the complexity of its 3-dimensional counterpart. Instead, we propose strong symplectic foliations as natural candidates for such a generalization and we prove in this article that they do yield some interesting rigidity results, such as potentially topological obstructions on the underlying ambient manifold. We introduce a high-dimensional generalization of 3-dimensional vanishing cycles for symplectic foliations, which we call Lagrangian vanishing cycles, and prove that they prevent a symplectic foliation from being strong, just as vanishing cycles prevent tautness in dimension 3 due to the classical result of Novikov from 1964. We then describe, in every codimension, examples of symplectically foliated manifolds which admit Lagrangian vanishing cycles, but for which more classical arguments fail to obstruct strongness. In codimension 1, this is achieved by a rather explicit modification of the symplectic foliation, which allows us to open up closed leaves having non-trivial holonomy on both sides, and is thus of independent interest. Since there is no comprehensive source on holomorphic curves with boundary in symplectic foliations, we also give a detailed introduction to much of the analytic theory, in the hope that it might serve as a reference for future work in this direction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.07090v2</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabio Gironella, Klaus Niederkr\"uger, Lauran Toussaint</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
