<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.SG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SG</link>
    <description>math.SG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 02:30:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite-dimensional Lagrange-Dirac systems with boundary energy flow I: Foundations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17551</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17551v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A new geometric approach to systems with boundary energy flow is developed using infinite-dimensional Dirac structures within the Lagrangian formalism. This framework satisfies a list of consistency criteria with the geometric setting of finite-dimensional mechanics. In particular, the infinite-dimensional Dirac structure can be constructed from the canonical symplectic form on the system's phase space; the system's evolution equations can be derived equivalently from either a variational perspective or a Dirac structure perspective; the variational principle employed is a direct extension of Hamilton's principle in classical mechanics; and the approach allows for a process of system interconnection within its formulation. This is achieved by developing an appropriate infinite dimensional version of the previously developed Lagrange-Dirac systems. A key step in this construction is the careful choice of a suitable dual space to the configuration space, specifically, a subspace of the topological dual that captures the system's behavior in both the interior and the boundary, while allowing for a natural extension of the canonical geometric structures of mechanics. This paper focuses on systems where the configuration space consists of differential forms on a smooth manifold with a boundary. To illustrate our theory, several examples, including nonlinear wave equations, the telegraph equation, and the Maxwell equations are presented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17551v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fran\c{c}ois Gay-Balmaz, \'Alvaro Rodr\'iguez Abella, Hiroaki Yoshimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Morse-Novikov homology and $\beta$-critical points</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17809v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a manifold $M$, some closed $\beta\in\Omega^1(M)$ and a map $f\in C^\infty(M)$, a $\beta$-critical point is some $x\in M$ such that $d_\beta f_{x}=0$ for the Lichnerowicz derivative $d_\beta$. In this paper, we will give a lower bound for the number of $\beta$-critical points of index $i$ of a $\beta$-Morse function $f$ in terms of the Morse-Novikov homology, and we generalize this result to generating functions (quadratic at infinity). We also give an application to the detection of essential Liouville chords of a set length. These are a type of chords that appear in locally conformally symplectic geometry as even-dimensional analogues to Reeb chords.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17809v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrien Currier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Integration of the elliptic tangent bundle and elliptic Poisson structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17487</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17487v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explicitly construct a Lie groupoid integrating the elliptic tangent bundle associated to a (possibly normal crossing) elliptic divisor, providing a necessary and sufficient topological condition for the existence of a Hausdorff integration. We also produce an explicit local model for the symplectic integration of an elliptic Poisson structure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17487v1</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bas Wensink</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symplectic wheelgebras and noncommutative geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.17764</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.17764v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this article, we explore the following statement made by V. Ginzburg and T. Schedler in [Selecta Math. (N.S.) 16 (2010), no. 4, 673-730]: "an adequate framework for doing noncommutative differential geometry is provided by the notion of wheelspace. Wheelspaces form a symmetric monoidal category". However, the category of wheelspaces turns out not to be monoidal. To address this, we introduce generalized wheelspaces, which do form a symmetric monoidal category and provide solid ground for the theory of wheelgebras. To support their first claim, Ginzburg and Schedler defined Poisson (Fock) wheelgebras in connection with Van den Bergh's double Poisson algebras via the Fock functor. We provide strong evidence to their claim by introducing symplectic wheelgebras and prove that the Fock functor sends smooth bisymplectic algebras, as defined by W. Crawley-Boevey, V. Ginzburg and P. Etingof, into our symplectic wheelgebras. In the process, we develop a Cartan calculus adapted to this wheeled context. Moreover, we present a wheeled version of the significant Van den Bergh functor, which facilitates a formalization of the Kontsevich-Rosenberg principle, bridging the noncommutative and commutative frameworks. After establishing that the classical Van den Bergh functor factors through our wheeled version, we show that symplectic Fock wheelgebras naturally induce symplectic algebras on representation schemes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.17764v1</guid>
      <category>math.QA</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RA</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Fern\'andez, Estanislao Herscovich</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A connected sum formula for embedded contact homology</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.01646</link>
      <description>arXiv:2305.01646v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Given two closed contact three-manifolds, one can form their contact connected sum via the Weinstein one-handle attachment. We study how pseudo-holomorphic curves in the symplectization behave under this operation. As a result, we give a connected sum formula for embedded contact homology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2305.01646v2</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luya Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
