<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.SG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SG</link>
    <description>math.SG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 04:03:16 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>On the mean indices of closed characteristics on dynamically convex star-shaped hypersurfaces in $\mathbb{R}^{2n}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04546</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04546v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we prove that for every dynamically convex compact star-shaped hypersurface $\Sigma\subset\mathbb{R}^{2n}$, there exist at least $\lfloor\frac{n+1}{2}\rfloor$ geometrically distinct closed characteristics possessing irrational mean indices provided the number of geometrically distinct closed characteristics on $\Sigma$ is finite, this improves Theorem 1.3 in \cite{LoZ} of Y. Long and C. Zhu by finding one more closed characteristic possessing irrational mean index when $n$ is odd. Moreover, there exist at least $\lfloor\frac{n+1}{2}\rfloor+1$ geometrically distinct closed characteristics such that the ratio of the mean indices of any two of them is a irrational number provided the number of geometrically distinct closed characteristics on $\Sigma$ is finite, this improves Theorem 1.2 in \cite{HuO} of X. Hu and Y. Ou when $n$ is odd. In particular, these estimates are sharp for $n=3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04546v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Dynamics of Invariant Graphs for Dissipative Twist Maps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.04938</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.04938v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For two-parameter families of dissipative twist maps, we study the dynamics of invariant graphs and the thresholds of their existence and breakdown. We obtain: (1) For arbitrary $C^1$-small perturbations, invariant graphs with prescribed rotation numbers can be realized through parameter adjustments; (2) The existence of almost sharp perturbations that trigger complete destruction of all invariant graphs; (3) When the perturbation lacks $C^1$-regularity, Lipschitz invariant graphs with non-differentiable points may persist despite the Lipschitz semi-norm satisfying the requirement of the normally hyperbolic invariant manifold theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.04938v1</guid>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Li, Lin Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shifted coisotropic structures for differentiable stacks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.09214</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.09214v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We introduce a notion of coisotropics on 1-shifted symplectic Lie groupoids (i.e. quasi-symplectic groupoids) using twisted Dirac structures and show that it satisfies properties analogous to the corresponding derived-algebraic notion in shifted Poisson geometry. In particular, intersections of 1-coisotropics are 0-shifted Poisson. We also show that 1-shifted coisotropic structures transfer through Morita equivalences, giving a well-defined notion for differentiable stacks. Most results are formulated with clean-intersection conditions weaker than transversality while avoiding derived geometry. Examples of 1-coisotropics that are not necessarily Lagrangians include Hamiltonian actions of quasi-symplectic groupoids on Dirac manifolds, and this recovers several generalizations of Marsden-Weinstein-Meyer's symplectic reduction via intersection and Morita transfer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.09214v3</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.aim.2025.110345</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Advances in Mathematics, Volume 475, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Maxence Mayrand</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The partial derivative of ratios of Schur polynomials and applications to symplectic quotients</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.19466</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.19466v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that a ratio of Schur polynomials $s_{\lambda}/s_{\rho}$ associated to partitions $\lambda$ and $\rho$ such $\lambda\subsetneq\rho$ has a negative partial derivative at any point where all variables are positive. This is accomplished by establishing an injective map between sets of pairs of skew semistandard Young tableaux that preserves the product of the corresponding monomials. We use this result and the description of the first Laurent coefficient of the Hilbert series of the graded algebra of regular functions on a linear symplectic quotient by the circle to demonstrate that many such symplectic quotients are not graded regularly diffeomorphic. In addition, we give an upper bound for this Laurent coefficient in terms of the largest two weights of the circle representation and demonstrate that all but finitely many circle symplectic quotients of each dimension are not graded regularly diffeomorphic to linear symplectic quotients by $\operatorname{SU}_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.19466v2</guid>
      <category>math.CO</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hans-Christian Herbig, Daniel Herden, Harper Kolehmainen, Christopher Seaton</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
