<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.SG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SG</link>
    <description>math.SG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jul 2025 01:28:23 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Exact Lagrangian fillability of 3-braid closures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16747</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16747v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We determine when a Legendrian quasipositive 3-braid closure in standard contact $\mathbb{R}^3$ admits an orientable or non-orientable exact Lagrangian filling. Our main result provides evidence for the orientable fillability conjecture of Hayden and Sabloff, showing that a 3-braid closure is orientably exact Lagrangian fillable if and only if it is quasipositive and the HOMFLY bound on its maximum Thurston-Bennequin number is sharp. Of possible independent interest, we construct explicit Legendrian representatives of quasipositive 3-braid closures with maximum Thurston-Bennequin number.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16747v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James Hughes, Jiajie Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intersection cohomology of Vinberg-Popov varieties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16492v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Vinberg-Popov variety of a simply connected reductive algebraic group $G$ is a singular affine variety that contains the basic affine space $G/U$ as a Zariski open subset. It is defined as the spectrum of the ring of functions on $G/U$, and can also be identified with the universal symplectic implosion for the maximal compact subgroup of $G$. We provide a recursive procedure for computing the intersection cohomology of this variety, with an emphasis on the case where $G = \operatorname{SL}_n$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16492v1</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.RT</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Dancer, Johan Martens, Nicholas Proudfoot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A note on a nontrivial connected component of the space of symplectic structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.16216</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.16216v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: This note provides the first example of a nontrivial connected component of the space of symplectic structures standard at infinity in dimension four.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.16216v2</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luya Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infinite connected components of the space of symplectic forms on ruled surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.14636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.14636v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We provide an infinite family of diffeomorphic symplectic forms on ruled surfaces, which are pairwise non-isotopic. This answers a uniqueness question regarding symplectic structures up to isotopy on closed symplectic four-manifolds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.14636v2</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianfeng Lin, Weiwei Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the blow-up formula of weighted stability for polarized toric manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.10082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.10082v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Let $X$ be a smooth projective toric variety, and let $\widetilde{X}$ denote the blow-up of $X$ at finitely many distinct tours-invariant points. This paper provides an explicit combinatorial formula for the Chow weight of $\widetilde{X}$ in terms of the base toric manifold $X$ and the symplectic cuts of its associated Delzant polytope. We apply this blow-up formula to the projective plane and compare Chow stability of toric blow-ups with that of blow-ups at general points. Furthermore, we derive the blow-up formula of the Futaki-Ono invariant, which serves an obstruction to asymptotic Chow semistability of a polarized toric manifold. In the final section, we extend our approach to study blow-up formulas for weighted (Chow/K-) stability using our combinatorial framework.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.10082v2</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>King Leung Lee, Naoto Yotsutani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Almost Hermitian structures on virtual moduli spaces of non-Abelian monopoles and applications to the topology of symplectic four-manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13809</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13809v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This work is a sequel to our previous monograph arXiv:2010.15789 (to appear in AMS Memoirs), where we initiated our program to prove that the Bogomolov-Miyaoka-Yau inequality holds for closed, symplectic four-manifolds and, more generally, for closed, smooth four-manifolds with a Seiberg-Witten basic class. This inequality was first proved for compact, complex surfaces of general type by Miyaoka (1977) and Yau (1978). Our approach uses a version of Morse theory for a natural Hamiltonian, the square of the $L^2$ norm of the coupled spinors, for the circle action on the moduli space of non-Abelian monopoles over a closed four-manifold. It has the aim of proving the existence of a projectively anti-self-dual connection on a rank-two Hermitian vector bundle over a blow-up of the four-manifold, where the first Pontrjagin number of the vector bundle is negative and greater than or equal to minus the Euler characteristic of the blown-up four-manifold. Our Morse theory argument relies on positivity of virtual Morse-Bott indices for critical points of Hamiltonians for circle actions on complex analytic spaces (or real analytic spaces that, locally, are sufficiently well-approximated by complex analytic model spaces), as developed by the first author in arXiv:2206.14710. In our application to the moduli space of non-Abelian monopoles, the critical points are fixed points of the circle action and thus represented by Seiberg-Witten monopoles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13809v3</guid>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paul M. N. Feehan, Thomas G. Leness</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Bordered contact invariants and half Giroux torsion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.14050</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.14050v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that there exist infinitely many closed contact 3-manifolds containing half Giroux torsion along a separating torus whose contact invariants do not vanish. This provides counterexamples to Ghiggini's conjecture and suggests that separating half Giroux torsion may not obstruct symplectic fillability. The main tools are the bordered contact invariants recently developed by the authors and the innermost contact structures on knot complements. We also show that there exists a closed contact 3-manifold containing convex torsion along a separating torus with non-vanishing contact invariant, which implies that $2\pi$ is the minimal amount of twisting necessary to ensure vanishing of the contact invariant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.14050v3</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jul 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hyunki Min, Konstantinos Varvarezos</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
