<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>math.SG updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SG</link>
    <description>math.SG updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/math.SG" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 02:08:31 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Hofer-continuous quasi-morphisms on Liouville manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23277v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We show that, given a complete Liouville manifold, any homogeneous quasi-morphism on its Hamiltonian group, which satisfies a strengthened version of Hofer continuity called stability, must vanish. This partially addresses a conjecture due to L. Polterovich.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23277v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.FA</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frol Zapolsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ECH capacities of concave singular toric domains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23429v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: By definition, a toric domain has a boundary contact manifold diffeomorphic to a three dimensional sphere. In the present work we extend the definition of the toric domains in dimension four so that it admits a contact manifold diffeomorphic to a lens space L(n, 1). We call them 'singular toric domains' since they naturally have an orbifold point. We calculate the ECH capacities for a specific subfamily of these singular toric domains that generalize the concave toric domains. Interestingly, even though we are calculating the capacities of an orbifold, the result can be adapted to study embedding problems in some of the desingularizations of these spaces, for example the unitary cotangent bundle of two dimensional sphere or the unitary cotangent bundle of projective plane.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23429v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Trejos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hyperbolic contact symplectic lifts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23740</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23740v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Given a complex manifold $M$ endowed with a holomorphic contact structure $V$, one can define a sub-Finsler pseudometric through holomorphic discs tangent to $V$. If the integrated pseudodistance is a distance, then $M$ is $V$-hyperbolic, a generalisation of Kobayashi hyperbolicity.
  In this paper, we focus on Reeb manifolds $M$, which are contact manifolds with a free holomorphic $\mathbb{C}$-action generated by a Reeb vector field. We show that every proper Reeb manifold is the total space of a {\sl contact symplectic lift}, that is, it admits a $\mathbb C$-principal bundle structure onto a complex manifold $S$ endowed with a $C^\infty$-exact holomorphic symplectic form $\omega$ so that the pull back of $\omega$ is related to the contact structure $V$ of $M$. Conversely, we prove that any $C^\infty$-exact holomorphic symplectic manifold is given as the base of a contact symplectic lift.
  We also prove that $M$ is (complete) $V$-hyperbolic if and only if $S$ is (complete) Kobayashi hyperbolic. This yields many new examples of $V$-hyperbolic manifolds.
  Finally, we study the automorphism group ${\sf Aut}_V M$ of those automorphisms of $M$ preserving $V$. In case $M$ is $V$-hyperbolic, this is a finite-dimensional Lie group, and we provide a classification in dimension $3$, where $2 \leq \dim_{\mathbb{R}} {\sf Aut}_V M \leq 7$, with the extremal upper case realised uniquely (up to natural equivalences) by the contact symplectic lift of the unit ball $\mathbb{B}^2$ endowed with the symplectic form $\frac{2}{(1-z)^3} dz \wedge dw$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23740v1</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.CV</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Filippo Bracci, Benjamin McKay, Riccardo Ugolini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbits and attainable Hamiltonian diffeomorphisms of mechanical Liouville equations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24960v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We study the approximate controllability problem for Liouville transport equations along a mechanical Hamiltonian vector field. Such PDEs evolve inside the orbit $$\mathcal{O}(\rho_0):=\left\{\rho_0\circ \Phi\mid \Phi\in {\rm DHam}(T^*M)\right\},\quad \rho_0\in L^r(T^*M,\mathbb{R}), \quad r\in[1,\infty),$$ where $\rho_0$ is the initial density and ${\rm DHam}(T^*M)$ is the group of Hamiltonian diffeomorphisms of the cotangent bundle manifold $T^*M$. The approximately reachable densities from $\rho_0$ are thus contained in $\overline{\mathcal{O}(\rho_0)}$, where the closure is taken with respect to the $L^r$-topology. Our first result is a characterization of $\overline{\mathcal{O}(\rho_0)}$ when the manifold $M$ is the Euclidean space $\mathbb{R}^d$ or the torus $\mathbb{T}^d$ of arbitrary dimension: $\overline{\mathcal{O}(\rho_0)}$ is the set of all the densities whose sub- and super-level sets have the same measure as those of $\rho_0$. This result is an approximate version, in the case of ${\rm DHam}(T^*M)$, of a theorem by J. Moser (Trans. Am. Math. Soc. 120: 286-294, 1965) on the group of diffeomorphisms.
  We then present two examples of systems, respectively on $M=\mathbb{R}^d$ and $\mathbb{T}^d$, where the small-time approximately attainable diffeomorphisms coincide with ${\rm DHam}(T^*M)$, respectively at the level of the group and at the level of the densities.
  The proofs are based on the construction of Hamiltonian diffeomorphisms that approximate suitable permutations of finite grids, and Poisson bracket techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24960v2</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.OC</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bettina Kazandjian, Eugenio Pozzoli, Mario Sigalotti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase spaces in field theory: Reduction vs. resolution</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.24450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.24450v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this note we review the concept of phase space in classical field theory, discussing several variations on the basic notion, as well as the relation between them. In particular we will focus on the case where the field theory admits local (gauge) symmetry, in which case the physical phase space of the system emerges after a (usually singular) quotient with respect to the action of the symmetry group. We will highlight the symplectic and Poisson underpinnings of the reduction procedure that defines a phase space, and discuss how one can replace quotients with graded smooth objects within classical field theory via cohomological resolutions, a practice that goes under the name of Batalin--Vilkovisky formalism. Special attention is placed on the reduction and resolution of gauge theories on manifolds with corners, which famously depend on a number of arbitrary choices. We phrase these choices in terms of homotopies for the variational bicomplex, and define a homotopy version of Noether's current and conservation theorem.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.24450v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aldo Riello, Michele Schiavina</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Holomorphic Floer theory and Donaldson-Thomas invariants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2210.17001</link>
      <description>arXiv:2210.17001v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present several expected properties of the holomorphic Floer theory of a holomorphic symplectic manifold. In particular, we propose a conjecture relating holomorphic Floer theory of Hitchin integrable systems and Donaldson-Thomas invariants of non-compact Calabi-Yau 3-folds. More generally, we conjecture that the BPS spectrum of a 4-dimensional $\mathcal{N}=2$ quantum field theory can be recovered from the holomorphic Floer theory of the corresponding Seiberg-Witten integrable system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2210.17001v2</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pierrick Bousseau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Robustly non-convex hypersurfaces in contact manifolds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.05979</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.05979v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We construct the first examples of hypersurfaces in any contact manifold of dimension 5 and larger that cannot be $C^2$-approximated by convex hypersurfaces, contrasting sharply with the foundational results of Giroux in dimension $3$ and Honda-Huang in the $C^0$ case. The main technical step is the first construction of a dynamical blender in the contact setting.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.05979v3</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math.DS</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Chaidez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalizing symplectic topology from 1 to 2 dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16223v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In symplectic topology one uses elliptic methods to prove rigidity results about symplectic manifolds and solutions of Hamiltonian equations on them, where the most basic example is given by geodesics on Riemannian manifolds. Harmonic maps from surfaces are the natural 2-dimensional generalizations of geodesics. In this paper, we give the corresponding generalization of symplectic manifolds and Hamiltonian equations, leading to a class of partial differential equations that share properties similar to Hamiltonian (ordinary) differential equations. Two rigidity results are discussed: a non-squeezing theorem and a version of the cuplength result for quadratic Hamiltonians on cotangent bundles. The proof of the latter uses a generalization of Floer curves, for which the necessary Fredholm and compactness results will be proven.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16223v2</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ronen Brilleslijper, Oliver Fabert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Darboux's Theorem in $p$-adic symplectic geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.15443</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.15443v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Let $p$ be a prime number. We derive an analog of Moser's Path Method for $p$-adic analytic manifolds and use it to prove a $p$-adic analog of Darboux's Theorem. Using it as a stepping stone we give a classification of second-countable $p$-adic analytic symplectic manifolds in terms of $p$-adic volume. This is a symplectic version of a classical result of Serre in $p$-adic analytic geometry from 1965. We also prove a $p$-adic version of Weinstein's generalization of Darboux's Theorem to neighborhoods of compact manifolds. Finally we find explicitly Darboux's coordinates for the physical models by Ablowitz-Ladik and Salerno of the Discrete Nonlinear Schr\"odinger equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.15443v2</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luis Crespo, \'Alvaro Pelayo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simple homotopy theory for Fukaya categories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05856</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05856v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a categorical framework for simple homotopy theory in Fukaya categories, based on the fundamental group of the ambient symplectic manifold. When the first Chern class vanishes, we show that any isomorphism in the Fukaya category of a Weinstein manifold has trivial Whitehead torsion. As an application, we prove that any pair of closed connected Lagrangians that are isomorphic in the Fukaya category of such Weinstein manifolds are simple homotopy equivalent, provided one of the Lagrangians is homotopy equivalent to the ambient symplectic manifold and their fundamental groups are isomorphic.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05856v2</guid>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yonghwan Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A proof of N.Takahashi's conjecture for $(\mathbb{P}^2,E)$ and a refined sheaves/Gromov-Witten correspondence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1909.02992</link>
      <description>arXiv:1909.02992v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We prove N.Takahashi's conjecture determining the contribution of each contact point in genus-$0$ maximal contact Gromov-Witten theory of $\mathbb{P}^2$ relative to a smooth cubic $E$. This is a new example of a question in Gromov-Witten theory which can be fully solved despite the presence of contracted components and multiple covers. The proof relies on a tropical computation of the Gromov-Witten invariants and on the interpretation of the tropical picture as describing wall-crossing in the derived category of coherent sheaves on $\mathbb{P}^2$, giving a translation of the original Gromov-Witten question into a known statement about Euler characteristics of moduli spaces of one-dimensional Gieseker semistable sheaves on $\mathbb{P}^2$.
  The same techniques allow us to prove a new sheaves/Gromov-Witten correspondence, relating Betti numbers of moduli spaces of one-dimensional Gieseker semistable sheaves on $\mathbb{P}^2$, or equivalently refined genus-$0$ Gopakumar-Vafa invariants of local $\mathbb{P}^2$, with higher-genus maximal contact Gromov-Witten theory of $(\mathbb{P}^2,E)$. The correspondence involves the non-trivial change of variables $y=e^{i \hbar}$, where $y$ is the refined/cohomological variable on the sheaf side, and $\hbar$ is the genus variable on the Gromov-Witten side. We explain how this correspondence can be heuristically motivated by a combination of mirror symmetry and hyperk\"ahler rotation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1909.02992v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>hep-th</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1215/00127094-2022-0095</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Pierrick Bousseau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Gromov-Witten approach to $G$-equivariant birational invariants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.07322</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.07322v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In arXiv:2404.19088, we initiated a program linking birational invariants with smooth ones and offering new interpretations of classical invariants, such as the Kervaire-Milnor invariants. Here, we rely on the profound geometric reasoning provided by Lupercio and Uribe in the early 00s to establish a connection between Chen-Ruan cohomology and several $G$-birational invariants introduced in the pioneering works Kontsevich, Kresch, Pestun, Tschinkel, along with presenting applications. Combined with the theory of atoms by Katzarkov, Kontsevich, Pantev, and Yu, the proposal in this paper program will lead to a theory of equivariant atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.07322v3</guid>
      <category>math.AG</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.DG</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Leonardo F. Cavenaghi, Lino Grama, Ludmil Katzarkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symplectic rational homology ball fillings of Seifert fibered spaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.09292</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.09292v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We characterize when some small Seifert fibered spaces can be the convex boundaries of symplectic rational homology balls and give strong restrictions for others to bound such manifolds. In particular, we show that the only spherical $3$-manifolds, oriented as links of the corresponding quotient singularities, which admit symplectic rational homology ball fillings, are the lens spaces $L(p^2,pq-1)$ previously identified by Lisca. In a different direction, we provide evidence for Gompf's conjecture that Brieskorn spheres do not bound Stein domains in $\mathbb{C}^2$. Finally, we establish restrictions on Lagrangian disk fillings of certain Legendrian knots in small Seifert fibered spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.09292v2</guid>
      <category>math.GT</category>
      <category>math.SG</category>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John B. Etnyre, Burak Ozbagci, B\"ulent Tosun</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
