<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 04:00:06 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Design of Amine-Functionalized Materials for Direct Air Capture Using Integrated High-Throughput Calculations and Machine Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13982v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Direct air capture (DAC) of carbon dioxide is a critical technology for mitigating climate change, but current materials face limitations in efficiency and scalability. We discover novel DAC materials using a combined machine learning (ML) and high-throughput atomistic modeling approach. Our ML model accurately predicts high-quality, density functional theory-computed CO$_{2}$ binding enthalpies for a wide range of nitrogen-bearing moieties. Leveraging this model, we rapidly screen over 1.6 million binding sites from a comprehensive database of theoretically feasible molecules to identify materials with superior CO$_{2}$ binding properties. Additionally, we assess the synthesizability and experimental feasibility of these structures using established ML metrics, discovering nearly 2,500 novel materials suitable for integration into DAC devices. Altogether, our high-fidelity database and ML framework represent a significant advancement in the rational development of scalable, cost-effective carbon dioxide capture technologies, offering a promising pathway to meet key targets in the global initiative to combat climate change.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13982v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Megan C. Davis, Wilton J. M. Kort-Kamp, Ivana Matanovic, Piotr Zelenay, Edward F. Holby</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase stability in the Hf-N and Zr-N systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14013v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hf and Zr nitrides are promising compounds for many technologically important areas, including high temperature structural applications, quantum computing and solar/optical applications. This article reports on a comprehensive first-principles statistical mechanics study of phase stability in the Hf-N and Zr-N binary systems. A high solubility of nitrogen in the hcp forms of Hf and Zr is predicted. The rocksalt forms of HfN and ZrN can also tolerate a high degree of off-stoichiometry through the introduction of nitrogen and metal vacancies. The Hf-N binary favors a family of stacking faulted parent crystal structures at intermediate nitrogen concentrations that host a unique form of short-range order among nitrogen interstitials and vacancies. These phases can accommodate some degree of configurational entropy and remain ordered to temperatures as high as 1200K.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14013v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonathan Li, Derick Ober, Anton Van der Ven</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DFT exploration of novel direct band gap semiconducting halide double perovskites, A2AgIrCl6 (A = Cs, Rb, K), for solar cells application</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14156v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Double perovskite halides are promising materials for renewable energy production, meeting the criteria to address energy scarcity issues. As a result, studying these halides could be useful for optoelectronic and solar cell applications. In this study, we investigated the structural, mechanical, thermodynamic, electronic, and optical properties of A2AgIrCl6 (A = Cs, Rb, K) double perovskite halides using density functional theory calculations with the full-potential linearized augmented plane-wave (FP-LAPW) approach, aiming to evaluate their suitability for renewable energy devices. The Goldsmith tolerance factor, octahedral factor, and new tolerance factor have confirmed the cubic stability of the predicted compounds. We have also verified the thermodynamic stability of these compounds by calculating the formation enthalpy, binding energy, and phonon dispersion curves. Additionally, Born-Huang stability requirements on stiffness constants confirmed the mechanical stability of the titled compounds. To predict the accurate optoelectronic properties, we employed the TB-mBJ potential. The electronic band structure calculations revealed that the titled halides exhibit a direct band gap semiconducting nature with values of 1.43 eV, 1.50 eV, and 1.55 eV for Cs2AgIrCl6, Rb2AgIrCl6, and K2AgIrCl6, respectively. Besides, all these compounds showed remarkably low effective electron masses, indicating their potential for high carrier mobility. Furthermore, the optical properties of A2AgIrCl6 (A = Cs, Rb, K) compounds demonstrated very low reflectivity and excellent light absorption coefficients (105 cm-1) in the visible light spectrum, suggesting their suitability as an absorbing layer in solar cells. The photoconductivity and absorption spectra of these compounds validate the accuracy of our band structure results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14156v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. A. Rayhan, M. M. Hossain, M. M. Uddin, S. H. Naqib, M. A Ali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-Confined Tunable Ferromagnetism on the Surface of a van der Waals Antiferromagnet NaCrTe2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14196</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14196v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The surface of three-dimensional materials provides an ideal and versatile platform to explore quantum-confined physics. Here, we systematically investigate the electronic structure of Na-intercalated CrTe2, a van der Waals antiferromagnet, using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy and ab-initio calculations. The measured band structure deviates from the calculation of bulk NaCrTe2 but agrees with that of ferromagnetic monolayer CrTe2. Consistently, we observe an unexpected exchange splitting of the band dispersions, persisting well above the N\'eel temperature of bulk NaCrTe2. We argue that NaCrTe2 features a quantum-confined 2D ferromagnetic state in the topmost surface layer due to strong ferromagnetic correlation in the CrTe2 layer. Moreover, the exchange splitting and the critical temperature can be controlled by surface doping of alkali-metal atoms, suggesting a feasible tunability of the surface ferromagnetism. Our work not only presents a simple platform to explore tunable 2D ferromagnetism but also provides important insights into the quantum-confined low-dimensional magnetic states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14196v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.nanolett.4c01542</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nano Lett. 24, 9832-9838 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yidian Li, Xian Du, Junjie Wang, Runzhe Xu, Wenxuan Zhao, Kaiyi Zhai, Jieyi Liu, Houke Chen, Yiheng Yang, Nicolas C. Plumb, Sailong Ju, Ming Shi, Zhongkai Liu, Jiangang Guo, Xiaolong Chen, Yulin Chen, Lexian Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning the Electronic Properties of Two-Dimensional Lepidocrocite Titanium Dioxide Based Heterojunctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14293</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14293v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) heterostructures reveal novel physicochemical phenomena at different length scales, that are highly desirable for technological applications. We present a comprehensive density functional theory study of van der Waals (vdW) heterostructures constructed by stacking 2D TiO2 and 2D MoSSe monolayers to form TiO2-MoSSe heterojunction. The heterostructure formation is found to be exothermic, indicating stability. We find that by varying the atomic species at the interfaces the electronic structure can be considerably altered, due to the differences in charge transfer, arising from the inherent electronegativity of the atoms. We demonstrate that the heterostructures possess a type II or type III band alignment, depending on the atomic termination of MoSSe at the interface. The observed charge transfer occurs from MoSSe to TiO2. Our results suggest that Janus interface enables the tuning of electronic properties, providing understanding of the possible applications of the TiO2-MoSSe heterostructure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14293v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsomega.3c06786</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>ACS Omega 8 (2023), 45056-45064</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Kati Asikainen, Matti Alatalo, Marko Huttula, S. Assa Aravindh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zero-point renormalization of the bandgap, mass enhancement, and spectral functions: Validation of methods and Verification of first-principles codes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14319v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Verification and validation of methods and first-principles software are at the core of computational solid-state physics but are too rarely addressed. We compare four first-principles codes: Abinit, Quantum ESPRESSO, EPW, ZG, and three methods: (i) the Allen-Heine-Cardona theory using density functional perturbation theory (DFPT), (ii) the Allen-Heine-Cardona theory using Wannier function perturbation theory (WFPT), and (iii) an adiabatic non-perturbative frozen-phonon method. For these cases, we compute the real and imaginary parts of the electron-phonon self-energy in diamond and BAs, including dipoles and quadrupoles when interpolating. We find excellent agreement between software that implements the same formalism as well as good agreement between the DFPT and WFPT methods. Importantly, we find that the Deybe-Waller term is momentum dependent which impacts the mass enhancement, yielding approximate results when using the Luttinger approximations. Finally, we compare the electron-phonon spectral functions between Abinit and EPW and find excellent agreement even away from the band edges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14319v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel Ponc\'e, Jae-Mo Lihm, Cheol-Hwan Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimizing Supercell Structures for Heisenberg Exchange Interaction Calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14356</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14356v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this paper, we introduce an efficient, linear algebra-based method for optimizing supercell selection to determine Heisenberg exchange parameters from DFT calculations. A widely used approach for deriving these parameters involves mapping DFT energies from various magnetic configurations within a supercell to the Heisenberg Hamiltonian. However, periodic boundary conditions in crystals limit the number of exchange parameters that can be extracted. To identify supercells that allow for more exchange parameters, we generate all possible supercell sizes within a specified range and apply null space analysis to the coefficient matrix derived from mapping DFT results to the Heisenberg Hamiltonian. By selecting optimal supercells, we significantly reduce computational time and resource consumption. This method, which involves generating and analyzing supercells before performing DFT calculations, has demonstrated a reduction in computational costs by 1-2 orders of magnitude in many cases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14356v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mojtaba Alaei, Artem R. Oganov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fragmented charged domain wall below the tetragonal-orthorhombic phase transition in BaTiO3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14476</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14476v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ferroelectric charged domain walls are known for their high electrical conductivity, making them promising candidates for applications in modern electronics. A remarkably high conductivity and nominal charge density has been found in the head-to-head ferroelastic domain wall of tetragonal barium titanate. Interestingly, the conductivity of this domain wall decreases by several orders of magnitude when the temperature drops down below about 5 degrees Celsius when the tetragonal phase transforms to the orthorhombic one. We thus explored the evolution of the ferroelectric charged domain walls in BaTiO3 crystals while they undergo this phase transition by in-situ optical microscopy. Our results reveal that, below the phase transition, the domains adjacent to charge domain walls become twinned and the head-to-head charged domain wall transforms into a superdomain wall, which is broken into alternating micron-scale segments with and without the excess bound charge. These observations naturally explains the observed loss of the domain wall conductivity below the phase transition because the macroscopic conductive channel along such fragmented superdomain wall is disrupted.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14476v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Petr S. Bednyakov, Iegor Rafalovskyi, Jiri Hlinka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-Principles Calculation of Alloy Scattering and n-type Mobility in Strained GeSn</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14478</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14478v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We use first-principles electronic-structure theory to determine the intra- and inter-valley electron-alloy scattering parameters in n-type GeSn alloys. These parameters are used to determine the alloy scattering contributions to the n-type electron mobility of GeSn at $300K$ and $15K$ using a first iteration of the Boltzmann transport equation in the relaxation time approximation. For unstrained GeSn, we find that a Sn concentration of at least $13.5\%$ is needed to achieve an electron mobility greater than that of Ge. Our results show that the mobility of GeSn can be over $25$ times higher than the mobility of Ge, or $10^5$ cm$^2$/(Vs). At $15K$, less than $6\%$ Sn incorporation into Ge quadruples its mobility, which suggests GeSn has potential applications as a high mobility 2D electron gas. Applying biaxial tensile strain to GeSn further increases the mobility and at a lower Sn content than in unstrained GeSn.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14478v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Sewell, Felipe Murphy-Armando</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kinetics, thermodynamics, and catalysis of the cation incorporation into GeO$_2$, SnO$_2$, and (Sn$_x$Ge$_{1-x}$)O$_2$ during suboxide molecular beam epitaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rutile GeO$_2$ is a promising ultra-wide bandgap semiconductor for future power electronic devices whose alloy with the wide bandgap semiconductor rutile-SnO$_2$ enables bandgap engineering and the formation of heterostructure devices. The (Sn$_x$Ge$_{1-x}$)O$_2$ alloy system is in its infancy and molecular beam epitaxy (MBE) is a well-suited technique for its thin-film growth, yet presents challenges in controlling the alloy composition and growth rate. To understand and mitigate this challenge, the present study comprehensively investigates the kinetics and thermodynamics of suboxide incorporation into GeO$_2$, SnO$_2$, and (Sn$_x$Ge$_{1-x}$)O$_2$ during suboxide MBE, the latest development in oxide MBE using suboxide sources. We find suboxide MBE to simplify the growth kinetics, offering better control over growth rates than conventional MBE but without supporting cation-driven oxide layer etching. During binary growth, SnO incorporation is kinetically favored due to its higher oxidation efficiency and lower vapor pressure compared to those of GeO. In (Sn$_x$Ge$_{1-x}$)O$_2$ growth, however, the GeO incorporation is preferred and the SnO incorporation is suppressed, indicating a catalytic effect, where SnO promotes GeO incorporation through cation exchange. The origin of this cation exchange is likely thermodynamic yet calls for further theoretical studies. Our experimental study provides guidance for controlling the growth rate and alloy composition of (Sn$_x$Ge$_{1-x}$)O$_2$ in suboxide MBE, highlighting the impact of the substrate temperature and active oxygen flux besides that of the mere SnO:GeO flux stoichiometry. The results are likely transferable to further physical and chemical vapor deposition methods, such as conventional and hybrid MBE, pulsed laser deposition, mist- or metalorganic chemical vapor deposition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14527v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenshan Chen, Kingsley Egbo, Joe Kler, Andreas Falkenstein, Jonas L\"ahnemann, Oliver Bierwagen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>La$_2$O$_3$Mn$_2$Se$_2$: a correlated insulating layered d-wave altermagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14542</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14542v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets represent a new class of magnetic phases without net magnetization that are invariant under a combination of rotation and time reversal. Unlike conventional collinear antiferromagnets (AFM), altermagnets could lead to new correlated states and important material properties deriving from their non-relativistic spin-split band structure. Indeed, they are the magnetic analogue of unconventional superconductors and can yield spin polarized electrical currents in the absence of external magnetic fields, making them promising candidates for next-generation spintronics. Here, we report altermagnetism in the correlated insulator, magnetically-ordered tetragonal oxychalcogenide, La$_2$O$_3$Mn$_2$Se$_2$. Symmetry analysis reveals a $\mathit{d}_{x^2 - y^2}$-wave type spin momentum locking, which is supported by density functional theory (DFT) calculations. Magnetic measurements confirm the AFM transition below $\sim$166 K while neutron pair distribution function analysis reveals a 2D short-range magnetic order that persists above the N\'eel temperature. Single crystals are grown and characterized using X-ray diffraction, optical and electron microscopy, and microRaman spectroscopy to confirm the crystal structure, stoichiometry, and uniformity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14542v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chao-Chun Wei, Xiaoyin Li, Sabrina Hatt, Xudong Huai, Jue Liu, Birender Singh, Kyung-Mo Kim, Rafael M. Fernandes, Paul Cardon, Liuyan Zhao, Thao T. Tran, Benjamin M. Frandsen, Kenneth S. Burch, Feng Liu, Huiwen Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature-Dependent Design of BCC High Entropy Alloys: Integrating Deep Learning, CALPHAD, and Experimental Validation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14614</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14614v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Due to their compositional complexity, refractory multi-principal element alloys (RMPEAs) exhibit a diverse range of material properties, making them highly suitable for several applications. Importantly, single-phase BCC RMPEAs are known for their superior strength. Nevertheless, identifying the stability of single-phase BCC is challenging because of the vast compositional space of RMPEAs. In this study, we develop a deep learning framework that predicts the fraction of RMPEA phases with high accuracy at several temperatures. Using the accurate predictive framework, we navigate the compositional space of Ti, Fe, Al, V, Ni, Nb and Zr elements to search for potentially stable single-phase BCC RMPEAs and provide design insights that can guide the synthesis of new RMPEAs in experiments. Furthermore, we develop a mathematical equation that enables the rapid and accurate identification of single-phase BCC RMPEAs with high accuracy. The machine learning (ML) model is finally evaluated against a high-fidelity experimental data from literature, confirming that our model accurately predicts the constituent phases of the experimental samples while provides insights that are laborious to extract from experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14614v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. K. Shargh, C. D. Stiles, J. A. El-Awady</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the Robustness of Machine Learning Models in Predicting Thermodynamic Properties: a Case of Searching for New Quasicrystal Approximants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13873</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13873v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Despite an artificial intelligence-assisted modeling of disordered crystals is a widely used and well-tried method of new materials design, the issues of its robustness, reliability, and stability are still not resolved and even not discussed enough. To highlight it, in this work we composed a series of nested intermetallic approximants of quasicrystals datasets and trained various machine learning models on them correspondingly. Our qualitative and, what is more important, quantitative assessment of the difference in the predictions clearly shows that different reasonable changes in the training sample can lead to the completely different set of the predicted potentially new materials. We also showed the advantage of pre-training and proposed a simple yet effective trick of sequential training to increase stability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13873v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fedor S. Avilov, Roman A. Eremin, Semen A. Budennyy, Innokentiy S. Humonen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evidence of Floquet electronic steady states in graphene under continuous-wave mid-infrared irradiation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13930</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13930v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Light-induced phenomena in materials can exhibit exotic behavior that extends beyond equilibrium properties, offering new avenues for understanding and controlling electronic phases. So far, non-equilibrium phenomena in solids have been predominantly explored using femtosecond laser pulses, which generate transient, ultra-fast dynamics. Here, we investigate the steady non-equilibrium regime in graphene induced by a continuous-wave (CW) mid-infrared laser. Our transport measurements reveal signatures of a long-lived Floquet phase, where a non-equilibrium electronic population is stabilized by the interplay between coherent photoexcitation and incoherent phonon cooling. The observation of non-equilibrium steady states using CW lasers opens a new regime for low-temperature Floquet phenomena, paving the way toward Floquet engineering of steady-state phases of matter.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13930v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yijing Liu, Christopher Yang, Gabriel Gaertner, John Huckabee, Alexey V. Suslov, Gil Refael, Frederik Nathan, Cyprian Lewandowski, Luis E. F. Foa Torres, Iliya Esin, Paola Barbara, Nikolai G. Kalugin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Explosive rigidity percolation in origami</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13945</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13945v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Origami, the traditional art of paper folding, has revolutionized science and technology in recent years and has been found useful in various real-world applications. In particular, origami-inspired structures have been utilized for robotics and mechanical information storage, in both of which the rigidity control of origami plays a crucial role. However, most prior works have only considered the origami design problem using purely deterministic or stochastic approaches. In this paper, we study the rigidity control of origami using the idea of explosive percolation. Specifically, to turn a maximally floppy origami structure into a maximally rigid origami structure, one can combine a random sampling process of origami facets and some simple selection rules, which allow us to exploit the power of choices and significantly accelerate or delay the rigidity percolation transition. We further derive simple formulas that connect the rigidity percolation transition effects with the origami pattern size and the number of choices, thereby providing an effective way to determine the optimal number of choices for achieving prescribed rigidity percolation transition accuracy and sharpness. Altogether, our work paves a new way for the rigidity control of mechanical metamaterials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13945v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rongxuan Li, Gary P. T. Choi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Intrinsic and Extrinsic $p$-type Dopability of Atomically Thin $\beta$-TeO$_2$ from First Principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14100</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14100v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) $\beta$-TeO$_2$ has gained attention as a promising material for optoelectronic and power device applications, thanks to its transparency and high hole mobility. However, the underlying mechanism behind its $p$-type conductivity and dopability remains unclear. In this study, we investigate the intrinsic and extrinsic point defects in monolayer and bilayer $\beta$-TeO$_2$, the latter of which has been experimentally synthesized, using the HSE+D3 hybrid functional. Our results reveal that most intrinsic defects are unlikely to contribute to $p$-type doping in 2D $\beta$-TeO$_2$. Moreover, Si contamination could further impair $p$-type conductivity. Since the point defects do not contribute to $p$-type conductivity, we propose two possible mechanisms for hole conduction: hopping conduction via localized impurity states, and substrate effects. We also explored substitutional $p$-type doping in 2D $\beta$-TeO$_2$ with 10 trivalent elements. Among these, the Bi dopant is found to exhibit a relatively shallow acceptor transition level. However, most dopants tend to introduce deep localized states, where hole polarons become trapped at Te's lone pairs. Interestingly, monolayer $\beta$-TeO$_2$ shows potential advantages over bilayers due to reduced self-compensation effects for $p$-type dopants. These findings provide valuable insights into defect engineering strategies for future electronic applications involving 2D $\beta$-TeO$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14100v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Costa-Amaral, Soungmin Bae, Vu Thi Ngoc Huyen, Yu Kumagai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Simultaneous study of acoustic and optic phonon scattering of electrons and holes in undoped $\mathrm{GaAs}$/$\mathrm{Al_{x} Ga_{1-x} As}$ heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14288</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14288v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The study of phonon coupling in doped semiconductors via electrical transport measurements is challenging due to unwanted temperature-induced effects such as dopant ionisation and parallel conduction. Here, we study phonon scattering in 2D electrons and holes in the $1.6-92.5$K range without the use of extrinsic doping, where both acoustic and longitudinal optic (LO) phonons come into effect. We use undoped GaAs/$\mathrm{Al_{x} Ga_{1-x} As}$ heterostructures and examine the temperature dependence of the sample resistivity, extracting phonon coupling constants and the LO activation energy. Our results are consistent with results obtained through approaches other than transport measurements, and highlight the benefit of this approach for studying electron-phonon and hole-phonon coupling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14288v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Y. Ashlea Alava, K. Kumar, C. Harsas, P. Mehta, P. Hathi, C. Chen, D. A. Ritchie, A. R. Hamilton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Bond-Based Machine Learning Model for Molecular Polarizabilities and A Priori Raman Spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14498</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14498v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The use of machine learning (ML) algorithms in molecular simulations has become commonplace in recent years. There now exists, for instance, a multitude of ML force field algorithms that have enabled simulations approaching ab initio level accuracy at time scales and system sizes that significantly exceed what is otherwise possible with traditional methods. Far fewer algorithms exist for predicting rotationally equivariant, tensorial properties such as the electric polarizability. Here, we introduce a kernel ridge regression algorithm for machine learning of the polarizability tensor. This algorithm is based on the bond polarizability model and allows prediction of the tensor components at the cost similar to that of scalar quantities. We subsequently show the utility of this algorithm by simulating gas phase Raman spectra of biphenyl and malonaldehyde using classical molecular dynamics simulations of these systems performed with the recently developed MACE-OFF23 potential. The calculated spectra are shown to agree very well with the experiments and thus confirm the expediency of our algorithm as well as the accuracy of the used force field. More generally, this work demonstrates the potential of physics-informed approaches to yield simple yet effective machine learning algorithms for molecular properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14498v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakub K. Sowa, Peter J. Rossky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chains of magnetic ions in NH$_4^+$-intercalated vanadium pentoxide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14562</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14562v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We explore the electronic and magnetic properties of NH$_4^+$-intercalated vanadium pentoxide (NH$_4^+$-V$_2$O$_5$), a material that has been identified as a promising cathode for aqueous zinc-ion batteries. Density Functional Theory (DFT) calculations incorporating the Hubbard U correction reveal that NH$_4^+$-V$_2$O$_5$ is an antiferromagnetic insulator with an energy gap of 1.97 eV. The introduction of NH$_4^+$ ions into the V$_2$O$_5$ structure results in significant structural distortions, leading to the formation of magnetic vanadium ions (V$^{4+}$, $3d^1$) and non-magnetic ions (V$^{5+}$, $3d^0$). The magnetic vanadium ions are organized into chains with antiferromagnetic order along the $a$-axis. Our findings indicate that NH$_4^+$-V$_2$O$_5$ exhibits strong electron correlation effects and negligible interchain magnetic interactions, rendering it a promising candidate for a one-dimensional magnetic van der Waals system. This work provides insights into the electronic and magnetic behaviors of NH$_4^+$-V$_2$O$_5$, with implications for its potential applications in energy storage technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14562v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anna A. Anisimova, Yaroslav M. Plotnikov, Dmitry M. Korotin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Onset and impact of plastic deformation in granular compaction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.14636</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.14636v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The role of plastic deformation in the high-pressure compaction of granular material is investigated using bonded particle model simulations. Grains are discretized into a set of computational particles connected by pairwise bonds. Bonds are harmonic up to a plastic onset strain $\epsilon_p$ above which they yield, capping out at a maximum force and producing an elastic-perfectly-plastic-like mechanical response in grains. Packings containing over one thousand monodisperse spherical grains are isotropically compacted to different packing fractions to quantify how decreasing $\epsilon_p$ softens the rise in pressure and impacts effective elastic properties of the confined system. By isolating the relative decrease in pressure due to plasticity, we find data can be collapsed across a wide range of values of $\epsilon_p$ suggesting that relatively simple mathematical descriptions may capture plasticity's effect in granular compaction. Lastly, we study the microscopic statistics of local strains in grains and connect their evolution to the observed macroscopic behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.14636v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joel T. Clemmer, Jeremy B. Lechman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain-induced dynamic control over the population of quantum emitters in two-dimensional materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.10273</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.10273v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The discovery of quantum emitters (QEs) in two-dimensional materials (2D) has triggered a surge of research to assess their suitability for quantum photonics. While their microscopic origin is still the subject of intense studies, position-controlled QEs are routinely fabricated using static strain gradients, which are used to drive excitons towards localized regions of the crystal where quantum light emission takes place. However, the use of strain in a dynamic fashion to control the brightness of single-photon sources in 2D materials has not been explored so far. In this work, we address this challenge by introducing a novel hybrid semiconductorpiezoelectric device in which WSe2 monolayers are integrated onto piezoelectric pillars that provide both static and dynamic strains. The static strains are first used to induce the formation of QEs, whose emission shows photon anti-bunching. Their energy and brightness are then controlled via the application of voltages to the piezoelectric pillars. Numerical simulations combined with drift-diffusion equations show that these effects are due to a strain-induced modification of the confining-potential landscape, which in turn leads to a net redistribution of excitons among the different QEs. Our work provides a method to dynamically control the brightness of single photon sources based on 2D materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.10273v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giuseppe Ronco, Abel Mart\'inez-Su\'arez, Davide Tedeschi, Matteo Savaresi, Aurelio Hierro-Rodr\'iguez, Stephen McVitie, Sandra Stroj, Johannes Aberl, Mortiz Brehm, Victor M. Garc\'ia-Su\'arez, Michele B. Rota, Pablo AlonsoGonz\'alez, Javier Mart\'in-S\'anchez, Rinaldo Trotta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electron-phonon coupling in ferromagnetic Fe-Co alloys from first principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.12650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.12650v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The measured magnetization dynamics of ferromagnetic iron--cobalt Fe$_{1-x}$Co$_x$ alloys show a strong dependence on the alloy composition, especially near $x=0.25$. Here, we calculate from first principles the electron-phonon coupling strength in Fe$_{1-x}$Co$_x$ alloys for compositions ranging from $x=0$ to $x=0.75$. We find a strong, spin-dependent variation of the electron-phonon coupling strength with alloy composition, with a minimum near $x=0.25$. We analyze the variation of the electron-phonon interaction with composition, as a function of electron spin, density of states, electron-phonon matrix elements, character of electron wavefunction at the Fermi level, orbital-resolved strength of the phonon perturbing potential, and phonon frequencies. We calculate the electron-phonon energy transfer coefficients, and find that they are in qualitative agreement with the phenomenological electron-phonon energy transfer coefficient deduced from magnetization dynamics experiments. Our findings show that variations in the composition of ferromagnetic alloys can significantly alter the magnetization dynamics and transport properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.12650v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kevin Moseni, Richard B Wilson, Sinisa Coh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrical Control Grain Dimensionality with Multilevel Magnetic Anisotropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.18256</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.18256v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In alignment with the increasing demand for larger storage capacity and longer data retention, electrical control of magnetic anisotropy has been a research focus in the realm of spintronics. Typically, magnetic anisotropy is determined by grain dimensionality, which is set during the fabrication of magnetic thin films. Despite the intrinsic correlation between magnetic anisotropy and grain dimensionality, there is a lack of experimental evidence for electrically controlling grain dimensionality, thereby impeding the efficiency of magnetic anisotropy modulation. Here, we demonstrate an electric field control of grain dimensionality and prove it as the active mechanism for tuning interfacial magnetism. The reduction in grain dimensionality is associated with a transition from ferromagnetic to superparamagnetic behavior. We achieve a non-volatile and reversible modulation of the coercivity in both the ferromagnetic and superparamagnetic regimes. Subsequent electrical and elemental analysis confirms the variation in grain dimensionality upon the application of gate voltages, revealing a transition from a multidomain to a single-domain state accompanied by a reduction in grain dimensionality. Furthermore, we exploit the influence of grain dimensionality on domain wall motion, extending its applicability to multilevel magnetic memory and synaptic devices. Our results provide a strategy for tuning interfacial magnetism through grain size engineering for advancements in high-performance spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.18256v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsnano.4c00422</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shengyao Li, Sabpreet Bhatti, Siew Lang Teo, Ming Lin, Xinyue Pan, Zherui Yang, Peng Song, Wanghao Tian, Xinyu He, Jianwei Chai, Xian Jun Loh, Qiang Zhu, S. N. Piramanayagam, Xiao Renshaw Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum embedding study of strain and charge induced Stark effects on the NV$^{-}$ center in diamond</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07772</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07772v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The NV$^{-}$ color center in diamond has been demonstrated as a powerful nanosensor for quantum metrology due to the sensitivity of its optical and spin properties to external electric, magnetic, and strain fields. In view of these applications, we use quantum embedding to derive a many-body description of strain and charge induced Stark effects on the NV$^{-}$ center. We quantify how strain longitudinal to the axis of NV$^{-}$ shifts the excited states in energy, while strain with a component transverse to the NV$^{-}$ axis splits the degeneracies of the $^{3}E$ and $^{1}E$ states. The largest effects are for the optically relevant $^{3}E$ manifold, which splits into $E_{x}$ and $E_{y}$ with transverse strain. From these responses we extract strain susceptibilities for the $E_{x/y}$ states within the quasi-linear regime. Additionally, we study the many-body dipole matrix elements of the NV$^{-}$ and find a permanent dipole 1.64 D at zero strain, which is somewhat smaller than that obtained from recent density functional theory calculations. We also determine the transition dipole between the $E_{x}$ and $E_{y}$ and how it evolves with strain.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07772v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel I. L\'opez-Morales, Joanna M. Zajac, Johannes Flick, Carlos A. Meriles, Cyrus E. Dreyer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TCAD Parameters for 4H-SiC: A Review</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.06798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.06798v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper we review the models and their parameters to describe the relative permittivity, bandgap, impact ionization, mobility, charge carrier recombination/effective masses and incomplete dopand ionization of 4H silicon carbide in computer simulations. We aim to lower the entrance barrier for newcomers and provide a critical evaluation of the status quo to identify shortcomings and guide future research. The review reveals a rich set of often diverging values in literature based on a variety of calculation and measurement methods. Although research for all the selected parameters is still active, we show that sometimes old values or those determined for other kinds of silicon carbide are commonly used.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.06798v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J\"urgen Burin, Philipp Gaggl, Simon Waid, Andreas Gsponer, Thomas Bergauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning Electric Polarization via Exchange Striction Interaction in CaMn$_7$O$_{12}$ by Sr-Doping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.12041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.12041v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetoelectric materials displaying strong magnetically induced polarization have attracted considerable interest due to their potential applications in spintronics and various fast electrically controlled magnetic devices. CaMn$_7$O$_{12}$ (CMO) stands out for its giant spin-induced ferroelectric polarization. However, the origin of the induced electric polarization in CMO remains highly controversial and continues to be a subject of ongoing debate. In this paper, through room temperature X-ray powder diffraction (XRPD), temperature-dependent magnetic susceptibility, and thermally stimulated depolarizing current (TSDC) measurements, we provide experimental evidence for a route to tune the magnetically induced polarization by modifying the exchange-striction in CMO via Sr-doping. Our findings demonstrate that the large and broad current peaks observed near the first magnetic phase transition ($T_N1 \sim 90$ K) indicate polarization contributions from both thermally stimulated depolarization current (TSDC) and intrinsic magnetically induced electric polarization. We suggest that this reduction in induced electric polarization in CMO originates from the increase in the Mn$^{3+}$ -- O -- Mn$^{4+}$ bond angle due to Sr$^{2+}$ doping, weakening the exchange-striction interaction. Meanwhile, the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya (DM) effect determines the direction of the induced electric polarization. Our result sheds light on understanding the intriguing giant-induced polarization in CMO and similar compounds with complex magnetic structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.12041v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Nonato, S. Y. Villar, J. Mira, Mar\'ia A. Se\~nar\'is-Rodr\'iguez, Manuel S\'anchez and\'ujar, J. Agostinho Moreira, A. Almeida, R. X. Silva, C. W. A. Paschoal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Million-atom heat transport simulations of polycrystalline graphene approaching first-principles accuracy enabled by neuroevolution potential on desktop GPUs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.13535</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.13535v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: First-principles molecular dynamics simulations of heat transport in systems with large-scale structural features are challenging due to their high computational cost. Here, using polycrystalline graphene as a case study, we demonstrate the feasibility of simulating heat transport with near first-principles accuracy in systems containing over 1.4 million atoms, achievable even with consumer desktop GPUs. This is enabled by the highly efficient neuroevolution potential (NEP) approach, as implemented in the open-source GPUMD package. Leveraging the NEP model's accuracy and efficiency, we quantify the reduction in thermal conductivity of polycrystalline graphene due to grain boundaries with varying grain sizes, resolving contributions from in-plane and out-of-plane (flexural) phonon modes. Additionally, we find that grain boundaries can lead to finite thermal conductivity even under significant tensile strain, in contrast to the divergent behavior observed in pristine graphene under similar conditions, indicating that grain boundaries may play a crucial role in thermal transport in low-dimensional momentum-conserving systems. These findings could offer insights for interpreting experimental observations, given the widespread presence of both large-scale grain boundaries and external strains in real materials. The demonstrated ability to simulate millions of atoms with near-first-principles accuracy on consumer desktop GPUs using the NEP approach will help make large-scale high-fidelity atomistic simulations more accessible to the broader research community.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.13535v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoye Zhou, Yuqi Liu, Benrui Tang, Junyuan Wang, Haikuan Dong, Xiaoming Xiu, Shunda Chen, Zheyong Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>3D Heisenberg universality in the Van der Waals antiferromagnet NiPS$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2310.07948</link>
      <description>arXiv:2310.07948v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Van der Waals (vdW) magnetic materials are comprised of layers of atomically thin sheets, making them ideal platforms for studying magnetism at the two-dimensional (2D) limit. These materials are at the center of a host of novel types of experiments, however, there are notably few pathways to directly probe their magnetic structure. We report the magnetic order within a single crystal of NiPS$_3$ and show it can be accessed with resonant elastic X-ray diffraction along the edge of the vdW planes in a carefully grown crystal by detecting structurally forbidden resonant magnetic X-ray scattering. We find the magnetic order parameter has a critical exponent of $\beta\sim0.36$, indicating that the magnetism of these vdW crystals is more adequately characterized by the three-dimensional (3D) Heisenberg universality class. We verify these findings with first-principle density functional theory, Monte-Carlo simulations, and density matrix renormalization group calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2310.07948v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rajan Plumley, Sougata Mardanya, Cheng Peng, Johannes Nokelainen, Tadesse Assefa, Lingjia Shen, Nicholas Burdet, Zach Porter, Alexander Petsch, Aidan Israelski, Hongwei Chen, Jun Sik Lee, Sophie Morley, Sujoy Roy, Gilberto Fabbris, Elizabeth Blackburn, Adrian Feiguin, Arun Bansil, Wei-Sheng Lee, Aaron Lindenberg, Sugata Chowdhury, Mike Dunne, Joshua J. Turner</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
