<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2024 02:42:20 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Time-dependent density-functional study of hydrogen adsorption and scattering on graphene surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06939</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06939v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Time-dependent density-functional theory simulations are performed to examine the effects of varying incident points and kinetic energies of hydrogen atom projectiles on a graphene-like structure. The simulations reveal that the incident point significantly influences the hydrogen atom's kinetic energy post-interaction, the vibrational dynamics of the graphene lattice, and the scattering angles. Incident points that do not directly collide with carbon atoms result in prolonged interaction times and reduced energy transfer, increasing the likelihood of overcoming the graphene's potential energy barrier and hydrogen atom adsorption. The study also explores the role of initial kinetic energy in determining adsorption, scattering, or transmission outcomes. These results emphasize the critical influence of initial parameters on the hydrogenation process and provide a foundation for future experimental validation and further exploration of hydrogen-graphene interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06939v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel S. Taylor, Nicholas Skoufis, Hongbo Du, Cody Covington, Kalman Varga</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flexible and Efficient Semi-Empirical DFTB Parameters for Electronic Structure Prediction of 3D, 2D Iodide Perovskites and Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07016v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Density Functional Tight-Binding (DFTB), an approximative approach derived from Density Functional Theory (DFT), has the potential to pave the way for simulations of large periodic or non-periodic systems. We have specifically tailored DFTB parameters to enhance the accuracy of electronic band gap calculations in both 3D and 2D lead-iodide perovskites, at a significantly reduced computational cost relative to state-of-the-art ab initio calculations. Our electronic DFTB parameters allow computing not only the band gap but also effective masses of perovskite materials with reasonable accuracy compared to existing experimental data and state-of-the-art DFT calculations. The electronic band structures of vacancy-ordered and, lead- and iodide- deficient perovskites are also explored. Additionally, we demonstrate the efficiency of DFTB in computing electronic band alignments in perovskite heterostructures. The DFTB-based approach is anticipated to be beneficial for studying large-scale systems such as heterostructures and nanocrystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07016v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junke Jiang, Tammo van der Heide, Simon Th\'ebaud, Carlos Ra\'ul Lien-Medrano, Arnaud Fihey, Laurent Pedesseau, Claudio Quarti, Marios Zacharias, George Volonakis, Mikael Kepenekian, B\'alint Aradi, Michael A. Sentef, Jacky Even, Claudine Katan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Recent progress on the solid-state materials for photocatalysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07110</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07110v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hydrogen is considered an alternative source of energy to fossil fuels for the fulfilment of current energy demands. Photocatalysis initiates the hydrogen evolution reaction which is believed to be the greenest approach to produce hydrogen through clean, safe, and environmentally friendly methods. In this Review, we focus mainly on the comprehensive analysis of the 2D and 3D bulk materials on the basis of their superior photocatalytic activities. However, several literatures have reported the superiority of 2D material over the bulk counterpart in terms of photocatalytic performance owing to their ultrathin layered structures, offer a higher surface-to-volume ratio, flexibility, large active sites for incoming H2O molecules, etc. We have thoroughly analysed the drawbacks of various hydrogen production methods focusing on the photocatalysis mechanism and the processes of evolution of hydrogen. In addition to this, a short overview of the various solid-state materials for photocatalysis that have been developed so far and their mechanisms are discussed. Lastly, we have discussed the recent developments in 2D materials and their composites as promising photocatalysts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07110v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. D. Tamang, S. Gurung, R. Zosiamliana, L. Celestine, B. Chettri, Jitendra Pal Singh, A. Laref, Mukhriddin E. Tursunov, Avazbek T. Dekhkonov, D. P. Rai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unlocking the Ion Migration in Solid-State Electrolytes via Path Entropy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07115v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Promoting ionic diffusion by reducing activation energy, as a thermally activated process following the Arrhenius relation, is a fundamental principle in designing materials for electrochemical batteries. However, this scenario is constrained by the enthalpy-entropy compensation mechanism (Meyer-Neldel Rule, MNR), which is ubiquitously observed in biological process and chemical reactions. This sets a limitation of promoting ion transport by reducing activation enthalpy. Notably, certain solid-state electrolytes characterized by disordering or degenerate saddle states exhibit anomalous behaviours and disobey MNR, suggesting the existence of an elusive source of entropy. Herein we propose the concept of path entropy (Sp) governs kinetic process in dense and mobile ionic systems such as lithium diffusion in solid-state electrolytes. By integrating Markov state method, well-tempered metadynamics, and machine learning-based softness analysis, we elucidate the intricate relationship between fast ionic hopping and microscopic local environments in inorganic thiophosphates. The Sp accounts for a strong fluctuation of free energy landscape perceived by Li cations and enables an assessment of their collective diffusion behaviour as well. A unified framework is established for handling time-evolved and group-collective ionic kinetics, which exploits pathway frustration, transcending common "static" scenario in traditional entropy-driven approach based on compositional multiplicity. This provides a new dimension for connecting structural disorder and the freedom of ionic diffusion pathways, suitable for a wide range of ionic-driven applications such as battery, superionic conductors and neuromorphic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07115v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiye Guan, Kaiyang Wang, Jingjie Yeo, Yongqing Cai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Absence of ferromagnetic instability and weak spin-orbit coupling effect in AV$_3$Sb$_5$ (A = Cs, Rb, and K)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07190v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A family of V-based kagome metals AV$_3$Sb$_5$ (A = Cs, Rb, K) presents an intriguing platform for exploring the interplay of time-reversal symmetry breaking, nontrivial topological bands, and electron correlations, resulting in a range of exotic quantum states, including the anomalous Hall effect, unconventional charge density waves, and superconductivity. These features prompt critical questions regarding the roles of magnetism and spin-orbit coupling (SOC) in these systems. Our density functional theory (DFT) calculations demonstrate a notable sensitivity of the magnetic properties to the choice of $k$-point mesh used in Brillouin zone integrations. Specifically, we find that using a dense $k$-point mesh yields a nonmagnetic pristine phase characterized by paramagnetic susceptibility, consistent with the recently observed Pauli paramagnetic behavior in single crystalline samples at high temperatures. In contrast, a coarser $k$-point mesh significantly increases the density of states at the Fermi level, inducing a ferromagnetic instability that satisfies the Stoner criterion. Moreover, our results show that the effect of SOC on both the geometric and electronic structures is minimal, with only a slight gap opening at the Dirac points, indicating a weak SOC influence in these materials. Importantly, our DFT band structure calculations closely align with angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy data, reinforcing the notion of weak electron correlations in these kagome metals. This refined understanding challenges recent theoretical assertions that the interplay of magnetism, SOC, and electron correlations is essential for determining the nature of charge density waves in AV$_3$Sb$_5$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07190v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chongze Wang, Shichang Yao, Shuyuan Liu, Bing Wang, Liangliang Liu, Yu Jia, Jun-Hyung Cho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion behavior of Li ions in crystalline and amorphous Li-Zr-O and Li-Nb-O phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07296</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07296v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Li containing transition metal oxides are known as good ionic conductors. Performing classical molecular dynamics simulations, the diffusion behavior of Li ions is investigated in crystalline and amorphous phases with the stoichiometries Li$_2$ZrO$_3$ and LiNbO$_3$. We first demonstrate the stability of the crystal structures for the used interatomic potential model and then analyze the amorphous phases, which result from melt-and-quench simulations, in terms of radial distribution functions. Diffusivities of Li ions in those systems are obtained from a statistical Arrhenius analysis of mean square displacement curves at different temperatures. The crystalline phase of Li$_2$ZrO$_3$ exhibits two well-defined migration mechanisms: vacancy-mediated migration is dominant below and a site exchange of Li ions above a crossover region between about 1700 and 1800 K. The latter mechanism also prevails in the amorphous phases of Li$_2$ZrO$_3$ with a strongly reduced activation energy, which is due to a smaller equilibrium separation of Li ions as in the crystal structure. This migration mechanism is found in amorphous LiNbO$_3$, too.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07296v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Daniel Mutter, Diego A. Pantano, Christian Els\"asser, Daniel F. Urban</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In-poor IGZO: superior resilience to hydrogen in forming gas anneal and PBTI</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07362v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Integrating In-Ga-Zn-oxide (IGZO) channel transistors in silicon-based ecosystems requires the resilience of the channel material to hydrogen treatment. Standard IGZO, containing 40% In (metal ratio) suffers from degradation under forming gas anneal (FGA) and hydrogen (H) driven positive bias temperature instability (PBTI). We demonstrate scaled top-gated ALD transistors with an In-poor (In $\le$ 17%) IGZO channel that show superior resilience to hydrogen compared to the In-rich (In=40%) counterpart. The devices, fabricated with a 300-mm FAB process with dimensions down to $W_\mathrm{CH} \times L_\mathrm{TG} = 80 \times 40 \mathrm{nm}^2$, show excellent stability in 2-hour 420$^\circ$C forming gas anneal ($0.06 \le \left| \Delta V_{\mathrm{TH}} \right| \le 0.33\mathrm{V}$) and improved resilience to H in PBTI at 125$^\circ$C (down to no detectable H-induced $V_{\mathrm{TH}}$ shift) compared to In-rich devices. We demonstrate that the device degradation by H in the FGA is different from the H-induced VTH instability in PBTI, namely oxygen scavenging by H and H release from a gate-dielectric into the channel, respectively, and that resilience to H in one process does not automatically translate to resilience to H in the other one. This significant improvement in IGZO resilience to H enables the use of FGA treatments during fabrication needed for silicon technology compatibility, as well as further scaling and 3D integration, bringing IGZO-based technologies closer to mass production.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07362v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Kruv, M. J. van Setten, A. Chasin, D. Matsubayashi, H. F. W. Dekkers, A. Pavel, Y. Wan, K. Trivedi, N. Rassoul, J. Li, Y. Jiang, S. Subhechha, G. Pourtois, A. Belmonte, G. Sankar Kar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Stoichiometry and Thickness of Epitaxial SrTiO$_{3}$ on Silicon (001): an Investigation of Physical, Optical and Electrical Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07395</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07395v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strontium titanate (SrTiO$_{3}$, STO) stands out as a promising material for various electronic applications thanks to its exceptional dielectric properties. Molecular beam epitaxy is one of the few techniques which allows epitaxial growth of STO directly on industry-relevant silicon substrates. However, maintaining precise stoichiometry and high crystalline quality in this process remains a significant challenge. Establishing this is essential to obtain STO with bulk-like dielectric properties and to minimize leakage current and optical absorbance. In this study, the importance of cationic stoichiometry and the effect of thickness are investigated for STO thin films epitaxially grown on silicon. We employed real-time reflection high-energy electron diffraction (RHEED) as a feedback loop mechanism to counteract Sr source oxidation and maintain a constant flux. Additionally, high-temperature post-growth annealing treatments in O$_{2}$ were investigated to promote layer relaxation and reduce oxygen vacancy concentration, thereby improving the physical, electrical, and optical properties of stoichiometric STO. As a result, high-quality STO thin films exceeding 100 nm were successfully fabricated featuring a bulk-like out-of-plane lattice parameter and refractive index, as well as rocking curve full width at half maximum below 0.2{\deg}, smooth surface (R$_{q}$ &lt; 0.2 nm) and a leakage current density below 1E-7 A/cm$^{2}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07395v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andries Boelen, Marina Baryshnikova, Anja Ulrich, Kamal Brahim, Joris Van de Vondel, Christian Haffner, Clement Merckling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Band Offsets at \beta/{\gamma}-$\mathrm{Ga}_{2}\mathrm{O}_{3}$ Interface</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07576</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07576v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ultrawide bandgap semiconductor gallium oxide (Ga2O3) and its polymorphs have recently attracted increasing attention across physics, materials science, and electronics communities. In particular, the self-organized formation of the beta/gamma-Ga2O3 double polymorph structures was demonstrated recently [A. Azarov et al., Nat. Commun. 14, 4855 (2023)], paving the way for prospective applications of such structures in electronics. Consequently, determining the conduction band offset in such structures is crucial since it dictates the behavior of conduction electrons at the interface and, consequently, the potential functionality of such interfaces. Thus, in this work, we calculate the band offsets at the beta/gamma-Ga2O3 interface using density functional theory in correlation with the data provided by the experimental atomistic interface analysis. Specifically, to unravel the strain state of the beta/gamma-Ga2O3 interface, nanoscale strain maps were recorded using high-resolution transmission electron microscopy. In its turn, theoretically, lineup potential and vacuum alignment methods were used to analyze the band offsets, with and without strain, at the beta/gamma-Ga2O3 interface. Altogether, the collected results suggest that the band offsets between the beta and gamma phases are likely not exceeding a few hundred meV, remaining highly sensitive to the strain state at the interface. At this end, we conclude that even though the formation of a two-dimensional electron gas (2DEG) at the beta/gamma interface is theoretically possible, the gradual strain relaxation--if it occurs as a function of the distance from the interface--poses a significant challenge, as it may shift the 2DEG localization or even reduce the overall probability of its formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07576v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huan Liu, Ilja Makkonen, Calliope Bazioti, Junlei Zhao, Alexander Azarov, Andrej Kuznetsov, Flyura Djurabekova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical studies of melanin films as a material for solar light absorbers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07609</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07609v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study investigates optical and electrical properties of thin melanin films self-organized grown from water solutions of eumelanin extracted from edible plants. The melanin films exhibit the characteristics of a transparent low conductive polymer with stable in time electrical parameters. The films demonstrate indirect allowed optical transitions, an optical band gap E_g = 1.7 eV and a phonon energy {\hbar \omega} = 0.185 eV as well as a high absorption coefficient in the ultraviolet range, which highlight the film potential for applications as light-absorbing layers in photovoltaic solar energy converters. Analysis of infrared transmission spectra evidences presence of a significant amount of OH groups in the films, pointing to their hydrophilicity, which may have an effect on the film electrical conductivity. It is hypothesized as well that the ratio of sp^3 to sp^2 hybridized CH_n bonds influences the films' optical and electrical properties and that higher concentration of the sp^2 bonds may increase the conductivity due to the enhanced {\pi}-electron delocalization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07609v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Obukhova, M. Semenenko, M. Dusheiko, S. Davidenko, Ye. S. Davidenko, S. S. Davidenko, S. Malyuta, S. Shahan, O. S. Pylypchuk, P. Mochuk, M. Voitovych, T. Kuzmenko, A. Sarikov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatiotemporal imaging of nonlinear optics in van der Waals waveguides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07640</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07640v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Van der Waals (vdW) semiconductors have emerged as promising platforms for efficient nonlinear optical conversion, including harmonic and entangled photon generation. Although major efforts are devoted to integrating vdW materials in nanoscale waveguides for miniaturization, the realization of efficient, phase-matched conversion in these platforms remains challenging. To address this challenge, we develop a far-field ultrafast imaging method to track the propagation of both fundamental and harmonic waves within vdW waveguides with extreme spatiotemporal resolution. Our approach allows systematic optimization of nonlinear conversion by determining the phase-matching angles, mode profiles, and losses in waveguides without a priori knowledge of material properties. We focus on light propagation in slab waveguides of rhombohedral-stacked MoS2, an emerging vdW semiconductor with giant nonlinear susceptibility. Our results reveal that these waveguides support birefringent phase-matching, demonstrating the material's potential for efficient on-chip nonlinear optics. This work establishes spatiotemporal imaging of light propagation in waveguides as an incisive and general method to identify new materials and architectures for efficient nonlinear nanophotonics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07640v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ding Xu, Zhi Hao Peng, Chiara Trovatello, Shan-Wen Cheng, Xinyi Xu, Aaron Sternbach, Dmitri N. Basov, P. James Schuck, Milan Delor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Role of Electron Correlation Beyond the Active Space in Achieving Quantitative Predictions of Spin-Phonon Relaxation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07749</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07749v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Single-molecule magnets (SMMs) are promising candidates for molecular-scale data storage and processing due to their strong magnetic anisotropy and long spin relaxation times. However, as temperature rises, interactions between electronic states and lattice vibrations accelerate spin relaxation, significantly limiting their practical applications. Recently, ab initio simulations have made it possible to advance our understanding of phonon-induced magnetic relaxation, but significant deviations from experiments have often been observed. The description of molecules' electronic structure has been mostly based on complete active space self-consistent field (CASSCF) calculations, and the impact of electron correlation beyond the active space remains largely unexplored. In this study, we provide the first systematic investigation of spin-phonon relaxation in SMMs with post-CASSCF multiconfigurational methods, specifically CAS followed by second-order perturbation theory and multiconfiguration pair-density functional theory. Taking Co(II)- and Dy(III)-based SMMs as case studies, we analyze how electron correlation influences spin-phonon relaxation rates across a range of temperatures, comparing theoretical predictions with experimental observations. Our findings demonstrate that post-CASSCF treatments make it possible to achieve quantitative predictions for Co(II)-based SMMs. For Dy(III)-based systems, however, accurate predictions require consideration of additional effects, underscoring the urgent necessity of further advancing the study of the effects of electronic correlation in these complex systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07749v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Soumi Haldar, Lorenzo A. Mariano, Alessandro Lunghi, Laura Gagliardi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structural, Electronic, and Li-ion Adsorption Properties of PolyPyGY Explored by First-Principles and Machine Learning Simulations: A New Multi-Ringed 2D Carbon Allotrope</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07753</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07753v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) carbon materials have been intensively investigated because of their distinctive structural framework and electronic behaviors as alternatives in energy conversion and storage applications. This study proposes a novel 2D carbon allotrope, Polymerized Pyracyclene Graphyne (PolyPyGY), characterized by a multi-ringed structure with 4-, 5-, 6-, 8-, and 16-membered rings comprising a porous structure. Using first-principles calculations and machine-learning techniques, we explore its structural, electronic, mechanical, optical, and lithium-ion storing properties. The vibrational properties assessed through the density functional perturbation theory framework confirm its structural stability. Moreover, ab initio molecular dynamics simulations at 1000 K demonstrate its thermal resilience, with no bond breaking or reconfiguration observed. The electronic band structure reveals a metallic nature, and the material exhibits anisotropic elastic properties, with Young's modulus varying between 421 and 664 GPa, suggesting good mechanical stability. Furthermore, lithium diffusion studies indicate low energy barriers (0.05-0.9 eV) and a high diffusion coefficient ( $&gt;$ 6 $\times$ 10$^{-6}$ cm$^{2}$/s), along with a stable open circuit voltage of 1.2 V. These results highlight PolyPyGY's potential as a highly effective and durable anode material for lithium-ion batteries, featuring rapid Li-ion diffusion, stable intercalation, and consistent performance during charge and discharge cycles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07753v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>K. A. L. Lima, D. A. da Silva, G. D. Amvame Nze, F. L. Lopes de Mendon\c{c}a, M. L. Pereira Jr, L. A. Ribeiro Jr</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Onset of wavenumber bandgaps via alternating Willis coupling signs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06798</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06798v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This article introduces a methodology for inducing wavenumber bandgaps via alternating signs of Willis coupling. A non-reciprocal wave equation of Willis-type is considered, and the wave dispersion analyses are carried out via the transfer matrix method. Further, reversing Willis-coupling signs is proven to yield reciprocal band structures with wavenumber bandgaps, and their width and limits are analytically quantified. Similarities between materials with reversed-sign Willis coupling and bi-layered phononic crystals are noted, followed by concluding remarks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06798v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hasan B. Al Ba'ba'a</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FE-PINNs: finite-element-based physics-informed neural networks for surrogate modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07126</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07126v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a method whereby the finite element method is used to train physics-informed neural networks that are suitable for surrogate modeling. The method is based on a custom convolutional operation called stencil convolution which leverages the inverse isoparametric map of the finite element method. We demonstrate the performance of the method in several training and testing scenarios with linear boundary-value problems of varying geometries. The resulting neural networks show reasonable accuracy when tested on unseen geometries that are similar to those used for training. Furthermore, when the number of training geometries is increased the testing errors systematically decrease, demonstrating that the neural networks learn how to generalize as the training set becomes larger. Further extending the method to allow for variable boundary conditions, properties, and body forces will lead to a general-purpose surrogate modeling framework that can leverage existing finite element codes for training.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07126v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pranav Sunil, Ryan B. Sills</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>X-ray magnetic circular dichroism and resonant inelastic X-ray scattering explained: role of many-body correlation and mixed-valence fluctuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07204v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: X-ray magnetic circular dichroism (XMCD) and resonant inelastic X-ray scattering with magnetic circular dichroism (RIXS-MCD) provide unparalleled insights into the electronic and magnetic dynamics of complex materials. Yet, their spectra remain challenging to interpret due to intricate many-body interactions. Here, we introduce a theoretical framework based on the Anderson impurity model, fully incorporating charge transfer (CT) and core-valence exchange correlation (CVEC) effects. Using epitaxial ferromagnetic La0.7Sr0.3MnO3 film as a model system, we capture elusive spectral features, demonstrating the necessity of CT inclusion for resolving XMCD subpeaks and revealing the profound impact of CVEC on RIXS-MCD spectra. Our approach not only successfully mirrors experimental results but also opens new avenues for exploring spin, orbital, and charge excitations in 3d transition metals and other correlated materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07204v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Beom Hyun Kim, Sang-Jun Lee, H. Huang, D. Lu, S. S. Hong, S. Lee, P. Abbamonte, Y. I. Joe, P. Szypryt, W. B. Doriese, D. S. Swetz, J. N. Ullom, C. -C. Kao, J. -S. Lee, Bongjae Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Little to lose: the case for a robust European green hydrogen strategy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07464</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07464v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The EU targets 10 Mt of green hydrogen production by 2030, but has not committed to targets for 2040. Green hydrogen competes with carbon capture and storage, biomass and imports in reaching emissions reductions; earlier studies have demonstrated the great uncertainty in future cost-optimal development of green hydrogen. In spite of this, we show that Europe risks little by setting green hydrogen production targets at around 25 Mt by 2040. Employing an extensive scenario analysis combined with novel near-optimal techniques, we find that this target results in systems that are within 10% of cost-optimal in most considered scenarios. Setting concrete targets is important in order to resolve significant uncertainty which hampers investments. Targeting green hydrogen reduces the dependence on carbon capture and storage and green fuel imports, making for a more robust European climate strategy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07464v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koen van Greevenbroek, Johannes Schmidt, Marianne Zeyringer, Alexander Horsch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>All-optical polarization control and routing by nonlinear interferometry at the nanoscale</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07714</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07714v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Optical metasurfaces are rapidly establishing as key-enabling platforms for nanophotonics applications. Along with the ability of taming light in subwavelength thicknesses, they can feature multiple functionalities in one device. The generation and control of light polarization by metasurfaces already provided a route towards ultracompact polarimetry devices in the linear regime. If translated to the nonlinear optical regime it may become a key-enabling tool in nonlinear imaging, optical holography and sensing. Here, we report the experimental ultrafast all-optical polarization modulation of upconverted light by all-dielectric metasurfaces via nonlinear interferometry. By controlling the relative phase between a pump beam at $\omega$ and its frequency-double replica at 2$\omega$, we can set the phase relation between two frequency-degenerate upconverted processes at 3$\omega$ $-$ Sum-Frequency Generation (SFG) and Third-Harmonic Generation (THG) $-$ stemming from an AlGaAs metasurface. By exploiting the opposite parity of the two nonlinear process and tuning their relative powers, we can achieve modulation of the polarization states of the light emitted at 3$\omega$ between linear and circular states with a degree of circular polarization (DOCP) up to 83$\%$. In particular, circularly polarized light features opposite handedness symmetrically located in the Fourier space, at coincidence with the first diffraction orders of the metasurface. Moreover, by toggling the phase delay by $\pi$, the handedness can be fully switched between the diffraction. Our work adds an additional layer of modulation in polarization beyond intensity to all-optical routing with precise phase control. The capability to route circular polarization states in the k-space holds significant potential for chiral sensing and advanced imaging techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07714v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yigong Luan, Attilio Zilli, Agostino Di Francescantonio, Vincent Vinel, Paolo Biagioni, Lamberto Du\`o, Aristide Lema\^itre, Giuseppe Leo, Michele Celebrano, Marco Finazzi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is the Mg-related GaN blue luminescence deep-level an MgO surface state?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2309.17212</link>
      <description>arXiv:2309.17212v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Mg is currently the only p-type dopant in technological use in GaN. Its incorporation into the GaN lattice is difficult. It requires a thermal treatment that only partially activates the Mg. To achieve moderate p-type doping requires high doses of Mg that mostly remain inactive. High p-type doping is thus typically achieved at the cost of certain lattice distortion and the creation of defects. Using low-temperature surface photovoltage spectroscopy, we obtain a wide spectrum of optical transitions within the bandgap of Mg-doped GaN. The results reveal an optical transition from the valence band into a deep trap around 0.49 eV above the valence band, along with what appears to be a complimentary transition from the same trap into the conduction band observed at 2.84 eV (coinciding with the energy of the famous Mg-related GaN blue luminescence). The similar shape of the spectra, their complimentary energies within the GaN gap and their opposite nature (hole vs. electron trap) appear to be more than a coincidence suggesting that this is an Mg-related surface state. The density of charge we calculate for this surface state is about 2x10^12 cm-2. We suggest that these small amounts of surface-segregated Mg partially oxidize during the growth and further oxidize during the consecutive Mg-activation heat treatment. This minute quantity of oxidized surface Mg should be about enough to form an Mg-related surface state. Etching the GaN with HCl is shown to affect the photovoltage at the blue-luminescence-related energy. Finally, we show that pure MgO powder produces the same blue luminescence even at the absolute absence of GaN.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2309.17212v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Or Haim Chaulker, Yury Turkulets, Ilan Shalish</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transfer Learning in Materials Informatics: structure-property relationships through minimal but highly informative multimodal input</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2401.09301</link>
      <description>arXiv:2401.09301v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work we propose simple, effective and computationally efficient transfer learning approaches for structure-property relation predictions in the context of materials, with highly informative input from different modalities. As materials properties stand from their electronic structure, representations are extracted directly from datasets of electronic charge density profile images using Neural Networks. We demonstrate transferability of the existing pre-trained Convolutional Neural Networks and Large Language Models knowledge to physics domain data, exploring a wide set of compositions for the regression of energetics- or structure- related properties, and the role of semantic crystallographic information in the context of multimodal approaches. We test the applicability of the CLIP multimodal model, and employ as well a training protocol for building a more interpretable and versatile stacked custom solution from different pre-trained modalities. The study offers a promising avenue for enhancing the effectiveness of descriptor identification in physical systems, shedding light on the power of multimodal transfer learning for materials property prediction. Instead of using the well-established GNN-based approaches, we explore the transfer learning of image- and text-based architectures, which can impact decision making for new low-cost AI methods in the field of Materials and Chemoinformatics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2401.09301v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dario Massa, Grzegorz Kaszuba, Stefanos Papanikolaou, Piotr Sankowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ferroelectricity at the extreme thickness limit in the archetypal antiferroelectric PbZrO$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.14176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2402.14176v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Size-driven transition of an antiferroelectric into a polar ferroelectric or ferrielectric state is a strongly debated issue from both experimental and theoretical perspectives. While critical thickness limits for such transitions have been explored, a bottom-up approach in the ultrathin limit considering few atomic layers could provide insight into the mechanism of stabilization of the polar phases over the antipolar phase seen in bulk PbZrO$_3$. Here, we use first-principles density functional theory to predict the stability of polar phases in Pt/PbZrO$_3$/Pt nanocapacitors. In a few atomic layer thick slabs of PbZrO$_3$ sandwiched between Pt electrodes, we find that the polar phase originating from the well established R3c phase of bulk PbZrO$_3$ is energetically favorable over the antipolar phase originating from the Pbam phase of bulk PbZrO$_3$. The famous triple-well potential of antiferroelectric PbZrO$_3$ is modified in the nanocapacitor limit in such a way as to swap the positions of the global and local minima, stabilizing the polar phase relative to the antipolar one. The size effect is decomposed into the contributions from dimensionality reduction, surface charge screening, and interfacial relaxation, which reveals that it is the creation of well-compensated interfaces that stabilizes the polar phases over the antipolar ones in nanoscale PbZrO$_3$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2402.14176v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikhilesh Maity, Milan Haddad, Nazanin Bassiri-Gharb, Amit Kumar, Lewys Jones, Sergey Lisenkov, Inna Ponomareva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Understanding chiral charge-density wave by frozen chiral phonon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.08982</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.08982v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Charge density wave (CDW) is discovered within a wide interval in solids, however, its microscopic nature is still not transparent in most realistic materials, and the recently studied chiral ones with chiral structural distortion remain unclear. In this paper, we try to understand the driving forces of chiral CDW transition by chiral phonons from the electron-phonon coupling scenario. We use the prototypal monolayer 1T-TiSe$_2$ as a case study to unveil the absence of chirality in the CDW transition and propose a general approach, i.e., symmetry-breaking stimuli, to engineer the chirality of CDW in experiments. Inelastic scattering patterns are also studied as a benchmark of chiral CDW (CCDW, which breaks the mirror/inversion symmetry in 2D/3D systems). We notice that the anisotropy changing of Bragg peak profiles, which is contributed by the soft chiral phonons, can show a remarkable signature for CCDW. Our findings pave a path to understanding the CCDW from the chiral phonon perspective, especially in van der Waals materials, and provide a powerful way to manipulate the chirality of CDW.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.08982v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41524-024-01440-1</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Zhang, S., Luo, K. &amp; Zhang, T. Understanding chiral charge-density wave by frozen chiral phonon. npj Comput Mater 10, 264 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Shuai Zhang, Kaifa Luo, Tiantian Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hydrogen Diffusion in Magnesium Using Machine Learning Potentials: a comparative study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.21088</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.21088v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding and accurately predicting hydrogen diffusion in materials is challenging due to the complex interactions between hydrogen defects and the crystal lattice. These interactions span large length and time scales, making them difficult to address with standard ab initio techniques. This work addresses this challenge by employing accelerated machine learning (ML) molecular dynamics simulations through active learning. We conduct a comparative study of different ML-based interatomic potential schemes, including VASP, MACE, and CHGNet, utilizing various training strategies such as on-the-fly learning, pre-trained universal models, and fine-tuning.By considering different temperatures and concentration regimes, we obtain hydrogen diffusion coefficients and activation energy values which align remarkably well with experimental results, underlining the efficacy and accuracy of ML-assisted methodologies in the context of diffusive dynamics. Particularly, our procedure significantly reduces the computational effort associated with traditional transition state calculations or ad-hoc designed interatomic potentials. The results highlight the limitations of pre-trained universal solutions for defective materials and how they can be improved by fine-tuning. Specifically, fine-tuning the models on a database produced during on-the-fly training of VASP ML force-field allows the retrieving of DFT-level accuracy at a fraction of the computational cost.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.21088v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Angeletti, Luca Leoni, Dario Massa, Luca Pasquini, Stefanos Papanikolaou, Cesare Franchini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Precise large-scale chemical transformations on surfaces: deep learning meets scanning probe microscopy with interpretability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.20014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.20014v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Scanning Probe Microscopy (SPM) techniques have shown great potential in fabricating nanoscale structures endowed with exotic quantum properties achieved through various manipulations of atoms and molecules. However, precise control requires extensive domain knowledge, which is not necessarily transferable to new systems and cannot be readily extended to large-scale operations. Therefore, efficient and autonomous SPM techniques are needed to learn optimal strategies for new systems, in particular for the challenge of controlling chemical reactions and hence offering a route to precise atomic and molecular construction. In this paper, we developed a software infrastructure named AutoOSS (\textbf{Auto}nomous \textbf{O}n-\textbf{S}urface \textbf{S}ynthesis) to automate bromine removal from hundreds of Zn(II)-5,15-bis(4-bromo-2,6-dimethylphenyl)porphyrin (\ch{ZnBr2Me4DPP}) on Au(111), using neural network models to interpret STM outputs and deep reinforcement learning models to optimize manipulation parameters. This is further supported by Bayesian Optimization Structure Search (BOSS) and Density Functional Theory (DFT) computations to explore 3D structures and reaction mechanisms based on STM images.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.20014v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nian Wu, Markus Aapro, Joakim S. Jestil\"a, Robert Drost, Miguel Mart{\i}nez Garc{\i}a, Tomas Torres, Feifei Xiang, Nan Cao, Zhijie He, Giovanni Bottari, Peter Liljeroth, Adam S. Foster</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Short-Range Order Based Ultra Fast Large-Scale Modeling of High-Entropy Alloys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18906</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18906v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: High-Entropy Alloys (HEAs) exhibit complex atomic interactions, with short-range order (SRO) playing a critical role in determining their properties. Traditional methods, such as Monte Carlo (MC) based ATAT and SCRAPs, and hybrid Monte Carlo-Molecular Dynamics (MC-MD), are often constrained by system size and computational inefficiency, limiting their applicability for large-scale modeling. We introduce PyHEA, a Python based toolkit with a high-performance C++ core, designed to efficiently model HEAs through a combination of global and local search algorithms, incremental SRO calculations, and GPU acceleration. PyHEA delivers an impressive speedup of more than 333,000x and 10,000x over state-of-the-art tools ATAT and SCRAPs respectively, ensuring accurate SRO calculations with unprecedented efficiency. In practical applications, PyHEA successfully modeled a 256,000-atom Fe-Mn-Cr-Co alloy, replicating literature results and reducing computational time from days to seconds with GPU acceleration, achieving over 1,000x speedup compared to hybrid MC-MD approaches. This huge breakthrough in computational efficiency revolutionizes HEA modeling by bridging theoretical predictions and practical applications, opening new horizons for the design of next-generation HEAs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18906v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caimei Niu, Lifeng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-throughput computational screening of small, eco-friendly, molecular crystals for sustainable piezoelectric materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06449</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06449v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Organic molecular crystals are ideally placed to become next-generation piezoelectric materials due to their diverse chemistries that can be used to engineer tailor-made solid-state assemblies. Using crystal engineering principles, and techniques such as co-crystallisation, these materials can be engineered to have a wide range of electromechanical properties. For materials that have been structurally characterised by methods such as X-Ray Diffraction, computational chemistry is an effective tool to predict their electromechanical properties, allowing researchers to screen these molecular crystals and identify materials best suited to their chosen application. Here we present our database of small molecular crystals, and their Density Functional Theory (DFT) predicted electromechanical properties, CrystalDFT (https://actuatelab.ie/CrystalDFT). We highlight the broad range of electromechanical properties amongst this primary dataset, and in particular, the high number of crystals that have a naturally occurring longitudinal d33 constant. This longitudinal electromechanical coupling is a prerequisite for several conventional sensing and energy harvesting applications, the presence of which is notably rare amongst the literature on biomolecular crystal piezoelectricity to date.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06449v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shubham Vishnoi, Geetu Kumari, Robert Guest, Pierre-Andr\'e Cazade, Sarah Guerin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable ultrastrong magnon magnon coupling and spin Hall magnetoresistance in a van der Waals antiferromagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.15558</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.15558v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Antiferromagnetic (AFM) magnons and the manipulation of magnetisation via spin currents in van der Waals (vdW) materials offer substantial potential for applications in magnonics and spintronics. In this study, we demonstrate ultrastrong magnon-magnon coupling in the GHz regime within a vdW AFM, achieving a maximum normalised coupling strength of 0.89. Our investigation shows the tunability of coupling strength through temperature-dependent magnetic anisotropies. We compare coupling strength values derived from gap size with those calculated directly through the coupling parameter, showing that gap size as a measure of coupling strength is limited when intrinsic symmetry breaking induced magnon mode coupling is present. Additionally, analytical calculations show the possibility to reach the deep-strong coupling regime, with normalised coupling strengths greater than 1 by tuning the anisotropy values. Finally, we report on spin Hall magnetoresistance in a vdW AFM-based device and study the field and temperature dependence. These findings highlight the transformative potential of vdW AFMs in advancing the field of spin-based technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.15558v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>C. W. F. Freeman, Z. Xue, A. K. Budniak, H. De Libero, T. Thomson, M. Bosman, G. Eda, H. Kurebayashi, M. Cubukcu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fingerprints of supersymmetric spin and charge dynamics observed by inelastic neutron scattering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.12626</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.12626v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Supersymmetry is an algebraic property of a class of quantum Hamiltonians, a guiding principle used in the development of nuclear theory and a concept that may underpin physics beyond the Standard Model. In condensed matter, any symmetry between bosonic and fermionic entities is usually strongly broken, as for the spin and charge sectors of the $t$-$J$ model describing the dynamics of fractionalized electrons in one-dimensional materials. While the triplet excitations of a quantum spin ladder in an applied magnetic field provide a close analogue of the $t$-$J$ chain, the supersymmetric nature of this system has not been explored. Here we perform neutron spectroscopy on the spin-ladder compounds (C$_5$D$_{12}$N)$_2$CuBr$_4$ and (C$_5$D$_{12}$N)$_2$CuCl$_4$ over a range of applied fields and temperatures, and apply matrix-product-state (MPS) methods to the ladder and equivalent chain models, to analyse the full, momentum-resolved dynamics of a single charge excitation in a bath of fractionalized spins. We find a dramatic difference in the effects of thermal fluctuations, where strong and coherent shifts of spectral weight at the zone edge contrast with a strict pole at the zone centre, whose persistence at all temperatures constitutes an observable consequence of supersymmetry in a quantum spin ladder.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.12626v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Wehinger, F. T. Lisandrini, N. Kestin, P. Bouillot, S. Ward, D. Biner, R. Bewley, K. W. Kr\"amer, B. Normand, C. Kollath, T. Giamarchi, A. M. L\"auchli, Ch. R\"uegg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Snap and Jump: How Elastic Shells Pop Out</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.08525</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.08525v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Grip, walk, crawl, and jump. Soft robots are integrated functional structures composed of compliant mechanisms, whose activity spans various industrial applications such as surgery, healthcare, surveillance, and even planetary exploration. One of their promising mobility mechanism is snap-buckling; the instability mode of flexible structures passing from one equilibrium state to another can instantaneously generate large power for its motion. Predicting their performance with even simple geometry requires disentangling material, geometric nonlinearity, and contact, thereby still being a challenging problem to date. Here, we study the jumping dynamics of hemispherical elastic shells driven by snap-buckling, as a model system of soft jumping mechanisms, combining experiments, simulations, and analytical theory. We find that the contact transition dynamics trigger the jumping phenomenon upon snap-buckling by constructing the analytical predictions with shell elasticity in excellent agreement with both experiments and simulations. Despite the simple geometry of the shell, its dynamical performance primarily relies on a complex interplay between elasticity, geometry, and contact friction. By elucidating the dynamics of the building blocks of soft robots that undergo large deformations, we can build their predictive experimental and numerical framework. Our research paves the way for designing soft robots suitable for the required loading conditions or structural requirements without empirical methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.08525v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takara Abe, Isamu Hashiguchi, Yukitake Nakahara, Shunsuke Kobayashi, Ryuichi Tarumi, Hidetoshi Takahashi, Genya Ishigami, Tomohiko G. Sano</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Measurement of the dynamic charge susceptibility near the charge density wave transition in ErTe$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.14746</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.14746v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: A charge density wave (CDW) is a phase of matter characterized by a periodic modulation of the valence electron density accompanied by a distortion of the lattice structure. The microscopic details of CDW formation are closely tied to the dynamic charge susceptibility, $\chi(q,\omega)$, which describes the behavior of electronic collective modes. Despite decades of extensive study, the behavior of $\chi(q,\omega)$ in the vicinity of a CDW transition has never been measured with high energy resolution ($\sim$meV). Here, we investigate the canonical CDW transition in ErTe$_3$ using momentum-resolved electron energy loss spectroscopy (M-EELS), a technique uniquely sensitive to valence band charge excitations. Unlike phonons in these materials, which undergo conventional softening due to the Kohn anomaly at the CDW wavevector, the electronic excitations display purely relaxational dynamics that are well described by a diffusive model. The diffusivity peaks around 250 K, just below the critical temperature. Additionally, we report, for the first time, a divergence in the real part of $\chi(q,\omega)$ in the static limit ($\omega \rightarrow 0$), a phenomenon predicted to characterize CDWs since the 1970s. These results highlight the importance of energy- and momentum-resolved measurements of electronic susceptibility and demonstrate the power of M-EELS as a versatile probe of charge dynamics in materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.14746v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dipanjan Chaudhuri, Qianni Jiang, Xuefei Guo, Jin Chen, Caitlin S. Kengle, Farzaneh Hoveyda-Marashi, Camille Bernal-Choban, Niels de Vries, Tai-Chang Chiang, Eduardo Fradkin, Ian R. Fisher, Peter Abbamonte</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental observation of repulsively bound magnons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.06350</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.06350v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Stable composite objects, such as hadrons, nuclei, atoms, molecules and superconducting pairs, formed by attractive forces are ubiquitous in nature. By contrast, composite objects stabilized by means of repulsive forces were long thought to be theoretical constructions owing to their fragility in naturally occurring systems. Surprisingly, the formation of bound atom pairs by strong repulsive interactions has been demonstrated experimentally in optical lattices. Despite this success, repulsively bound particle pairs were believed to have no analogue in condensed matter owing to strong decay channels. Here we present spectroscopic signatures of repulsively bound three-magnon states and bound magnon pairs in the Ising-like chain antiferromagnet BaCo$_2$V$_2$O$_8$. In large transverse fields, below the quantum critical point, we identify repulsively bound magnon states by comparing terahertz spectroscopy measurements to theoretical results for the Heisenberg-Ising chain antiferromagnet, a paradigmatic quantum many-body model. Our experimental results show that these high-energy repulsively bound magnon states are well separated from continua, exhibit significant dynamical responses and, despite dissipation, are sufficiently long-lived to be identified. As the transport properties in spin chains can be altered by magnon bound states, we envision such states could serve as resources for magnonics based quantum information processing technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.06350v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41586-024-07599-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature 631, 760 - 764 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Zhe Wang, Catalin-Mihai Halati, Jean-S\'ebastien Bernier, Alexey Ponomaryov, Denis I. Gorbunov, Sandra Niesen, Oliver Breunig, J. Michael Klopf, Sergei Zvyagin, Thomas Lorenz, Alois Loidl, Corinna Kollath</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
