<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2024 03:19:41 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesis and Stability Kinetics of Nanoporous TaC Derived from Ta Precursors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18657</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18657v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ultra-high temperature ceramics (UHTCs) are promising materials for use in next-generation aerospace structures but have primarily been used as monolithic materials or coatings due to processing limitations. Here, new functionality (e.g., ablation resistance) is introduced to these materials by developing a porous form factor that can be later infiltrated with a secondary phase. This UHTC scaffold is synthesized via gas-phase carburization of nanoporous tantalum to the ultra-high-temperature ceramic, TaC. The kinetics of Ta conversion in a carburizing environment was examined over a range of temperatures to determine rate-limiting behavior and activation energy for the process. A 1-D moving interface model was constructed to predict carburization depth and compare data from the present work to that in the literature. It was found that the activation energy for carburization increases as conversion proceeds, suggesting a transition from grain boundary to bulk diffusion. Additionally, to simulate potential use cases of this nanoporous ceramic, the compositional and morphological stability was evaluated in a high temperature environment. Finally, the utility of this thermally stable porous UHTC was demonstrated through synthesis of a nanostructured composite of TaC and oxidation-resistant material, SiO2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18657v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Catherine Ott, Vaibhav Verma, Adam Peters, Ian McCue</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing the Interaction Between Topological and Rashba-like Surface States in MnBi$_2$Te$_4$ Through Sn Doping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18666v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The presence of Rashba-like surface states (RSS) in the electronic structure of topological insulators (TIs) has been a longstanding topic of interest due to their significant impact on electronic and spin structures. In this study, we investigate the interaction between topological and Rashba-like surface states (TSS and RSS) in Mn$_{1-x}$Sn$_x$Bi$_2$Te$_4$ systems using density functional theory (DFT) calculations and high-resolution ARPES. Our findings reveal that increasing Sn concentration shifts RSS downward in energy, enhancing their influence on the electronic structure near the Fermi level. ARPES validates these predictions, capturing the evolution of RSS and their hybridization with TSS. Orbital analysis shows RSS are localized within the first three Te-Bi-Te trilayers, dominated by Bi $p$-orbitals, with evidence of the orbital Rashba effect enhancing spin-momentum locking. At higher Sn concentrations, RSS penetrate deeper into the crystal, driven by Sn $p$-orbital contributions. These results position Mn$_{1-x}$Sn$_x$Bi$_2$Te$_4$ as a tunable platform for tailoring electronic properties in spintronic and quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18666v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. V. Tarasov, D. A. Estyunin, A. G. Rybkin, A. S. Frolov, A. I. Sergeev, A. V. Eryzhenkov, V. V. Anferova, T. P. Estyunina, D. A. Glazkova, K. A. Kokh, V. A. Golyashov, O. E. Tereshchenko, S. Ideta, Y. Miyai, Y. Kumar, K. Shimada, A. M. Shikin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photoreforming of plastic waste into valuable products and hydrogen using a high-entropy oxynitride with distorted atomic-scale structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18722</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18722v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The persistent existence of plastic waste causes serious problems for the environment, directly and indirectly affecting the health of organisms and humans. Photoreforming is a nature-friendly method that only uses solar energy to convert plastic waste into green hydrogen (H2) and valuable organic products. This study shows that a high-entropy oxynitride (HEON) photocatalyst, synthesized by the addition of nitrogen to a Ti-Zr-Hf-Nb-Ta-containing high-entropy oxide (HEO), exhibits a higher potential for the production of H2, formic acid and acetic acid from polyethylene terephthalate (PET) photoreforming compared to the relevant HEO. Examination of X-ray absorption near edge structure (XANES) and extended X-ray absorption fine structure (EXAFS) by synchrotron light shows that, in addition to hybridization of 2p orbitals from oxygen and nitrogen, nitrogen atoms distort the structure and completely change the neighborhood of niobium and titanium (a main contributor to the conduction band), expands the atomic bonds of zirconium and tantalum, contracts the atomic bonds of hafnium and decreases the binding energy of titanium, niobium and tantalum. These electronic structure changes lead to a narrower bandgap and diminished electron-hole recombination, enhancing the photoreforming performance. This study introduces HEONs with distorted atomic bond structures as efficient low-bandgap and stable catalysts for transforming plastics into high-value organic chemicals and H2 by photocatalysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18722v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.apcatb.2024.124968</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Applied Catalysis B, Vol. 365, p. 124968, 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Ho Truong Nam Hai, Thanh Tam Nguyen, Maiko Nishibori, Tatsumi Ishihara, Kaveh Edalati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unusual topological polar texture in moir\'e ferroelectrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18763v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Topological polar textures in ferroelectrics have attracted significant interest for their potential for energy-efficient and high-density data storage and processing. Among these, polar merons and antimerons are predicted in strained and twisted bilayers of inversion symmetry broken systems. However, experimental observation of these polar textures within twisted two-dimensional van der Waals (2D vdW) materials remains challenging. Here, we utilize vector piezoresponse force microscopy (PFM) to reconstruct the polarization fields in R-type marginally twisted hexagonal boron nitride (hBN). We observe alternating out-of-plane (OOP) polarizations at domain regions and in-plane (IP) vortex-like polarization patterns along domain walls (DWs), indicative of a network of polar merons and antimerons. Notably, the OOP polarization exhibits three polarity reversals across a DW. Similar polar textures are identified in marginally twisted MoSe2 and WSe2 homobilayers. Our theoretical simulations attribute these unusual polarization reversals near the DWs to the competition between moir\'e ferroelectricity and piezoelectricity. These results provide experimental evidence of complex polar textures in moir\'e ferroelectrics, offering new insights into the electronic band topology in twisted transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDCs).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18763v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuhao Li, Yuanhao Wei, Ruiping Guo, Yifei Wang, Hanhao Zhang, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Yan Shi, Yi Shi, Chong Wang, Zaiyao Fei</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the local elemental arrangements across the interfaces inside CdSe/Cd1-xZnxS core-shell and CdSe/CdS/ Cd1-xZnxS core-crown-shell quantum wells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report on a systematic study of the Cd, Zn, Se, and S elemental distributions across the interfaces in CdSe/Cd1-xZnxS core-shell and CdSe/CdS/Cd1-xZnxS core-crown-shell quantum wells with the CdSe core thickness ranging from 3.5 to 5.5 ML. By processing the XAS data, we observe that the Cd-Se bonds dominate at the CdSe/Cd1-xZnxS core-shell interface of structures with the 3.5 ML cores, while the Cd-Se bonds were more abundant in the cases of the 4.5 and 5.5 ML cores. The complementary information about prevailing bonds were extracted for other constituting elements, thus, describing the distribution of the elements at the core-shell interface of CdSe-based NPLs. The naked CdSe cores are covered with an organic shell via bridging oxygen atoms. Also, we address the issue of stability of such core-shell systems over the time. We demonstrate that after a half year of aging of the commercial-ready 4.5 ML CdSe/CdxZn1-xS NPLs, the Cd-Se bonds become more evident due to the partial degradation of the Cd-S bonds. This is the first experimental assessment of prevailing interatomic bonds at the core-shell interface in the CdSe-based NPLs of incremental structural heterogeneity, providing factual evidences about the elemental arrangement inside the core-crown-shell NPLs and the growth path of crowns and shells.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18795v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tatiana Lastovina, Oleg Usoltsev, Furkan Isik, Andriy Budnyk, Messaoud Harfouche, Betul Canimkurbey, Hilmi Volkan Demir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theory of fractional corner charges in cylindrical crystal shapes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18871</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18871v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent studies showed that topologically trivial insulators may have fractionally quantized corner charges due to the topological invariant called a filling anomaly. Such crystal shapes in three dimensions are restricted to vertex-transitive polyhedra, which are classified into spherical and cylindrical families. The previous works derived formulas of the fractional corner charge for the spherical family, which corresponds to the tetrahedral and cubic space groups (SGs). In this study, we derive all the corner charge formulas for the cylindrical family, which corresponds to the orthorhombic, tetragonal, hexagonal, and trigonal crystal shapes. We show that all the real-space formulas of the filling anomaly for the cylindrical SGs are universally determined by the total charges at the Wyckoff position (WP) 1a. Moreover, we derive the k-space formulas of the corner charge for the cylindrical cases with time-reversal symmetry (TRS). From our results, we also show that CsLi$_{2}$Cl_{3}, KN_{3}, and Li_{3}N are candidate materials with a quantized corner charge by using the ab initio calculations. Together with our previous work, we exhaust corner charge formulas for all the SGs and crystal shapes having quantized corner charges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18871v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hidetoshi Wada, Tiantian Zhang, Shuichi Murakami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling the effect of grain boundary diffusivity and trapping on hydrogen transport using a phase-field compatible formulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18974</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18974v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hydrogen grain boundary (GB) trapping is widely accepted as the main cause for hydrogen induced intergranular failure. Several studies were conducted to unveil the role of GBs on hydrogen transport; however, a clear understanding is yet to be attained. This is due to the limitations of the state-of-the-art experimental procedures for such highly kinetic processes. In this study, we aim at providing a deeper understanding of hydrogen-GB interactions using full-field representative volume element (RVE). The phase-field method is chosen for generating RVEs, since it is the an appropriate numerical tool to represent GBs. A novel fully-kinetic formulation for hydrogen diffusion and GB trapping is presented, which is compatible with the phase-field based RVEs. GB diffusivity ($D_\mathrm{gb}$) and trap-binding energy ($E_\mathrm{gb}$) were used as parameters to understand the interactions between diffusion and GB trapping. Uptake and permeation simulations were performed with constant and gradient occupancy boundary conditions respectively. In both cases, increasing $E_\mathrm{gb}$, increased the hydrogen GB occupancy. The permeation simulations showed that the hydrogen flux along the GBs increased with increasing both, $D_\mathrm{gb}$ and, surprisingly, $E_\mathrm{gb}$. Since trapping increases the hydrogen occupancy along GBs, it also increases the occupancy gradients, resulting in a higher flux. This led to the conclusion that, in the case of an external occupancy gradient, GB trapping and diffusion cooperate, rather than compete, to increase the hydrogen flux. On the other hand, the decisive factor for the retention of hydrogen at the GBs in permeation simulations was $D_\mathrm{gb}$ rather than $E_\mathrm{gb}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18974v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ijhydene.2023.11.270</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Abdelrahman Hussein, Byungki Kim, Tom Depover, Kim Verbeken</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Developing a single-phase and nanograined refractory high-entropy alloy ZrHfNbTaW with ultrahigh hardness by phase transformation via high-pressure torsion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19006</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19006v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High-entropy alloys (HEAs) are potential candidates for applications as refractory materials. While dual-phase refractory HEAs containing an ordered phase exhibit high hardness, there is high interest in developing intermetallic-free and single-phase refractory HEAs with high hardness. In this study, a new equiatomic HEA ZrHfNbTaW with an ultrahigh hardness of 860 Hv is developed. The alloy is first synthesized with a dual-phase structure via arc melting and further homogenized to a single body-centered cubic (BCC) structure by phase transformation via high-pressure torsion (HPT), using the concept of ultra-severe plastic deformation process. The ultrahigh hardness of the alloy, which is higher than those reported for refractory alloys and single-phase HEAs, is attributed to (i) solution hardening by severe lattice distortion, (ii) Hall-Petch grain boundary hardening by the formation of nanograins with 12 nm average size, and (iii) dislocation hardening confirmed by high-resolution transmission electron microscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19006v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jallcom.2024.178274</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shivam Dangwal, Kaveh Edalati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extremely Large Anisotropy of Effective Gilbert Damping in Half-Metallic CrO2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19077</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19077v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Half-metals are a class of quantum materials with 100% spin-polarization at the Fermi level and have attracted a lot of attention for future spintronic device applications. CrO2 is one of the most promising half-metal candidates, for which the electrical and magnetic properties have been intensively studied in the last several decades. Here, we report the observation of a giant anisotropy (~1600%) of effective Gilbert damping in the single crystalline half metallic (100)-CrO2 thin films, which is significantly larger than the values observed on conventional ferromagnetic Fe and CoFe thin films. Furthermore, the effective Gilbert damping exhibits opposite temperature-dependent behaviors below 50 K with magnetic field along [010] direction and near [001] direction. These experimental results suggest the strong spin-orbit coupling anisotropy of the half-metallic CrO2 and might pave the way for future magnonic computing applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19077v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.nanolett.4c05630.</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nano Letters 2024 24 (51), 16436-16442</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Liangliang Guo, Ranran Cai, Zhenhua Zhang, Wenyu Xing, Weiliang Qiao, Rui Xiong, Zhihong Lu, Xincheng Xie, Wei Han</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Towards structural softness and enhanced electromechanical responses in HfO2 ferroelectrics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19093v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Structural softness - often characterized by unstable phonon modes and large electromechanical responses - is a hallmark of ferroelectric perovskites like BaTiO3 or Pb(Ti,Zr)O3. Whether HfO2 ferroelectrics present any such structural softness is still a matter of debate. Here, using first principles calculations, we predict that it is possible to induce structural instabilities in hafnia. More specifically, our calculations show that in-plane epitaxial tensile strain causes a mechanical instability of the ferroelectric phase, which transforms discontinuously into an antipolar polymorph. Then, upon release of the tensile strain, the antipolar polymorph transforms back to the ferroelectric state by a soft phonon instability. We show that the softening is accompanied by enhancements in the dielectric and piezoelectric responses. While these transitions occur at high epitaxial strains for pure ferroelectric HfO2, we show that the required deformations are considerably lowered in superlattices with other simple oxides, which may facilitate realizing these effects experimentally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19093v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Binayak Mukherjee, Natalya S. Fedorova, Jorge \'I\~niguez-Gonz\'alez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The role of potential energy landscape research in the development of new electrolyte solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19103</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19103v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The development of new electrolyte solutions with improved characteristics is a key challenge for creating high-performance batteries, fuel cells, supercapacitors, and other electrochemical devices. The study of the potential energy landscape (PEL) plays an important role in this process, providing information about the interactions between solution components at the molecular level. In this work, we review the practice of applying PEL research methods based on classical and quantum-chemical algorithms to analyze the structure, dynamics, and thermodynamic properties of electrolyte solutions. Intermolecular and ion-molecular interactions at the microscopic level, which determine the macroscopic properties of the electrolyte solution, are considered in detail. The importance of identifying stable configurations of ions and their solvates is emphasized. PEL analysis allows for the systematic determination of the most probable structures and complexes formed in solution, which is important for understanding ion transport mechanisms. The study of the PEL allows for the determination of the energy barriers that must be overcome for ion migration, which is related to the conductivity of the electrolyte. The application of PEL research methods in combination with experimental data opens up new possibilities for the rational design of electrolyte solutions with desired physicochemical properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19103v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vitaly V. Chaban</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of an Ultra-Stable Antiferromagnetic Two-Dimensional CrF3 Phase with Anisotropic Quasi-1D Mechanical, Electronic, and Thermal Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19118</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19118v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report the discovery of an ultra-stable antiferromagnetic two-dimensional (2D) CrF3 phase that is energetically more favorable than the traditionally assumed hexagonal structure. Using first-principles calculations and evolutionary structure searches, we identify a new low-energy rectangular configuration of CrF3 with remarkable anisotropic properties. Mechanically, this phase exhibits zero in-plane Poisson's ratio, a rare negative out-of-plane Poisson's ratio, and quasi-one-dimensional (quasi-1D) behavior characterized by minimal coupling between orthogonal directions. Electronically, CrF3 shows quasi-1D transport with two independent conduction bands near the Fermi level, tunable via uniaxial strain. The calculated bandgap is 3.05 eV, which can be modulated under strain, enabling control over its electronic properties. The material also displays out-of-plane antiferromagnetic ordering with a magnetic anisotropy energy of 0.098 meV per Cr atom and an estimated Neel temperature of 20 K. Additionally, we investigate the thermal conductivity of monolayer rectangular CrF3 (r-CrF3), revealing significant anisotropy in heat transport. The thermal conductivity along the y-axis is approximately 60.5 W/mK at 300 K, much higher than along the x-axis at 13.2 W/mK. The thermal anisotropic factor is 4.58, surpassing that of other 2D materials like black phosphorene, WTe2, and arsenene, highlighting r-CrF3's potential for advanced directional heat management. Consequently, the rectangular CrF3 phase is a promising candidate for applications in spintronics, strain-engineered nanoelectronics, mechanical metamaterials, and thermal management technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19118v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Chen, Fengyi Zhou, Yan Suo, Cheng Shao, Duo Wang, Biplab Sanyal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The effect of grain boundary misorientation on hydrogen flux using a phase-field based diffusion and trapping model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19129v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding hydrogen-grain boundary (GB) interactions is critical to the analysis of hydrogen embrittlement in metals. This work presents a mesoscale fully kinetic model to investigate the effect of GB misorientation on hydrogen diffusion and trapping using phase-field based representative volume elements (RVEs). The flux equation consists of three terms: a diffusive term and two terms for high and low angle grain boundary (H/LAGB) trapping. Uptake simulations showed that decreasing the grain size resulted in higher hydrogen content due to increasing the GB density. Permeation simulations showed that GBs are high flux paths due to their higher enrichment with hydrogen. Since HAGBs have higher enrichment than LAGBs, due to their higher trap-binding energy, they generally have the highest hydrogen flux. Nevertheless, the flux shows a convoluted behavior as it depends on the local concentration, alignment of GB with external concentration gradient as well as the GB network connectivity. Finally, decreasing the grain size resulted in a larger break-through time and a larger steady-state exit flux.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19129v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adem.202401561</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Abdelrahman Hussein, Byungki Kim, Kim Verbeken, Tom Depover</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Switchable magnetic phases in CrSBr$_{1-x}$Cl$_x$ and CrSBr/CrSCl heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19136</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19136v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strategies such as chemical substitution, strain engineering and van der Waals stacking offer powerful means to control magnetism in 2D materials, enabling the emergence of novel quantum phenomena. Here, we investigate the magnetic properties of bulk CrSBr$_{1-x}$Cl$_x$ ($x = 0{-}1$) and the strain-dependent switchable magnetic phases in bilayers CrSBr, CrSCl, and CrSBr/CrSCl heterostructures, using firstprinciples calculations. Our findings demonstrate that Cl incorporation in CrSBr induces competing interlayer antiferromagnetic and ferromagnetic couplings, leading to a spin-glass state when the Cl content exceeds a 67%. This is accompanied by a decrease of magnetic anisotropy, where a $XY$-type magnetic ground state is observed in pristine CrSCl. For CrSBr and CrSCl bilayers, we report a reversible strain-induced switching between interlayer antiferromagnetic and ferromagnetic configurations. Furthermore, we reveal the emergence of interfacial ferromagnetism in CrSBr/CrSCl heterostructures, stabilizing an in-plane magnetization axis for CrSCl by proximity to CrSBr. These results underscore the potential of manipulating magnetism in 2D magnetic materials through precise control of magnetic phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19136v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alberto M. Ruiz, Jos\'e J. Baldov\'i</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating global search of adsorbate molecule position using machine-learning interatomic potentials with active learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19162v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present an algorithm for accelerating the search of molecule's adsorption site based on global optimization of surface adsorbate geometries. Our approach uses a machine-learning interatomic potential (moment tensor potential) to approximate the potential energy surface and an active learning algorithm for the automatic construction of an optimal training dataset. To validate our methodology, we compare the results across various well-known catalytic systems with surfaces of different crystallographic orientations and adsorbate geometries, including CO/Pd(111), NO/Pd(100), NH$_3$/Cu(100), C$_6$H$_6$/Ag(111), and CH$_2$CO/Rh(211). In the all cases, we observed an agreement of our results with the literature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19162v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Olga Klimanova, Nikita Rybin, Alexander Shapeev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physical nature of quasi-stable structures existing in antimony melt</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19177v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Equilibrium antimony melt near the melting temperature is characterised by structural features that are not present in simple single-component liquids. The cause of these features may be long-lived structural formations that are not yet fully understood. The present work provides the detailed characterization of the structures formed in liquid antimony near the melting temperature based on the results of quantum chemical calculations and the available neutron and X-ray diffraction data. The quasi-stable structures in antimony melt are detected with lifetimes exceeding the structural relaxation time of this melt. These structures are characterised by a low degree of order and spatial localisation. It is shown for the first time that the elementary units of these quasi-stable structures are triplets of atoms with characteristic lengths of $3.07$\,\AA~and $4.7$\,\AA~and characteristic angles of $45$ and $90$ degrees. It was found that these triplets can form chains and percolating clusters up to $\sim15$\,\AA~in length. The characteristic lengths of these triplets are fully consistent with the correlation lengths associated with short-range order in the antimony melt as determined by diffraction experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19177v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.molliq.2024.126699</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Molecular Liquids 418 (2025) 126699</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Artem A. Tsygankov, Bulat N. Galimzyanov, Anatolii V. Mokshin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast opto-acoustics in single nickel cavities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19267</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19267v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mechanical stress produced in nano- and micro-scale structures can enhance materials properties, such as the high mobility of silicon in modern transistors or amplified magnetization dynamics in spintronic devices. Here, we report on the dynamics of coherent acoustic phonons excited by femtosecond light pulses and confined in a single freestanding nickel layer, acting as an acoustic cavity. By combining Fourier transform analysis of the experimental signal and numerical multi-physics simulations, we show that high-frequency (&gt; 10 GHz) longitudinal acoustic pulses can resonate inside the cavity and display lower damping compared to a reference nickel film on SiO2 substrate given that the conditions of total reflection are nearly met in the cavity. Our results provide a thorough understanding of the opto-acoustic response in suspended membranes of magnetic materials, which we foresee can be used to amplify magnetization precession dynamics and to develop magneto-acousto-optical modulators.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19267v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alba Viejo Rodr\'iguez, Marco Gandolfi, Andrea Rossetti, Yoav Urbina Elgueta, Evgeny B. Modin, Svetlana Starikovskaia, Tatloon Chng, Vasily Temnov, Maria Antonietta Vincenti, Daniele Brida, Paolo Vavassori, Nicol\`o Maccaferri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying Split Vacancies with Foundation Models and Electrostatics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19330</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19330v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Point defects are ubiquitous in solid-state compounds, dictating many functional properties such as conductivity, catalytic activity and carrier recombination. Over the past decade, the prevalence of metastable defect geometries and their importance to relevant properties has been increasingly recognised. A particularly striking example of this is split vacancies, where an isolated atomic vacancy transforms to a stoichiometry-conserving complex of two vacancies and an interstitial ($V_X \rightarrow [V_X + X_i + V_X]$), which can be accompanied by a dramatic lowering of the defect energy and change in behaviour. Such species are particularly challenging to identify from computation, due to the `non-local' nature of this reconstruction. Here, I present an approach for efficiently identifying such species in solid-state compounds, through tiered screening which combines geometric analysis, electrostatic energies and foundation machine learning (ML) models. This approach allows the screening of all compounds in the Materials Project database (including all entries in the ICSD, along with several thousand predicted metastable materials), identifying thousands of split vacancy configurations, hitherto unknown. This study highlights both the potential utility of machine-learning potentials for defect investigations, with important caveats, and the importance of global optimisation approaches for correctly identifying stable defect geometries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19330v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Se\'an R. Kavanagh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SuperSalt: Equivariant Neural Network Force Fields for Multicomponent Molten Salts System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19353v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Molten salts are crucial for clean energy applications, yet exploring their thermophysical properties across diverse chemical space remains challenging. We present the development of a machine learning interatomic potential (MLIP) called SuperSalt, which targets 11-cation chloride melts and captures the essential physics of molten salts with near-DFT accuracy. Using an efficient workflow that integrates systems of one, two, and 11 components, the SuperSalt potential can accurately predict thermophysical properties such as density, bulk modulus, thermal expansion, and heat capacity. Our model is validated across a broad chemical space, demonstrating excellent transferability. We further illustrate how Bayesian optimization combined with SuperSalt can accelerate the discovery of optimal salt compositions with desired properties. This work provides a foundation for future studies that allows easy extensions to more complex systems, such as those containing additional elements. SuperSalt represents a shift towards a more universal, efficient, and accurate modeling of molten salts for advanced energy applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19353v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chen Shen, Siamak Attarian, Yixuan Zhang, Hongbin Zhang, Mark Asta, Izabela Szlufarska, Dane Morgan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Guidelines for Correlative Imaging and Analysis of Reactive Lithium Metal Battery Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19376v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To unlock the full potential of lithium metal batteries, a deep understanding of lithium metal reactivity and its solid electrolyte interphase is essential. Correlative imaging, combining focused ion beam and electron microscopy offers a powerful approach for multi-scale characterization. However, the extreme reactivity of lithium metal and its SEI presents challenges in investigating deposition and stripping mechanisms. In this work, we systematically evaluated the storage stability of lithium metal in glovebox before and after electrochemical deposition. We then assessed different FIB ion sources for their impact on lithium metal lamella preparation for transmission electron microscopy. Furthermore, we examined cryogenic-TEM transfer methods, optimizing for minimal contamination during sample handling. Contrary to prior assumptions, we demonstrate that high resolution imaging of pure lithium metal at room temperature is achievable using inert gas transfer with an electron dose rate exceeding 1000 e/A2/s, without significant detectable damage. In contrast, SEI components, such as Li2CO3 and LiF display much greater sensitivity to electron beams, requiring cryogenic conditions and precise dose control for nano/atomic scale imaging. We quantified electron dose limits for these SEI components to track their structural evolution under irradiation. Based on these findings, we propose a robust protocol for lithium metal sample handling - from storage to atomic-level characterization - minimizing damage and contamination. This work paves the way for more accurate and reproducible studies, accelerating the development of next-generation lithium metal batteries by ensuing the preservation of native material properties during analysis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19376v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuang Bai, Zhao Liu, Diyi Cheng, Bingyu Lu, Nestor J. Zaluzec, Ganesh Raghavendran, Shen Wang, Thomas S. Marchese, Brandon van Leer, Letian Li, Lin Jiang, Adam Stokes, Joseph P. Cline, Rachel Osmundsen, Paul Barends, Alexander Bright, Minghao Zhang, Ying Shirley Meng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seed-Driven Stepwise Crystallization (SDSC) for Growing Rutile GeO2 Films via MOCVD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19429v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Germanium dioxide (r-GeO2) is an emerging new ultrawide bandgap (UWBG) semiconductor with significant potential for power electronics, thanks to its large-size substrate compatibility and ambipolar doping capability. However, phase segregation during metal-organic chemical vapor deposition (MOCVD) on substrates like r-TiO2 has posed a significant barrier to achieving high-quality films. Conventional optimization of growth parameters has been found so far not very insufficient in film coverage and film quality. To address this, a seed-driven stepwise crystallization (SDSC) growth approach was employed in this study, featuring multiple sequential deposition steps on a pre-templated substrate enriched with r-GeO2 seeds. The process began with an initial 180-minute deposition to establish r-GeO2 nucleation seeds, followed by a sequence of shorter deposition steps (90, 60, 60, 60, 60, and 60 minutes). This stepwise growth strategy progressively increased the crystalline coverage to 57.4%, 77.49%, 79.73%, 93.27%, 99.17%, and ultimately 100%. Concurrently, the crystalline quality improved substantially, evidenced by a ~30% reduction in the Full Width at Half Maximum (FWHM) of X-ray diffraction rocking curves. These findings demonstrate the potential of the SDSC approach for overcoming phase segregation and achieving high-quality, large-area r-GeO2 films.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19429v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Imteaz Rahaman, Botong Li, Bobby Duersch, Hunter D. Ellis, Kai Fu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Investigation of the Pressure Dependent Physical Properties of MAX Phase Ti2AlX (X = B, C, and N) Compounds: A First-Principles Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19431</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19431v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The physical properties and their pressure dependence of recently synthesized Ti2AlX (X = B, C, and N) MAX phases are investigated for the very first time applying density functional theory (DFT).</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19431v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. I. Naher, M. Montasir, M. Y. H. Khan, M. A. Ali, M. M. Hossain, M. M. Uddin, M. Z. Hasan, M. A. Hadi, S. H. Naqib</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Low driving-force stable bending cooling via fatigue-resistant hierarchical NiTi shape memory alloy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19440</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19440v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Elastocaloric cooling with shape memory alloys (SMAs) is emerging as a promising candidate for next-generation, environmentally friendly refrigeration. However, its development is hindered by the large driving force and low efficiency associated with uniaxial loading modes. In response, we present an innovative elastocaloric air cooling approach that utilizes the bending of NiTi beams, offering a low-force and energy-efficient solution. We achieve a continuous maximum temperature drop of 0.91 K and a dissipated energy of 15.1 N mm at a low specific driving force of 220 N. Notably, the specimen achieves over 5 million cycles under a maximum surface tensile strain of 1.94% for macroscopic cyclic bending, via a pre-strained, warm laser shock peening (pw-LSP) method. This unprecedented fatigue resistance originates from the formation of a hierarchical microstructure and a large compressive residual stress of over 1 GPa. This work demonstrates the great potential of bending induced elastocaloric cooling in the near future.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19440v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Yan, Kangjie Chu, Peng Hua, Pengbo Wei, Hanlin Gu, Qiming Zhuang, Weifeng He, Fuzeng Ren, Qingping Sun, Robert O. Ritchie</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Theoretical Study of Cavity-modulated Topological Anderson Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19508</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19508v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strong light-matter interaction has been demonstrated feasible for controlling phases of matter. In this work, the interplay with disorder is studied and rich phenomena are demonstrated. Specifically, the topological phases of the disordered longer-range Su-Schrieffer-Heeger (SSH) model coupled with cavity photons are studied numerically. It is found that cavity photons modify the hopping amplitudes, resulting in the change of phase transition boundaries, and disorder induced topological Anderson insulating (TAI) phases even in the presence of cavity photons. The critical disorder strength at the phase transitions, determined by localization lengths, can be modulated by cavity photons through the modified hopping amplitudes. Our work extends the study of cavity-coupled solid state systems to disordered lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19508v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Cheng Shaw, Hsiu-Chuan Hsu, J. S. You</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photoluminescence efficiency droop in Perovskites</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19572</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19572v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The commercialization prospects of perovskite light emitting diodes depend on its luminescence efficiency under large carrier densities. The decrease in luminescence efficiency under such high injection conditions could lead to an undesired increase in power consumption with associated degradation and stability concerns. Here, through detailed modeling of thermal transport and carrier generation-recombination, we unravel the physical mechanisms that cause luminescence droop under high injection conditions. We show that self-heating leads to a reduction in the radiative recombination (both bimolecular and excitonic). The resultant increase in non-radiative recombination and hence the thermal dissipation acts as a positive feedback mechanism that leads to efficiency droop in perovskites. Our model predictions, well supported by experimental results, could be of broad interest towards the degradation-aware thermal design of perovskite optoelectronics and stability.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19572v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pradeep R. Nair, Karthik Raitani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical Investigation of (Zn, Co) co-Doped BaTiO3 for Advanced Energy and Photonic Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19591v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In light of recent advancements in energy technology, there is an urgent need for lead-free barium titanate (BTO) -based materials that exhibit remarkable ferroelectric and photoelectric properties. Notwithstanding the considerable experimental advances, a theoretical understanding from the electron and atomic perspectives remains elusive. This study employs the generalized gradient approximation plane wave pseudopotential technique to investigate the structural, electronic, ferroelectric, and optical properties of (Zn,Co) co-doped BaTiO3 (BZCT) based on density functional theory. The objective is to ascertain the extent of performance enhancement and the underlying mechanism of (Zn,Co) co-doping on barium titanate. Our findings reveal that incorporating (Zn,Co) into the BaTiO3 lattice significantly augments the tetragonality of the unit cell. Moreover, the ferroelectric properties are enhanced, with a spontaneous polarization stronger than that observed in pure BTO, exhibiting excellent ferroelectricity. The results of the Hubbard+U algorithm indicate that the band gap of BZCT is reduced. Concurrently, the enhanced ferroelectric polarization increases the built-in electric field of the material, facilitating the separation of photogenerated carriers and improving optical absorption. Consequently, the optical absorption ability and photorefractive ability are effectively enhanced. BZCT, with its high spontaneous polarization and outstanding optical properties, can be a promising candidate material in energy storage and photovoltaics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19591v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng Kang, Mei Wu, Yiyu Feng, Jiahao Li, Jieming Zhang, Haiyi Tian, Ancheng Wang, Yunkai Wu, Xu Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DFT based comparative analysis of physical properties of binary metallic diborides XB$_2$ (X = Cr, Mo and W)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19687</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19687v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transition-metal borides (TMBs) have long attracted attention of the researchers because of their unique mechanical and electrical properties including superconductivity. We have explored the structural, mechanical, electronic, optical, and some thermophysical properties of XB$_2$ (X = Cr, Mo and W) binary metallic diborides in detail employing density functional theory based first-principles method. Many of the physical properties, including direction-dependent mechanical properties, optical properties, and thermo-mechanical properties are being investigated for the first time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19687v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Razu Ahmed, Md. Sohel Rana, Md. Sajidul Islam, S. H. Naqib</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-principles investigation of thermodynamics and electronic transitions in vacancy-ordered rare-earth perovskite nickelates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19700v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Controlled introduction of oxygen vacancies offers an effective route to induce metal-to-insulator transition in strongly correlated rare-earth nickelates ($R$NiO$_3$) at room temperature. However, the role played by the rare-earth cations on the structure, thermodynamic stability, and electronic properties of oxygen-deficient nickelates remains unclear. Here, we employ density functional theory calculations with Hubbard corrections (DFT + $U$) to investigate the whole family of $R$NiO$_{2.5}$ ($R$ = Pr-Er) compounds in two commonly observed oxygen-vacancy ordered configurations, namely brownmillerite, and square planar. We find that square planar polymorph is always more stable ($\sim$0.4 eV/u.f) than the brownmillerite for all rare-earth cations, owing to the exceedingly low volumetric strains (&lt; 1\%). Formation energy of $R$NiO$_{2.5}$ gradually increases with decreasing size of $R$ owing to stronger Ni-O covalent interactions in pristine $R$NiO$_3$ with small $R^{3+}$ cations. This necessitates more oxygen-lean environments for synthesis of $R$NiO$_{2.5}$ with smaller $R^{3+}$ cations. Analysis of the density of states and band structures reveals that electronic structure of $R$NiO$_{2.5}$ is governed by two factors: (a) localization of electron on NiO$_6$ octahedra yielding a Mott insulating state with strong correlations as Ni $e_g$ is half filled, and (b) crystal field splitting in the NiO$_4$ tetrahedra/square planar polyhedra. Brownmillerite $R$NiO$_{2.5}$ is metallic, while square planar $R$NiO$_{2.5}$ is an insulator with a predicted gap of $\sim$ 0.2-0.3 eV, depending on the $R^{3+}$ cation. Crystal orbital Hamilton population (COHP) analysis indicates that the Ni-O bond belonging to square-planar NiO$_4$ polyhedra exhibit much greater covalent character than those in NiO$_6$ octahedra in square planar $R$NiO$_{2.5}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19700v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Devang Bhagat, Ranga Teja Pidathala, Badri Narayanan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tuning Nonlinear Elastic Materials under Small and Large Deformations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18631v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In computer graphics and engineering, nonlinear elastic material properties of 3D volumetric solids are typically adjusted by selecting a material family, such as St. Venant Kirchhoff, Linear Corotational, (Stable) Neo-Hookean, Ogden, etc., and then selecting the values of the specific parameters for that family, such as the Lame parameters, Ogden exponents, or whatever the parameterization of a particular family may be. However, the relationships between those parameter values, and visually intuitive material properties such as object's "stiffness", volume preservation, or the "amount of nonlinearity", are less clear and can be tedious to tune. For an arbitrary isotropic hyperelastic energy density function psi that is not parameterized in terms of the Lame parameters, it is not even clear what the Lame parameters and Young's modulus and Poisson's ratio are. Starting from psi, we first give a concise definition of Lame parameters, and therefore Young's modulus and Poisson's ratio. Second, we give a method to adjust the object's three salient properties, namely two small-deformation properties (overall "stiffness", and amount of volume preservation, prescribed by object's Young's modulus and Poisson's ratio), and one large-deformation property (material nonlinearity). We do this in a manner whereby each of these three properties is decoupled from the other two properties, and can therefore be set independently. This permits a new ability, namely "normalization" of materials: starting from two distinct materials, we can "normalize" them so that they have the same small deformation properties, or the same large-deformation nonlinearity behavior, or both. Furthermore, our analysis produced a useful theoretical result, namely it establishes that Linear Corotational materials (arguably the most widely used materials in computer graphics) are the simplest possible nonlinear materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18631v1</guid>
      <category>cs.GR</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Huanyu Chen, Jernej Barbic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Excited States of Chichibabin, M\"uller and related Singlet Diradicaloids based on Polyhalogenated Trityl Radicals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18638v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The tris(2,4,6-trichlorophenyl)methyl radical (TTM) has inspired the synthesis of several luminescent diradicals and diradicaloids, providing an extraordinary opportunity to control the nature of the low-lying excited states by fine-tuning the diradical character. However, the photophysical properties of TTM-derived diradicals remain not fully understood yet. Here we present a comprehensive theoretical investigation on a series of symmetric TTM-derived diradicals, featuring radical moieties separated by pi-conjugated spacers of different length with distinct conjugation extension. All these diradicals exhibit a singlet electronic ground state. The nature of the lowest excited electronic states that control the pho-tophysical behavior of the diradicals, is discussed in detail. The theoretical study is complemented by a complete spectro-scopic characterization of the TTM-TTM diradical, synthesized using a novel, simpler and more efficient procedure ex-ploiting the unique reactivity of TTM. The lowest excited states of the diradicals differ qualitatively from those of TTM: two novel low-lying states emerge in the diradical, due to charge resonance (CR) between the two radical units. The low-est CR state is a dark state for symmetric diradicals. The CR nature explains the blue-shifted emission observed by in-creasing the distance between the radical centres as seen in TTM-ph-TTM. This insight suggests different design strate-gies to improve the luminescence properties of TTM-derived diradicals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18638v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Davide Mesto, Michele Orza, Brunella Bardi, Angela Punzi, Imma Ratera, Jaume Veciana, Gianluca Farinola, Anna Painelli, Francesca Terenziani, Davide Blasi, Fabrizia Negri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Entropy Theory Investigation of the Relatively High Segmental Fragility of Many Glass-Forming Polymers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18712v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We utilize the generalized entropy theory (GET) of glass formation to address one of the most singular and least understood properties of polymer glass-forming liquids in comparison to atomic and small molecule liquids -- the often relatively high fragility of the polymer dynamics on a segmental scale, $m_s$. We first analyze the relation between $m_s$ and the ratio, $S_c^*/ S_c(T_{\mathrm{g}})$. We find that an apparently general nonlinear relation between $m_s$ and $S_c^*/ S_c(T_{\mathrm{g}})$ holds to a good approximation for a large class of polymer models, $m_s \approx 7.9 \exp [0.6S_c^*/ S_c(T_{\mathrm{g}})]$. The predicted ranges of $m_s$ and $S_c^*/ S_c(T_{\mathrm{g}})$ are consistent with experimental estimates for high molecular-mass polymer, oligomeric, small molecule, and atomic glass-forming liquids. In particular, relatively high values of $m_s$ are found for polymers having complex monomer structures and significant chain stiffness. The variation of $m_s$ with molecular mass, chain stiffness, and intermolecular interaction strength can be traced to the variation of $S_c^*$, which is shown to provide a measure of packing frustration defined in terms of the dimensionless thermal expansion coefficient and isothermal compressibility. The often relatively high fragility and large extent of cooperative motion are found in the GET to derive from the often relatively large packing frustration in this class of polymer glass-forming liquids. Finally, we also develop a tentative model of the ``dynamical segmental relaxation time'' based on the GET, in which the polymers on a coarse-grained scale are modeled as strings of structureless ``beads'', as assumed in the Rouse and reptation models of polymer dynamics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18712v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaolei Xu, Jack F. Douglas, Wen-Sheng Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic tuning of ENZ wavelength in conductive polymer films via polaron excitation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18878v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Traditional metal and n-type doped semiconductor materials serve as emerging epsilon-near-zero (ENZ) materials, showcasing great potential for nonlinear photonic applications. However, a significant limitation for such materials is the lack of versatile ENZ wavelength tuning, and thus dynamic tuning of the ENZ wavelength remains a technical challenge, thereby restricting their potential applications, such as multi-band communications. Here, dynamic tuning of the ENZ wavelength in p-type organic PEDOT: PSS films is achieved through a reversible change in hole concentrations originated from the polaron formation/decoupling following optical excitation, and a tunable ENZ wavelength shift up to 150 nm is observed. Experimental investigations about ultrafast dynamics of polaron excitation reveal an approximately 80 fs time constant for polaron buildup and an approximately 280 fs time constant for polaron decoupling, indicating the potential of reversal ultrafast switching for the ENZ wavelength within subpicosecond time scale. These findings suggest that $p$--type organic semiconductors can serve as a novel platform for dynamically tuning the ENZ wavelength through polaron excitation, opening new possibilities for ENZ--based nonlinear optical applications in flexible optoelectronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18878v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hongqi Liu, Junjun Jia, Menghui Jia, Chengcan Han, Sanjun Zhang, Hui Ye, Heping Zeng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the nonrelativistic spin current polarization in an altermagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.18937</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.18937v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spin current plays a central role in spintronics for driving exotic spin-dependent phenomena and high-performance device applications. Recently, a magnetic spin Hall effect has been discovered in spin-split antiferromagnets including noncollinear antiferromagnets and altermagnets, allowing the efficient generation of unconventional spin currents even in the absence of spin-orbit coupling. However, although such nonrelativistic spin currents are proposed to have a magnetic origin, the direct connection between the Neel vector and the spin current polarization is still missing. Here, using the altermagnetic RuO2 as a representative example, we unveil the spin current polarization by disentangling the conventional and magnetic spin Hall effects using a technique we developed based on the spin Hall magnetoresistance measurement. The results suggest that the nonrelativistic spin current hosts a polarization very close to the Neel vector. Our work offers unambiguous evidence of the magnetic origin of the nonrelativistic spin current in altermagnetic RuO2, and paves a straightforward route to understand the unconventional spin currents that are crucial in spintronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.18937v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chang Pan, Shuai Hu, Fanli Yang, Dongchao Yang, Weijia Fan, Zhong Shi, Liqing Pan, Shiming Zhou, Xuepeng Qiu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DPmoire: A tool for constructing accurate machine learning force fields in moir\'e systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19333</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19333v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In moir\'e systems, the impact of lattice relaxation on electronic band structures is significant, yet the computational demands of first-principles relaxation are prohibitively high due to the large number of atoms involved. To address this challenge, We introduce a robust methodology for the construction of machine learning potentials specifically tailored for moir\'e structures and present an open-source software package DPmoire designed to facilitate this process. Utilizing this package, we have developed machine learning force fields (MLFFs) for MX$_2$ (M = Mo, W; X = S, Se, Te) materials. Our approach not only streamlines the computational process but also ensures accurate replication of the detailed electronic and structural properties typically observed in density functional theory (DFT) relaxations. The MLFFs were rigorously validated against standard DFT results, confirming their efficacy in capturing the complex interplay of atomic interactions within these layered materials. This development not only enhances our ability to explore the physical properties of moir\'e systems with reduced computational overhead but also opens new avenues for the study of relaxation effects and their impact on material properties in two-dimensional layered structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19333v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaxuan Liu, Zhong Fang, Hongming Weng, Quansheng Wu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reconstruction of non-trivial magnetization textures from magnetic field images using neural networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19381v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Spatial imaging of magnetic stray fields from magnetic materials is a useful tool for identifying the underlying magnetic configurations of the material. However, transforming the magnetic image into a magnetization image is an ill-poised problem, which can result in artefacts that limit the inferences that can be made on the material under investigation. In this work, we develop a neural network fitting approach that approximates this transformation, reducing these artefacts. Additionally, we demonstrate that this approach allows the inclusion of additional models and bounds that are not possible with traditional reconstruction methods. These advantages allow for the reconstruction of non-trivial magnetization textures with varying magnetization directions in thin-film magnets, which was not possible previously. We demonstrate this new capability by performing magnetization reconstructions on a variety of topological spin textures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19381v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David A. Broadway, Mykhailo Flaks, Adrien E. E. Dubois, Patrick Maletinsky</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital magnetic susceptibility of type-I, II, and III massless Dirac fermions in two dimensions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19407</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19407v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the orbital magnetic susceptibility of tilted massless Dirac fermions in two dimensions. It is well-known that the type-I massless Dirac fermions exhibit divergingly-large diamagnetic susceptibility, whereas less is known about the types II and III cases. We first clarify that the orbital magnetic susceptibility is vanishing for the types II and III in the continuum model. We then compare the three types of Dirac fermions for the lattice models. We employ three tight-binding models with different numbers of Dirac points, all of which are two-band models defined on a square lattice. For all three models, we find that the type-I Dirac fermions show the divergingly-large orbital diamagnetic susceptibility, whereas the type-II Dirac fermions exhibit non-diverging paramagnetic susceptibility. The type-III Dirac fermions exhibit diamagnetism but its susceptibility is small compared with the type-I case.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19407v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tomonari Mizoguchi, Hiroyasu Matsuura, Masao Ogata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Transport through Asymmetrical Molecular channel Azulene: Role of Orbital Interference</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19472</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19472v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We investigate electron transport through azulene molecule with four distinct electrode contact geometries using the non-equilibrium Green's function formalism within the tight-binding Hamiltonian. Employing the Q-matrix approach, we analyze quantum interference (QI) among the molecular orbitals in each contact configuration. Our results reveal distinct transmission profiles and varying current responses among configurations, with the configuration 1-3 displaying the highest conductivity at higher bias due to strong constructive interference of the Highest Occupied Molecular Orbital (HOMO). Conversely, configuration 5-7 exhibit weak conductance and antiresonance at the Fermi energy, attributed to dominant destructive interference among the frontier molecular orbitals. Configuration 2-6 is found to exhibit asymmetric I-V characteristics, due to the dipolar nature of the azulene molecule. These findings underscore the significance of QI effects in shaping the transport properties of azulene, and molecule-based devices in general.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19472v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koushik R. Das, Sudipta Dutta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two superconducting thin films systems with potential integration of different quantum functionalities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19493v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Quantum computation based on superconducting circuits utilizes superconducting qubits with Josephson tunnel junctions. Engineering high-coherence qubits requires materials optimization. In this work, we present two superconducting thin film systems, grown on silicon (Si), and one obtained from the other via annealing. Cobalt (Co) thin films grown on Si were found to be superconducting [EPL 131 (2020) 47001]. These films also happen to be a self-organised hybrid superconductor/ferromagnet/superconductor (S/F/S) structure. The S/F/S hybrids are important for superconducting $\pi$-qubits [PRL 95 (2005) 097001] and in quantum information processing. Here we present our results on the superconductivity of a hybrid Co film followed by the superconductivity of a CoSi$_2$ film, which was prepared by annealing the Co film. CoSi$_2$, with its $1/f$ noise about three orders of magnitude smaller compared to the most commonly used superconductor aluminium (Al), is a promising material for high-coherence qubits. The hybrid Co film revealed superconducting transition temperature $T_c$ = 5 K and anisotropy in the upper critical field between the in-plane and out-of-plane directions. The anisotropy was of the order of ratio of lateral dimensions to thickness of the superconducting Co grains, suggesting a quasi-2D nature of superconductivity. On the other hand, CoSi$_2$ film showed a $T_c$ of 900 mK. In the resistivity vs. temperature curve, we observe a peak near $T_c$. Magnetic field scan as a function of $T$ shows a monotonic increase in intensity of this peak with temperature. The origin of the peak has been explained in terms of parallel resistive model for the particular measurement configuration. Although our CoSi$_2$ film contains grain boundaries, we observed a perpendicular critical field of 15 mT and a critical current density of 3.8x10$^7$ A/m$^2$, comparable with epitaxial CoSi$_2$ films.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19493v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Snehal Mandal, Biplab Biswas, Suvankar Purakait, Anupam Roy, Biswarup Satpati, Indranil Das, B. N. Dev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear valley Hall effect in a bilayer transition metal dichalcogenide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19502</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19502v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Valley-contrasting Hall transport conventionally relies on the inversion symmetry breaking in two-dimensional systems, which greatly limits the selection range of valley materials. In particular, while monolayer transition metal dichalcogenides have been widely utilized as a well-known class of valley materials in valleytronics, the centrosymmetric nature hinders the realization of valley-contrasting properties in the bilayer counterparts. Here, taking MoS$_{2}$ as an example, we discover valley-contrasting transport in bilayer transition metal dichalcogenides by exploring nonlinear transport regime. Using effective models and first-principles calculations, our work demonstrates that nonvanishing nonlinear valley Hall conductivities emerge in a uniaxially strained MoS$_{2}$ bilayer, owing to strain-induced band tilts of Dirac fermions. With the aid of small spin-orbit-coupling induced band splittings, the conduction bands generate much remarkable nonlinear valley Hall conductivity. Moreover, the nonlinear conductivities are highly tunable through modulating the strength and the direction of the strain, chemical potential, and interlayer gap. Our findings not only expands material choices for valleytronic applications, but also provides opportunities for designing advanced electronic devices that leverage nonlinear valley transports.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19502v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhichao Zhou, Ruijing Fang, Zhen Zhang, Xiaoyu Wang, Jiayan Rong, Xiao Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anisotropic Band Flattening in Twisted Bilayer of M-Valley MXenes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19613</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19613v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Experimental studies on moir\'e materials have predominantly focused on twisted hexagonal lattice with low-energy states near the $\Gamma$- or K-points. These materials, characterized by isotropic low-energy dispersion, are fundamentally distinct from those with anisotropic properties. Here we introduce a series of semiconducting transition metal carbides (MXenes) $M_2$C$T_2$ ($M$ = Ti, Zr, Hf, Sc, Y; $T$ = O, F, Cl) as a novel platform for M-valley moir\'e materials. Take Ti$_2$CO$_2$ and Zr$_2$CO$_2$ as representative examples, large-scale \emph{ab initio} calculations show that their AB-stacked twisted homobilayer features three three-fold rotational symmetry related M-valleys with time-reserval symmetry and giant anisotropic band flattening. We derive a simplified moir\'e Hamiltonian for these systems and conduct a detailed analysis of their band structures, where the origins of anisotropic band flattening are clearly elucidated. This research broadens the scope of moir\'e materials, where the valley- and spin-degenerate two-dimensional array of quasi-one-dimensional system could serve as a potential platform for realizing many interesting correlated phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19613v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kejie Bao, Huan Wang, Zhaochen Liu, jing Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Key Steps and Distinct Performance Trends of Pyrrolic vs. Pyridinic M-N-C Catalysts in Electrocatalytic Nitrate Reduction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19615</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19615v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electrochemical nitrate reduction reaction(NO3RR)offers a sustainable route for ambient ammonia synthesis. While metal-nitrogen-carbon (M-N-C) single-atom catalysts have emerged as promising candidates for NO3RR, the structure-activity relations underlying their catalytic behavior remain to be elucidated. Through systematic analysis of reported experimental data and pH-field coupled microkinetic modelling on a reversible hydrogen electrode (RHE) scale, we reveal that the coordination-dependent activity originates from distinct scaling relations governed by metal-intermediate interactions. M-N-Pyrrolic catalysts demonstrate higher turnover frequencies for ammonia production, whereas M-N-Pyridinic catalysts exhibit broader activity ranges across the activity volcano plot. Meanwhile, the adsorption and protonation of nitrate, which is a step often dismissed and/or assumed to be simultaneous in many previous reports, is identified to be the rate-determining step (RDS) in NO3RR. Remarkably, our subsequent experimental validation confirms the theoretical predictions under both neutral and alkaline conditions. This study offers a comprehensive mechanistic framework for interpreting the electrocatalytic activity of M-N-C catalysts in NO3RR, showing that a classical thermodynamic limiting-potential model is not sufficiently accurate to capture the RDS and the catalytic performance trends of different materials (even on M-N-Pyrrolic and M-N-Pyridinic catalysts). These findings provide brand new insights into the reaction mechanism of NO3RR and establish fundamental design principles for electrocatalytic ammonia synthesis.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19615v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qiuling Jiang, Mingyao Gu, Tianyi Wang, Fangzhou Liu, Xin Yang, Di Zhang, Zhijian Wu, Ying Wang, Li Wei, Hao Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High performance Black Phosphorus/Graphitic Carbon Nitride Heterostructure-based Wearable Sensor for Real-time Sweat Glucose Monitoring</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.19633</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.19633v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Wearable, non-invasive glucose sensors capable of accurate and continuous monitoring are crucial for managing metabolic conditions yet achieving high sensitivity and stability in these devices remains challenging. In this work, we present a Black Phosphorus/Graphitic Carbon Nitride (BP/g-CN) heterostructure engineered to leverage phosphorus-nitrogen interactions for enhanced electrochemical glucose oxidation activity. Compared to pristine gCN, the BP-gCN heterostructure demonstrates a significantly improved electrochemical surface area (ECSA) and nearly two-fold reduction in charge transfer resistance (Rct), achieving remarkable glucose sensitivity of 1.1 uA mM(^-1) cm(^-2) at physiological pH. Density functional theory (DFT) calculations revealed stronger glucose adsorption and higher charge transfer on the BP-gCN heterostructure compared to pristine gCN surface. These theoretical insights complement the experimental findings, highlighting the superior electrocatalytic performance of the heterostructure and the role of oxidized BP surface. Furthermore, the BP-gCN sensor is integrated into a wearable device platform with microfluidic layers and a Near Field Communication (NFC) chip, forming a conformal skin patch that enables real-time sweat glucose monitoring. This demonstration of a high-performance, non-enzymatic wearable glucose sensor based on a heterostructure design underscores the potential of the device for seamless health management and paves the way for next generation biosensing platforms aimed at improving personalized and continuous health monitoring.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.19633v1</guid>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ecem Ezgi Ozkahraman, Zafer Eroglu, Vladimir Efremov, Arooba Maryyam, Taher Abbasiasl, Ritu Das, Hadi Mirzajani, Berna Akgenc Hanedar, Levent Beker, Onder Metin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetization reversal of a ferromagnetic Pt/Co/Pt film by helicity dependent absorption of visible to near-infrared laser pulses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2201.01141</link>
      <description>arXiv:2201.01141v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The practical difficulty in distinguishing the impact of magnetic circular dichroism and the inverse Faraday effect fuels intense debates over which mechanism predominantly drives the process of helicity dependent all-optical switching of magnetization in ferromagnets. Here, we quantitatively measure the efficiency of the switching process in a Pt/Co/Pt multilayered stack using visible- to near-infrared optical pulses. We find that the switching efficiency increases by a factor of 8.6 upon increasing the pumping wavelength from 0.5 $ \mu $m to 1.1 $ \mu $m, becoming 100 % efficient at even longer wavelengths up to 2.0 $ \mu $m. Our experimental results can be successfully explained by the phenomenon of magnetic circular dichroism, making a significant step towards resolving the long-standing controversy over the origin of the all-optical process of magnetization reversal in ferromagnets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2201.01141v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kihiro T. Yamada, Carl S. Davies, Fuyuki Ando, Tian Li, Teruo Ono, Theo Rasing, Alexey V. Kimel, Andrei Kirilyuk</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin density wave in the bilayered nickelate La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_{7-\delta}$ at ambient pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.19213</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.19213v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The recent discovery of high-temperature superconductivity in high-pressurized La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_{7-\delta}$ has garnered significant attention. Using density functional theory, we investigate the magnetic properties of La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_{7-\delta}$ at ambient pressure. Our calculations suggest that with $\delta=0$, the double spin stripe phase is favored as the magnetic ground state. Oxygen vacancies may effectively turn nearest Ni spins into \textit{charge} sites. Consequently, with moderate $\delta$ values, our theoretical magnetic ground state exhibits characteristics of both double spin stripe and spin-charge stripe configurations, providing a natural explanation to reconcile the seemingly contradictory experimental findings that suggest both the configurations as candidates for the spin-density-wave phase. With higher $\delta$ values, we anticipate the ground state to become a spin-glass-like noncollinear magnetic phase with only short-range order. The oxygen vacancies are expected to significantly impact the magnetic excitations and the transition temperatures $T_{SDW}$. Notably, the magnetic ordering also induces concomitant charge ordering and orbital ordering, driven by spin-lattice coupling under the low symmetry magnetic order. We further offer a plausible explanation for the experimental observations that the measured $T_{SDW}$ appears insensitive to the variation of samples and the lack of direct evidence for long-range magnetic ordering.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.19213v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiao-Sheng Ni, Yuyang Ji, Lixin He, Tao Xie, Dao-Xin Yao, Meng Wang, Kun Cao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancement of piezoelectric response in V doped LiNbO3 films deposited by RF magnetron sputtering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.20864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.20864v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: LiNbO3 films doped with vanadium (V) were deposited using RF magnetron sputtering technique. To realize doping with a wider range of V concentration, a 30 mm V metal inlaid target asymmetrically embedded in the 150 mm lithium niobate target was used. The V concentration in the deposited films was a decreasing function of the distance from the V target. The V/Nb ratio in the film decreased from 0.155 to 0.024. Surface and inner morphology and structure, phase and element composition, microstructure, and ferroelectric properties of the undoped and V doped LiNbO3 films were studied. The measured maximal d33 constant of the LiNbVO film with V/Nb ratio of 0.07 was about three times higher than that of the undoped LiNbO3 film, 13.5 pC/N and 4.76 pC/N, respectively. The optimal composition in the deposition geometry used was within the V/Nb ratio range of 0.05 to 0.13. Undoped and V doped LiNbO3 thin films were used as bulk acoustic wave ultrasonic transducers deposited on stainless steel plates to generate longitudinal waves and compare their ultrasonic performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.20864v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaomei Zeng, Ting Lv, Xiangyu Zhang, Zhong Zeng, Bing Yang, Alexander Pogrebnjak, Vasiliy O. Pelenovich, Sheng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A data driven approach to classify descriptors based on their efficiency in translating noisy trajectories into physically-relevant information</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.12570</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.12570v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Reconstructing the physical complexity of many-body dynamical systems can be challenging. Starting from the trajectories of their constitutive units (raw data), typical approaches require selecting appropriate descriptors to convert them into time-series, which are then analyzed to extract interpretable information. However, identifying the most effective descriptor is often non-trivial. Here, we report a data-driven approach to compare the efficiency of various descriptors in extracting information from noisy trajectories and translating it into physically relevant insights. As a prototypical system with non-trivial internal complexity, we analyze molecular dynamics trajectories of an atomistic system where ice and water coexist in equilibrium near the solid/liquid transition temperature. We compare general and specific descriptors often used in aqueous systems: number of neighbors, molecular velocities, Smooth Overlap of Atomic Positions (SOAP), Local Environments and Neighbors Shuffling (LENS), Orientational Tetrahedral Order, and distance from the fifth neighbor ($d_5$). Using Onion Clustering -- an efficient unsupervised method for single-point time-series analysis -- we assess the maximum extractable information for each descriptor and rank them via a high-dimensional metric. Our results show that advanced descriptors like SOAP and LENS outperform classical ones due to higher signal-to-noise ratios. Nonetheless, even simple descriptors can rival or exceed advanced ones after local signal denoising. For example, $d_5$, initially among the weakest, becomes the most effective at resolving the system's non-local dynamical complexity after denoising. This work highlights the critical role of noise in information extraction from molecular trajectories and offers a data-driven approach to identify optimal descriptors for systems with characteristic internal complexity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.12570v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Simone Martino, Domiziano Doria, Chiara Lionello, Matteo Becchi, Giovanni M. Pavan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancement of spin Hall angle by an order of magnitude via Cu intercalation in MoS2/CoFeB heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.18582</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.18582v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) are a novel class of quantum materials with significant potential in spintronics, optoelectronics, valleytronics, and opto-valleytronics. TMDs exhibit strong spin-orbit coupling, enabling efficient spin-charge interconversion, which makes them ideal candidates for spin-orbit torque-driven spintronic devices. In this study, we investigated the spin-to-charge conversion through ferromagnetic resonance in MoS2/Cu/CoFeB heterostructures with varying Cu spacer thicknesses. The conversion efficiency, quantified by the spin Hall angle, was enhanced by an order of magnitude due to Cu intercalation. Magneto-optic Kerr effect microscopy confirmed that Cu did not significantly modify the magnetic domains, indicating its effectiveness in decoupling MoS2 from CoFeB. This decoupling preserves the spin-orbit coupling (SOC) of MoS2 by mitigating the exchange interaction with CoFeB, as proximity to localized magnetization can alter the electronic structure and SOC. First-principles calculations revealed that Cu intercalation notably enhances the spin Berry curvature and spin Hall conductivity, contributing to the increased spin Hall angle. This study demonstrates that interface engineering of ferromagnet/TMD-based heterostructures can achieve higher spin-to-charge conversion efficiencies, paving the way for advancements in spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.18582v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abhisek Mishra, Pritam Das, Rupalipriyadarsini Chhatoi, Soubhagya Dash, Shubhransu Sahoo, Kshitij Singh Rathore, Pil-Ryung Cha, Seung-Cheol Lee, Satadeep Bhattacharjee, Subhankar Bedanta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CrystalFlow: A Flow-Based Generative Model for Crystalline Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.11693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.11693v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Deep learning-based generative models have emerged as powerful tools for modeling complex data distributions and generating high-fidelity samples, offering a transformative approach to efficiently explore the configuration space of crystalline materials. In this work, we present CrystalFlow, a flow-based generative model specifically developed for the generation of crystalline materials. CrystalFlow constructs Continuous Normalizing Flows to model lattice parameters, atomic coordinates, and/or atom types, which are trained using Conditional Flow Matching techniques. Through an appropriate choice of data representation and the integration of a graph-based equivariant neural network, the model effectively captures the fundamental symmetries of crystalline materials, which ensures data-efficient learning and enables high-quality sampling. Our experiments demonstrate that CrystalFlow achieves state-of-the-art performance across standard generation benchmarks, and exhibits versatile conditional generation capabilities including producing structures optimized for specific external pressures or desired material properties. These features highlight the model's potential to address realistic crystal structure prediction challenges, offering a robust and efficient framework for advancing data-driven research in condensed matter physics and material science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.11693v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoshan Luo, Zhenyu Wang, Jian Lv, Lei Wang, Yanchao Wang, Yanming Ma</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Neural Canonical Transformations for Quantum Anharmonic Solids of Lithium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.12451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.12451v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Lithium is a typical quantum solid, characterized by cubic structures at ambient pressure. As the pressure increases, it forms more complex structures and undergoes a metal-to-semiconductor transformation, complicating theoretical and experimental analyses. We employ the neural canonical transformation approach, an \textit{ab initio} variational method based on probabilistic generative models, to investigate the quantum anharmonic effects in lithium solids at finite temperatures. This approach combines a normalizing flow for phonon excited-state wave functions with a probabilistic model for the occupation of energy levels, optimized jointly to minimize the free energy. Our results indicate that quantum anharmonicity lowers the \textit{bcc}-\textit{fcc} transition temperature compared to classical molecular dynamics predictions. At high pressures, the predicted fractional coordinates of lithium atoms in the \textit{cI16} structure show good quantitative agreement with experimental observations. Finally, contrary to previous beliefs, we find that the poor metallic \textit{oC88} structure is stabilized by the potential energy surface obtained via high-accuracy electronic structure calculations, rather than thermal or quantum nuclear effects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.12451v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qi Zhang, Xiaoyang Wang, Rong Shi, Xinguo Ren, Han Wang, Lei Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Interplay Between Electron Localization, Magnetic Order, and Jahn-Teller Distortion that Dictates LiMnO$_2$ Phase Stability</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16816</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16816v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The development of Mn-rich cathodes for Li-ion batteries promises to alleviate supply chain bottlenecks in battery manufacturing. Challenges in Mn-rich cathodes arise from Jahn-Teller (JT) distortions of Mn$^{3+}$, Mn migration, and phase transformations to spinel-like order, which can affect the electrochemical performance. These phenomena motivate an ab initio re-examination of the thermodynamics of the LiMnO2 polymorphs. It is found that the generalized gradient approximation (GGA - PBEsol) and meta-GGA (r2SCAN) density functionals with empirical on-site Hubbard U corrections yield spurious stable phases for LiMnO2, such as predicting a phase with gamma-LiFeO2-like order (g-LiMnO2) to be the ground state instead of the orthorhombic (Pmmn) phase, which is the experimentally known ground state. Accounting for the antiferromagnetic (AFM) order in each structure has a substantial effect on the total energies and resulting phase stability. By using hybrid-GGA (HSE06) and GGA with extended Hubbard parameters (on-site U and inter-site V) that are self-consistently determined, the experimentally observed LiMnO2 phase stability trends are recovered. The calculated Hubbard U in the experimentally observed orthorhombic, layered, and spinel phases (around 5.8 eV) are significantly smaller than U in g-LiMnO2 and disordered layered structures (around 6.4 eV). The smaller values of U are correlated with a collinear ordering of JT distortions, in which all $e_g$ orbitals are oriented in the same direction. This cooperative JT effect leads to increased Mn-O covalency, which contributes to the greater electronic stability compared to the phases with noncollinear JT arrangements, and also generate greater vibrational entropy, which helps stabilize these phases at high temperature. These phases are shown to be strongly insulating with large calculated band gaps &gt; 3 eV, computed using HSE06 and $G_0W_0$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16816v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ronald L. Kam, Luca Binci, Aaron D. Kaplan, Kristin A. Persson, Nicola Marzari, Gerbrand Ceder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hall mass and transverse Noether spin currents in noncollinear antiferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.12898</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.12898v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Noncollinear antiferromagnets (AFMs) have recently attracted attention in the emerging field of antiferromagnetic spintronics because of their various interesting properties. Due to the noncollinear magnetic order, the localized electron spins on different magnetic sublattices are not conserved even when spin-orbit coupling is neglected, making it difficult to understand the transport of spin angular momentum. Here we study the conserved Noether current due to spin-rotation symmetry of the local spins in noncollinear AFMs. Interestingly, we find that a Hall component of the spin current can be generically created by a longitudinal driving force associated with a propagating spin wave, inherently distinguishing noncollinear AFMs from collinear ones. We coin the corresponding Hall coefficient, an isotropic rank-4 tensor, as the Hall (inverse) mass, which generally exists in noncollinear AFMs and their polycrystals. The resulting Hall spin current can be realized by spin pumping in a ferromagnet (FM)-noncollinear AFM bilayer structure as we demonstrate numerically, for which we also give the criteria of ideal boundary conditions. Our results shed light on the potential of noncollinear AFMs in manipulating the polarization and flow of spin currents in general spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.12898v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Luke Wernert, Basti\'an Pradenas, Oleg Tchernyshyov, Hua Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological insulators on fractal lattices: A general principle of construction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13767</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.13767v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Fractal lattices, featuring the self-similarity symmetry, are often geometric descents of parent crystals, possessing all their discrete symmetries (such as rotations and reflections) except the translational ones. Here, we formulate three different general approaches to construct real space Hamiltonian on a fractal lattice starting from the Bloch Hamiltonian on the parent crystal, fostering for example strong and crystalline topological insulators resulting from the interplay between the nontrivial geometry of the underlying electronic wave functions and the crystal symmetries. As a demonstrative example, we consider a generalized square lattice Chern insulator model and within the framework of all three methods we successfully showcase incarnations of strong and crystalline Chern insulators on the Sierpi\'nski carpet fractal lattices. The proposed theoretical framework thus lays a generic foundation to build a tower of topological phases on the landscape of fractal lattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.13767v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.L241302</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 110, L241302 (2024)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Daniel J. Salib, Aiden J. Mains, Bitan Roy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning-Based Reward-Driven Tuning of Scanning Probe Microscopy: Towards Fully Automated Microscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.04055</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.04055v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Since the dawn of scanning probe microscopy (SPM), tapping or intermittent contact mode has been one of the most widely used imaging modes. Manual optimization of tapping mode not only takes a lot of instrument and operator time, but also often leads to frequent probe and sample damage, poor image quality and reproducibility issues for new types of samples or inexperienced users. Despite wide use, optimization of tapping mode imaging is an extremely hard problem, ill-suited to either classical control methods or machine learning. Here we introduce a reward-driven workflow to automate the optimization of SPM in the tapping mode. The reward function is defined based on multiple channels with physical and empirical knowledge of good scans encoded, representing a sample-agnostic measure of image quality and imitating the decision-making logic employed by human operators. This automated workflow gives optimal scanning parameters for different probes and samples and gives high-quality SPM images consistently in the attractive mode. This study broadens the application and accessibility of SPM and opens the door for fully automated SPM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.04055v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Liu, Roger Proksch, Jason Bemis, Utkarsh Pratiush, Astita Dubey, Mahshid Ahmadi, Reece Emery, Philip D. Rack, Yu-Chen Liu, Jan-Chi Yang, Sergei V. Kalinin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic states in superconducting type-II Dirac semimetal: 1T-PdSeTe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.15500</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.15500v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We have investigated the surface and bulk electronic structures of the superconducting type-II Dirac semimetal 1T-PdSeTe. The superconducting transition temperature $T_C = 3.2$ K was almost twice as high as $T_C = 1.6$ K in 1T-PdTe$_2$. Scanning transmission electron microscopy measurements showed homogeneously mixed Se and Te atoms in the chalcogen layers, consistent with the CdI$_2$-type crystal structure. Angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy measurements and density functional theory calculations indicated the existence of the topological surface states, and the overall band structures were similar to those of 1T-PdTe$_2$. These results suggest that CdI$_2$-type lattice symmetry dictates the band dispersion, regardless of atomic disorder in the chalcogen layers. As the electronic band dispersion and the local structures were persistent upon substitution, the enhancement of $T_C$ is likely associated with the chemical pressure. Our results provide insight into the effects of the solid solution on the surface and bulk electronic states as well as the superconducting transition temperature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.15500v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yogendra Kumar, Shiv Kumar, Venkateswara Yenugonda, Ryohei Oishi, Jayita Nayak, Chaoyu Chen, Ravi Prakash Singh, Takahiro Onimaru, Yasuyuki Shimura, Shinichiro Ideta, Kenya Shimada</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical study on the crystal structure of a bilayer nickel-oxychloride Sr$_3$Ni$_2$O$_5$Cl$_2$ and analysis on the occurrence of possible unconventional superconductivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.06935</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.06935v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The discovery of superconductivity under high pressure with $T_c$ exceeding 80 K in a bilayer nickelate La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ has led to a strong desire to realize similar high $T_c$ phenomena at ambient pressure. As one possible path toward realizing superconductivity at ambient pressure, we here propose to consider Sr$_3$Ni$_2$O$_5$Cl$_2$ as a possible candidate. In this study, we theoretically investigate the electronic structure of Sr$_3$Ni$_2$O$_5$Cl$_2$ and its structural stability. Our phonon calculation shows that this compound with the $I4/mmm$ tetragonal structure is dynamically stable even at ambient pressure. The characteristic crystal field in this compound lowers the Ni-$d_{3z^2-r^2}$ orbital energy, by which the Ni-$d_{3z^2-r^2}$ orbital becomes rather closer to the half-filling in Sr$_3$Ni$_2$O$_5$Cl$_2$ than La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$. As a result, we find that superconductivity is enhanced even though a relatively strong orbital hybridization between the $t_{2g}$ and $e_g$ orbitals is somewhat detrimental for superconductivity. We also check the formation enthalpy, which shows that the high-pressure synthesis can be a good way to actually produce Sr$_3$Ni$_2$O$_5$Cl$_2$. We find that Sr$_3$Ni$_2$O$_5$Cl$_2$ is a promising new candidate of bilayer-nickelate superconductors, which can possess even higher $T_c$ than pressurized La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$, at ambient pressure.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.06935v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masayuki Ochi, Hirofumi Sakakibara, Hidetomo Usui, Kazuhiko Kuroki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhancing Large Language Models with Domain-Specific Knowledge: The Case in Topological Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.13732</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.13732v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Large language models (LLMs), such as ChatGPT, have demonstrated impressive performance in the text generation task, showing the ability to understand and respond to complex instructions. However, the performance of naive LLMs in speciffc domains is limited due to the scarcity of domain-speciffc corpora and specialized training. Moreover, training a specialized large-scale model necessitates signiffcant hardware resources, which restricts researchers from leveraging such models to drive advances. Hence, it is crucial to further improve and optimize LLMs to meet speciffc domain demands and enhance their scalability. Based on the condensed matter data center, we establish a material knowledge graph (MaterialsKG) and integrate it with literature. Using large language models and prompt learning, we develop a specialized dialogue system for topological materials called TopoChat. Compared to naive LLMs, TopoChat exhibits superior performance in structural and property querying, material recommendation, and complex relational reasoning. This system enables efffcient and precise retrieval of information and facilitates knowledge interaction, thereby encouraging the advancement on the ffeld of condensed matter materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.13732v2</guid>
      <category>cs.CL</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>HuangChao Xu, Baohua Zhang, Zhong Jin, Tiannian Zhu, Quansheng Wu, Hongming Weng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Laser-Induced Gas-Phase Transfer and Direct Stamping of Nanomaterials: Comparison of Nanosecond and Femtosecond Pulses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09725</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09725v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The two-dimensional nanomaterial, hexagonal boron nitride (hBN) was cleanly transferred via a blister-based laser-induced forward-transfer method. The transfer was performed utilizing femtosecond and nanosecond laser pulses for separation distances of ~16 and ~200 micrometers between a titanium donor film deposited on a glass substrate and a silicon/silicon dioxide receiver. Transfer efficiency was examined for isolated laser pulses as well as for series of overlapping pulses and single layer transfer was confirmed. It was found that hBN is transferable for all tested combinations of pulse duration and transfer distances. The results indicate that transfer proceeds via direct stamping for short donor-to-receiver distances while, for the larger distance, the material is ejected from the donor and lands on the receiver. Furthermore, with overlapping pulses, nanosecond laser pulses enable a successful printing of hBN lines while, for fs laser pulses, the Ti film can be locally disrupted by multiple pulses and molten titanium may be transferred along with the hBN flakes. For reproducibility, and to avoid contamination with metal deposits, low laser fluence transfer with ns pulses and transfer distances smaller than the blister height provide the most favourable and reproducible condition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09725v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nathan T. Goodfriend, Inam Mirza, Alexander V. Bulgakov, Eleanor E. B. Campbell, Nadezhda M. Bulgakova</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Interference Driven Electron Transport through Fano-Anderson Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.16529</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.16529v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We investigate the electronic transport behavior of Fano-Anderson (FA) systems, consisting of a one-dimensional finite backbone chain and an attached side-group of varying length. The tight-binding model within the non-equilibrium Green's function (NEGF) reveals distinct interference patterns between the frontier orbitals of odd and even side-group systems that lead to distinct transport mechanisms across various configurations. The even side-group systems exhibit resonant tunneling peaks, while the odd ones demonstrate significant destructive interference at Fermi energy leading to antiresonance and reduced current responses. Further exploration of the role of electron-electron interactions within mean-field Hubbard Hamiltonian indicates the emergence of negative differential resistance (NDR) in odd side-group systems at lower biases, a phenomenon absent in the non-interacting case. Our study demonstrates the critical role of quantum interferences among the frontier molecular orbitals and electron correlations in shaping the transport behavior of FA systems, providing insights for the design of molecular-scale electronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.16529v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Koushik R. Das, Sudipta Dutta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytic 3D vector non-uniform Fourier crystal optics in arbitrary $\bar{\bar{\varepsilon}}$ dielectric</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.17224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.17224v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: To find a suitable incubator for nonlinear crystal optics(NCO), we have revisited linear crystal optics(LCO). At the methodological level, three widely used plane wave bases are compared in terms of eigenanalysis in reciprocal space and light field propagation in real space. Inspired by complex ray tracing, we expand M.V. Berry's 2003 uniform plane wave model to non-uniform Fourier crystal optics(FCO) and ultimately derive the explicit form of its 3$\times$2 transition matrix, bridging the two major branches of crystal optics(CO) in reciprocal space, where either ray direction $\hat{k}$ or spatial frequency $\bar{k}_{\mathrm{\rho}}$ serves as the input variable. Using this model, we create the material-matrix tetrahedral compass(M-M TC) to conduct a detailed analysis of how the four fundamental characteristics of materials (linear/circular birefringence/dichroism) influence the eigensystems of the vector electric field in two-dimensional(2D) spatial frequency $\bar{k}_{\mathrm{\rho}}$ domain and its distribution in three-dimensional(3D) $\bar{r}$ space with a crystal-2f system. Along this journey, we have uncovered new territories in LCO in both real and reciprocal space, such as infinite singularities arranged in disk-, ring-, and crescent-like shapes, ``L shorelines'' resembling hearts, generalized haunting theorem, double conical refraction, and optical knots it induces. We also present our model's early applications in focal engineering and NCO.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.17224v3</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math.AP</category>
      <category>nlin.SI</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Dec 2024 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chenzhu Xie, Yong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
