<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 04:00:19 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Mobility of single vacancies and adatoms in graphene at room temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20843</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20843v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We investigate the mobility of structural defects, adatoms, and defect-adatom combinations in self-supporting graphene subjected to keV ion irradiation. In the first scenario, homogeneous irradiation using 20 keV Ar$^+$ ions at a dose of $3 \times 10^{14}$ ions/cm$^2$ induces tensile strain of up to 0.8\%. This strain diminishes with increasing defect density at the dose of $5 \times 10^{14}$ ions/cm$^2$, indicating a strain-relaxation mechanism. Contrary to the expected localized behavior, vacancies exhibit long-range interactions, contributing to global strain effects across the lattice. In the second scenario, by employing a nanopore mask, we spatially confined defect generation to periodically aligned circular regions surrounded by non-irradiated material, enabling direct observation of vacancy and adatom dynamics. Selected area electron diffraction (SAED) reveals significant structural damage in areas adjacent to the irradiated regions, suggesting that single vacancies migrate over distances on the order of 100 nm from irradiated to non-irradiated zones even at room temperature. The build-up of lattice strain observed in this study may play a key role in lowering the migration barrier of single vacancies, thereby facilitating their diffusion into pristine lattice regions. Furthermore, the findings highlight the role of pre-existing surface contaminants in preserving lattice integrity through a self-healing mechanism, where adatom-induced lattice reconstruction mitigates defect-induced structural degradation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20843v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tuan T. Tran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unraveling the electronic, vibrational, thermodynamic, optical and piezoelectric properties of LiNbO$_3$, LiTaO$_3$ and Li$_2$NbTaO$_6$ from first-principles calculations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20845</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20845v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We have investigated the electronic, vibrational, optical, thermal and piezoelectric properties of LiNbO$_3$, LiTaO$_3$ and Li$_2$NbTaO$_6$ using the first-principles calculation based on the density functional theory. It also shows structural phase transition below $T_c$ due to ionic displacement that may alter the properties of material. We have checked the structural stability by calculating the tolerance factor and formation energy before proceeding to the further calculations. The ground state electronic band structures and corresponding density of states show its semiconducting nature with a band gap range of 3.5-3.7 eV. Optical properties such as dielectric function, absorption coefficient, optical conductivity, refractive index, absorbance and reflectance are calculated using time-dependent density functional theory. Furthermore, the piezoelectric properties and Born effective charges were analyzed to find the correlation between them. In these materials, the distortion induced by the small ionic radius of Li$^{+}$ coupled with strong covalent interaction between transition metal and oxygen leads to high spontaneous polarization which can enhance both piezoelectric and optical properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20845v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Debidutta Pradhan, Rojalin Swain, Souvagya Kumar Biswal, Jagadish Kumar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward Sustainable Polymer Design: A Molecular Dynamics-Informed Machine Learning Approach for Vitrimers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20956v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Vitrimer is an emerging class of sustainable polymers with self-healing capabilities enabled by dynamic covalent adaptive networks. However, their limited molecular diversity constrains their property space and potential applications. Recent development in machine learning (ML) techniques accelerates polymer design by predicting properties and virtually screening candidates, yet the scarcity of available experimental vitrimer data poses challenges in training ML models. To address this, we leverage molecular dynamics (MD) data generated by our previous work to train and benchmark seven ML models covering six feature representations for glass transition temperature (Tg) prediction. By averaging predicted Tg from different models, the model ensemble approach outperforms individual models, allowing for accurate and efficient property prediction on unlabeled datasets. Two novel vitrimers are identified and synthesized, exhibiting experimentally validated higher Tg than existing bifunctional transesterification vitrimers, along with demonstrated healability. This work explores the possibility of using MD data to train ML models in the absence of sufficient experimental data, enabling the discovery of novel, synthesizable polymer chemistries with superior properties. The integrated MD-ML approach offers polymer chemists an efficient tool for designing polymers tailored to diverse applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20956v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiwen Zheng, Agni K. Biswal, Yaqi Guo, Prakash Thakolkaran, Yash Kokane, Vikas Varshney, Siddhant Kumar, Aniruddh Vashisth</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modeling Practical Capacitive Structures for Electronic and Dielectric Property Extraction and Analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A method for modeling the full steady-state and small-signal behavior of practical capacitive structures, such as metal-insulator-metal capacitors, diodes, and transistors, is presented. Simple lumped element models fail to properly represent the behavior of most practical structures, resulting in incorrect electronic material property extraction and evaluation. The methodology and model presented in this paper properly characterizes practical structures and can be employed to more accurately understand and evaluate experimental results, extract various electronic and dielectric properties of the constituent materials, and predict possible behavior of new structures and materials. The impact of dielectric properties (e.g., real versus complex permittivity, conductance, Cole-Cole dielectric response) and geometry on observed behavior of practical structures, especially with regard to extracting correct property values, is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20961v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>James G. Champlain, Vikrant J. Gokhale, Matthew T. Hardy, Eric N. Jin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable multi-bit stochasticity in La$_{0.67}$Sr$_{0.33}$MnO$_{3}$-based probabilistic bits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20970v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: One promising approach to combat the rapidly escalating computational demands is to use networks of naturally stochastic units called probabilistic bits (p-bits). To date, hardware implementations of p-bits have predominantly relied on thermally unstable nanomagnets. However, the search continues for alternative material platforms exhibiting easily accessible, intrinsic forms of stochasticity. In this work, we demonstrate hitherto unreported p-bit functionality in epitaxial thin films of La0.67Sr0.33MnO3, a material showing an electrically triggered metal-insulator transition, grown on twin-textured LaAlO3 substrates. By leveraging the combined effects of phase and structural inhomogeneities, we show two distinct modes of voltage-tunable stochastic operation: clocked binary switching and unclocked multi-bit switching. Our findings suggest that the differences result from variations in the energy landscape near the phase transition. This tunability of the energy landscape is promising for designing diverse stochastic behavior within the same material, highlighting its potential for applications in true random number generation for cryptography and probabilistic computing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20970v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. Bhaduri (Zernike Institute for Advanced Materials, Groningen Cognitive Systems and Materials Center), A. Jaman (Zernike Institute for Advanced Materials, Groningen Cognitive Systems and Materials Center), W. Qui\~nonez (Instituto de Nanociencia y Nanotecnolog\'ia), A. Gupta (Zernike Institute for Advanced Materials), T. Banerjee (Zernike Institute for Advanced Materials, Groningen Cognitive Systems and Materials Center)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic Berry phase contribution to Hall conductivity in CoS$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21027</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21027v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In Weyl semi-metals, the conduction and valence bands intersect at distinct points on the Brillouin zone (Weyl points), which act as monopoles of Berry curvature in momentum space. This nontrivial band topology, identified from electronic structure calculations, gives rise to various exotic magneto-transport properties. Hybrid functional calculations that incorporate a portion of exact exchange, magneto-transport measurements, and temperature-dependent resistivity confirm nontrivial band topology and half-metallicity in CoS$_2$ of magnetic ordering temperature $T_{\rm C} \approx 120~\mathrm{K}$. However, electronic structure calculations also show that application of small strain transforms this half metallic character to the metallic. Interestingly, the magnetoresistance (MR) of the CoS$_2$ films is characterized by a reentrant weak localization above a critical field at $T \leq 60\,\mathrm{K}$ and a negative to positive transition in MR as the $T$ goes from $&lt;T_{\rm C}$ to $&gt;T_{\rm C}$. Experimental observation of anomalous Hall resistivity and $ab~initio$ computed band structure, Berry curvature, and Hall conductivity ($\sigma_{xy}$) demonstrate that the $\sigma_{xy}$ in CoS$_2$ is primarily driven by the intrinsic Karplus-Luttinger contribution, often linked to Berry phase physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21027v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tamal Kumar Dalui, Hari Paudyal, Durga Paudyal, Ramesh C Budhani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of charge to spin conversion in p-orbital InBi alloy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21129v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: High density data storage and spin-logic devices require highly efficient all-electric control of spin moments. So far, charge-to-spin conversion through the spin Hall effect limits to d-orbital materials associated with strong spin-orbit coupling, especially heavy metals. However, d-orbital heavy metals with strong spin-orbit coupling results in a short spin diffusion length, which restricts the spin transport and accumulation in spintronic devices. Therefore, the conflict between charge-to-spin conversion efficiency and spin transport ability is irreconcilable in d-orbital materials. Here, we report a large charge to spin conversion experimentally observed in the p-orbital In2Bi alloy, exhibiting the coexistence of a large spin Hall angle comparable to heave metal Pt and a long spin diffusion length (4 times that of Pt). First-principles calculations reveal that topological symmetry-protected gap opening near the Fermi level results in large Berry curvature-related spin Hall conductivity. Due to the delocalized nature of p-orbitals and semimetal properties of In2Bi, its spin current can overcome the physical barriers between spin Hall angle and spin diffusion length in d-orbital metals, thereby advancing the development of high-performance spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21129v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gen Li, Ying Zhang, Xiaoguang Xu, Lei Shen, Zheng Feng, Kangkang Meng, Ang Li, Lu Cheng, Kang He, Wei Tan, Yong Wu, Yihong Wu, Yong Jiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Composition based machine learning to predict phases &amp; strength of refractory high entropy alloys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21146</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21146v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Refractory high-entropy alloys can function at temperatures exceeding those of nickel-based superalloys. Aluminum, as an alloying element, contributes multiple advantageous characteristics to various high-temperature alloys. The Aluminum containing RHEAs have the potential of being the best high temperature materials. In the present study we use the machine learning(ML) technique to determine the phase and yield strength of aluminum containing RHEAs. In this regard, we created the Al-RHEA dataset from the published [1] compilation of RHEA data. We applied multiple ML algorithms to the training set and determined that the CatBoost algorithm gave the best performance. We optimized the hyperparameters of this algorithm and tested it for robustness using cross-validation methods. The CatBoost model predicts the yield strength of test data accurately (R2=0.98). The algorithm was applied to estimate the yield strength for alloy compositions absent from our current dataset, achieving accurate predictions for these unrecorded alloys indicating that the model has learnt the underlying rules to predict the yield strength sufficiently. We then predict the effect of varying aluminum content on yield strength of RHEA. The model predictions were rationalized in view of published data on Al-RHEAs. We also developed the CatBoost classifier model that predicts the phases formed in the alloy of a given composition accurately. The cause for errors in phase prediction is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21146v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Sreenidhi Iyengar (nSpire AI, San Francisco, CA, USA), M. K Anirudh (EY, International Tech Park, Madhapur, Hyderabad, Telangana 500081), P. H. Anantha Desik (Tata Consultancy Services, Hyderabad, India 500081), M. P. Phaniraj (Department of Metallurgical and Materials Engineering, Mahatma Gandhi Institute of Technology, Hyderabad, India)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Crystal Structure Prediction Using Genetic Algorithm and Universal Neural Network Potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21201</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21201v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Crystal structure prediction (CSP) is crucial for identifying stable crystal structures in given systems and is a prerequisite for computational atomistic simulations. Recent advances in neural network potentials (NNPs) have reduced the computational cost of CSP. However, searching for stable crystal structures across the entire composition space in multicomponent systems remains a significant challenge. Here, we propose a novel genetic algorithm (GA) -based CSP method using a universal NNP. Our GA-based methods are designed to efficiently expand convex hull volumes while preserving the diversity of crystal structures. This approach draws inspiration from the similarity between convex hull updates and Pareto front evolution in multi-objective optimization. Our evaluation shows that the present method outperforms the symmetry-aware random structure generation, achieving a larger convex hull with fewer trials. We demonstrated that our approach, combined with the developed universal NNP (PFP), can accurately reproduce and explore phase diagrams obtained through DFT calculations; this indicates the validity of PFP across a wide range of crystal structures and element combinations. This study, which integrates a universal NNP with a GA-based CSP method, highlights the promise of these methods in materials discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21201v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takuya Shibayama, Hideaki Imamura, Katsuhiko Nishimra, Kohei Shinohara, Chikashi Shinagawa, So Takamoto, Ju Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tailoring non-collinear magnetism and 3d $-$ 4f exchange interactions in RVO$_3$ epitaxial thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21327v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In orthorhombic perovskite oxides (RMO$_3$), substituting R$^{3+}$ rare-earth cations tailors the spin, orbital, and charge degrees of freedom of the central M$^{3+}$ transition metal cations through lattice distortions. In turn, these modify also the surrounding environment of R$^{3+}$. When both R$^{3+}$ and M$^{3+}$ exhibit magnetic properties, phenomena such as spin reorientation and magnetization reversal can occur. In fact, the underlying exchange interactions between M-$3d$ spins and R-$4f$ magnetic moments enrich the multifunctional character of RMO$_3$, particularly when combined with structural distortions. They play a crucial role in achieving appealing properties such as robust magnetoelectricity with non-collinear magnetic orders. Here, we explore the exchange coupling in epitaxial PrVO$_3$ thin films, selectively probing the magnetism of cation sublattices, and uncovering simultaneous V$^{3+}$ $3d$ spin reorientation and Pr$^{3+}$ $4f$ magnetization reversal using spectroscopy techniques. By strain engineering, we manipulate the lattice distortions to rationalize their role in coupling $3d$ spins and $4f$ magnetic moments. Theorectical calculations show that octahedral rotations and Jahn-Teller distortions act as tuning mechanisms, promoting competition between orbital and spin orders. The observed coupling between magnetic cations and lattice distortions can be extended to other orthorhombic RMO$_3$ systems, advancing the understanding of controlling spins in engineered perovskite heterostructures and superlattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21327v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>O. Copie, J. Varignon, I. C. Infante, M. Martirosyan, F. Choueikani, P. Ohresser, P. -E. Janolin, A. Pautrat, A. David, P. Ghosez, W. Prellier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Subtle Structural Anomaly under Compression in Line-Nodal CaSb$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21340</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21340v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We report X-ray diffraction patterns and calculated electronic band structures of the Dirac line-nodal material CaSb$_2$ under pressure. Its superconducting transition temperature ($T_{\mathrm{c}}=1.7$ K) increases under pressure and reaches a maximum at 3.4 K at around 3 GPa. We observed subtle anomalies in lattice parameters accompanied by a jump in bulk modulus without any change in crystal symmetry at around 3 GPa. First-principles calculations revealed that the distorted lattice of Sb(1) site deforms in the pressure range of 0-3 GPa. Those results suggest the existence of a first-order structural transition and arouse expectations for unusual phononic properties affecting the superconducting state. The calculated pressure dependence of the electronic density of states (DOS) confirms that it is not the change in the DOS that governs the variations in $T_{\mathrm{c}}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21340v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.7566/JPSJ.94.044605</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 94, 044605 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hidemitsu Takahashi, Atsutoshi Ikeda, Shunsaku Kitagawa, Hirokazu Kadobayashi, Naohisa Hirao, Kenji Ishida, Tsuyoshi Imazu, Yoshiteru Maeno</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>THz carrier dynamics in $SrTiO_{3}/LaTiO_{3}$ interface two-dimensional electron gases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21341</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21341v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A two-dimensional electron gas (2DEG) forms at the interface of complex oxides like $SrTiO_{3}$ (STO) and $LaTiO_{3}$ (LTO), despite each material having a low native conductivity, as a band and a Mott insulator, respectively. The interface 2DEG hosts charge carriers with moderate charge carrier density and mobility that raised interest as a material system for applications like field-effect transistors or detectors. Of particular interest is the integration of these oxide systems in silicon technology. To this end we study the carrier dynamics in a STO/LTO/STO heterostructure epitaxially grown on Si(001) both experimentally and theoretically. Linear THz spectroscopy was performed to analyze the temperature dependent charge carrier density and mobility, which was found to be in the range of $10^{12}$ $cm^2$ and 1000 $cm^2V^{-1}s^{-1}$, respectively. Pump-probe measurements revealed a very minor optical nonlinearity caused by hot carriers with a relaxation time of several 10 ps, even at low temperature. Density functional theory calculations with a Hubbard U term on ultrathin STO-capped LTO films on STO(001) show an effective mass of 0.64-0.68 $m_{e}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21341v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahana Bhattacharya, Andri Darmawan, Jeong Woo Han, Frederik Steinkamp, Nicholas S. Bingham, Ryan J. Suess, Stephan Winnerl, Markus E. Grune, Eric N. Jin, Frederick J. Walker, Charles H. Ahn, Rossitza Pentcheva, Martin Mittendorff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insight into magnetocaloric properties of Mn2Nb molecular magnet by relaxation calorimetry: A comprehensive case study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21343v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Magnetocaloric effect in [Nb$^\mathrm{IV}${($\mu$-CN)$_4$Mn$^\mathrm{II}$(H$_2$O)$_2$]}$_2\cdot$4H$_2$O]$_n$ molecular magnet is reported. The compound crystallizes in the tetragonal I4/m space group. It exhibits a phase transition to a long-range ferrimagnetically ordered state at $T_\mathrm{c}$ = 47.0(2) K. In order to calculate magnetocaloric properties relaxation calorimetry measurements are performed and a self-consistent scheme based on the magnetic entropy counting for the baseline determination is developed. The molecular field model is used to simulate the temperature and field dependence of the magnetic entropy change. The exchange coupling constant between the Mn$^\mathrm{II}$ and Nb$^\mathrm{IV}$ ions is estimated to be equal to -10.26 K. At the lowest temperatures and for the lowest applied field change values the inverse magnetocaloric effect is revealed, which seems to be characteristic for systems with antiferromagnetic coupling. The temperature dependence of exponent $n$ quantifying the field dependence of $\Delta S_\mathrm{M}$ is calculated on the basis of the experimental results and within the mean-field model. Its predicting power for the universality class of the critical behavior is discussed. Finally, the studied compound is employed as the working substance in the two most natural refrigeration cycles, i.e. the Brayton cycle and the Ericsson cycle, to assess its cooling effectiveness. A cascade system is suggested for the most efficient cooling performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21343v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert Pelka, Yuji Miyazaki, Yasuhiro Nakazawa, Dawid Pinkowicz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Limited Diffusion of Silicon in GaN: A DFT Study Supported by Experimental Evidence</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21382v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Silicon (Si) is the primary donor dopant in gallium nitride (GaN), introduced through epitaxial growth or ion implantation. However, precise control over Si diffusion remains a critical challenge for high-performance device applications. This study investigates Si diffusion mechanisms in bulk GaN using first-principles density functional theory (DFT) calculations, supported by ultra-high-pressure annealing (UHPA) experiments. Vacancy-mediated diffusion pathways were analyzed using the SIESTA code, with minimum energy paths (MEPs) and activation barriers determined via the nudged elastic band (NEB) method. The results indicate that Si diffusion barriers vary with crystallographic direction, with the lowest barrier of 3.2 eV along [11-20] and the highest barrier of ~9.9 eV along [1-100], rendering diffusion in this direction highly improbable. Alternative diffusion mechanisms, including direct exchange and ring-like migration, exhibit prohibitively high barriers ($&gt;$12 eV). Phonon calculations confirm that temperature-induced reductions in effective diffusion barriers are minimal. Experimental validation using SIMS analysis on Si-implanted GaN samples subjected to UHPA (1450{\deg}C, 1 GPa) confirms negligible Si diffusion under these extreme conditions. These findings resolve inconsistencies in prior reports and establish that Si-doped GaN remains highly stable, ensuring reliable doping profiles for advanced electronic and optoelectronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21382v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karol Kawka, Pawel Kempisty, Akira Kusaba, Krzysztof Golyga, Karol Pozyczka, Michal Fijalkowski, Michal Bockowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>No-drift phase-change memory alloy for neuromorphic computing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21446</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21446v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spontaneous structural relaxation is intrinsic to glassy materials due to their metastable nature. For phase-change materials (PCMs), the resultant temporal change in electrical resistance seriously hamper in-memory computing (IMC) applications. Here, we report an ab-initio-calculation-informed design of amorphous PCM composed of robust "molecule-like" motifs with minimal Peierls distortion, depriving the amorphous alloy of structural ingredients that would gradually evolve upon aging to entail resistance drift. We demonstrate amorphous CrTe3 thin films that display practically no resistance drift at any working temperature from -200 to 165 degree C. We achieve multilevel programming of CrTe3 through both step-wise crystallization and step-wise amorphization using a hybrid opto-electronic device at various temperatures. Moreover, the application potential of CrTe3 in neuromorphic computing is testified by its incorporation in a vehicle with automatic path-tracking function. Our work opens a new avenue to achieving IMC-requisite properties via judicious design of the composition and atomic-level structure of disordered PCM alloys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21446v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaozhe Wang, Ruobing Wang, Suyang Sun, Ding Xu, Chao Nie, Zhou Zhou, Chenyu Wen, Junying Zhang, Ruixuan Chu, Xueyang Shen, Wen Zhou, Zhitang Song, Jiang-Jing Wang, En Ma, Wei Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An appraisal of Understanding Pressure Effects on Structural, Optical, and Magnetic Properties of CsMnF_{4} and Other 3d^{n} Compounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21451</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21451v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A recently published article in Inorganic Chemistry (DOI: 10.1021/acs.inorgchem.4c00599) offers theoretical calculations on the effects of pressure on the structural, optical, and magnetic behavior of CsMnF_{4}. Although a thorough theoretical and experimental understanding of this material is certainly warranted, there are previously published experimental results on CsMnF_{4}, as well as on other Mn^{3+} fluorides, under pressure that have not been considered in the aforementioned article. These findings raise questions about the accuracy of the theoretical estimates and the validity of the methodology used to determine the reported structural, optical, and magnetic properties. This paper intends to provide the readers of Inorganic Chemistry and the broader scientific community with a perspective on a publication that directly contradicts interpretations presented in prior research.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21451v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acs.inorgchem.4c00599</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Fernando Rodriguez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interface-plane parameterization for macroscopic grain boundary identification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21482</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21482v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The geometric state of a flat boundary is frequently described using the so-called macroscopic parameters. They are a principal tool for dealing with interfaces at the continuous scale. The paper describes a new method for macroscopic identification of boundaries. The proposed approach is based on Euler angles representing orientations of the crystals. Two pairs of the angles are directly related to two vectors normal to the boundary plane in the crystal reference frames, and the new boundary representation can be viewed as a triplet composed of these vectors and the angle of rotation about the axis perpendicular to the plane. The representation resembles the `interface-plane scheme', but unlike the latter, it is a proper parameterization. Basic practical aspects of the parameterization (such as equivalences due to symmetries, fundamental regions, uniform distribution of boundaries) are considered. The parameterization is applied to examination of Bulatov-Reed-Kumar model of grain boundary energy and reveals its previously unknown features. The proposed boundary identification method, apart from its use in numerical calculations, appeals to physical intuition.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21482v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adam Morawiec</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast control of coherent acoustic lattice dynamics in the transition metal dichalcogenide alloy WSSe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21520v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Coherent acoustic phonons (CAPs)$-$propagating strain waves that can dynamically modify the structure and symmetry of a crystal$-$offer unique opportunities for controlling material properties. We investigate CAP generation in the Janus-like layered alloy tungsten sulfide selenide (WS$_x$Se$_{1-x}$, hereafter WSSe). Employing high-fluence photoexcitation at 400 nm combined with ultrafast transient reflection spectroscopy, we capture the carrier-lattice dynamics governed by a cascade of processes including rapid exciton formation, phonon recycling, and thermoelastic deformation. These phenomena precede the emergence of a robust CAP mode at 27 GHz. Notably, the CAP amplitude in WSSe substantially exceeds that observed in the symmetric parent crystals WS$_2$ and WSe$_2$, which we attribute to an enhanced coupling mediated by a built-in out-of-plane electric field arising from the inversion asymmetry of the WSSe alloy. Furthermore, the implementation of a tailored two-pulse excitation sequence enables optical control of the CAP, underscoring the potential of WSSe and related Janus-like layered alloys as versatile building blocks in optomechanical and nanoacoustic device applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21520v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sergio I. Rey, Martin J. Cross, Malte L. Welsch, Frederik Schr\"oder, Binbin Zhou, Nicolas Stenger, Peter U. Jepsen, Edmund J. R. Kelleher</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Statistical learning of structure-property relationships for transport in porous media, using hybrid AI modeling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21560</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21560v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The 3D microstructure of porous media, such as electrodes in lithium-ion batteries or fiber-based materials, significantly impacts the resulting macroscopic properties, including effective diffusivity or permeability. Consequently, quantitative structure-property relationships, which link structural descriptors of 3D microstructures such as porosity or geodesic tortuosity to effective transport properties, are crucial for further optimizing the performance of porous media. To overcome the limitations of 3D imaging, parametric stochastic 3D microstructure modeling is a powerful tool to generate many virtual but realistic structures at the cost of computer simulations. The present paper uses 90,000 virtually generated 3D microstructures of porous media derived from literature by systematically varying parameters of stochastic 3D microstructure models. Previously, this data set has been used to establish quantitative microstructure-property relationships. The present paper extends these findings by applying a hybrid AI framework to this data set. More precisely, symbolic regression, powered by deep neural networks, genetic algorithms, and graph attention networks, is used to derive precise and robust analytical equations. These equations model the relationships between structural descriptors and effective transport properties without requiring manual specification of the underlying functional relationship. By integrating AI with traditional computational methods, the hybrid AI framework not only generates predictive equations but also enhances conventional modeling approaches by capturing relationships influenced by specific microstructural features traditionally underrepresented. Thus, this paper significantly advances the predictive modeling capabilities in materials science, offering vital insights for designing and optimizing new materials with tailored transport properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21560v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Somayeh Hosseinhashemi, Philipp Rieder, Orkun Furat, Benedikt Prifling, Changlin Wu, Christoph Thon, Volker Schmidt, Carsten Schilde</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermoelectric Performance Boost by Chemical Order in Epitaxial L2$_1$ (100) and (110) Oriented undoped Fe$_2$VAl Thin Films: An Experimental and Theoretical Study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21575</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21575v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study demonstrates the direct correlation between the presence of the L2$_1$ ordered phase and the large enhancement in the thermoelectric performance of Fe$_2$VAl thin films deposited on MgO and Al$_2$O$_3$ substrates at temperatures varying between room temperature and 950$^{\circ}$C. We employ both experimental techniques and computational modeling to analyze the influence of crystallographic orientation and deposition temperature on the thermoelectric properties, including the Seebeck coefficient, electrical conductivity, and thermal conductivity. Our findings indicate that the presence of the L2$_1$ phase significantly enhances the power factor (PF) and figure of merit (zT), surpassing previously reported values for both bulk and thin film forms of Fe$_2$VAl, achieving a PF of 480 $\mu$W/m$\cdot$K$^2$ and a zT of 0.025.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21575v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jos\'e Mar\'ia Dom\'inguez-V\'azquez, Olga Caballero-Calero, Ketan Lohani, Jos\'e J. Plata, Antonio M. Marquez, Cristina V. Manzano, Miguel \'Angel Tenaguillo, Hiromichi Ohta, Alfonso Cebollada, Andres Conca, Marisol Mart\'in-Gonz\'alez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic Limitation of Conductivity in Depolymerized Sodium-ion Glassy Networks</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21624</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21624v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The electric properties of a model fast-ion electrolyte ((100-x)SiS2-xNa2S) glass are investigated by means of classical molecular dynamics simulations. These systems appear promising for battery applications and the conductivity is thought to be essentially driven by the concentration of charge carriers (Na) so that the usual amount is found to be of about 50% &lt; x &lt; 80%. We first set up a Buckingham-Coulomb type potential that describes the atomic structure and experimental structure functions (structure factor) in an improved fashion with respect to previous reported force fields. A systematic investigation of properties with modifier content Na2S permits to acknowledge an unexpected result which manifests by a near constant of conductivity upon Na2S for various isotherms in the liquid state. The analysis indicates that unlike Li-based electrolytes, the diffusivity difference between networks species (Si,S) and modifier (Na) is too small so that the contribution to conductivity is essentially driven by the former. The main reason is the reduction of the concentration of network species in the range 66% &lt; x &lt; 80% without any dramatic increase in Na diffusivity, and the emergence of molecular Na2S in the structure at large modifier content which also induces profound structural changes. Unlike Lithium glassy electrolytes, the design of Na-based batteries must, therefore, take into account the contribution of the network species.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21624v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L\'eo Legrand, Louis-Martin Poitras, Nicolas Sator, Matthieu Micoulaut</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Shear Strain-Induced Multiferroic Response in the Altermagnetic Semiconductor CuFeS$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21637</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21637v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: CuFeS$_2$ is an altermagnetic semiconductor that is lattice-matched with silicon and has a high N\'eel temperature. It is nonpolar and magnetically compensated in its structural ground state. However, the crystal belongs to a magnetic symmetry class allowing simultaneous piezoelectricity and -magnetism, indicating that distortion by shear strain may enable functional properties not observed in its tetragonal ground state. This first-principles study explores how biaxial and shear strain affect the crystal structure and functional properties. Biaxial strain lowers crystal symmetry when applied to two of the three crystallographic {001} planes considered, enhancing the altermagnetic lifting of the Kramers degeneracy. Shear strain has a compressive effect on the crystal, enhancing the effects on the electronic structure seen under biaxial compressive strain. Applying it to any one of the three {001} planes induces a polar phase with an out-of-plane electric polarization, perpendicular to the strained plane. Moreover, applying shear strain to two out of the three {001} planes induces a net magnetization simultaneously with electric polarization, producing a multiferroic response.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21637v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roman Malyshev, Bj{\o}rnulf Brekke, Ingeborg-Helene Svenum, Sverre M. Selbach, Christoph Br\"une, Arne Brataas, Thomas Tybell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of non-equilibrium in ultrafast irradiation of matter</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21647</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21647v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This proceeding discusses nonequilibrium effects in matter exposed to XUV/X-ray irradiation. When ultrashort, intense XUV/X-ray pulses interact with materials, they trigger a complex sequence of processes, including electronic excitation, nonequilibrium electron kinetics, energy exchange with the atomic system, electronic thermalization, and subsequent atomic dynamics. These effects were investigated using XTANT-3, a hybrid simulation tool that simultaneously models all relevant dynamics. XTANT-3 integrates (a) a Monte Carlo transport method for photon absorption and fast electron kinetics, (b) the Boltzmann equation for nonequilibrium slow electron dynamics, (c) a transferable tight-binding approach for electronic structure evolution and interatomic potential modeling, and (d) molecular dynamics for atomic system response. This approach enables a detailed study of nonequilibrium effects in each subsystem and their interplay with nonthermal damage, where electronic excitation alters the interatomic potential. Methods of quantifying the nonequilibrium in the electronic and atomic subsystems are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21647v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nikita Medvedev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning Assisted Modeling of Amorphous TiO$_2$-Doped GeO$_2$ for Advanced LIGO Mirror Coatings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21701</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21701v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The mechanical loss angle of amorphous TiO$_2$-doped GeO$_2$ can be lower than 10$^{-4}$, making it a candidate for Laser Interferometer Gravitational-wave Observatory (LIGO) mirror coatings. Amorphous oxides have complex atomic structures that are influenced by various factors, including doping concentration, preparation, and thermal history, resulting in different mass densities and physical properties. Modeling at atomistic level enables capturing these effects by generating atomic structure models according to experimental conditions. In order to obtain reliable and physical amorphous models at an affordable cost, we develop classical and machine-learning potentials (MLP) to speed up simulations. First-principles calculations are used to train and validate MLP as well as validating structure models. To better reproduce properties such as elastic modulus, radial distribution function (RDF) and the variations in mass density of doped amorphous oxides, density functional theory (DFT) calculations are used to optimize the final models. We find that the mass densities of amorphous systems are correlated with the total void volume. The experimental mass density matches the models with the most symmetric potential energy wells under volume change. The elastic response of the metal-oxygen network is also studied. The 27\% TiO$_2$ doped GeO$_2$ system shows the least number of large atom-atom distance changes, while for 44\% TiO$_2$ doped GeO$_2$, a majority of Ti-O distances are significantly changed. In response to strains, the metal-oxygen network at low mass densities prefers to adjust bond angles, while at high mass densities, the adjustment is mainly done by changing atom-atom distance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21701v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jun Jiang, Rui Zhang, Kiran Prasai, Riccardo Bassiri, James N. Fry, Martin M. Fejer, Hai-Ping Cheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Heterostructure Effects on the Magnetocrystalline Anisotropy Energy of MnN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21707</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21707v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Thin film effects on the Magnetocrystalline Anisotropy Energy (MAE) of MnN were studied using density functional theory (DFT). Initially, strain effects on bulk MnN were considered as a proxy for lattice-matching induced strain and a linear relationship between the c/a ratio and the MAE was found. This relationship was explained in terms of underlying point group symmetry. Strain and charge-transfer effects were then considered for an ultra-thin film. It was found that a Ta seed-layer suppresses the net spin moment on the Mn ions, leading to a reduction of the MAE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21707v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robert A. Lawrence, Matt I. J. Probert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Host-dependent frequency offsets in $^{229}$Th nuclear clockwork</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.20984</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.20984v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recent advances in laser excitation of the low-energy nuclear isomer transition in $^{229}$Th have opened avenues for developing nuclear clocks, a novel quantum technology with exceptional performance and sensitivity to exotic physics. Here we explore the host-dependence of the nuclear clock frequency, focusing on the isomer shift induced by the difference in the nuclear charge distribution between the ground and excited nuclear states. We combine relativistic many-body methods of atomic structure with periodic density functional theory to evaluate the isomer shifts in solid-state hosts. Our analysis predicts nuclear clock frequencies for various solid-state and trapped ion platforms: $ \omega_\text{clk}(\text{solid state}) = 2,020,407,384(40) \, \text{MHz}$, $\omega_\text{clk}($$^{229}$Th$^{4+}) = 2,020,407,648(70) \, \text{MHz}$, and $\omega_\text{clk}(^{229}\text{Th}{3+})= 2,020,407,114(70) \, \text{MHz}$. We also determine the nuclear transition energy for the bare $^{229}$Th nucleus to be $\omega_\text{nuc} = 8.272(22) \,\text{eV}$. Our calculated valence-band isomer shifts for different host materials constrain the nuclear transition frequencies to an 80 MHz-wide frequency window, aiding experimental searches for the $^{229}$Th nuclear transition in novel materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.20984v1</guid>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>nucl-th</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>U. C. Perera, H. W. T. Morgan, Eric R. Hudson, Andrei Derevianko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Insulator-to-Metal Transition via Magnetic Reconstruction at Oxide Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21093</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21093v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ultrathin two-dimensional (2D) electronic systems at the interfaces of layered materials are highly desirable platforms for exploring of novel quantum phenomena and developing advanced device applications. Here, we investigate ultrathin heterostructures composed of SrIrO3 (SIO) and SrRuO3 (SRO) layers to uncover their emergent properties. Strikingly, despite the fact that both individual layers are antiferromagnetic insulators, the interfaced heterostructure exhibits emergent metallicity. Through transport measurements, magnetic characterization, and angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES), we analyze the underlying mechanisms governing this insulator-to-metal transition. Our findings reveal that the transition is driven by interface-induced magnetic reconstruction, which is further corroborated by density functional theory (DFT) calculations. The staggered Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction at the SIO/SRO interface is identified as the key driving force for this spin reorganization, as it stabilizes ferromagnetism in the coupled antiferromagnetic insulating layers. These findings highlight the significant potential of engineering interfacial magnetic interactions as a powerful approach to generate and control emergent electronic properties, paving the way for novel functionalities that are unattainable in individual ultrathin films.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21093v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zengxing Lu, Jiatai Feng, Xuan Zheng, You-guo Shi, Run-Wei Li, Carmine Autieri, Mario Cuoco, Milan Radovic, Zhiming Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Valley-polarized Quantum Anomalous Hall and Topological Metal Phase in Rashba induced pseudospin-1 lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21209</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21209v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the topological properties of Rashba spin-orbit coupling and exchange coupling induced pseudospin-$1$ system Dice lattice under the influence of a staggered electric potential and magnetization. The band structure and topological phases of the system are investigated and compared with pseudospin-$\frac{1}{2}$ system honeycomb lattice. Under individual influence of the staggered electric field and magnetization, the system undergoes a distinct phase transition: (i) a staggered electric potential drives the system from a quantum anomalous Hall $(C_n = 2)$ to a valley polarized quantum anomalous Hall phase $(C_n = -1)$ associated with edge modes with a flip in the chirality; while (ii) a staggered magnetization changes the system to a topological metal associated with unconventional antichiral edge bands, from a topological insulator. These results are further supported by calculations of the Chern numbers, Hall conductance, zigzag, and armchair edge states. Our findings enhance the understanding of new topological phases in the 2D pseudospin-1 system and open up a new platform to explore the anti-chiral edge states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21209v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Puspita Parui, Bheema Lingam Chittari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effects of Stirring Time on Formation of Microplastics Fragmented from Photo-aged Polypropylene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21373v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This paper examines the evolution of microplastic (MP) size distributions fragmented from photo-aged polypropylene (PP) in stirred water. PP specimens fragmented into MPs with their size of 1-30 um after UV irradiation and stirring in laboratory settings. MPs were dispersed into the water during the stirring process. A series of MP size distributions was analyzed from optical microscope images of obtained MPs. The MP size distribution was described by an exponential function in the short stirring time domain, whereas it changed to a power-law function as the stirring time increased. The fragmentation rate of MPs and nanoplastics (NPs) decreased with increasing stirring time. The obtained MP exhibited higher crystallinity than the photo-aged PP specimen after stirring. This result implies that MP fragmentation is induced by the chemi-crystallization of PP.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21373v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kazuya Haremaki, Takumitsu Kida, Yusuke Koide, Takashi Uneyama, Yuichi Masubuchi, Takato Ishida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrafast Saddletronics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21376</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21376v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Low energy valleys in the band structure of 2d materials represent a potential route to the ultrafast writing of information in quantum matter by laser light, with excited charge at the K or K$^\ast$ valleys representing the fundamental states of 1 and 0. Here we demonstrate that a second electronic feature, the saddle point, is endowed with lightwave control over information states. Linearly polarized light is shown to excite 2 of the 3 inequivalent M point saddles in graphene, generating three possible excited configurations, with which of these are realised determined by the polarization vector direction. We show that saddle excitation is highly robust, with "saddle polarized" states created both in the sub-cycle strong field regime and the long time limit of extended multi-cycle pulses. Our findings, applicable to other members of the graphene family and Xenes such as stanene, point towards a rich and ultrafast light based manipulation of matter based on the saddle point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21376v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sangeeta Sharma, Deepika Gill, John Kay Dewhurst, Peter Elliott, Sam Shallcross</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Fe-Ni phase diagram and the Earth's inner core structure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21493</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21493v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Fe-Ni alloy is believed to be the main component of Earth's core. Yet, a comprehensive understanding of phase equilibria near the melting point of this alloy under core conditions is still lacking, leaving the effect of nickel inconclusive. Using ab initio simulations, we computed Gibbs free energy and phase diagram for liquid and solid solutions of the Fe-Ni alloy under conditions close to the inner core, considering inner-shell electron contributions and non-ideal mixing effects. The Fe-Ni phase diagram provides crucial insights for understanding previous experimental observations and crystallization simulations of the Fe-Ni alloy under core conditions. It also presents new scenarios for inner core structures, suggesting bcc-liquid coexistence at the inner core boundary and the possibility of multi-layer structures consisting of bcc-hcp composites within the inner core. Our work clarifies nickel's substantial impact on the inner core structure, providing new constraints for the study of core's composition and formation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21493v1</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liangrui Wei, Kai-Ming Ho, Renata M. Wentzcovitch, Yang Sun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amplifying solid-state high harmonic generations with momentum k-gaps in band structure engineering</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21549v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel amplification mechanism for high harmonic generation (HHG) in solids by leveraging bandgap engineering with momentum k-gaps. By constructing a simple diatomic lattice featuring balanced, alternating gain and loss profiles, facilitated by an array of four-level systems, we explore the physics of k-gap-amplified Bloch oscillations in the intraband channel of solid-state HHG. Through numerical simulations, we elucidate the coexistence of amplification and harmonic radiation processes in a solid. Our finding reveals that advanced bandgap engineering can define k-space optical devices - such as Brillouin cavity, Bloch-Zener oscillator and k-gap amplifier - thereby enabling the coherent manipulation of semiconductor radiation and high harmonic generation in both semiconductor superlattices and artificial materials. Furthermore, we analyze the spectrogram and material realizations required for amplifying solid-state HHG. These results underscore the potential of k-gap band structure engineering to advance coherent light sources at extremely short wavelengths.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21549v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yiming Pan, Danni Chen, Xiaoxi Xu, Zhaopin Chen, Huaiqiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Alloying as a new route to generating interlayer excitons</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21607</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21607v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose a novel route for the generation of interlayer excitons based on the synthesis of a transition metal dichalcogenide bilayer alloy material, WS$_{2x}$Se$_{2(1-x)}$. Using piezoelectric force microscopy, we demonstrate the existence of an internal electric field oriented in the out-of-plane direction. Interlayer excitons have so far been mostly observed in heterostructures with a type-II band alignment. In the presence of an internal electric field, a similar alignment occurs in the alloy bilayer resulting in an efficient generation of interlayer excitons. Photoluminescence spectroscopy measurements involving circularly polarised light come up with key observations like a negative degree of circular polarization of the interlayer excitons which increases as a function of temperature. A simple theoretical model provides a physical understanding of the major experimentally observed features. With experimentally fitted parameter values, the dominant contribution to the degree of circular polarization is shown to arise from spin polarization and not from valley polarization, a consequence of the spin-valley-layer coupling characteristic of a TMDC bilayer.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21607v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Suvadip Masanta, Chumki Nayak, Indrani Bose, Achintya Singha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic structure dimensionality of the quantum-critical ferromagnet YbNi$_4$P$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.21662</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.21662v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: YbNi$_4$P$_2$ is the first known ferromagnetic metal showing a second-order quantum phase transition. Current theoretical understanding rules out second order ferromagnetic quantum criticality in centrosymmetric 2D and 3D metals. Thus, studying the electronic structure of YbNi$_4$P$_2$ is of prime fundamental importance. Using angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy, we experimentally prove the existence of 1D Fermi surface contours. In addition, our results demonstrate that part of the electronic structure of YbNi$_4$P$_2$ is made of states of higher dimensionality, thereby bringing into question the fact that ferromagnetic quantum criticality in centrosymmetric crystals, is exclusively found in 1D systems. Our experimental data show that the electronic structure of YbNi$_4$P$_2$ is a playground of mixed dimensionality, electron correlations, strong hybridization and spin-orbit coupling, all of them providing new insights in understanding the origin of ferromagnetic quantum criticality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.21662v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.134.126401</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett.134, 126401 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>J. Dai, A. Antezak, W. Broad, M. Thees, V. Zatko, R. L. Bouwmeester, F. Fortuna, P. Le F\`evre, J. E. Rault, K. Horiba, D. V. Vyalikh, H. Kumigashira, K. Kliemt,  S.,  Friedemann, C. Krellner, E. Frantzeskakis, A. F. Santander-Syro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Two-dimensional atomic-scale ultrathin lateral heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2208.12696</link>
      <description>arXiv:2208.12696v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Ultrathin lateral heterostructures of monolayer MoS2 and WS2 have successfully been realized with the metal-organic chemical vapor deposition method. Atomic-resolution HAADF-STEM observations have revealed that the junction widths of lateral heterostructures range from several nanometers to single-atom thickness, the thinnest heterojunction in theory. The interfaces are atomically flat with minimal mixing between MoS2 and WS2, originating from rapid and abrupt switching of the source supply. Due to one-dimensional interfaces and broken rotational symmetry, the resulting ultrathin lateral heterostructures, 1~2 mixed-dimensional structures, can show emergent optical/electronic properties. The MOCVD growth developed in this work allows us to access various ultrathin lateral heterostructures, leading to future exploration of their emergent properties absent in each component alone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2208.12696v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nanami Ichinose, Mina Maruyama, Takato Hotta, Zheng Liu, Ruben Canton-Vitoria, Susumu Okada, Fanyu Zeng, Feng Zhang, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Ryo Kitaura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2D Hexagonal Boron Nitride-based Anticorrosion Coatings</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.01220</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.01220v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The corrosion of metallic surfaces poses significant challenges across industries such as petroleum, energy, and biomedical sectors, leading to structural degradation, safety risks, and substantial maintenance costs. Traditional organic and metallic coatings provide some protection, but their limited durability and susceptibility to harsh environmental conditions necessitate the development of more advanced and efficient solutions. This has driven significant interest in two-dimensional (2D) materials, with graphene extensively studied for its exceptional mechanical strength and impermeability to gases and ions. However, while graphene offers short-term corrosion protection, its high electrical conductivity presents a long-term issue by promoting galvanic corrosion on metal surfaces. In contrast, hexagonal boron nitride (h-BN) has emerged as a promising alternative for anticorrosion coatings. h-BN combines exceptional chemical stability, impermeability, and electrical insulation, making it particularly suited for long-term protection in highly corrosive or high-temperature environments. While h-BN holds promise as anticorrosion material, challenges such as structural defects, agglomeration of nanosheets, and poor dispersion within coatings limit its performance. This review provides a comprehensive analysis of recent advancements in addressing these challenges, including novel functionalization strategies, scalable synthesis methods, and hybrid systems that integrate h-BN with complementary materials. By bridging the gap between fundamental research and industrial applications, this review outlines the potential for h-BN to revolutionize anticorrosion technologies. These obstacles necessitate advanced strategies such as surface functionalization to improve compatibility with polymer matrices and dispersion optimization to minimize agglomeration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.01220v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Onurcan Kaya, Luca Gabatel, Sebastiano Bellani, Fabrizio Barberis, Francesco Bonaccorso, Ivan Cole, Stephan Roche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge Density Wave and Ferromagnetism in Intercalated CrSBr</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.08631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.08631v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In materials with one-dimensional electronic bands, electron-electron interactions can produce intriguing quantum phenomena, including spin-charge separation and charge density waves (CDW). Most of these systems, however, are non-magnetic, motivating a search for anisotropic materials where the coupling of charge and spin may affect emergent quantum states. Here, chemical intercalation of the van der Waals magnetic semiconductor CrSBr yields $Li_{0.17(2)} (tetrahydrofuran)_{0.26(3)} CrSBr$, which possess an electronically driven quasi-1D CDW with an onset temperature above room temperature. Concurrently, electron doping increases the magnetic ordering temperature from 132 K to 200 K and switches its interlayer magnetic coupling from antiferromagnetic to ferromagnetic. The spin-polarized nature of the anisotropic bands that give rise to this CDW enforces an intrinsic coupling of charge and spin. The coexistence and interplay of ferromagnetism and charge modulation in this exfoliatable material provides a promising platform for studying tunable quantum phenomena across a range of temperatures and thicknesses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.08631v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Margalit L. Feuer, Morgan Thinel, Xiong Huang, Zhi-Hao Cui, Yinming Shao, Asish K. Kundu, Daniel G. Chica, Myung-Geun Han, Rohan Pokratath, Evan J. Telford, Jordan Cox, Emma York, Saya Okuno, Chun-Ying Huang, Owethu Bukula, Luca M. Nashabeh, Siyuan Qiu, Colin P. Nuckolls, Cory R. Dean, Simon J. L. Billinge, Xiaoyang Zhu, Yimei Zhu, Dmitri N. Basov, Andrew J. Millis, David R. Reichman, Abhay N. Pasupathy, Xavier Roy, Michael E. Ziebel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interactive Multiscale Modeling to Bridge Atomic Properties and Electrochemical Performance in Li-CO$_2$ Battery Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10954v5 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Li-CO$_2$ batteries show promise as energy storage solutions, offering high theoretical energy density and CO$_2$ fixation. Their operation is based on the formation and decomposition of Li$_2$CO$_3$/C during discharge and charge cycles, respectively. We used a multiscale modeling framework that integrates Density Functional Theory (DFT), Ab-Initio Molecular Dynamics (AIMD), classical Molecular Dynamics (MD), and Finite Element Analysis (FEA) to investigate atomic and cell-level properties. The considered Li-CO$_2$ battery consists of a lithium metal anode, an ionic liquid electrolyte, and a carbon cloth porous cathode with Sb$_{0.67}$Bi$_{1.33}$Te$_3$ as a catalyst. DFT and AIMD determined the electrical conductivities of Sb$_{0.67}$Bi$_{1.33}$Te$_3$ and Li$_2$CO$_3$ using the Kubo-Greenwood formalism and studied the CO$_2$ reduction mechanism on the cathode catalyst. MD simulations calculated the CO$_2$ diffusion coefficient, Li$^+$ transference number, ionic conductivity, and Li$^+$ solvation structure. The FEA model, incorporating results from atomistic simulations, reproduced experimental voltage-capacity profiles at 1 mA/cm$^2$ and revealed spatio-temporal variations in Li$_2$CO$_3$/C deposition, porosity, and CO$_2$ concentration dependence on discharge rates in the cathode. Accordingly, Li$_2$CO$_3$ can form large and thin film deposits, leading to dispersed and local porosity changes at 0.1 mA/cm$^2$ and 1 mA/cm$^2$, respectively. The capacity decreases exponentially from 81,570 mAh/g at 0.1 mA/cm$^2$ to 6,200 mAh/g at 1 mA/cm$^2$, due to pore clogging from excessive discharge product deposition that limits CO$_2$ transport to the cathode interior. Therefore, the performance of Li-CO$_2$ batteries can be improved by enhancing CO$_2$ transport, regulating Li$_2$CO$_3$ deposition, and optimizing cathode architecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10954v5</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Lemaalem, Selva Chandrasekaran Selvaraj, Ilias Papailias, Naveen K. Dandu, Arash Namaeighasemi, Larry A. Curtiss, Amin Salehi-Khojin, Anh T. Ngo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-Dimensional to Layered Halide Perovskites: A Parameter-Free Hybrid Functional Method for Predicting Electronic Band Gaps</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.13852</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.13852v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accurate prediction of electronic band gaps in halide perovskites using density functional theory is crucial for optoelectronic applications. Standard hybrid functionals like HSE and PBE0 are becoming computationally accessible, yet can fail at predicting the band gaps for three-dimensional (3D) and/or layered halide perovskite. This study evaluates the doubly screened dielectric-dependent hybrid (DSH) functional for predicting band gaps of Pb- and Sn-based inorganic and hybrid 3D halide perovskites, as well as layered hybrid perovskites. The DSH functional employs material-dependent mixing parameters derived from macroscopic dielectric constants, and accurately predicts band gaps for 3D perovskites only if structural local disorder is taken into account. For layered hybrid perovskites, the DSH functional based on average dielectric constants tends to overestimate the band gaps. To improve predictions, we propose using the calculated dielectric constant of the respective 3D perovskites to define the DSH screening. This method is then applied to Pb- and Sn-based layered halide perovskites with various organic spacers and multilayered structures, such as $BA_2MA_{n-1}Pb_{n}I_{3n-1}$ with n =1, 2, 3, resulting in improved precision. The HSE functional systematically underestimates band gaps in layered perovskites due to the missing non-local long-range dielectric screening. On the other hand, the PBE0 is in good agreement with the experimental values, in particular for the layered iodide perovskites. The computational framework introduced here provides an efficient parameter-free \textit{ab initio} methodology suitable for predicting the electronic properties of 3D, layered halide perovskites and their heterostructures, towards modelling materials for advanced optoelectronic devices</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.13852v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ibrahim Buba Garba, Lorenzo Trombini, Claudine Katan, Jacky Even, Marios Zacharias, Mikael Kepenekian, George Volonakis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deep learning with reflection high-energy electron diffraction images to predict cation ratio in Sr$_{2x}$Ti$_{2(1-x)}$O$_{3}$ thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18523</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18523v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Machine learning (ML) with in situ diagnostics offers a transformative approach to accelerate, understand, and control thin film synthesis by uncovering relationships between synthesis conditions and material properties. In this study, we demonstrate the application of deep learning to predict the stoichiometry of Sr$_{2x}$Ti$_{2(1-x)}$O$_{3}$ thin films using reflection high-energy electron diffraction images acquired during pulsed laser deposition. A gated convolutional neural network trained for regression of the Sr atomic fraction achieved accurate predictions with a small dataset of 31 samples. Explainable AI techniques revealed a previously unknown correlation between diffraction streak features and cation stoichiometry in Sr$_{2x}$Ti$_{2(1-x)}$O$_{3}$ thin films. Our results demonstrate how ML can be used to transform a ubiquitous in situ diagnostic tool, that is usually limited to qualitative assessments, into a quantitative surrogate measurement of continuously valued thin film properties. Such methods are critically needed to enable real-time control, autonomous workflows, and accelerate traditional synthesis approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18523v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sumner B. Harris, Patrick T. Gemperline, Christopher M. Rouleau, Rama K. Vasudevan, Ryan B. Comes</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable altermagnetism via inter-chain engineering in parallelassembled atomic chains</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05785</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05785v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnetism has recently drawn considerable attention in three- and twodimensional materials. Here, we extend this concept to quasi-one-dimensional (Q1D) monolayers assembled from single-atomic magnetic chains. Through systematically examining nine types of structures, two stacking orders, and intra-/inter-chain magnetic couplings, we identify four out of thirty promising structural prototypes for hosting altermagnetism, which yields 192 potential monolayer materials. We further confirm eight thermodynamically stable Q1D monolayers via high-throughput calculations. Using symmetry analysis and first-principles calculations, we find that the existence of altermagnetism is determined by the type of inter-chain magnetic coupling and predict three intrinsic altermagnets,\(CrBr_3\),\(VBr_3\),\(MnBr_3\),due to their ferromagnetic inter-chain couplings and five extrinsic ones,\(CrF_3\),\(CrCl_3\),\(CrI_3\),\(FeCl_3\)and \(CoTe_3\), ascribed to their neglectable or antiferromagnetic inter-chain couplings. Moreover, the inter-chain magnetic coupling here is highly tunable by manipulating the inter-chain spacing, leading to experimentally feasible transitions between altermagnetic and nodal-line semiconducting states. In addition, applying external electric fields can further modulate the spin splitting. Our findings establish a highly tunable family of Q1D altermagnets, offering fundamental insights into the intricate relationship between geometry, electronic structure, and magnetism.These discoveries hold significant promises for experimental realization and future spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05785v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Deping Guo, Canbo Zong, Weihan Zhang, Cong Wang, Junwei Liu, Wei Ji</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing Nanostructures in High-Entropy Alloys via Machine-Learning Accelerated Scalable Monte Carlo Simulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12591</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12591v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The computational cost of traditional first-principles method quickly becomes prohibitively expensive as the number of atoms increases. This challenge is further amplified by the need to evaluate finite-temperature properties with Monte Carlo (MC) simulations, which is inherently challenging to parallelize due to sequential Markov chain updates. Here, we introduce Scalable Monte Carlo (SMC), an efficient MC simulation method that overcomes the parallelization bottlenecks in conventional MC simulation, reducing the computational complexity of a MC sweep from quadratic to linear. We present a GPU implementation of the SMC method, SMC-GPU, which simultaneously harnesses the thousands of processing cores on a GPU to accelerate the computation. By adopting a data-driven workflow that surrogates the computationally expensive density functional theory (DFT) with ML models, we demonstrate that SMC-GPU is capable of simulating systems of more than one-billion atoms, while maintaining the accuracy of first-principles methods. Using this unprecedented capability, we performed billion-atom MC simulations to investigate the nanostructure evolution of two important high-entropy alloys (HEAs), FeCoNiAlTi and MoNbTaW, in which the nanostructures are believed to be responsible for their superb mechanical properties. Our results reveal a rich diversity of nanostructures, including nanoparticles (NP), 3D-connected NP, and disorder protected nanophases. We quantitatively analyze the size, composition, and morphology of the nanostructures, as well as directly simulate the atom-probe-tomography (APT) needle. The results align well with available experimental observations. This work underscores the promising potential of leveraging large-scale MC simulation to explore the largely uncharted territory of nanostructure evolution in HEAs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12591v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xianglin Liu, Kai Yang, Yongxiang Liu, Fanli Zhou, Dengdong Fan, Zongrui Pei, Pengxiang Xu, Yonghong Tian</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anatomy of torques from orbital Rashba textures: the case of Co/Al interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.16319</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.16319v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the context of orbitronics, the rising of the orbital angular momentum generated at light metal interfaces from orbital textures via orbital Rashba-Edelstein effects nowadays represent extraordinary alternatives to the usual heavy-metal spin-based materials. In the light of very recent experimental results [\textcolor{blue}{S. Krishnia \textit{et al.}, Nanoletters 2023, 23, 6785}], starting from state-of-the-art density functional theory simulations, we provide theoretical insights into the emergence of very strong orbital torques at the Co/Al interface location a strong orbital Rashba texture. By using linear response theory, we calculate the exerted orbital torque amplitudes, mainly of field-like intraband character, acting onto the ultrathin Co. Moreover, we show that an insertion of a single atomic plane of Pt between Co and Al is enough to suppress the effect which questions about the anatomy of the torque action clearly behaving differently than in the standard way. This work opens new routes to the engineering of spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.16319v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Pezo, N. Sebe, A. Manchon, V. Cros, H. Jaffr\`es</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Review of the Electrochemical Double Layer Theory and Its Applications in Battery Electrode Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.18202</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.18202v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The interface plays a critical role in electrochemical systems, driving the development of various theories to investigate properties at nanoscale and microscale levels, including the electrictrochemical double layer (EDL) theory and continuum theory. However, the application of EDL theory within the realm of battery electrode materials has not been clearly defined according to material type. The diverse range of materials and their intricate interactions with interface theories often lead to misunderstandings. This review meticulously outlines the origins and principles of the EDL theory. Additionally, it categorizes battery electrode materials into two main groups: semiconductors and conductors. A comprehensive examination is presented on the implementation of EDL and other interface theories, accompanied by a comparative evaluation of the fundamental models and experiments described. The review also explores the potential advancements of EDL and other interface theories, as well as their application in electrode materials. This exhaustive review serves as an invaluable resource for scholars in electrochemistry and materials science, aiding in their understanding of interface theories, their scope of applicability, and the integration of these theories with practical experimental approaches.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.18202v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yitao He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electric conductivity in graphene: Kubo model versus a nonlocal quantum field theory model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.02279</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.02279v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We compare three models of graphene electric conductivity: a non-local Kubo model, a local model derived by Falkovsky, and finally, a non-local quantum field theory (QFT) polarization-based model. These models are supposed to provide consistent results since they are derived from the same Hamiltonian. While we confirm that the local model is a proper $\textbf{q}\to\textbf{0}$ limit of both the non-local Kubo and the non-local QFT model (once losses are added to this last model), we find hard inconsistencies in the non-local QFT model as derived and currently used in literature. In particular, in the genuine non-local region ($\textbf{q}\neq\textbf{0}$), the available QFT model shows an intrinsic non-physical plasma-like behavior for the interband transversal electric conductivity at low frequencies (even after introducing the unavoidable losses). The Kubo model, instead, shows the expected behavior, i.e., an almost constant electric conductivity as a function of frequency $\omega$ with a gap for frequencies $\hbar\omega&lt;\sqrt{(\hbar v_F q)^{2}+4m^{2}}$. We show that the Kubo and QFT models can be expressed using an identical Polarization operator $\Pi_{\mu\nu}(\omega,\textbf{q})$, but they employ different expressions for the electric conductivity $\sigma_{\mu\nu}(\omega,\textbf{q})$. In particular, the Kubo model uses a standard regularized expression, a direct consequence of Ohm's Law and causality, as we rigorously re-derive. We show that, once the standard regularized expression for $\sigma_{\mu\nu}(\omega,\textbf{q})$ is used in the QFT model, and losses are included, the Kubo and QFT model coincide, and all its anomalies naturally disappear. Our findings show the necessity to appropriately define and regularize the electric conductivity to connect it with the available QFT model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.02279v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.115428</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 111, 115428 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Pablo Rodriguez-Lopez, Jian-Sheng Wang, Mauro Antezza</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pressure effects on the electronic structure and magnetic properties of infinite-layer nickelates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.07176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.07176v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by the discovery of superconductivity in infinite-layer nickelates RNiO$_2$ (R= rare-earth), and the subsequent enhancement of their T$_c$ with pressure, we investigate the evolution of the electronic structure and magnetic properties of this family of materials via first-principles calculations employing hydrostatic and chemical pressure as tuning knobs. Overall, our analysis shows that pressure tends to increase the R-$5d$ self-doping effect, as well as the Ni-$d _{x^{2}-y^{2}}$ bandwidth, the $e_g$ energy splitting, the charge transfer energy, and the superexchange ($J$). Using the energy scale of $J$ as a predictor of superconducting tendencies, we anticipate that pressure can indeed be a feasible means to further increase the T$_c$ in this family of materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.07176v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.110.155156</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Shekhar Sharma, Myung-Chul Jung, Harrison LaBollita, Antia S. Botana</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven Azimuthal RHEED construction for in-situ crystal growth characterization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.15339</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.15339v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Reflection High-Energy Electron Diffraction (RHEED) is a powerful tool to probe the surface reconstruction during MBE growth. However, raw RHEED patterns are difficult to interpret, especially when the wafer is rotating. A more accessible representation of the information is therefore the so-called Azimuthal RHEED (ARHEED), an angularly resolved plot of the electron diffraction pattern during a full wafer rotation. However, ARHEED requires precise information about the rotation angle as well as of the position of the specular spot of the electron beam. We present a Deep Learning technique to automatically construct the Azimuthal RHEED from bare RHEED images, requiring no further measurement equipment. We use two artificial neural networks: an image segmentation model to track the center of the specular spot and a regression model to determine the orientation of the crystal with respect to the incident electron beam of the RHEED system. Our technique enables accurate and real-time ARHEED construction on any growth chamber equipped with a RHEED system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.15339v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Abdourahman Khaireh-Walieh, Alexandre Arnoult, S\'ebastien Plissard, Peter R. Wiecha</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
