<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 04:01:02 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Decoding optoelectronic behavior in X$_3$BI$_3$ antiperovskite derivatives through many-body perturbation theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19029</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19029v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Antiperovskite derivatives have emerged as promising candidates for optoelectronic applications. However, due to the significant computational cost, their excitonic and polaronic properties remain underexplored despite being critical for optoelectronic performance. Here, we present the structural, electronic, optical, excitonic, and polaronic properties of a series of antiperovskite derivatives with the chemical formula X$_{3}$BI$_{3}$ (X = Ca, Sr; B = P, As, Sb, Bi) using state-of-the-art first-principles calculations. All the compounds exhibit direct bandgaps with G$_{0}$W$_{0}$@PBE bandgap ranging from 2.42 to 3.02 eV, optimal for efficient light absorption with minimal energy loss. Exciton binding energies (0.258-0.318 eV) indicate moderate Coulomb attraction, favoring exciton dissociation. Employing the Feynman polaron model, we established the polaronic properties, where weak to intermediate carrier-phonon coupling was observed, with polaron mobilities reaching values up to 37.19 cm$^{2}$V$^{-1}$s$^{-1}$. These properties establish X$_{3}$BI$_{3}$ materials as viable candidates for next-generation optoelectronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19029v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ayan Chakravorty, Surajit Adhikari, Priya Johari</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>First-principles calculation of electronic and topological properties of low-dimensional tellurium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19079</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19079v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We employ first-principles density-functional theory to investigate the structural, thermodynamic, electronic, and topological properties of tellurium in its various dimensional forms: bulk trigonal tellurium (Te-I), two-dimensional (2D) monolayers $\alpha$-Te, $\beta$-Te and one-dimensional helical nanowire (Te-h). A softening of the acoustic phonon modes is seen in most of the 2D phases, suggesting a tendency to structural distortions or phase transitions under small perturbations. The trigonal 3D Te-I structure is characterized as a narrow-gap semiconductor hosting Weyl nodes at high-symmetry locations in the Brillouin zone, which is supported by the characteristic spin texture seen in momentum space, where spins align radially, forming Berry monopoles. This topological feature, along with the observation of Weyl phonons is attributed to inversion symmetry breaking and strong SOC. Ultrathin Te-h nanowires also exhibit signatures of Weyl nodes and presents a considerable energy gap under SOC. On the other hand, the two-dimensional monolayers $\alpha$-Te, $\beta$-Te, are classified as topologically trivial, as indicated by their topological invariants, which arises from the preservation of both spatial inversion and time-reversal symmetries in these systems. The potential for inducing topological phase transitions via external perturbations suggest that these monolayers are promising candidates for engineered Weyl phases or other topological states. We demonstrate that tellurium and its low-dimensional derivatives are versatile materials that exhibit a broad range of electronic and phononic phenomena intrinsically linked to chirality and symmetry breaking. The tunability of their electronic and topological properties places tellurium as a promising material platform for the exploration and application of Weyl physics in next-generation electronic and optoelectronic technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19079v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gabriel Elyas Gama Araujo, Andreia Luisa da Rosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Transient Absorption Spectroscopy of NbOI$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19188v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: NbOI$_2$ has recently emerged as a new van der Waals material combining semiconducting behavior with intrinsic in plane ferroelectricity and pronounced transport and optical anisotropy. However, its photocarrier dynamics remain largely unexplored. Here we report transient absorption spectroscopy of NbOI$_2$ using femtosecond pump probe reflectance measurements. A pronounced transient absorption feature is observed near the 2.34 eV excitonic resonance, arising from photocarrier induced excitonic energy shifts and saturation. The decay dynamics reveal an exciton lifetime of several tens of picoseconds and show density-dependent behavior consistent with exciton exciton annihilation, yielding an annihilation coefficient of 0.09 cm$^2$ s$^{-1}$, which is comparable to that in monolayer transition metal dichalcogenides. Polarization resolved measurements further reveal a pronounced in-plane anisotropy in the transient response that follows the linear absorption anisotropy. These findings provide fundamental insight into photocarrier dynamics in NbOI$_2$ and establish key parameters for understanding and exploiting its optoelectronic behavior.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19188v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Salman Ahsanullah, Neema Rafizadeh, Hui Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Efficiency Nonrelativistic Charge-Spin Conversion in X-Type Antiferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets have attracted considerable interest for their capacity to generate spin splitting while preserving zero net magnetization. This work proposes a distinct class of antiferromagnetic materials, termed X-type antiferromagnets, which are shown to produce more efficient $\cal T$-odd spin currents than altermagnets along specific crystallographic directions due to their unique Fermi surface geometry. The spin current polarization is controlled by the N\'eel vector orientation. In the (110)-oriented $\beta-\mathrm{Fe}_2\mathrm{PO}_5$, the Fermi surface exhibits a $d$-wave altermagnetic-like characteristic and becomes compressed into an approximately X-shaped $d$-wave configuration, yielding highly efficient $\cal T$-odd spin currents with a charge-to-spin conversion efficiency reaching 90%. Moreover, when the N\'eel vector is tilted via unit cell selection or external means, the system generates out-of-plane spin-polarized currents with efficiencies substantially exceeding those of known ferromagnets, altermagnets, noncollinear antiferromagnets, and low-symmetry materials. The highly efficient charge-spin conversion in X-type antiferromagnets provides a novel and highly effective spin source system for the development of low-power spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19194v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiabin Wang, Wancheng Zhang, Yong Liu, Rui Xiong, Zhenhua Zhang, Zhihong Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesizability Prediction of Crystalline Structures with a Hierarchical Transformer and Uncertainty Quantification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19251</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19251v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Predicting which hypothetical inorganic crystals can be experimentally realized remains a central challenge in accelerating materials discovery. SyntheFormer is a positive-unlabeled framework that learns synthesizability directly from crystal structure, combining a Fourier-transformed crystal periodicity (FTCP) representation with hierarchical feature extraction, Random-Forest feature selection, and a compact deep MLP classifier. The model is trained on historical data from 2011 through 2018 and evaluated prospectively on future years from 2019 to 2025, where the positive class constitutes only 1.02 per cent of samples. Under this temporally separated evaluation, SyntheFormer achieves a test area under the ROC curve of 0.735 and, with dual-threshold calibration, attains high-recall screening with 97.6 per cent recall at 94.2 per cent coverage, which minimizes missed opportunities while preserving discriminative power. Crucially, the model recovers experimentally confirmed metastable compounds that lie far from the convex hull and simultaneously assigns low scores to many thermodynamically stable yet unsynthesized candidates, demonstrating that stability alone is insufficient to predict experimental attainability. By aligning structure-aware representation with uncertainty-aware decision rules, SyntheFormer provides a practical route to prioritize synthesis targets and focus laboratory effort on the most promising new inorganic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19251v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Danial Ebrahimzadeh, Sarah Sharif, Yaser Mike Banad</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exciton thermal radiation from structure-sorted carbon nanotube membranes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19387</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19387v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Owing to their small binding energies, excitons in bulk semiconductors typically exhibit a sharp optical peak at low temperatures only. This limitation can be overcome by single-walled carbon nanotubes (SWCNTs) and other low-dimensional semiconductors with highly enhanced exciton binding energies. Exciton thermal radiation, which can potentially be exploited for selective thermal emission and energy harvesting, has been recently observed in individual SWCNTs heated under photoirradiation. However, whether macroscale-SWCNT assemblies can emit exciton thermal radiation under conduction heating remains unclear and constitutes an important challenge for practical applications. Herein, we observed peaked exciton thermal radiation from structure-sorted SWCNT membranes. Transmission spectroscopy showed robust exciton resonance at high temperatures, resulting in clear exciton resonance in the thermal radiation band. The absolute emissivity spectra of the membranes were determined at 850 K. Exciton dominance suppresses the contribution of thermal free carriers to the infrared absorption/emission spectra, maintaining the transparency below the optical gap even at elevated temperatures. These phenomena are not observed in bulk semiconductors, highlighting the structure-sorted SWCNT membranes as unique semiconductors leveraging stable exciton resonances at elevated temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19387v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akiteru Takahashi, Kaichi Teranishi, Shonosuke Takaichi, Taishi Nishihara, Yuhei Miyauchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synergistic effects of rare-earth doping on the magnetic properties of orthochromates: A machine learning approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19391</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19391v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Multiferroic materials, particularly rare-earth orthochromates (RECrO$_3$), have garnered significant interest due to their unique magnetic and electric-polar properties, making them promising candidates for multifunctional devices. Although extensive research has been conducted on their antiferromagnetic (AFM) transition temperature (N$\acute{\textrm{e}}$el temperature, $T_\textrm{N}$), ferroelectricity, and piezoelectricity, the effects of doping and substitution of rare-earth (RE) elements on these properties remain insufficiently explored. In this study, convolutional neural networks (CNNs) were employed to predict and analyze the physical properties of RECrO$_3$ compounds under various doping scenarios. Experimental and literature data were integrated to train machine learning models, enabling accurate predictions of $T_\textrm{N}$, besides remanent polarization ($P_\textrm{r}$) and piezoelectric coefficients ($d_{33}$). The results indicate that doping with specific RE elements significantly impacts $T_\textrm{N}$, with optimal doping levels identified for enhanced performance. Furthermore, high-entropy RECrO$_3$ compounds were systematically analyzed, demonstrating how the inclusion of multiple RE elements influences magnetic properties. This work establishes a robust framework for predicting and optimizing the properties of RECrO$_3$ materials, offering valuable insights into their potential applications in energy storage and sensor technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19391v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guanping Xu, Zirui Zhao, Muqing Su, Hai-Feng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin injection and emission helicity switching in a 2D perovskite/WSe2 heterostructure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19447</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19447v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The initialization and control of a long-lived spin population in lead halide perovskites are prerequisites for their use in spintronic applications. Here, we demonstrate circular polarization of the interlayer exciton emission in a (BA)2PbI4/WSe2 monolayer heterostructure. The helicity of this emission is controlled by tuning the energy of the excitation laser through the manifold of exciton resonances of the WSe2 monolayer, together with an emerging interlayer absorption feature of the heterostructure. Theoretical calculations show that this resonance arises from hybridized (BA)2PbI4/WSe2 states in the valence band. This hybrid character enables its observation in both linear absorption and ultrafast pump-probe spectroscopies, and plays a key role in controlling the sign of the helicity of the interlayer exciton emission. The tunable spin polarization demonstrated here, with the WSe2 monolayer effectively acting as a tunable spin filter, represents an important step toward the use of 2D perovskites in opto-spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19447v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakub Jasinski, Francesco Gucci, Thomas Brumme, Swaroop Palai, Armando Genco, Alessandro Baserga, Jonas D. Ziegler, Takashi Taniguchi, Kenji Watanabe, Mateusz Dyksik, Christoph Gadermaier, Michal Baranowski, Duncan K. Maude, Alexey Chernikov, Giulio Cerullo, Agnieszka Kuc, Stefano Dal Conte, Paulina Plochocka, Alessandro Surrente</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active high-entropy photocatalyst designed by incorporating alkali metals to achieve d0+d10+s0 cationic configurations and wide electronegativity mismatch</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19486</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19486v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Photocatalytic hydrogen (H2) production and carbon dioxide (CO2) conversion to methane (CH4) are considered promising solutions for reducing CO2 emissions. However, the development of highly active photocatalysts is essential to efficiently drive these reactions without harming the environment. In this study, we introduce a strategy that incorporates elements with both low and high electronegativities into catalysts based on transition metals, thereby enhancing both reactant adsorption and charge transfer. This strategy is implemented in a high-entropy oxide (HEO) by adding cesium, an alkali metal with very low electronegativity, and gallium, a metal with high electronegativity, to transition metals titanium, niobium and tantalum. The resulting oxide, TiNbTaGaCsO9 with a large concentration of oxygen vacancies, exhibits strong light absorption, a low bandgap and a suitable band structure for both hydrogen evolution and CO2 conversion. Compared to HEOs with only d0 or d0+d10 cationic configurations, the synthesized oxide with a wide electronegativity difference and mixed d0+d10+s0 cationic configurations shows significantly higher activity for both H2 and CH4 production, even without using a cocatalyst. These results demonstrate a design strategy for creating highly active HEOs containing alkali metals by taking advantage of the electronegativity mismatch across the periodic table.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19486v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.actamat.2025.121632</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jacqueline Hidalgo-Jimenez, Taner Akbay, Tatsumi Ishihara, Kaveh Edalati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic nonlinear Hall effect beyond Bloch geometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19515</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19515v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The theory of the intrinsic Hall effect, both linear and nonlinear, is rooted in a geometry which is defined in the Bloch-vector parameter space; the formal expressions are mostly derived from semiclassical concepts. When disorder and interaction are considered there is no Bloch vector to speak of; one needs a more general quantum geometry, defined in a different parameter space. Such higher-level geometrical formulation of the intrinsic Hall effect provides very compact expressions, which have the additional virtue -- in the Bloch special case -- of yielding the known results in a straightforward way: the logic is not concealed by the algebra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19515v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Raffaele Resta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic displacements drive flat band formation and lateral electron and hole separation in near-60 degree twisted MoSe2/WSe2 bilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19596</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19596v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transition metal dichalcogenide (TMD) bilayers with an interlayer twist exhibit a moire super-period, whose effects can manifest in both structural and electronic properties. Atomic displacements can lead to reconstruction into domains of aligned stacking, and flat bands can form that may host correlated electron states. In heterobilayers angular mismatch is nearly unavoidable, so understanding the consequences of an interlayer twist is essential. Using ab initio density functional theory, we find that in near-60 degree twisted MoSe2/WSe2 bilayers valence and conduction band flat bands emerge at ~3 degree twist. Despite relatively limited reconstruction at these angles, atomic displacement creates a polarization gradient that forms a confining potential, localizing and laterally separating electrons and holes within the moire supercell. Excitons formed from flat band electrons and holes should therefore have not only the out-of-plane dipole moment familiar from MoSe2/WSe2 interlayer excitons, but an in-plane dipole moment as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19596v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Madeleine Phillips, C. Stephen Hellberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>DFT-informed Design of Radiation-Resistant Dilute Ternary Cu Alloys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19638</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19638v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This research establishes a systematic, high-throughput computational framework for designing radiation-resistant, dilute ternary copper-based alloys by addition of solutes that bind to vacancies and reduce their mobility, thus promoting interstitial-vacancy recombination. The first challenge in developing alloys by this method is mitigating the vacancy-mediated solute drag effect, since density functional theory (DFT) calculations show that solutes that bind strongly to vacancies are also rapidly dragged to point-defect sinks, and thus removed from the matrix. To overcome this issue, two types of solutes are added to the Cu matrix: A first solute with a strong vacancy binding energy (B-type species) and another solute that binds to 'B' and is a slow diffuser in Cu (C-type species). Using DFT, 21 synergistic solute pairs are screened, with 'B'=Zr, Ge, Sn and 'C'=Fe, Co, Mo, Ni, Nb, W, Cr. Two promising alloys, Cu(Zr,Co) and Cu(Zr,Fe) are then investigated in detail in the dilute regime. Diffusion and solute drag in these alloys are modeled using the kinetic cluster expansion approach (KineCluE) under irradiation conditions. It is shown that strong Zr-'C' thermodynamic binding, especially between Zr and Co, significantly reduces the mobility of Zr solute and suppresses the vacancy-mediated solute drag. Using an analytical framework for the standard five-jump frequency model for diffusion in binary alloys, it is found that vacancy-Zr-Co triplets disrupt the kinetic circuits that promote solute drag in the binary alloy by raising the dissociation barrier for the vacancy from the solute.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19638v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vaibhav Vasudevan (Materials Research Laboratory, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, IL), Thomas Schuler (Universit\'e Paris-Saclay, CEA, Service de recherche en Corrosion et Comportement des Mat\'eriaux, SRMP, Gif-sur-Yvette, France), Pascal Bellon (Materials Research Laboratory, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, IL), Robert Averback (Materials Research Laboratory, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign, Urbana, IL)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dara: Automated multiple-hypothesis phase identification and refinement from powder X-ray diffraction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19667</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19667v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Powder X-ray diffraction (XRD) is a foundational technique for characterizing crystalline materials. However, the reliable interpretation of XRD patterns, particularly in multiphase systems, remains a manual and expertise-demanding task. As a characterization method that only provides structural information, multiple reference phases can often be fit to a single pattern, leading to potential misinterpretation when alternative solutions are overlooked. To ease humans' efforts and address the challenge, we introduce Dara (Data-driven Automated Rietveld Analysis), a framework designed to automate the robust identification and refinement of multiple phases from powder XRD data. Dara performs an exhaustive tree search over all plausible phase combinations within a given chemical space and validates each hypothesis using a robust Rietveld refinement routine (BGMN). Key features include structural database filtering, automatic clustering of isostructural phases during tree expansion, peak-matching-based scoring to identify promising phases for refinement. When ambiguity exists, Dara generates multiple hypothesis which can then be decided between by human experts or with further characteriztion tools. By enhancing the reliability and accuracy of phase identification, Dara enables scalable analysis of realistic complex XRD patterns and provides a foundation for integration into multimodal characterization workflows, moving toward fully self-driving materials discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19667v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.SE</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuxing Fei, Matthew J. McDermott, Christopher L. Rom, Shilong Wang, Gerbrand Ceder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Opto-electronic and kinetic properties of defect states in FA0.7Cs0.3Pb(I0.9Br0.1)3 thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19712</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19712v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Despite the remarkable success in increasing the efficiency and stability of perovskite solar cells over the last decade, the underlying defect landscape of halide perovskites remains unclear. Some charged defects in perovskites migrate in response to an applied electric field, which complicates their characterization with standard techniques. We combine thermal admittance spectroscopy (TAS) with lateral photoconductivity-based methods, such as the thermal steady-state photocurrent (SSPC) and the steady-state photocarrier grating (SSPG), to estimate the kinetic and electrical properties of defects in thin films of vacuum-deposited FA$_{0.7}$Cs$_{0.3}$Pb(I$_{0.9}$Br$_{0.1}$)$_3$ perovskite. The experimental results are consistent with exponential band tails states coming from the lattice disorder, an acceptor-like Gaussian distribution 0.21~eV below the conduction band and approximately equal concentrations of donors and acceptors ($1.7\times10^{17}$ cm$^{-3}$). One of the dopants has room temperature mobility of $(0.5{-}1)\times10^{-7}$ cm$^2$ V$^{-1}$ s$^{-1}$ with a thermal activation energy of 0.28--0.40 eV.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19712v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. Kopprio, J. Caram, S. Le Gall, F. Ventosinos, L. Gil-Escrig, H. J. Bolink, C. Longeaud, J-P. Kleider, J. Schmidt</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accelerating Moment Tensor Potentials through Post-Training Pruning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19737</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19737v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Moment Tensor Potentials (MTPs) are machine-learning interatomic potentials whose basis functions are typically selected using a level-based scheme that is data-agnostic. We introduce a post-training, cost-aware pruning strategy that removes expensive basis functions with minimal loss of accuracy. Applied to nickel and silicon-oxygen systems, it yields models up to seven times faster than standard MTPs. The method requires no new data and remains fully compatible with current MTP implementations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19737v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zijian Meng, Karim Zongo, Matthew Thoms, Ryan Eric Grant, Laurent Karim B\'eland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hexa-Graphyne: A Transparent and Semimetallic 2D Carbon Allotrope with Distinct Optical Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Herein, we conduct a comprehensive investigation of Hexa-graphyne (HXGY), a planar carbon allotrope formed by distorted hexagonal and rectangular rings incorporating sp and sp$^2$-hybridized carbon atoms. First-principles calculations confirm its energetic, dynamical and thermal stability (up to at least 1000 K). Regarding its band structure, this material exhibits a semimetallic nature. It exhibits high mechanical compliance, with a Young's modulus approximately 13 times lower and a Poisson's ratio nearly 4 times higher than those of graphene. The optical response is marked by strong ultraviolet absorption, high infrared reflectivity, and pronounced transparency in the visible-light range. Raman and infrared spectra exhibit sharp and well-separated peaks, providing a clear signature of acetylenic linkage stretching vibrations. Nanoribbon structures derived from HXGY show distinct electronic behaviors depending on the edge termination type and width. These findings highlight the HXGY potential for nanoelectronic and optoelectronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19795v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jhionathan de Lima, Cristiano Francisco Woellner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Foundation Models for Discovery and Exploration in Chemical Space</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18900</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18900v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate prediction of atomistic, thermodynamic, and kinetic properties from molecular structures underpins materials innovation. Existing computational and experimental approaches lack the scalability required to efficiently navigate chemical space. Scientific foundation models trained on large unlabeled datasets offer a path toward exploring chemical space across diverse application domains. Here we develop MIST, a family of molecular foundation models with up to an order of magnitude more parameters and data than prior works. Trained using a novel tokenization scheme that comprehensively captures nuclear, electronic, and geometric information, MIST learns from a diverse range of molecules. MIST models have been fine-tuned to predict more than 400 structure -- property relationships and match or exceed state-of-the-art performance across benchmarks spanning physiology, electrochemistry, and quantum chemistry. We demonstrate the ability of these models to solve real-world problems across chemical space, including multiobjective electrolyte solvent screening, olfactory perception mapping, isotope half-life prediction, stereochemical reasoning for chiral organometallic compounds, and binary and multi-component mixture property prediction. Probing MIST models using mechanistic interpretability methods reveals identifiable patterns and trends not explicitly present in the training data, suggesting that the models learn generalizable scientific concepts. We formulate hyperparameter-penalized Bayesian neural scaling laws and use them to reduce the computational cost of model development by an order of magnitude. The methods and findings presented here represent a significant step toward accelerating materials discovery, design, and optimization using foundation models and provide valuable guidance for training compute-optimal scientific foundation models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18900v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Alexius Wadell, Anoushka Bhutani, Victor Azumah, Austin R. Ellis-Mohr, Celia Kelly, Hancheng Zhao, Anuj K. Nayak, Kareem Hegazy, Alexander Brace, Hongyi Lin, Murali Emani, Venkatram Vishwanath, Kevin Gering, Melisa Alkan, Tom Gibbs, Jack Wells, Lav R. Varshney, Bharath Ramsundar, Karthik Duraisamy, Michael W. Mahoney, Arvind Ramanathan, Venkatasubramanian Viswanathan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Haerter-Shastry kinetic magnetism and metallicity in the triangular Hubbard model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18954v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The fermionic Hubbard model, when combined with the ingredient of frustration, associated with the breaking of particle-hole symmetry, harbors a rich phase diagram. Aspects of theoretical findings associated with the nature of magnetism and metallicity, in a diverse set of parameter regimes, are now being actively investigated in triangular Hubbard cold atom and solid-state (moir\'e) based emulators. Building on the theoretical work of Haerter and Shastry [Phys. Rev. Lett. 95,087202 (2005)], we explore the impact of kinetically frustrated magnetism, a phenomenon where antiferromagnetic order emerges without any underlying magnetic interactions, at finite hole density. We numerically study the infinite-$U$ triangular Hubbard model using the density matrix renormalization group algorithm and estimate the extent of stability of the kinetically induced $120^{\circ}$ antiferromagnetic state to hole doping. Beyond the Haerter-Shastry regime, we find an intermediate phase with multimer (involving multiple correlated spins) stripes that eventually gives way to a paramagnet. We also find evidence of gapless charge excitations (metallicity) throughout the phase diagram for finite hole density. We discuss the implications at large, but finite and realistic values of $U/t$, and investigate whether kinetic magnetism and superexchange collaborate or compete.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18954v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sogoud Sherif, Prakash Sharma, Aman Kumar, Hitesh J. Changlani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ferro-spinetic Altermagnets from Electronic Correlations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.18973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.18973v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Altermagnets are fully compensated collinear antiferromagnets that lack the combined time-reversal and translation symmetry. Here we show that their symmetry allows for a switchable ferro-spinetic polarization - the spin analogue of ferroelectricity - in a direction dictated by the lattice symmetry. We demonstrate this effect first in its purest form in an interacting altermagnetic fermion model, in which a many-body chiral symmetry forbids any charge polarization. Our quantum Monte Carlo simulations reveal edge-localized, reversible spin accumulations fully consistent with this symmetry locking. Breaking the chiral symmetry releases the charge sector: a ferroelectric polarization emerges orthogonal to the ferro-spinetic one, yielding mutually perpendicular switchable spin- and charge-polarized responses. We identify Mn-based metal-organic frameworks as realistic hosts for this effect, offering a practical route for experimental verification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.18973v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Toshihiro Sato, Mengli Hu, Ion Cosma Fulga, Oleg Janson, Jorge I. Facio, Alessandro Stroppa, Fakher F. Assaad, Jeroen van den Brink</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine-learned domain partitioning for computationally efficient coupling of continuum and particle simulations of membrane fabrication</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19051</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19051v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: All simulation approaches eventually face limits in computational scalability when applied to large spatiotemporal domains. This challenge becomes especially apparent in molecular-level particle simulations, where high spatial and temporal resolution leads to rapidly increasing computational demands. To overcome these limitations, hybrid methods that combine simulations with different levels of resolution offer a promising solution. In this context, we present a machine learning-based decision model that dynamically selects between simulation methods at runtime. The model is built around a Multilayer perceptron (MLP) that predicts the expected discrepancy between particle and continuum simulation results, enabling the localized use of high-fidelity particle simulations only where they are expected to add value. This concurrent approach is applied to the simulation of membrane fabrication processes, where a particle simulation is coupled with a continuum model. This article describes the architecture of the decision model and its integration into the simulation workflow, enabling efficient, scalable, and adaptive multiscale simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19051v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthias Busch, Gregor H\"afner, Jiayu Xie, Marius Tacke, Marcus M\"uller, Christian J. Cyron, Roland C. Aydin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>iDART: Interferometric Dual-AC Resonance Tracking nano-electromechanical mapping</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19063</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19063v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Piezoresponse force microscopy (PFM) has established itself as a very successful and reliable imaging and spectroscopic tool for measuring a wide variety of nanoscale electromechanical functionalities. Quantitative imaging of nanoscale electromechanical phenomena requires high sensitivity while avoiding artifacts induced by large drive biases. Conventional PFM often relies on high voltages to overcome optical detection noise, leading to various non-ideal effects including electrostatic crosstalk, Joule heating, and tip-induced switching. To mitigate this situation, we introduce interferometrically detected, resonance-enhanced dual AC resonance tracking (iDART), which combines femtometer-scale displacement sensitivity of quadrature phase differential interferometry with contact resonance amplification. Through this combination, iDART achieves 10x or greater signal-to-noise improvement over current state of the art PFM approaches including both single frequency interferometric PFM or conventional, resonance enhanced PFM using optical beam detection. In this work, we demonstrate a &gt;10x improvement of imaging sensitivity on PZT and Y-HfO. Switching spectroscopy shows similar improvements, where further demonstrates reliable hysteresis loops at small biases, mitigating nonlinearities and device failures that can occur at higher excitation amplitudes. These results position iDART as a powerful approach for probing conventional ferroelectrics with extremely high signal to noise down to weak piezoelectric systems, extending functional imaging capabilities to thin films, 2D ferroelectrics, beyond-CMOS technologies and bio-materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19063v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Bemis, F. Wunderwald, U. Schroeder, X. Xu, A. Gruverman, R. Proksch</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab Initio Free Energy Surfaces for Coupled Ion-Electron Transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19106v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The Marcus theory of electron transfer assumes that diabatic energy gaps are sampled from a single ensemble. This assumption can break down in spatially anisotropic environments, such as electrochemical interfaces or biomolecular structures, where distinct solvent ensembles arise along a collective variable describing the anisotropy. Treating this collective variable as an additional reaction coordinate linearly independent from the Marcus reaction coordinate, we develop a formalism that enables calculation of the resulting Coupled Ion-Electron Transfer (CIET) free-energy surface directly from constrained ab initio trajectories. Applied to CO2 redox on a gold electrode, this method reveals strong coupling to the anisotropy, predicting significantly different activation barriers compared to either coordinate alone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19106v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ethan Abraham, Martin Z. Bazant, Troy Van Voorhis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantitative measurement of magnetic dichroic signals at sub-nanometer to atomic scale resolution conditions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19115</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19115v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: When aiming for atomic resolution electron magnetic circular dichroism (EMCD) in STEM mode, the high convergence angle of the electron probe can lead to unforeseen artefacts and strong reductions of the signal to noise ratio (SNR) in the measurement of magnetic magnitudes. In this work, the EMCD signal is measured in STEM mode at semi-convergence angles ranging from \alpha=\ 2-10\ mrad\ using iron samples with high structural perfection. We observe that the relative EMCD signal remains very similar for all convergence angles, which is in good agreement with simulations. The improvement in the signal-to-noise ratio as compared to earlier works is due to better crystalline quality of the Fe sample, high control of the sample orientation, better control over sample thickness, and factors such as higher beam current and the use of a fast and sensitive hybrid-pixel electron detector. One of the key factors to remove experimental ambivalences is the use of an acquisition geometry where the two conjugate EMCD spectra are acquired simultaneously. Furthermore the high crystalline quality Fe sample enables the acquisition of statistical entities of spectra at the same sample orientation, which in turn results in high SNR EMCD signals. We obtain high SNR EMCD signals for all semi convergence angles and could measure the orbital to spin magnetic moment ratio ml/ms with high precision. We observed that at high convergence angles, the ml/ms ratio gets sensitive to minute changes in sample orientation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19115v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sharath Kumar Manjeshwar Sathyanath, Anna L. Ravensburg, Vassilios Kapaklis, Jan Rusz, Bj\"orgvin Hj\"orvarsson, Klaus Leifer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Many-Body Perturbation Theory for Driven Dissipative Quasiparticle Flows and Fluctuations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19124</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19124v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a unified many-body perturbation theory for open quantum systems, that treats dissipation, correlations, and external driving on equal footing. Using a Keldysh-Lindblad formalism, we introduce diagrammatic treatment of dissipative interaction lines representing quasiparticle flows and fluctuations. Two new Feynman rules render the evaluation of dissipative diagrams compact and systematically improvable, while preserving the Keldysh and anti-Hermitian symmetries of the closed-system theory. Consequently, the structure of the Kadanoff-Baym equations (KBE) remains unchanged, enabling existing numerical methods to be directly applied. To illustrate this, we derive dissipative versions of the second Born and GW approximations, identifying the physical content of the self-energy components. Moreover, we demonstrate that time-linear approximations to the full KBE retain their closed structure and can be efficiently used to simulate relaxation and decoherence dynamics. This framework establishes a general route toward first-principles modeling of correlated, driven, and dissipative quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19124v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Thomas Blommel, Enrico Perfetto, Gianluca Stefanucci, Vojtech Vlcek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Control of out-of-plane anti-damping spin torque with a canted ferromagnetic spin source</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19142v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: To achieve efficient anti-damping switching of nanoscale magnetic memories with perpendicular magnetic anisotropy using spin-orbit torque requires that the anti-damping spin-orbit torque have a strong out-of-plane component. The spin anomalous Hall effect and the planar Hall effect spin current produced by a ferromagnetic layer are candidate mechanisms for producing such an out-of-plane anti-damping torque, but both require that the magnetic moment of the spin source layer be canted partly out of the sample plane at zero applied magnetic field. Here we demonstrate such a canted configuration for a ferromagnetic SrRuO3 layer and we characterize all vector components of the torque that it produces, including non-zero out-of-plane anti-damping torques. We verify that the out-of-plane spin component can be tuned by the orientation of magnetic moment, with significant contributions from both the spin anomalous Hall effect and the planar Hall effect spin current.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19142v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoxi Huang, Daniel A. Pharis, Hang Zhou, Zishen Tian, Thow Min Jerald Cham, Kyoungjun Lee, Yilin Evan Li, Chaoyang Wang, Yuhan Liang, Maciej Olszewski, Di Yi, Chang-Beom Eom, Darrell G. Schlom, Lane W. Martin, Ding-Fu Shao, Daniel C. Ralph</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Identifying the Catalytic Descriptor of Single-Atom Catalysts in Nitrate Reduction Reaction: An Interpretable Machine-Learning Method</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19343</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19343v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Elucidating the catalytic descriptor that accurately characterizes the structure-activity relationships of typical catalysts for various important heterogeneous catalytic reactions is pivotal for designing high-efficient catalytic systems. Here, an interpretable machine learning technique was employed to identify the key determinants governing the nitrate reduction reaction ($\rm NO_3RR$) performance across 286 single-atom catalysts (SACs) with the active sites anchored on double-vacancy $\rm BC_3$ monolayers. Through Shapley Additive Explanations (SHAP) analysis with reliable predictive accuracy, we quantitatively demonstrated that, favorable $\rm NO_3RR$ activity stems from a delicate balance among three critical factors: low $\rm N_V$, moderate $\rm D_N$, and specific doping patterns. Building upon these insights, we established a descriptor ($\psi$) that integrates the intrinsic catalytic properties and the intermediate O-N-H angle ($\theta$), effectively capturing the underlying structure-activity relationship. Guided by this, we further identified 16 promising catalysts with predicted low limiting potential ($U_{\rm L}$). Importantly, these catalysts are composed of cost-effective non-precious metal elements and are predicted to surpass most reported catalysts, with the best-performing Ti-V-1N1 is predicted to have an ultra-low $U_{\rm L}$ of $-0.10$ V.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19343v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhen Zhu, Shan Gao, Jing Zhang, Xuxin Kang, Shunfang Li, Xiangmei Duan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High Uniformity GaN Micro-pyramids and Platelets by Selective Area Growth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19697v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The development of uniform GaN micro-pyramids and platelets via selective area growth is a critical step toward advancing III-nitride device technologies, particularly for micro-light-emitting diode applications. This work investigates the origins of morphological non-uniformity in micro-pyramids and micro-platelets grown by metal-organic chemical vapor deposition (MOCVD). We observe that a direct one-step growth approach leads to significant growth rate inhomogeneity across arrays. To shed light on this issue, we examine the mechanisms driving non-uniformity and explore process modifications aimed at mitigating these effects. Building on these insights, we propose a controlled multi-step growth strategy that combines sequen-tial growth and thermal treatment phases. This approach is demonstrated to enhance surface morphology and structural regularity. The work contributes to the broader objective of enabling scalable, high-precision GaN microstructure fabrication for next-generation optoelectronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19697v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Changhao Li, Vitaly Z. Zubialevich, Peter J. Parbrook, Brian Corbett, Zhi Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-Locked Helical Currents and Pure Spin Pumping in Altermagnetic Nanotubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19700</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19700v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We show that rolling a two-dimensional altermagnet into a nanotube turns it into a spin-programmable chiral nanosolenoid with two reciprocal, SOC-free functionalities. (i) Direct: injecting a single-spin-polarized current produces a steady helical current whose handedness is locked to the spin orientation, yielding opposite axial magnetic fields for opposite spins. (ii) Inverse: a time-varying axial flux Phi(t) induces a circumferential Faraday field E_theta = -(dPhi/dt)/(2 pi R) that drives equal-magnitude, opposite-sign axial charge currents in the two spin channels, Iz^up = - Iz^down, thereby pumping a pure spin current Is = (hbar/2e)(Iz^up - Iz^down) with zero net charge flow. Both effects arise from the interplay between momentum-odd spin polarization inherent to altermagnets and the screw symmetry of the rolled geometry, and persist in the complete absence of spin-orbit coupling. Using V2Se2O as a prototype, first-principles calculations reveal spin-dependent chiral wave functions near both the conduction- and valence-band edges. These results establish a nonrelativistic route toward compact spin-controlled flux generators and charge-neutral spin injectors in light-element materials without static magnetic bias.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19700v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xin Chen, Linyang Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Atomic Scale Polarisation Vortices in BaTiS3</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.09530</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.09530v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Topological defects, such as vortices and skyrmions in magnetic and dipolar systems, can give rise to properties that are not observed in typical magnets and dielectrics. Here, we report the discovery of long-range ordered periodic dipole arrays of atomic-scale vortices and antivortices in the unconventional charge-density-wave (CDW) phase of BaTiS3, a quasi-1D chalcogenide. Synchrotron X-ray diffraction (XRD) reveals the presence of a multi-q ordering in BaTiS3 that confines vortex-vortex-antivortex polarisation triplets to the a-b plane with alternating handedness along the c-axis. The multi-q displacive distortions are characterised by three distinctive off-centre TiS6 configurations, whose ratios are independently confirmed by 47/49Ti solid-state nuclear magnetic resonance (SSNMR). Using first-principles calculations and phenomenological modelling, we show that the dipolar vortex unit cell in BaTiS3 arises from the coupling between multiple lattice instabilities arising from flat, soft phonon bands. This mechanism contrasts with classical dipolar textures in ferroelectric heterostructures that emerge from the competition between electrostatic and strain energies. The observation of dipolar vortices in BaTiS3 brings the ultimate scaling limit for real-space dipolar topological structures down to about a nanometre and unveils the intimate connection between crystal symmetry and real-space topology. Our work sets up zero-filling semiconducting materials with competing structural instabilities as a playground for realising and understanding quantum polarisation topologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.09530v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boyang Zhao, Gwan Yeong Jung, Shantanu Singh, Robert B. Smith, Huandong Chen, Guodong Ren, Chuangtang Wang, Sara Termos, Sean T. Holmes, Frederic Mentink-Vigier, Weizhe Zhang, Zhengyu Du, Claire Wu, M. J. Swamynadhan, Qinai Zhao, Kevin Ye, Donald A. Walko, Nicholas S. Settineri, Simon J. Teat, Liuyan Zhao, Robert W. Schurko, Haidan Wen, Rohan Mishra, Jayakanth Ravichandran</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct imaging and control of Berry curvature in noncollinear antiferromagnetic single-crystal thin films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.02990</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.02990v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The discovery of the intrinsic anomalous Hall effect (AHE) in noncollinear antiferromagnets where transverse Hall voltage emerges without magnetic field, has opened a plethora of promising opportunities in antiferromagnetic devices. The key challenges limiting their full potential are (1) high-quality epitaxial thin-film growth and (2) the understanding of Berry curvature domain physics. Here, we focus on a noncollinear antiperovskite antiferromagnet Mn3NiN as a model system, successfully grown as a single-crystal epitaxial thin film. Combining multiple experiments supported by theoretical calculations, we probe the Berry curvature associated with antiferromagnetic {\Gamma}4g domains in Mn3NiN and its strong connection to an AHE. We directly image the intrinsic Berry curvature with high-resolution Sagnac microscopy, controlling spatial distribution and dynamics by varying temperature and applied magnetic fields. We discover that the {\Gamma}4g domains are switchable near the N\'eel transition, but become frozen and unresponsive to external stimuli at low temperature. This behavior enables the tuning of Berry-curvature driven AHE and magneto-optic Kerr effect responses through controlled experimental conditions. Our findings provide critical advancement of the fundamental understanding and wide tunability of Berry curvature in noncollinear antiferromagnets important for realization in potential spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.02990v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuchuan Yao, Pratap Pal, Camron Farhang, Weihang Lu, Mohamed Elekhtiar, Paul Lenharth, Neil G. Campbell, Gautam Gurung, Roger D. Johnson, Pascal Manuel, Mark S. Rzchowski, Evgeny Y. Tsymbal, Jing Xia, Chang-Beom Eom</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microwave power and chamber pressure studies for single-crystalline diamond film growth using microwave plasma CVD</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.01096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.01096v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Single-crystalline diamond (SCD) films possess exceptional thermal, chemical, and optical properties, making them ideal for advanced applications. However, achieving uniform film quality via microwave plasma chemical vapor deposition (MPCVD) remains challenging due to spatial variations in plasma characteristics. This study systematically examines the influence of microwave power and chamber pressure on the growth of SCD films using CH4/H2 gas mixtures. Under optimized conditions (3,900 W, 120 Torr), the films exhibit low surface roughness (~2.0 nm), a sharp sp3 Raman peak at 1,332.2 cm-1, and no detectable C-H related features, indicating high crystalline purity. Cross-sectional TEM analysis confirms a uniform (100)-oriented single-crystal structure across the entire sample. These findings advance the understanding of the interplay between deposition parameters and film quality, and establish a more robust foundation for optimizing MPCVD processes in large-area, high-purity diamond fabrication.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.01096v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.vacuum.2025.114818</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Vacuum 243, 114818 (2026)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Truong Thi Hien, Jaesung Park, Cuong Manh Nguyen, Jeong Hyun Shim, Sangwon Oh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ABACUS: An Electronic Structure Analysis Package for the AI Era</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08697v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: ABACUS (Atomic-orbital Based Ab-initio Computation at USTC) is an open-source software for first-principles electronic structure calculations and molecular dynamics simulations. It mainly features density functional theory (DFT) and molecular dynamics functions and is compatible with both plane-wave basis sets and numerical atomic orbital basis sets. ABACUS serves as a platform that facilitates the integration of various electronic structure methods, such as Kohn-Sham DFT, stochastic DFT, orbital-free DFT, and real-time time-dependent DFT, etc. In addition, with the aid of high-performance computing, ABACUS is designed to perform efficiently and provide massive amounts of first-principles data for generating general-purpose machine learning potentials, such as DPA models. Furthermore, ABACUS serves as an electronic structure platform that interfaces with several AI-assisted algorithms and packages, such as DeePKS-kit, DeePMD, DP-GEN, DeepH, DeePTB, HamGNN, etc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08697v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiqing Zhou, Daye Zheng, Qianrui Liu, Denghui Lu, Yu Liu, Peize Lin, Yike Huang, Xingliang Peng, Jie J. Bao, Chun Cai, Zuxin Jin, Jing Wu, Haochong Zhang, Gan Jin, Yuyang Ji, Zhenxiong Shen, Xiaohui Liu, Liang Sun, Yu Cao, Menglin Sun, Jianchuan Liu, Tao Chen, Renxi Liu, Yuanbo Li, Haozhi Han, Xinyuan Liang, Taoni Bao, Zichao Deng, Tao Liu, Nuo Chen, Hongxu Ren, Xiaoyang Zhang, Zhaoqing Liu, Yiwei Fu, Maochang Liu, Zhuoyuan Li, Tongqi Wen, Zechen Tang, Yong Xu, Wenhui Duan, Xiaoyang Wang, Qiangqiang Gu, Fu-Zhi Dai, Qijing Zheng, Yang Zhong, Hongjun Xiang, Xingao Gong, Jin Zhao, Yuzhi Zhang, Qi Ou, Hong Jiang, Shi Liu, Ben Xu, Shenzhen Xu, Xinguo Ren, Lixin He, Linfeng Zhang, Mohan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acoustic phonon-restricted four-phonon interactions: Impact on thermal and thermoelectric transport in monolayer h-NbN</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.12520</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.12520v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To explore the thermal and thermoelectric potential of 2D materials, we study the h-NbN monolayer, which lacks mirror symmetry and features a large acoustic-optical phonon gap and quadratic flexural mode. First-principles calculations and the Boltzmann transport formalism reveal a complex interplay of multi-phonon scattering processes, where flexural phonons and four-phonon interactions play a significant role in heat transport, primarily dominated by acoustic phonons. Notably, the four-phonon interactions are predominantly confined to acoustic phonons. Tensile strain preserves the underlying scattering mechanisms while reducing anharmonicity, consequently, the scattering rates, enhancing thermal conduction. Simultaneously, competing modifications in thermal and electrical transport shape the strain-dependent thermoelectric response, achieving a figure of merit approaching 1 at elevated temperatures, a testament to its thermoelectric promise. Our findings underscore the critical role of microscopic transport modeling in accurately capturing thermal and thermoelectric properties, paving the way for advanced applications of 2D materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.12520v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1039/D5NR02796A</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nanoscale 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Himanshu Murari, Subhradip Ghosh, Mukul Kabir, Ashis Kundu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High heating rate effects in sintering: A phase-field study of La-doped alumina</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.07353</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.07353v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Sintering is a widespread manufacturing process, accounting for a significant portion of global energy expenditure. However, controlling this process has been mostly a trial-and-error process, being costly in both time and money. The recent advance of high heating rate sintering methods, which promise higher energy efficiency and better properties, only adds to this. This paper aims to reduce these costs by shedding light on the microstructural evolution during high heating rate sintering, which will allow for quicker parameter optimization and improved properties. The focus will be on how a representative microstructure changes locally as well as globally while resolving grains and the green body at scale, which no prior paper has done. A representative multiphysics phase-field solver is employed, incorporating a novel particle-based temperature model, which recovered many characteristics typical of high heating rate sintering. Comparing the simulation data to experimental data showed reasonable agreement over a large density range without parameter adjustment. Furthermore, the advance of a sintering front including grain growth effects could be shown simulatively for the first time in literature. These findings suggest that the model can be used for the design of practical heating schedules for the sintering of novel materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.07353v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.matdes.2025.114889</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Materials &amp; Design Volume 259, November 2025, 114889</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Marco Seiz, Tomohiro Takaki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Observation of relativistic domain wall motion in amorphous ferrimagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.13950</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.13950v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Domain walls in ferrimagnets and antiferromagnets behave as relativistic sine-Gordon solitons with the spin-wave group velocity setting the ultimate velocity of domain walls and speed of magnetic devices. While this relativistic regime has been achieved in crystalline ferrimagnets, they cannot be routinely integrated in devices. To enable technological breakthroughs, relativistic dynamics must be demonstrated in easy-to-integrate ferrimagnets such as rare-earth -- transition-metal alloys. However, this scenario remains elusive due to the inherent magnetic disorder of these materials, complex spin-wave spectra, and challenges in modeling their ultrafast dynamics. Here, we demonstrate relativistic domain wall motion in amorphous ferrimagnetic GdFeCo devices operated in the proximity of the angular momentum compensation point. The current-induced domain wall velocity saturates within 10% of the spin-wave speed of 2 km/s, a behavior consistent with relativistic model of domain wall motion. Our observation of relativistic dynamics in technologically relevant ferrimagnets opens the way to magnetic devices operating at the ultimate speed limit.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.13950v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pietro Diona, Luca Maranzana, Sergey Artyukhin, Giacomo Sala</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A generalized and adaptable tensor-contraction-based cluster expansion formalism for multicomponent solids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04686</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04686v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Density functional theory (DFT)-based simulations of materials have first-principles accuracy, but are very computationally expensive. For simulating various properties of multi-component alloys, the cluster expansion (CE) technique has served as the standard workaround to improve computational efficiency. However, the standard CE technique is difficult to extend to exotic and/or low-symmetry lattices, often implemented via iteration over particular cluster types, which must be enumerated per lattice structure. In this work, we introduce the tensor cluster expansion (TCE), implemented in the open-source code tce-lib, which maps correlation functions to mixed tensor contractions, eliminating the need to iterate over cluster types and additionally making the calculation of correlation functions well-suited for massively parallel architectures like GPUs. We show that local interaction energies are an immediate consequence of the TCE formalism, yielding nearly $\mathcal{O}(1)$ energy difference calculations. We then use this formalism to fit CE models for the TaW and CoNiCrFeMn systems, and use these models to respectively compute the enthalpy of mixing curve and Cowley short-range order parameters, showing excellent agreement with ground truth data.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04686v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jacob Jeffries, Bochuan Sun, Enrique Martinez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Accurate and Efficient Machine-Learned Potential for SiC from Ambient to Extreme Environments</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01827</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01827v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Silicon carbide (SiC) polymorphs are widely employed as nuclear materials, mechanical components, and wide-bandgap semiconductors. The rapid advancement of SiC-based applications has been complemented by computational modeling studies, including both ab initio and classical atomistic approaches. In this work, we develop a computationally efficient and general-purpose machine-learned interatomic potential (ML-IAP) capable of multimillion-atom molecular dynamics simulations over microsecond timescales. Using the ML-IAP, we systematically map the comprehensive pressure-temperature phase diagram and the threshold displacement energy distributions for the 2H and 3C polymorphs. Furthermore, collision cascade simulations provide in-depth insights into polymorph-dependent primary radiation damage clustering, a phenomenon that conventional empirical potentials fail to accurately capture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01827v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jintong Wu, Zhuang Shao, Junlei Zhao, Flyura Djurabekova, Kai Nordlund, Fredric Granberg, Qingmin Zhang, and Jesper Byggm\"astar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Structure and stability of 7:3 rare earth oxide-phosphates: a combined ab initio and experimental study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.16654</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.16654v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Rare earth oxide-phosphates (REOPs) form a largely unexplored family of refractory lanthanides and yttrium compounds with general formula RExOy(PO4)z. They are of interest for applications ranging from thermal barrier coatings to catalysts and magnetic materials. At least four REOPs phases were experimentally identified with RE/P ratios from 7:3 to 6:1, however the structures were solved only for 3:1 phases (RE3O3(PO4)). In this work we report the structure for the 7:3 phases (RE7O6(PO4)3) derived by ab initio analysis of models based on previously reported oxide-vanadate analogues. The most stable structures for all 7:3 REOPs were found to be isotypic, adopting monoclinic symmetry with space group P21/c. The structures were validated by comparison of their powder X-ray diffraction patterns to those of synthesized La, Pr, Nd, Sm, Eu, Gd and Tb 7:3 phases (Rietveld refinement for all except Tb). Ab initio analysis of thermodynamic stability showed that all 7:3 REOPs are unstable at 0 K toward decomposition to REPO4 and RE3PO7 or RE2O3. The entropy contribution stabilizes RE7O6(PO4)3 phases for light rare earth elements above 1000 K, however, starting with Dy, computationally predicted stabilization temperature is higher than estimated melting points of RE7O6(PO4)3, which is consistent with observed synthesis pattern.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.16654v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ligen Wang, Konrad Burkmann, Sergey V. Ushakov, Edric X. Wang, Jared Matteucci, Mara Scheuermann, Erik Melnitschuk, Robert Glaum, Hongwu Xu, Elizabeth J. Opila, Alexandra Navrotsky, Qi-Jun Hong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Achieving Empirical Potential Efficiency with DFT Accuracy: A Neuroevolution Potential for the $\alpha$-Fe--C--H System</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.17151</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.17151v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: A neuroevolution potential (NEP) for the ternary $\alpha$-Fe--C--H system was developed based on a database generated from spin-polarized density functional theory (DFT) calculations, achieving empirical potential efficiency with DFT accuracy. At the same power consumption, simulation speeds using NEP are comparable to, or even faster than, those with bond order potentials. The NEP achieves DFT-level accuracy across a wide range of scenarios commonly encountered in studies of $\alpha$-Fe- and $\alpha$-Fe--C under hydrogen environments. The NEP enables large-scale atomistic simulations with DFT-level accuracy at the cost of empirical potentials, offering a practical tool to study hydrogen embrittlement in steel.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.17151v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fan-Shun Meng, Shuhei Shinzato, Zhiqiang Zhao, Jun-Ping Du, Lei Gao, Zheyong Fan, Shigenobu Ogata</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetizing weak links by time-dependent spin-orbit interactions: momentum conserving and non-conserving processes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.18961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.18961v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Rashba spin-orbit interactions generated by time-dependent electric fields acting on weak links (that couple together non-magnetic macroscopic leads) can magnetize the junction. The Rashba spin-orbit interaction that affects the spins of electrons tunneling through the weak links changes their momentum concomitantly. We establish the connection between the magnetization flux induced by processes that conserve the momentum and the magnetization created by tunneling events that do not. Control of the induced magnetization can be achieved by tuning the polarization of the AC electric field responsible for the spin-orbit Rashba interaction (e.g., from being circular to linear), by changing the applied bias voltage, and by varying the degree of a gate voltage-induced asymmetry of the device.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.18961v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Fizyka Nyzkykh Temperatur/Low Temperature Physics, 51, 1593, (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Debashree Chowdhury, O. Entin-Wohlman, A. Aharony, R. I. Shekhter, M. Jonson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatial correlations of charge density wave order across the transition in 2H-NbSe2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.02991</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.02991v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Charge density waves (CDWs) involve coupled amplitude and phase degrees of freedom, but direct access to local amplitude correlations remains experimentally challenging. Here, we report cryogenic four-dimensional scanning transmission electron microscopy (4D-STEM) measurements of CDW ordering in a 2H-NbSe2 flake of 24 nm thickness, enabled by liquid helium-based cooling. By mapping the spatial distribution of CDW superlattice intensities at nanometer-scale resolution and analyzing their autocorrelations, we extract the temperature-dependent correlation length associated with the local amplitude of the CDW order parameter, independent of global phase coherence. Our results reveal that a finite local CDW amplitude is already established well above the transition temperature. When the system is cooled below the transition temperature down to 20 K, the correlation length extends to nearly 110 nm, and the local CDW amplitude is found to strongly anticorrelate with the local strain field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.02991v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seokjo Hong, Jaewhan Oh, Jemin Park, Woohyun Cho, Soyoung Lee, Colin Ophus, Yeongkwan Kim, Heejun Yang, SungBin Lee, Yongsoo Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Model for the Thermodynamics of Iron at High Pressures Near Melting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.03386</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.03386v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Fe pressure-temperature phase diagram and its melting line have a wide range of applications, including providing constraints for iron-core planetary models. We propose an equation of state (EOS) model based on the interstitial theory of simple condensed matter (ITCM), as suggested by A.V. Granato. When applied to Fe, this model enables the extrapolation of measured melting lines to the conditions of the Earth's inner core boundary (ICB). The ITCM describes the solid-liquid phase transition in metals as resulting from a strong structural perturbation due to a high concentration of interstitial-like defects. The strong nonlinearity of their self-interaction causes the stabilization of this interstitial-rich phase. The original model is expanded to describe melting over a wide range of pressures and temperatures rather than focusing on a specific isobaric transition. Using this model, we fit the measured melting data, extrapolate it to cover ICB conditions, and develop a multiphase equation of state that encompasses this regime. The model is used to explain contradictory data regarding the location of the melting line, resulting from a novel phase transition between two separate liquid phases, specifically between FCC-based and HCP-based liquids. This additional liquid phase offers a new interpretation of the previously suggested near-melting high-pressure phase and may also provide a solution to the inner core nucleation paradox.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.03386v3</guid>
      <category>physics.geo-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rann Shikler, Noya Dimanstein Firman, Yinon Ashkenazy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Asymmetric Effects Underlying Dynamic Heterogeneity in Miscible Blends of Poly(methyl methacrylate) with Poly(ethylene oxide)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12143</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12143v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The emergence of spatially variable local dynamics, or dynamic heterogeneity, is common in multicomponent polymer systems. Although often attributed to differences in the intrinsic dynamics of each component, the molecular origin of their coupling and its dependencies remain unclear. Here, we use molecular dynamics simulations of polyethylene oxide (PEO)/poly(methyl methacrylate) (PMMA) blends, across the full range of compositions and multiple thermal regimes, to characterize local fluctuations and sub-chain relaxations for both PEO and PMMA. By constructing probability distributions of local composition and computing entropic measures, we connect nanoscale heterogeneity to differences in mobility between PEO and PMMA, extending beyond mean-field treatments. While PMMA segmental fluctuations in blends broadly align with $T_\text{g}$-equivalent neat PMMA systems, PEO exhibits enhanced mobility correlated with increased free volume and broader, more diverse local compositions upon blending. Rouse-mode analysis, used to probe relaxation dynamics over different length scales, shows that PEO relaxation approaches neat-like behavior in PEO-rich domains, whereas PMMA relaxation accelerates uniformly across all mode numbers. Given the local mobility enhancement of PMMA by PEO, this uniform shift suggests a nanoscale facilitation process that extends PEO's influence beyond its immediate environment. These findings link the statistics of local compositional heterogeneity to dynamic asymmetry across length scales, provide physical insight into the behavior of this archetypal blend system, and establish a framework for analyzing dynamic coupling in others.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12143v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shannon Zhang, Michael A. Webb</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Photocurrents induced by k-linear terms in semiconductors and semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21450</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21450v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We develop a six-band $\mathbf{k} \cdot \mathbf{p}$ model to describe the electronic structure and optical response of chiral multifold semimetals, such as RhSi. By means of invariants method we construct the effective Hamiltonian describing the states near the $\Gamma$-point of the Brillouin zone where the spin-orbit coupling and $\mathbf{k}$-linear Rashba terms, which are crucial for circular photogalvanic effect, are taken into account. The model is parameterized using tight-binding calculations. We compute the interband absorption spectrum, showing a linear-in-frequency dependence at low energies and a resonant feature near the spin-orbit splitting energy. Furthermore, we calculate the circular photogalvanic effect. In agreement with previous works the current generation rate at low frequencies exhibits a quantized low-frequency response, governed by the universal value $|\mathcal{C}| = 4$ for the effective topological charge. Our results provide an analytical framework for understanding the role of Rashba coupling and topology in the optoelectronic properties of multifold chiral semimetals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21450v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. M. Glazov, E. L. Ivchenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconductivity governed by Janus-faced fermiology in strained bilayer nickelates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.21480</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.21480v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: High-temperature superconductivity in pressurized and strained bilayer nickelates (La,Pr)$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ has emerged as a new frontier. One of the key unresolved issues concerns the fermiology that underlies superconductivity. On both theoretical and experimental sides, no general consensus has been reached, and conflicting results exist regarding whether the relevant Fermi surface involves a $\gamma$ pocket -- a hole pocket with $d_{z^2}$-orbital character centered at the Brillouin zone corner. Here, we address this issue by unveiling a Janus-faced role of the $\gamma$ pocket in spin-fluctuation-mediated superconductivity. We show that this pocket simultaneously induces dominant pair-breaking and pair-forming channels for the leading $s_\pm$-wave pairing. Consequently, an optimal superconducting transition temperature $T_\mathrm{c}$ is achieved when the $\gamma$ pocket surfaces at the Fermi level, placing the system near a Lifshitz transition. This suggests that superconductivity can emerge, provided the maximum energy level of the $\gamma$ pocket lies sufficiently close to the Fermi level, either from below or above. Our finding not only reconciles two opposing viewpoints on the fermiology, but also naturally explains recent experiments on (La,Pr)$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ thin films, including the superconductivity under compressive strain, two conflicting measurements on the Fermi surface, and the dome shape of $T_\mathrm{c}$ as a function of hole doping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.21480v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Siheon Ryee, Niklas Witt, Giorgio Sangiovanni, Tim O. Wehling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of an external static magnetic field on prebreakdown electron emission and heating</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.09113</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.09113v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: High magnetic fields can increase the occurrence of vacuum arcing, suggesting that both electric and magnetic fields can play a role in the vacuum arcing process. The mechanism of vacuum arcing in high magnetic fields is believed to involve both the cathode and the anode, with the cathode serving as the originator of field-emitting nanoprotrusions or tips, while the anode serves a secondary role. Significant heating of the anode surface can be achieved by magnetic focusing of the emitted electron beam, leading to increased heat flux due to greater current density. We simulated the emitted electron beam in different configurations of the electric and magnetic fields using the particle-in-cell (PIC) and finite element methods (FEM). The heating caused by the impacting electron beam was simulated for magnetic fields ranging from 0 T to 30 T. The directions of the electric and magnetic fields were found to play a major role in the focusing of the electron beam. We found that a sufficient temperature increase on the anode surface for evaporation can be reached at magnetic fields on the order of 10-30 T, suggesting the possibility of plasma initiation on the anode side.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.09113v2</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Roni Koitermaa, Marzhan Toktaganova, Andreas Kyritsakis, Tauno Tiirats, Alexej Grudiev, Veronika Zadin, Flyura Djurabekova</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
