<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 01:38:21 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Artificial ferroelectric-like hysteresis in antiferroelectrics with non-uniform disorder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19394</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19394v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Antiferroelectrics exhibit unique double-hysteresis polarization loops, which have garnered significant attention due to their potential applications such as energy storage, electromechanical transduction, as well as synapse devices. However, numerous antiferroelectric materials have been reported to display signs of hysteresis loops resembling those of ferroelectric materials, and a comprehensive understanding remains elusive. In this work, we provide a phenomenological model that reproduces such widely observed artificial ferroelectric hysteresis with a superposition of numerous disordered antiferroelectric loops that have varying antiferroelectric-to-ferroelectric transition fields, particularly when these field ranges intersect. Experimentally, we realized such artificial ferroelectric-like hysteresis loops in the prototypical antiferroelectric PbZrO$_3$ and PbHfO$_3$ thin films, by introducing non-uniform local disorder (e.g., defects) via fine-tuning of the film growth conditions. These ferroelectric-like states are capable of persisting for several hours prior to transitioning back into the thermodynamically stable antiferroelectric ground state. Those results provide insights into the fundamental impact of disorder on the AFE properties and new possibilities of disorder-tailored functions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19394v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.actamat.2025.121085</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Acta Materialia, 294, (2025), 121085</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yi Zhang, Xinyu Zhang, Zihao Zheng, Jiyang Xie, Jing Lou, Jiayi Qin, Shanhu Wang, Yang He, Yifeng Du, Bin Yang, Xin Huang, Huiping Han, Yilin Wu, Shuya Liu, Afzal Kjan, Zhidong Li, Qianxu Ye, Sheng'an Yang, Ji Ma, Hui Zhang, Xiang Liu, Qingming Chen, Wanbiao Hu, Jing Ma, Jianhong Yi, Jinming Guo, Shou Peng, Hao Pan, Liang Wu, Ce-Wen Nan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable Electronic Interactions and Weak Antilocalization in Bulk Ge$_2$Sb$_2$Te$_{5-5x}$Se$_{5x}$ Phase Change Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19510</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19510v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Phase change materials (PCMs) are well-known for their reversible and rapid switching between crystalline and amorphous phases through thermal excitations mediated by strong electrical or laser pulses. This crystal-to-amorphous transition is accompanied by a remarkable contrast in optical and electronic properties, making PCMs useful in nonvolatile data storage applications. Here, we combine electrical transport and angle resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) measurements to study the electronic structure of bulk Ge$_2$Sb$_2$Te$_{5-5x}$Se$_{5x}$ (GSST) for $0\le x \le 0.8$, where $x$ represents the amount of Se substituting Te in Ge$_2$Sb$_2$Te$_5$ (GST)-- a prototypical PCM. The single-particle density of states (SDOS) derived from the integrated ARPES data displays metallic behavior for all $x$, as evidenced by the presence of a finite density of states in the vicinity of the chemical potential. Transport measurements also display clear signatures of metallic transport, consistent with the SDOS data. The temperature dependence of the resistance indicates the onset of moderate electron-electron Coulomb interaction effects at low temperatures for $x\geq 0.6$. At the same time, the magnetoresistance data shows signatures of weak antilocalization for $x\geq 0.6$. An analysis on the temperature dependence of the phase coherence length suggests that electron dephasing is primarily due to inelastic electron-electron scattering. We find that these effects are enhanced with increasing $x$, portraying GSST as a novel PCM where electronic interactions can be tuned via chemical doping.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19510v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicholas Mazzucca, Junjing Zhao, Zhenyang Xu, Despina Louca, Utpal Chatterjee, Marc Bockrath</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytical analysis of the spin wave dispersion in the cycloidal spin structures under the influence of magneto-electric coupling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19543</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19543v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin waves and coupling of the spin waves with electromagnetic waves are considered in the multiferroic materials with the electric dipole moment proportional to the scalar product of spins. Dispersion dependence for the spin waves propagating as the perturbation of the equilibrium state described by spin cycloid is found. The dielectric permeability as the response on the electromagnetic perturbations associated with the magneto-electric coupling for the same equilibrium state is calculated.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19543v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavel A. Andreev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic defect intolerance in the ultra-pure metal PtSn$_4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19807</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19807v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ultra-pure materials are highly valued as model systems for the study of intrinsic physics. Frequently, however, the crystal growth of such pristine samples requires significant optimization. PtSn$_4$ is a rare example of a material that naturally forms with a very low concentration of crystalline defects. Here, we investigate the origin of its low defect levels using a combination of electrical resistivity measurements, computational modeling, and scanning tunneling microscopy imaging. While typical flux-grown crystals of PtSn$_4$ can have residual resistivity ratios (RRRs) that can exceed 1000, we show that even at the most extreme formation speeds, the RRR cannot be suppressed below 100. This aversion to defect formation extends to both the Pt and Sn sublattices, which contribute with equal weight to the conduction properties. Direct local imaging with scanning tunneling microscopy further substantiates the rarity of point defects, while the prohibitive energetic cost of forming a defect is demonstrated through density functional theory calculations. Taken together, our results establish PtSn$_4$ as an intrinsically defect-intolerant material, making it an ideal platform to study other properties of interest, including extreme magnetoresistance and topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19807v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samikshya Sahu, Dong Chen, Niclas Heinsdorf, Ashley N. Warner, Markus Altthaler, Ashutosh K. Singh, Douglas A. Bonn, Sarah A. Burke, Alannah M. Hallas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The orbital-driven topological phase transition and planar Hall responses in ternary tellurides Weyl semi-metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19818</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19818v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Here we study electronic properties of the ternary tellurides TaXTe$_4$ (X=Rh, Ir) using density functional theory and investigate chiral anomaly mediated planar Hall response from ab initio calculations. We show that TaRhTe$_4$ is a hybrid Weyl semimetal (WSM), hosting Weyl points (WPs) of both type-I, type-II, while TaIrTe$_4$ is a type-II WSM as it hosts only type-II WPs with spin-orbit couplings (SOC). All WPs lie in the $k_z=0$ plane, and remain well-separated in both momentum and energy landscape. We observe long Fermi arcs connecting Weyl nodes of opposite chirality. We report both SOC and orbital driven topological phase transition in ternary tellurides. TaIrTe$_4$ undergoes topological phase transition under SOC. Whereas orbital driven topological phase transition due to d$_{xz}$ orbital has been observed in TaRhTe$_4$ even without SOC. Furthermore, the evolution of the band structures and the annihilation of WPs due to d$_{xz}$-Ir/Rh orbitals associated with the phase transitions in TaXTe$_4$ are also discussed. This systematic study opens new routes for engineering topological materials relying beyond strong SOC and sheds light on the possible role of correlation effects originating from orbital orbital degree of freedoms in tellurides. We further report an enhancement of planar Hall effects due to orbital driven topological phase transition in TaXTe$_4$ and we make resort to a tight-binding model to correlate the above findings with the effective mass anisotropy in different types of WSMs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19818v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Banasree Sadhukhan, Tanay Nag</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phase Stability and Superconductivity in Hydrogenated and Lithiated Janus GaXS2 (X = Ga, In) Monolayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19922v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hydrogen and lithium functionalization of two-dimensional (2D) materials offers a promising route to enhance electronic properties and induce superconductivity. Here, we employ first-principles calculations to explore the phase stability and superconducting behavior of hydrogenated and lithiated Janus GaXS2 (X = Ga, In) monolayers. Among Ga2SH, Ga2SLi, GaInSH, and GaInSLi, only the 2H-GaInSLi structure is dynamically, thermally, and mechanically stable, as confirmed by phonon dispersion, ab initio molecular dynamics, and elastic constants. This monolayer adopts a hexagonal lattice, exhibits metallic behavior, and has a negative formation energy, suggesting experimental feasibility. Anisotropic Migdal-Eliashberg analysis reveals phonon-mediated superconductivity with a critical temperature Tc of 4.8 K. Notably, three distinct superconducting gaps emerge, linked to specific atomic orbitals and phonon modes. Electron doping of 0.2 e per cell increases Tc to nearly 6.2 K while maintaining the three-gap character. These results highlight the effectiveness of selective functionalization in engineering superconductivity and identify GaInSLi as a promising platform for next-generation multi-gap 2D superconducting devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19922v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakkapat Seeyangnok, Udomsilp Pinsook</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Type-II Band Alignment in the ${\beta}$-Ga$_2$O$_3$/Rutile GeO$_2$ Heterojunction toward Solar-Blind Photodetection: A first-principles study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19948</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19948v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Semiconductor heterostructures capable of separating photogenerated electrons and holes have a wide range of optoelectronic applications, including photodetectors, solar cells, and photocatalysts. ${\beta}$-Ga$_2$O$_3$ and rutile GeO$_2$ are both ultrawide-bandgap semiconductors, with bandgaps of 4.85 eV and 4.68 eV, respectively. In this work, we employ first-principles calculations based on density functional theory to investigate the band alignment of the ${\beta}$-Ga$_2$O$_3$/rutile GeO$_2$ heterojunction and explore the effect of interfacial oxygen vacancy. Calculations using the PBE0 hybrid functional based on an interface model show that a type-II band alignment emerges at the ${\beta}$-Ga$_2$O$_3$/rutile GeO$_2$ interface, which facilitates the separation of photogenerated carriers. The valence band maximum of ${\beta}$-Ga$_2$O$_3$ lies 0.38 eV below that of rutile GeO$_2$, and its conduction band minimum lies 0.36 eV below. The presence of interfacial oxygen vacancy in the stable configuration leads to a reduction in the band offset. Our results suggest that the ${\beta}$-Ga$_2$O$_3$/rutile GeO$_2$ heterojunction holds significant promise for application in strictly solar-blind photodetectors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19948v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Q. Fang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate prediction of optical transitions in epitaxial InGaAs/InAlAs asymmetric coupled quantum well structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19951v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Atomically-resolved Z-contrast and strain mappings are used to extract a model of the composition of an InGaAs/InAlAs asymmetric coupled quantum-well structure grown on InP using metal-organic vapor phase epitaxy. The model accounts for grading across the multiple alloy interfaces. The model is used to compute intersubband absorption in the structure. The simulation accurately predicts the experimental absorption spectrum of the structure within only a few meV, an almost ten-fold improvement over simulations using a square-band profile with nominal alloy compositions, and a significant step forward in accurate and predictive simulations of the optical properties epitaxial heterostructures for emission, modulation and detection in mid-infrared.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19951v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Konstantinos Pantzas, Virginie Trinit\'e, Angel Vasanelli, Carlo Sirtori, Gr\'egoire Beaudoin, Isabelle Sagnes, Jean-Luc Reverchon, Gilles Patriarche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Efficient Grand Canonical Global Optimization with On-the-fly-trained Machine-learning Interatomic Potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19968</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19968v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The characterization of nanostructued materials under reactive environments is challenging due to the complexity of the structural motifs involved and their chemical transformations. Global optimization approaches allow predicting stable structures for targeted materials but addressing the configurational and compositional search spaces is both computationally demanding and inefficient, especially when first principles calculations are required. In this work, we implement and evaluate a computationally efficient grand canonical global optimization algorithm able to identify stable structures and chemical states of targeted systems under given reaction conditions (e.g. reactant pressure and temperature). The algorithm leverages an on-the-fly trained machine-learning interatomic potential based on sparse Gaussian Process Regression and the smooth overlap of atomic positions descriptor to reduce the number of first principles energy evaluations carried out during global optimization searches. The \textit{ab initio} thermodynamics framework is incorporated to approximate the Gibbs energy of evaluated candidates, performing environment-aware optimizations over multiple stoichiometries. We demonstrate the computational performance of this approach and its ability to reproduce some literature examples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19968v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jon Eunan Quinlivan Dominguez, Mads-Peter Verner Christiansen, Konstantin M. Neyman, B{\o}jrk Hammer, Albert Bruix</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High pressure lattice dynamics study of few layer-$\alpha$-In$_2$Se$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19969v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Few-layer $\alpha$-In$_2$Se$_3$ has been studied under pressure using Raman spectroscopy in a diamond anvil cell up to 60 GPa (at room temperature). A combination of AFM and Raman was used to estimate the thickness of the specimens. While few-layer $\alpha$-In$_2$Se$_3$ shows identical structural evolution with the one of the bulk powder-like form of $\alpha$-In$_2$Se$_3$ ( $\alpha$ $\rightarrow$ $\beta^{'}$ $\rightarrow$ IV ), an abrupt $\beta^{'}$ $\rightarrow$ IV phase transition (at 45 GPa) was observed, in contrast with the case of the bulk specimen where the two phases coexist over a wide pressure range. This is attributed to the difference in specimens morphology, $i.e.$ single crystal and powder in the case of few-layer and bulk $\alpha$-In$_2$Se$_3$, respectively. This study documents the significance of specimens morphology on the observed pressure-induced phase transitions. The methodology developed in this study for performing high-pressure Raman measurements can be applied to other nanodimensional layered materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19969v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shiyu Feng, Anurag Ghosh, Gautham Vijayan, Ziyi Xu, Qian Zhang, Elad Koren, Elissaios Stavrou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Universal Framework for Controlling Non-Relativistic Spin Splitting</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20041</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20041v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Non-relativistic spin splitting in antiferromagnets has recently attracted considerable attention. Here we present a universal framework for controlling such spin splitting by identifying and manipulating the key atomic distortions that govern it through external perturbations. We demonstrate this concept by tuning the spin-splitting energy in three representative materials with diverse symmetries, inversion-symmetric MnF$_2$, ferroelectric BaCuF$_4$, and LaMnO$_3$/RMnO$_3$ superlattices. Our results emphasize the essential role of higher-order magnetic multipoles and the intrinsic structure-spin correlations in these systems, thereby advancing current efforts to control spin splitting in real materials and motivating future experimental studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20041v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aniruddha Ray, Subhadeep Bandyopadhyay, Sayantika Bhowal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced White-Light Emission from Self-Trapped Excitons in Antimony and Bismuth Halides through Structural Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20087</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20087v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lead halide perovskites have catalyzed the rise of main-group metal halide materials as promising candidates for next-generation optoelectronics, including solar cells, light-emitting diodes, lasers, sensors, and photocatalysts. Among these, effi-cient light-emission arises from self-trapped excitons, wherein excited states induce transient lattice distortions that localize excitons. However, the complex interplay of factors, such as lattice distortions, lattice softness, and electron-phonon cou-pling dynamics, obscures the direct structure-property relationships complicating the targeted material design. In this study, we advance the understanding of self-trapped exciton (STE)-based emission in hybrid antimony and bismuth halides, em-phasizing the interplay of structural and electronic factors that enhance white-light emission. We systematically vary com-position, anion dimensionality, connectivity, and the organic cation and find that the presence of Bi/Sb and Cl in edge-sharing anion motifs promotes white-light emission and optimal electron-phonon coupling. Chlorides outperform bromides, and organic cations, such as CMA and BZA, only subtly influence optical behavior by altering lattice dynamics and rigidity, resulting in tunable emission characteristics without compromising STEs. This work deepens the understanding of the emis-sion mechanisms in hybrid halide perovskites and establishes guiding principles for tailoring optoelectronic properties, paving the way for advanced materials with enhanced white-light emission for next-generation optoelectronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20087v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Philip Klement, Lukas G\"umbel, Meng Yang, Jan-Heinrich Littmann, Tatsuhiko Ohto, Hirokazu Tada, Sangam Chatterjee, Johanna Heine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multipole analysis of spin currents in altermagnetic MnTe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20120</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20120v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets, a class of unconventional antiferromagnets where antiparallel spins are connected by combined rotational and translational symmetries, have recently emerged as promising candidates for spintronic applications, as they can efficiently generate spin currents while maintaining vanishing net magnetization. Here, we investigate charge transport and spin currents in $\alpha$-MnTe, a prototypical altermagnet, using symmetry analysis within the multipole framework and fully relativistic first-principles calculations using the Kubo formalism. Our results show that different magnetic configurations with N\'eel vectors $\hat{N}\parallel y$ and $\hat{N}\parallel x$ in MnTe induce distinct order parameters. This distinction gives rise to spin-momentum locking with different parities and magnetic spin Hall effects (magnetic SHEs) with different anisotropies. Strikingly, our calculations show that the combination of intrinsic spin-orbit coupling and altermagnetic spin splitting yields a large magnetic spin Hall angle of up to 16 \% rivaling or exceeding that of heavy metals such as Pt. On the other hand, the anisotropy of the magnetic SHE provides a practical means to identify the type of order parameter. This establishes, through the powerful framework of multipoles, a general approach for studying transport phenomena that extends to a broader class of altermagnets beyond MnTe.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20120v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryosuke Hirakida, Karma Tenzin, Chao Chen Ye, Berkay Kilic, Carmine Autieri, Jagoda S{\l}awi\'nska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Intrinsic Electro-Optic Kerr Rotation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20139</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20139v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We uncover a previously overlooked contribution to the electro-optic Kerr rotation of reflected light, arising from the interplay of matter, the static electric field, and the magnetic component of light. Remarkably, this mechanism dominates in isotropic nonmagnetic homogeneous metals. We derive analytical expressions for the Kerr rotation in both two-dimensional layers and semi-infinite systems. Within the relaxation-time approximation, we predict experimentally accessible signal magnitudes. This intrinsic mechanism thereby opens new opportunities for probing electronic properties in materials through Kerr spectroscopy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20139v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Erlend Sylju{\aa}sen, Alireza Qaiumzadeh, Rembert A. Duine, Arne Brataas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Single crystal growth, structural and physical properties, and absence of a charge density wave in Ti_{0.85}Fe6Ge6</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20142</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20142v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Kagome materials with charge density waves (CDWs) are fascinating quantum systems, offering an ideal platform to explore intertwined orders and to uncover novel mechanisms behind CDW formation. Chemical models have been developed and applied to predict CDW in $AM_6X_6$-type kagome materials, such as the rattling chain model based on ScV6Sn6 and the magnetic energy-saving model based on FeGe. In this study, we successfully synthesized Ti_{0.85}Fe6Ge6 single crystals using the vapor transport method. As predicted by the rattling chain model, these crystals are expected to exhibit kagome CDW behavior. Magnetization measurements indicate that Ti_{0.85}Fe6Ge6 is an easy-axis antiferromagnet with T_N = 488 K and transport measurements reveal metallic behavior primarily driven by electron-type carriers. However, no clear signatures of a CDW were observed in Ti_{0.85}Fe6Ge6. Density functional theory calculations demonstrate a markedly distinct electronic structure compared to related compounds: instead of a carrier-doping-induced rigid shift, the density of states shifted away from the Fermi level. Consistent with our structural investigations, the absence of a CDW and the unusual band structure can be attributed to the bonding characteristic within Ti_{0.85}Fe6Ge6. The strong covalent bonds of Ti-Ge1b, along with the solid Ge1b-Ge1b dimers, prevent the Ti-Ge1b-Ge1b-Ti chain from rattling. The presence of Fe-Fe antibonding state at the Fermi level enhances the spin polarization and depletes the electronic density around the Fermi level. Our results suggest that both the ionic radius and the bonding characteristics of the filler atom are crucial for the formation of CDWs in kagome materials. These factors can serve as supplementary terms to the rattling chain model, providing new insights for the discovery of novel kagome CDW materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20142v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dechao Cheng, Nour Maraytta, Xiuhua Chen, Xizhi Li, Xueliang Wu, Xiangxiang Jing, Yong Hu, Youpin Gong, Mingquan He, Yisheng Chai, Xiaoyuan Zhou, Pengfei Jiang, Yilin Wang, Michael Merz, Aifeng Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the magnetic behavior of C$_{\rm3}$N$_{\rm4}$ 2D material by defect creation, defect passivation, and transition metal adsorption</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20156</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20156v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Using the density functional tight binding method (DFTB) and the GFN1-xTB (Geometries, Frequencies, and Noncovalent interactions Tight Binding) Hamiltonian, we have investigated the structural, electronic and magnetic properties of vacancy defects, hydrogen and oxygen passivated defects, and Fe adsorption in two-dimensional (2D) graphitic carbon nitride (gt-C$_3$N$_4$) 2D material. The ring shape is the most preferred vacancy evolution path, with significant stability of the semicircle fourfold C-N-C-N vacancy. We found that bare gt-C$_3$N$_4$ which is non-magnetic becomes magnetic by 2-, and 5-defects creation, hydrogen/oxygen passivation of the defects, and upon Fe adsorption. Interestingly, Fe atoms interact with the gt-C$_3$N$_4$ sheet and result in a ground ferromagnetic (FM) state. In addition, we investigate the effects of passivating the vacancies by hydrogen in gt-C$_3$N$_4$ on its structural, electrical, and magnetic properties. We found that substituting the 1, 2, and 3 vacancies with hydrogen and passivating the 6-defect with oxygen turns on magnetism in the system. Due to structural distortion, the passivated defects do not have a well-ordered magnetic orientation. However, passivating the remaining defected structures maintains the nonmagnetic state. It is also shown that passivation leads to a semiconductor with a band gap value higher than that of the bare material. We also calculate the electronic and magnetic properties of transition metal (TM) atoms, including V, Cr, Mn, Fe, Co, Ni-adsorbed gt-C$_3$N$_4$ monolayer. All TM atoms show slight lattice distortion, and the adsorbed system almost maintains the original structure type. Moreover, a FM alignment was observed with a total magnetic moments of 2.89 $\mu_B$, 2 $\mu_B$, and 1 $\mu_B$ for V, Fe, and Co atoms, respectively. The Cr, Mn, and Ni atoms induce no magnetism to the non magnetic gt-C$_3$N$_4$ system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20156v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1007/s10853-025-11399-z</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Taoufik Sakhraoui, Franti\v{s}ek Karlick\'y</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Massive Discovery of Low-Dimensional Materials from Universal Computational Strategy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20164</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20164v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Low-dimensional materials have attractive properties that drive intense efforts for novel materials discovery. However, experiments are tedious for systematic discovery, and present computational methods are often tuned to two-dimensional (2D) materials, overlooking other low-dimensional materials. Here, we combined universal machine-learning interatomic potentials (UMLIPs) and an advanced, interatomic force constant (FC) -based dimensionality classification method to make a massive discovery of novel low-dimensional materials. We first benchmarked UMLIPs' first-principles-level accuracy in quantifying FCs and calculated phonons for 35,689 materials from the Materials Project database. We then used the FC-based method for dimensionality classification to discover 9139 low-dimensional materials, including 1838 0D clusters, 1760 1D chains, 3057 2D sheets/layers, and 2484 mixed-dimensionality materials, all of which conventional geometric descriptors have not recognized. By calculating the binding energies for the discovered 2D materials, we also identified 960 sheets that could be easily or potentially exfoliated from their parent bulk structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20164v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Bagheri, Ethan Berger, Hannu-Pekka Komsa, Pekka Koskinen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A follow-up on the sulphur atom popping model for MoS$_2$ memristor</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20179</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20179v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The mechanism of resistive switching in two-dimensional (2D) semiconductor-based memristors is intriguing, and our conventional knowledge of bulk-oxide based memristors does not apply to these devices. Experimental data indicate that the genesis of resistive switching may be intrinsic to the 2D semiconducting active layer, as well as resulting from the movement of electrode atoms. Employing reactive-force field (ReaxFF) molecular dynamics simulations, we introduced the "sulphur atom popping model" [npj 2D Mater. Appl. 5, 33 (2021)] to elucidate the intrinsic nature of non-volatile resistive switching in 2D molybdenum disulfide-based memristors. In this paper we provide additional perspective to this model using density functional theory. We also discuss the limitations of universal machine learning interatomic potentials in reproducing ReaxFF simulation results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20179v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sanchali Mitra, Santanu Mahapatra</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>AMaRaNTA: Automated First-Principles Exchange Parameters In 2D Magnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20226v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) magnets host a wide range of exotic magnetic textures, whose low-energy excitations and finite-temperature properties are typically described by effective spin models based on Heisenberg-like Hamiltonians. A key challenge in this framework is the reliable determination, from ab initio calculations, of exchange parameters and their anisotropic components, crucial for stabilising long-range order. Among the different strategies proposed for this task, the energy-mapping method -- based on total-energy calculations within Density Functional Theory (DFT) -- is the most widely adopted, but it typically requires laborious, multi-step procedures. To overcome this limitation, we introduce AMaRaNTA (Automating Magnetic paRAmeters iN a Tensorial Approach), a computational package that systematically automates the energy-mapping method, specifically through its ``four-state'' formulation, to extract exchange and anisotropy parameters in 2D magnets. In its current implementation, AMaRaNTA returns the nearest-neighbour exchange tensor, complemented by scalar parameters for second- and third-nearest-neighbour exchange interactions as well as single-ion anisotropy. Together, these provide a minimal yet sufficient set of parameters to capture magnetic frustration and anisotropies, essential for stabilising several observed magnetic states in 2D materials. Applied to a representative subset of the Materials Cloud 2D Structure database, AMaRaNTA demonstrates robust, automated and reproducible screening of magnetic interactions, with clear potential for high-throughput simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20226v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Federico Orlando (Physics Department - Politecnico di Milano, Milan, Italy, Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche CNR-SPIN, c/o Universit\`a degli Studi "G. D'Annunzio", Chieti, Italy), Andrea Droghetti (Department of Molecular Sciences and Nanosystems, Ca' Foscari University of Venice, Venice, Italy, Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche CNR-SPIN, c/o Universit\`a degli Studi "G. D'Annunzio", Chieti, Italy), Lorenzo Varrassi (Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia, Universit\`a di Bologna, Bologna, Italy), Giuseppe Cuono (Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche CNR-SPIN, c/o Universit\`a degli Studi "G. D'Annunzio", Chieti, Italy), Cesare Franchini (University of Vienna, Faculty of Physics and Center for Computational Materials Science, Vienna, Austria, Dipartimento di Fisica e Astronomia, Universit\`a di Bologna, Bologna, Italy), Paolo Barone (Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche CNR-SPIN, Area della Ricerca di Tor Vergata, Rome, Italy), Antimo Marrazzo (Scuola Internazionale Superiore di Studi Avanzati), Marco Gibertini (Dipartimento di Scienze Fisiche, Informatiche e Matematiche, Universit\`a di Modena e Reggio Emilia, Modena, Italy, Centro S3, Istituto Nanoscienze-CNR, Modena, Italy), Srdjan Stavri\'c (Vin\v{c}a Institute of Nuclear Sciences - National Institute of the Republic of Serbia, University of Belgrade, Belgrade, Serbia, Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche CNR-SPIN, c/o Universit\`a degli Studi "G. D'Annunzio", Chieti, Italy), Silvia Picozzi (Department of Materials Science, University of Milan - Bicocca, Milan, Italy, Consiglio Nazionale delle Ricerche CNR-SPIN, c/o Universit\`a degli Studi "G. D'Annunzio", Chieti, Italy)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>4D-QENS Analysis of Correlated Ionic Conduction in SrCl$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20312</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20312v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Methods of elucidating the mechanisms of fast-ion conduction in solid-state materials are pivotal for advancements in energy technologies such as batteries, fuel cells, sensors, and supercapacitors. In this study, we examine the ionic conduction pathways in single crystal SrCl$_2$, which is a fast-ion conductor above 900~K, using four-dimensional Quasi-Elastic Neutron Scattering (4D-QENS). We explore both coherent and incoherent neutron scattering at temperatures above the transition temperature into the superionic phase to explore the correlated motion of hopping anions. Refinements of the incoherent QENS yield residence times and jump probabilities between lattice sites in good agreement with previous studies, confirming that ionic hopping along nearest-neighbor directions is the most probable conduction pathway. However, the coherent QENS reveals evidence of de Gennes narrowing, indicating the importance of ionic correlations in the conduction mechanism. This highlights the need for improvements both in the theory of ionic transport in fluorite compounds and the modeling of coherent 4D-QENS in single crystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20312v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jared Coles, Omar Chmaissem, Matthew Krogstad, Daniel M. Pajerowski, Feng Ye, Duck Young Chung, Mercouri G. Kanatzidis, Stephan Rosenkranz, Raymond Osborn</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical correlation effects in twisted bilayer graphene under strain and lattice relaxation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19436</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19436v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We study the impact of lattice effects due to heterostrain and relaxation on the correlated electron physics of magic-angle twisted bilayer graphene, by applying dynamical mean-field theory to the topological heavy fermion model. Heterostrain is responsible for splitting the 8-fold degenerate flat bands into two 4-fold degenerate subsets, while relaxation breaks the particle-hole symmetry of the unperturbed THF model. The interplay of dynamical correlation effects and lattice symmetry breaking enables us to satisfactorily reproduce a wide set of experimentally observed features: splitting the flat band degeneracy has observable consequences in the form of a filling-independent maximum in the spectral density away from zero bias, which faithfully reproduces scanning tunneling microscopy and quantum twisting microscopy results alike. We also observe an overall reduction in the size and degeneracy of local moments upon lowering the temperature, in agreement with entropy measurements. The absence of particle-hole symmetry has as a consequence the stronger suppression of local moments on the hole-doped side relatively to the electron-doped side, and ultimately causes the differences in existence and stability of the correlated phases for negative and positive doping. Our results show that even fine-level structures in the experimental data can now be faithfully reproduced and understood.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19436v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lorenzo Crippa, Gautam Rai, Dumitru C\u{a}lug\u{a}ru, Haoyu Hu, Jonah Herzog-Arbeitman, B. Andrei Bernevig, Roser Valent\'i, Giorgio Sangiovanni, Tim Wehling</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Dynamics of Electron Scattering from Skyrmions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19437</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19437v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Scattering of electrons from chiral spin textures such as the skyrmions is an emerging research area due to its richness in topological quantum transport, which is significant for spintronic devices. We study the dynamical process of scattering of the spin-$\frac{1}{2}$ particles in the form of Gaussian wavepackets from skyrmions with the aid of the non-relativistic time-dependent Schr\"odinger equation. The scattering cross section shows a rich angular dependence and is deterministically influenced by the iterative flipping of the spin state inside the skyrmion. The latter leads to a set of non-trivial outcomes which include finite transmission and reflection probabilities irrespective of interaction strength, formation of secondary wavefronts associated with back-converted spin components, and a long-lived quasi-bound state at the scattering center. In addition to the rich and intriguing physics, the numerical recipe developed here can be easily adopted for any arbitrary spin texture, which will prepare a playground to explore tunable spin transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19437v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hareram Swain, Arijit Mandal, S. Satpathy, B. R. K. Nanda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reaction/Diffusion Competition Drives Anomalous Relaxation of Vitrimers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19496</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19496v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Vitrimers are an emerging class of crosslinked polymer networks in which dynamic covalent bonds can exchange and rearrange, without any significant change in population of bonded states.1 Because these bonds can rearrange at high temperatures without disintegration of the network, vitrimers could combine the mechanical stability of traditional permanently crosslinked networks with the recyclability of glasses and physical networks. However, unlike classical transient/physical networks, vitrimers can relax at a rate that is decoupled from the mobility of their polymer segments. This challenges our fundamental understanding of how dynamic covalent networks relax and deform. Here we combine simulations, theory, and experiments to show that vitrimer dynamics exhibit two very different regimes: (i) a high temperature regime controlled by the local bond-exchange reaction rate and (ii) a low temperature regime controlled by segmental diffusion. This fundamental difference from traditional physical networks explains why vitrimers can exhibit Arrhenius dynamics, providing a foundation for their rational design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19496v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Makayla R. Branham-Ferrari, Shinian Cheng, Alexei P. Sokolov, David S. Simmons</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Universal Deep Learning for Electronic-Structure Hamiltonian Prediction of Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19877</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19877v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Deep learning methods for electronic-structure Hamiltonian prediction has offered significant computational efficiency advantages over traditional DFT methods, yet the diversity of atomic types, structural patterns, and the high-dimensional complexity of Hamiltonians pose substantial challenges to the generalization performance. In this work, we contribute on both the methodology and dataset sides to advance universal deep learning paradigm for Hamiltonian prediction. On the method side, we propose NextHAM, a neural E(3)-symmetry and expressive correction method for efficient and generalizable materials electronic-structure Hamiltonian prediction. First, we introduce the zeroth-step Hamiltonians, which can be efficiently constructed by the initial charge density of DFT, as informative descriptors of neural regression model in the input level and initial estimates of the target Hamiltonian in the output level, so that the regression model directly predicts the correction terms to the target ground truths, thereby significantly simplifying the input-output mapping for learning. Second, we present a neural Transformer architecture with strict E(3)-Symmetry and high non-linear expressiveness for Hamiltonian prediction. Third, we propose a novel training objective to ensure the accuracy performance of Hamiltonians in both real space and reciprocal space, preventing error amplification and the occurrence of "ghost states" caused by the large condition number of the overlap matrix. On the dataset side, we curate a high-quality broad-coverage large benchmark, namely Materials-HAM-SOC, comprising 17,000 material structures spanning 68 elements from six rows of the periodic table and explicitly incorporating SOC effects. Experimental results on Materials-HAM-SOC demonstrate that NextHAM achieves excellent accuracy and efficiency in predicting Hamiltonians and band structures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19877v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shi Yin, Zujian Dai, Xinyang Pan, Lixin He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical prediction of Structural Stability and Superconductivity in Janus Ti2CSH MXene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19907</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19907v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive first-principles investigation of the structural stability, vibrational characteristics, and superconducting properties of the Janus Ti2CSH monolayer. Janus MXene (JMXene) materials, such as Ti2CSH, have attracted significant attention due to their intrinsic two-dimensional structure and the absence of out-of-plane symmetry, which give rise to novel physical phenomena. Phonon calculations confirm the dynamical stability of the monolayer, while electronic structure and electron-phonon coupling analyses reveal a strong phonon-mediated pairing mechanism. Anisotropic Migdal-Eliashberg theory predicts a single-gap superconducting state, with gap values between 4.29 and 4.71 meV at 10 K and a critical temperature Tc of 22.6 K. These findings establish Ti2CSH as a promising two-dimensional superconductor with potential applications in quantum and nanoscale technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19907v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jakkapat Seeyangnok, Udomsilp Pinsook</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploration of Altermagnetism in $\mathrm{RuO_{2}}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19932</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19932v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The fundamental role of magnetic materials in modern science and technology has driven a rapid surge in research on unconventional magnetism in recent years. In particular, altermagnets, which simultaneously exhibit zero net magnetization in real space and anisotropic spin splitting in momentum space, have garnered significant interest for both fundamental physics and technological applications. Among these, $\mathrm{RuO_{2}}$ stands as the pioneering and most extensively studied altermagnet. While the intrinsic magnetic order of $\mathrm{RuO_{2}}$ is still a subject of active debate, numerous exotic phenomena characteristic of altermagnetism have been observed in $\mathrm{RuO_{2}}$ samples. In this review, we explore each facet of the altermagnetism through specific case studies in $\mathrm{RuO_{2}}$, systematically surveying its crystal and magnetic structures, electronic band properties, and transport phenomena. We critically assess the debate surrounding the intrinsic magnetism in $\mathrm{RuO_{2}}$, incorporating evidence from altermagnetic signatures in transport, as well as contrasting results from magnetic and spectroscopic measurements. Finally, possible future research directions in this field are discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19932v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu-Xin Li, Yiyuan Chen, Liqing Pan, Shuai Li, Song-Bo Zhang, Hai-Zhou Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable Machine Learning Model for Energy Decomposition Analysis in Aqueous Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.19983</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.19983v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Energy decomposition analysis (EDA) based on absolutely localized molecular orbitals provides detailed insights into intermolecular bonding by decomposing the total molecular binding energy into physically meaningful components. Here, we develop a neural network EDA model capable of predicting the electron delocalization energy component of water molecules, which captures the stabilization arising from charge transfer between occupied absolutely localized molecular orbitals of one molecule and the virtual orbitals of another. Exploiting the locality assumption of the electronic structure, our model enables accurate prediction of electron delocalization energies for molecular systems far beyond the size accessible to conventional density functional theory calculations, while maintaining its accuracy. We demonstrate the applicability of our approach by modeling hydration effects in large molecular complexes, specifically in metal-organic frameworks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.19983v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hossein Tahmasbi, Michael Beerbaum, Bartosz Brzoza, Attila Cangi, Thomas D. K\"uhne</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Resistive switching behaviors in vertically aligned MoS$_2$ films with Cu, Ag, and Au electrodes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20061v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Neuromorphic computing circuits can be realized using memristors based on low-dimensional materials enabling enhanced metal diffusion for resistive switching. Here, we investigate memristive properties of vertically aligned MoS$_2$ (VA-MoS$_2$) films with three different metal electrodes: Ag, Cu, and Au. Despite having the same active material, all three metals show distinct switching behavior, which are crucial for neuromorphic computing applications: Ag enables volatile switching, Cu demonstrates stable non-volatile switching with retention over 2500 s, and Au shows no memristive response. Cu devices show abrupt resistance changes, and significant increase of copper content upon biasing, indicative of stable non-volatile switching based on filament formation and rupture. About 85% of Ag and Cu devices exhibit reliable memristor behavior. Our findings provide valuable insights into the memristive switching mechanism in VA-MoS$_2$ and present a promising avenue for facile fabrication of neuromorphic circuits by employing a set of different metals on a single active material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20061v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuei-De Huang, Touko Lehenkari, Topias J\"arvinen, Seyed Hossein Hosseini-Shokouh, Farzaneh Bouzari, Krisztian Kordas, Hannu-Pekka Komsa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extended Low-Rank Approximation Accelerates Learning of Elastic Response in Heterogeneous Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.20276</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.20276v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Predicting how the microstructure governs the mechanical response of heterogeneous materials is essential for optimizing design and performance. Yet this task remains difficult due to the complex, high dimensional nature of microstructural features. Relying on physics based simulations to probe the microstructural space is computationally prohibitive. This motivates the development of computational tools to efficiently learn structure property linkages governing mechanical behavior. While contemporary data driven approaches offer new possibilities, they often require large datasets. To address this challenge, this work presents the Extended Low Rank Approximation (xLRA), a framework that employs canonical polyadic tensor decomposition. It efficiently maps high dimensional microstructural information to the local elastic response by adaptively incorporating higher rank terms. xLRA accurately predicts the local elastic strain fields in porous microstructures, requiring a maximum rank of only 4. The compact formulation of xLRA achieves accurate predictions when trained on just 5% of the dataset, demonstrating significant data efficiency. Moreover, xLRA proves transferability by delivering results across representative material systems, including two phase composites and single and dual phase polycrystals. Despite being compact, xLRA retains essential microstructural details, enabling accurate predictions on unseen microstructures. Benchmarking shows that xLRA outperforms contemporary methods in predictive accuracy, generalizability, and computational efficiency, while requiring 6 orders of magnitude fewer floating point operations. In summary, xLRA provides an efficient framework for predicting the elastic response from microstructures, enabling scalable mapping of structure property linkages.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.20276v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Prabhat Karmakar, Sayan Gupta, Ilaksh Adlakha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Fabrication of self-powered photodetector materials based on Ni-doped ZnO/p-Si heterojunctions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.05441</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.05441v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, Ni-doped ZnO films were grown on a p-type silicon substrate via spray pyrolysis. The Ni dopant concentrations were varied by adjusting the weight ratio between Zinc Acetate Dehydrate (ZAD) and Nickel Chloride Hexahydrate (NCH), resulting in the ZnO, ZnO:Ni1%, and ZnO:Ni3% samples. Field-effect scanning electron microscopy (FESEM) images revealed that Ni doping significantly reduced the nanostructure size from 326 nm (ZnO) to 146 nm (ZnO:Ni3%). Similarly, X-ray diffraction (XRD) analysis also shows the decrease of the crystallite size with increasing Ni doping, from 44 nm (ZnO) to 35 nm (ZnO:Ni3%). Current-voltage (I-V) measurements were conducted at a bias voltage of 0 and 5 V to examine electrical and self-powered photodetection properties. All samples demonstrate self-powered photodetector performance. At the bias of 0 V, the undoped ZnO exhibited a higher photo-to-dark-current ratio (162) as compared to ZnO:Ni1% (18) and ZnO:Ni3% (16). The ZnO:Ni3% samples displayed faster rise (0.4 s) and fall times (1.7 s) as compared to the pure ZnO (10.8 s for rise time and 9.1 s for fall time), highlighting their potential for applications requiring rapid photoresponse. The findings provide valuable insights into optimizing the performance of ZnO-based photodetectors through controlled Ni doping, enabling advancements in self-powered photodetection technology for energy-efficient optoelectronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.05441v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.nxmate.2025.101215</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Next Materials 9 (2025) 101215</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Eka Nurfani, Aldi Saputra, Novalia Pertiwi, Muhamad F. Arif</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vector pulse magnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.14896</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.14896v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The underlying symmetry of the crystal, electronic structure, and magnetic structure manifests itself in the anisotropy of materials' properties, which is a central topic of the present condensed matter research. However, it demands such a considerable effort to fill the explorable space that only a small part has been conquered. We report a vector pulse magnet (VPM) as an alternative experimental technique to control the direction of applied magnetic fields, which may complement the conventional methods with its characteristic features. The VPM combines a conventional pulse magnet and a vector magnet. The VPM can create vector pulsed magnetic fields and swiftly rotating pulsed magnetic fields. As a demonstration, the three-dimensional magnetoresistance measurement of a highly oriented pyrolytic graphite is carried out using the AC four-probe method at 4.5 K and 6 T. The two-dimensional electronic structure of graphite is visualized in the three-dimensional magnetoresistance data. One can uncover the rotational and time-reversal symmetry of materials using a VPM and a variety of measurement techniques.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.14896v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kosuke Noda, Kenta Seki, Dilip Bhoi, Kazuyuki Matsubayashi, Kazuto Akiba, Akihiko Ikeda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Faceting transition in aluminum as a grain boundary phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.13550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.13550v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Grain boundaries facet due to anisotropic grain boundary energies: While the faceted boundary has a larger area than the corresponding straight boundary, a significantly lower energy of the facets compared to a straight segment can drive the faceting. This picture is complicated by faceting/defaceting transitions where the free energy difference between the two states depends on the temperature. Such transitions have been observed and modeled before, but their exact nature was not fully understood. Here, we use atomistic computer simulations to show that a well known faceting transition in $\Sigma 3$ [111] tilt grain boundaries in Al is in fact a grain boundary phase transition (also called complexion transition). This means that the faceted and defaceted boundaries are associated with different atomic structures, which have different thermodynamic stability ranges. At low temperatures, the grain boundary phase associated with faceting is stable, while at high temperatures the flat grain boundary phase is stable. We also report on our thorough tests of Al interatomic potentials for this purpose, which include comparisons to density-functional theory calculations. Our chosen potential performs well for our grain boundaries. As a consequence we were able to obtain results that align with previous experimental results.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.13550v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/2dnf-zdz8</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Mater. 9, 083607 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yoonji Choi, Tobias Brink</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Open DAC 2025 Dataset for Sorbent Discovery in Direct Air Capture</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.03162</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.03162v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Identifying useful sorbent materials for direct air capture (DAC) from humid air remains a challenge. We present the Open DAC 2025 (ODAC25) dataset, a significant expansion and improvement upon ODAC23 (Sriram et al., ACS Central Science, 10 (2024) 923), comprising nearly 60 million DFT single-point calculations for CO$_2$, H$_2$O, N$_2$, and O$_2$ adsorption in 15,000 MOFs. ODAC25 introduces chemical and configurational diversity through functionalized MOFs, high-energy GCMC-derived placements, and synthetically generated frameworks. ODAC25 also significantly improves upon the accuracy of DFT calculations and the treatment of flexible MOFs in ODAC23. Along with the dataset, we release new state-of-the-art machine-learned interatomic potentials trained on ODAC25 and evaluate them on adsorption energy and Henry's law coefficient predictions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.03162v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Anuroop Sriram, Logan M. Brabson, Xiaohan Yu, Sihoon Choi, Kareem Abdelmaqsoud, Elias Moubarak, Pim de Haan, Sindy L\"owe, Johann Brehmer, John R. Kitchin, Max Welling, C. Lawrence Zitnick, Zachary Ulissi, Andrew J. Medford, David S. Sholl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning Time Propagators for Time-Dependent Density Functional Theory Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.16554</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.16554v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Time-dependent density functional theory (TDDFT) is a widely used method to investigate electron dynamics under external time-dependent perturbations such as laser fields. In this work, we present a machine learning approach to accelerate electron dynamics simulations based on real time TDDFT using autoregressive neural operators as time-propagators for the electron density. By leveraging physics-informed constraints and featurization, and high-resolution training data, our model achieves superior accuracy and computational speed compared to traditional numerical solvers. We demonstrate the effectiveness of our model on a class of one-dimensional diatomic molecules under the influence of a range of laser parameters. This method has potential in enabling on-the-fly modeling of laser-irradiated molecules and materials by utilizing fast machine learning predictions in a large space of varying experimental parameters of the laser.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.16554v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karan Shah, Attila Cangi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Energy dependent Chemical Interface Damping induced by 1-Decanethiol Self-Assembled Monolayer on Au(111)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05025v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The chemical interface damping (CID) effect increases the collision frequency of free electrons in metals by changes of the metal surface. We have now experimentally disentangled the two contributions to CID: induced roughness and direct charge transfer. The latter is an important area of research in photoelectrochemistry with potential applications in light-induced chemical reactions. We present a broadband investigation of the CID effect on Au(111) covered by a self-assembled monolayer of decanethiol. Spectroscopic ellipsometry measurements show a photon energy dependent increase of collision frequency. We observe a constant, photon energy independent contribution, which is attributed to induced roughness and a contribution that linearly increases with photon energy from about 1 eV upwards which we attribute to direct charge transfer. The onset of the charge transfer mechanism corresponds to occupied orbitals of thiols bound to the Au surface, as confirmed by density functional theory calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05025v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Maurice Pfeiffer, Gregor B. Vonbun-Feldbauer, Jacob B. Khurgin, Olga Matts, Ahmed Shqer, Nadiia Mameka, Manfred Eich, Alexander Petrov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Correlation Matrix Method for Phonon Quasiparticles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.05960</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.05960v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Phonon anharmonicity is ubiquitous in real materials and is crucial for understanding thermal properties and phase stability. In this work, we show that anharmonic phonon modes can be obtained by maximizing their lifetimes during fitting the atomic trajectory. We prove that all information about these quasiparticles is contained in two small correlation matrices $\mathcal{S}$ and $\mathcal{Q}$, which can be constructed directly from molecular dynamics simulations. Based on these matrices, we proposed an optimization scheme, which allows us to efficiently determine temperature-dependent phonon modes along with their frequencies and lifetimes. We verified this method by applying it to silicon and cubic CaSiO$_3$, where it successfully captured their temperature-dependent phonon behaviors and the well-known phonon softening in cubic CaSiO$_3$. This theory provides a convenient tool for investigating phonon quasiparticles and can be extended to study other quasiparticles, such as electrons, holes, and magnons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.05960v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenjing Li, Yong Lu, Fawei Zheng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Barrier Electrostatics and Contact Engineering for Ultra-Wide Bandgap AlGaN HFETs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.15715</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.15715v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report ultra-wide bandgap (UWBG) AlGaN heterostructure field-effect transistors (HFETs) exhibiting a high breakdown field (&gt; 5.3 MV/cm) and a low contact resistance (~1.55 {\Omega}mm), tailored for high-power radiofrequency applications. A split-doped barrier architecture, employing two distinct doping concentrations, is shown to enhance both the breakdown field and contact resistance. This design enables a state-of-the-art combination of maximum drain current (487 mA/mm) and breakdown field, along with a high cutoff frequency of 7.2 GHz. These results demonstrate a viable pathway to push device performance toward the material limits while minimizing contact resistance in UWBG AlGaN HFETs, paving the way for next-generation high-power, high-frequency applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.15715v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seungheon Shin, Can Cao, Jon Pratt, Yinxuan Zhu, Brianna A. Klein, Andrew Armstrong, Andrew A. Allerman, Siddharth Rajan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spatially-Controlled Planar Czochralski Growth of Low-Loss Phase Change Materials for Programmable Photonics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.16603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.16603v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Photonic integrated devices are progressively evolving beyond passive components into fully programmable systems, notably driven by the progress in chalcogenide phase-change materials (PCMs) for non-volatile reconfigurable nanophotonics. However, the stochastic nature of their crystal grain formation results in strong spatial and temporal crystalline inhomogeneities. Here, we propose the concept of spatially-controlled planar Czochralski growth, a novel method for programming the quasi-monocrystalline growth of low-loss Sb2S3 PCM, leveraging the seeded directional and progressive crystallization within confined channels. This guided crystallization method is experimentally shown to circumvent the current limitations of conventional PCM-based nanophotonic devices, including a multilevel non-volatile optical phase-shifter exploiting a silicon nitride-based Mach-Zehnder interferometer, and a programmable metasurface with spectrally reconfigurable bound state in the continuum. Precisely controlling the growth of PCMs to ensure uniform crystalline properties across large areas is the cornerstone for the industrial development of non-volatile reconfigurable photonic integrated circuits.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.16603v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fouad Bentata, Arnaud Taute, Capucine Laprais, R\'egis Orobtchouk, Eva Kempf, Alban Gassenq, Yves Pipon, Michele Calvo, St\'ephane Monfray, Guillaume Saint-Girons, Nicolas Baboux, Hai Son Nguyen, Xavier Letartre, Lotfi Berguiga, Patrice Genevet, S\'ebastien Cueff</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate crystal field Hamiltonians of single-ion magnets at mean-field cost</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.16905</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.16905v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The effective crystal field Hamiltonian provides the key description of the electronic properties of single-ion magnets, but obtaining its parameters from ab initio computation is challenging. We introduce a simple approach to derive the effective crystal field Hamiltonian through density functional calculations of randomly rotated mean-field states within the low-energy manifold. In benchmarks on five lanthanide-based complexes, we find that we compute with mean-field cost an effective crystal field Hamiltonian that matches the state-of-the-art from much more expensive multi-configurational quantum chemistry methods. In addition, we are able to reproduce the experimental low-energy spectrum and magnetic properties with an accuracy exceeding prior attempts. Due to its low cost, our approach provides a crucial ingredient in the computational design of single-ion magnets with tailored physical properties and low-energy spectra.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.16905v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Linqing Peng, Shuanglong Liu, Xing Zhang, Xiao Chen, Chenghan Li, Hai-Ping Cheng, Garnet Kin-Lic Chan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atom-surface interaction induced by quenched monopolar charge disorder</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2508.12280</link>
      <description>arXiv:2508.12280v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We study the modification to the energy level shifts of an atom induced by the quenched monopolar charge disorder inside the bulk of neighboring dielectric slabs as well as their surfaces. By assuming that the charge disorder follows Gaussian statistics with a zero mean, we find that the disorder generally results in a downward shift of the energy levels, which corresponds to an attractive force that can compete with and overcome the nonresonant Casimir-Polder force for sufficiently large atom-surface separations $z_0$. For an atom near a single semi-infinite slab with bulk (surface) charge disorder, the shift decays as $z_0^{-1}$ ($z_0^{-2}$). For both surface and bulk disorder, the shift is proportional to the variance of the charge disorder density. In addition, we investigate the behavior of the charge disorder-induced energy level shift for an atom confined to a vacuum gap between two coplanar and semi-infinite slabs of the same dielectric material, finding that the position of net zero disorder-induced force occurs closer to the surface of the slab with the smaller charge disorder variance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2508.12280v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.atom-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/f19n-7bdn</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Bing-Sui Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Vibrational Fingerprints of Strained Polymers: A Spectroscopic Pathway to Mechanical State Prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.16266</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.16266v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The vibrational response of polymer networks under load provides a sensitive probe of molecular deformation and a route to non-destructive diagnostics. Here we show that machine-learned force fields reproduce these spectroscopic fingerprints with quantum-level fidelity in realistic epoxy thermosets. Using MACE-OFF23 molecular dynamics, we capture the experimentally observed redshifts of para-phenylene stretching modes under tensile load, in contrast to the harmonic OPLS-AA model. These shifts correlate with molecular elongation and alignment, consistent with Badger's rule, directly linking vibrational features to local stress. To capture IR intensities, we trained a symmetry-adapted dipole moment model on representative epoxy fragments, enabling validation of strain responses. Together, these approaches provide chemically accurate and computationally accessible predictions of strain-dependent vibrational spectra. Our results establish vibrational fingerprints as predictive markers of mechanical state in polymer networks, pointing to new strategies for stress mapping and structural-health diagnostics in advanced materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.16266v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Sep 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Julian Konrad, Janina Mittelhaus, David M. Wilkins, Bodo Fiedler, Robert Mei{\ss}ner</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
