<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 11:11:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Alloying to Tune the Bandgap of the AM2Pn2 Zintl Compounds</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00127</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00127v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The AM2Pn2 Zintl compounds are a large class of semiconductor materials that have a wide range of bandgaps and are mostly stable in the same crystal structure. Representative compounds BaCd2P2 and CaZn2P2 have recently been found to exhibit high visible light absorption and long carrier lifetime. Here we use high throughput first-principles calculations to study AM2Pn2 alloys for applications as tandem top cell absorbers (i.e., bandgaps around 1.8 eV) and far infrared detector materials (i.e., bandgaps lower than 0.5 eV). Using a first-principles computational screening workflow for assessing stability and electronic structure of alloys, we identify several promising candidates. These include Ca(Cd0.8Mg0.2)2P2 with a suitable direct bandgap for use in tandem top cells on silicon bottom cells and SrCd2(Sb1-xBix)2 for far infrared detectors. We demonstrate that alloys of AM2Pn2 materials can be realized by experimentally synthesizing Ca(Zn0.8Mg0.2)2P2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00127v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Pike, Zhenkun Yuan, Muhammad Rubaiat Hasan, Smitakshi Goswami, Krishanu Samanta, Miguel I. Gonzalez, Jifeng Liu, Kirill Kovnir, Geoffroy Hautier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Kokkos-Accelerated Moment Tensor Potential Implementation for LAMMPS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00193</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00193v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a Kokkos-accelerated implementation of the Moment Tensor Potential (MTP) for LAMMPS, designed to improve both computational performance and portability across CPUs and GPUs. This package introduces an optimized CPU variant--achieving up to 2x speedups over existing implementations--and two new GPU variants: a thread-parallel version for large-scale simulations and a block-parallel version optimized for smaller systems. It supports three core functionalities: standard inference, configuration-mode active learning, and neighborhood-mode active learning. Benchmarks and case studies demonstrate efficient scaling to million-atom systems, substantially extending accessible length and time scales while preserving the MTP's near-quantum accuracy and native support for uncertainty quantification.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00193v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zijian Meng, Karim Zongo, Edmanuel Torres, Christopher Maxwell, Ryan Eric Grant, Laurent Karim B\'eland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of edge Laser-Induced Periodic Surface Structures (LIPSS) on the electrical properties of fs laser-machined ITO microcircuits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00200</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00200v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Scalable and cost-effective methods for processing transparent electrodes at the microscale are transversal for advancing in electrochemistry, optoelectronics, microfluidics, and energy harvesting. In these fields, the precise fabrication of micrometric circuits plays a critical role in determining device performance and integration with added-value substrates. In this context, Laser Subtractive Manufacturing stands out among microfabrication techniques for its adaptability to diverse materials and complex configurations, as well as its straightforward scalability and affordability nature. However, a challenge in micromachining metals and metal oxides is the inherent formation of LIPSS, which can significantly impair electrical conductivity, particularly when circuit dimensions fall within the micrometer range. Herein, we investigate the micromachining of TCOs using ultrashort pulse laser systems applied to ITO thin films. We analyze the formation of LIPSS at the edges of the micromachined regions associated with the Gaussian distribution of the energy within the laser spot and their impact on the electrical properties depending on the circuit characteristics. Thus, we evaluate the influence of LIPSS orientation and periodicity by fabricating various circuit patterns using femtosecond lasers at green (515 nm) and ultraviolet (343 nm) wavelengths. A correlation between electrical resistivity measurements and structural analysis reveals distinct effects of nanostructure formation depending on the laser source. For green wavelength, the regions where LIPSS are oriented perpendicular to the ITO track exhibit higher resistance, by a factor just above two, compared to those where LIPSS are parallel. Additionally, UV laser processing results in a pronounced reduction of ITO thickness at the boundary between the LIPSS region and the substrate.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00200v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Frechilla, E. Mart\'inez, J. del Moral, C. L\'opez-Santos, J. Frechilla, F. Nu\~nez-G\'alvez, V. L\'opez-Flores, G. F. de la Fuente, D. H\"ulag\"u, J. Bonse, A. R. Gonz\'alez-Elipe, A. Borr\'as, L. A. Angurel</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Search for Active and Inactive Ion Insertion Sites in Organic Crystalline Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00278</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00278v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The position of mobile active and inactive ions, specifically ion insertion sites, within organic crystals, significantly affects the properties of organic materials used for energy storage and ionic transport. Identifying the positions of these atom (and ion) sites in an organic crystal is difficult, especially when the element has a low X-ray scattering power, such as lithium (Li) and hydrogen, which are difficult to detect with powder X-ray diffraction (XRD) methods. First-principles calculations, exemplified by density functional theory (DFT), are very effective for confirming the relative stability of ion positions in materials. However, the lack of effective strategies to identify ion sites in these organic crystalline frameworks renders this task extremely challenging. This work presents two algorithms: (i) Efficient Location of Ion Insertion Sites from Extrema in electrostatic local potential and charge density (ELIISE), and (ii) ElectRostatic InsertioN (ERIN), which leverage charge density and electrostatic potential fields accessed from first-principles calculations, combined with the Simultaneous Ion Insertion and Evaluation (SIIE) workflow -- that inserts all ions simultaneously -- to determine ion positions in organic crystals. We demonstrate that these methods accurately reproduce known ion positions in 16 organic materials and also identify previously overlooked low-energy sites in tetralithium 2,6-naphthalenedicarboxylate (Li$_4$NDC), an organic electrode material, highlighting the importance of inserting all ions simultaneously as done in the SIIE workflow.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00278v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harshan Reddy Gopidi, Alae Eddine Lakraychi, Abhishek A. Panchal, Yiming Chen, V. S. Chaitanya Kolluru, Jiaqi Wang, Ying Chen, Liu Jue, Kamila Wiaderek, Maria K. Y. Chan, Yan Yao, Pieremanuele Canepa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Anomalous low-field magnetoresistance in Fe$_3$Ga$_4$ single crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00408</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00408v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Fe$_3$Ga$_4$ possesses a helical spin spiral with a complex competition between ferromagnetic and antiferromagnetic ground states. This competition generates multiple metamagnetic transitions that are governed by both applied magnetic field and temperature. At intermediate temperatures between T$_1$ (68 K) and T$_2$ (360 K), the ferromagnetically aligned spins transition to an antiferromagnetic spin spiral. In this study, magnetoresistance (MR) measurements are performed on an aligned single crystal and compared to magnetization properties in order to gain insight on the unique alignment of the spins. The high-field MR is positive at low temperatures indicating cyclotronic behavior and negative at high temperature from electron-magnon scattering. Of particular significance is a large anomalous positive MR at low fields, possibly due to emergent spin fluctuations thus prompting further exploration of this multifaceted material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00408v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Michelle E. Jamer, Gregory M. Stephen, Brandon Wilfong, Radhika Barua, Frank M. Abel, Steven P. Bennett, Joseph C. Prestigiacomo, Don Heiman, Dave Graf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metallic Oxides and the Overlooked Role of Bandwidth</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Oxides exhibiting metallic conduction are crucial for various applications, including fuel cells, battery electrodes, resistive and magnetoresistive materials, electrocatalysts, transparent conductors, and high-temperature superconductors. Oxides that approach metallicity also play significant roles in switching applications, where the metal-insulator transition phenomenon is utilized across a range of technologies. This perspective, motivated by the question of when oxides are metallic, employs electronic structure calculations on metallic oxides to identify the typical feature in the electronic structures that promote metallic behavior. The critical factor of the bandwidth of the electronic energy bands near the Fermi energy is emphasized since it has been somewhat overlooked in the literature. For example, bandwidth considerations would suggest that the recently proposed phosphate "LK-99" would never be a suitable target for superconductivity. From the analysis performed here, we learn that if the width of the conduction band as obtained from density functional theory-based electronic structure calculations is less than 1 eV, then the likelihood of obtaining a metallic compound is vanishingly small. This survey of representative oxide metals highlights the essential elements of extended covalency that lead to wide bands. A key takeaway is that oxyanion compounds such as borates, carbonates, silicates, sulfates, nitrates, and phosphates are unlikely to exhibit metallic conduction at ambient pressure. While the focus here is on oxides, the general findings should apply across various material families, extending to organic crystals, polymers, and framework materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00424v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aurland K. Watkins, Anthony K. Cheetham, Ram Seshadri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microscopic origin of the magnetic easy-axis switching in Fe3GaTe2 under pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00429</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00429v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The two-dimensional layered ferromagnet Fe3GaTe2, composed of a Te-FeI-FeII/Ga-FeI-Te stacking sequence, hosts two inequivalent Fe sites and exhibits a high Curie temperature and strong out-of-plane magneticanisotropy, making it a promising platform for spintronic applications. Recent experiments have observed a pressure-induced switching of the magnetic easy axis from out-of-plane to in-plane near 10 GPa, though its microscopic origin remains unclear. Here, we employ first-principles calculations to investigate the pressure dependence of the magnetocrystalline anisotropy energy in Fe3GaTe2. Our results reveal a clear easy-axis switching at a critical pressure of approximately 10 GPa, accompanied by a sharp decrease in the magnetic moments arising from FeI and FeII atoms. As pressure increases, spin-up and spin-down bands broaden and shift oppositely due to band dispersion effects, leading to a reduction in net magnetization. Simultaneously, the SOC contribution from FeI, which initially favors an out-of-plane easy axis, diminishes and ultimately changes sign, thereby promoting in-plane anisotropy. The SOC contribution from the outer-layer Te atoms also decreases steadily with pressure, although it retains its original sign; this additional reduction further reinforces the in-plane magnetic easy axis. In contrast, FeII atoms continue to favor an out-of-plane orientation, but their contribution is insufficient to counterbalance the dominant in-plane preference at high pressure. These findings elucidate the origin of magnetic easy-axis switching in Fe3GaTe2 and provide insights for tuning magnetic anisotropy in layered materials for spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00429v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiaqi Li, Shuyuan Liu, Chongze Wang, Fengzhu Ren, Bing Wang, Jun-Hyung Cho</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrotoroidicity: New Paradigm for Transverse Electromagnetic Responses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00462</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00462v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The exploration of transverse electromagnetic responses in solids with broken spatial-inversion (I) and/or time-reversal (T) symmetries has unveiled numerous captivating phenomena, including the (anomalous) Hall effect, Faraday rotations, non-reciprocal directional dichroism, and off-diagonal linear magnetoelectricity, all within the framework of magnetotoroidicity. Here, we introduce a novel class of transverse electromagnetic responses originating from electrotoroidicity in ferro-rotational (FR) systems with preserved I and T symmetries, distinct from magnetotoroidicity. We discover a high-order off-diagonal magnetic susceptibility of FR domains and a reduced linear diagonal magnetic susceptibility at FR domain walls in doped ilmenite FeTiO3. The non-trivial "Hall-like" effect of the former corresponds to an anomalous transverse susceptibility in the presence of spontaneous electrotoroidal moments in FR materials. Our findings unveil an emergent type of transverse electromagnetic responses even in I and T symmetry-conserved conditions and illustrate new functionalities of abundant FR materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00462v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kai Du, Daegeun Jo, Xianghan Xu, Fei-Ting Huang, Ming-Hao Lee, Ming-Wen Chu, Kefeng Wang, David Vanderbilt, Hyun-Woo Lee, Sang-Wook Cheong</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic networks as highways for holes in oxygen-deficient amorphous oxides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00473</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00473v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Oxygen-deficient amorphous tellurium oxides ($a$-TeO$_x$) have recently challenged the intrinsic hole mobility limits of amorphous oxides, with thin-film transistors reaching mobilities up to 15 cm$^{2}$V$^{-1}$s$^{-1}$ upon Se doping. However, the atomistic origins of this behavior, and its seeming contradiction with established semiconductor physics, have remained unresolved. Here, we combine machine-learning-accelerated ab initio molecular dynamics with hybrid-functional defect calculations to establish a new microscopic picture. We show that substantial oxygen loss drives spontaneous segregation into interpenetrating $a$-Te and $a$-TeO$_2$ domains, rather than forming dispersed oxygen vacancies. The diffuse Te-$5p$ states from the $a$-Te network supply percolative pathways for holes, so mobility rises monotonically with oxygen deficiency, enabling mobilities that exceed current records. Doped Se incorporates into the $a$-Te domain, enhancing the connectivity of conductive pathways, thereby increasing hole mobility. Similar behavior in amorphous SeO$_x$ suggests domain percolation as a general route to high-mobility p-type transport in amorphous oxides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00473v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafael Costa-Amaral, Yu Kumagai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital Altermagnetism</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00509</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00509v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We introduce the concept of \emph{orbital altermagnetism}, a symmetry-protected magnetic order of pure orbital degrees of freedom. It is characterized with ordered anti-parallel orbital magnetic moments in real space but momentum-dependent orbital band splittings, analogous to spin altermagnetism. Using a minimal tight-binding model with complex hoppings in a square-kagome lattice, we show that such order inherently arises from staggered loop currents, producing a $d$-wave-like orbital-momentum locking. First-principles calculations show that orbital altermagnetism emerges independent of spin ordering in in-plane ferromagnets of CuBr$_2$ and VS$_2$, so that it can be unambiguously identified experimentally. On the other hand, it may also coexist with spin altermagnetism, such as in monolayer MoO and CrO. The orbital altermagnetism offers an alternative platform for symmetry-driven magnetotransport and orbital-based spintronics, as exemplified by large nonlinear current-induced orbital magnetization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00509v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mingxiang Pan, Feng Liu, Huaqing Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning Prediction of Charged Defect Formation Energies from Crystal Structures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00513</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00513v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Recent advances in materials informatics have expanded the number of synthesizable materials. However, screening promising candidates, such as semiconductors, based on defect properties remains challenging. This is primarily due to the lack of a general framework for predicting defect formation energies in multiple charge states from structural data. In this Letter, we present a protocol, namely data normalization, Fermi level alignment, and treatment of perturbed host states, and validate it by accurately predicting oxygen vacancy formation energies in three charge states using a single model. We also introduce a joint machine-learning model that integrates defect formation energies and band-edge predictions for virtual screening. Using this framework, we identify 89 hole-dopable oxides, including BaGaSbO, a potential ambipolar photovoltaic material. Our protocol is expected to become a standard approach for machine-learning studies on point defect formation energies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00513v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shin Kiyohara, Chisa Shibui, Soungmin Bae, Yu Kumagai</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FourPhonon_GPU: A GPU-accelerated framework for calculating phonon scattering rates and thermal conductivity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00518</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00518v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurately predicting phonon scattering is crucial for understanding thermal transport properties. However, the computational cost of such calculations, especially for four-phonon scattering, can often be more prohibitive when large number of phonon branches and scattering processes are involved. In this work, we present FourPhonon_GPU, a GPU-accelerated framework for three-phonon and four-phonon scattering rate calculations based on the FourPhonon package. By leveraging OpenACC and adopting a heterogeneous CPU-GPU computing strategy, we efficiently offload massive, parallelizable tasks to the GPU while using the CPU for process enumeration and control-heavy operations. Our approach achieves over 25x acceleration for the scattering rate computation step and over 10x total runtime speedup without sacrificing accuracy. Benchmarking on various GPU architectures confirms the method's scalability and highlights the importance of aligning parallelization strategies with hardware capabilities. This work provides an efficient and accurate computational tool for phonon transport modeling and opens pathways for accelerated materials discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00518v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ziqi Guo, Xiulin Ruan, Guang Lin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possible evidence for Harper broadening in the yellow exciton series of Cu2O at ultrahigh magnetic fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00661</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00661v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hydrogen-like systems in ultra-high magnetic fields are of significant interest in interdisciplinary research. Previous studies have focused on the exciton wavefunction shrinkage under magnetic fields down to artificial crystal lattices (e.g., quantum wells, superlattices), where the effective mass approximation remains valid. However, further compression toward the natural crystal lattice scale remains experimentally challenging. In this study, we report magneto-absorption measurements on the yellow-exciton series in Cu2O using pulsed magnetic fields of up to 500 T. The strong low energy absorption features are assigned to the spin Zeeman split 2p0 and 3p0 exciton states. The high field data provides a value for the reduced effective mass of the exciton u* = 0.415 \pm 0.01me. Intriguingly, the broadening of the 2p0 ground state transition exhibits a sudden increase for ultrahigh magnetic fields above 300 T, providing possible evidence for Harper broadening - an indication of the breakdown of the effective mass approximation when the magnetic length becomes comparable to the lattice constant of the crystal.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00661v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhuo Yang, Jinbo Wang, Yuto Ishii, Duncan K. Maude, Atsuhiko Miyata, Yasuhiro H. Matsuda</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization Domain Mapping From 4D-STEM Using Deep Learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00693</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00693v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Polarization in ferroelectric domains arises from atomic-scale structural variations that govern macroscopic functionalities. The interfaces between these domains known as domain walls host distinct physical responses, making their identification and control critical. Four dimensional scanning transmission electron microscopy (4DSTEM) enables simultaneous acquisition of real and reciprocal-space information at the atomic scale, offering a powerful platform for domain mapping. However, conventional analyses rely on computationally intensive processing and manual interpretation, which are time consuming and prone to misalignment and diffraction artefacts. Here, we present a convolutional neural network that, with minimal training, classifies polarization directions from diffraction data and segments domains in real space. We further introduce an adaptive sampling strategy that prioritizes images from domain wall regions, reducing the number of training images required while improving accuracy and interpretability. We demonstrate this approach for domain mapping in ferroelectric boracite, Cu3B7O13Cl.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00693v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fintan G. Hardy, Sinead M. Griffin, Mariana Palos, Yaqi Li, Geri Topore, Aron Walsh, Michele Shelly Conroy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three-fold Superstructured Superlattice HfN/HfAlN Thin Films for Enhanced Toughness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00716</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00716v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To simultaneously achieve high hardness and high toughness in protective coatings remains a fundamental challenge. Here, we harness the superlattice architecture to combine Koehler hardening while the coherent interfaces reduce the crack driving force and improve toughness, enabling coatings that are both hard and damage tolerant. We design and fabricate epitaxial HfN$_{1.33}$/Hf$_{0.76}$Al$_{0.24}$N$_{1.15}$ superlattices, deposited on MgO(001) substrates using low-energy, high-flux ion-assisted reactive magnetron sputtering. These superlattices with bilayer periods ranging from 6 to 20 nm, exhibit a unique three-fold superstructure, confirmed by X-ray diffraction and reciprocal space mapping (RSM). Each constituent forms distinct 3D checkerboard superstructures, with a period of 7.5 {\AA} for HfN and 12.5 A for HfAlN. RSMs further reveal low mosaicity, high crystalline quality, and in-plane compressive strains, indicating well preserved coherence across interfaces. Mechanical testing shows that the superlattices maintain the high hardness of HfAlN (\~36 GPa) independent of bilayer period, while surpassing the softer HfN (~27 GPa), consistent with interface-driven Koehler strengthening. Micropillar compression shows brittle fracture on the {110}&lt;110&gt; system, yet with distributed cracking and faster mechanical recovery compared to monolithic films, suggesting improved toughness. Cube-corner indentation further corroborate this behavior, with pile-up and suppressed fracture events. These results demonstrate that epitaxial HfN/HfAlN superlattices uniquely combine high hardness with improved toughness, enabled by their three-fold superstructured architecture. Leveraging the intrinsic high-temperature stability of HfN-based materials, this design offers a robust pathway toward next-generation protective coatings capable of maintaining performance under extreme conditions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00716v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Lorentzon, R. Hahn, J. Palisaitis, H. Riedl, L. Hultman, J. Birch, N. Ghafoor</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Material Synthesis 2025 (MatSyn25) Dataset for 2D Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00776</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00776v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) materials have shown broad application prospects in fields such as energy, environment, and aerospace owing to their unique electrical, mechanical, thermal and other properties. With the development of artificial intelligence (AI), the discovery and design of novel 2D materials have been significantly accelerated. However, due to the lack of basic theories of material synthesis, identifying reliable synthesis processes for theoretically designed materials is a challenge. The emergence of large language model offers new approaches for the reliability prediction of material synthesis processes. However, its development is limited by the lack of publicly available datasets of material synthesis processes. To address this, we present the Material Synthesis 2025 (MatSyn25), a large-scale open dataset of 2D material synthesis processes. MatSyn25 contains 163,240 pieces of synthesis process information extracted from 85,160 high-quality research articles, each including basic material information and detailed synthesis process steps. Based on MatSyn25, we developed MatSyn AI which specializes in material synthesis, and provided an interactive web platform that enables multifaceted exploration of the dataset (https://matsynai.stpaper.cn/). MatSyn25 is publicly available, allowing the research community to build upon our work and further advance AI-assisted materials science.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00776v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chengbo Li, Ying Wang, Qianying Wang, Zhizhi Tan, Haiqing Jia, Yi Liu, Li Qian, Nian Ran, Jianjun Liu, Zhixiong Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning Difference Charge Density</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00788</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00788v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In density functional theory (DFT), the ground state charge density is the fundamental variable which determines all other ground state properties. Many machine learning charge density models are developed by prior efforts, which have been proven useful to accelerate DFT calculations. Yet they all use the total charge density (TCD) as the training target. In this work, we advocate predicting difference charge density (DCD) instead. We term this simple technique by $\Delta$-SAED, which leverages the prior physical information of superposition of atomic electron densities (SAED). The robustness of $\Delta$-SAED is demonstrated through evaluations over diverse benchmark datasets, showing an extra accuracy gain for more than 90% structures in the test sets. Using a Si allotropy dataset, $\Delta$-SAED is demonstrated to advance model's transferability to chemical accuracy for non-self-consistent calculations. By incorporating physical priors to compensate for the limited expressive power of machine learning models, $\Delta$-SAED offers a cost-free yet robust approach to improving charge density prediction and enhancing non-self-consistent performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00788v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiwen Li, LiangLiang Hong, Yingwei Chen, Hongjun Xiang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orbital-Engineered Spin Asymmetry and Multifunctionality in Eu-Activated CaAlSiN$_3$: A First-Principles Roadmap to Optical-Thermoelectric Fusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00863</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00863v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Rare-earth-doped nitride phosphors are promising materials for solid-state lighting and photonic applications due to their thermal stability, sharp emission lines, and strong UV-blue absorption. In this work, we present a first-principles density functional theory (DFT) study, using the GGA+U approach, of pristine and Eu3+-doped CaAlSiN3 at doping levels of 8.5% and 17%. Electronic structure calculations show that Eu incorporation introduces localized 4f states within the band gap, leading to band-gap narrowing and enabling red photoluminescence through the 5D0 -&gt; 7F2 transition. Spin-polarized density of states and spin density mapping confirm the magnetic nature of Eu3+, while charge density, Bader analysis, and electron localization function (ELF) indicate mixed ionic-covalent bonding and charge transfer from Eu to neighboring N and Al atoms, stabilizing the doped lattice. Optical spectra, including dielectric function, absorption, refractive index, and reflectivity, reveal red-shifted absorption edges and enhanced visible-range light-matter interactions, consistent with experimental red to near-infrared emission. Formation energy analysis confirms the thermodynamic feasibility of Eu substitution, while elastic constants and Pugh's ratio indicate mechanical robustness and ductility. Thermoelectric transport properties, obtained using WIEN2k and BoltzTraP, suggest that moderate Eu3+ doping improves the power factor and reduces lattice thermal conductivity through disorder scattering. These results establish Eu-doped CaAlSiN3 as a stable and efficient red-emitting phosphor for white light-emitting diodes (WLEDs) and provide theoretical insights for crystal site engineering in advanced optoelectronic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00863v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Tayyab, Faiq Umar, Sikander Azam, Qaiser Rafiq, Rajwali Khan, Muhammad Tahir Khan, Vineet Tirth, Ali Algahtani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Determining the Density of In-gap States in Organic Semiconductors: A Pitfall of Photoelectron Yield Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00865</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00865v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accurate determination of electronic states with low density in the bandgap (in-gap states) is crucial for understanding and optimizing the performance of organic optoelectronic devices. In the device research field, photoelectron yield spectroscopy (PYS) has been widely used to evaluate such states, and its derivative is commonly employed to estimate the density of states (DOS). However, low-energy photons in PYS can generate excitons and anions in organic semiconductors, raising questions about whether derivative PYS spectra truly represent the DOS. Here, we applied hv-dependent high-sensitivity ultraviolet photoelectron spectroscopy with low-energy photons to probe the origin of photoelectrons in organic semiconductors. We show that PYS signals arise from the single-quantum external photoelectron effect (SQEPE) of in-gap states, from SQEPE of the singly occupied molecular orbital (SOMO) in anions, and biphotonic electron emission (BEE) effect via exciton fusions. Because the BEE signal masks the DOS, derivative PYS can misestimate the DOS of in-gap states. In contrast, constant final state yield spectroscopy (CFS-YS) can reliably determine the DOS. For example, in Tris(8-hydroxyquinoline) aluminum (Alq3), we observed BEE, and CFS-YS revealed the DOS of in-gap states and SOMO over six orders of magnitude. The direct determination of the SOMO DOS allowed us to clarify the role of Alq3 in the electron injection layer in organic light-emitting diodes. Moreover, the BEE process can act as both a carrier-generation and degradation pathway in organic optoelectronic devices. These findings demonstrate that CFS-YS provides a reliable method to determine the DOS of in-gap states and to probe exciton and/or anion interactions. We establish practical guidelines for determining the DOS of in-gap states for low-energy photon measurements, such as examining photon-flux dependence.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00865v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ryotaro Nakazawa, Masaya Kitaoka, Ryota Kaimori, Manato Tateno, Runa Hoshikawa, Yuya Tanaka, Hisao Ishii</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exploring Chalcogen Influence on Sc2BeX4 (X = S, Se) for Green Energy Applications Using DFT</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00955</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00955v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a first-principles density functional theory study of the structural, electronic, optical, and thermoelectric properties of Sc2BeX4 (X = S, Se) chalcogenides for energy applications. Both compounds are dynamically and thermodynamically stable, exhibiting negative formation energies of -2.6 eV (Sc2BeS4) and -2.2 eV (Sc2BeSe4). They feature direct band gaps of 1.8 eV and 1.2 eV, respectively, within the TB-mBJ approximation, indicating strong visible-light absorption. Optical analysis reveals high static dielectric constants (9.0 for S and 16.5 for Se), absorption peaks near 13.5 eV, and reflectivity below 30 percent. Thermoelectric calculations predict p-type conduction with Seebeck coefficients reaching 2.5e-4 V/K and electrical conductivities of 2.45e18 and 1.91e18 (Ohm m s)^-1 at 300 K. Power factors approach 1.25e11 W/K^2 m s, with a maximum dimensionless figure of merit (ZT) of 0.80 at 800 K. Calculated Debye temperatures (420 K for Sc2BeS4 and 360 K for Sc2BeSe4) imply low lattice thermal conductivity. These findings establish Sc2BeX4 chalcogenides as promising materials for photovoltaic and thermoelectric applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00955v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ahmad Ali, Haris Haider, Sikander Azam, Muhammad Talha, Muhammad Jawad, Imran Shakir</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Deterministic Detection of Single Ion Implantation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01035</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01035v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Single ion implantation using focused ion beam systems enables high spatial resolution and maskless doping for rapid and scalable engineering of materials for quantum technologies, particularly qubits and colour centres in solid-state hosts. In such applications, the confidence with which a single ion can be deterministically implanted is crucial, and so the efficiency of the detection mechanism is a vital parameter. Here, we present a study of the single-ion detection efficiency for a variety of ion species (Si, P, Mn, Co, Ge, Sb, Au and Bi) into various hosts (Si, SiO2, Al2O3, GaAs, diamond and SiC). The effect of varying ion mass, charge and kinetic energy are studied, in addition to the cluster implantation of Sb, Au and Bi. We demonstrate that it is possible to achieve detection efficiencies &gt;90% for a wide range of ion species and substrate combination through selection of the implantation parameters. Furthermore, detection efficiencies of 100% are found for the doping of Sb clusters which is of direct relevance for the future fabrication of quantum devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01035v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mason Adshead, Lok Kan Wan, Maddison Coke, Richard J Curry</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Pressure DFT Study of BeX (X = S, Se, Te): Phonon Spectra, Optical Properties, and Thermodynamic Stability for Advanced Optoelectronic Applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01056</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01056v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present a comprehensive first-principles investigation of the structural, electronic, optical, and thermodynamic properties of BeX compounds (X = S, Se, Te) under hydrostatic pressures ranging from 0 to 10 GPa. Calculations were performed using density functional theory (DFT) within the Generalized Gradient Approximation (GGA) using the Perdew-Burke-Ernzerhof (PBE) functional, as implemented in the CASTEP code. Phonon dispersion analyses confirm the dynamical stability of all compounds across the studied pressure range, as indicated by the absence of imaginary frequencies throughout the Brillouin zone. The electronic band structure reveals pressure-induced band modifications, with BeS retaining the widest bandgap. Optical properties, including the dielectric function, absorption coefficient, reflectivity, and energy loss spectra, were computed for photon energies up to 30 eV. The materials exhibit strong optical absorption in the ultraviolet region, suggesting potential for UV optoelectronic applications. Thermodynamic parameters such as Debye temperature, heat capacity, and entropy were evaluated, showing pressure-dependent trends. Notably, increasing pressure leads to reduced atomic vibrations and heat capacity, while the Gibbs free energy exhibits a consistent slope with temperature, reflecting entropy variation. These results highlight the suitability of BeX compounds for pressure-sensitive optoelectronic and thermoelectric devices, as well as thermal barrier applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01056v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Shahzad, Sikander Azam, Syed Awais Ahmad, Ming Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>exa-AMD: An Exascale-Ready Framework for Accelerating the Discovery and Design of Functional Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01170</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01170v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Exascale computing is transforming the field of materials science by enabling simulations of unprecedented scale and complexity. We present exa-AMD, an open-source, high-performance simulation code specifically designed for accelerated materials discovery on modern supercomputers. exa-AMD addresses the computational challenges inherent in large-scale materials discovery by employing task-based parallelization strategies and optimized data management tailored for high performance computers. The code features a modular design, supports both distributed and on-node parallelism, and is designed for flexibility and extensibility to accommodate a wide range of materials science applications. We detail the underlying algorithms and implementation, and provide comprehensive benchmark results demonstrating strong scaling across multiple high performance computing platforms. We provide two example applications, the design of Fe-Co-Zr and Na-B-C compounds, to illustrate the code's effectiveness in accelerating the discovery and characterization of novel materials. With only a set of elements as input, exa-AMD automates the workflow on CPU or GPU-enabled clusters, outputs the structures and energies of promising candidates, and updates the phase diagram. exa-AMD is publicly available on GitHub, with detailed documentation and reproducible test cases to support community engagement and collaborative research. This work aims to advance materials science by providing a robust, efficient, and extensible tool ready for exascale platforms.ady for exascale platforms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01170v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiyi Xiaa, Maxim Moraru, Ying Wai Li, Cai-Zhuang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>BigBang-Proton Technical Report: Next-Word-Prediction is Scientific Multitask Learner</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00129</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00129v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We introduce BigBang-Proton, a unified sequence-based architecture for auto-regressive language modeling pretrained on cross-scale, cross-structure, cross-discipline real-world scientific tasks to construct a scientific multi-task learner. BigBang-Proton incorporates three fundamental innovations compared to mainstream general-purpose LLMs: Theory-Experiment Learning paradigm aligns large-scale numerical experimental data with theoretical text corpora; Binary Patch Encoding replaces byte pair encoding(BPE) tokenization; Monte Carlo Attention substitutes traditional transformer architectures. Through next-word-prediction pretraining on cross-discipline scientific datasets of real-world problems mixed with general textual corpus, followed by fine-tuning and inference on downstream tasks, BigBang-Proton demonstrates 100\% accuracy in up to 50-digit arithmetic addition operations, performance on par with leading specialized models in particle physics jet tagging, matching MAE of specialized models in inter-atomic potential simulation, performance comparable to traditional spatiotemporal models in water quality prediction, and benchmark-exceeding performance in genome modeling. These results prove that language-guided scientific computing can match or exceed the performance of task-specific scientific models while maintaining multitask learning capabilities. We further hypothesize to scale the pretraining to the universe scale as a fundamental step toward developing material world foundational model.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00129v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hengkui Wu, Liujiang Liu, Jihua He, Qihao Wang, Keke Zhao, Shuyang Hu, Renle Fu, Dahao Liang, Lingyu Zeng, Bruce Liu, Yuan Liu, Jin Zhan, Jiaqiang Niu, Xinglong Jia, Yaqin Hu, Wenjun Ji, Panpan Chi, Ken Chen, Hengyuan Wu, Yingsi Xin, Yongfeng Zhu, Yuexin Wang, Manqi Ruan, Ningtao Bian, Xiaohua Wu, Weipeng Xu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning from the electronic structure of molecules across the periodic table</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00224</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00224v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Machine-Learned Interatomic Potentials (MLIPs) require vast amounts of atomic structure data to learn forces and energies, and their performance continues to improve with training set size. Meanwhile, the even greater quantities of accompanying data in the Hamiltonian matrix H behind these datasets has so far gone unused for this purpose. Here, we provide a recipe for integrating the orbital interaction data within H towards training pipelines for atomic-level properties. We first introduce HELM ("Hamiltonian-trained Electronic-structure Learning for Molecules"), a state-of-the-art Hamiltonian prediction model which bridges the gap between Hamiltonian prediction and universal MLIPs by scaling to H of structures with 100+ atoms, high elemental diversity, and large basis sets including diffuse functions. To accompany HELM, we release a curated Hamiltonian matrix dataset, 'OMol_CSH_58k', with unprecedented elemental diversity (58 elements), molecular size (up to 150 atoms), and basis set (def2-TZVPD). Finally, we introduce 'Hamiltonian pretraining' as a method to extract meaningful descriptors of atomic environments even from a limited number atomic structures, and repurpose this shared embedding space to improve performance on energy-prediction in low-data regimes. Our results highlight the use of electronic interactions as a rich and transferable data source for representing chemical space.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00224v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Manasa Kaniselvan, Benjamin Kurt Miller, Meng Gao, Juno Nam, Daniel S. Levine</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reward driven discovery of the optimal microstructure representations with invariant variational autoencoders</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00243v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Microscopy techniques generate vast amounts of complex image data that in principle can be used to discover simpler, interpretable, and parsimonious forms to reveal the underlying physical structures, such as elementary building blocks in molecular systems or order parameters and phases in crystalline materials. Variational Autoencoders (VAEs) provide a powerful means of constructing such low-dimensional representations, but their performance heavily depends on multiple non-myopic design choices, which are often optimized through trial-and-error and empirical analysis. To enable automated and unbiased optimization of VAE workflows, we investigated reward-based strategies for evaluating latent space representations. Using Piezoresponse Force Microscopy data as a model system, we examined multiple policies and reward functions that can serve as a foundation for automated optimization. Our analysis shows that approximating the latent space with Gaussian Mixture Models (GMM) and Bayesian Gaussian Mixture Models (BGMM) provides a strong basis for constructing reward functions capable of estimating model efficiency and guiding the search for optimal parsimonious representations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00243v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Boris N. Slautin, Kamyar Barakati, Hiroshi Funakubo, Maxim A. Ziatdinov, Vladimir V. Shvartsman, Doru C. Lupascu, Sergei V. Kalinin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A poor man's theory of circular dichroism in single-wall carbon nanotubes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00385v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The theory of circular dichroism in single-wall carbon nanotubes derived within the tight-binding method by a complicated approach in previous work is rederived in a straightforward way using the multipolar expansion of the light-matter interaction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00385v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. V. Goupalov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Possibility of ferro-octupolar order in Ba$_2$CaOsO$_6$ assessed by X-ray magnetic dichroism measurements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00448</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00448v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Localized $5d^2$ electrons in a cubic crystal field possess multipoles such as electric quadrupoles and magnetic octupoles. We studied the cubic double perovskite Ba$_2$CaOsO$_6$ containing the Os$^{6+}$ ($5d^2$) ions, which exhibits a phase transition to a `hidden order' below $T^* \sim$ 50 K, by X-ray absorption spectroscopy (XAS) and X-ray magnetic circular dichroism (XMCD) at the Os $L_{2,3}$ edge. The cubic ligand-field splitting between the $t_{2g}$ and $e_g$ levels of Os $5d$ was deduced by XAS to be $\sim$4 eV. The temperature dependence of the XMCD spectra was consistent with a $\sim$18 meV residual cubic splitting of the lowest $J_{\rm eff} =$ 2 multiplet state into the non-Kramers $E_g$ doublet ground state and the $T_{2g}$ triplet excited state. Ligand-field (LF) multiplet calculation under fictitious strong magnetic fields indicated that the exchange interaction between nearest-neighbor octupoles should be as strong as $\sim$1.5 meV if a ferro-octupole order is stabilized in the `hidden-ordered' state, consistent with the exchange interaction of $\sim$1 meV previously predicted theoretically using model and density functional theory calculations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00448v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Goro Shibata, Naomi Kawamura, Jun Okamoto, Arata Tanaka, Hiroaki Hayashi, Kazunari Yamaura, Hsiao-Yu Huang, Amol Singh, Chien-Te Chen, Di-Jing Huang, Sergey V. Streltsov, Atsushi Fujimori</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excitons and Optical Response in Excitonic Insulator Candidate TiSe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00556</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00556v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The origin of the charge density wave (CDW) phase in TiSe$_2$ is a highly debated topic, with lattice and excitonic correlations proposed as the main driving mechanisms. One of the proposed scenarios is the excitonic insulator (EI) mechanism, where soft electronic mode drives the phase transition. However, the existence of this purely electronic mode is controversial. Here, we perform fully ab-initio calculations of the electron excitation spectra in TiSe$_2$ with electron-hole excitonic effects included via Bethe-Salpeter equations. In the normal high-temperature phase the excitation spectra is dominated by the exciton mode at 1.6 eV, while no well-defined soft electronic modes that could support the EI phase are present. In the CDW phase, the structural distortions induce a CDW band-gap opening between Ti-$d$ and Se-$p$ states, which supports the formation of the two low-energy excitonic modes in the optical spectrum at 0.4 eV and 80 meV. Close to the transition temperature $T_{\rm CDW}$, these two excitonic modes are softened and approach zero energy. These results suggest that the EI mechanism is not a main driving force in the formation of the CDW phase in TiSe$_2$, but there is a region in the phase diagram near $T_{\rm CDW}$ where EI fluctuations could be relevant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00556v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dino Novko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature Dependence of the Response Functions of Graphene: Impact on Casimir and Casimi-Polder Forces in and out of Thermal Equilibrium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00672</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00672v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We review and obtain some new results on the temperature dependence of spatially nonlocal response functions of graphene and their applications to calculation of both the equilibrium and nonequilibrium Casimir and Casimir-Polder forces. After a brief summary of the properties of the polarization tensor of graphene obtained within Dirac model in the framework of quantum field theory, we derive the expressions for the longitudinal and transverse dielectric functions. The behavior of these functions at different temperatures is investigated in the regions below and above the threshold. Special attention is paid to the double pole at zero frequency which is present in the transverse response function of graphene. An application of the response functions of graphene to calculation of the equilibrium Casimir force between two graphene sheets and Casimir-Polder forces between an atom (nanoparticle) and a graphene sheet is considered with due attention to the role of a nonzero energy gap, chemical potential and a material substrate underlying the graphene sheet. The same subject is discussed for out-of-thermal-equilibrium Casimir and Casimir-Polder forces. The role of the obtained and presented results for fundamental science and nanotechnology is outlined.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00672v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/physics7040044</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physivs, v.7, N4, 44 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>G. L. Klimchitskaya, V. M. Mostepanenko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Altermagnetism of ultrathin CrSb slabs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.00985</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.00985v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Altermagnets exhibit momentum-dependent spin splitting without net magnetization, combining characteristics of both ferromagnets and antiferromagnets, making them highly interesting for spintronics applications. CrSb is a prime candidate with a high N\'eel temperature ($\sim700$~K) and a large exchange-driven splitting of $\sim0.6$--1~eV. Using ab-initio calculations, we consider slabs of various orientations in the ultrathin limit. We find that (100) oriented slabs have spin-degenerate bands. In (0001) oriented slabs, the exchange-driven altermagnetic spin splitting collapses, but including spin-orbit coupling restores a residual anisotropic splitting of $\sim70$~meV. In contrast, the (110) oriented slabs show an altermagnetic spin splitting of $\sim400$~meV, and emerges as a robust candidate for realizing large, exchange-driven altermagnetism</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.00985v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Brahim Marfoua, Mohammad Amirabbasi, Marcus Ekholm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sequential Bayesian Inference of the GTN Damage Model Using Multimodal Experimental Data</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01016v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Reliable parameter identification in ductile damage models remains challenging because the salient physics of damage progression are localized to small regions in material responses, and their signatures are often diluted in specimen-level measurements. Here, we propose a sequential Bayesian Inference (BI) framework for the calibration of the Gurson-Tvergaard-Needleman (GTN) model using multimodal experimental data (i.e., the specimen-level force-displacement (F-D) measurements and the spatially resolved digital image correlation (DIC) strain fields). This calibration approach builds on a previously developed two-step BI framework that first establishes a low-computational-cost emulator for a physics-based simulator (here, a finite element model incorporating the GTN material model) and then uses the experimental data to sample posteriors for the material model parameters using the Transitional Markov Chain Monte Carlo (T-MCMC). A central challenge to the successful application of this BI framework to the present problem arises from the high-dimensional representations needed to capture the salient features embedded in the F-D curves and the DIC fields. In this paper, it is demonstrated that Principal Component Analysis (PCA) provides low-dimensional representations that make it possible to apply the BI framework to the problem. Most importantly, it is shown that the sequence in which the BI is applied has a dramatic influence on the results obtained. Specifically, it is observed that applying BI first on F-D curves and subsequently on the DIC fields produces improved estimates of the GTN parameters. Possible causes for these observations are discussed in this paper, using AA6111 aluminum alloy as a case study.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01016v1</guid>
      <category>stat.CO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammad Ali Seyed Mahmoud, Dominic Renner, Ali Khosravani, Surya R. Kalidindi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Macro-Dipole-Constrainted Learning of Atomic Charges for Accurate Electrostatic Potentials at Electrochemical Interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01042</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01042v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Large thermal fluctuations of the liquid phase obscure the weak macroscopic electric field that drives electrochemical reactions, rendering the extraction of reliable interfacial charge distributions from ab initio molecular dynamics extremely challenging. We introduce SMILE-CP (Scalar Macro-dipole Integrated LEarning - Charge Partitioning), a macro-dipole-constrained scheme that infers atomic charges using only the instantaneous atomic coordinates and the total dipole moment of the simulation cell - quantities routinely available from standard density-functional theory calculations. SMILE-CP preserves both the global electrostatic field and the local potential without invoking any explicit charge-partitioning scheme. Benchmarks on three representative electrochemical interfaces - nanoconfined water, Mg2+ dissolution in water, and a kinked Mg vicinal surface under anodic bias - show that SMILE-CP eliminates the qualitative errors observed for unconstrained charge decompositions. The method is computationally inexpensive and data-efficient, opening the door to charge-aware machine-learning potentials capable of bias-controlled, nanosecond-scale simulations of realistic electrochemical systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01042v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jing Yang, Bingxin Li, Samuel Mattoso, Ahmed Abdelkawy, Mira Todorova, J\"org Neugebauer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-Hermitian Dynamics in Quantum Anomalous Hall Insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.01125</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.01125v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnetically doped topological insulators (TIs) exhibit two distinct phases: the quantum anomalous Hall (QAH) phase when the Fermi level resides within the surface gap, and a metallic phase outside the gap. The QAH phase hosts unidirectional transport channels known as chiral edge states, while the metallic phase exhibits non-reciprocal transport due to unbalanced bidirectional edge states. Utilizing the chiral edge states in Cr-doped (Bi, Sb)2Te3 sandwich structures, we realize non-Hermitian conductance matrices in a one-dimensional Corbino chain with well-defined chirality. By tuning the boundary conditions from open to periodic, we reveal the non-Hermitian skin effect, where eigenstates localize exponentially at one end of the chain. In the metallic phase, we further observe asymmetric, bidirectional coupling between the neighboring sites in the conductance matrix, a direct consequence of the system's intrinsic non-reciprocity. These results establish magnetic TIs as a powerful platform for investigating emergent non-Hermitian phenomena in topological systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.01125v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Le Yi, Emma Steinebronn, Asmaul Smitha Rashid, Nitin Samarth, Ramy El-Ganainy, Sahin L. Ozdemir, Morteza Kayyalha</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Graph Transformer Networks for Accurate Band Structure Prediction: An End-to-End Approach</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.16483</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.16483v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Predicting electronic band structures from crystal structures is crucial for understanding structure-property correlations in materials science. First-principles approaches are accurate but computationally intensive. Recent years, machine learning (ML) has been extensively applied to this field, while existing ML models predominantly focus on band gap predictions or indirect band structure estimation via solving predicted Hamiltonians. An end-to-end model to predict band structure accurately and efficiently is still lacking. Here, we introduce a graph Transformer-based end-to-end approach that directly predicts band structures from crystal structures with high accuracy. Our method leverages the continuity of the k-path and treat continuous bands as a sequence. We demonstrate that our model not only provides accurate band structure predictions but also can derive other properties (such as band gap, band center, and band dispersion) with high accuracy. We verify the model performance on large and diverse datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.16483v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiyi Gong, Tao Sun, Hexin Bai, Jeng-Yuan Tsai, Haibin Ling, Qimin Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>OBELiX: A Curated Dataset of Crystal Structures and Experimentally Measured Ionic Conductivities for Lithium Solid-State Electrolytes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14234v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Solid-state electrolyte batteries are expected to replace liquid electrolyte lithium-ion batteries in the near future thanks to their higher theoretical energy density and improved safety. However, their adoption is currently hindered by their lower effective ionic conductivity, a quantity that governs charge and discharge rates. Identifying highly ion-conductive materials using conventional theoretical calculations and experimental validation is both time-consuming and resource-intensive. While machine learning holds the promise to expedite this process, relevant ionic conductivity and structural data is scarce. Here, we present OBELiX, a database of $\sim$600 synthesized solid electrolyte materials and their experimentally measured room temperature ionic conductivities gathered from literature and curated by domain experts. Each material is described by their measured composition, space group and lattice parameters. A full-crystal description in the form of a crystallographic information file (CIF) is provided for $\sim$320 structures for which atomic positions were available. We discuss various statistics and features of the dataset and provide training and testing splits carefully designed to avoid data leakage. Finally, we benchmark seven existing ML models on the task of predicting ionic conductivity and discuss their performance. The goal of this work is to facilitate the use of machine learning for solid-state electrolyte materials discovery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14234v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>F\'elix Therrien, Jamal Abou Haibeh, Divya Sharma, Rhiannon Hendley, Leah Wairimu Mungai, Sun Sun, Alain Tchagang, Jiang Su, Samuel Huberman, Yoshua Bengio, Hongyu Guo, Alex Hern\'andez-Garc\'ia, Homin Shin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Extremely high excitonic $g$-factors in 2D crystals by alloy-induced admixing of band states</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.23071</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.23071v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Monolayers (MLs) of semiconducting transition metal dichalcogenides (\mbox{S-TMDs}) emit light very efficiently and display rich spin-valley physics, with gyromagnetic ($g$-) factors of about -4. Here, we investigate how these properties can be tailored by alloying. Magneto-optical spectroscopy is used to reveal the peculiar properties of excitonic complexes in Mo$_{x}$W$_{1-x}$Se$_2$ MLs with different Mo and W concentrations. We show that the alloys feature extremely high $g$-factors for neutral excitons, that change gradually with the composition up to reaching values of the order of -10 for $x \approx 0.2$. First-principles calculations corroborate the experimental findings and provide evidence that alloying in S-TMDs results in a non-trivial band structure engineering, being at the origin of the high $g$-factors. The theoretical framework also suggests a higher strain sensitivity of the alloys, making them promising candidates for tailor-made optoelectronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.23071v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katarzyna Olkowska-Pucko, Tomasz Wo\'zniak, Elena Blundo, Natalia Zawadzka, {\L}ucja Kipczak, Paulo E. Faria Junior, Jan Szpakowski, Grzegorz Krasucki, Salvatore Cianci, Diana Vaclavkova, Dipankar Jana, Piotr Kapu\'sci\'nski, Amit Pawbake, Shalini Badola, Magdalena Grzeszczyk, Daniele Cecchetti, Giorgio Pettinari, Igor Antoniazzi, Zden\v{e}k Sofer, Iva Plutnarov\'a, Kenji Watanabe, Takashi Taniguchi, Clement Faugeras, Marek Potemski, Adam Babi\'nski, Antonio Polimeni, Maciej R. Molas</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning simple heuristic rules for classifying materials based on chemical composition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.02361</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.02361v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In the past decade, there has been a significant interest in the use of machine learning approaches in materials science research. Conventional deep learning approaches that rely on complex, nonlinear models have become increasingly important in computational materials science due to their high predictive accuracy. In contrast to these approaches, we have shown in a recent work that a remarkably simple learned heuristic rule -- based on the concept of topogivity -- can classify whether a material is topological using only its chemical composition. In this paper, we go beyond the topology classification scenario by also studying the use of machine learning to develop simple heuristic rules for classifying whether a material is a metal based on chemical composition. Moreover, we present a framework for incorporating chemistry-informed inductive bias based on the structure of the periodic table. For both the topology classification and the metallicity classification tasks, we empirically characterize the performance of simple heuristic rules fit with and without chemistry-informed inductive bias across a wide range of training set sizes. We find evidence that incorporating chemistry-informed inductive bias can reduce the amount of training data required to reach a given level of test accuracy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.02361v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrew Ma, Marin Solja\v{c}i\'c</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Defect analysis of the $\beta$- to $\gamma$-Ga$_{2}$O$_{3}$ phase transition</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.03541</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.03541v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this study, we investigate the ion-irradiation-induced phase transition in gallium oxide (Ga2O3) from the $\beta$ to the $\gamma$ phase, the role of defects during the transformation, and the quality of the resulting crystal structure. Using a multi-method analysis approach including X-ray diffraction (XRD), transmission electron microscopy (TEM), Rutherford backscattering spectrometry in channeling mode (RBS/c), Doppler broadening variable energy positron annihilation spectroscopy (DB-VEPAS) and variable energy positron annihilation lifetime spectroscopy (VEPALS) supported by density functional theory (DFT) calculations, we have characterized defects at all the relevant stages before, during, and after the phase transition. Reduction in backscattering yield was observed in RBS/c spectra after the transition to the $\gamma$ phase. This is corroborated by a significant decrease in the positron trapping center density due to generation of embedded vacancies intrinsic for the $\gamma$-Ga2O3 but too shallow in order to trap positrons. A comparison of the observed positron lifetime of $\gamma$-Ga2O3 with different theoretical models shows good agreement with the three-site $\gamma$ phase approach. A characteristic increase in the effective positron diffusion length and the positron lifetime at the transition point from $\beta$-Ga2O3 to $\gamma$-Ga2O3 enables visualization of the phase transition with positrons for the first time. Moreover, a subsequent reduction of these quantities with increasing irradiation fluence was observed, which we attribute to further evolution of the $\gamma$-Ga2O3 and changes in the gallium vacancy density as well as relative occupation in the crystal lattice.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.03541v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Umutcan Bektas, Maciej O. Liedke, Huan Liu, Fabian Ganss, Maik Butterling, Nico Klingner, Ren\'e H\"ubner, Ilja Makkonen, Andreas Wagner, Gregor Hlawacek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Analytical model for the remote epitaxial potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.09913</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.09913v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We propose an analytical model for the remote bonding potential of the substrate that permeates through graphene during remote epitaxy. Our model, based on a Morse interatomic potential, includes the attenuation due to the increased film-substrate separation and due to graphene free carrier screening. Compared with previous slab density functional theory calculations, which use the electrostatic potential as a proxy for bonding, our analytical model includes covalent and van der Waals bonding interactions, includes screening (which is often ignored), and is based on simple, physically interpretable, and well benchmarked parameters that build understanding. We show that for typical graphene free carrier concentrations of order $10^{12}$ cm$^{-2}$, the magnitude of $|\phi_{remote}|$ for most semiconductor and oxide substrates is few to tens of meV, similar to the van der Waals potential of graphene. This suggests interference between the graphene and remote substrate potentials must be considered when interpreting experiments on remote epitaxy. Furthermore, we show that (1) the strength of the remote potential is tunable by screening (graphene carrier density), (2) the remote potential is vanishingly weak through two or more graphene layers, (3) the spatial extent of the potential, rather than degree of ionicity, controls the strength of the permeated bonding potential. Our model provides a simple framework for benchmarking direct measurements of the remote epitaxial potential, and we propose several experimental paths to measure this quantity. De-convolving the effects of the native remote potential, graphene defects, and tunable growth kinetics is key to understanding and tuning the mechanisms of remote epitaxy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.09913v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jason K Kawasaki, Quinn T Campbell</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab-initio exploration of Gd monolayer interfaced with WSe$_2$: from electronic and magnetic properties to the anomalous Hall effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.15583</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.15583v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Heterostructures involving transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs) have attracted significant research interest due to the richness and versatility of the underlying physical phenomena. In this work, we investigate a heterostructure consisting of a rare-earth material, specifically a Gd monolayer, interfaced with WSe$_2$. We explore its electronic structure, magnetic properties, and transport behavior, with particular emphasis on the emergence of the anomalous Hall effect (AHE). Both Gd and W are heavy elements, providing strong spin-orbit coupling (SOC), which plays a crucial role in triggering the AHE. The combination of strong SOC and inversion symmetry breaking leads to pronounced asymmetries between the $\Gamma-K$ and $\Gamma-K^\prime$ directions in the Brillouin zone. Our calculations reveal a substantial anomalous Hall conductivity (AHC) at the ferromagnetic interface, primarily originating from numerous avoided crossings involving the d-states of both Gd and W near the Fermi level. Moreover, we demonstrate that the AHC is highly tunable, either by adjusting the in-plane lattice constant or by reducing the separation between Gd and WSe$_2$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.15583v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1088/1361-648X/ae0dd4</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Lyes Mesbahi (Laboratoire de Physique et Chimie Quantique), Omar Messaoudi (Laboratoire de Physique et Chimie Quantique), Hamid Bouzar (Laboratoire de Physique et Chimie Quantique), Samir Lounis (Institute of Physics, Martin-Luther-University Halle-Wittenberg, Halle)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetocaloric effect in Tb$_{31}$Co$_{69}$ and Dy$_{31}$Co$_{69}$ thin films deposited on Si substrates</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.23555</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.23555v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We present the structural, magnetic, and magnetocaloric properties of thin films with stoichiometry Tb$_{31}$Co$_{69}$ and Dy$_{31}$Co$_{69}$ deposited on naturally oxidized silicon Si (100) substrates. Samples with a thickness $d=50$ nm covered with a protective Au overlayer with a thickness $d_{\rm Au} =5 $ nm were produced using the pulsed laser deposition technique. X-ray diffraction analysis indicated the presence of crystallized Laves phases and amorphous phases in the prepared materials. Magnetization measurements as a function of temperature revealed ferrimagnetic behavior in both samples. We estimated the compensation temperature $T_{\rm comp}$ of the amorphous phase for Tb$_{31}$Co$_{69}$ at 81.5 K and for Dy$_{31}$Co$_{69}$ at 88.5 K, while we found the Curie temperature $T_{\rm C,\ Laves}$ of the crystallized Laves phases at 204.5 K and at 117 K, respectively. We investigated the magnetocaloric effect in a wide temperature range, covering $T_{\rm comp}$ of amorphous phases and $T_{\rm C,\ Laves}$ of crystallized Laves phases. The analysis for the magnetic field change of $\Delta \mu_0H=5$ T showed values of the magnetic entropy change of $-\Delta S_{\rm M}=4.9$ mJ cm$^{-3}$ K$^{-1}$ at $T_{\rm comp}$ and $-\Delta S_{\rm M}=6.6$ mJ cm$^{-3}$ K$^{-1}$ at $T_{\rm C,\ Laves}$ for Tb$_{31}$Co$_{69}$, while for Dy$_{31}$Co$_{69}$, we determined the values of $-\Delta S_{\rm M}=35$ mJ cm$^{-3}$ K$^{-1}$ at $T_{\rm comp}$ and $-\Delta S_{\rm M}=28$ mJ cm$^{-3}$ K$^{-1}$ at $T_{\rm C,\ Laves}$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.23555v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Skokowski (Institute of Molecular Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences, Pozna\'n, Poland), M. Matczak (Institute of Molecular Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences, Pozna\'n, Poland), {\L}. Fr\k{a}ckowiak (Institute of Molecular Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences, Pozna\'n, Poland), T. Bednarchuk (Institute of Low Temperatures and Structural Research, Polish Academy of Sciences, Wroc{\l}aw, Poland), M. Kowacz (Institute of Molecular Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences, Pozna\'n, Poland), B. Anastaziak (Institute of Molecular Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences, Pozna\'n, Poland, NanoBioMedical Centre, Adam Mickiewicz University, Pozna\'n, Poland), K. Synoradzki (Institute of Molecular Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences, Pozna\'n, Poland)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dislocation Transmission Across Tilt Low-Angle Grain Boundaries in BCC Fe: The Role of Elastic Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.07787</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.07787v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Low-angle grain boundaries (LAGBs) are often regarded as penetrable interfaces to dislocation motion, yet recent studies suggest they can also act as strong barriers. The origin of this duality remains debated, particularly regarding the role of elastic interactions. Here, large-scale molecular dynamics simulations are employed to investigate dislocation transmission across various tilt LAGBs in BCC Fe. The results show that transmission resistance varies widely with boundary-dislocation geometry. Contrary to the prevailing view that dislocation reactions dominate, elastic interactions between lattice and boundary dislocations emerge as the primary controlling factor. Screw and screw-like dislocations generate shear stresses that bend GB dislocations and produce strong barriers, whereas edge dislocations lack such stresses and transmit more readily. Consequently, barrier strength increases as the dislocation character angle decreases, with screw dislocations experiencing the strongest resistance. From these insights, we develop an analytical model that quantitatively links net transmission stress to dislocation character, boundary inclination, and boundary misorientation, reproducing the simulation results with excellent agreement. These results establish the dominant role of elastic interactions in dislocation-LAGB interactions and provide a predictive basis for designing materials strengthened by controlled boundary architectures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.07787v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shuai Zhang, Zhishun Chen, Zhuoming Xie, Jun Song, Huiqiu Deng, Wangyu Hu, Jie Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum-to-classical transition and H-theorem in surface diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.18844</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.18844v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this work, surface diffusion is studied with a different perspective by showing how the corresponding open dynamics is transformed when passing, in a continuous and smooth way, from a pure quantum regime to a full classical regime; the so-called quantum-to-classical transition. This continuous process is carried out from the Liouville-von Neumann equation by scaling Planck's constant. For this goal, the Brownian motion of an adsorbate on a flat surface is analyzed in order to show how this transition takes place. In particular, this open dynamics is studied from the master equation for the reduced density matrix within the Caldeira-Leggett formalism; in particular, the two extreme time behaviors, the ballistic and diffusive motions. It is also shown that the origin of the ballistic motion is different for the quantum and classical regimes. In this scenario, the corresponding Gaussian function for the intermediate scattering function is governed by the thermal velocity in the classical regime versus the initial spreading velocity of the wave packet for the quantum regime, leading to speak of classical and quantum ideal gas, respectively. Finally, in the diffusive regime, and starting from the Chudley-Elliott model, the quantum-to-classical transition is also discussed in terms of the well-known H-function for three surface temperatures in the diffusion of H and D on a Pt(111) surface. The main goal in this analysis is if one can discriminate the irreversibility coming from tunneling and thermal activation diffusion.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.18844v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>E. E. Torres-Miyares, S. Miret-Art\'es</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Domain Boundaries in a Metallic Distortive Polar Metal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.23831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.23831v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Polar metals are an underexplored material class combining two properties that are typically incompatible, namely a polar crystal structure and reasonable electrical conductivity. While intriguing given that metals favor centrosymmetry, these materials also exhibit potential functional properties relevant to memory, optoelectronic, catalytic, and other applications. The distortive polar metal (DPM) subclass forms through a centrosymmetry-lifting phase transformation into a polar crystal structure. In the process, domains with uniform geometric polar directions form, oftentimes separated by domain boundaries with polarity discontinuities arranged in "charged" head-to-head (H-H) or tail-to-tail (T-T) morphologies. To date, only metallic oxide DPM microstructures have been studied. Here we reveal in the intermetallic DPM Mn5Al8 different chemical reactivity and surface interactions at domain boundaries depending on their H-H or T-T character. Variable surface electron-transfer reactivity suggests localized changes in electronic work functions due to an increase (H-H) or depletion (T-T) in the electronic density of states. This behavior is unintuitive in a metal where electrostatic de-polarizing fields should not account for fluctuations in carrier densities. These findings suggest that metallic DPMs may offer functionalizable domain boundary behavior and deserve increased attention. Metallic DPMs allow highly tunable chemistries that can undergo various thermomechanical processing and transformation protocols. Ultimately, this study marks a milestone in metal physics and uncovers novel intermetallic properties, propelling the discovery and design of advanced electronic materials and devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.23831v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Adrian Savovici, Barak Ratzker, Xuyang Zhou, Stefan Zaefferer, Martina Ruffino, Iliya Radulov, Patricia Jovi\v{c}evi\'c-Klug, Shyam Katnagallu, Amir Hamzehei, Philipp Watermeyer, Alexandra Vogel, J\"org Neugebauer, Matic Jovi\v{c}evi\'c-Klug, Christoph Freysoldt, Dierk Raabe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Discovery of oxide Li-conducting electrolytes in uncharted chemical space via topology-constrained crystal structure prediction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.25763</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.25763v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Oxide Li-conducting solid-state electrolytes (SSEs) offer excellent chemical and thermal stability but typically exhibit lower ionic conductivity than sulfides and chlorides. This motivates the search for new oxide materials with enhanced conductivity. Crystal structure prediction is a powerful approach for identifying such candidates. However, the structural complexity of oxide SSEs, often involving unit cells with more than 100 atoms, presents significant challenges for conventional methods. In this study, we introduce TOPIC, a structure prediction algorithm that reduces configurational complexity by enforcing corner-sharing (CS) bond topology constraints. We demonstrate that TOPIC successfully reproduces the ground-state and metastable structures of known oxide SSEs, including LiTa$_2$PO$_8$ and Li$_7$La$_3$Zr$_2$O$_{12}$, which contain up to about 200 atoms per unit cell. By combining this approach with a pretrained machine-learning interatomic potential, we systematically screen quaternary oxide compositions and identify 92 promising candidates with CS frameworks. In particular, Li$_4$Hf$_2$Si$_3$O$_{12}$, which corresponds to the ground state at its composition, exhibits an ionic conductivity of 14 mS cm$^{-1}$, a hull energy of 21 meV atom$^{-1}$, and a band gap of 6.5 eV. Through our investigation, we identify the Li ratio as one of the key factors determining the stability of CS structures. Overall, our approach provides a practical and scalable pathway for discovering high-performance oxide solid electrolytes in previously unexplored chemical spaces.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.25763v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seungwoo Hwang, Jiho Lee, Seungwu Han, Youngho Kang, Sungwoo Kang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Singular Spectrum Analysis of Time-series Data from Time-dependent density-functional theory in Real-time</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.09252</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.09252v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: This paper introduces a spectral analysis of time-seires data derived from real-time time-dependent density functional theory (TDDFT) using Singular Spectrum Analysis (SSA). TDDFT is a robust method for obtaining molecular excited states and optical spectra by tracking the time evolution of dynamical dipole moments. However, the spectral resolution can be compromised when Fourier transformation's total time duration is insufficient. SSA enabled the extraction of specific oscillation components from the time-series data, facilitating the generation of higher-precision spectra. Even with relatively short time-series dataset, the predictive extension of SSA yielded high-resolution spectra, demonstrating substantial agreement with results obtained through conventional methods. The efficacy of this approach was validated for several small molecules, including ethylene, benzene, and others. SSA's ability to conduct detailed spectral anasysis in specific energy regions enhance spectral resolution and facilitates the clarification of oscillation components within these regions. Real-time TDDFT combined with SSA provides a new analytical method for analyzing the optical properties of molecules, significantly improving the accuracy of the analysis of emission and absorption spectra analysis. This method is expected to have various applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.09252v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naoki Tani, Satoru S. Kano, Yasunari Zempo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Wilson polygons and the topology of zero-dimensional systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.00226</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.00226v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We show that zero-dimensional (0-D) systems can host non-trivial topology analogous to macroscopic topological materials in greater dimensions. Unlike macroscopic periodic systems with translational symmetry, zero-dimensional materials such as molecules, clusters and quantum dots can exhibit discrete rotation symmetry. The eigenstates can thus be grouped into discrete bands and Bloch-like wave functions. Since the symmetry is discrete, the Berry phase and the topological indices must be defined by discrete Wilson polygons. Here, we demonstrate non-trivial Z2 orders in two representative 0-D molecules, [m]-Cycloparaphenylene and [m]-iso-thianaphthene, where topological transitions occur when modifying the coupling between the repeating units. Similar to macroscopic topological systems in greater dimensions, localized boundary states emerge in composite nanohoops formed by segments that are topologically distinct. This opens up the possibility of non-trivial topological phases in 0-D systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.00226v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gen Yin, Rameswar Bhattacharjee, Thomas Wang, Miklos Kertesz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Foundations of the ionization potential condition for localized electron removal in density functional theory</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.00629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.00629v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Optimal tuning of functional parameters in density functional theory approximations, based on enforcing the ionization potential theorem, has emerged as the method of choice for the non-empirical prediction of the electronic structure of finite systems. This method has recently been extended to the bulk limit, based on an ansatz that generalizes the ionization potential theorem to the removal of an electron from a localized Wannier orbital. This Wannier-localization based optimal tuning method has been shown to be highly successful for a wide range of periodic systems, accurately predicting electronic and optical properties. However, a rigorous theoretical justification for its foundational ansatz has been lacking. Here, we establish an ionization potential condition for the removal of a localized electron, by extending the piecewise linearity and Janak's theorems in density functional theory. We also provide numerical evidence supporting our theory.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.00629v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Guy Ohad, Mar\'ia Camarasa-G\'omez, Jeffrey B. Neaton, Ashwin Ramasubramaniam, Tim Gould, Leeor Kronik</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>An Atomic Cluster Expansion Potential for Twisted Multilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.15061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.15061v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Twisted multilayer graphene, characterized by its moir\'e patterns arising from inter-layer rotational misalignment, serves as a rich platform for exploring quantum phenomena. Machine learning interatomic potentials (MLIPs) are a promising approach to model such systems. Our work develops a method to generate training and test datasets for fitting MLIPs that capture all possible misalignments but remain small-scale to facilitate efficient data generation and parameter estimation. To achieve this, we generate configurations with periodic boundary conditions suitable for DFT calculations, and then introduce an internal twist and shift within those supercell structures. Using this technique, supplemented with an active learning workflow, we fit an Atomic Cluster Expansion potential for simulating twisted multilayer graphene and test it for accuracy and robustness on a range of simulation tasks.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.15061v2</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yangshuai Wang, Drake Clark, Sambit Das, Ziyan Zhu, Daniel Massatt, Vikram Gavini, Mitchell Luskin, Christoph Ortner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dissipationless dynamics of spin supersolid states in a spin-1/2 triangular antiferromagnet with impurities</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.03489</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.03489v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Motivated by recent experimental observations of the possible spin supersolid states in triangular lattice compounds, we study the dynamical properties of various ground states in the spin-1/2 easy-axis antiferromagnetic Heisenberg model with impurities under magnetic fields using numerical methods. In both low- and high-field spin supersolid states, the gapless Goldstone mode at the $K$ points remains robust against impurities, which is related to the presence of spin superfluidity. By contrast, we find that impurities induce a splitting of the magnon bands at the same density level in the conventional magnetic state, the so-called up-up-down state. In addition, the finite superfluid stiffness probed by the twisted phase in the spin supersolid states is consistent with the excitation spectrum. We argue that this excitation spectrum with impurity provides direct evidence for the dissipationless dynamics in the spin supersolid states, which could be tested in neutron scattering experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.03489v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yixuan Huang, Yuan Gao, Wei Li, Seiji Yunoki, Sadamichi Maekawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strongly Entangled Kondo and Kagome Lattices and the Emergent Magnetic Ground State in Heavy-Fermion Kagome Metal YbV$_6$Sn$_6$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.04641</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.04641v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Applying angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy and density functional theory calculations, we present compelling spectroscopic evidence demonstrating the intertwining and mutual interaction between the Kondo and kagome sublattices in heavy-fermion intermetallic compound YbV$_6$Sn$_6$. We reveal the Yb 4$f$-derived states near the Fermi level, along with the presence of bulk kagome bands and topological surface states. We unveil strong interactions between the 4$f$ and itinerant electrons, where the kagome bands hosting the Dirac fermions and van Hove singularities predominate. Such findings are well described using a $c$-$f$ hybridization model. On the other hand, our systematic characterization of magnetic properties demonstrates an unusually enhanced antiferromagnetic ordering, where the kagome-derived van Hove singularities near $E_F$ play a vital role in determining the unconventional nature of the Ruderman-Kittel-Kasuya-Yosida interaction and Kondo coupling. These unique kagome-state-mediated exchange interactions have never been reported before and could lead to a novel phase diagram and various quantum critical behaviors in YbV$_6$Sn$_6$ and its siblings. Our results not only expand the family of exotic quantum phases entangled with kagome structure to the strongly correlated regime, but also establish YbV$_6$Sn$_6$ as an unprecedented platform to explore unconventional many-body physics beyond the standard Kondo picture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.04641v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/sqbn-vtcj</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. Lett. 135, 146902 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rui Lou, Max Mende, Riccardo Vocaturo, Hao Zhang, Qingxin Dong, Man Li, Pengfei Ding, Erjian Cheng, Zhiguang Liao, Yu Zhang, Junfa Lin, Reza Firouzmandi, Vilmos Kocsis, Laura T. Corredor, Yurii Prots, Oleksandr Suvorov, Anupam Jana, Jun Fujii, Ivana Vobornik, Oleg Janson, Wenliang Zhu, Jeroen van den Brink, Cornelius Krellner, Minghu Pan, Bosen Wang, Tianlong Xia, Jinguang Cheng, Shancai Wang, Claudia Felser, Bernd B\"uchner, Sergey Borisenko, Rong Yu, Denis V. Vyalikh, Alexander Fedorov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal rectification in jointless Pb solid wire</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2509.14631</link>
      <description>arXiv:2509.14631v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Thermal rectification is observed in jointless Pb wires at temperatures near the superconducting transition of Pb under magnetic fields. Using different magnetic-field (H) response of temperature dependence of thermal conductivity (\k{appa}-T) under H parallel to J and H perpendicular to J where J is heat flow, we fabricated a jointless thermal diode. Thermal rectification is observed with the thermal rectification ratio (TRR) of 1.5 and the difference in \k{appa} of 330 W m-1 K-1 at T = 5.11 K under H = 400 Oe for a Pb wire with a 50%-bent (H perpendicular to J) and 50%-straight (H parallel to J) structure. The peak temperature of TRR can be tuned by the strength of applied magnetic field. By changing bent ratio to 40%-bent, a higher TRR exceeding 2 was observed. The Pb-jointless thermal diode will be a useful material for thermal management at cryogenic temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2509.14631v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Masayuki Mashiko, Poonam Rani, Yuto Watanabe, Yoshikazu Mizuguchi</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
