<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 02:30:27 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>X-ray diffraction characterization of suspended structures for MEMS applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10424</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10424v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Mechanical stress control is becoming one of the major challenges for the future of micro and nanotechnologies. Micro scanning X-ray diffraction is one of the promising techniques that allows stress characterization in such complex structures at sub micron scales. Two types of MEMS structure have been studied: a bilayer cantilever composed of a gold film deposited on poly-silicon and a boron doped silicon bridge. X-ray diffraction results are discussed in view of numerical simulation experiments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10424v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.class-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Goudeau (SP2MI, LMP), N. Tamura (LBNL), B. Lavelle (CEMES), S. Rigo (ENIT), T. Masri (ENIT), A. Bosseboeuf (IEF), T. Sarnet (IEF, CNRS), J. -A. Petit (ENIT), J. -M. Desmarres (CNES)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pilot study of electrochemical reduction of selected nucleotides and double-stranded DNA at pristine micro-/ultrananocrystalline boron-doped diamond electrodes at very negative potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10469</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10469v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Pristine polycrystalline boron-doped diamond electrodes (BDDEs) -- microcrystalline (B-MCDE) and ultrananocrystalline (B-UNCDE) were applied for the electrochemical reduction of several selected purine nucleotides -- Guanosine 5'-monophosphate (GMP), 2'-Deoxyguanosine 5'-monophosphate (dGMP), Adenosine 5'-monophosphate (AMP), Adenosine 5'-diphosphate (ADP), Adenosine 5'-triphosphate (ATP), and pyrimidine nucleotides -- Cytidine 5'-monophosphate (CMP), Thymidine 5'-monophosphate (TMP), as well as low-molecular-weight double-stranded DNA (dsDNA) at very negative potentials via linear sweep voltammetry (LSV). Three different types of electrode surfaces were employed -- "H-terminated" B-MCDE (H-B-MCDE) and "O-terminated" B-MCDE/B-UNCDE (O-B-MCDE/O-B-UNCDE). It was found that electrochemical reduction of all tested analytes (except GMP) is possible at H-B-MCDE. On the other hand, electrochemical reduction of all selected analytes (except dsDNA) is possible at O-B-MCDE/O-B-UNCDE. Ambient oxygen and preadsorption step in the manner of incubation of the corresponding sensor in the analyte solution for 30 s had a profound effect on the repeatability of the results and, in the case of H-B-MCDE, also on the magnitude of voltammetric signals and the possibility of electrochemical reduction of dGMP. The use of the proposed sensors and their main advantages and disadvantages for the voltammetric determination of the tested analytes (demonstrated via electrochemical reduction of AMP) in the presence of hydrogen evolution reaction (HER) is also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10469v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.electacta.2024.145549</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Michal August\'in, Vlastimil Vysko\v{c}il, Ondrej Szab\'o, Kate\v{r}ina Aubrechtov\'a Dragounov\'a, Rene Pfeifer, Frank-Michael Matysik, Ji\v{r}\'i Barek, Mari\'an Marton, Alexander Kromka</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rubidium intercalation in epitaxial monolayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10477v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Alkali metal intercalation of graphene layers has been of particular interest due to potential applications in electronics, energy storage, and catalysis. Rubidium (Rb) is one of the largest alkali metals and the one less investigated as intercalant. Here, we report a systematic investigation, with a multi-technique approach, of the phase formation of Rb under epitaxial monolayer graphene on SiC(0001). We explore a wide phase space with two control parameters: the Rb density (i.e., deposition time) and sample temperature (i.e., room- and low-temperature). We reveal the emergence of $(2 \times 2)$ and $(\sqrt{3} \times \sqrt{3})$R30{\deg} structures formed by a single alkali metal layer intercalated between monolayer graphene and the interfacial C-rich reconstructed surface, also known as buffer layer. Rb intercalation also results in a strong n-type doping of the graphene layer. Progressively annealing to high temperatures, we first reveal diffusion of Rb atoms which results in the enlargement of intercalated areas. As desorption sets in, intercalated regions progressively shrink and fragment. Eventually, at approximately 600{\deg}C the initial surface is retrieved, indicating the reversibility of the intercalation process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10477v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Letizia Ferbel, Stefano Veronesi, Tevfik Onur Mentes, Lars Bu{\ss}, Antonio Rossi, Neeraj Mishra, Camilla Coletti, Jan Ingo Flege, Andrea Locatelli, Stefan Heun</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polymer-based solid-state electrolytes for lithium sulfur batteries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10567v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Lithium-sulfur (Li-S) batteries offer substantial theoretical energy density gains over Li-ion bat-teries, a crucial factor for transportation electrification. In addition, sulfur is an earth-abundant, inexpensive material obtainable from multiple resources; thus, Li-S batteries are envisioned to provide environmentally sustainable solutions to the growing demand for energy storage. A crit-ical roadblock to the realization of commercial Li-S batteries is the formation of polysulfides and their secondary reactions with liquid organic electrolytes, resulting in low coulombic efficiency for charging and fast self-discharge rates. The realization of solid-state electrolytes for Li-S bat-teries provides potential pathways to address the safety concerns of liquid electrolytes and inhib-it the formation of polysulfides and/or prevent their diffusion into the anode electrode. However, current solid-state electrolytes are limited by low ionic conductivity, inadequate electrode inter-facial compatibility, and restricted electrochemical windows. This review discusses the status of polymer-based electrolytes for Li-S batteries, and outlines current methods for their fabrication, their transport characteristics and ongoing research aimed at overcoming material properties hindering the development of all-solid-state Li-S batteries.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10567v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Praveen Balaji T, Soumyadip Choudhury, Ernesto E. Marinero</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spin-Degenerate Bulk Bands and Topological Surface States of RuO2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10649</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10649v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets are a novel platform to realize exotic electromagnetic properties distinct from those of conventional ferromagnets and antiferromagnets. We report results of micro-focused angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) on RuO2, of which altermagnetic nature has been under fierce debate. We have elucidated the band structure of the (100), (110) and (101) surfaces of a bulk single crystal. We found that, irrespective of the surface orientation, the experimental band structures obtained by ARPES commonly show a semi-quantitative agreement with the bulk-band calculation for the nonmagnetic phase, but display a severe disagreement with that for the antiferromagnetic phase. Moreover, spin-resolved ARPES signifies a negligible spin polarization for the bulk bands. These results suggest the absence of antiferromagnetism and altermagnetic spin splitting. Furthermore, we identified a flat surface band and a dispersive one near the Fermi level at the (100)/(110) and (101) surfaces, respectively, both of which are attributed to the topological surface states associated with the bulk Dirac nodal lines. The present ARPES results suggest that the crystal-orientation-dependent topological surface/interface states need to be taken into account to properly capture the transport and catalytic characteristics of RuO2.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10649v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>T. Osumi, K. Yamauchi, S. Souma, P. Shubhankar, A. Honma, K. Nakayama, K. Ozawa, M. Kitamura, K. Horiba, H. Kumigashira, C. Bigi, F. Bertran, T. Oguchi, T. Takahashi, Y. Maeno, T. Sato</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic switching of phonon angular momentum in a ferrimagnetic insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10650</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10650v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Phonons, which carry circular atomic motions, offer a new route for mediating angular momentum in solids. However, controlling phonon angular momentum without altering the material's structure or composition remains challenging. Here, we demonstrate the non-volatile switching of angular momentum-carrying phonons by leveraging intrinsic ferrimagnetism in an insulator. We find a pair of chiral phonons with giant energy splitting reaching 20% of the phonon frequency, due to spontaneously broken time-reversal symmetry. With a moderate magnetic field, the phonon angular momentum of the two chiral phonon branches can be switched along with the magnetization. Notably, near the critical temperature, the effective phonon magnetic moment is enhanced, reaching 2.62 Bohr magneton, exceeding the moment of a magnon. A microscopic model based on phonon-magnon coupling accounts for the observations. Furthermore, we identify two types of phononic domains with opposite phonon Zeeman splitting and propose the existence of topologically protected phononic edge modes at domain boundaries. These results demonstrate effective manipulation of chiral phonons with magnetism, and pave the way for engineering chiral phononic domains on the micrometer scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10650v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fangliang Wu, Jing Zhou, Song Bao, Liangyue Li, Jinsheng Wen, Yuan Wan, Qi Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Microwave-driven synthesis and modification of nanocarbons and hybrids in liquid and solid phases</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10706</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10706v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Over the past 20 years, nanocarbons have become more significant as nanostructured fillers in composites and, more recently, as functional elements in a brand-new class of hybrid materials. Microwave-assisted synthesis and processing is a burgeoning subject matter in materials research with significant strides in the realm of nanocarbon during the last decade. The review examines recent approaches to producing various nanocarbons using microwaves as energy sources, the characterization of such materials for various applications, and their results. The underlying factors supporting the increased performance of such materials or their composites are analyzed and reaction mechanisms are presented wherever necessary. In particular, the recently developed and verified approaches to produce porous carbon materials, CNTs and fibers, carbon nanospheres, carbon dots, CQDs, reduced graphene oxide, nanocarbon hybrid materials, and the purification and modification of CNTs are discussed. The reduction of graphene oxide and the preparation of graphene derivative hybrids using solid-state and liquid-state routes such as polyopl, mixed solvents, ionic liquids, and microwave-assisted hydrothermal/solvothermal methods are analyzed in detail. In addition, the principles of microwave heating in liquid and solid states, the use of metals particles as arcing agents or catalysts, and carbonaceous materials as internal or external susceptors during synthesis and modifications are presented in detail.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10706v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.est.2025.115315</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Journal of Energy Storage 2025, 111, 115315</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Nagaraj Nandihalli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Density of States Calculation of CeO$_2$ Based on VASP</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10724</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10724v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this study, the Density of States (DOS) of CeO$_2$ was analyzed in detail using the Density Functional Theory (DFT) method based on VASP software. As an important functional material, CeO$_2$ finds wide applications in catalysis, optics, and electronic devices. Through structural optimization, self-consistent electronic calculations, and non-self-consistent calculations, we thoroughly investigated the crystal structure and electronic energy level distribution of CeO$_2$. The lattice parameter optimization results from the structural calculations indicated a stable crystal structure for CeO$_2$. Self-consistent electronic calculations revealed a bandgap of approximately 2.403 eV, with the valence band maximum primarily contributed by O 2p orbitals and the conduction band minimum mainly originating from Ce 4f orbitals. Non-self-consistent calculations further demonstrated the total DOS and partial DOS of CeO$_2$, confirming the significant roles of Ce 4f and O 2p states in its electronic conduction and optical properties. These results not only provide theoretical support for the applications of CeO$_2$ in catalysis and electronic materials but also deepen our understanding of its fundamental electronic structural characteristics, offering guidance for the design and development of novel CeO$_2$-based materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10724v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruyi Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Materials design criteria for ultra-high thermoelectric power factors in metals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10790</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10790v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Metals have high electronic conductivities, but very low Seebeck coefficients, which traditionally make them unsuitable for thermoelectric materials. Recent studies, however, showed that metals can deliver ultra-high thermoelectric power factors (PFs) under certain conditions. In this work, we theoretically examine the electronic structure and electronic transport specifications which allow for such high PFs. Using Boltzmann transport (BTE) simulations and a multi-band electronic structure model, we show that metals with: i) high degree of transport asymmetry between their bands, ii) strong inter-band scattering, and iii) a large degree of band overlap, can provide ultra-high power factors. We show that each of these characteristics adds to the steepness of the transport distribution function of the BTE, which allows for an increase of the Seebeck coefficient to sizable values, simultaneously with an increase in the electrical conductivity. This work generalizes the concept that transport asymmetry (i.e., mixture of energy regions of high and low contributions to the electrical conductivity), through a combination of different band masses, scattering strengths, or energy filtering scenarios, etc., can indeed result in very high thermoelectric power factors, even in the absence of a material bandgap. Under certain conditions, transport asymmetry can over-compensate any performance degradation to the PF due to bipolar conduction and the naturally low Seebeck coefficients that otherwise exist in this class of materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10790v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PRXEnergy.3.043009</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>PRX Energy 3, 043009, 2024</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Patrizio Graziosi, Kim-Isabelle Mehnert, Rajeev Dutt, Jan-Willem G. Bos, Neophytos Neophytou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is p-Type Doping in SeO2 Feasible?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10912</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10912v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The significance of p-type transparent oxide semiconductors (TOS) in the semiconductor industry is paramount, driving advancements in optoelectronic technologies for transparent electronic devices with unique properties. The recent discovery of p-type behavior in SeO2 has stirred both interest and confusion in the scientific community. In this Letter, we employ density functional theory calculations to unveil the intrinsic insulating characteristics of SeO2, highlighting substantial challenges in carrier doping. Our electronic structure analyses indicate that the Se 5s2 states are energetically positioned too low to effectively interact with the O 2p orbitals, resulting in a valence band maximum (VBM) primarily dominated by the O 2p orbitals. The deep and localized nature of the VBM in SeO2 limits its potential as a high-mobility p-type TOS. Defect calculations demonstrate that all intrinsic defects in SeO2 exhibit deep transition levels within the bandgap. The Fermi level consistently resides in the mid-gap region, regardless of synthesis conditions. Furthermore, deep intrinsic acceptors and donors exhibit negative formation energies in the n-type and p-type regions, respectively, facilitating their spontaneous formation and impeding external doping efforts. Thus, the reported p-type conductivity in SeO2 samples is unlikely intrinsic and is more plausibly attributed to reduced elemental Se, a well-known p-type semiconductor.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10912v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zewen Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling an in-plane Hall effect in rutile RuO$_2$ films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10931</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10931v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The in-plane-magnetic-field-induced Hall effect (IPHE) observed in Weyl semimetals and PT-symmetric antiferromagnets has attracted increasing attention, as it breaks the stereotype that the Hall effect is induced by an out-of-plane magnetic field or magnetization. To date, the IPHE has been discussed mainly for materials with low-symmetry crystal/magnetic point groups. Here, we show that even if symmetry forbids an inherent IPHE that arises from any mechanism, an apparent IPHE can be generated by selecting a low-symmetry crystalline plane for measurement. For rutile RuO$_2$, although its high symmetry forbids an inherent IPHE, films grown along the low-symmetry (1 1 1) and (1 0 1) orientations are found to exhibit a distinct IPHE. The in-plane Hall coefficients are quantitatively reproduced by referring to the out-of-plane Hall coefficients measured for the high-symmetry (1 0 0) and (0 0 1) planes, indicating that the observed IPHE is caused by a superposition of inequivalent out-of-plane Hall effects. Similar behaviour is also observed for paramagnetic rutile systems, indicating the ubiquity of the apparent IPHE in electronic and spintronic devices with low-symmetry crystalline planes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10931v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s42005-025-01943-3</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Meng Wang, Jianbing Zhang, Di Tian, Pu Yu, Fumitaka Kagawa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interactive Multiscale Modeling to Bridge Atomic Properties and Electrochemical Performance in Li-CO$_2$ Battery Design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10954</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10954v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Li-CO$_2$ batteries show promise as energy storage solutions, offering high theoretical energy density and CO$_2$ fixation. Their performance relies on the formation and decomposition of Li$_2$CO$_3$/C during discharge and charge cycles, respectively. We used a multiscale modeling framework that integrates Density Functional Theory (DFT), Ab-Initio Molecular Dynamics (AIMD), classical Molecular Dynamics (MD), and Finite Element Analysis (FEA) to investigate atomic and cell-level properties. The Li-CO$_2$ battery consists of a lithium metal anode, an ionic liquid electrolyte, and a carbon cloth porous cathode with a Sb$_{0.67}$Bi$_{1.33}$Te$_3$ catalyst. DFT and AIMD determined the electrical conductivities of Sb$_{0.67}$Bi$_{1.33}$Te$_3$ and Li$_2$CO$_3$ using the Kubo-Greenwood formalism and studied the CO$_2$ reduction mechanism on the cathode catalyst. MD simulations calculated the CO$_2$ diffusion coefficient, Li$^+$ transference number, ionic conductivity, and Li$^+$ solvation structure. The FEA model, incorporating results from atomistic simulations, reproduced experimental voltage-capacity profiles at 1 mA/cm$^2$ and revealed spatio-temporal variations in Li$_2$CO$_3$/C deposition, porosity, and CO$_2$ concentration dependence on discharge rates in the cathode. Accordingly, Li$_2$CO$_3$ can form toroidal and thin film deposits, leading to dispersed and local porosity changes at 0.1 mA/cm$^2$ and 1 mA/cm$^2$, respectively. The capacity decreases exponentially from 81,570 mAh/g at 0.1 mA/cm$^2$ to 6,200 mAh/g at 1 mA/cm$^2$, due to pore clogging that limits CO$_2$ transport to the cathode interior. Therefore, the performance of Li-CO$_2$ batteries can be significantly improved by enhancing CO$_2$ transport, regulating Li$_2$CO$_3$ deposition, and optimizing cathode architecture.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10954v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mohammed Lemaalem, Selva Chandrasekaran Selvaraj, Ilias Papailias, Naveen K. Dandu, Arash Namaeighasemi, Larry A. Curtiss, Amin Salehi-Khojin, Anh T. Ngo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal conductivity of 3C-SiC from configuration space sampling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11008</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11008v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Cubic silicon carbide phonon thermal conductivity has been calculated using anharmonic phonon analysis. The atomic interaction model was built using displacement-force data obtained with the High Efficiency Configuration Space Sampling (HECSS) technique and density functional theory calculated forces. In the new version of HECSS we replaced the Markov chain scheme of Metropolis-Hastings Monte-Carlo with weighting of the final sampling according to the target distribution. This increased the efficiency of the method and allowed to use -- with appropriate weight -- all generated and ab-initio evaluated samples. The quality of the proposed method is confirmed by the accuracy with which the experimental results taken from the literature were reproduced.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11008v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pawe{\l} T. Jochym, Jan {\L}a\.zewski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Learning the Electrostatic Response of the Electron Density through a Symmetry-Adapted Vector Field Model</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11019</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11019v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A current challenge in atomistic machine learning is that of efficiently predicting the response of the electron density under electric fields. We address this challenge with symmetry-adapted kernel functions that are specifically derived to account for the rotational symmetry of a three-dimensional vector field. We demonstrate the equivariance of the method on a set of rotated water molecules and show its high efficiency with respect to number of training configurations and features for liquid water and naphthalene crystals. We conclude showcasing applications for relaxed configurations of gold nanoparticles, reproducing the scaling law of the electronic polarizability with size, up to systems with more than 2000 atoms. By deriving a natural extension to equivariant learning models of the electron density, our method provides an accurate and inexpensive strategy to predict the electrostatic response of molecules and materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11019v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mariana Rossi, Kevin Rossi, Alan M. Lewis, Mathieu Salanne, Andrea Grisafi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A large anomalous Hall effect and Weyl nodes in bulk FeNi$_3$: a density functional theory study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11025</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11025v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In this work, we report the study of electronic structure, magnetism, and the existence of Weyl nodes in a pristine bulk FeNi$_{3}$, a member of Fe-Ni inver alloy compounds, known as good metal catalysts with high activity and stability for water splitting for a very long time. Our observation of Weyl points in the bulk FeNi$_{3}$ may lead to a new technology to design highly efficient topological catalysts. While the previous literature \cite{PhysRev.97.304} mainly focused on the thermal and catalytic properties of FeNi$_{3}$ we report the interplay of Fe $d$-Ni $d$ hybridization and spin-orbit coupling give rise to the ferromagnetic Weyl nodes in the bulk FeNi$_{3}$. Our study shows that the ground state of the bulk FeNi$_{3}$ is a Weyl metal with a large number of Weyl nodes at the Fermi energy away from high-symmetry $k$-points. Furthermore, we predict a large intrinsic anomalous Hall conductivity of about $10000~S/m$ at the ground state. In addition, we show the existence of Weyl nodes along the high symmetry $k$-points $~0.2eV$ above and $~0.05eV$ below self-consistent Fermi level that may be achieved either by the electron or hole doping, or by external perturbation. In this article, FeNi$_{3}$ has been studied to explore this scenario using first-principles density functional theory and subsequent Wannier90-based tight-binding method. Furthermore, we report the existence of two types of Weyl cones, type-I and type-II, $~0.2eV$ above the Fermi level. Our report provides a realistic material to further explore the intrinsic properties related to Weyl cones, and the spintronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11025v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivani Thakur, Santu Baidya</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing the role played by $\alpha$- and $\beta$-relaxation in hydrostatically compressed metallic glasses</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11026v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Any property of metallic glasses is controlled by the microscopic ongoing relaxation processes. While the response of these processes to temperature is well documented, little is known on their pressure dependence, owning to non-trivial experimental challenges. By combining fast differential scanning calorimetry, X-ray diffraction and high-pressure technologies, we identify the origin of a recently discovered pressure-induced rejuvenation in metallic glasses from the different pressure response of the $\alpha$- and $\beta$-relaxation in a series of hydrostatically compressed Vit4 glasses. While the localized $\beta$-relaxation promotes rejuvenation and is associated to a constant looser atomic packing independent of the applied pressure, the collective $\alpha$-relaxation triggers density driven ordering processes promoting the stability. The latter parameter however cannot be solely described by the degree of equilibration reached during the compression, which instead determines the crossover between the two regimes allowing to rescale the corresponding activation energies of the two processes on a master curve.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11026v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jie Shen, Antoine Cornet, Alberto Ronca, Eloi Pineda, Fan Yang, Jean-Luc Garden, Gael Moiroux, Gavin Vaughan, Marco di Michiel, Gaston Garbarino, Fabian Westermeier, Celine Goujon, Murielle Legendre, Jiliang Liu, Daniele Cangialosi, Beatrice Ruta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrahigh interfacial thermal conductance for cooling gallium oxide electronics using cubic boron arsenide</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11082</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11082v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Gallium oxide (Ga$_2$O$_3$) has attracted significant interest for its unique potential especially in power electronics. However, its low and anisotropic thermal conductivity poses a major challenge for heat dissipation. Here, we explore an effective cooling strategy centering on the heterogeneous integration of $\beta$-Ga$_2$O$_3$ devices with cubic boron arsenide (cBAs), an emerging material with an ultrahigh thermal conductivity $\kappa$ of ~1300 Wm$^{-1}$K$^{-1}$. Machine-learned potentials for representative $\beta$-Ga$_2$O$_3$/cBAs interfaces are trained, enabling accurate and efficient calculation of the interfacial thermal conductance $G$ via nonequilibrium molecular dynamics. At 300 K, remarkable $G$ values of 749$\pm$33 MWm$^{-2}$K$^{-1}$ and 824$\pm$35 MWm$^{-2}$K$^{-1}$ are predicted for Ga-As and O-B bonding across the interface, respectively, which are primarily attributed to the well-matched phonon density of states considering the similar Debye temperatures of $\beta$-Ga$_2$O$_3$ and cBAs. Moreover, finite-element simulations directly show a notable device temperature reduction when comparing cBAs with other substrates. The simultaneously ultrahigh $\kappa$ and $G$ highlight cBAs as an ideal substrate for Ga$_2$O$_3$ electronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11082v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenjiang Zhou, Nianjie Liang, Wei Xiao, Zhaofei Tong, Fei Tian, Bai Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Atom Probe Tomography of SrTiO$_3$: Measurement Methodology and Impurity Detection Limits</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11089</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11089v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Strontium titanate (STO) possesses promising properties for applications in thermoelectricity, catalysis, fuel cells, and more, but its performance is highly dependent on stoichiometry and impurity levels. While atom probe tomography (APT) can provide detailed three-dimensional atomic-scale chemical information, STO specimens have been challenging to analyze due to premature specimen fracture. In this study, we show that by applying a thin metal coating to atom probe tips, STO specimens can be analyzed with nearly 100% success. Using this approach, we investigate both undoped STO and 1 at% Nb-doped STO, achieving sufficient sensitivity to detect Nb concentrations as low as 0.7 at%. This work establishes a reliable APT method for high-resolution chemical analysis of STO at the nanoscale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11089v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. E. Rybak, J. Arlt, B. Gault, C. A. Volkert</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grain boundary interstitial segregation in substitutional binary alloys</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11101</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11101v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Grain boundary (GB) segregation is a powerful approach for optimizing the thermal and mechanical properties of metal alloys. In this study, we report significant GB interstitial segregation in a representative substitutional binary alloy system (Al-Ni) through atomistic simulations, challenging prevailing assumptions in the literature. Our findings show that Ni atoms preferentially segregate to interstitial sites within numerous kite-like GB structures in the Al bicrystals. An intriguing interplanar interstitial segregation pattern was also observed and analyzed. Additionally, interstitial segregation can induce unexpected GB transitions, such as kite transitions and nano-faceting, due to the existence of small interstitial sites. Building upon these observations, we developed a robust method to systematically identify the interstitial candidate sites for accommodating solutes at GBs. This approach combines site detection with structural filtering to produce distributions of interstitial sites that closely match atomistic simulation results. Applied to nanocrystalline alloys, this method enabled the calculation of interstitial segregation energies, significantly improving GB segregation predictions for the Al-Ni system. Furthermore, machine learning models using smooth overlap of atomic positions descriptors successfully predicted per-site interstitial segregation energy. This study highlights the critical role of GB interstitial segregation in advancing our understanding of solute behavior and provides valuable insights for designing next-generation alloys.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11101v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zuoyong Zhang, Chuang Deng</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Computational statistics of segregation and dislocation activities of hydrogen charged free surfaces and grain boundaries</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11134</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11134v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Revealing statistics of H-defect interactions provides insights into significant ductility loss due to the particular strain partitioning in H-charged structural alloys. Experimental investigation of these interactions is extremely difficult, labor-intensive, and costly. Here, we used MD and GCMC simulations and studied H-diffusion deformation at polycrystalline scale with atomic resolution efficiently. To study H-free surface interactions, large pillars including all possible angles and planes of free surfaces were modeled. To study H-grain boundary interactions, several polycrystalline models containing comparable statistics of low and high angle grain boundaries were examined. We studied the statistics of H-segregation tendencies based on free surface angles and grain boundary types. Dislocation activities were also classified for these various types and total density and strength were compared and analyzed compared to H-free samples. In the free surface model, it was observed that H was evenly distributed along the model's surface. Although the dislocation density was reduced compared to H-free samples, localized bands of dislocations were produced. Additionally in the polycrystalline samples, it was concluded that H tends to segregate along grain boundaries with misorientation angles less than or equal to 25 degrees. However, specific misorientation angle interactions -- namely $&gt;45$ degrees -- led to increased dislocation density in H-charged samples compared to their H-free counterparts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11134v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew J. Melfi, S. Mohadeseh Taheri-Mousavi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Surface Reconstructions in Thin-Films of Magnetic Topological Insulator MnBi$_2$Te$_4$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11176</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11176v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Understanding the nature of surface states and their exchange gaps in magnetic topological insulator MnBi$_2$Te$_4$ (MBT) thin films is crucial for achieving robust topological Chern and Axion insulating phases where the Quantum Anomalous Hall Effect and the Topological Magneto-electric Effect can be realized. Here, we focus on the rather unexplored issue of how surface reconstructions, which are likely to occur in experiments, influence these properties. Using first-principles calculations together with molecular dynamics simulations accelerated by machine learning force field, we demonstrate that interstitial-2H and peripheral-2H type atomic reconstructions are responsible for modifying the exchange gap and surface characteristics of MBT thin films, with important implications for the topological indices and the nature of quasi one-dimensional side-wall edge states dominating quantum transport. \textcolor{blue}{Specifically, the calculation of the energy landscape and barriers for the proposed surface reconstructions indicates that the interstitial-2H reconstruction is thermodynamically more stable than the peripheral-2H reconstruction. The latter case is also hypothesized as providing a plausible explanation for the Rashba surface states observed} in Angle-Resolved Photoemission Spectroscopy (ARPES) measurements. Our analysis provides a theoretical framework to elucidate the nature and effect of reconstructions in MBT thin films, with predictions for the experimental realization of different topological phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11176v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shahid Sattar, Daniel Hedman, C. M. Canali</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advances in modeling complex materials: The rise of neuroevolution potentials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11191</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11191v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Interatomic potentials are essential for driving molecular dynamics (MD) simulations, directly impacting the reliability of predictions regarding the physical and chemical properties of materials. In recent years, machine-learned potentials (MLPs), trained against first-principles calculations, have become a new paradigm in materials modeling as they provide a desirable balance between accuracy and computational cost. The neuroevolution potential (NEP) approach, implemented in the open-source GPUMD software, has emerged as a promising machine-learned potential, exhibiting impressive accuracy and exceptional computational efficiency. This review provides a comprehensive discussion on the methodological and practical aspects of the NEP approach, along with a detailed comparison with other representative state-of-the-art MLP approaches in terms of training accuracy, property prediction, and computational efficiency. We also demonstrate the application of the NEP approach to perform accurate and efficient MD simulations, addressing complex challenges that traditional force fields typically can not tackle. Key examples include structural properties of liquid and amorphous materials, chemical order in complex alloy systems, phase transitions, surface reconstruction, material growth, primary radiation damage, fracture in two-dimensional materials, nanoscale tribology, and mechanical behavior of compositionally complex alloys under various mechanical loadings. This review concludes with a summary and perspectives on future extensions to further advance this rapidly evolving field.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11191v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Penghua Ying, Cheng Qian, Rui Zhao, Yanzhou Wang, Feng Ding, Shunda Chen, Zheyong Fan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Control of ferroelectric domain wall dynamics by point defects: Insights from ab initio based simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11193</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11193v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The control of ferroelectric domain walls and their dynamics on the nanoscale becomes increasingly important for advanced nanoelectronics and novel computing schemes. One common approach to tackle this challenge is the pinning of walls by point defects. The fundamental understanding on how different defects influence the wall dynamics is, however, incomplete. In particular, the important class of defect dipoles in acceptor-doped ferroelectrics is currently underrepresented in theoretical work. In this study, we combine molecular dynamics simulations based on an \textit{ab\ initio}-derived effective Hamiltonian and methods from materials informatics, and analyze the impact of these defects on the motion of 180$^{\circ}$ domain walls in tetragonal BaTiO$_3$. We show how these defects can act as local pinning centers and restoring forces on the domain structure. Furthermore, we reveal how walls can flow around sparse defects by nucleation and growth of dipole clusters, and how pinning, roughening and bending of walls depend on the defect distribution. Surprisingly, the interaction between acceptor dopants and walls is short-ranged. We show that the limiting factor for the nucleation processes underlying wall motion is the defect-free area in front of the wall.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11193v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sheng-Han Teng, Aris Dimou, Benjamin Udofia, Majid Ghasemi, Markus Stricker, Anna Gr\"unebohm</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Metallicity and Anomalous Hall Effect in Epitaxially-Strained, Atomically-thin RuO2 Films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11204</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11204v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The anomalous Hall effect (AHE), a hallmark of time-reversal symmetry breaking, has been reported in rutile RuO2, a debated metallic altermagnetic candidate. Previously, AHE in RuO2 was observed only in strain-relaxed thick films under extremely high magnetic fields (~50 T). Yet, in ultrathin strained films with distinctive anisotropic electronic structures, there are no reports, likely due to disorder and defects suppressing metallicity thus hindering its detection. Here, we demonstrate that ultrathin, fully-strained 2 nm TiO2/t nm RuO2/TiO2 (110) heterostructures, grown by hybrid molecular beam epitaxy, retain metallicity and exhibit a sizeable AHE at a significantly lower magnetic field (&lt; 9 T). Density functional theory calculations reveal that epitaxial strain stabilizes a non-compensated magnetic ground state and reconfigures magnetic ordering in RuO2 (110) thin films. These findings establish ultrathin RuO2 as a platform for strain-engineered magnetism and underscore the transformative potential of epitaxial design in advancing spintronic technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11204v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Seung Gyo Jeong, Seungjun Lee, Bonnie Lin, Zhifei Yang, In Hyeok Choi, Jin Young Oh, Sehwan Song, Seung wook Lee, Sreejith Nair, Rashmi Choudhary, Juhi Parikh, Sungkyun Park, Woo Seok Choi, Jong Seok Lee, James M. LeBeau, Tony Low, Bharat Jalan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CNN-based TEM image denoising from first principles</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11225</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11225v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Transmission electron microscope (TEM) images are often corrupted by noise, hindering their interpretation. To address this issue, we propose a deep learning-based approach using simulated images. Using density functional theory calculations with a set of pseudo-atomic orbital basis sets, we generate highly accurate ground truth images. We introduce four types of noise into these simulations to create realistic training datasets. Each type of noise is then used to train a separate convolutional neural network (CNN) model. Our results show that these CNNs are effective in reducing noise, even when applied to images with different noise levels than those used during training. However, we observe limitations in some cases, particularly in preserving the integrity of circular shapes and avoiding visible artifacts between image patches. To overcome these challenges, we propose alternative training strategies and future research directions. This study provides a valuable framework for training deep learning models for TEM image denoising.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11225v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.CV</category>
      <category>eess.IV</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jinwoong Chae, Sungwook Hong, Sungkyu Kim, Sungroh Yoon, Gunn Kim</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electronic States and Mechanical Behaviors of Phosphorus Carbide Nanotubes -- Structural and Quantum Phase Transitions in a Quasi-one-dimensional Material</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11239</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11239v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Quasi-one-dimensional (1D) materials can manifest exotic electronic properties in manners that are distinct from the bulk phase or other low-dimensional systems. Helical symmetries in such materials -- e.g., nanotubes with intrinsic or applied twist -- can simultaneously lead to strong electronic correlation and anomalous transport behavior. However, these materials remain underexplored, in part due to computational challenges. Using specialized symmetry-adapted first-principles calculations, we show that mono-layer $P_2C_3$ -- identified in a previous letter to possess ``double Kagome bands'' -- exhibits a number of striking properties when rolled up into phosphorous carbide nanotubes ($P_2C_3$NTs). Both armchair and zigzag $P_2C_3$NTs are stable at room temperature and display a degenerate combination of Dirac points and electronic flat bands at the Fermi level. Notably, these flat bands are highly resilient to elastic deformations. Large strains can transform the nanotube structure from honeycomb-kagome to ``brick-wall'', and trigger multiple quantum phase transitions. Edge states in $P_2C_3$NTs, spin-degeneracy lifting induced by vacancies and dopants, and strain-tunable magnetism are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11239v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivam Sharma, Chenhaoyue Wang, Hsuan Ming Yu, Amartya S. Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Machine-Learning Bond-Order Potential for Exploring the Configuration Space of Carbon</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11297</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11297v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Construction of transferable machine-learning interatomic potentials with a minimal number of parameters is important for their general applicability. Here, we present a machine-learning interatomic potential with the functional form of the bond-order potential for comprehensive exploration over the configuration space of carbon. The physics-based design of this potential enables robust and accurate description over a wide range of the potential energy surface with a small number of parameters. We demonstrate the versatility of this potential through validations across various tasks, including phonon dispersion calculations, global structure searches for clusters, phase diagram calculations, and enthalpy-volume mappings of local minima structures. We expect that this potential can contribute to the discovery of novel carbon materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11297v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ikuma Kohata, Kaoru Hisama, Keigo Otsuka, Shigeo Maruyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct ab initio calculation of magnons in altermagnets: method, spin-space symmetry aspects, and application to MnTe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11327</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11327v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We suggest the method for direct ab initio calculation of magnons in complex collinear magnets. The method is based on the density-functional-theory calculation under two different constraints: one constraint governs the change of the magnetization with respect to the ground state, and the other is the symmetry constraint responsible for the value of the magnon wave vector. The performance of the method is demonstrated by the application to an altermagnet MnTe. An important role in both the formulation and the application of the method play the aspects of generalized symmetry described by the spin-space groups. The symmetry analysis connects in one coherent picture the following three parts of the consideration: (i) the generalized translational symmetry of the magnons as a crucial condition for their efficient ab-initio calculation, (ii) altermagnetic spin-splitting of the electron states in the ground magnetic state, and (iii) chirality splitting of the magnon excitations. It is demonstrated that both the spin splitting of the electron states and the chirality splitting of the magnons have identical patterns in the corresponding wave vector spaces. Since the altermagnetism of MnTe is the consequence of the presence of the Te atoms, an adequate attention is devoted to the symmetry analysis and calculation results for the Te moments induced in the magnon states. The knowledge of the symmetry properties of the Te moments allows to accelerate the numerical convergence of the magnon states and serves as a test for the accuracy of the calculations. To expose the connection between electron band structures of the magnon states of the system and the chirality properties of these states we investigate the transformation of the electron structure in the transition from the collinear ground state to a noncollinear magnon state.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11327v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>L. M. Sandratskii, K. Carva, V. M. Silkin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Effect of Te doping in GeSe parent thick film by experimental in situ temperature-dependent structural investigation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11373</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11373v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As-deposited and unencapsulated GeSe$_{1-x}$Te$_x$ ($x = 0, 0.25$) 3-$\mu$m-thick amorphous films on Si(001) were obtained via the co-evaporation technique to study the effect of selenium (Se) substitution for tellurium (Te) on the GeSe parent structure in the function of the heating temperature. In situ, grazing-incidence X-ray scattering (XRS), and fluorescence X-ray Absorption Near Edge Structure (XANES) data were collected in isochronal annealing conditions under nitrogen flow. The results show that the onset temperature of crystallization $T_c$ and the crystallized phase symmetry are susceptible to the Te 25 at. % doping. Furthermore, Ge and Se K-edge XANES analyses reveal significant alterations in the local atomic environments surrounding Ge and Se atoms during the transition from the amorphous to the crystalline state. These modifications are accompanied by an observable increase in local structural disorder upon substitution with Te atoms.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11373v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.materresbull.2024.113280</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Materials Research Bulletin, 2025, 185, pp.113280</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>P. Armand (ICGM, UM), R. Escalier (ICGM, UM), G. Silly (ICGM, UM), J. Lizion (ICGM, UM), A. Piarristeguy (ICGM, UM)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nitrogen-Vacancy Centers in Epitaxial Laterally Overgrown Diamond: Towards Up-scaling of Color Center-based Quantum Technologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11481v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Providing high-quality, single-crystal diamond (SCD) with a large area is desirable for up-scaling quantum technology applications that rely on color centers in diamond. Growth methods aiming to increase the area of SCD are an active research area. Native color centers offer a sensitive probe for local crystal quality in such novel materials e.g., via their reaction to stress. In this work, we investigate individual native nitrogen-vacancy (NV) centers in SCD layers manufactured via laterally overgrowing hole arrays in a heteroepitaxially grown large-scale substrate. Heteroepitaxy has become a common tool for growing large SCDs; however, achieving the high crystal quality needed for quantum applications remains a challenge. In the overgrown layer, we identify NV centers with spin-decoherence times in the order of hundreds of microseconds, comparable to high-purity homoepitaxial SCD. We quantify the effective crystal strain in different regions of the overgrown layer, indicating a low stress overall and a stress reduction in the diamond layer above the holes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11481v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nimba Oshnik, Sebastian Westrich, Nina Burmeister, Oliver Roman Opaluch, Lahcene Mehmel, Riadh Issaoui, Alexandre Tallaire, Ovidiu Brinza, Jocelyn Achard, Elke Neu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Influence of the pretreatment anneal on Co germanide Schottky contacts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11492</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11492v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A thin cobalt layer is deposited by electron beam evaporation onto a germanium substrate after an in situ cleaning annealing at 400 or 700 C. The effect of these pretreatments on the Co/Ge Schottky barrier properties and on the germanide formation is investigated by using different techniques. A strong influence of the pre-treatment is observed. The pre-treatment at 700 C removes the native oxide but enhances the diffusion of contaminants. After post-metal deposition annealing, the sample pre-treated at 700 C shows a double layer structure due to interdiffusion, whereas some large isolated islands are present in the sample pre-treated at 400 C.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11492v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.mssp.2008.09.014</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Materials Science in Semiconductor Processing 11 2008 300 304</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>L. Lajaunie, M. L. David, F. Pailloux, C. Tromas, E. Simoen, C. Claeys, J. F. Barbot</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>SANS evidence for the dispersion of nanoparticles in W-1Y$_2$O$_3$ and W-1La$_2$O$_3$ processed by hot isostatic pressing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11521</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11521v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The development of dispersion of nanoparticles in the W-1%Y$_2$O$_3$ and W-1%La$_2$O$_3$ (wt%) alloys processed by hot isostatic pressing has been investigated using small angle neutron scattering. The mode values of these centers are found at 10 and 40 nm in W-1%Y$_2$O$_3$, and 15 and 80 nm in W-1%La$_2$O$_3$. The scanning electron microscopy analyses showed the presence of small second phase particles. The contribution of the pore space to the scattering curves has been analyzed using the results obtained for pure W processed following the same procedure used for the alloys, and the porosity measurements of the samples.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11521v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.ijrmhm.2012.01.010</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Inter. Journal of Refractory Metals and Hard Materials, Volume 33, 2012, Pages 6 9</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. Munoz, J. Martinez, M. A. Monge, B. Savoini, R. Pareja, A. Radulescu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nanostructured thin films of indium oxide nanocrystals confined in alumina matrixes</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nanocrystals of indium oxide (In$_2$O$_3$) with sizes below 10 nm were prepared in alumina matrixes by using a co-pulverization method. The used substrates such as borosilicate glasses or (100) silicon as well as the substrate temperatures during the deposition process were modified and their effects characterized on the structural and physical properties of alumina-In$_2$O$_3$ films. Complementary investigation methods including X-ray diffraction, optical transmittance in the range 250-1100 nm and transmission electron microscopy were used to analyze the nanostructured films. The crystalline order, morphology and optical responses were monitored as function of the deposition parameters and the post-synthesis annealing. The optimal conditions were found and allow realizing suitable nanostructured films with a major crystalline order of cubic phase for the In$_2$O$_3$ nanocrystals. The optical properties of the films were analyzed and the key parameters such as direct and indirect band gaps were evaluated as function of the synthesis conditions and the crystalline quality of the films.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11527v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.tsf.2010.11.018</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Thin Solid Films Volume 519, Issue 7, 31 January 2011, Pages 2141 2145</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>A. Bouifoulen, M. Edely, N. Errien, A. Kassiba, A. Outzourhit, M. Makowska-Janusik, N. Gautier, L. Lajaunie, A. Oueriagli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Navigating the Complexities of Multiple Redox State Interactions in Aqueous Systems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11536</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11536v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Numerous aqueous systems host elements in multiple redox states, with wide ranging implications such as their influence on the formation/dissolution of minerals, water toxicity, and nutrient cycling. To uncover governing mechanisms and complex chemical interactions in aqueous systems, reactive-transport models have increasingly gained importance. However, their predictive capabilities remain limited because existing approaches struggle to accurately account for the full complexities of redox reactions. Here, we develop a reactive-transport framework that leverages recent advancements in thermodynamic modelling, speciation chemistry, and redox kinetics. Distinct from traditional models, we uniquely treat redox kinetics along with transport as transient phenomena, decoupled from Gibbs free energy minimisation. Ensuring ion concentrations are governed by non-equilibrium rate laws, this approach allows predicting the tempo-spatial distribution of speciation and precipitation of species across oxidation states. We illustrate the versatility of our framework through two case studies: manganese speciation in natural waters and the fate of dissolved iron in aqueous/porous media. Our framework significantly enhances the modelling of a diverse range of redox-sensitive environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11536v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shishir Mundra, Mohit Pundir, Barbara Lothenbach, David S. Kammer, Ueli M. Angst</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Mapping the Configuration Space of Half-Heusler Compounds via Subspace Identification for Thermoelectric Materials Discovery</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11644</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11644v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Half-Heuslers are a promising family for thermoelectric (TE) applications, yet only a small fraction of their potential chemistries has been experimentally explored. In this work, we introduce a distinct computational high-throughput screening approach designed to identify underexplored yet promising material subspaces, and apply it to half-Heusler thermoelectrics. We analyze 1,126 half-Heuslers satisfying the $``$18 valence electron rule $''$, including 332 predicted to be semiconductors, using electronic structure calculations, semi-empirical transport models, and thermoelectric quality factor $\beta$. Unlike conventional filtering workflows, our approach employs statistical analysis of candidate material groups to uncover trends in their collective behavior, providing robust insights and minimizing reliance on uncertain predictions for individual compounds. Our findings link $n$-type performance to ultra-high mobility at conduction band edges and $p$-type performance to high band degeneracy. Statistical correlations reveal elemental subspaces associated with high $\beta$. We identify two primary (Y- and Zr-containing) and two secondary (Au- and Ir-containing) subspaces that reinforce key physical design principles, making them promising candidates for further exploration. These recommendations align with previous experimental results on yttrium pnictides. Inspired by these insights, we synthesize and characterize rare-earth gold stannides (REAuSn), finding Sc$_{0.5}$Lu$_{0.5}$AuSn to exhibit low thermal conductivity (0.9-2.3 Wm$^{-1}$K$^{-1}$ at 650 K). This work demonstrates alternative strategies for high throughput screening when using approximate but unbiased models, and offers predictive tools and design strategies for optimizing half-Heusler chemistries for TE performance.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11644v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Angela Pak, Kamil Ciesielski, Maria Wr\'oblewska, Eric S. Toberer, Elif Ertekin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomistic Modeling of Martensitic Phase Transition in Hexamethylbenzene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11719</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11719v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Materials exhibiting a martensitic phase transition are essential for applications in shape memory alloys, actuators and sensors. Hexamethylbenzene (HMB) has long been considered as a classical example of ferroelastic organic crystals since Mnyukh's pioneering work in 1970s. However, the atomistic mechanism underlying this phase transition has never been clarified. In this work, we present a direct molecular dynamics simulation to investigate the phase transition mechanism in HMB. For the first time, we report a simulation results that can accurately reproduce both the transition temperature and hysteresis loop observed in previous experimental studies. By analyzing the MD trajectories, the potential energy surface, we identified that a low-barrier atomic sliding mode along the close-packed (11$\overline{1}$) plane of the low-temperature phase is the key to trigger the phase transition at the critical temperature window. This is further confirmed by the observed continuous softening of shear modulus around the transition window. Our results demonstrate that the integration of various atomistic modeling techniques can provide invaluable insight into the martensitic phase transition mechanisms in organic crystals and guide the development of new organic martensites.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11719v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zarif Fahim, Pedro A. Santos-Florez, Qiang Zhu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Double-tough ceramics: Optimization-supported multiscale computational design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11728v2 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: To overcome the brittleness limitation of ceramics, various toughening mechanisms have been proposed. Some of the most remarkable, especially for oxides, include the tetragonal-to-monoclinic phase transformation leading to crack shielding in zirconia, and bioinspired brick-and-mortar microstructures fostering crack deflection. It has, however, proven challenging to incorporate both these mechanisms into a single all-ceramic material. In this work, we propose a computational methodology for the design of a material that combines these two toughening strategies, using a multiscale modeling approach that captures both their individual contributions and the overall fracture performance. This is achieved by developing an all-ceramic composite with a brick-and-mortar microstructure, in which the nanocrystalline mortar is transformation-toughened. Key factors influencing phase transformation, such as grain boundary properties, grain orientations, and kinetic coefficients, are analyzed, and the resulting transformation stress-strain behavior is incorporated into the microscale mortar constitutive model. We demonstrate that the synergistic effect of the two toughening mechanisms is achievable, and that it is an extremely effective strategy to boost fracture performance. The influence of brick size, mortar thickness, and properties of the constituent materials is then systematically investigated. Finally, a gradient-free optimization algorithm is employed to identify optimal geometric and material parameters, revealing that longer, thinner bricks with minimal mortar thickness provide the best fracture resistance. Optimal combinations of material properties are identified for given brick sizes and mortar thicknesses.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11728v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jian Zhang, Francesco Aiello, Mauro Salazar, Diletta Giuntini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The critical role of entropy in glass transition kinetics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11857v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Glass transition is a reversible transition that occurs in most amorphous materials. However, the nature of glass transition remains far from being clarified. A key to understand the glass transition is to clarify what determines the glass transition temperature (Tg) and liquid fragility (m). Here the glass transition thermodynamics for 150 different glass-forming systems are studied statistically. It is found that the activation characters in the energy landscape are crucial to precisely portray the glass transition and, in particular, both the activation free energy (G*) and the activation entropy (S*) play critical roles. G* determines Tg, Tg=G*/290+25.5, while S* determines m, m=S*/Rln10+15 with R is gas constant. Based on the Boltzmann definition of entropy, the fragility is an indication of the number of the degeneracy of the evolution paths. This explains why the nano-confined, low-dimension or high-pressured glasses exhibit stronger characteristics, which has been a puzzling phenomenon for a long time.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11857v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lijian Song, Meng Gao, Juntao Huo, Li-Min Wang, Yuanzheng Yue, Jun-Qiang Wang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Development of an uncertainty-aware equation of state for gold</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11878</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11878v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: This study introduces a framework that employs Gaussian Processes (GPs) to develop high-fidelity equation of state (EOS) tables, essential for modeling material properties across varying temperatures and pressures. GPs offer a robust predictive modeling approach and are especially adept at handling uncertainties systematically. By integrating Error-in-Variables (EIV) into the GP model, we adeptly navigate uncertainties in both input parameters (like temperature and density) and output variables (including pressure and other thermodynamic properties). Our methodology is demonstrated using first-principles density functional theory (DFT) data for gold, observing its properties over maximum density compression (up to 100 g/cc) and extreme temperatures within the warm dense matter region (reaching 300 eV). Furthermore, we assess the resilience of our uncertainty propagation within the resultant EOS tables under various conditions, including data scarcity and the intrinsic noise of experiments and simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11878v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lin H. Yang, James A. Gaffney</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybrid Gauge Approach for Accurate Real-Time TDDFT Simulations with Numerical Atomic Orbitals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Ultrafast real-time dynamics are critical for understanding a broad range of physical processes. Real-time time-dependent density functional theory (rt-TDDFT) has emerged as a powerful computational tool for simulating these dynamics, offering insight into untrafast processes and light-matter interactions. In periodic systems, the velocity gauge is essential because it preserves the system's periodicity under an external electric field. Numerical atomic orbitals (NAOs) are widely employed in rt-TDDFT codes due to their efficiency and localized nature. However, directly applying the velocity gauge within the NAO basis set neglects the position-dependent phase variations within atomic orbitals induced by the vector potential, leading to significant computational errors-particularly in current calculations. To resolve this issue, we develop a hybrid gauge that incorporates both the electric field and the vector potential, preserving the essential phase information in atomic orbitals and thereby eliminating these errors. Our benchmark results demonstrate that the hybrid gauge fully resolves the issues encountered with the velocity gauge in NAO-based calculations, providing accurate and reliable results. This algorithm offers a robust framework for future studies on ultrafast dynamics in periodic systems using NAO bases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11961v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haotian Zhao, Lixin He</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ferromagnetic resonance in Y3AlFe4O12 garnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11969</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11969v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin dynamics in Al-substituted yttrium iron garnets is investigated using broadband ferromagnetic resonance measurements in the temperature range T=200-360 K. Using the measured data, the resonance field and linewidth as well as their temperature dependence are determined, with implications for the uniformity and overall quality of the samples prepared via different chemical fabrication routes. These key parameters governing the spin dynamics in the material are important for its applications in high-speed spintronic and magnonic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11969v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Popadiuk, V. Borynskyi, A. Kravets, Y. Shlapa, S. Solopan, A. Belous, A. Tovstolytkin, V. Korenivski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Basic aspects of ferroelectricity induced by noncollinear alignment of spins</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11970v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Basic principles of ferroelectric activity induced by the noncollinear spins are reviewed. There is a fundamental reason why the inversion symmetry can be broken by magnetic order. Such situation occurs when the magnetic order simultaneously involves ferromagnetic ($F$) and antiferromagnetic ($A$) patterns, transforming under the spatial inversion $\mathcal{I}$ and time reversal $\mathcal{T}$ as $\mathcal{I}F=F$ and $\mathcal{IT}A=A$. The incompatibility of these two conditions breaks the inversion symmetry, imposing a constraint on possible dependencies of polarization on directions of spins, which can include only antisymmetric coupling and single-ion anisotropy in the from $\vec{P} = \vec{\boldsymbol{\mathcal{P}}}_{12} [ \boldsymbol{e}_{1} \times \boldsymbol{e}_{2} ] + \boldsymbol{e}_{1} \vec{\mathbb{\Pi}} \boldsymbol{e}_{1} - \boldsymbol{e}_{2} \vec{\mathbb{\Pi}} \boldsymbol{e}_{2}$. $\vec{\boldsymbol{\mathcal{P}}}_{12}$ can be evaluated in the framework of superexchange theory, resulting in $\vec{\boldsymbol{\mathcal{P}}}_{12} \sim \vec{\boldsymbol{r}}_{12}^{\phantom{0}}$, where $\vec{\boldsymbol{r}}_{12}^{\phantom{0}}$ is the part of the position operator produced by the spin-orbit coupling. $\vec{\boldsymbol{r}}_{12}$ remains invariant under $\mathcal{I}$, explaining why noncollinear spins can induce $\vec{P}$ even in the centrosymmetric case. The properties of $\vec{\boldsymbol{r}}_{12}$ are rationalized from the viewpoint of symmetry of the Kramers states. The Katsura-Nagaosa-Balatsky rule $\vec{P} \propto \vec{\epsilon}_{21} \times [\boldsymbol{e}_{1} \times \boldsymbol{e}_{2}]$ ($\vec{\epsilon}_{21}$ being the bond direction) is justified only for relatively high symmetry. The single-ion anisotropy vanishes for the spin 1/2 or if magnetic ions are located in the inversion centers. The properties of known multiferroics are reconsidered from the viewpoint of these principles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11970v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>I. V. Solovyev</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Advanced Spectroscopic Analyses on a:C-H Materials: Revisiting the EELS Characterization and its Coupling with multi-wavelength Raman Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11973</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11973v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hydrogenated amorphous carbon thin films (a:C-H) are very promising materials for numerous applications. The growing of relevance of a:C-H is mainly due to the long-term stability of their outstanding properties. For improving their performances, a full understanding of their local chemistry is highly required. Fifteen years ago, electron energy-loss spectroscopy (EELS), developed in a transmission electron microscope (TEM), was the technique of choice to extract such kind of quantitative information on these materials. Other optical techniques, as Raman spectroscopy, are now clearly favored by the scientific community. However, they still lack of the spatial resolution offered by TEM-EELS. In addition, nowadays, the complexity of the physics phenomena behind EELS is better known. Here, a:C-H thin films have been isothermally annealed and the evolution of their physical and chemical parameters have been monitored at the local and macroscopic scales. In particular, chemical in-depth inhomogeneities and their origins are highlighted. Furthermore, a novel procedure to extract properly and reliably quantitative chemical information from EEL spectra is presented. Finally, the pertinence of empirical models used by the Raman community is discussed. These works demonstrate the pertinence of the combination of local and macroscopic analyses for a proper study of such complex materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11973v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.carbon.2016.10.092</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Carbon Volume 112, February 2017, Pages 149-161 Volume 112, February 2017, Pages 149-161</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>L. Lajaunie, C. Pardanaud, C. Martin, P. Puech, C. Hu, M. J. Biggs, R. Arenal</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Generalized Bond Polarizability model for more accurate atomistic modeling of Raman spectra</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12059v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Raman spectroscopy is an important tool for studies of molecules, liquids and solids. While Raman spectra can be obtained theoretically from molecular dynamics (MD) simulations, this requires the calculation of the electronic polarizability along the simulation trajectory. First-principles calculations of electronic polarizability are computationally expensive, motivating the development of atomistic models for the evaluation of the changes in the electronic polarizability with the changes in the atomic coordinates of the system. The bond polarizability model (BPM) is one of the oldest and simplest such atomistic models, but cannot reproduce the effects of angular vibrations, leading to inaccurate modeling of Raman spectra. Here, we demonstrate that the generalization of BPM through inclusion of terms for atom pairs that are traditionally considered to be not involved in bonding dramatically improves the accuracy of polarizability modeling and Raman spectra calculations. The generalized BPM (GBPM) reproduces the ab initio polarizability and Raman spectra for a range of tested molecules (SO2, H2S, H2O, NH3, CH4, CH3OH and CH3CH2OH) with high accuracy and also shows significantly improved agreement with ab initio results for the more complex ferroelectric BaTiO3 systems. For liquid water, the anisotropic Raman spectrum derived from atomistic MD simulations using GBPM evaluation of polarizability shows significantly improved agreement with the experimental spectrum compared to the spectrum derived using BPM. Thus, GBPM can be used for the modeling of Raman spectra using large-scale molecular dynamics and provides a good basis for the further development of atomistic polarizability models.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12059v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Atanu Paul, Nagaprasad Reddy Samala, Ilya Grinberg</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the thermal transport mechanism in compressed plastic crystals assisted by deep potential</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12078</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12078v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The unique properties of plastic crystals highlight their potential for use in solid-state refrigeration. However, their practical applications are limited by thermal hysteresis due to low thermal conductivity. In this study, the effect of compressive strain on the thermal transport properties of plastic crystal [(CH3)4N][FeCl4] was investigated using molecular dynamic simulation with a deep neural network potential. It is found that a 9% strain along [001] direction enhances thermal conductivity sixfold. The underlying mechanisms are analyzed through vibrational density of states, spectral energy densities, and mean square displacements. The enhancement in thermal conductivity is primarily due to increased group velocity and reduced phonon scattering, driven by volume compression within the 0-1 THz. These findings offer theoretical insights for the practical application of plastic crystals in thermal management systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12078v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yangjun Qin, Zhicheng Zong, Junwei Che, Tianhao Li, Haisheng Fang, Nuo Yang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction chirality reversal with ferromagnetic thickness</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12098</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12098v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: In ultrathin ferromagnetic films sandwiched between two distinct heavy metal layers or between a heavy metal and an oxide layer, the Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction (DMI) is recognized as being of interfacial origin. Its chirality and strength are determined by the properties of the adjacent heavy metals and the degree of oxidation at the interfaces. Here, we demonstrate that the chirality of the DMI can change solely with variations in the thickness of the ferromagnetic layer - an effect that has not been experimentally observed or explained until now. Our experimental observation in the trilayer system Ta/FeCoB/TaOx is supported by ab initio calculations: they reveal that variations in orbital filling and inter-atomic distances at the interface, driven by the number of ferromagnetic atomic layers, lead to an inversion of DMI chirality. This mechanism takes place for ferromagnetic layers with more than three atomic layers, for which the two interfaces start to be decoupled. We hence propose a new degree of freedom to tune DMI chirality and the associated chiral spin textures by tailoring crystal structure e.g. using strain or surface acoustic waves.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12098v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Capucine Gueneau, Fatima Ibrahim, Johanna Fischer, Libor Voj\'a\v{c}ek, Charles-\'Elie Fillion, Stefania Pizzini, Laurent Ranno, Isabelle Joumard, St\'ephane Auffret, J\'er\^ome Faure-Vincent, Claire Baraduc, Mairbek Chshiev, H\'el\`ene B\'ea</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic Metal-Support Interaction Dictates Cu Nanoparticle Sintering on Al$_2$O$_3$ Surfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12283</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12283v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nanoparticle sintering remains a critical challenge in heterogeneous catalysis. In this work, we present a unified deep potential (DP) model for Cu nanoparticles on three Al$_2$O$_3$ surfaces ($\gamma$-Al$_2$O$_3$(100), $\gamma$-Al$_2$O$_3$(110), and $\alpha$-Al$_2$O$_3$(0001)). Using DP-accelerated simulations, we reveal striking facet-dependent nanoparticle stability and mobility patterns across the three surfaces. The nanoparticles diffuse several times faster on $\alpha$-Al$_2$O$_3$(0001) than on $\gamma$-Al$_2$O$_3$(100) at 800 K while expected to be more sluggish based on their larger binding energy at 0 K. Diffusion is facilitated by dynamic metal-support interaction (MSI), where the Al atoms switch out of the surface plane to optimize contact with the nanoparticle and relax back to the plane as the nanoparticle moves away. In contrast, the MSI on $\gamma$-Al$_2$O$_3$(100) and on $\gamma$-Al$_2$O$_3$(110) is dominated by more stable and directional Cu-O bonds, consistent with the limited diffusion observed on these surfaces. Our extended long-time MD simulations provide quantitative insights into the sintering processes, showing that the dispersity of nanoparticles (the initial inter-nanoparticle distance) strongly influences coalescence driven by nanoparticle diffusion. We observed that the coalescence of Cu$_{13}$ nanoparticles on $\alpha$-Al$_2$O$_3$(0001) can occur in a short time (10 ns) at 800 K even with an initial inter-nanoparticle distance increased to 30 \r{A}, while the coalescence on $\gamma$-Al$_2$O$_3$(100) is inhibited significantly by increasing the initial inter-nanoparticle distance from 15 \r{A} to 30 \r{A}. These findings demonstrate that the dynamics of the supporting surface is crucial to understanding the sintering mechanism and offer guidance for designing sinter-resistant catalysts by engineering the support morphology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12283v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiayan Xu, Shreeja Das, Amar Deep Pathak, Abhirup Patra, Sharan Shetty, Detlef Hohl, Roberto Car</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building unconventional magnetic phases on graphene by H atom manipulation: From altermagnets to Lieb ferrimagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12329</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12329v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Engineering all fundamental magnetic phases within a single material platform would mark a significant milestone in materials science and spintronics, reducing complexity and costs in device fabrication by eliminating the need for integrating and interfacing different materials. Here, we demonstrate that graphene can host all non-relativistic magnetic phases-namely, diamagnetism, paramagnetism, ferromagnetism, antiferromagnetism, ferrimagnetism, altermagnetism and fully compensated ferrimagnetism -- by using single hydrogen atoms as building blocks. Through precise manipulation of these atoms by scanning tunneling microscopy, we can experimentally create all such magnetic phases. Their different magnetic character is confirmed by density functional theory and mean-field Hubbard calculations. In particular, we show that the new magnetic paradigm known as altermagnetism can be realized, exhibiting directionally spin-split energy bands coexisting with zero net magnetization due to protecting spatial symmetries. It is furthermore possible to create fully compensated ferrimagnets, lacking these symmetries and therefore presenting unrestricted spin splitting of the bands, with a vanishing net magnetization which in this case is protected by Lieb's theorem. These findings put forward H-functionalized graphene as a versatile platform to design, build and study these new emergent magnetic phases at the atomic scale.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12329v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>B. Vi\~na-Baus\'a, M. A. Garc\'ia-Bl\'azquez, S. Chourasia, R. Carrasco, D. Exp\'osito, I. Brihuega, J. J. Palacios</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Direct imaging of hydrogen-driven dislocation and strain field evolution in a stainless steel grain</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12364</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12364v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Hydrogen embrittlement (HE) poses a significant challenge to the durability of materials used in hydrogen production and utilization. Disentangling the competing nanoscale mechanisms driving HE often relies on simulations and electron-transparent sample techniques, limiting experimental insights into hydrogen-induced dislocation behavior in bulk materials. This study employs in situ Bragg coherent X-ray diffraction imaging to track three-dimensional dislocation and strain field evolution during hydrogen charging in a bulk grain of austenitic 316 stainless steel. Tracking a single dislocation reveals hydrogen-enhanced mobility and relaxation, consistent with dislocation dynamics simulations. Subsequent observations reveal dislocation unpinning and climb processes, likely driven by osmotic forces. Additionally, nanoscale strain analysis around the dislocation core directly measures hydrogen-induced elastic shielding. These findings experimentally validate theoretical predictions and offer mechanistic insights into hydrogen-driven dislocation behavior, paving the way for the design of HE-resistant materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12364v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>David Yang, Mujan Seif, Guanze He, Kay Song, Adrien Morez, Benjamin de Jager, Ross J. Harder, Wonsuk Cha, Edmund Tarleton, Ian K. Robinson, Felix Hofmann</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autonomous Microscopy Experiments through Large Language Model Agents</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10385</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10385v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The emergence of large language models (LLMs) has accelerated the development of self-driving laboratories (SDLs) for materials research. Despite their transformative potential, current SDL implementations rely on rigid, predefined protocols that limit their adaptability to dynamic experimental scenarios across different labs. A significant challenge persists in measuring how effectively AI agents can replicate the adaptive decision-making and experimental intuition of expert scientists. Here, we introduce AILA (Artificially Intelligent Lab Assistant), a framework that automates atomic force microscopy (AFM) through LLM-driven agents. Using AFM as an experimental testbed, we develop AFMBench-a comprehensive evaluation suite that challenges AI agents based on language models like GPT-4o and GPT-3.5 to perform tasks spanning the scientific workflow: from experimental design to results analysis. Our systematic assessment shows that state-of-the-art language models struggle even with basic tasks such as documentation retrieval, leading to a significant decline in performance in multi-agent coordination scenarios. Further, we observe that LLMs exhibit a tendency to not adhere to instructions or even divagate to additional tasks beyond the original request, raising serious concerns regarding safety alignment aspects of AI agents for SDLs. Finally, we demonstrate the application of AILA on increasingly complex experiments open-ended experiments: automated AFM calibration, high-resolution feature detection, and mechanical property measurement. Our findings emphasize the necessity for stringent benchmarking protocols before deploying AI agents as laboratory assistants across scientific disciplines.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10385v1</guid>
      <category>cs.CY</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Indrajeet Mandal, Jitendra Soni, Mohd Zaki, Morten M. Smedskjaer, Katrin Wondraczek, Lothar Wondraczek, Nitya Nand Gosvami, N. M. Anoop Krishnan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Using Domain Knowledge with Deep Learning to Solve Applied Inverse Problems</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10481v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Advancements in deep learning have improved the ability to model complex, nonlinear relationships, such as those encountered in complex material inverse problems. However, the effectiveness of these methods often depends on large datasets, which are not always available. In this study, the incorporation of domain-specific knowledge of mechanical behavior is investigated to evaluate the impact on the predictive performance of the models in data-scarce scenarios. To demonstrate this, stress-strain curves were used to predict key microstructural features of porous materials, and the performance of models trained with and without domain knowledge was compared using five deep learning models: Convolutional Neural Networks, Extreme Gradient Boosting, K-Nearest Neighbors, Long Short-Term Memory, and Random Forest. The results of the models with domain-specific characteristics consistently achieved higher $R^2$ values and improved learning efficiency compared to models without prior knowledge. When the models did not include domain knowledge, the model results revealed meaningful patterns were not recognized, while those enhanced with mechanical insights showed superior feature extraction and predictions. These findings underscore the critical role of domain knowledge in guiding deep learning models, highlighting the need to combine domain expertise with data-driven approaches to achieve reliable and accurate outcomes in materials science and related fields.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10481v1</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.CE</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qinyi Tian, Winston Lindqwister, Manolis Veveakis, Laura E. Dalton</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Non-contact quantitative measurement of thermal Hall angle and transverse thermal conductivity by lock-in thermography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10485v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We propose and demonstrate a non-contact quantitative measurement method for the thermal Hall effect (THE) based on magnetic-field-modulated lock-in thermography. This method enables visualization of THE-induced temperature change and quantitative estimation of the thermal Hall angle $\theta_{\rm THE}$ by applying periodic magnetic fields to a sample and obtaining the first harmonic response of thermal images. By combining this method with LIT-based measurement techniques for the longitudinal thermal conductivity $\kappa_{xx}$, we also quantify the transverse thermal conductivity $\kappa_{xy}$. We validate our measurement methods by estimating $\theta_{\rm THE}$, $\kappa_{xx}$, and $\kappa_{xy}$ in a ferromagnetic Heusler alloy Co$_2$MnGa slab showing large THE.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10485v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takumi Imamura, Takamasa Hirai, Koichi Oyanagi, Ryo Iguchi, Kenta Takamori, Satoru Kobayashi, Ken-ichi Uchida</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Amorphous silicon structures generated using a moment tensor potential and the activation relaxation technique nouveau</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10549</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10549v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Preparing realistic atom-scale models of amorphous silicon (a-Si) is a decades-old condensed matter physics challenge. Herein, we combine the Activation Relaxation Technique nouveau (ARTn) to a Moment Tensor Potential (MTP) to generate seven a-Si models containing between 216 and 4096 atoms. A thorough analysis of their short-range and medium-range structural properties is performed, alongside assessments of excess energy and mechanical properties. The seven ARTn-MTP models are compared with available experimental data and other high quality a-Si models present in the literature. The seven ARTn-MTP a-Si models are in excellent agreement with available experimental data. Notably, several of our models, including the 216-atom, 512-atom, and 1000-atom a-Si models, exhibit low coordination defects without any traces of crystalline grains. Historically overlooked in previous research, our study underlines the need to assess the validity of the continuous random-network hypothesis for the description of perfect amorphous model by characterizing local crystalline environment and to explore the crystallisation process of a-Si through modelling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10549v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Karim Zongo, Hao Sun, Claudiane Ouellet-Plamondon, Normand Mousseau, Laurent Karim B\'eland</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Accurate and thermodynamically consistent hydrogen equation of state for planetary modeling with flow matching</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10594</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10594v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Accurate determination of the equation of state of dense hydrogen is essential for understanding gas giants. Currently, there is still no consensus on methods for calculating its entropy, which play a fundamental role and can result in qualitatively different predictions for Jupiter's interior. Here, we investigate various aspects of entropy calculation for dense hydrogen based on ab initio molecular dynamics simulations. Specifically, we employ the recently developed flow matching method to validate the accuracy of the traditional thermodynamic integration approach. We then clearly identify pitfalls in previous attempts and propose a reliable framework for constructing the hydrogen equation of state, which is accurate and thermodynamically consistent across a wide range of temperature and pressure conditions. This allows us to conclusively address the long-standing discrepancies in Jupiter's adiabat among earlier studies, demonstrating the potential of our approach for providing reliable equations of state of diverse materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10594v1</guid>
      <category>astro-ph.EP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hao Xie, Saburo Howard, Guglielmo Mazzola</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrical and Structural Properties of In-Situ MOCVD Grown Al$_2$O$_3$/$\beta$-Ga$_2$O$_3$ and Al$_2$O$_3$/$\beta$-(Al$_x$Ga$_{1-x}$)$_2$O$_3$ MOSCAPs</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10628</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10628v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This study investigates the electrical and structural properties of MOSCAPs with in-situ MOCVD-grown Al$_2$O$_3$ dielectrics on (010) $\beta$-Ga$_2$O$_3$ and $\beta$-(Al$_x$Ga$_{1-x}$)$_2$O$_3$ films. The Al$_2$O$_3$/$\beta$-Ga$_2$O$_3$ MOSCAPs showed a strong dependence on Al$_2$O$_3$ deposition temperature. At 900$^\circ$C, reduced voltage hysteresis ($\sim$0.3 V) and improved reverse breakdown voltage (74.5 V) were observed, with breakdown fields of 5.01 MV/cm in Al$_2$O$_3$ and 4.11 MV/cm in $\beta$-Ga$_2$O$_3$. At 650$^\circ$C, higher hysteresis ($\sim$3.44 V) and lower reverse breakdown voltage (38.8 V) were observed, with breakdown fields of 3.69 MV/cm in Al$_2$O$_3$ and 2.87 MV/cm in $\beta$-Ga$_2$O$_3$. However, forward breakdown fields improved from 5.62 MV/cm (900$^\circ$C) to 7.25 MV/cm (650$^\circ$C). STEM revealed improved crystallinity and sharper interfaces at 900$^\circ$C, enhancing reverse breakdown performance. For Al$_2$O$_3$/$\beta$-(Al$_x$Ga$_{1-x}$)$_2$O$_3$ MOSCAPs, increasing Al composition ($x$ = 5.5\% to 9.2\%) reduced carrier concentration and improved reverse breakdown fields from 2.55 to 2.90 MV/cm in $\beta$-(Al$_x$Ga$_{1-x}$)$_2$O$_3$ and 2.41 to 3.13 MV/cm in Al$_2$O$_3$. Forward breakdown fields in Al$_2$O$_3$ improved from 5.0 to 5.4 MV/cm as Al composition increased. STEM confirmed compositional homogeneity and excellent stoichiometry of Al$_2$O$_3$ and $\beta$-(Al$_x$Ga$_{1-x}$)$_2$O$_3$ layers. These findings highlight the robust electrical performance, high breakdown fields, and structural quality of Al$_2$O$_3$/$\beta$-Ga$_2$O$_3$ and Al$_2$O$_3$/$\beta$-(Al$_x$Ga$_{1-x}$)$_2$O$_3$ MOSCAPs for high-power applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10628v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A F M Anhar Uddin Bhuiyan, Lingyu Meng, Dong Su Yu, Sushovan Dhara, Hsien-Lien Huang, Vijay Gopal Thirupakuzi Vangipuram, Jinwoo Hwang, Siddharth Rajan, Hongping Zhao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MOFA: Discovering Materials for Carbon Capture with a GenAI- and Simulation-Based Workflow</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10651</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10651v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present MOFA, an open-source generative AI (GenAI) plus simulation workflow for high-throughput generation of metal-organic frameworks (MOFs) on large-scale high-performance computing (HPC) systems. MOFA addresses key challenges in integrating GPU-accelerated computing for GPU-intensive GenAI tasks, including distributed training and inference, alongside CPU- and GPU-optimized tasks for screening and filtering AI-generated MOFs using molecular dynamics, density functional theory, and Monte Carlo simulations. These heterogeneous tasks are unified within an online learning framework that optimizes the utilization of available CPU and GPU resources across HPC systems. Performance metrics from a 450-node (14,400 AMD Zen 3 CPUs + 1800 NVIDIA A100 GPUs) supercomputer run demonstrate that MOFA achieves high-throughput generation of novel MOF structures, with CO$_2$ adsorption capacities ranking among the top 10 in the hypothetical MOF (hMOF) dataset. Furthermore, the production of high-quality MOFs exhibits a linear relationship with the number of nodes utilized. The modular architecture of MOFA will facilitate its integration into other scientific applications that dynamically combine GenAI with large-scale simulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10651v1</guid>
      <category>cs.DC</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaoli Yan, Nathaniel Hudson, Hyun Park, Daniel Grzenda, J. Gregory Pauloski, Marcus Schwarting, Haochen Pan, Hassan Harb, Samuel Foreman, Chris Knight, Tom Gibbs, Kyle Chard, Santanu Chaudhuri, Emad Tajkhorshid, Ian Foster, Mohamad Moosavi, Logan Ward, E. A. Huerta</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multilayered MXenes for future two-dimensional nonvolatile magnetic memories</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10678</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10678v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: MXenes have attracted considerable attention in recent years due to their two-dimensional (2D) layered structure with various functionalities similar to the existing graphene and transition metal dichalcogenides. Aiming to open a new application field for MXenes in the realm of electronic devices such as ultrahigh-integrated magnetic memory, we have developed a spin-orbit torque (SOT) bilayer structure consisting of bare MXene of Cr2N: substrate//Cr2N/[Co/Pt]3/MgO using magnetron sputtering technique. We demonstrate the field-free current-induced magnetization switching (CIMS) in the Hall-cross configuration with the critical current density of ~30 MA/cm2. An attempt to replace the Cr2N layer by the Pt layer leads to the absence of field-free CIMS. As the SOT efficiency increases with increasing the Cr2N thickness, the first-principles calculation predicts the pronounced orbital-Hall conductivity in the out-of-plane component, compared to the spin-Hall conductivity in the Cr2N. X-ray magnetic circular dichroism reveals the out-of-plane uncompensated magnetic moment of Cr in the Cr2N layer at the interface, by contacting with Co in the [Co/Pt]3 ferromagnetic layer. The interfacial spin-filtering-like effect against the out-of-plane polarized spin owing to the uncompensated magnetic moment of Cr might be a possible cause for the field-free CIMS. These results show a significant milestone in the advanced 2D-spintronics, promising low-power and ultrahigh-integration.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10678v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>P. Kumar, Y. Miura, Y. Kotani, A. Sumiyoshiya, T. Nakamura, Gaurav K. Shukla, S. Isogami</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nanowire design by deep learning for energy efficient photonic technologies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.10911</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.10911v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: This work describes our vision and proposal for the design of next generation photonic devices based on custom-designed semiconductor nanowires. The integration of multi-million-atom electronic structure and optical simulations with the supervised machine learning models will pave the way for transformative nanowire-based technologies, offering opportunities for the next generation energy-efficient greener photonics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.10911v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Muhammad Usman</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Refining Au/Sb alloyed ohmic contacts in undoped Si/SiGe strained quantum wells</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11059</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11059v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Shallow undoped Si/SiGe quantum wells are the leading platforms for hosting quantum processors based on spin-qubits. The ohmic contacts to the electron gas in these systems are accomplished by ion-implantation technique since the conventional Au/Sb alloyed contacts present a rough surface consisting of sharp islands and pits. These sharp protrusions cause electrical discharge across the gate-dielectric between the ohmic contacts and the accumulation-gates causing device break-down. A clear understanding of the surface morphology, elemental, compositional and electrical characterization of the alloyed region would enable one to engineer a smoother post alloyed surface. In this work, we find that the rough surface morphology is a cumulative effect of the Au/Si eutectic reaction and the threading dislocations inherent in the heterostructure. The structural, elemental, and chemical-state analysis show that the inverted pyramidal pits are resulting from the enhanced Au/Si eutectic reaction at the threading dislocations stemming from the heterostructure interface, while, the sharp protrusions causing accumulation gate-leakage are gold-rich precipitations. The protrusions are removed using an aqua regia treatment prior to the deposition of the gate-oxide and gate electrode. Exploiting a Hall bar device, we analyse the mobility and carrier concentration of the undoped Si/SiGe consisting of Au/Sb alloyed contacts down to 1.5 K. The measured mobility ~10^5 cm^2/Vs and carrier concentration of ~10^11/cm^2are comparable to the reported values on similar high-mobility heterostructures confirming the efficacy of our modified Au/Sb alloy technique in accomplishing high-efficiency contacts to undoped Si/SiGe heterostructures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11059v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>LuckyDonald L Kynshi, Umang Soni, Chithra H Sharma, Shengqiang Zhou and, Madhu Thalakulam</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superlubric-Locked Transition of Twist Grain Boundaries in 3D Crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11061v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Properties of twist grain boundaries (TGB), long known structurally but not tribologically, are simulated under sliding and load, with Au(111) our test case. The load-free TGB moir\'e is smooth and superlubric at incommensurate twists. Strikingly, load provokes a first-order structural transformation, where the highest energy moir\'e nodes are removed -- an Aubry-type transition for which we provide a Landau theory and a twist-load phase diagram. Upon frictional sliding, the transformation causes a superlubric-locked transition, with a huge friction jump, and irreversible plastic flow. The predicted phenomena are robust, also recovered in a Lennard-Jones lattice TGB, and not exclusive to gold or to metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11061v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jin Wang, Erio Tosatti</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ultrasonic monitoring of carbonation in Portland cements</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11147</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11147v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Chemical reactions resulting from the ingress of carbonates into the cement matrix modify the properties of its pore solution, as well as its pore distribution and size. These changes lead to corrosion of the steel in reinforced concrete. The nature of conventional testing for the estimation of carbonation in cement-based materials is time-consuming and destructive. This paper presents a set of non-destructive ultrasound-based indexes, obtained solely from non-linear and linear analyses of ultrasonic signals, for measuring the carbonation of Portland cement pastes. Class 30RS cement pastes with three water/cement ratios by weight (0.4, 0.5, and 0.6) were considered. Carbonation was carried out for 120 days with a constant CO2 level of 4% by volume under controlled temperature and humidity, considering a unidirectional carbonation, parallel to the longitudinal axis of the samples. The level of carbonation was validated by FTIR measurements. From these analyses, different indexes with high correlation were obtained, estimated only from the ultrasonic signals and as a function of the days of exposure to carbonation, as well as of the percentage of carbonation. Further study is required for the evaluation of the reliability of these promising indexes for the determination of carbonation in cement-based materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11147v1</guid>
      <category>eess.SP</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. Villarreal, P. F. J. Cano-Barrita, F. M. Leon-Martinez, L. Medina, F. Castellanos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Hall effect driven by spin-charge-coupled motive force</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11234</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11234v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Parity-time-reversal symmetric ($\mathcal{PT}$-symmetric) magnets have garnered much attention due to their spin-charge coupled dynamics enriched by the parity-symmetry breaking. By real-time simulations, we study how localized spin dynamics can affect the nonlinear Hall effect in $\mathcal{PT}$-symmetric magnets. To identify the leading-order term, we derive analytical expressions for the second-order optical response and classify the contributions by considering their transformation properties under $\mathcal{PT}$ symmetry. Notably, our results reveal that the sizable contribution is attributed to the mixed dipole effect, which is analogous to the Berry curvature dipole term.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11234v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kohei Hattori, Hikaru Watanabe, Ryotaro Arita</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-throughput calculations of two-dimensional auxetic $M_4X_8$ with magnetism, electrocatalysis, and alkali metal battery applications</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11242</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11242v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) materials with multifunctional properties, such as negative Poisson's ratio (NPR), magnetism, catalysis, and energy storage capabilities, are of significant interest for advanced applications in flexible electronics, spintronics, catalysis, and lithium-ion batteries. However, the discovery of such materials, particularly in low-dimensional forms, remains a challenge. In this study, we perform high-throughput density-functional theory (DFT) calculations to explore a new class of 2D V-shaped monolayers with remarkable physicochemical properties. Among 18 stable $M_4X_8$ (M = transition metal; X = halogen) compounds, we identify 9 auxetic monolayers, with \ce{Pd4I8} standing out for its exceptionally high NPR of -0.798. Notably, 4 of these materials exhibit half semiconductor properties, while 5 others are bipolar magnetic semiconductors, offering a unique combination of electronic and magnetic behavior. Additionally, these materials demonstrate promising catalytic activity for hydrogen and oxygen evolution reactions (HER/OER) and show potential as anodes for rechargeable metal-ion batteries, particularly in alkali-ion systems. This work not only expands the family of 2D NPR materials but also introduces new candidates with multifunctional capabilities for a wide range of applications in nanoelectronics, catalysis, and energy storage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11242v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haidi Wang, Wei Lin, Weiduo Zhu, Zhao Chen, Zhongjun Li, Xiaofeng Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical control of the crystal structure in the bilayer nickelate superconductor La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ via nonlinear phononics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11377</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11377v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Superconductivity in the bilayer nickelate La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ occurs when the interlayer Ni-O-Ni bond angle becomes straight under pressure, suggesting a strong relationship between the crystal structure and the emergence of superconductivity. In this study, we theoretically propose a way to control the crystal structure of La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$ toward the tetragonal symmetry via light irradiation instead of pressure using the idea of nonlinear phononics. Here, resonant optical excitation of an infrared-active (IR) lattice vibration induces a nonlinear Raman-mode displacement through the anharmonic phonon-phonon coupling. We calculate the light-induced phonon dynamics on the anharmonic lattice potential determined by first-principles calculation. We find that the interlayer Ni-O-Ni bond angle gets slightly closer to straight when an appropriate IR mode is selectively excited. Our study suggests that light irradiation can be a promising way for structural control of La$_3$Ni$_2$O$_7$.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11377v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shu Kamiyama, Tatsuya Kaneko, Kazuhiko Kuroki, Masayuki Ochi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Clinically Ready Magnetic Microrobots for Targeted Therapies</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11553</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11553v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Systemic drug administration often causes off-target effects limiting the efficacy of advanced therapies. Targeted drug delivery approaches increase local drug concentrations at the diseased site while minimizing systemic drug exposure. We present a magnetically guided microrobotic drug delivery system capable of precise navigation under physiological conditions. This platform integrates a clinical electromagnetic navigation system, a custom-designed release catheter, and a dissolvable capsule for accurate therapeutic delivery. In vitro tests showed precise navigation in human vasculature models, and in vivo experiments confirmed tracking under fluoroscopy and successful navigation in large animal models. The microrobot balances magnetic material concentration, contrast agent loading, and therapeutic drug capacity, enabling effective hosting of therapeutics despite the integration complexity of its components, offering a promising solution for precise targeted drug delivery.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11553v1</guid>
      <category>cs.RO</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.SY</category>
      <category>eess.SY</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.med-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian C. Landers, Lukas Hertle, Vitaly Pustovalov, Derick Sivakumaran, Oliver Brinkmann, Kirstin Meiners, Pascal Theiler, Valentin Gantenbein, Andrea Veciana, Michael Mattmann, Silas Riss, Simone Gervasoni, Christophe Chautems, Hao Ye, Semih Sevim, Andreas D. Flouris, Josep Puigmart\'i-Luis, Tiago Sotto Mayor, Pedro Alves, Tessa L\"uhmann, Xiangzhong Chen, Nicole Ochsenbein, Ueli Moehrlen, Philipp Gruber, Miriam Weisskopf, Quentin Boehler, Salvador Pan\'e, Bradley J. Nelson</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nanopillar-Driven Antibacterial Surfaces: Elucidating Bactericidal Mechanisms and Engineering Nanostructures for Enhanced Efficacy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11727</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11727v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Insects like dragonflies and cicadas possess nanoprotusions on their wings that rupture bacterial membranes upon contact, inspiring synthetic antibacterial surfaces mimicking this phenomenon. Designing such biomimetic surfaces requires understanding the mechanical interaction between nanopillars and bacterial membranes. However, the small scales of these interactions pose challenges. Molecular Dynamics simulations offer precise and efficient modeling at these scales. This study presents a coarse-grained membrane model to explore the mechanical responses of gram-positive and gram-negative bacterial membranes to nanopillar arrays. By varying bacterial shapes (spherical and cylindrical), membrane bending rigidity, and loading rates, we identified two distinct failure mechanisms. Low bending rigidity, typical of gram-negative bacteria, leads to tearing near nanopillar tips, contrary to prior assumptions. High bending rigidity, characteristic of gram-positive bacteria, results in puncturing at contact points. Gram-positive bacteria are more resistant, requiring a threefold increase in loading rate for effective piercing. Nanopillar height and spacing also critically impact bactericidal efficacy: greater heights enhance activity beyond a critical threshold, while increased spacing reduces efficacy. This simplified coarse-grained model, representing bacterial membranes with high fidelity, enables cost-effective, full-scale simulations over extended periods. Our findings provide essential insights for optimizing nanopillared surface designs, advancing antibacterial technology through tailored height and spacing configurations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11727v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.bio-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Akash Singh, Yi Zhang, Qing Cao, Yumeng Li</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strain induced topological phase transitions in split and line graphs of bipartite lattices featuring flat bands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11783v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In recent years, materials with topological flat bands have attracted significant attention due to their association with extraordinary transport properties and strongly correlated electrons. This includes phenomena such as high-temperature superconductivity, magnetism, Wigner crystallization, and Mott-insulating behavior. Among these systems, two-dimensional (2D) materials are particularly compelling as they can host electronic states with unique band structures, such as dispersionless states alongside linearly dispersive Dirac cones. In this work, we use tight-binding models to comprehensively investigate a class of 2D lattices that generically support flat bands, and focus on the effects of strain on their electronic and topological properties. The studied lattices are constructed within a unifying graph-theoretic framework, whereupon split-graph and line-graph operations on bipartite square and hexagonal lattices are employed to generate new structures. In the absence of strain, the introduction of spin-orbit coupling (SOC) induces a bulk excitation gap, which transforms flat bands into quasi-flat bands with topologically nontrivial characteristics. By tuning system parameters and external strain, we observe the emergence of directional flat bands, and tilted and semi-Dirac cones. Remarkably, all lattices studied show phase transitions among trivial insulating, semimetallic, and topological phases. Our results highlight the potential of strain engineering as a versatile tool for manipulating electronic and topological phases in a wide variety of 2D materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11783v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shivam Sharma, Amartya S. Banerjee</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Room-temperature quantum emission from $\mathrm{Cu_{Zn}}$-$\mathrm{V_{S}}$ defects in ZnS:Cu colloidal nanocrystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.11812</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.11812v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We report room-temperature observations of $\mathrm{Cu_{Zn}}$-$\mathrm{V_{S}}$ quantum emitters in individual ZnS:Cu nanocrystals (NCs). Using time-gated imaging, we isolate the distinct, $\sim$3-$\mu$s-long, red photoluminescence (PL) emission of $\mathrm{Cu_{Zn}}$-$\mathrm{V_{S}}$ defects, enabling their precise identification and statistical characterization. The emitters exhibit distinct blinking and photon antibunching, consistent with individual NCs containing two to four $\mathrm{Cu_{Zn}}$-$\mathrm{V_{S}}$ defects. The quantum emitters' PL spectra show a pronounced blue shift compared to NC dispersions, likely due to photochemical and charging effects. Emission polarization measurements of quantum emitters are consistent with a $\sigma$-character optical dipole transition and the symmetry of the $\mathrm{Cu_{Zn}}$-$\mathrm{V_{S}}$ defect. These observations motivate further investigation of $\mathrm{Cu_{Zn}}$-$\mathrm{V_{S}}$ defects in ZnS NCs for use in quantum technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.11812v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yossef E. Panfil, Sarah M. Thompson, Gary Chen, Jonah Ng, Cherie R. Kagan, Lee C. Bassett</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quantum Dynamics of Dissipative Polarizable Media</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12070</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12070v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Classical polarizable approaches have become the gold standard for simulating complex systems and processes in the condensed phase. These methods describe intrinsically dissipative polarizable media, requiring a formal definition within the framework of open quantum systems. We present a Hamiltonian formulation for the quantum dynamics of polarizable sources based on a generalized theory of the damped harmonic oscillator, using pseudo-boson theory to characterize their coherent state dynamics. Exploiting the phase space formulation of quantum mechanics and the integrability of quadratic Hamiltonians, we derive a self-consistent relation for the emitted electric field of the polarizable medium under the semiclassical approximation, based on exact formulas for medium polarization. Finally, we derive the master equation describing the open dynamics of a quantum system interacting with the quantum polarizable medium, along with analytical expressions for correlation functions calculated over arbitrary Gaussian states.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12070v1</guid>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Frank Ernesto Quintela Rodriguez, Piero Lafiosca, Tommaso Giovannini, Chiara Cappelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the practical applicability of modern DFT functionals for chemical computations. Case study of DM21 applicability for geometry optimization</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12149</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12149v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Density functional theory (DFT) is probably the most promising approach for quantum chemistry calculations considering its good balance between calculations precision and speed. In recent years, several neural network-based functionals have been developed for exchange-correlation energy approximation in DFT, DM21 developed by Google Deepmind being the most notable between them. This study focuses on evaluating the efficiency of DM21 functional in predicting molecular geometries, with a focus on the influence of oscillatory behavior in neural network exchange-correlation functionals. We implemented geometry optimization in PySCF for the DM21 functional in geometry optimization problem, compared its performance with traditional functionals, and tested it on various benchmarks. Our findings reveal both the potential and the current challenges of using neural network functionals for geometry optimization in DFT. We propose a solution extending the practical applicability of such functionals and allowing to model new substances with their help.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12149v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kirill Kulaev, Alexander Ryabov, Michael Medvedev, Evgeny Burnaev, Vladimir Vanovskiy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Magnetic Trampoline Resonators from (La,Sr)MnO3 Single-Crystal Thin Films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12177</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12177v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Micro-electro-mechanical resonators employing a magnetic element have been proposed for magnetic field sensing applications, but the integration of magnetic materials with standard semiconductor compounds is challenging and requires complex fabrication protocols. We present a different approach relying on (La0.7,Sr0.3)MnO3 (LSMO), an oxide compound that works both as structural element for the resonator and functional magnetic layer. Suspended trampolines are realized in a single step process from LSMO thin films and show quality factor up to 60k and fQ products reaching 10$^{10}$ Hz. Their magnetic properties are probed by a SQUID magnetometer and magnetic force microscopy, showing saturation magnetization of 240 kA/m at room temperature and in-plane magnetic domains with coercivity of 2.5 mT. Being entirely made from a magnetic material, these resonators exhibit a larger magnetic interaction volume compared to other solutions, making them ideal candidates as building blocks for high-sensitivity magnetic field sensors.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12177v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nicola Manca, Dhavalkumar Mungpara, Leon\'elio Cichetto Jr., Alejandro E. Plaza, Gianrico Lamura, Alexander Schwarz, Daniele Marr\'e, Luca Pellegrino</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Strong phonon-mediated high temperature superconductivity in Li$_2$AuH$_6$ under ambient pressure</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12222</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12222v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We used our developed AI search engine~(InvDesFlow) to perform extensive investigations regarding ambient stable superconducting hydrides. A cubic structure Li$_2$AuH$_6$ with Au-H octahedral motifs is identified to be a candidate. After performing thermodynamical analysis, we provide a feasible route to experimentally synthesize this material via the known LiAu and LiH compounds under ambient pressure. The further first-principles calculations suggest that Li$_2$AuH$_6$ shows a high superconducting transition temperature ($T_c$) $\sim$ 140 K under ambient pressure. The H-1$s$ electrons strongly couple with phonon modes of vibrations of Au-H octahedrons as well as vibrations of Li atoms, where the latter is not taken seriously in other previously similar cases. Hence, different from previous claims of searching metallic covalent bonds to find high-$T_c$ superconductors, we emphasize here the importance of those phonon modes with strong electron-phonon coupling (EPC). And we suggest that one can intercalate atoms into binary or ternary hydrides to introduce more potential phonon modes with strong EPC, which is an effective approach to find high-$T_c$ superconductors within multicomponent compounds.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12222v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhenfeng Ouyang, Bo-Wen Yao, Xiao-Qi Han, Peng-Jie Guo, Ze-Feng Gao, Zhong-Yi Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Charge-density-wave quantum critical point under pressure in 2$H$-TaSe$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.12315</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.12315v2 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Suppressing of an ordered state that competes with superconductivity is one route to enhance superconducting transition temperatures. Whereas the effect of suppressing magnetic states is still not fully understood, materials featuring charge-density waves and superconductivity offer a clearer scenario as both states can be associated with electron-phonon coupling. Metallic transition-metal dichalcogenides are prime examples for such intertwined electron-phonon-driven phases, yet, various compounds do not show the expected interrelation or feature additional mechanisms which makes an unambiguous interpretation difficult. Here, we report high-pressure X-ray diffraction and inelastic X-ray scattering measurements of the prototypical transition-metal dichalcogenide 2$H$-TaSe$_2$ and determine the evolution of the charge-density-wave state and its lattice dynamics up to and beyond its suppression at the critical pressure $p_c = 19.9(1)\,\rm{GPa}$ and at low temperatures. The high quality of our data allows the full refinement of the commensurate charge-density-wave superstructure at low pressure and we find the quantum critical point of the charge-density-wave to be in close vicinity to the reported maximum superconducting transition temperature $T_{sc} = 8.2\,\rm{K}$. $Ab-initio$ calculations corroborate that 2$H$-TaSe$_2$ is a reference example of order-suppressed enhanced superconductivity and can serve as a textbook case to investigate superconductivity near a charge-density-wave quantum critical point.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.12315v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuliia Tymoshenko, Amir-Abbas Haghighirad, Rolf Heid, Tom Lacmann, Alsu Ivashko, Adrian Merritt, Xingchen Shen, Michael Merz, Gaston Garbarino, Luigi Paolasini, Alexei Bosak, Florian K. Diekmann, Kai Rossnagel, Stephan Rosenkranz, Ayman H. Said, Frank Weber</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Prediction and observation of the first antiferromagnetic topological insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1809.07389</link>
      <description>arXiv:1809.07389v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Magnetic topological insulators (MTIs) are narrow gap semiconductor materials that combine non-trivial band topology and magnetic order. Unlike their nonmagnetic counterparts, MTIs may have some of the surfaces gapped due to breaking the time-reversal symmetry, which enables a number of exotic phenomena having potential applications in spintronics. So far, MTIs have only been created by means of doping nonmagnetic TIs with 3d transition metal elements, however, such an approach leads to strongly inhomogeneous magnetic and electronic properties of these materials, restricting the observation of important effects to very low temperatures. Finding intrinsic MTI, i.e. a stoichiometric well-ordered magnetic compound, could be an ideal solution to these problems, but no such material was observed to date. Here, using density functional theory we predict and further confirm by means of structural, transport, magnetic, angle- and spin-resolved photoemission spectroscopy measurements the realization of the antiferromagnetic (AFM) TI phase, that is hosted by the van der Waals layered compound MnBi$_2$Te$_4$. An interlayer AFM ordering makes MnBi$_2$Te$_4$ invariant with respect to the combination of the time-reversal ($\Theta$) and primitive-lattice translation ($T_{1/2}$) symmetries, $S = \Theta T_{1/2}$, giving rise to the $Z_2$ topological classification of AFM insulators. We find $Z_2 = 1$ for MnBi$_2$Te$_4$, which confirms its topologically nontrivial nature. The $S$-breaking (0001) surface of MnBi$_2$Te$_4$ exhibits a giant bandgap in the topological surface state as evidenced by ab initio calculations and photoemission measurements. These results culminate almost a decade-long search of an AFMTI, predicted in 2010. Furthermore, MnBi$_2$Te$_4$ is the first intrinsic magnetic TI realized experimentally.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1809.07389v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41586-019-1840-9</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature 576, 416-422 (2019)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail M. Otrokov, Ilya I. Klimovskikh, Hendrik Bentmann, Dmitry Estyunin, Alexander Zeugner, Ziya S. Aliev, Sebastian Gass, Anja U. B. Wolter, Alexandra V. Koroleva, Alexander M. Shikin, Mar\'ia Blanco-Rey, Martin Hoffmann, Igor P. Rusinov, Alexandra Yu. Vyazovskaya, Sergey V. Eremeev, Yury M. Koroteev, V. M. Kuznetsov, F. Freyse, J. S\'anchez-Barriga, Imamaddin R. Amiraslanov, Mahammad B. Babanly, Nazim T. Mamedov, Nadir A. Abdullayev, Vladimir N. Zverev, Alexey Alfonsov, Vladislav Kataev, Bernd B\"uchner, Eike F. Schwier, Shiv Kumar, Akio Kimura, Luca Petaccia, Giovanni Di Santo, Raphael C. Vidal, Sonja Schatz, Katharina Ki{\ss}ner, M. \"Unzelmann, Chul-Hee Min, Simon K. Moser, Thiago R. F. Peixoto, Friedrich Reinert, Arthur Ernst, Pedro M. Echenique, Anna Isaeva, Evgueni V. Chulkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrochemically induced switching from antiferromagnetic spin-chain to frustrated spin-glass state in maple-leaf lattice Na2Mn3O7</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.10399</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.10399v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the electrochemical tuning of magnetic properties in the Na2Mn3O7 maple-leaf lattice (MLL) through ion deintercalation, revealing a switch from the 1D antiferromagnetic (AFM) spin-chain behavior of the S=3/2 MLL structure to frustrated magnetism spin-glass behavior. By utilizing Na deintercalation, we stabilize ferromagnetic (FM) short-range interactions within the original short-range AFM system, creating magnetic frustration within the system beyond that induced from the MLL geometrically frustrated structure, leading to a spin-glass state. Magnetic and structural analyses, combined with density functional theory (DFT) calculations, demonstrate the near-degeneracy between AFM and FM configurations in Na2Mn3O7, suggesting that the altered lattice distortions and disorder introduced via deintercalation are responsible for the frustrated magnetism. Our findings provide a novel platform for studying low-dimensional magnetism, spin glass behavior, and potential applications in spintronics and computing technologies. This study represents the first observation of an induced spin glass state in MLL materials and is a rare example of electrochemically induced spin glass state, highlighting the critical role of ion intercalation in tuning magnetic interactions.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.10399v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Corson Chao, Shivani Srivastava, Ming Lei, Bachu Sravan Kumar, Varun Kamboj, Hari Ramachandran, Zhelong Jiang, Anirudh Adavi, Kevin H. Stone, Mark Asta, Lilia S. Xie, Iwnetim I. Abate</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Data-driven Investigation of Cotton Fabric Behavior Modified by Straight and Zig-Zag Stitches</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2301.13270</link>
      <description>arXiv:2301.13270v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, we demonstrate a data-driven approach to investigate the behavior of cotton fabric modified by straight and zig-zag stitches. Existing literature in understanding the mechanical behavior of soft materials (e.g., textile-based fibers or fabrics) heavily relies on stress-strain analyses. However, the strain-induced deformation behavior can be further analyzed by taking advantage of data-driven constitutive models. Such an approach reveals intermolecular parameters that can be utilized further in design and development analyses. For that, we exhibit the altered mechanics of base cotton fabric induced by two types of singular stitches (straight and zig-zag). We have sewn simple straight and zig-zag cotton stitches to investigate the mechanics of the base cotton fabrics using uniaxial stress-strain experimental data. Then, we leveraged the constitutive models (i.e., three-network model, TNM) obtained from MCalibration software to reveal eleven intermolecular parameters for data-driven investigations. Our experimental analyses, combined with the data, suggest a 99.99% confidence in assessing the mechanical impact of stitches on cotton fabrics. We have also used distributed strain energy to analyze the mechanics and failure of the base and stitched fabrics. Once adopted, our study may contribute to an improved understanding of the production of smart wearables and e-textiles.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2301.13270v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Harmony Werth, Kazi Zihan Hossain, Momena Monwar, M. Rashed Khan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emergent Atomic Environments in Twisted Bilayer Graphene and Their Use in the Prediction of the Vibrational Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.12864</link>
      <description>arXiv:2312.12864v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: While Bernal stacked bilayer graphene bears two distinct atom types in its lattice, there exists no analytical framework addressing the number of atomic environments that emerge in twisted bilayer graphene superlattices. Here, we computationally analyze 140 different twisted bilayer superlattices using descriptor functions to study the emergent local environments. Our study reveals that the number of atoms with unique local environments depend on the superlattice size linearly manifesting itself on two distinct lines in accordance with the respective space groups. We then introduce the use of local environments in the investigation of vibrational properties. Local phonon density of states of the atoms with unique local environments are calculated by molecular dynamics simulations and are used to train a machine learning model. This model is used to predict the phonon density of states of twisted bilayer structures. Performance of the trained model is cross validated and discussed thoroughly via different selection of training and test sets. It is shown that the model proves effective in predicting the vibrational properties of any given twisted bilayer structure. Since the generic method presented reaches far beyond twisted bilayer graphene the possible applications ranging from non-periodic structures to strain induced moir\'e superlattices are also discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2312.12864v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Dilara Ickecan, Yunus Emre Okyayli, Erdi Ata Bleda, Dogan Erbahar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Proximity-induced flipped spin state in synthetic ferrimagnetic Pt/Co/Gd heterolayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.04655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.04655v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: To develop new devices based on synthetic ferrimagnetic heterostructures, understanding the material's physical properties is pivotal. Here, the induced magnetic moment (IMM), magnetic exchange coupling, and spin textures are investigated in Pt(1 nm)/Co(1.5 nm)/Gd(1 nm) multilayers using a multiscale approach. The magnitude and direction of the IMM are interpreted in the framework of both X-ray magnetic circular dichroism and density functional theory. The IMM transferred by Co across the Gd paramagnetic thickness leads to a nontrivial flipped spin state (FSS) within the Gd layers, in which their magnetic moments couple antiparallel/parallel with the ferromagnetic Co near/far from the Co/Gd interface, respectively. The FSS depends on the magnetic field, which, on average, reduces the Gd magnetic moment as the field increases. For the Pt, in both Pt/Co and Gd/Pt interfaces, the IMM follows the same direction as the Co magnetic moment, with negligible IMM in the Gd/Pt interface. Additionally, zero-field spin spirals were imaged using scanning transmission X-ray microscopy, whereas micromagnetic simulations were employed to unfold the interactions, stabilizing the ferrimagnetic configurations, where the existence of a sizable Dzyaloshinskii-Moriya interaction is demonstrated to be crucial.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.04655v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>J. Brand\~ao, P. C. Carvalho, I. P. Miranda, T. J. A. Mori, F. B\'eron, A. Bergman, H. M. Petrilli, A. B. Klautau, J. C. Cezar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Building Workflows for Interactive Human in the Loop Automated Experiment (hAE) in STEM-EELS</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.07381</link>
      <description>arXiv:2404.07381v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Exploring the structural, chemical, and physical properties of matter on the nano- and atomic scales has become possible with the recent advances in aberration-corrected electron energy-loss spectroscopy (EELS) in scanning transmission electron microscopy (STEM). However, the current paradigm of STEM-EELS relies on the classical rectangular grid sampling, in which all surface regions are assumed to be of equal a priori interest. This is typically not the case for real-world scenarios, where phenomena of interest are concentrated in a small number of spatial locations. One of foundational problems is the discovery of nanometer- or atomic scale structures having specific signatures in EELS spectra. Here we systematically explore the hyperparameters controlling deep kernel learning (DKL) discovery workflows for STEM-EELS and identify the role of the local structural descriptors and acquisition functions on the experiment progression. In agreement with actual experiment, we observe that for certain parameter combinations the experiment path can be trapped in the local minima. We demonstrate the approaches for monitoring automated experiment in the real and feature space of the system and monitor knowledge acquisition of the DKL model. Based on these, we construct intervention strategies, thus defining human-in the loop automated experiment (hAE). This approach can be further extended to other techniques including 4D STEM and other forms of spectroscopic imaging.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2404.07381v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.HC</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Utkarsh Pratiush, Kevin M. Roccapriore, Yongtao Liu, Gerd Duscher, Maxim Ziatdinov, Sergei V. Kalinin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Nanowire Morphological Instability and Pinch-Off by Surface Electromigration</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2405.01331</link>
      <description>arXiv:2405.01331v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Surface diffusion and surface electromigration may lead to a morphological instability of thin solid films and nanowires. In this paper two nonlinear analyses of a morphological instability are developed for a single-crystal cylindrical nanowire that is subjected to an axial current. These treatments extend the conventional linear stability analyses without surface electromigration, that manifest a Rayleigh-Plateau instability. A weakly nonlinear analysis is done slightly above the Rayleigh-Plateau (longwave) instability threshold. It results in a one-dimensional Sivashinsky amplitude equation that describes a blow-up of a surface perturbation amplitude in a finite time. This is a signature of a pinching singularity of a cylinder radius, which leads to a wire separation into a disjoint segments. The time- and electric field-dependent dimensions of the focusing self-similar amplitude profile approaching a blow-up are characterized via the scaling analysis. Also, a weakly nonlinear multi-scale analysis is done at the arbitrary distance above a longwave or a shortwave instability threshold. The time- and electric field-dependent Fourier amplitudes of the major instability modes are derived and characterized.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2405.01331v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mikhail Khenner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-temperature threshold of damage of SiC by swift heavy ions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.07963</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.07963v4 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: At ambient conditions, SiC is known to be resistant to irradiation with swift heavy ions (SHI) decelerating in the electronic stopping regime. However, there is no experimental data on the SiC irradiation at elevated temperatures. To investigate this problem, we evaluate the stability of SiC to SHI impacts at high temperatures up to 2200 K. We apply the combination of the Monte-Carlo code TREKIS-3, describing excitation of the electronic and atomic systems using temperature-dependent scattering cross-sections, with molecular-dynamic modeling of the lattice response to the excitation. We demonstrate that increasing irradiation temperature increases the energy transferred to the atomic lattice from the excited electronic system. This material heating leads to formation of a stable nanometric damaged core along the trajectory of 710 MeV Bi ion when the irradiation temperature overcomes the threshold of ~1800 K. In this case, a chain of nanometric voids along the ion trajectory forms due to the mass transport from the track core by edge dislocations. Voids of larger sizes appear at higher irradiation temperatures. At lower irradiation temperatures, the damaged regions recrystallize completely within ~100 ps after the ion passage.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.07963v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jallcom.2025.178524</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>J. Alloys Compd. 1013 (2025) 178524</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>D. I. Zainutdinov, V. A. Borodin, S. A. Gorbunov, N. Medvedev, R. A. Rymzhanov, M. V. Sorokin, R. A. Voronkov, A. E. Volkov</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Additively manufacturable high-strength aluminum alloys with thermally stable microstructures enabled by hybrid machine learning-based design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.17457</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.17457v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Additively manufactured (AM) aluminum alloys with high strength and thermal stability have broad applications in turbine engines, vacuum pumps, heat exchangers, and many other industrial systems. Employing precipitates with an L1$_2$ structure to block dislocation motions is a widespread strategy to strengthen aluminum. However, to achieve high strength, a high volume fraction of small precipitates is required, and these characteristics are generally mutually exclusive. Here, we show that for certain compositions of Al alloys, L1$_2$ phases initially precipitate as sub-micron metastable ternary phases under the rapid solidification conditions of powder bed AM, yet the subsequent L1$_2$ phases that precipitate during heat treatment of the sample remain at the nanoscale, imparting high strength. For strength to be retained at elevated temperature, these nanoprecipitates must have low coarsening rates. To inversely design the composition of an alloy to have these target microstructural features, we used hybrid calculation of phase diagram (CALPHAD)-based integrated computational materials engineering (ICME) and Bayesian optimization techniques. We tested our approach by designing an Al-Er-Zr-Y-Yb-Ni model alloy, and the selected composition was manufactured in powder form as AM feedstock. The strength of specimens manufactured via laser powder bed fusion (LPBF) from the designed composition is comparable to that of wrought Al 7075, yet without cracking that occurs upon LPBF of Al 7075. After high-temperature (400$^\circ$C) aging the designed alloy is 50% stronger than the strongest known benchmark printable Al alloy.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.17457v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Mohadeseh Taheri-Mousavi, Michael Xu, Florian Hengsbach, Clay Houser, Zhaoxuan Ge, Benjamin Glaser, Shaolou Wei, Mikro Schaper, James M. LeBeau, Greg B. Olson, A. John Hart</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orientation reconstruction of transformation $\alpha$ titanium alloys via polarized light microscopy: methodology and assessment</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.20014</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.20014v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Emerging microstructural characterization methods have received increased attention owing to their promise of relatively inexpensive and rapid measurement of polycrystalline surface morphology and crystallographic orientations. Among these nascent methods, polarized light microscopy (PLM) is attractive for characterizing alloys comprised of hexagonal crystals, but is hindered by its inability to measure complete crystal orientations. In this study, we explore the potential to reconstruct quasi-deterministic orientations for titanium microstructures characterized via PLM by considering the Burgers orientation relationship between the room temperature $\alpha$ (HCP) phase fibers measured via PLM, and the $\beta$ (BCC) phase orientations of the parent grains present above the transus temperature. We describe this method -- which is capable of narrowing down the orientations to one of four possibilities -- and demonstrate its abilities on idealized computational samples in which the parent $\beta$ microstructure is fully, unambiguously known. We further utilize this method to inform the instantiation of samples for crystal plasticity simulations, and demonstrate the significant improvement in deformation field predictions when utilizing this reconstruction method compared to using results from traditional PLM.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.20014v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Amit Singh, Mark Obstalecki, Darren C. Pagan, Michael Glavicic, Matthew Kasemer</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact formula with two dynamically screened electron-phonon couplings for positive phonon-linewidths approximations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12285</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.12285v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this paper, we present an exact formula for the phonon linewidths involving only dressed electron-phonon couplings and ensuring the positivity property. The formula is designed to account for both nonadiabatic and correlation effects, and it provides an alternative proof that Density Functional Perturbation Theory calculations of phonon linewidths are not affected by a double counting of screening diagrams. Furthermore, we extend the treatment to nonequilibrium scenarios and offer a rigorous justification for employing the phononic Boltzmann equation.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.12285v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review B 111, 024307 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Gianluca Stefanucci, Enrico Perfetto</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Twin branching in shape memory alloys: a 1D model with energy dissipation effects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.07382</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.07382v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We develop a 1D model of twin branching in shape memory alloys. The free energy of the branched microstructure comprises the interfacial and elastic strain energy contributions, both expressed in terms of the average twin spacing treated as a continuous function of the position. The total free energy is then minimized, and the corresponding Euler-Lagrange equation is solved numerically using the finite element method. The model can be considered as a continuous counterpart of the recent discrete model of Seiner et al. (2020), and our results show a very good agreement with that model in the entire range of physically relevant parameters. Furthermore, our continuous setting facilitates incorporation of energy dissipation into the model. The effect of rate-independent dissipation on the evolution of the branched microstructure is thus studied. The results show that significant effects on the microstructure and energy of the system are expected only for relatively small domain sizes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.07382v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Stanislaw Stupkiewicz, Seyedshoja Amini, Mohsen Rezaee-Hajidehi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing the phonon bottleneck limit in negatively charged CdS quantum dots</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.17365</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.17365v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The capture of photoexcited hot electrons in semiconductors before they lose their excess energy to cooling is a long-standing goal in photon energy conversion. Semiconductor nanocrystals have large electron energy spacings that are expected to slow down electron relaxation by phonon emission, but hot electrons in photoexcited nanocrystals nevertheless cool rapidly by energy transfer to holes. This makes the intrinsic phonon-bottleneck limited electron lifetime in nanocrystals elusive. We used a combination of theory and experiments to probe the hot electron dynamics of negatively charged Cadmium Sulfide (CdS) colloidal quantum dots (QDs) in the absence of holes. Experiments found that these hot electrons cooled on a 100 ps timescale. Theoretical simulations predicted that pure phonon-bottleneck limited electron cooling occurs on a similar timescale. This similarity suggests that the experimental measurements reflect the upper limit on hot electron lifetimes in these CdS QDs and the lower limit on the rates of processes that can harvest those hot electrons.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.17365v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Skylar J. Sherman, Bokang Hou, Matthew J. Coley-O'Rourke, Katherine E. Shulenberger, Lauren Pellows, Eran Rabani, Gordana Dukovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-order van Hove singularities and nematic instability in the kagome superconductor CsTi$_3$Bi$_5$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.20944</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.20944v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: ATi$_3$Bi$_5$ (A = Cs or Rb) are emerging topological kagome metals that exhibit superconductivity and nematicity without intertwining translational symmetry-breaking charge orders. In this work, we explore the fermiology of their titanium kagome electrons and identify a set of sublattice-pure, high-order van Hove singularities (VHSs) that can suppress charge ordering and enhance electronic correlations and superconductivity. Our calculations of charge susceptibility for kagome bands with both normal and high-order VHSs emphasize the role of these VHSs in driving electronic nematicity in CsTi$_3$Bi$_5$. Additionally, we compute the phonon spectrum and electron-phonon interactions for CsTi$_3$Bi$_5$ under pristine, doped, and kagome-exposed surface conditions, revealing its robustness against structural instabilities while enhancing the superconducting transition temperature. Our work positions ATi$_3$Bi$_5$ as a key platform for investigating superconductivity and electronic nematicity without translational symmetry-breaking states in kagome metals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.20944v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.045135</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 045135 (2025) [Editors' Suggestion]</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Bikash Patra, Amrita Mukherjee, Bahadur Singh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Variational formulation of dynamical electronic response functions in presence of nonlocal exchange interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.22889</link>
      <description>arXiv:2410.22889v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We consider the dynamical electronic response function in theoretical frameworks that include nonlocal exchange interactions, such as the Bethe-Salpeter equation with the frequency independent approximation of the screened interaction, Hartree-Fock, and range-separated Hybrid DFT approaches. Within these pictures, we demonstrate that any time-dependent electronic linear response function allows for a formulation which is variational in the electronic density matrix. To achieve our goal, we consider the usual form of a response function, written in terms of a screened and a bare electronic vertices (`bare-screen'), and perform an exact rewriting in terms of purely screened electronic vertices (`screen-screen'). Within the `screen-screen' formulation, the response function can be written as a stationary point of a functional of the exact density matrix. Further, we show that the imaginary part of any electronic response can be written in the form of a generalized Fermi Golden Rule, by introducing an exact complementary rewriting in terms of vertices related by complex conjugation (`screen*-screen'). The screen-screen formulation can be further extended partitioning the electronic interaction in separate contributions, expressing the response in terms of partially screened electronic vertices (`partial screen-partial screen'), preserving the stationary properties. We numerically validate the effectiveness of our formalism by calculating the optical conductivity of graphene, which exhibits strong excitonic effects. To do so, we solve the Bethe-Salpeter Equation on a tight-binding model, including exchange effects in the response of graphene. Our findings show the advantages of the variationality of the screen-screen formulation over the others both in convergence properties and robustness with density-matrix approximations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2410.22889v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Giovanni Caldarelli, Alberto Guandalini, Francesco Macheda, Francesco Mauri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rational Design Heterobilayers Photocatalysts for Efficient Water Splitting Based on 2D Transition-Metal Dichalcogenide and Their Janus</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03396</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03396v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Direct Z-scheme heterobilayers with enhanced redox potential are viewed as promising for solar-driven water splitting, arising from the synergy between intrinsic dipoles in Janus materials and interfacial electric fields across the layers. This study explores 20 two-dimensional Janus transition-metal dichalcogenide (TMDC) heterobilayers for efficient water splitting. Using density-functional theory (DFT) calculations, we screen them based on band gaps and intrinsic electric fields to identify promising candidates, then further assess carrier mobility and surface chemistry to fully evaluate their overall performance. By examining the alignment of synthetic and internal electric fields, we distinguish between Type-I, Type-II, and Z-scheme configurations, enabling the targeted design of optimal photocatalytic materials. Furthermore, we employ the Fr\"{o}hlich interaction model to quantify the mobility contributions from the longitudinal optical phonon mode, providing detailed insights into how carrier mobility, influenced by phonon scattering, affects photocatalytic performance. Our findings demonstrate the potential of Janus-based Z-scheme systems to overcome existing limitations in photocatalytic water splitting by optimizing the electronic and structural properties of 2D materials, highlighting a viable pathway for advancing clean energy generation through enhanced photocatalytic processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03396v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nguyen Tran Gia Bao, Ton Nu Quynh Trang, Nam Thoai, Phan Bach Thang, Vu Thi Hanh Thu, Nguyen Tuan Hung</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flexible and Efficient Semi-Empirical DFTB Parameters for Electronic Structure Prediction of 3D, 2D Iodide Perovskites and Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.07016</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.07016v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Density Functional Tight-Binding (DFTB), an approximative approach derived from Density Functional Theory (DFT), has the potential to pave the way for simulations of large periodic or non-periodic systems. We have specifically tailored DFTB parameters to enhance the accuracy of electronic band gap calculations in both 3D and 2D lead-iodide perovskites, at a significantly reduced computational cost relative to state-of-the-art ab initio calculations. Our electronic DFTB parameters allow computing not only the band gap but also effective masses of perovskite materials with reasonable accuracy compared to existing experimental data and state-of-the-art DFT calculations. The electronic band structures of vacancy-ordered and, lead- and iodide- deficient perovskites are also explored. Additionally, we demonstrate the efficiency of DFTB in computing electronic band alignments in perovskite heterostructures. The DFTB-based approach is anticipated to be beneficial for studying large-scale systems such as heterostructures and nanocrystals.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.07016v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junke Jiang, Tammo van der Heide, Simon Th\'ebaud, Carlos Ra\'ul Lien-Medrano, Arnaud Fihey, Laurent Pedesseau, Claudio Quarti, Marios Zacharias, George Volonakis, Mikael Kepenekian, B\'alint Aradi, Michael A. Sentef, Jacky Even, Claudine Katan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamical electron-phonon vertex correction</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01866</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01866v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The dynamical screening of the electron--phonon vertex is caused by the retarded oscillations of the electronic charge following the electron--hole scattering with a phonon mode. This retardation induces a frequency dependence of the electron--phonon interaction. Model Hamiltonians and {\em ab--initio} approaches have instilled the idea that this retardation is, in most of the cases, negligible. In this work I demonstrate that the dynamical screening of the electron--phonon vertex cannot be neglected {\em a priori}. By using a perturbative expansion I introduce a controllable and physically sound method to evaluate and include dynamical screening effects. Based on the exact results of the homogeneous electron gas I propose a dynamical vertex correction function $\Gamma_{e-p}(\omega)$ designed to screen the commonly used adiabatic electron--phonon interaction. This function is expressed in terms of adiabatic quantities, that can be easily calculated and used to evaluate the strength of the dynamical corrections, even in realistic materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01866v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andrea Marini</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ABACUS: An Electronic Structure Analysis Package for the AI Era</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.08697</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.08697v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: ABACUS (Atomic-orbital Based Ab-initio Computation at USTC) is an open-source software for first-principles electronic structure calculations and molecular dynamics simulations. It mainly features density functional theory (DFT) and is compatible with both plane-wave basis sets and numerical atomic orbital basis sets. ABACUS serves as a platform that facilitates the integration of various electronic structure methods, such as Kohn-Sham DFT, stochastic DFT, orbital-free DFT, and real-time time-dependent DFT, etc. In addition, with the aid of high-performance computing, ABACUS is designed to perform efficiently and provide massive amounts of first-principles data for generating general-purpose machine learning potentials, such as DPA models. Furthermore, ABACUS serves as an electronic structure platform that interfaces with several AI-assisted algorithms and packages, such as DeePKS-kit, DeePMD, DP-GEN, DeepH, DeePTB, etc.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.08697v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Weiqing Zhou, Daye Zheng, Qianrui Liu, Denghui Lu, Yu Liu, Peize Lin, Yike Huang, Xingliang Peng, Jie J. Bao, Chun Cai, Zuxin Jin, Jing Wu, Haochong Zhang, Gan Jin, Yuyang Ji, Zhenxiong Shen, Xiaohui Liu, Liang Sun, Yu Cao, Menglin Sun, Jianchuan Liu, Tao Chen, Renxi Liu, Yuanbo Li, Haozhi Han, Xinyuan Liang, Taoni Bao, Nuo Chen, Hongxu Ren, Xiaoyang Zhang, Zhaoqing Liu, Yiwei Fu, Maochang Liu, Zhuoyuan Li, Tongqi Wen, Zechen Tang, Yong Xu, Wenhui Duan, Xiaoyang Wang, Qiangqiang Gu, Fu-Zhi Dai, Qijing Zheng, Jin Zhao, Yuzhi Zhang, Qi Ou, Hong Jiang, Shi Liu, Ben Xu, Shenzhen Xu, Xinguo Ren, Lixin He, Linfeng Zhang, Mohan Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological Optical Pseudospin Injection Beyond Weyl Semimetals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.09235</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.09235v4 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Photoinduced effects are now reckoned to be important tools to reveal a rich gamut of entrancing physics in topological materials, which are normally inaccessible to conventional probes. Here we investigate one of these intriguing effects, namely, optical pseudospin injection (OPI) beyond ordinary Weyl semimetals (WSMs), specifically in multi-WSMs (mWSMs) and higher-order WSMs. Remarkably, we demonstrate that OPI in mWSMs is independent of the frequency of the light and linearly proportional to the quantized topological charge as a consequence of the inherent band linearity in their dispersions. Interestingly, while the response does not depend on the tilting of a type-I node, it is a decreasing function of the same in type-II mWSMs. We also reveal that the frequency independence can be destroyed either by going beyond a certain cutoff frequency under lattice regularization or by going to a higher-order Weyl phase. The predicted signatures of OPI beyond the ordinary WSM could be experimentally exploited, leading to effective access as well as distinguishing between different nontrivial Weyl topologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.09235v4</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.L041402</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, L041402 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Suvendu Ghosh, Chuanchang Zeng, A. Taraphder, Jian-Xin Zhu, Snehasish Nandy</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Constraints on the orbital flux phase in $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$ from polar Kerr effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.16398</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.16398v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$ ($A=$ K, Rb, Cs) family of Kagome metals hosts unconventional charge density wave order whose nature is still an open puzzle. Accumulated evidences point to a time-reversal symmetry breaking orbital flux phase that carries loop currents. Such an order may support anomalous Hall effect. However, the polar Kerr effect measurements that probe the a.c. anomalous Hall conductivity seems to have yielded contradictory results. We first argue on symmetry grounds that some previously proposed orbital flux order, most notably the one with Star-of-David distortion, shall not give rise to anomalous Hall or polar Kerr effects. We further take the tri-hexagonal orbital flux phase as an exemplary Kagome flux order that does exhibit anomalous Hall response, and show that the Kerr rotation angle at two relevant experimental optical frequencies generally reaches microradians to sub-milliradians levels. A particularly sharp resonance enhancement is observed at around $\hbar \omega =1$ eV, suggesting exceedingly large Kerr rotation at the corresponding probing frequencies not yet accessed by previous experiments. Our study can help to interpret the Kerr measurements on $A$V$_3$Sb$_5$ and to eventually resolve the nature of their CDW order.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.16398v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.L041109</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, L041109(2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Hao-Tian Liu, Junkang Huang, Tao Zhou, Wen Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Laser-scanning of induction-melted Al alloys: are they representative of additively manufactured ones?</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.06138</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.06138v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The bottleneck of alloy design for powder-based additive manufacturing (AM) resides in customized powder production - an expensive and time-consuming process hindering the rapid closed-loop design iterations. This study analyzed an expedited experimental workflow, i.e., multipath laser scanning of induction-melted samples, to mimic rapid solidification of AM to serve as an alternative approach to down-select from the design space. Using Al-Ni-Zr-Er model alloy, comprehensive multi-scale characterizations were performed to compare microstructural features between laser-scanned and laser powder bed fusion (LPBF) samples. Although demonstrating a difference in melt pool geometries, the microstructures in scanning electron microscopy (SEM)- and transmission electron microscopy (TEM)- scale demonstrate a high degree of similarity, in terms of microstructure morphology, grain size, presence of precipitates, and phase distribution. The mechanical performance was evaluated by microhardness tests. The results revealed a 20% reduction in laser-scanned samples compared to LPBF samples, attributed to the thermal history and potential differences in phase fractions. The decreasing trend was also observed in the benchmark alloy showing a 10% absolute error with respect to the model alloy. This study underscores the potential of this workflow to accelerate alloy design in AM by circumventing customized powder production and encourages further exploration across diverse materials and processing parameters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.06138v3</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zhaoxuan Ge, Sebastian Calderon, S. Mohadeseh Taheri-Mousavi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Role of Superlattice Phonons in Charge Localization Across Quantum Dot Arrays</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02188</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.02188v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Understanding charge transport in semiconductor quantum dot (QD) assemblies is important for developing the next generation of solar cells and light-harvesting devices based on QD technology. One of the key factors that governs the transport in such systems is related to the hybridization between the QDs. Recent experiments have successfully synthesized QD molecules, arrays, and assemblies by directly fusing the QDs, with enhanced hybridization leading to high carrier mobilities and coherent band-like electronic transport. In this work, we theoretically investigate the electron transfer dynamics across a finite CdSe-CdS core-shell QD array, considering up to seven interconnected QDs in one dimension. We find that, even in the absence of structural and size disorder, electron transfer can become localized by the emergent low-frequency superlattice vibrational modes when the connecting neck between QDs is narrow. On the other hand, we also identify a regime where the same vibrational modes facilitate coherent electron transport when the connecting necks are wide. Overall, we elucidate the crucial effects of electronic and superlattice symmetries and their couplings when designing high-mobility devices based on QD superlattices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.02188v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Bokang Hou, Matthew Coley-O'Rourke, Uri Banin, Michael Thoss, Eran Rabani</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Superconducting flip-chip devices using indium microspheres on Au-passivated Nb or NbN as under-bump metallization layer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2408.14655</link>
      <description>arXiv:2408.14655v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Superconducting flip-chip interconnects are crucial for the three-dimensional integration of superconducting circuits in sensing and quantum technology applications. We demonstrate a simplified approach for a superconducting flip-chip device using commercially available indium microspheres and an in-house-built transfer stage for bonding two chips patterned with superconducting thin films. We use a gold-passivated niobium or niobium nitride layer as an under-bump metallization (UBM) layer between an aluminum-based superconducting wiring layer and the indium interconnect. At millikelvin temperatures, our flip-chip assembly can transport a supercurrent with tens of milliamperes, limited by the smallest geometric feature size and critical current density of the UBM layer and not by the indium interconnect. We show that the pressed indium interconnect itself can carry a supercurrent exceeding 1A due to its large size of about 500 micrometer diameter. Our flip-chip assembly does not require electroplating nor patterning of indium. The assembly process does not need a flip-chip bonder and can be realized with a transfer stage using a top chip with transparency or through-vias for alignment. These flip-chip devices can be utilized in applications that require few superconducting interconnects carrying large currents at millikelvin temperatures.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2408.14655v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1063/5.0235266</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Appl. Phys. Lett. 126, 022601 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Achintya Paradkar, Paul Nicaise, Karim Dakroury, Fabian Resare, Witlef Wieczorek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Harnessing the natural resonances of time-varying dispersive interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2409.01831</link>
      <description>arXiv:2409.01831v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Space-time modulation of electromagnetic parameters offers novel exciting possibilities for advanced field manipulations. In this study, we explore wave scattering from a time-varying interface characterized by a Lorentz-type dispersion with a step-like temporal variation in its parameters. Our findings reveal a new process: an unconventional frequency generation at the natural resonances of the system. Remarkably, this phenomenon enables the coupling of propagating waves to evanescent ones, allowing the direct far-field excitation of surface-wave modes without the mediation of spatial gratings or prisms. These results suggest a novel strategy for designing compact and ultra-fast photonic devices, eliminating the necessity for subwavelength spatial structuring or prolonged temporal modulations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2409.01831v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevLett.133.186902</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Carlo Rizza, Maria Antonietta Vincenti, Giuseppe Castaldi, Alessandra Contestabile, Vincenzo Galdi, Michael Scalora</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable amplitude of Sondheimer oscillations in thin cadmium crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.11586</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.11586v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Decades ago, Sondheimer discovered that the electric conductivity of metallic crystals hosting ballistic electrons oscillates with magnetic field. These oscillations, periodic in magnetic field with the period proportional to the sample thickness, have been understood in a semi-classical framework. Here, we present a study of longitudinal and transverse conductivity in cadmium single crystals with thickness varying between 12.6 to 475 $\mu$m. When the magnetic field is sufficiently large or the sample sufficiently thick, the amplitude of oscillation falls off as $B^{-4}$ as previously reported. In contrast, the ten first oscillations follow a $B^{-2.5}e^{-B/B_0}$ field dependence and their amplitude is set by the quantum of conductance, the sample thickness, the magnetic length and the Fermi surface geometry. This expression is in disagreement with what was predicted in semi-classical scenarios, which neglect Landau quantization. We argue that the classical/quantum crossover occurs at accessible magnetic fields for states whose Fermi wave-vector is almost parallel to the magnetic field. As a consequence, the intersection between the lowest Landau tube and flat toroids on the Fermi surface induced by confinement give rise to oscillations with a periodicity identical to the semi-classical one. A rigorous theoretical account of our data is missing.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.11586v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Xiaodong Guo, Xiaokang Li, Lingxiao Zhao, Zengwei Zhu, Kamran Behnia</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Orthogonal Geometry of Magneto-Optical Kerr Effect Enabled by Magnetization Multipole of Berry Curvature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.09857</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.09857v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Magneto-Optical Kerr Effect (MOKE) is a fundamental tool in magnetometry, pivotal for advancing research in optics, magnetism, and spintronics as a direct probe of magnetization. Traditional MOKE measurements primarily detect the magnetization components parallel to the Poynting vector, which can only access the magnitude but not the direction of the orthogonal component. In this study, we introduce an orthogonal MOKE geometry in which the Kerr signal detects both the magnitude and direction of the magnetization component perpendicular to the Poynting vector. We demonstrate the broad applicability of this orthogonal geometry through the MOKE measurements in cubic ferromagnets and van der Waals ferromagnet. We theoretically show that the orthogonal MOKE geometry is enabled by the multipolar structure of Berry curvature in the magnetization space, which generally induces a Voigt vector orthogonal to the magnetization, thereby accounting for the unique magnetization angle dependence distinct from conventional MOKE. The establishment of the orthogonal MOKE geometry not only introduces a new paradigm for magneto-optical measurements but also provides a framework for exploring the magnetization multipoles of Berry curvature across the electromagnetic spectrum.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.09857v2</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Haolin Pan, Han Li, Jixiang Huang, Zheng Liu, Mingyue Fang, Yanan Yuan, Daxiang Liu, Xintong Hu, Wenzhi Peng, Zhenguo Liang, Xiao Chang, Zhigao Sheng, Xianzhe Chen, Lingfei Wang, Qian Li, Peng Li, Qian Niu, Yang Gao, Qinghui Yang, Dazhi Hou</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Cascades in transport and optical conductivity of Twisted Bilayer Graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2412.20855</link>
      <description>arXiv:2412.20855v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Using a combined Dynamical Mean Field Theory and Hartree (DMFT+H) calculation we study the transport and optical properties of the 8-band heavy fermion model for Twisted Bilayer Graphene (TBG) in the normal state. We find resistive states around integer fillings which resemble the ones observed in transport experiments. From a Drude fitting of the low frequency optical conductivity, we extract a very strongly doping-dependent Drude weight and scattering rate, resetting at the integers. For most dopings, particularly above the integers, the Drude scattering rate is high but notably smaller than that of the local electrons. This highlights the important role of itinerant electrons in the transport properties, despite their limited spectral weight on the flat bands. At far infrared frequencies, the optical conductivity exhibits cascades characterized by highly asymmetric resets of the intensity and oscillations in the interband peak frequencies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2412.20855v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. J. Calder\'on, A. Camjayi, A. Datta, E. Bascones</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kitaev Quantum Spin Liquids</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.05608</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.05608v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Quantum spin liquids (QSLs) represent exotic states of matter where quantum spins interact strongly yet evade long-range magnetic order down to absolute zero. Characterized by non-local quantum entanglement and resultant fractionalized excitations, QSLs have emerged as a frontier in condensed matter physics, bolstered by the recent identification of several candidate materials. This field holds profound implications for understanding strong correlations, topological order, and emergent phenomena in quantum materials. Among them, the spin-1/2 Kitaev honeycomb model, featuring bond-directional Ising interactions, provides a rare exactly solvable QSL example. Its ground state is a topological QSL, with spin degrees of freedom fractionalized into emergent Majorana fermions. Under an applied magnetic field, the Kitaev QSL transitions to a topologically non-trivial chiral spin liquid state with non-Abelian anyons, offering potential resources for topological quantum computation. The non-Abelian character of these anyons in the Kitaev QSL demonstrates a profound connection to certain topological superconductors and even-denominator fractional quantum Hall states. Since the theoretical prediction that the Kitaev model could manifest in spin-orbit-coupled materials such as honeycomb iridates and ruthenates, research has focused on identifying candidate compounds. In particular, experimental evidence suggests spin fractionalization and topological phenomena akin to the Kitaev model in the spin-orbit Mott insulator $\alpha$-RuCl$_3$. However, results and interpretations remain actively debated. This review presents a comprehensive survey of existing studies on Kitaev candidate materials, with a particular focus on $\alpha$-RuCl$_3$. Rather than offering conclusive remarks, our aim is to inspire future research by examining several key aspects of the current literature and perspectives.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.05608v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2025 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuji Matsuda, Takasada Shibauchi, Hae-Young Kee</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
