<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 22 May 2025 01:48:55 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Saturday</day>
      <day>Sunday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Autonomous nanoparticle synthesis by design</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13571v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Controlled synthesis of materials with specified atomic structures underpins technological advances yet remains reliant on iterative, trial-and-error approaches. Nanoparticles (NPs), whose atomic arrangement dictates their emergent properties, are particularly challenging to synthesise due to numerous tunable parameters. Here, we introduce an autonomous approach explicitly targeting synthesis of atomic-scale structures. Our method autonomously designs synthesis protocols by matching real time experimental total scattering (TS) and pair distribution function (PDF) data to simulated target patterns, without requiring prior synthesis knowledge. We demonstrate this capability at a synchrotron, successfully synthesising two structurally distinct gold NPs: 5 nm decahedral and 10 nm face-centred cubic structures. Ultimately, specifying a simulated target scattering pattern, thus representing a bespoke atomic structure, and obtaining both the synthesised material and its reproducible synthesis protocol on demand may revolutionise materials design. Thus, ScatterLab provides a generalisable blueprint for autonomous, atomic structure-targeted synthesis across diverse systems and applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13571v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Andy S. Anker, Jonas H. Jensen, Miguel Gonzalez-Duque, Rodrigo Moreno, Aleksandra Smolska, Mikkel Juelsholt, Vincent Hardion, Mads R. V. Jorgensen, Andres Faina, Jonathan Quinson, Kasper Stoy, Tejs Vegge</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Symmetry-Driven Trimer Formation in Kagome Correlated Electron Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13659</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13659v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Correlated electron materials with molecular orbital states extending over transition metal clusters can host multiferroicity, spin frustration, and unconventional insulating phases. However, the fundamental criteria that govern cluster formation and stability remain unclear. Here, we identify a symmetry, correlation, and electron filling driven criteria that stabilize triangular metal trimers in materials displaying transition metal kagome patterns. Using density functional theory and chemical bonding analysis, we show that trimer formation emerges when 6 to 8 electrons occupy molecular orbitals derived from transition metal d-states, achieving near complete filling of bonding states while avoiding antibonding occupation, and correlations are of intermediate strength. This principle explains the stability of Nb$_3$X$_8$ (X = Cl, Br, I), and more broadly, our findings offer a general design rule to obtain quantum materials with quantum states extended across transition metal clusters.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13659v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Varsha Kumari, Julia Bauer, Alexandru B. Georgescu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Early Stages of Self-Healing at Tungsten Grain Boundaries from Ab Initio Machine Learning Simulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13744</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13744v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Nanostructured tungsten has been reported as a possible alternative plasma-facing material due to its potential ability to self-heal radiation-induced defects, a property that is attributed to its high density of grain boundaries (GB). Here, we study the initial stages of self-healing at tungsten interfaces with molecular dynamics simulations driven by a machine-learning interatomic potential tailored to one of the most common GBs found in experiments. Our model accurately reproduces the ab initio potential energy surface derived from density functional theory (DFT) calculations and outperforms previously reported empirical interatomic potentials in predicting defect energetics. The simulations reveal low-temperature defect migration to GBs driven by rapid dumbbell-like ordering and subsequent accommodation along GB grooves. In contrast to empirical potentials, which predict unexpected GB degradation at high temperatures after defect migration, our model maintains stable GB motifs over the investigated temperature range. The temperature-dependent defect counts, evaluated using an Arrhenius-like fit, yield an average interstitial migration energy of 0.048 eV, in agreement with experiment.
  This work underscores the capabilities of ab initio machine learning simulations in accurately modeling defect-GB interactions and highlights their potential to contribute to the development of radiation tolerant materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13744v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jorge Su\'arez-Recio, Pablo M. Piaggi, Francisco J. Dom\'inguez-Guti\'errez, Raquel Gonzalez-Arrabal, Roberto Iglesias</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Active-Spin-State-Derived Descriptor for Hydrogen Evolution Reaction Catalysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13786</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13786v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Spin states are pivotal in modulating the electrocatalytic activity of transition-metal (TM)-based compounds, yet quantitatively evaluating the activity-spin state correlation remains a formidable challenge. Here, we propose an 'activity index n' as a descriptor, to assess the activity of the spin states for the hydrogen evolution reaction (HER). n descriptor integrates three key electronic parameters: the proportion (P), broadening range (R) and center cc of active spin state, which collectively account for the electronic structure modulation induced by both the intrinsic active site and its local coordination environment. Using 1T-phase ZrSe2-anchored TM atoms (TM=Sc to Ni) as prototypes, we reveal that the correlation between Gibbs free energy and the n value follows a linear relation, namely, the vGH reduces as the n decreases. Notably, ZrSe2-Mn exhibits the optimal n value (-0.56), corresponding the best HER activity with a vGH of 0.04 eV closer to the thermoneutral ideal value (0 eV) than even Pt (vGH = -0.09 eV). This relationship suggests that n is the effective descriptor of active spin state for HER of TM-based catalysts. Our study brings fundamental insights into the HER activity-spin state correlation, offering new strategies for HER catalyst design.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13786v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yu Tan, Lei Li, Zi-Xuan Yang, Tao Huang, Qiao-Ling Wang, Tao Zhang, Jing-Chun Luo, Gui-Fang Huang, Wangyu Hu, Wei-Qing Huang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Substrate Effect on Electronic Band Structure and Topological Property in Monolayer V2O3 Magnetic Topological Insulator</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13795</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13795v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Monolayer V2O3, a two-dimensional magnetic topological insulator with intrinsic ferromagnetic order and a nontrivial band gap, offers a promising platform for realizing quantum anomalous Hall (QAH) states. Using first-principles density functional theory calculations, we systematically investigate the impact of substrate selection on its electronic and topological properties. By modeling heterostructures with van der Waals (vdW) substrates, we demonstrate that non-magnetic substrates such as h-BN preserve the QAH phase with a Chern number C = 1, maintaining gapless chiral edge states. In contrast, ferromagnetic substrates induce extra electrons, destroying the topological order by shifting the Fermi level. These findings establish substrate engineering as a pivotal strategy for experimental realization of dissipationless edge transport in V2O3-based vdW heterostructures, advancing their potential applications as low-power topological electronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13795v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Zheng Wang, Kaixuan Chen, Shu-Shen Lyu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Experimental and theoretical studies of WO3-Vulcan XC-72 electrocatalyst enhanced H2O2 yield ORR performed in acid and alkaline medium</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13800</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13800v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The oxygen reduction reaction (ORR) plays a pivotal role in clean energy generation and sustainable chemical production, particularly in the synthesis of hydrogen peroxide (H\textsubscript{2}O\textsubscript{2}). In this study, WO\textsubscript{3}/Vulcan-XC72 electrocatalysts were synthesized and characterized for ORR applications, evaluating the WO\textsubscript{3} to Vulcan-XC72 ratio and examining electrolyte pH effects across acidic and alkaline media. Structural characterization confirmed successful synthesis of monoclinic WO\textsubscript{3} with nanoflower morphology, which enhanced surface hydrophilicity and oxygen functional groups. Electrochemical tests demonstrated WO\textsubscript{3}/C's superior H\textsubscript{2}O\textsubscript{2} selectivity compared to pure Vulcan-XC72 in both media, revealing a pH-dependent ORR mechanism. Using WO\textsubscript{3}/C gas diffusion electrodes (GDEs), we achieved 862,mg,L\textsuperscript{-1} H\textsubscript{2}O\textsubscript{2} accumulation after 120,min at 100,mA,cm\textsuperscript{-2}. The enhanced performance stems from increased oxygen functional groups, improved hydrophilicity, and WO\textsubscript{3} nanoflower synergistic effects, as supported by theoretical calculations, establishing WO\textsubscript{3}/Vulcan as a promising catalyst for electrochemical H\textsubscript{2}O\textsubscript{2} production.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13800v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jece.2024.113182</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Jo\~ao Paulo C Moura, Lanna EB Lucchetti, Caio M Fernandes, Aline B Trench, Camila N Lange, Bruno L Batista, James M Almeida, Mauro C Santos</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Physics-Guided Sequence Modeling for Fast Simulation and Design Exploration of 2D Memristive Devices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13882</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13882v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Modeling hysteretic switching dynamics in memristive devices is computationally demanding due to coupled ionic and electronic transport processes. This challenge is particularly relevant for emerging two-dimensional (2D) devices, which feature high-dimensional design spaces that remain largely unexplored. We introduce a physics-guided modeling framework that integrates high-fidelity finite-volume (FV) charge transport simulations with a long short-term memory (LSTM) artificial neural network (ANN) to predict dynamic current-voltage behavior. Trained on physically grounded simulation data, the ANN surrogate achieves more than four orders of magnitude speedup compared to the FV model, while maintaining direct access to physically meaningful input parameters and high accuracy with typical normalized errors &lt;1%. This enables iterative tasks that were previously computationally prohibitive, including inverse modeling from experimental data, design space exploration via metric mapping and sensitivity analysis, as well as constrained multi-objective design optimization. Importantly, the framework preserves physical interpretability via access to detailed spatial dynamics, including carrier densities, vacancy distributions, and electrostatic potentials, through a direct link to the underlying FV model. Our approach establishes a scalable framework for efficient exploration, interpretation, and model-driven design of emerging 2D memristive and neuromorphic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13882v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Benjamin Spetzler, Elizaveta Spetzler, Saba Zamankhani, Dilara Abdel, Patricio Farrell, Kai-Uwe Sattler, Martin Ziegler</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modulating Thermometric Performance via Dopant Concentration and Morphology in Luminescence Thermometer Exhibiting Dual Structural Phase Transitions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13956</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13956v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Expanding the operational range of luminescent thermometers that utilize thermally induced structural phase transitions in lanthanide-doped materials necessitates the exploration of novel host matrices with diverse thermal behaviors. In line with this objective, the present study offers a comprehensive analysis of the temperature-dependent spectroscopic properties of Li3Sc2(PO4)3:Eu3+. The findings reveal that the studied material undergoes two reversible phase transitions: {\gamma}LT - {\alpha}/\b{eta} phase transition at approximately 160 K, followed by an \b{eta} HT transition around 550 K. These transitions are evidenced by notable alterations in the emission spectra and luminescence decay kinetics of Eu3+ ions. By employing an appropriate luminescence intensity ratio, the sensitivity was determined to be 7.8 % K-1 at 160 K for 0.1%Eu3+ and 0.65 % K-1 at 550 K for 0.5%Eu3+. Furthermore, the study demonstrates that the phase transition temperature in Li3Sc2(PO4)3:Eu3+ can be modulated through variations in dopant ion concentration and annealing conditions, which in turn influence the material's morphology. These strategies enable the fine-tuning of thermometric performance in phase transition-based luminescent thermometers. To the best of our knowledge, this represents the first report in the literature of a luminescent thermometer exhibiting dual thermal operating ranges.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13956v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Malgorzata Kubicka, Maja Szymczak, Maciej Ptak, Damian Szymanski, Vasyl Kinzhybahlo, Marek Drozd, Lukasz Marciniak</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Theoretical investigation of interface atomic structure of graphene on NiFe alloy substrate</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14026</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14026v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two processes have been proposed to fabricate graphene/NiFe alloy interfaces for tunneling magnetoresistance devices. One is the transfer of graphene and the other is the evaporation of alloys onto graphene. The formation energy of a NiFe alloy substrate and the adsorption energy of graphene on the NiFe alloy substrate are investigated by a density functional theory calculations to reveal the difference in the atomic structure of the interface between the two processes. It is found that Ni-rich surfaces are preferable for the bare substrate, whereas Fe surfaces are stable for the graphene adsorbed on the substrate. This result indicates that the composition ratio of the surface layer depends on the interface fabrication process.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14026v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Naohiro Matsumoto, Ryusuke Endo, Mitsuharu Uemoto, Tomoya Ono</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Scalable alloy-based sputtering of high-conductivity PdCoO$_2$ for advanced interconnects</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14094</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14094v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: As integrated circuits continue to scale down, the search for new metals is becoming increasingly important due to the rising resistivity of traditional copper-based interconnects. A layered oxide PdCoO$_2$ is one of the candidate materials for interconnects, having bulk ab-plane conductivity exceeding that of elemental Al. Despite its potential, wafer-scale vacuum deposition of PdCoO$_2$, crucial for interconnect applications, has not yet been reported. In this study, we succeeded in the scalable growth of c-axis oriented PdCoO$_2$ thin films via reactive sputtering from Pd-Co alloy targets. Our method paves the way to harness the unique properties of PdCoO$_2$ in semiconductor devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14094v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Takayuki Harada, Zuin Ping Lily Ang, Yuki Sakakibara, Takuro Nagai, Yasushi Masahiro</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reactive Glass Metal Interaction under Ambient Conditions Enables Surface Modification of Gold Nanoislands</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14095</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14095v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Stabilizing gold nanoparticles with tunable surface composition via reactive metal support interactions under ambient conditions remains a significant challenge. We discovered that a reactive glass metal interaction (RGMI) under ambient conditions, driven by the intrinsic catalytic activity of gold nanoislands (GNIs) and the unique properties of sodium aluminophosphosilicate glass, including its chemical composition, molar volume, and high Na ion mobility, enables the formation of robustly anchored GNIs with altered surface compositions. Comprehensive characterization reveals that the adsorption of Na and P at the GNI surfaces induces lattice distortions in the Au(111) planes. Additionally, a smooth GNI glass interface significantly influences the hot carrier dynamics of the GNIs. Altogether, RGMI presents a versatile strategy for engineering stable, multi element nanostructures with potential applications in heterogeneous catalysis, sensing, and optoelectronics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14095v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Sinorul Haque, Shweta R. Keshri, G. Ganesh, Kaustuv Chatterjee, Shubhangi Majumdar, Sudheer Ganisetti, Indrajeet Mandal, Dudekula Althaf Basha, Prabir Pal, Pramit K Chowdhury, Niharika Joshi, Subrahmanyam Sappati, Nitya Nand Gosvami, Eswaraiah Varrla, N. M. Anoop Krishnan, Amarnath R. Allu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Atomic Topology and Magnetic Microstructure of Highly Mobile Type I and Supermobile Type II Twin Boundaries in 10M Ni-Mn-Ga Single Crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14096</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14096v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: The atomic topology and magnetic microstructure of individual, highly mobile Type I and Type II twin boundaries in 10M Ni-Mn-Ga martensite were investigated by transmission electron microscopy (TEM). The twin boundaries established in a bulk single crystal showed twinning stresses of ~1 MPa for Type I and ~0.1 MPa for Type II twin boundaries. TEM lamellae with a (010) cross-section, their c-axis (easy-magnetization direction) lying in-plane, were prepared by focused ion-beam milling, each containing a single twin boundary of specific type. High-resolution TEM confirmed an atomically sharp Type I twin boundary oriented along the rational (101) plane. The Type II boundary was also atomically sharp, apart from occasional single-atomic-plane steps. This contrasts with previous suggestions of its diffuse nature. Lorentz TEM showed 180{\deg} domain walls within martensite variants. The magnetic induction reorients sharply on both twin boundaries, forming 90{\deg}-like magnetic domain walls that follow the c-axis easy-magnetization direction.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14096v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ladislav Straka, Marek Vronka, Jan Ma\v{n}\'ak, Petr Ve\v{r}t\'at, Hanu\v{s} Seiner, Oleg Heczko</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Poleval: A Python package for HAXPES analysis</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14194v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: POLEVAL provides a software toolbox for collaborative, persistent and reproducible analysis of XPS experiments. It allows to treat, analyse and visualise the results of an extended experimental campaign in a single python notebook in a consistent manner. Managing experimental data in adequate objects enables experimentalists to process and analyse measurements in very few lines of code, so as to provide decision aids through online data analysis during e.g. beamtime experiments. The persistent and self-documentary style of the notebook-based analysis allows for easy communication of intermediate results and enables progressive refinements into publishable figures or exporting the results to other programs. The toolbox facilitates various routines for data treatment (normalization, cropping, etc.) and aggregation of spectra into groups to analyse trends. It also enables quantitative analysis with three major functions: First, normalization to the photoionization cross-section and probability of emission into the analyser cone allows for quantitative comparisons between intensities from different core levels. The integrated haxquantpy package allows easy retrieval of literature values for this purpose. Second, an extensive fitting functionality is implemented to treat groups of spectra together, rather than spectrum-by-spectrum. This grouping allows reinforcing the fit algorithm with prior knowledge, such as the equivalence of peak widths or positions between spectra, which enables for more consistent, and importantly, more confident fit results for sets of potentially noisy spectra. Third, a simple formalism to estimate the thickness of adsorbate layers based on the ratio between the substrate's and adsorbate's XPS signal is implemented.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14194v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.data-an</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Robin Yo\"el Engel, Patrick L\"omker</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Parallel Exploration of the Optoelectronic Properties of (Sb,Bi)(S,Se)(Br,I) Chalcohalides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14208</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14208v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chalcohalides are an emerging family of semiconductors with irresistible material properties, shaped by the intricate interplay between their unique structural chemistry and vibrational dynamics. Despite their promise for next-generation solar energy conversion devices, their intrinsic optoelectronic properties remain largely unexplored. Here, we focus on the (Sb,Bi)(S,Se)(Br,I) system, a subset of compounds that share the same quasi-1D crystal structure. Using a two-step physical vapor deposition (PVD) process, we synthesize the eight ternary chalcohalide compounds, demonstrating bandgaps ranging from 1.38 to 2.08 eV with sharp, single-component photoluminescence (PL) peaks. In a parallel exploration of carrier dynamics and intrinsic electron-phonon interactions -- comprehensively studied using power-, temperature-dependent, and time-resolved PL measurements -- we map their direct impact on optoelectronic performance. Supported by first-principles density functional theory (DFT) defect calculations, we establish clear structure-property relations, identifying solid-solutions engineering as an effective means to fine-tune the native phonon structures and further suppress non-radiative recombination. This study provides a blueprint for optimizing chalcohalides as high-efficiency materials across a wide range of optoelectronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14208v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rasmus S. Nielsen, \'Angel Labordet \'Alvarez, Axel G. Medaille, Ivan Ca\~no, Alejandro Navarro-G\"uell, Cibr\'an L. \'Alvarez, Claudio Cazorla, David R. Ferrer, Zacharie J. Li-Kao, Edgardo Saucedo, Mirjana Dimitrievska</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Path-integral molecular dynamics with actively-trained and universal machine learning force fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14245</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14245v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Accounting for nuclear quantum effects (NQEs) can significantly alter material properties at finite temperatures. Atomic modeling using the path-integral molecular dynamics (PIMD) method can fully account for such effects, but requires computationally efficient and accurate models of interatomic interactions. Empirical potentials are fast but may lack sufficient accuracy, whereas quantum-mechanical calculations are highly accurate but computationally expensive. Machine-learned interatomic potentials offer a solution to this challenge, providing near-quantum-mechanical accuracy while maintaining high computational efficiency compared to density functional theory (DFT) calculations. In this context, an interface was developed to integrate moment tensor potentials (MTPs) from the MLIP-2 software package into PIMD calculations using the i-PI software package. This interface was then applied to active learning of potentials and to investigate the influence of NQEs on material properties, namely the temperature dependence of lattice parameters and thermal expansion coefficients, as well as radial distribution functions, for lithium hydride (LiH) and silicon (Si) systems. The results were compared with experimental data, quasi-harmonic approximation calculations, and predictions from the universal machine learning force field MatterSim. These comparisons demonstrated the high accuracy and effectiveness of the MTP-PIMD approach.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14245v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>A. A. Solovykh (Lomonosov Moscow State University, Faculty of Physics, Moscow, Russian Federation, Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology, Moscow, Russian Federation), N. E. Rybin (Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology, Moscow, Russian Federation, Digital Materials LLC, Odintsovo, Russian Federation), I. S. Novikov (Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology, Moscow, Russian Federation, Emanuel Institute of Biochemical Physics of the Russian Academy of Sciences, Moscow, Russian Federation), A. V. Shapeev (Skolkovo Institute of Science and Technology, Moscow, Russian Federation, Digital Materials LLC, Odintsovo, Russian Federation)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In-situ observation of elastic instability of stress-induced B19$^\prime$ martensite in thin NiTi wires</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14259</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14259v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A laser-ultrasonic approach was used to measure elastic properties of a superelastic nickel-titanium wire with the aim to evaluate their evolution with stress and temperature in stress-induced martensite. It was observed that this evolution can be well described by a single smooth surface in the stress-temperature space, with the values of Young's modulus ranging from 30 to 50 GPa. The evolution of the modulus was then monitored in-situ with further heating under fixed strain, that is, during the shape setting. The results revealed that the martensite phase experienced further softening during this process, reaching Young's modulus of nearly 10 GPa at high temperatures and high stresses. In addition, the measurement enabled a direct detection of the initiation and termination temperatures of the shape setting from the elasticity data, which was used to show that it occurs in the same temperature interval for tension-induced and torsion-induced martensite.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14259v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Petr Sedl\'ak (Institute of Thermomechanics, Czech Academy of Sciences, Prague), Miroslav Frost (Institute of Thermomechanics, Czech Academy of Sciences, Prague), Martin \v{S}ev\v{c}\'ik (Institute of Thermomechanics, Czech Academy of Sciences, Prague), Luk\'a\v{s} Kade\v{r}\'avek (FZ\'U - Institute of Physics, Czech Academy of Sciences, Prague), Hanu\v{s} Seiner (Institute of Thermomechanics, Czech Academy of Sciences, Prague)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reference lattice, sound, stiffness, and magnetic transitions of Ising monolayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14416</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14416v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: A reference lattice, away from which elastic distortions induced by the spin texturing of 2D magnets take hold, is motivated from a picture of pairwise Biot-Savart interactions among identical solenoids that either elongate or compress a (``zero-current'') spring lattice. Applied to a paradigmatic CrSiTe$_3$ monolayer (ML), the reference is given by the average between the atomic positions of FM and N\'eel AFM lattices; such an atomic disposition permits understanding structural distortions and elastic energies due to magnetism readily. Furthermore, the anisotropic speed of sound in the magnetic ground state explains an observed anisotropy of vibrational frequencies on similar magnets. Elastic stiffness constants are reported, too. Magnetic energies in four Ising structural configurations were calculated, and the strain needed for those 2D magnets to undergo an AFM to FM quantum phase transition was determined as well.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14416v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>John M. Davis, Amador Garcia-Fuente, Jaime Ferrer, Salvador Barraza-Lopez</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thermal conductivity of boron arsenide above 2100 watts per meter per Kelvin at room temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14434</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14434v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Boron arsenide (BAs) single crystals had been previously reported to have thermal conductivity of 1500 W/mK at room temperature. Now we achieved thermal conductivity above 2100 W/mK at room temperature in BAs crystals due to much lower concentration of impurities Si, C, and O grown from purified arsenic. We also observed a T-1.8 dependence of the thermal conductivity, suggesting a more significant contribution from four-phonon scatterings than suggested by previous theory. We found that our experimental result can be fit with a modified theoretical calculation by tuning down the three-phonon scattering for phonons in the 4-8 THz range, although current phonon transport theory cannot provide a physical explanation. Such an advance will not only attract more effort on growing BAs single crystals and studying their practical applications but also stimulate theoretical work to predict more materials with possibly even higher thermal conductivities.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14434v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ange Benise Niyikiza, Zeyu Xiang, Fanghao Zhang, Fengjiao Pan, Chunhua Li, David Broido, Ying Peng, Bolin Liao, Zhifeng Ren</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Acidity-Mediated Metal Oxide Heterointerfaces: Roles of Substrates and Surface Modification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14488</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14488v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Although strong modulation of interfacial electron concentrations by the relative acidity of surface additives has been suggested, direct observation of corresponding changes in surface conductivity, crucial for understanding the role of local space charge, has been lacking. Here, we introduce a model platform comprising well-aligned mixed ionic-electronic conducting $\mathrm{Pr}_{0.2}\mathrm{Ce}_{0.8}\mathrm{O}_{2-\delta}$ nanowire arrays ($\mathrm{PCO}_{\mathrm{NA}}$) to show that acidity-modulated heterointerfaces predict electron depletion or accumulation, resulting in tunable electrical properties. We confirm three orders of magnitude increased $\mathrm{PCO}_{\mathrm{NA}}$ conductivity with basic $\mathrm{Li}_{2}\mathrm{O}$ infiltration. Moreover, the relative acidity of the insulating substrate supporting the $\mathrm{PCO}_{\mathrm{NA}}$ strongly influences its electronic properties as well. This strategy is further validated in purely ionic-conducting nanostructured ceria as well as $\mathrm{PCO}_{\mathrm{NA}}$. We suggest that observed conductivity changes stem not only from acidity-mediated space charge potentials at heterointerfaces but also from grain boundaries, chemically-modulated by cation in-diffusion. These findings have broad implications for how substrate and surface treatment choices can alter the conductive properties of nanostructured functional oxides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14488v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Gyu Rac Lee, Thomas Defferriere, Jinwook Kim, Han Gil Seo, Yeon Sik Jung, Harry L. Tuller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Electrical manipulation of magnetic domain structure in van der Waals ferromagnetic Fe$_3$GaTe$_2$ using ferroelectric PMN-PT single crystal</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14567</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14567v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) van der Waals (vdW) ferromagnets have emerged as promising materials for spintronic applications due to their unique magnetic properties and tunability. Controlling ferromagnetism via external stimuli is critical for both fundamental research and device integration. In particular, modulation of magnetic anisotropy and exchange interactions through strain offers a viable pathway for functional control. Owing to their weak interlayer coupling, vdW ferromagnets exhibit pronounced sensitivity to strain, enabling effective tuning of their magnetic states. In this study, we investigate electric-field-induced magnetoelectric coupling in the above-room-temperature vdW ferromagnet Fe$_3$GaTe$_2$ integrated on a ferroelectric PMN-PT substrate. We demonstrate that application of an electric field leads to a substantial reduction in coercive force along with dynamic reconfiguration of the magnetic domain structure. These effects are attributed to electric-field-induced modulation of the vdW interlayer gap and enhancement of the DzyaloshinskiiMoriya interaction. Our findings reveal a strong interplay between electric fields and magnetism in vdW systems, offering a viable route toward the development of low-power, multifunctional magnetic devices. This work establishes a foundation for the electric-field control of magnetic properties in vdW ferromagnets and highlights their potential in next-generation spintronic technologies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14567v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Riku Iimori, Yuta Kodani, Shaojie Hu, Takashi Kimura</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Interplay between altermagnetic order and crystal symmetry probed using magnetotransport in epitaxial altermagnet MnTe</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14589</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14589v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets are a new class of magnetic materials characterized by fully compensated spins arranged in alternating local structures, allowing for spin-split bands similar to those found in ferromagnets without net magnetism. Recently, MnTe has emerged as a prototypical altermagnetic material exhibiting spin-polarized electronic bands and anomalous transport phenomena. Although recent work has explored the magnetic and structural properties of MnTe, detailed experimental investigations into the relationship between altermagnetic order and crystal symmetry are lacking. Here, we report the relationship between altermagnetic order and crystal symmetry by investigating magnetotransport properties of MnTe epitaxial altermagnetic thin films grown by molecular beam epitaxy. We observe a spontaneous anomalous Hall effect and show the control of Hall response with the altermagnetic order using the magnetic field and the crystallographic angle dependence. Detailed measurements establish that both the longitudinal and transverse electronic responses depend on the relative orientation of the applied current and N\'eel vector as well as on the crystal orientation and altermagnetic order. These results provide new insights into the interplay between crystal symmetry and altermagnetism for future device applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14589v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Himanshu Bangar, Polychronis Tsipas, Prasanna Rout, Lalit Pandey, Alexei Kalaboukhov, Akylas Lintzeris, Athanasios Dimoulas, Saroj P. Dash</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Genetic Algorithm-Accelerated Computational Discovery of Liquid Crystal Polymers with Enhanced Optical Properties</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13477</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13477v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Liquid crystal polymers with exceptional optical properties are highly promising for next-generation virtual, augmented, and mixed reality (VR/AR/MR) technologies, serving as high-performance, compact, lightweight, and cost-effective optical components. However, the growing demands for optical transparency and high refractive index in advanced optical devices present a challenge for material discovery. In this study, we develop a novel approach that integrates first-principles calculations with genetic algorithms to accelerate the discovery of liquid crystal polymers with low visible absorption and high refractive index. By iterating within a predefined space of molecular building blocks, our approach rapidly identifies reactive mesogens that meet target specifications. Additionally, it provides valuable insights into the relationships between molecular structure and properties. This strategy not only accelerates material screening but also uncovers key molecular design principles, offering a systematic and scalable alternative to traditional trial-and-error methods.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13477v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jianing Zhou, Yuge Huang, Arman Boromand, Keian Noori, Lafe Purvis, Chulwoo Oh, Lu Lu, Zachary W. Ulissi, Vahe Gharakhanyan, Xinyue Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Evaluation of the Influence of Structural Parameters on the Mechanical Properties of Foam Glasses via In-Situ Micro-CT Mechanical Testing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13481</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13481v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Foam glass made from waste glass has high chemical and mechanical stability and flexible structural properties, making it suitable for a wide range of applications. To ensure its reliability, it is essential to understand its mechanical properties and fracture mechanisms. In this study, we investigated morphological features related to pore structure alongside mechanical properties, specifically Young's modulus and compressive strength, of three different monolithic foam glass samples using micro-computed tomography combined with ex-situ and in-situ uniaxial compression experiments and Digital Volume Correlation (DVC) analysis. The foam glasses exhibit an inverse relationship between mechanical strength and factors such as wall thickness, porosity, pore size and irregularity, with the compressive strength following a power-law correlation with the proportion of large pores. The multi-peak behavior of the stress-strain curves indicates micro-cracking within the porous lattice. Micro-CT data show that damage is concentrated at the upper and lower extremes of the specimens, and that the applied strain induces changes in the porosity, mean pore diameter, and pore sphericity, driven by deformation and collapse of the pore structures. DVC analysis quantitatively validated these observations.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13481v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.dis-nn</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Mateus Gruener Lima, Tobias G\"unther, Thu Trang V\~o, Eduardo Inocente Jussiani, Dirk Enke, Urs A. Peuker, Ralf B. Wehrspohn, Juliana Martins de Souza e Silva</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Impact of Acid Hydrolysis on Morphology, Rheology, Mechanical Properties, and Processing of Thermoplastic Starch</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13485</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13485v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We modified native wheat starch using 15, 30, and 60 min of acid hydrolysis (AH). The non-modified and AH-modified starches were converted to highly-homogeneous thermo-plastic starches (TPS) using our two-step preparation protocol consisting of solution cast-ing and melt-mixing. Our main objective was to verify if the AH can decrease the pro-cessing temperature of TPS. All samples were characterized in detail by microscopic, spectroscopic, diffraction, thermomechanical, rheological, and micromechanical methods, including in situ measurements of torque and temperature during the final melt-mixing step. The experimental results showed that: (i) the AH decreased the average molecular weight preferentially in the amorphous regions, (ii) the lower-viscosity matrix in the AH-treated starches resulted in slightly higher crystallinity, and (iii) all AH-modified TPS with less viscous amorphous phase and higher content of crystalline phase exhibited similar properties. The effect of the higher crystallinity predominated at laboratory tem-perature and low deformations, resulting in slightly stiffer material. The effect of the low-er-viscosity dominated during the melt mixing, where the shorter molecules acted as a lubricant and decreased the in situ measured processing temperature. The AH-induced decrease in the processing temperature could be beneficial for energy savings and/or pos-sible temperature-sensitive admixtures to TPS systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13485v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.3390/polym17101310</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Saffana Kouka, Veronika Gajdosova, Beata Strachota, Ivana Sloufova, Radomir Kuzel, Zdenek Stary, Miroslav Slouf</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polymer Data Challenges in the AI Era: Bridging Gaps for Next-Generation Energy Materials</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13494</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13494v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The pursuit of advanced polymers for energy technologies, spanning photovoltaics, solid-state batteries, and hydrogen storage, is hindered by fragmented data ecosystems that fail to capture the hierarchical complexity of these materials. Polymer science lacks interoperable databases, forcing reliance on disconnected literature and legacy records riddled with unstructured formats and irreproducible testing protocols. This fragmentation stifles machine learning (ML) applications and delays the discovery of materials critical for global decarbonization. Three systemic barriers compound the challenge. First, academic-industrial data silos restrict access to proprietary industrial datasets, while academic publications often omit critical synthesis details. Second, inconsistent testing methods undermine cross-study comparability. Third, incomplete metadata in existing databases limits their utility for training reliable ML models. Emerging solutions address these gaps through technological and collaborative innovation. Natural language processing (NLP) tools extract structured polymer data from decades of literature, while high-throughput robotic platforms generate self-consistent datasets via autonomous experimentation. Central to these advances is the adoption of FAIR (Findable, Accessible, Interoperable, Reusable) principles, adapted to polymer-specific ontologies, ensuring machine-readability and reproducibility. Future breakthroughs hinge on cultural shifts toward open science, accelerated by decentralized data markets and autonomous laboratories that merge robotic experimentation with real-time ML validation. By addressing data fragmentation through technological innovation, collaborative governance, and ethical stewardship, the polymer community can transform bottlenecks into accelerants.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13494v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ying Zhao, Guanhua Chen, Jie Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature dependence of coercivity for isolated Ni nanowires unraveled by high-sensitivity micromagnetometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13675</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13675v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Magnetic nanowires are critical components in fields such as data storage and spintronics, where precise control of their magnetic properties is essential for device optimization. In particular, the behavior of isolated nanowires is often different from that of an ensemble, offering an opportunity to explore the role that dipolar and magnetoelastic interactions play in the latter system. Unfortunately, the comparison between a collection of nanowires and single ones is often poorly characterized, as measuring individual nanowires with weak magnetic signals is a challenging task. In this work, we employ a highly-sensitive micromechanical torsional oscillator to measure the magnetic response of few individual Ni nanowires with 72 +/- 5 nm average diameter, fabricated by electrodeposition in anodic aluminum oxide templates as an array and subsequently released from this membrane. When comparing the magnetic properties as a function of temperature between single nanowires and the array, we show that coercivity values of individual nanowires are at least twice as large as for the array in the range 5 K - 200 K. Also, we characterize the differences in the hysteresis loops, which are more squared for isolated nanowires, with a high magnetic remanence close to 80 % of the saturation value. Our results highlight the crucial role of dipolar and mechanical interactions in modifying the magnetic behavior of nanowires arrays, providing valuable insights for the design and application of nanowires-based magnetic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13675v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Evelyn A. Escudero Bruna, Federico Rom\'a, Fernando Meneses, Paula. G. Bercoff, Moira I. Dolz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Probing and Tuning Strain-localized Exciton Emission in 2D Material Bubbles at Room Temperature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13783</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13783v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Excitons in 2D material bubbles-nanoscale deformations in atomically thin materials, typically exhibiting a dome-like shape-are confined by the strain effect, exhibiting extraordinary emission properties, such as single photon generation, enhanced light emission, and spectrally tunable excitonic states. While the strain profiles of these bubbles have been extensively studied, this work provides an approach (1) to directly visualize the associated exciton properties, revealing an intrinsic emission wavelength shift of approximately 40 nm, and (2) actively modify local strain, enabling further exciton emission tuning over a range of 50 nm. These are achieved by emission mapping and nanoindentation using a dielectric near-field probe, which enables the detection of local emission spectra and emission lifetimes within individual bubbles. Statistical analysis of 67 bubbles uncovers an emission wavelength distribution centered around 780 nm. Furthermore, saturation behavior in the power-dependent studies and the associated lifetime change reveal the localized nature of the strain-induced states. These findings provide direct insights into the strain-localized emission dynamics in bubbles and establish a robust framework for non-destructive, reversible, and predictable nanoscale emission control, presenting a potential avenue for developing next-generation tunable quantum optical sources.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13783v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Junze Zhou, John Thomas, Thomas P. Darlington, Edward S. Barnard, Atsushi Taguchi, Adam Schwartzberg, Alexander Weber-Bargioni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Micromagnetic Study of the Dipolar-Exchange Spin Waves in Antiferromagnetic Thin Films</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13970</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13970v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In antiferromagnets, dipolar coupling is often disregarded due to the cancellation of magnetic moments between the two sublattices, leaving spin-wave dispersion predominantly determined by exchange interactions. However, antiferromagnetic spin waves typically involve a slight misalignment of the magnetic moments on the sublattices, giving rise to a small net magnetization that enables long-range dipolar coupling. In this paper, we investigate the role of this dipolar coupling in spin-wave excitations and its influence on the spin-wave dispersion. Our findings show that: (i) when the N\'{e}el vector is perpendicular to the film plane or lies within the film plane and parallel to the wave vector, the dispersion branches can be divided into two groups -- those unaffected by the dipolar field and those influenced by it. In these cases, the total magnetic moment remains linearly polarized, but the polarization directions differ between the two types of branches; (ii) when the N\'{e}el vector lies in the film plane and is perpendicular to the wave vector, the dipolar interactions affect both types of dispersion branches, leading to their hybridization. This hybridization alters the polarization of the magnetic moment, resulting in elliptical polarization.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13970v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiongjie Wang, Jiang Xiao</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hybridized and Localized 4f Electronic States of Nd-based Intermetallic Compounds in Cubic Symmetry Probed by High-Energy Photoemission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.13999</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.13999v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We have performed soft and hard X-ray photoemission spectroscopies on NdTi2Al20 and NdBe13 which show antiferromagnetic ordering at low temperatures. The Nd 3d core-level photoemission and Nd 3d-4f valence-band resonant photoemission spectra show finite 4f4 initial-state components in addition to the 4f3 configurations attributed to the c-f hybridization effects in NdTi2Al20, while the 4f3 initial-state components with localized character are dominant in NdBe13. These results imply the emergence of overscreening channel due to the two-channel Kondo effect in NdTi2Al20 through the the strong c-f hybridization effect.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.13999v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>M. Sakaguchi, A. Enomoto, H. Fujiwara, G. Nozue, S. Hamamoto, Y. Torii, T. D. Nakamura, N. U. Sakamoto, K. Yamagami, T. Kiss, Y. Kanai-Nakata, S. Imada, A. Irizawa, A. Yamasaki, A. Higashiya, M. Oura, K. Tamasaku, M. Yabashi, T. Ishikawa, H. Sugawara, H. Amitsuka, T. Yanagisawa, H. Hidaka, A. Sekiyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A novel variant of rhombic Penrose tiling</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14013</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14013v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present a novel variant of a planar quasiperiodic tiling with tenfold symmetry, employing the same thick and thin rhombuses as the celebrated rhombic Penrose tiling. Despite its distinct visual appearance, this new tiling shares several key features with its predecessor, including similar vertex environments, polygonal acceptance domains based on regular pentagons, and an inflation/deflation symmetry associated with the golden mean as its fundamental scaling ratio. Additional complexities arise from an increased number of prototiles and a dual grid pattern that incorporates folded lines alongside ordinary straight lines. This tiling exhibits a high density of a compact decagonal motif forming a two-tiered, five-petaled flower pattern, which spans a substantial portion of the tiling. We identify a slightly enhanced degree of hyperuniform order compared to the standard rhombic Penrose tiling.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14013v1</guid>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nobuhisa Fujita, Komajiro Niizeki</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Revealing Information from Weak Signal in Electron Energy-Loss Spectroscopy with a Deep Denoiser</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14032</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14032v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electron energy-loss spectroscopy (EELS) coupled with scanning transmission electron microscopy (STEM) is a powerful technique to determine materials composition and bonding with high spatial resolution. Noise is often a limitation especially with the increasing sophistication of EELS experiments. The signal characteristics from direct electron detectors provide a new opportunity to design superior denoisers. We have developed a CNN based denoiser, the unsupervised deep video denoiser (UDVD), which can be applied to EELS datasets acquired with direct electron detectors. We described UDVD and explained how to adapt the denoiser to energy-loss spectral series. To benchmark the performance of the denoiser on EELS datasets, we generated and denoised a set of simulated spectra. We demonstrate the charge spreading effect associated with pixel interfaces on direct electron detectors, which leads to artifacts after denoising. To suppress such artifacts, we propose some adjustments. We demonstrate the effectiveness of the denoiser using two challenging real data examples: mapping Gd dopants in $CeO_2$ nanoparticles and characterizing vibrational modes in hexagonal boron nitride (h-BN) with atomic resolution.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14032v1</guid>
      <category>physics.ins-det</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yifan Wang, Mai Tan, Carlos Fernandez-Granda, Peter A. Crozier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nanoconfined superionic water is a molecular superionic</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14171</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14171v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Superionic ice, where water molecules dissociate into a lattice of oxygen ions and a rapidly diffusing 'gas' of protons, represents an exotic state of matter with broad implications for planetary interiors and energy applications. Recently, a nanoconfined superionic state of water has been predicted which, in sharp contrast to bulk ice, is comprised of intact water molecules. Here, we apply machine learning and electronic structure simulations to establish how nanoconfined water can be both molecular and superionic. We also explore what insights this material offers for superionic materials and behavior more generally. Similar to bulk ice and other superionic materials, nanoconfined water conducts via concerted chain-like proton migrations which cause the rapid propagation of defects. However, unlike other molecular phases of water, its exceptional conductivity arises from the activation of the Grotthuss mechanism by (i) low barriers to proton transfer and (ii) a flexible hydrogen-bonded network. We propose that these are two key characteristics of fast ionic conduction in molecular superionics. The insights obtained here establish design principles for the discovery of other molecular superionic materials, with potential applications in energy storage and beyond.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14171v1</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Samuel W. Coles, Amir Hajibabaei, Venkat Kapil, Xavier R. Advincula, Christoph Schran, Stephen J. Cox, Angelos Michaelides</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Topological electron and phonon flat bands in novel kagome superconductor XPd5 (X=Ca, Sr, Ba)</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14223</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14223v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Fermionic and bosonic localized states induced by geometric frustration in the kagome lattice provide a distinctive research platform for investigating emergent exotic quantum phenomena in strongly correlated systems. Here, we report the discovery of coexisting electronic and phononic flat bands induced by geometric frustration in a novel kagome superconductor XPd5 (X=Ca, Sr, Ba). The electronic flat band is located around the Fermi level and possesses a nontrivial topological invariant with Z2=1. Additionaly, we identify multiple van Hove singularities (vHS) arise from the kagome Pd d orbitals with distinct dispersion and sublattice features, including conventional, higher-order vHS and p-type, m-type vHS. Specifically, our investigation of the vibrational modes of the phononic flat band reveals that its formation originates from destructive interference between adjacent kagome lattice sites with antiphase vibrational modes. A spring-mass model of phonons is established to probe the physical mechanism of the phononic flat bands. Furthermore, the calculations of electron-phonon coupling in the XPd5 reveal superconducting ground states with critical temperatures (Tc) of 4.25 K, 2.75 K, and 3.35 K for CaPd5, SrPd5, and BaPd5, respectively. This work provides a promising platform to explore the Fermion-boson many-body interplay and superconducting states, while simultaneously establishing a novel analytical framework to elucidate the origin of phononic flat bands in quantum materials.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14223v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiefeng Ye, Zhigao Huang, Xianxin Wu, Jian-Min Zhang</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Infrared markers of topological phase transitions in quantum spin Hall insulators</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14277</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14277v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Using first principles techniques, we show that infrared optical response can be used to discriminate between the topological and the trivial phases of two-dimensional quantum spin Hall insulators (QSHI). We showcase germanene and jacutingaite, of recent experimental realization, as prototypical systems where the infrared spectrum is discontinuous across the transition, due to sudden and large discretized jumps of the value of Born effective charges (up to 2). For these materials, the topological transition can be induced via the application of an external electrostatic potential in the field-effect setup. Our results are rationalized in the framework of a low-energy Kane-Mele model and are robust with respect to dynamical effects which come into play when the energy gap of the material is of the same order of the infrared active phonon frequency. In the small gap QSHI germanene, due to dynamical effects, the in-plane phonon resonance in the optical conductivity shows a Fano profile with remarkable differences in the intensity and the shape between the two phases. Instead, the large gap QSHI jacutingaite presents several IR-active phonon modes whose spectral intensities drastically change between the two phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14277v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Paolo Fachin, Francesco Macheda, Paolo Barone, Francesco Mauri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Water-rich amorphous state from drying mixed-metal sulfate solutions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14334</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14334v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Amorphous and glassy materials are important for many advanced applications, from flexible solar cells to drug delivery systems. To this end, new glasses are in high demand, but precise chemical design of amorphous materials remains challenging. By studying the crystallization of mixed salt solutions, we have discovered an entirely new type of amorphous material: water-rich amorphous mixed sulfates. Specifically, we show that drying of sulfate salt mixtures of both mono- and higher valency cations almost exclusively yields a glassy or amorphous state, where the stability of the amorphous state depends on the cations present and ranges from seconds to months. Furthermore, we show that the glassy state is viscoelastic, behaves like a soft solid (G' 10^5 - 10^6 Pa), retains a large amount of water (30 to 40 weight percent), and is X-ray amorphous. Additionally, confocal Raman microspectroscopy reveals disordered sulfate orientations and Fourier-transform infrared spectroscopy highlights increased hydrogen bonding during drying, which together with strong cation hydration is hypothesized to prevent crystallization. These results provide insights for the production of a new class of amorphous materials, and help to elucidate the mystery of the high abundance of such amorphous salts found on Mars.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14334v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.soft</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christiaan T. van Campenhout, Romane Le Diz\`es Castell, Tess Heeremans, Sander Woutersen, Daniel Bonn, Noushine Shahidzadeh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>phaser: An all-in-one package for (multislice) electron ptychography</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14372</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14372v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Electron ptychography is a groundbreaking technique for the advanced characterization of materials. Successful ptychography relies on robust implementations of reconstruction algorithms with process raw data into phase images. Current software has enabled deep sub-angstrom multislice electron ptychographic reconstructions, but reconstructions remain challenging and computationally expensive. In addition, current software generally lacks the modularity to act as a platform for the development and testing of new solver components and algorithms. For instance, algorithms based on gradient descent and autodifferentiation promise faster reconstructions with higher quality, but it is difficult to implement these algorithms in existing software. Here, we present \texttt{phaser}, an open source Python package which provides a unified interface to both conventional and gradient descent based ptychographic algorithms. Reconstructions are specified in a declarative format, and can be run from a command line, Jupyter notebook, or web interface. Multiple computational backends are supported to provide maximum flexibility. With the JAX computational backend, a 6x improvement in iteration speed is achieved over a state-of-the-art package, \texttt{fold\_slice}. Additionally, \texttt{phaser}'s gradient descent solver achieves improved reconstruction quality.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14372v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Colin Gilgenbach, James M. LeBeau</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Phonon Mean Free Path Spectroscopy By Raman Thermometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14506</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14506v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: In this work, we exemplify on a bulk silicon sample that Raman thermometry is capable of phonon mean free path (PMFP) spectroscopy. Our experimental approach is similar to the variation of different characteristic length scales $l_{c}$ during thermal reflectance measurements in the time or frequency domain and transient thermal grating spectroscopy. In place of $l_{c}$, we vary the laser focus spot size ($w_{e}$) and the light penetration depth ($h_{\alpha}$) during one-laser Raman thermometry (1LRT) measurements. For our largest $w_{e}$ values, the derived effective thermal conductivities $\kappa_{eff}$ converge towards the bulk thermal conductivity $\kappa_{bulk}$ for silicon. However, towards smaller $w_{e}$ values, we observe a pronounced increase for the $\kappa_{eff}$ values, which amounts up to a factor of 5.3 at 293K and even 8.3 at 200K. We mainly assign this phenomenon to quasi-ballistic phonon transport. As a result, we can compare our measured $\kappa_{eff}(w_{e})$ trends with the thermal accumulation function $\kappa_{cum}$ and its dependence on the phonon mean free path $l_{ph}$, which we derive from ab initio solutions of the linearized phonon Boltzmann transport equation (BTE). Since the variation of $w_{e}$ can be experimentally cumbersome, we also suggest varying $h_{\alpha}(\lambda)$ via the applied Raman laser wavelength $\lambda$ during 1LRT. In this regard, we present proof-of-principle 1LRT measurements, yielding a step-like $\kappa_{eff}(\lambda)$ trend for four different $\lambda$ values, which we also interpret in terms of quasi-ballistic phonon transport. Our results shall seed future PMFP spectroscopy based on 1LRT, which can directly be benchmarked against state-of-art theory by comparison of $\kappa_{\text{cum}}$ trends and not only $\kappa$ values, aiming to test our understanding of the intricate phonon transport physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14506v1</guid>
      <category>physics.optics</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Katharina Dudde (Institut f\"ur Festk\"orperphysik, Universit\"at Bremen, Otto-Hahn-Allee 1, 28359 Bremen, Germany), Mahmoud Elhajhasan (Institut f\"ur Festk\"orperphysik, Universit\"at Bremen, Otto-Hahn-Allee 1, 28359 Bremen, Germany), Guillaume W\"ursch (Institut f\"ur Festk\"orperphysik, Universit\"at Bremen, Otto-Hahn-Allee 1, 28359 Bremen, Germany), Julian Themann (Institut f\"ur Festk\"orperphysik, Universit\"at Bremen, Otto-Hahn-Allee 1, 28359 Bremen, Germany), Jana Lierath (Institut f\"ur Festk\"orperphysik, Universit\"at Bremen, Otto-Hahn-Allee 1, 28359 Bremen, Germany), Dwaipayan Paul (Institut f\"ur Physik and Center for the Science of Materials Berlin), Nakib H. Protik (Institut f\"ur Physik and Center for the Science of Materials Berlin), Giuseppe Romano (MIT-IBM Watson AI Lab, 214 Main St., Cambridge, Massachusetts 02141, USA), Gordon Callsen (Institut f\"ur Festk\"orperphysik, Universit\"at Bremen, Otto-Hahn-Allee 1, 28359 Bremen, Germany)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Dynamic correlations of frustrated quantum spins from high-temperature expansion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.14571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.14571v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: For quantum spin systems in equilibrium, the dynamic structure factor (DSF) is among the most feature-packed experimental observables. However, from a theory perspective it is often hard to simulate in an unbiased and accurate way, especially for frustrated and high-dimensional models at intermediate temperature. We address this challenge by introducing a dynamic extension of the high-temperature expansion as an efficient numerical approach to the DSF for arbitrary lattices. We focus on the nearest-neighbor Heisenberg model and spin-lengths S=1/2 and 1. We present a user-friendly numerical implementation and provide comprehensive benchmarks on spin chains. As applications we treat a variety of frustrated two- and three dimensional antiferromagnets. In particular we shed new light on the anomalous intermediate temperature regime of the S=1/2 triangular lattice model and reproduce the DSF measured recently for a S=1 pyrochlore material.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.14571v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ruben Burkard, Benedikt Schneider, Bj\"orn Sbierski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Coexistence of high electron-mobility, unpaired spins, and superconductivity at high carrier density SrTiO$_3$-based interfaces</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2411.03824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2411.03824v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The $t_{2g}$ band-structure of SrTiO$_3$-based two-dimensional electron gasses (2DEGs), have been found to play a role in features such as the superconducting dome, high-mobility transport, and the magnitude of spin-orbit coupling. This adds to the already very diverse range of phenomena, including magnetism and extreme magnetoresistance, exhibited by this particular material platform. Tuning and/or combining these intriguing attributes could yield significant progress within quantum and spintronics technologies. Doing so demands precise control of the parameters, which requires a better understanding of the factors that affect them. Here we present effects of the $t_{2g}$ band-order inversion, stemming from the growth of spinel-structured $\gamma$-Al$_2$O$_3$ onto perovskite SrTiO$_3$. Electronic transport measurements show that with LaAlO$_3$/SrTiO$_3$ as the reference, the carrier density and electron mobility are enhanced, and the sample displays a reshaping of the superconducting dome. Additionally, unpaired spins are evidenced by increasing Anomalous Hall Effect with decreasing temperature, entering the same temperature range as the superconducting transition, and a Kondo-like upturn in the sheet resistance. Finally, it is argued that the high-mobility $d_{xz/yz}$-band is more likely than the $d_{xy}$-band to host the supercurrent.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2411.03824v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevMaterials.9.056202</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Physical Review Materials 9, 056202 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Thor Hvid-Olsen, Christina H. Christoffersen, Damon J. Carrad, Nicolas Gauquelin, Dags Olsteins, Johan Verbeeck, Nicolas Bergeal, Thomas S. Jespersen, Felix Trier</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pyramidal charged domain walls in ferroelectric BiFeO$_3$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2501.01190</link>
      <description>arXiv:2501.01190v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Domain structures play a crucial role in the electric, mechanical and other properties of ferroelectric materials. In this study, we uncover the physical origins of the enigmatic zigzag domain structure in the prototypical multiferroic material BiFeO$_3$. Using phase-field simulations within the Landau-Ginzburg-Devonshire framework, we demonstrate that spatially-homogeneous defect charges result in domain structures that closely resemble those observed experimentally. The acquired understanding of the underlying physics of pyramidal-domain formation may enable the engineering of new materials with self-assembled domain structures exhibiting defined domain periodicity at the nanometre scale, opening avenues for advanced applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2501.01190v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Pavel Marton, Marek Pa\'sciak, Mauro Gon\c{c}alves, Ond\v{r}ej Nov\'ak, Ji\v{r}\'i Hlinka, Richard Beanland, Marin Alexe</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Kitaev interaction and proximate higher-order skyrmion crystal in the triangular lattice van der Waals antiferromagnet NiI2</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.14167</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.14167v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Topological spin textures, such as magnetic skyrmions, are a spectacular manifestation of magnetic frustration and anisotropy. Most known skyrmion systems are restricted to a topological charge of one, require an external magnetic field for stabilization, and are only reported in a few materials. Here, we investigate the possibility that the Kitaev anisotropic-exchange interaction stabilizes a higher-order skyrmion crystal in the insulating van der Waals magnet NiI2. We unveil and explain the incommensurate static and dynamic magnetic correlations across three temperature-driven magnetic phases of this compound using neutron scattering measurements, simulations, and modeling. Our parameter optimisation yields a minimal Kitaev-Heisenberg Hamiltonian for NiI2 which reproduces the experimentally observed magnetic excitations. Monte Carlo simulations for this model predict the emergence of the higher-order skyrmion crystal but neutron diffraction and optical experiments in the candidate intermediate temperature regime are inconclusive. We discuss possible deviations from the Kitaev-Heisenberg model that explains our results and conclude that NiI2, in addition to multiferroic properties in the bulk and few-layer limits, is a Kitaev bulk material proximate to the finite temperature higher-order skyrmion crystal phase.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.14167v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Chaebin Kim, Olivia Vilella, Youjin Lee, Pyeongjae Park, Yeochan An, Woonghee Cho, Matthew B. Stone, Alexander I. Kolesnikov, Yiquing Hao, Shinichiro Asai, Shinichi Itoh, Takatsugu Masuda, Sakib Matin, Sujin Kim, Sung-Jin Kim, Martin Mourigal, Je-Geun Park</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rapid low-temperature synthesis of graphene-coated SiC substrates for remote and van der Waals epitaxy</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2502.17799</link>
      <description>arXiv:2502.17799v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Non-conventional epitaxial techniques, such as van der Waals epitaxy (vdWE) and remote epitaxy, have attracted substantial attention in the semiconductor research community for their capability to repeatedly produce high-quality free-standing films from a single mother wafer. Successful implementation of these epitaxial techniques depends on creating a robust, uniform two-dimensional (2D) material surface. The conventional method for fabricating graphene on silicon carbide (SiC) is high-temperature graphitization. However, the extremely high temperature required for silicon sublimation (typically above 1500 {\deg}C) causes step-bunching of the SiC surface, forming non-uniform multilayer graphene stripes and an unfavorable surface morphology for epitaxial growth. Here, we developed a wafer-scale graphitization technique that allows fast synthesis of single-crystalline graphene at ultra-low temperatures by metal-assisted graphitization (MAG). We found annealing conditions that enable SiC dissociation while avoiding silicide formation, producing uniform single-crystalline graphene while maintaining the surface morphology of the substrate. The graphene thickness can be controlled by varying the metal thickness or annealing temperature, enabling remote epitaxy or vdWE. We successfully produced freestanding single-crystalline III-N (AlN, GaN) films on graphene/SiC via the 2D material-based layer transfer technique. Our results show that low-temperature graphene synthesis via MAG offers a promising route to producing large-scale ultra-wide bandgap free-standing crystalline membranes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2502.17799v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Se H. Kim, Hanjoo Lee, Dong Gwan Kim, Donghan Kim, Seugki Kim, Hyunho Yang, Yunsu Jang, Jangho Yoon, Hyunsoo Kim, Seoyong Ha, ByoungTak Lee, Jung-Hee Lee, Roy Byung Kyu Chung, Hongsik Park, Sungkyu Kim, Tae Hoon Lee, Hyun S. Kum</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesis of intrinsic magnetic topological insulator MnBi2nTe3n+1 family by chemical vapor transport method with feedback regulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.08397</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.08397v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: MnBi2nTe3n+1 (MBT) is a representative family of intrinsic magnetic topological insulators, in which numerous exotic phenomena such as the quantum anomalous Hall effect are expected. The high-quality crystal growth and magnetism manipulation are the most essential processes. Here we develop a modified chemical vapor transport method using a feedback-regulated strategy, which provides the closed-loop control of growth temperature within +/- 0.1 degree Celsius. Single crystals of MnBi2Te4, MnBi4Te7, and MnBi6Te10 are obtained under different temperature intervals respectively, and show variable tunability on magnetism by finely tuning the growth temperatures. Specifically, the cold-end temperatures not only vary the strength of antiferromagnetic coupling in MnBi2Te4, but also induce magnetic ground state transitions from antiferromagnetism to ferromagnetism in MnBi4Te7 and MnBi6Te10. In MnBi2Te4 with optimized magnetism, quantized transport with Chern insulator state is also realized at the low field of 3.7 T. Our results provide a systematic picture for the crystal growth and the rich magnetic tunability of MBT family, providing richer platforms for the related researches combining magnetism and topological physics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.08397v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1002/adma.202405686</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Adv. Mater. 2025, 2405686</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Heng Zhang, Yiying Zhang, Yong Zhang, Bo Chen, Jingwen Guo, Yu Du, Jiajun Li, Hangkai Xie, Zhixin Zhang, Fuwei Zhou, Tianqi Wang, Wuyi Qi, Xuefeng Wang, Fucong Fei, Fengqi Song</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Oxyfluoride glasses obtained through incorporation of CaF$_2$ into photovoltaic cover glass melts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.07571</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.07571v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: The glass industry has limited options to mitigate its environmental footprint, and the demand for cover glass to produce photovoltaic panels is increasing. Currently, the majority of this special type of glass is not being recycled, and in this work, we propose to reuse it as raw material to obtain oxyfluoride glasses. The incorporation of CaF$_2$ and the increasing Na$_2$CO$_3$ content resulted in a melting temperature of about 1200$^o$C, significantly lower than in soda-lime glasses, which adds up to the environmental benefits of reusing end-of-life cover glass. The obtained samples show high transparency and thermal stability, allowing the cover glass to make up to 80\% of its weight. XRF analysis was employed to determine the elemental composition of the samples, while XRD and Raman indicated that by adding CaF$_2$, the glass network was depolymerized. In situ XRD as a function of temperature showed the formation of a few crystalline phases in these oxyfluoride samples, evidencing that it can be explored as a matrix to obtain different glass-ceramics. The combination of the glass properties indicates that this method and the resulting material can contribute to reducing the environmental impact of the glass industry, by creating new glass or glass-ceramic materials that can be obtained at a reduced temperature compared to the soda-lime glass, while cover glass being the primary raw material could reduce the need to extract minerals from nature.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.07571v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Rafaela Valcarenghi, Brenno Greatti Silva, Robson Ferrari Muniz, Vitor Santaella Zanuto, Anna Paulla Simon, Ricardo Schneider, Raquel Dosciatti Bini, M\'arcio Ant\^onio Fiori, Maxence Vigier, Emmanuel Veron, Mathieu Allix, Marcelo Sandrini, Marcos Paulo Belan\c{c}on</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tunable and Persistent Polarization in Centrosymmetric Oxides</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.09745</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.09745v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Introducing symmetry breaking in materials enables the emergence of functionalities. This can be microscopically and macroscopically driven by applying external stimuli such as mechanical stress, electric field, temperature, and chemical modification. For instance, non-zero net dipole moments are formed in a material with the presence of local charged defects or their clusters, which can alter the crystal structure, charge states, and electrostatic potential across the material. Here, we demonstrate a conceptual approach to defects-mediated symmetry breaking that allows for built-in polarization in a centrosymmetric oxide, $\mathrm{Gd}_x\mathrm{Ce}_{1-x}\mathrm{O}_{2-\delta}$ (CGO) films, via creating a macroscopic charge asymmetry. Our results show that switchable and enduring polarization in CGO films is governed by the redistribution of oxygen vacancies. This leads to notable and persistent pyroelectric effects with coefficient of approximately 180 $\mu\mathrm{C}\cdot\mathrm{m}^{-2}\cdot\mathrm{K}^{-1}$. Our findings highlight the potential to develop high-performance, sustainable, environmentally friendly polar film materials by manipulating ionic defects from their centrosymmetric ground states. This approach provides new opportunities to expand polar materials in current and future energy and electronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.09745v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. -S. Park, N. Pryds, N. Gauquelin, M. Hadad, D. Chezganov, A. Palliotto, D. Jannis, J. \'I\~niguez-Gonz\'alez, J. Verbeeck, P. Muralt, D. Damjanovic</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Achieving accurate entropy and melting point by ab initio molecular dynamics and zentropy theory: Application to fluoride and chloride molten salts</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10692</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10692v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We have recently developed a breakthrough methodology for rapidly computing entropy in both solids and liquids by integrating a multiscale entropy approach (known as zentropy theory) with molecular dynamics (MD) simulations. This approach enables entropy estimation from a single MD trajectory by analyzing the probabilities of local structural configurations and atomic distributions, effectively addressing the long-standing challenge of capturing configurational entropy. Here, we demonstrate the power of this method by predicting entropies, enthalpies, and melting points for 25 binary and ternary chlorite- and fluoride-based molten salts using ab initio MD (AIMD) simulations. The strong agreement between our predictions and experimental data underscores the potential of this approach to transform computational thermodynamics, offering accurate, efficient, and direct predictions of thermodynamic properties across both solid and liquid phases.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10692v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shun-Li Shang, Nigel L. E. Hew, Rushi Gong, Cillian Cockrell, Paul A. Bingham, Xiaofeng Guo, Qi-Jun Hong, Zi-Kui Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Pull-off force prediction in viscoelastic adhesive Hertzian contact by physics augmented machine learning</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11685</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11685v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Understanding and predicting the adhesive properties of viscoelastic Hertzian contacts is crucial for diverse engineering applications, including robotics, biomechanics, and advanced material design. The maximum adherence force of a Hertzian indenter unloaded from a viscoelastic substrate has been studied with analytical and numerical models. Analytical models are valid within their assumptions, numerical methods offer precision but can be computationally expensive, necessitating alternative solutions. This study introduces a novel physics-augmented machine learning (PA-ML) framework as a hybrid approach, bridging the gap between analytical models and data-driven solutions, which is capable of rapidly predicting the pull-off force in an Hertzian profile unloaded from a broad band viscoelastic material, with varying Tabor parameter, preload and retraction rate. Compared to previous models, the PA-ML approach provides fast yet accurate predictions in a wide range of conditions, properly predicting the effective surface energy and the work-to-pull-off. The integration of the analytical model provides critical guidance to the PA-ML framework, supporting physically consistent predictions. We demonstrate that physics augmentation enhances predictive accuracy, reducing mean squared error (MSE) while increasing model efficiency and interpretability. We provide data-driven and PA-ML models for real-time predictions of the adherence force in soft materials like silicons and elastomers opening to the possibility to integrate PA-ML into materials and interface design. The models are openly available on Zenodo and GitHub.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11685v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ali Maghami, Merten Stender, Antonio Papangelo</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unveiling the thermal transport properties of Biphenylene nanotubes: A molecular dynamics study</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.11981</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.11981v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Biphenylene nanotubes (BPNNTs) represent a novel class of carbon-based nanomaterials, constructed by rolling a biphenylene network (BPN) monolayer into a one-dimensional tubular structure. In this study, the thermal transport properties of BPNNTs are investigated using reverse non-equilibrium molecular dynamics simulations. At room temperature, the lattice thermal conductivity of armchair and zigzag BPNNTs is found to be approximately 100 W/m.K and 90 W/m.K, respectively. These values are at least one order of magnitude lower than those of single-walled carbon nanotubes (SWCNTs). This significant reduction is attributed to the unique atomic arrangement of BPNNTs, which promotes enhanced phonon scattering and significantly lower phonon group velocity. Furthermore, the effects of nanotube length, diameter, and temperature on thermal transport are systematically analyzed. To elucidate the mechanisms underlying the geometry- and temperature-dependent thermal behavior, a comprehensive analysis of phonon dispersion relations, vibrational density of states, and phonon group velocities is conducted. This study offers valuable insight into the thermal transport properties of BPNNTs, with implications for thermal management and energy-related applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.11981v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jhionathan de Lima, Cristiano F. Woellner</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Excitonic topology and quantum geometry in organic semiconductors</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.11951</link>
      <description>arXiv:2406.11951v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Excitons drive the optoelectronic properties of organic semiconductors which underpin devices including solar cells and light-emitting diodes. Here we show that excitons can exhibit topologically non-trivial states protected by inversion symmetry and identify a family of organic semiconductors realising the predicted excitonic topological phases. We also demonstrate that the topological phase can be controlled through experimentally realisable strains and chemical functionalisation of the material. Appealing to quantum Riemannian geometry, we predict that topologically non-trivial excitons have a lower bound on their centre-of-mass spatial spread, which can significantly exceed the size of a unit cell. Furthermore, we show that the dielectric environment allows control over the excitonic quantum geometry. The discovery of excitonic topology and excitonic Riemannian geometry in organic materials brings together two mature fields and suggests many new possibilities for a range of future optoelectronic applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2406.11951v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.quant-gas</category>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.supr-con</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1038/s41467-025-59257-5</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Nature Communications 16, 4661 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Wojciech J. Jankowski, Joshua J. P. Thompson, Bartomeu Monserrat, Robert-Jan Slager</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Free energy barrier and thermal-quantum behavior of sliding bilayer graphene</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.04532</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.04532v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: In multilayer graphene, the stacking order of the layers plays a crucial role in the electronic properties and the manifestation of superconductivity. By applying shear stress, it is possible to induce sliding between different layers, altering the stacking order. Here, focusing on bilayer graphene, we analyze how ionic fluctuations alter the free energy barrier between different stacking equilibria. We calculate the free energy barrier through the state-of-the-art self-consistent harmonic approximation, which can be evaluated at unstable configurations. We find that above 100 K there is a large reduction of the barrier of more than 30% due to thermal vibrations, which significantly improves the agreement between previous first-principles theoretical work and experiments in a single graphite crystal. As the temperature increases, the barrier remains nearly constant up to around 500 K, with a more pronounced decrease only at higher temperatures. Our approach is general and paves the way for systematically accounting for thermal effects in free energy barriers of other macroscopic systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.04532v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jean Paul Nery, Lorenzo Monacelli, Francesco Mauri</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optical Absorption and Emission from Wannier-Stark Spectra of Moir\'{e} Superlattices</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.14670</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.14670v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Using a formalism based on the non-Abelian Berry connection, we explore quantum geometric signatures of Wannier-Stark spectra in two-dimensional superlattices. The Stark energy can be written as \textit{intraband} Berry phases, while Zener tunneling is given by \textit{interband} Berry connections. We suggest that the gaps induced by interband hybridization can be probed by THz optical absorption and emission spectroscopy. This is especially relevant to modern moir\'{e} materials wherein mini-bands are often spectrally entangled, leading to strong interband hybridization in the Wannier-Stark regime. Furthermore, owing to their large superlattice constants, both the low-field and high-field regimes can be accessed in these materials using presently available technology. Importantly, even at moderate electric fields, we find that stimulated emission can dominate absorption, raising the possibility of lasing at practically relevant parameter regimes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.14670v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Vo Tien Phong, Francisco Guinea, Cyprian Lewandowski</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Incommensurate and commensurate antiferromagnetic orders in the kagome compound UV$_{6}$Sn$_{6}$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.12922</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.12922v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: We report on the synthesis of single crystals of the kagome compound, UV$_6$Sn$_6$, and present the results of magnetization, electrical resistivity, heat capacity, x-ray, and neutron diffraction experiments to characterize the structure and magnetic properties. UV$_6$Sn$_6$ crystallizes in a large supercell of the HfFe$_6$Ge$_6$ parent structure with an hexagonal symmetry in which some of the U atoms are shifted by $c/2$ in an ordered fashion. Below $T_{N1}\approx$ 29 K, an incommensurate magnetic structure with a temperature-dependent wave vector $(0,0,k_z)$ is observed. Below $T_{N2}=$ 23.5 K, the wave vector locks in to $(0,0,0.5)$, forming an antiferromagnetic ground state. The U moments align along the $c$ axis retaining a large magnetic anisotropy. These findings highlight the role of the $5f$ orbitals from uranium in this structural family in driving both magnetic ordering and structural modulation and distinguish UV$_6$Sn$_6$ from its lanthanide-based analogs.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.12922v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/PhysRevB.111.174432</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 111, 174432 (2025) [Editors' Suggestion]</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Midori Amano Patino, Stephane Raymond, Georg Knebel, Pierre Le Berre, Stanislav Savvin, Elise Pachoud, Eric Ressouche, James C. Fettinger, Olivier Leynaud, Jacques Pecaut, Peter Klavins, Klaus Hasselbach, Jean-Pascal Brison, Gerard Lapertot, Valentin Taufour</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
