<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci</link>
    <description>cond-mat.mtrl-sci updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/cond-mat.mtrl-sci" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 03:00:05 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>Floating zone growth of high-purity MgO substrate single crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20961</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20961v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: MgO single crystals with diameters between 3.5 and 5 mm and lengths up to 40 mm were grown by the optical floating zone technique (OFZ). Despite challenging material properties such as the high melting point of 2825 {\deg}C, very high evaporation rate and perfect {100} cleaving characteristics, crack-free crystals were grown at high growth rates exceeding 40 mm/h and at high thermal gradients. Chemical investigations revealed that the OFZ technique is suitable for the preparation of substrate crystals with a purity of 5N to facilitate the development of novel demonstrator devices based on epitaxially grown thin films. The achieved purity level is improved by more than one order of magnitude if compared to commercial MgO substrate single crystals graded as high purity.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20961v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Christo Guguschev, Michael Schulze, Andrea Dittmar, Detlef Klimm, Kaspars Dadzis, Thomas Schroeder, Knut Peters, Aakash Pushp</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Multistability of interstitial magnesium and its carrier recombined migration in gallium nitride</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21145</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21145v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present density-functional-theory calculations which provide a microscopic picture of the recombination-enhanced migration of interstitial Mg in GaN. We determine stable structures and migration pathways with accurate HSE approximation to the exchange-correlation energy, and also computed recombination rates using the obtained energy spectrum and wavefunctions. It is found that the migration between the most stable octahedral sites (Mg$_{\textrm{O}}$) via newly found interstitial complex structure shows the lowest migration energy in which one or two electrons are captured during the migration, that the most stable charge state of 2+ changes to 1+ or neutral, and that by this recombination of carriers the migration barrier is significantly reduced. Starting from Mg$_{\textrm{O}}^{2+}$, Mg captures an electron becoming the 1+ charge state and overcomes the barrier of 1.65 eV, much reduced from 2.23 eV in case of the migration with the 2+ charge state kept. Moreover, further electron capture is realized accompanied by substantial structural relaxation, thus Mg becoming neutral. Detailed HSE calculations for this second capture show that the migration barrier is 1.55 eV, thus clarifying the important role of the carrier recombination for Mg migration in GaN. These findings are corroborated by the present quantitative calculations of recombination rates based on electronic Hamiltonian constructed from our DFT-obtained energy spectrum. The timescale of the recombination is clarified to be in or under the timescale of the migration with typical electron density and the enhancement is expected to be significant.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21145v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Yuansheng Zhao, Kenji Shiraishi, Tetsuo Narita, Atsushi Oshiyama</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Temperature-Dependent Spectroscopy of Cr3+:YGG Nanophosphors with Multisite Emission</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21237</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21237v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: An important feature of Cr3+ is the ability to tune the absorption and emission spectra by changing the host. However, in some cases, different emission spectra can be detected in samples with similar Racah parameters. The present paper reports changes in the luminescence properties of Cr3+:YGG nanocrystals. Cr3+:YGG nanocrystals were synthesized by a modified Pechini method to obtain nanocrystals containing two fractions of Cr3+:YGG nanocrystals with different lattice parameters and crystalline sizes. The increase in the concentration of Cr3+ ions leads to a redshift of the 4T2g emission from 750 nm to 850 nm for luminescence spectra measured at 80K. In contrast, room temperature luminescence spectra showed similarity in the shape of the emission spectra. The calculated crystal field strength was found to increase with the concentration of Cr3+ ions, so the detected patterns in low-temperature luminescence spectra were explained by energy transfer chain processes.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21237v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.materresbull.2025.113841</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Chaika, M. (2025). Temperature-Dependent Spectroscopy of Cr3+: YGG Nanophosphors with Multisite Emission. Materials Research Bulletin, 113841</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Mykhailo Chaika</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Toward more performant eye safe lasers: effect of increasing sensitizer amount in Yb3+,Er3+:YAG transparent ceramic on its spectral characteristics</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21243</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21243v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Developing efficient Er3+,Yb3+:YAG eye-safe lasers is a priority of modern laser technology. This paper focuses on the influence of the concentration of Yb3+ ions on the spectroscopic properties of Er3+,Yb3+:YAG transparent ceramics. Four samples with different concentrations of Yb3+ ions were prepared by solid-state reaction sintering. The study revealed the influence of Yb3+ ions on the microstructure and the sintering process. A high concentration of Yb3+ ions leads to the formation of Y3+-rich impurity phases and causes segregation of Er3+ and Yb3+ and Si4+ into these phases. The influence of Yb3+ ions on the shape of emission spectra and the lifetimes of both Er3+ and Yb3+ ions was shown. Changes in the spectroscopic properties were ascribed to increase in neat transfer between Yb3+ and Er3+ ions. IQE of Er3+ and Yb3+ luminescence were calculated, and optimal Er3+/Yb3+ ions ratio were proposed</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21243v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1016/j.jeurceramsoc.2025.117365</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Szysiak, A., e.all (2025). Toward more performant eye safe lasers: Effect of increasing sensitizer amount in Yb3+, Er3+: YAG transparent ceramic on its spectral characteristics. Journal of the European Ceramic Society, 45(11), 117365</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Agnieszka Szysiak, Robert Tomala, Helena W\k{e}glarz, Juraj Kajan, Miros{\l}aw S{\l}obodzian, Mykhailo Chaika</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lossy phononic metamaterials for valley manipulation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21359</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21359v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Non-Hermitian physics characterized by complex band spectra has established a new paradigm in condensed matter systems and metamaterials. Recently, non-Hermitian gain and nonreciprocity are deliberately introduced to valley manipulation, leading to various phenomena beyond the Hermitian scenarios, such as the amplified topological whispering gallery modes as an acoustic laser. In contrast, pure loss is inevitable in practice and generally regarded as a detrimental factor. Here, we reveal that the coupling loss can manipulate valley degrees of freedom in a phononic metamaterial. Three distinct valley-related effects, including valley-resolved nonreciprocity that functions as a valley filter, valley-dependent skin effects where bulk states from different valleys localize at opposite boundaries, and valley-projected edge states with boundary-dependent lifetimes that leads to an anomalous beam splitting, are demonstrated through theoretical analysis and airborne sound experiments. Owing to the easy preparation of loss, our findings shed light on both non-Hermitian and valley physics and may facilitate innovative applications of valley-related devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21359v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Shunda Yin, Qiuyan Zhou, Yuxiang Xi, Weiyin Deng, Wei Chen, Jiuyang Lu, Manzhu Ke, Zhengyou Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>2D Excitonics with Atomically Thin Lateral Heterostructures</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21422</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21422v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Semiconducting transition metal dichalcogenides (TMDs), such as MoSe$_2$ and WSe$_2$, exhibit unique optical and electronic properties. Vertical stacking of layers of one or more TMDs, to create heterostructures, has expanded the fields of moir\'e physics and twistronics. Bottom-up fabrication techniques, such as chemical vapor deposition, have advanced the creation of heterostructures beyond what was possible with mechanical exfoliation and stacking. These techniques now enable the fabrication of lateral heterostructures, where two or more monolayers are covalently bonded in the plane of their atoms. At their atomically sharp interfaces, lateral heterostructures exhibit additional phenomena, such as the formation of charge-transfer excitons, in which the electron and hole reside on opposite sides of the interface. Due to the energy landscape created by differences in the band structures of the constituent materials, unique effects such as unidirectional exciton transport and excitonic lensing can be observed in lateral heterostructures. This review outlines recent progress in exciton dynamics and spectroscopy of TMD-based lateral heterostructures and offers an outlook on future developments in excitonics in this promising system.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21422v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>S. Shradha, R. Rosati, H. Lamsaadi, J. Picker, I. Paradisanos, Md T. Hossain, L. Krelle, L. F. Oswald, N. Engel, D. I. Markina, K. Watanabe, T. Taniguchi, P. K. Sahoo, L. Lombez, X. Marie, P. Renucci, V. Paillard, J. -M. Poumirol, A. Turchanin, E. Malic, B. Urbaszek</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Examining the Spin Structure of Altermagnetic Candidate MnTe Grown with Near Ideal Stoichiometry</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21511</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21511v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Altermagnets are a recently-discovered class of materials with magnetic ordering that have a zero net magnetization and a momentum-dependent spin splitting in their band structure, arising from a collinear spin arrangement with alternating polarizations in the crystal lattice. The nickeline-structured manganese telluride ({\alpha}-MnTe) is an attractive altermagnet candidate due to its predicted large spin splitting energy and a transition temperature near 300K. In this work, we present a thorough investigation of the spin structure of {\alpha}-MnTe thin films grown by molecular beam epitaxy with very high crystal quality and low residual magnetization. The epitaxial {\alpha}-MnTe films have a full-width-at-half-maximum of 0.1{\deg} as measured by x-ray-diffraction rocking curves and a root-mean-square roughness below 1 nm. Neutron diffraction measurements confirm the antiferromagnetic order in the {\alpha}-MnTe film and show a N\'eel temperature of 307 K. Polarized neutron reflectometry detects a vanishingly small net magnetization which may be confined to the MnTe/InP interface, highlighting the near-ideal stoichiometry in the sample. In vacuo angle resolved photoemission spectroscopy reveals that the bulk band spectrum of the MnTe films is consistent with the weak altermagnetic order as theoretically predicted and observed for the high symmetry nodal plane in the center of the Brillouin zone. This study establishes optimized growth conditions for the synthesis of stoichiometric {\alpha}-MnTe thin films which exhibit exceptional structural and magnetic ordering, thereby providing a robust platform for the precise characterization of their altermagnetic properties.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21511v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Qihua Zhang, Christopher J. Jensen, Alexander J. Grutter, Sandra Santhosh, William D. Ratcliff, Julie A. Borchers, Thomas W. Heitmann, Narendirakumar Narayanan, Timothy R. Charlton, Mingyu Yu, Ke Wang, Wesley Auker, Nitin Samarth, Stephanie Law</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hexagonal InOI monolayer: a 2D phase-change material combining topological insulator states and piezoelectricity</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21527</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21527v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Two-dimensional (2D) phase-change materials (PCMs) with moderate transition barriers and distinctly contrasting properties are highly desirable for multifunctional devices, yet such systems remain scarce. Using first-principles calculations, we propose a hexagonal InOI monolayer as a promising 2D PCM. This material exhibits two distinct polymorphs: an energetically favorable T$^{\prime}$ phase and a metastable T phase, differentiated by iodine atom positions. The T$^{\prime}$-to-T structural phase transition features a moderate energy barrier $E_b$ of 72.1 meV per formula unit, facilitating reversible switching. Notably, strain engineering tailors the electronic transition, inducing either a metal-to-topological-insulator or a metal-to-normal-insulator transformation. Additionally, this phase transition modulates the piezoelectric response and shifts optical absorption from the infrared to the visible range. These multifunctional properties make 2D hexagonal InOI highly promising for applications in non-volatile memory, low-contact-resistance spintronics, and optical switching devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21527v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Wenhui Wan, Xinyue Liu, Yanfeng Ge, Ziqang Li, Yong Liu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Zeeman Spectroscopy of Vacancy-Charge-Compensated Er3+ Sites in CaWO4 under Vector Magnetic Fields</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21622</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21622v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: We present polarization-resolved optical absorption measurements on Er3+ ions in CaWO4 under vector magnetic fields, focusing on charge-compensated sites arising from local Ca2+ vacancies. While the known axial Er3+ site displays a single symmetric Zeeman-split transition pattern consistent with S4 symmetry, two additional sites exhibit more complex spectral behavior, including sets of transitions that interchange under 90{\deg} crystal rotations-evidence of reduced, rhombic-like symmetry. From these polarization- and temperature-dependent spectra, we extract effective g-factors. Our findings are corroborated by electron paramagnetic resonance measurements and support a model of multiple inequivalent Ca2+ vacancies around Er3+ sites in the host lattice. This detailed characterization contributes to understanding defect-engineered rare-earth sites for quantum information applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21622v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Fabian Becker, Sudip KC, Lorenz J. J. Sauerzopf, Tim Schneider, Luis Risinger, Christian Schmid, Kai M\"uller</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Tailoring dispersion and evanescent modes in multimodal nonlocal lattices using positive-only interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21629</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21629v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Metamaterials derive their unconventional properties from engineered microstructures, with periodic lattices providing a versatile framework for modeling wave propagation. Dispersion relations, obtained from Bloch-Floquet theory, govern how waves propagate, attenuate, or localize within such systems. Extending interactions beyond nearest neighbors, through nonlocality, substantially enriches the design space of band diagrams, enabling phenomena such as negative or zero group velocities, roton-like extrema, and band-gap localization. However, existing approaches to dispersion tailoring often rely on analytical formulations or Fourier-based identifications, which become impractical for complex coupling mechanisms and offer limited control over physical constraints such as stiffness positivity. This work introduces a general interpolation-based framework for customizing dispersion relations in uniform nonlocal lattices. Rather than reconstructing full dispersion curves, the method enforces prescribed frequency-wavenumber points as interpolation constraints, enabling localized and tunable control of wave behavior. The formulation is applied to both spring- and beam-interaction lattices, and demonstrated on an Euler-Bernoulli beam model with adjustable nonlocal couplings. Through systematic parameter tuning, the framework enables the creation of rotons, the adjustment of group-velocity dispersion, and the design of evanescent waves with controlled exponential decay within band gaps, all while ensuring real, positive-only stiffness parameters and passive mechanical behavior. Altogether, this parametric interpolation strategy provides a physically consistent and computationally efficient route for engineering advanced phononic functionalities in periodic nonlocal systems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21629v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Lucas Rouhi, Christophe Droz</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Piezochiral Effect</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21674</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21674v1 Announce Type: new 
Abstract: Chirality is a pervasive property of matter that underpins many important phenomena across physics, chemistry and biology. Given its broad significance, the development of protocols for rational control of chirality in solid state systems is highly desirable, especially if this effect can be tuned continuously and in two directions. Yet, this goal has remained elusive due to the absence of a universal conjugate field that couples linearly to this structural order. Here, we introduce the piezochiral effect, which enables control of chirality through mechanical strain. We first show by symmetry analysis that uniaxial strain induces chirality in a broad class of achiral crystals that host fragments of opposite chirality within each unit cell, an effect that has so far remained unrecognized. The strain-induced handedness can be tuned either by changing the strain direction or by switching between compressive and tensile strain. We experimentally verify this effect in AgGaS2, using measurements of the optical activity under strain. Our discovery establishes a new scheme for chirality control, with potential applications that range from spintronics to asymmetric catalysis, and enantioselective interactions in biosystems.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21674v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>new</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Z. Zeng, M. F\"orst, M. Fechner, X. Deng, A. Cavalleri, P. G. Radaelli</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>ComProScanner: A multi-agent based framework for composition-property structured data extraction from scientific literature</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20362</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20362v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Since the advent of various pre-trained large language models, extracting structured knowledge from scientific text has experienced a revolutionary change compared with traditional machine learning or natural language processing techniques. Despite these advances, accessible automated tools that allow users to construct, validate, and visualise datasets from scientific literature extraction remain scarce. We therefore developed ComProScanner, an autonomous multi-agent platform that facilitates the extraction, validation, classification, and visualisation of machine-readable chemical compositions and properties, integrated with synthesis data from journal articles for comprehensive database creation. We evaluated our framework using 100 journal articles against 10 different LLMs, including both open-source and proprietary models, to extract highly complex compositions associated with ceramic piezoelectric materials and corresponding piezoelectric strain coefficients (d33), motivated by the lack of a large dataset for such materials. DeepSeek-V3-0324 outperformed all models with a significant overall accuracy of 0.82. This framework provides a simple, user-friendly, readily-usable package for extracting highly complex experimental data buried in the literature to build machine learning or deep learning datasets.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20362v1</guid>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Aritra Roy, Enrico Grisan, John Buckeridge, Chiara Gattinoni</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Probability Space at Inception of Stochastic Process</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20824</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20824v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Recently, progress has been made in the theory of turbulence, which provides a framework on how a deterministic process changes to a stochastic one owing to the change in thermodynamic states. It is well known that, in the framework of Newtonian mechanics, motions are dissipative; however, when subjected to periodic motion, a system can produce nondissipative motions intermittently and subject to resonance. It is in resonance that turbulence occurs in fluid flow, solid vibration, thermal transport, etc. In this, the findings from these physical systems are analyzed in the framework of statistics with their own probability space to establish their compliance to the stochastic process. In particular, a systematic alignment of the inception of the stochastic process with the signed measure theory, signed probability space, and stochastic process was investigated. It was found that the oscillatory load from the dissipative state excited the system and resulted in a quasi-periodic probability density function with the negative probability regimes. In addition, the vectorial nature of the random velocity splits the probability density function along both the positive and negative axes with slight asymmetricity. By assuming that a deterministic process has a probability of 1, we can express the inception of a stochastic process, and the subsequent benefit is that a dynamic fractal falls on the probability density function. Moreover, we leave some questions of inconsistency between the physical system and the measurement theory for future investigation. We believe that the establishment of the probability density function of resonance nondissipative dynamics in contemporary statistics should make many mathematical tools available and the analytical formulas for the random velocity and probability density function can provide a convenient platform for the development of statistics.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20824v1</guid>
      <category>nlin.CD</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Liteng Yang, Yuliang Liu, Jing Liu, Hongxuan Li, Wei Chen</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Universal Chern Model on Arbitrary Triangulations</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20862</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20862v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Given a triangulation of a closed orientable surface, we consider the lattice with sites at the vertices, edges and facets of the triangulation. Borrowing from mathematics literature, we introduce on this lattice a pair of tight-binding Hamiltonians derived from the boundary and Poincar\'e duality maps of finite simplicial manifolds. These Hamiltonians have been proved to have clean topological spectral gaps carrying non-trivial Chern numbers in the limit of infinite refinement of the triangulation. We confirm this via numerical simulations, and demonstrate how these models enable topological edge modes at the surfaces of real-world objects. Furthermore, we describe a metamaterial whose dynamics reproduces that of the proposed model, thus bringing the topological metamaterials closer to real-world applications.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20862v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>math.OA</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Nigel Higson, Emil Prodan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Landau Polarons as Generators of Quantum-Coherent States</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20962</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20962v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Since Landau's theory, polarons have been understood as quasiparticles in which charges are dressed by the lattice field, yet decades of transport and spectroscopic studies have yielded only static indirect renormalizations. Whether such dressing can dynamically reorganize electronic spectra to generate new quantum-coherent states has remained unresolved. Here we use femtosecond coherent multidimensional spectroscopy on size and composition controlled perovskite quantum dots to track polaronic field-induced dynamics in real time, revealing their consequences. We observe a delayed condensation into a confined spectrum of coherent states on 50-150 fs timescales, with couplings between these states evolving dynamically on the same timescale. The splittings are robust, exhibit anomalous linear size dependence, exceed single-particle splittings and manifest at 300 K. A Raman-constrained spin-boson Hamiltonian captures both the anomalous scaling and dynamical onset, establishing polarons as generators of coherent manifolds that enable collective quantum phenomena including superradiance, superfluorescence and superabsorption.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20962v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Arnab Ghosh, Patrick Brosseau, Dmitry N. Dirin, Rui Tao, Maksym V. Kovalenko, Patanjali Kambhampati</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grain Boundary Diffusion in Yukawa Crystals</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.20980</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.20980v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: We present calculations of diffusion coefficients in grain boundaries in Yukawa crystals for astrophysics. Our methods follow from our recent work calculating diffusion coefficients in perfect body-centered cubic crystals. These diffusion coefficients show only a weak dependence on the crystal orientations at the grain boundary and are consistent with those expected for a supercooled liquid scaled down by one to two orders of magnitude. We argue that the local disorder at the grain boundary produces a landscape of potential barriers similar to that of an amorphous liquid thin film, significantly reducing activation barriers to diffusive hops relative to the bulk solid. This also introduces a screening dependence, such that boundary diffusion does not exhibit the same universality as the bulk crystal. These diffusion coefficients suggest that grain boundaries may be a dominant source of viscous dissipation in neutron star crusts.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.20980v1</guid>
      <category>physics.plasm-ph</category>
      <category>astro-ph.HE</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Matthew E. Caplan, Nevin T. Smith, Dany Yaacoub, Roberto F. Serrano, Elias Taira, Ashley Bransgrove</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The spinterface mechanism for the chiral-induced spin selectivity effect: A Critical Perspective</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21061</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21061v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The chiral-induced spin selectivity (CISS) effect, whereby chiral molecules preferentially transmit electrons of one spin orientation, remains one of the most intriguing and debated phenomena at the interface of spintronics, molecular electronics, and quantum materials. Despite extensive experimental observations across diverse platforms - including transport junctions, photoemission, and enantioselective chemistry - a comprehensive theoretical framework is still lacking. In this perspective, we critically examine the spinterface mechanism as a unifying explanation for the CISS effect. The spinterface model, which hypothesizes a feedback interaction between electron motion in chiral molecules and fluctuating surface magnetic moments, is shown to quantitatively reproduce experimental data across various systems and conditions. We contrast it with some existing theoretical models, highlighting key experimental features. Importantly, we also address open questions and criticisms of this model, including the nature of surface magnetism, the role of dissipation, and the applicability of the mechanism to non-helical or electrode-free systems. By offering falsifiable predictions and reconciling theory with experimental raw data, this work aims to sharpen the dialogue surrounding the microscopic origin of CISS and stimulate further experimental and theoretical progress.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21061v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1021/acsnano.5c16086</arxiv:DOI>
      <dc:creator>Subhajit Sarkar, Amos Sharoni, Oliver L. A. Monti, Yonatan Dubi</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Optimal spin-charge interconversion in graphene through spin-pseudospin entanglement control</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21240</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21240v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The electrical generation of spin signals is of central interest for spintronics, where graphene stands as a relevant platform as its spin-orbit coupling (SOC) is tuned by proximity effects. Here, we propose an enhancement of spin-charge interconversion in graphene by controlling the intraparticle entanglement between the spin and pseudospin degrees of freedom. We demonstrate that, although the spin alone is not conserved in Rashba-Dirac systems, a combined spin-pseudospin operator is conserved. This conserved quantity represents the interconversion between pure spin and pseudospin textures to a spin-pseudospin entangled structure, where Kane-Mele SOC tunes this balance. By these means, we achieve spin-charge interconversion of 100\% efficiency via the Rashba-Edelstein effect. Quantum transport simulations in disordered micron-size systems demonstrate the robustness of this effect, and also reveal a disorder resilient spin Hall effect generated by the interplay between Rashba and Kane-Mele SOC. Our findings propose a platform for maximally efficient spin-charge interconversion, and establish spin-pseudospin correlations as a mechanism to tailor spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21240v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Joaqu\'in Medina Due\~nas, Santiago Gim\'enez de Castro, Jose H. Garcia, Stephan Roche</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Combining metal dewetting and lateral etching for the scalable top-down fabrication of GaN nanowire arrays with independently tunable diameter and spacing</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21305</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21305v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: The top-down fabrication of nanowires based on patterning via metal dewetting is a cost-effective and scalable approach that is particularly suited for applications requiring large arrays of nanowires. Advantageously, the nanowire diameter can be tailored by the initial metal film thickness. However, we show here that metal dewetting inherently leads to a coupling between the nanowire diameter and spacing. To overcome this limitation, we introduce two strategies that are exemplified for GaN nanowires: (i) modification of the surface and interface energies within the dewetting system, and (ii) thinning of the nanowires by lateral etching. In the first strategy, GaN(0001), SiOx, and SiNx substrate surfaces are combined with Au, Pt, and Pt-Au alloy dewetting metals to tune the dewetting behavior. The differences in interface energies affect the relation between nanowire diameter and spacing, albeit within a limited range. The second strategy adds a lateral etching step to the conventional top-down nanowire fabrication process. This step at the same time reduces the nanowire diameter and increases the spacing, thus enabling combinations beyond the constraints of metal dewetting alone. When in addition different initial nanowire diameters are employed, it is possible to independently control diameter and spacing over a substantially extended range. Therefore, the inherent limitation of conventional dewetting-based patterning approaches for the top-down fabrication of nanowires is overcome.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21305v1</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jingxuan Kang, Rose-Mary Jose, Oliver Brandt, Lutz Geelhaar</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Controlling bubble and skyrmion lattice order and dynamics via stripe domain engineering in ferrimagnetic Fe/Gd multilayers</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.21320</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.21320v1 Announce Type: cross 
Abstract: Ferrimagnetic Fe/Gd multilayers host maze-like stripe domains that transform into a disordered bubble/skyrmion lattice under out-of-plane magnetic fields at ambient temperature. Femtosecond magneto-optics distinguishes these textures via their distinct coherent breathing dynamics. Crucially, applying a brief in-plane ``set'' magnetic field to the stripe state enhances both frequency and amplitude of the bubble/skyrmion lattice breathing mode. Lorentz transmission electron microscopy, magnetic force microscopy, and micromagnetic simulations reveal that this enhancement arises from field-aligned stripes nucleating a dense, near-hexagonal bubble/skyrmion lattice upon out-of-plane field application, with strong indications for a pure skyrmion lattice. Thus, modifying the initial domain configuration by in-plane fields enables precise control of coherent magnetization dynamics on picosecond to nanosecond timescales and potentially even of topology.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.21320v1</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Tim Titze (I. Physikalisches Institut, Universit\"at G\"ottingen, G\"ottingen, Germany), Sabri Koraltan (Institute of Applied Physics, TU Wien, Vienna, Austria, Physics of Functional Materials, Faculty of Physics, University of Vienna, Austria), Timo Schmidt (Institute of Physics, University of Augsburg, Augsburg, Germany), Mailin Matthies (I. Physikalisches Institut, Universit\"at G\"ottingen, G\"ottingen, Germany), Amalio Fern\'andez-Pacheco (Institute of Applied Physics, TU Wien, Vienna, Austria), Dieter Suess (Physics of Functional Materials, Faculty of Physics, University of Vienna, Austria), Manfred Albrecht (Institute of Physics, University of Augsburg, Augsburg, Germany), Stefan Mathias (I. Physikalisches Institut, Universit\"at G\"ottingen, G\"ottingen, Germany, International Center for Advanced Studies of Energy Conversion), Daniel Steil (I. Physikalisches Institut, Universit\"at G\"ottingen, G\"ottingen, Germany)</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Solidification of Icosahedral Quasicrystals: Viewpoint Based on a Quaternion Orientational Order Parameter and the Formation of the E8 Lattice</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/1905.12165</link>
      <description>arXiv:1905.12165v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: In this article, the solidification phase transition between isotropic liquids and icosahedral quasicrystalline structures is classified by the application of a quaternion orientational order parameter. We suggest that the formation of the E8 lattice in 8-dimensions, from which three-dimensional icosahedral quasicrystals derive by projection, occurs without dimensionally restricting the degrees of freedom of the quaternion orientational order parameter to the quaternion plane. This is different from the development of regular crystalline solids in three-dimensions, which occurs in "restricted dimensions" and requires topological-ordering, as previously discussed by the authors. In other words, herein, the formation of lattices in eight-dimensions is considered as a higher-dimensional analogy to the formation of "bulk" superfluidity. It follows that, the solidification of lattices in 8-dimensions (and derivative icosahedral quasicrystalline solids) should occur without the necessity of topological defects.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:1905.12165v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>gr-qc</category>
      <category>hep-lat</category>
      <category>math-ph</category>
      <category>math.MP</category>
      <category>physics.atm-clus</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Caroline S. Gorham, David E. Laughlin</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Polarization-dependent photocurrent in a quadrilateral-shaped bulk crystalline tellurium chip with near-infrared light excitation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2504.00413</link>
      <description>arXiv:2504.00413v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: We report the detection of zero-bias photocurrents induced by interband excitation using oblique near-infrared light ({\lambda}=0.780 {\mu}m) along the directions parallel and perpendicular to the helical axis in a millimeter-sized Te crystal. The photocurrent parallel to the helical axis exhibits a circular-polarization-dependent component, namely circular photogalvanic effect. We create a framework for estimating the gyrotropic photoconductivity tensor \b{eta}, the ratio between the circular-polarization-dependent photocurrent density and intensity of light, through which extrinsic \b{eta} values ranging from a few to a few tens of nA/W are obtained. Searching the \b{eta} values through existing literatures reveals that these values vary significantly with sample conditions, excitation wavelengths, and forms of crystallite samples. A particular interesting point found in our study is that the \b{eta} values for the interband excitation may be greater than those for intraband excitation as far as bulk Te is concerned.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2504.00413v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Hiro Munekata, Gakuto Kusuno, Kohei Miyazaki, Takuya Satoh</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Space Group Equivariant Crystal Diffusion</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.10994</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.10994v3 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Accelerating inverse design of crystalline materials with generative models has significant implications for a range of technologies. Unlike other atomic systems, 3D crystals are invariant to discrete groups of isometries called the space groups. Crucially, these space group symmetries are known to heavily influence materials properties. We propose SGEquiDiff, a crystal generative model which naturally handles space group constraints with space group invariant likelihoods. SGEquiD-iff consists of an SE(3)-invariant, telescoping discrete sampler of crystal lattices; permutation-invariant, transformer-based autoregressive sampling of Wyckoff positions, elements, and numbers of symmetrically unique atoms; and space group equivariant diffusion of atomic coordinates. We show that space group equivariant vector fields automatically live in the tangent spaces of the Wyckoff positions. SGEquiDiff achieves state-of-the-art performance on standard benchmark datasets as assessed by quantitative proxy metrics and quantum mechanical calculations. Our code is available at https://github.com/rees-c/sgequidiff.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.10994v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>NeurIPS 2025</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Rees Chang, Angela Pak, Alex Guerra, Ni Zhan, Nick Richardson, Elif Ertekin, Ryan P. Adams</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear Transport Signatures of Hidden Symmetry Breaking in a Weyl Altermagnet</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2505.20603</link>
      <description>arXiv:2505.20603v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Phase transitions in solids are often accompanied by structural changes, but subtle lattice distortions can remain hidden from conventional crystallographic probes, hindering the identification of the correct order parameters. A case in point is Ca$_3$Ru$_2$O$_7$, a correlated polar ruthenate with well-characterized phase transitions, whose ground state structure has recently become a subject of debate. This uncertainty stems from extremely small atomic displacements ($\sim$0.001 \AA) between competing phases, beyond the resolution of X-ray diffraction, neutron scattering, or optical second-harmonic generation. In this work, we propose a method to detect hidden symmetry breaking by leveraging nonlinear transport induced by quantum geometry. We show that Ca$_3$Ru$_2$O$_7$ is a Weyl chain semimetal in both phases. The low-symmetry phase, classified as an altermagnet by symmetry, features distorted topological surface states that are asymmetric along the polar ($b$) axis. However, the nonrelativistic spin splitting is too weak ($\sim$0.1 meV) to be resolved directly, regarding the altermagnetism. In contrast, Weyl chains generate a large quantum metric at the Fermi surface, leading to nonlinear conductivities that are orders of magnitude stronger in the low-symmetry phase. A longitudinal nonlinear conductivity along the polar axis emerges exclusively in this phase, providing a sensitive probe to qualitatively distinguish it from the high-symmetry structure and demonstrate the emergence of altermangetism, which is confirmed by a recent experiment. Our work establishes a route for identifying hidden symmetry breaking in complex quantum materials through the interplay of crystal symmetry, topology and nonlinear quantum transport.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2505.20603v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mes-hall</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <arxiv:DOI>10.1103/f3vr-x4fx</arxiv:DOI>
      <arxiv:journal_reference>Phys. Rev. B 112, 165127 (2025)</arxiv:journal_reference>
      <dc:creator>Yufei Zhao, Zhiqiang Mao, Binghai Yan</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>High-Efficiency Nonrelativistic Charge-Spin Conversion in X-Type Antiferromagnets</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19194</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19194v2 Announce Type: replace 
Abstract: Altermagnets have attracted considerable interest due to the symmetry-induced anisotropic spin splitting while preserving zero net magnetization, which enables efficient generation of spin currents. This work proposes a distinct class of antiferromagnetic materials, termed X-type antiferromagnets, which are shown to produce more efficient $\cal T$-odd spin currents than common altermagnets along specific crystallographic directions due to their unique Fermi surface geometry. The spin current polarization is controlled by the N\'eel vector orientation. As a prototype conducting X-type antiferromagnet, the Fermi surface of $\beta-\mathrm{Fe}_2\mathrm{PO}_5$ exhibits a distinct $d$-wave altermagnetic characteristic, which compresses into a nearly X-shaped configuration. This results in highly efficient $\cal T$-odd spin currents, achieving a charge-spin conversion efficiency of up to 90%. Moreover, when the N\'eel vector tilts to the out-of-plane direction, an in-plane injected charge current can generate a special spin current component with both spin polarization and propagation along the out-of-plane direction, whose charge-spin conversion efficiency substantially exceeds that of known ferromagnets, altermagnets, noncollinear antiferromagnets, and low-symmetry materials. The highly efficient charge-spin conversion in X-type antiferromagnets provides a novel and highly effective spin source system for the development of low-power spintronic devices.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19194v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>physics.comp-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jiabin Wang, Wancheng Zhang, Yong Liu, Rui Xiong, Zhenhua Zhang, Zhihong Lu</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Synthesis of graphene aerogels toward the absorption of liquid and gas pollutants</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16392</link>
      <description>arXiv:2407.16392v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Environmental disasters, such as the oil spill in Mexico gulf or, more recently, the Mauritius oil spill caused by a bulk carrier vessel, are some of the ecological issues that the modern society faces frequently. These accidents highlight the need for development of efficient materials that can be employed to eliminate pollutants including crude oil and its derivatives, as well as toxic organic solvents. The objective of the present study is to achieve the synthesis of graphene aerogels with two main methods and to determine their efficiency as absorbents of liquid and gas pollutants. Graphene aerogels were prepared according to the information given by Hong et al. (2015) and Yang et al. (2015). Both methods are based on the chemical reduction of graphene oxide as the first step and the formation of the aerogel as the second, providing a more cost-effective solution and resulting in a lattice structure similar to graphene. The fabricated materials were investigated for their absorption capacity for liquid and gas pollutants. The specimens were mounted in airtight microenvironments saturated with a specific Volatile Organic Compound (VOC). Three VOCs were tested; formaldehyde, acetic acid and hydrochloric acid and the results were based on gravimetric measurements. In order to increase the accuracy of the obtained data, a VOCs sensor was used to measure the change of voltage before and after the introduction of graphene aerogels in a saturated microenvironment. Furthermore, the graphene aerogels were evaluated as absorbents in organic solvents, namely acetone, ethanol and methanol.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2407.16392v3</guid>
      <category>physics.app-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>George Gorgolis, Natalia Pastra, George Paterakis, Costas Galiotis</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Flat band driven itinerant magnetism in the Co-pnictides CaCo$_2$As$_2$ and LaCo$_2$P$_2$</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2503.02728</link>
      <description>arXiv:2503.02728v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Flat bands can induce strong electron correlation effects that help stabilize both magnetic and superconducting states. Here, we carry out angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy and density functional theory calculations to study the electronic structure of the Co-pnictides CaCo$_2$As$_2$ and LaCo$_2$P$_2$. We find that, while the $k_z$ Fermi topology of ferromagnetic LaCo$_2$P$_2$ is markedly 2-dimensional, antiferromagnetic CaCo$_2$As$_2$ develops a 3D Fermi surface described by a $zig-zag$-like band dispersion perpendicular to the Co-As plane. Furthermore, the magnetism is driven by the electronic correlations of the flat bands with $d_{xy}$ and $d_{z^2}$ orbital character at the Fermi level. Our results link the electronic dimensionality and the magnetic order, and emphasize the critical role of the As-As and P-P bond strength along the $c$-direction to understand the electronic band structure and the rich phase diagram of transition metal pnictides.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2503.02728v2</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>D. Subires, M. Garc\'ia-D\'iez, A. Kar, C. -Y. Lim, Victoria M. Li, V. Yannello, Dina Carbone, P. Gargiani, T. Yilmaz, J. Dai, M. Tallarida, E. Vescovo, M. Shatruk, Maia G. Vergniory, S. Blanco-Canosa</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Emission Properties of a Hybrid Metallized Diamond(001) Photocathode</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.12550</link>
      <description>arXiv:2506.12550v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The spectral emission characteristics of a proof-of-concept hybrid metallized diamond(001) photocathode are presented. The quantum efficiency (QE) is shown to be determined by the photo-injection efficiency across the ohmic contact at the back metallized face, whereas the mean transverse energy (MTE) of the photoemitted electrons is consistent with a (optical)phonon-assisted and momentum-resonant Franck-Condon mechanism [Phys. Rev. Applied 23, 054065 (2025)] following electron drift transport to the untreated diamond(001) front emission face. Emission is observed from both the lower and upper conduction bands of diamond with positive and negative electron affinity respectively. A potential route to the realization of a red-visible photocathode based on this concept with a sub-50meV MTE and a QE greater than 0.1% is discussed.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2506.12550v2</guid>
      <category>physics.acc-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.other</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Louis A. Angeloni, Ir-Jene Shan, W. Andreas Schroeder</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Exact downfolding and its perturbative approximation</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.16916</link>
      <description>arXiv:2507.16916v3 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Solving the many-electron problem, even approximately, is one of the most challenging and simultaneously most important problems in contemporary condensed matter physics with various connections to other fields. The standard approach is to follow a divide and conquer strategy that combines various numerical and analytical techniques. A crucial step in this strategy is the derivation of an effective model for a subset of degrees of freedom by a procedure called downfolding, which often corresponds to integrating out energy scales far away from the Fermi level. In this work we present a rigorous formulation of this downfolding procedure, which complements the renormalization group picture put forward by Honerkamp [PRB 85, 195129 (2012)}]. We derive an exact effective model in an arbitrarily chosen target space (e.g. low-energy degrees of freedom) by explicitly integrating out the the rest space (e.g. high-energy degrees of freedom). Within this formalism we state conditions that justify a perturbative truncation of the downfolded effective interactions to just a few low-order terms. Furthermore, we utilize the exact formalism to formally derive the widely used constrained random phase approximation (cRPA), uncovering underlying approximations and highlighting relevant corrections in the process. Lastly, we detail different contributions in the material examples of fcc Nickel and the infinite-layer cuprate SrCuO$_2$. Our results open up a new pathway to obtain effective models in a controlled fashion and to judge whether a chosen target space is suitable.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2507.16916v3</guid>
      <category>cond-mat.str-el</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>cond-mat.stat-mech</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Jonas B. Profe, Jak\v{s}a Vu\v{c}i\v{c}evi\'c, P. Peter Stavropoulos, Malte R\"osner, Roser Valent\'i, Lennart Klebl</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ab Initio Free Energy Surfaces for Coupled Ion-Electron Transfer</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.19106</link>
      <description>arXiv:2510.19106v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: The Marcus theory of electron transfer assumes that diabatic energy gaps are sampled from a single ensemble. This assumption can break down in spatially anisotropic environments, such as electrochemical interfaces or biomolecular structures, where distinct solvent ensembles arise along a collective variable describing the anisotropy. Treating this collective variable as an additional reaction coordinate linearly independent from the Marcus reaction coordinate, we develop a formalism that enables calculation of the resulting Coupled Ion-Electron Transfer (CIET) free-energy surface directly from constrained ab initio trajectories. Applied to CO2 redox on a gold electrode, this method reveals strong coupling to the anisotropy, predicting significantly different activation barriers compared to either coordinate alone.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2510.19106v2</guid>
      <category>physics.chem-ph</category>
      <category>cond-mat.mtrl-sci</category>
      <category>quant-ph</category>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Ethan Abraham, Martin Z. Bazant, Troy Van Voorhis</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
