<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<rss xmlns:arxiv="http://arxiv.org/schemas/atom" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
  <channel>
    <title>q-bio.MN updates on arXiv.org</title>
    <link>http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.MN</link>
    <description>q-bio.MN updates on the arXiv.org e-print archive.</description>
    <atom:link href="http://rss.arxiv.org/rss/q-bio.MN" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <docs>http://www.rssboard.org/rss-specification</docs>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2024 04:00:25 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <managingEditor>rss-help@arxiv.org</managingEditor>
    <pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
    <skipDays>
      <day>Sunday</day>
      <day>Saturday</day>
    </skipDays>
    <item>
      <title>CADGL: Context-Aware Deep Graph Learning for Predicting Drug-Drug Interactions</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.17210</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.17210v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Examining Drug-Drug Interactions (DDIs) is a pivotal element in the process of drug development. DDIs occur when one drug's properties are affected by the inclusion of other drugs. Detecting favorable DDIs has the potential to pave the way for creating and advancing innovative medications applicable in practical settings. However, existing DDI prediction models continue to face challenges related to generalization in extreme cases, robust feature extraction, and real-life application possibilities. We aim to address these challenges by leveraging the effectiveness of context-aware deep graph learning by introducing a novel framework named CADGL. Based on a customized variational graph autoencoder (VGAE), we capture critical structural and physio-chemical information using two context preprocessors for feature extraction from two different perspectives: local neighborhood and molecular context, in a heterogeneous graphical structure. Our customized VGAE consists of a graph encoder, a latent information encoder, and an MLP decoder. CADGL surpasses other state-of-the-art DDI prediction models, excelling in predicting clinically valuable novel DDIs, supported by rigorous case studies.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.17210v2</guid>
      <category>cs.LG</category>
      <category>cs.AI</category>
      <category>cs.IR</category>
      <category>q-bio.BM</category>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Azmine Toushik Wasi, Taki Hasan Rafi, Raima Islam, Serbetar Karlo, Dong-Kyu Chae</dc:creator>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>FluxGAT: Integrating Flux Sampling with Graph Neural Networks for Unbiased Gene Essentiality Classification</title>
      <link>https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.18666</link>
      <description>arXiv:2403.18666v2 Announce Type: replace-cross 
Abstract: Gene essentiality, the necessity of a specific gene for the survival of an organism, is crucial to our understanding of cellular processes and identifying drug targets. Experimental determination of gene essentiality requires large growth screens that are time-consuming and expensive, motivating the development of in-silico approaches. Existing methods predominantly utilise flux balance analysis (FBA), a constraint-based optimisation algorithm; however, they are fundamentally limited by the necessity of a predefined cellular objective function. This requirement introduces an element of observer bias, as the objective function often reflects the researcher's assumptions rather than the cell's biological goals. Here, we present FluxGAT, a graph neural network (GNN) model capable of predicting gene essentiality directly from graphical representations of flux sampling data. Flux sampling removes the need for objective functions, thereby eliminating observer bias. FluxGAT leverages the unique strengths of GNNs in learning representations of complex relationships within metabolic reaction networks. The success of our approach in predicting experimentally determined gene essentiality, with almost double the sensitivity of FBA, explores the possibility of predicting cellular phenotypes in cases when objectives are less understood. Thus, we demonstrate a method for more general gene essentiality predictions across a broader spectrum of biological systems and environments.</description>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">oai:arXiv.org:2403.18666v2</guid>
      <category>q-bio.QM</category>
      <category>q-bio.MN</category>
      <arxiv:announce_type>replace-cross</arxiv:announce_type>
      <dc:rights>http://arxiv.org/licenses/nonexclusive-distrib/1.0/</dc:rights>
      <dc:creator>Kieren Sharma, Lucia Marucci, Zahraa S. Abdallah</dc:creator>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
